<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Against Former Teammate, Delgado Again Struggles to Produce for Mets</title>
    <meta content="16curry" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/sports/baseball/16curry.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854843"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Puerto Rico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Puerto Rico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (NYC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Puerto Rico</location>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Delgado, Carlos</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clemens, Roger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6D6153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Against Former Teammate, Delgado Again Struggles to Produce for Mets</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Against Former Teammate, Delgado Again Struggles to Produce for Mets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Carlos Delgado of the Mets patiently listened to the statistics, heard that he had a .324 average against Roger Clemens, then pushed the numbers aside and called them meaningless.</p>
        <p>''The way I look at it, whatever I did, it doesn't matter,'' Delgado said. ''It's what I do today.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Carlos Delgado looked like a mannequin as he struck out in all four of his at-bats, three versus Clemens, and stranded five runners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Carlos Delgado of the Mets patiently listened to the statistics, heard that he had a .324 average against Roger Clemens, then pushed the numbers aside and called them meaningless.</p>
        <p>''The way I look at it, whatever I did, it doesn't matter,'' Delgado said. ''It's what I do today.''</p>
        <p>Delgado was relaxed as he discussed his history with Clemens, from giving the pitcher his beloved No. 21 while they were teammates on the Toronto Blue Jays to guarding against Clemens's nasty split-finger fastball. He repeated that facing the Yankees' Clemens was a new challenge, and that the past was irrelevant.</p>
        <p>Apparently, Delgado was right. That challenge proved too much for a power hitter who has not provided much power this season. Delgado looked like a mannequin as he struck out in all four of his at-bats, three versus Clemens, and stranded five runners. He is 1 for his last 21 with runners in scoring position.</p>
        <p>Since Oliver Pérez and the Mets danced to a 2-0 victory against the Yankees, the void Delgado left in the cleanup position was not as noticeable. But it is there, and it is a nagging problem. Delgado acknowledged that he is not thrilled with his production, and that was before Clemens overwhelmed him.</p>
        <p>Afterward, the usually cooperative Delgado provided a course in speed showering and speed dressing. He was the first Met to bolt, not interested in discussing his night. Before the game, Delgado spoke about how the Mets would emerge from their slumber.</p>
        <p>''We don't forget how to play overnight,'' Delgado said. ''Sometimes, it feels that way. But you don't.''</p>
        <p>Still, sometimes Delgado has looked as if he has forgotten how to hit. Delgado, who is batting .221 with 10 homers and 39 runs batted in, saw 17 pitches from Clemens and fouled off two. Other than that, Delgado, whose swings were long and unsteady, did nothing against a pitcher who will turn 45 in August.</p>
        <p>Delgado said that he had been too jumpy at the plate, but he added that his problems were unrelated to the operations he had on his right elbow and his right wrist in October. If Delgado can remind himself to stay back in his batting stance and not be overly aggressive, he will have more reaction time.</p>
        <p>''His mechanics are out of whack,'' Manager Willie Randolph said. ''He needs to stay back on the ball. He's in one of those funks.''</p>
        <p>What is disturbing to the Mets is that Delgado has been seeing the ball better than he did at the outset of the season. In Delgado's first 121 at-bats, he batted .207 with a home run and 12 R.B.I. In his last 128 at-bats, Delgado is batting .234, with 9 home runs and 27 R.B.I.</p>
        <p>Still, for a player who is supposed to be one of the Mets' leading power sources, Delgado realizes that he must do a lot more. Delgado said he trusts that ''things are going to work out,'' a promise that the Mets want to believe.</p>
        <p>More than a decade ago, Delgado had something that Clemens wanted. Clemens, who is more assertive than he is subtle, was upfront and asked for it. Clemens, who had signed a free-agent contract with the Blue Jays in December 1996, asked for the No. 21.</p>
        <p>Delgado wore 21 as a tribute to Roberto Clemente, the Hall of Famer from his native Puerto Rico who died in a plane crash while on a good-will mission. But, as important as the number was to Delgado, he never hesitated in parting with it. Surrendering it was a sign of respect for Clemens's career.</p>
        <p>''When you're Roger Clemens and you've got that many years in, you don't need a sales pitch,'' Delgado said.</p>
        <p>About two months later, during spring training, the pitcher thanked the first baseman by handing him a Rolex. Delgado, who is back to wearing No. 21 for the Mets, said ''it wasn't a big deal'' to give the number to Clemens. Delgado wore the watch for a while, stored it in a safe-deposit box for a while, and now keeps it at home. Delgado said that he does not need the number to honor Clemente.</p>
        <p>''What you have inside is more important than what you have on the outside,'' Delgado said.</p>
        <p>But what Delgado had last night were some unfulfilling at-bats. He whiffed on a 2-2 splitter with two on in the first, missed a 2-2 fastball with two on in the third, and stared at a 3-2 fastball with a man on in the fifth, all against Clemens. Delgado also flailed at Mike Myers's 2-2 slider in the eighth.</p>
        <p>Some accounts said Clemens paid $20,000 for Delgado's watch, while others said it was $15,000. Delgado said it did not ''really make a difference,'' which was true. The watch is part of the past. Delgado needs to be worried about the future.</p>
        <p>''He'll bounce out of it,'' Randolph said. ''When he does, I guarantee you there will be some payback.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
