<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Injured Mickelson's Chances of Making Cut Were Fat or Slim</title>
    <meta content="16sidebar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/sports/golf/16sidebar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">United States Golf Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Mickelson, Phil</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E1D8153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Injured Mickelson's Chances of Making Cut Were Fat or Slim</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Injured Mickelson’s Chances of Making Cut Were Fat or Slim</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa., June 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The caddie Jim Mackay, who is known as Bones, is paid to feed numbers into the golfing machine that is Phil Mickelson. Yards to the green, feet to the pin; those are the figures that Mackay is used to calculating.</p>
        <p>But the United States Open cutline? That one had Mackay scrambling Friday, because the terrain was so unfamiliar. Mickelson had missed qualifying for the weekend only once in 16 previous Open appearances, in 1992 in his first year as a professional.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a trying week for Phil Mickelson, who, thanks in part to a nagging injury, missed the cut in the United States Open by one stroke.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The caddie Jim Mackay, who is known as Bones, is paid to feed numbers into the golfing machine that is Phil Mickelson. Yards to the green, feet to the pin; those are the figures that Mackay is used to calculating.</p>
        <p>But the United States Open cutline? That one had Mackay scrambling Friday, because the terrain was so unfamiliar. Mickelson had missed qualifying for the weekend only once in 16 previous Open appearances, in 1992 in his first year as a professional.</p>
        <p>It certainly did not seem as if the cut was going to come into play earlier in the day when Mickelson birdied two of the first six holes at Oakmont Country Club to infiltrate the leader board at two over par. But he played Holes 7 through 10 in six over par, and just like that, a sublime round turned into a test of survival.</p>
        <p>On the par-3 16th, Mickelson left his tee shot short of the green, hit a mediocre chip shot and two-putted for a bogey that dropped him to 10 over for the tournament. As Mickelson made his way to the 17th tee box wearing a somnolent smile that is his game face, he was alone with his thoughts.</p>
        <p>Mackay had momentarily left his side to collect some critical information. ''Any educated guess what the cut's going to be?'' he asked a group standing just inside the gallery ropes that included Mickelson's spokesman, T. R. Reinman.</p>
        <p>At that point, nobody could say for sure with many golfers waiting to tee off, including the two-time United States Open champion Tiger Woods and the two first-round leaders, Nick Dougherty and Ángel Cabrera.</p>
        <p>The best guess was that Mickelson was probably right at the cutoff to qualify for the final 36 holes. If he made par on the last two holes, he probably was in.</p>
        <p>After sinking an 8-foot par putt at No. 17, Mickelson hit a poor tee shot at No. 18, the ball coming to rest in a lateral hazard to the left of the fairway.</p>
        <p>He had the option of accepting a one-stroke penalty and receiving a free drop, but that is not his style. Mickelson chose to hit out of the hazard and failed on his first attempt. His third shot landed about 90 yards in front of the pin. After sending his fourth shot 10 feet from the hole, Mickelson made the uphill putt for a bogey 5.</p>
        <p>All that scrambling for a second-round 77 and a cumulative score of 11-over-par 151, which even a golfer with as fertile an imagination as Mickelson could not envision as being good enough to qualify for the weekend.</p>
        <p>''Eleven over making the cut?'' he said. ''I think there is no chance.''</p>
        <p>Much later in the day, Cabrera, who started on the back nine, birdied his last hole of the day -- No. 9 -- to finish at par for the first two rounds and prove Mickelson right as he missed the cut by a stroke.</p>
        <p>An argument could be made that surviving the cut was the less desirable alternative for Mickelson, who received a cortisone shot for the pain in his heavily taped left wrist so he could get through the first two rounds. He sustained the injury while hitting out of the rough on this course during a practice round last month.</p>
        <p>It was hard to tell which bothered Mickelson more, his injury or the indignity of essentially being punished for having gone out of his way to prepare for the year's second major.</p>
        <p>''It's disappointing to dream as a kid about winning the U.S. Open and spend all this time getting ready for it, and have the course setup injure you, you know?'' said Mickelson, who turns 36 Saturday. ''You're trying to win and hit great shots, but you're also trying to not end your career on one shot -- or at least suspend it for a while. That's a little disappointing.''</p>
        <p>It was a trying week for Mickelson, who was also dismayed when he was summoned Wednesday by officials of the United States Golf Association, who checked the black wrap on his wrist to make sure it was not a device that would aid his swing.</p>
        <p>It had to have seemed ludicrous to Mickelson, who has won three majors, to imagine his sore left wrist somehow giving him an unfair advantage. Although he refused to blame it for his errant play, it was clearly on his mind all week.</p>
        <p>Why else would he leave his driver out of his bag Friday? He chose to use a 3-wood and a hybrid club in its place, the better to avoid the rough. He was hoping to save his wrist from the physical trauma of hacking out of the tall grass.</p>
        <p>It was a good idea in theory, but then Mickelson went out and hit only 5 of 14 fairways in each of his rounds. His approach shots were not much crisper, which put more pressure on his putting.</p>
        <p>When Mickelson tied for second last year at Winged Foot, he ranked third in putts per round. On Friday, he four-putted from 45 feet on No. 10 and finished with 17 putts on his back nine and 32 for the round.</p>
        <p>After six holes Friday, Mickelson liked his chances to contend for his fourth major title. Twelve holes later, he was facing a grimmer reality. ''I felt I had made a great move early in the round,'' he said, ''but 7 through 10 did me in.''</p>
        <p>Cabrera's final birdie merely made it official.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
