<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On His First Visit to Fenway, Bonds Has Some Kind Words</title>
    <meta content="16bonds" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854832"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EED7153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="712" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On His First Visit to Fenway, Bonds Has Some Kind Words</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, June 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shortly before Barry Bonds of the Giants played his first game at Fenway Park on Friday night, he answered many questions with platitudes. But he responded to one directly and forcefully.</p>
        <p>Would it be important to play in the All-Star Game on July 10 in San Francisco, two weeks before his 43rd birthday?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shortly before Barry Bonds of the Giants played his first game at Fenway Park on Friday night, he answered many questions with platitudes. But he responded to one directly and forcefully.</p>
        <p>Would it be important to play in the All-Star Game on July 10 in San Francisco, two weeks before his 43rd birthday?</p>
        <p>''It would be important to me because it's at home, yes, definitely,'' Bonds said before the Red Sox defeated the Giants, 10-2, in the opener of a three-game interleague series. ''If it doesn't happen, it doesn't happen. But it would be important, yes.''</p>
        <p>Bonds had one single and one intentional walk, and made two outs, in the first appearance of his career in baseball's oldest ballpark. Dustin Pedroia, Boston's second baseman, went 5 for 5, including a two-run homer in the first, and drove in five runs as Juli치n Tav치rez (4-4) defeated Barry Zito (6-7).</p>
        <p>The Red Sox' victory ended a two-game losing streak and increased their lead in the American League East to eight and a half games against the second-place Yankees, who lost to the Mets on Friday, 2-0. The Red Sox had lost 9 of their previous 14 games since leading the division by 11 1/2 games May 29.</p>
        <p>For most superstars, an All-Star appearance for someone of Bonds's stature would seem to be a fait accompli. He came into Friday's game with 747 career home runs, eight behind Hank Aaron's record.</p>
        <p>Bonds is one of the greatest hitters to play the game. He grew up in San Francisco and has played there since 1993. He has been accused of using steroids for extra power, but he has never been revealed to have tested positive for steroids.</p>
        <p>Still, he is being investigated by a federal grand jury for alleged perjury in testimony about steroids. Last week, Bonds dropped to fourth place in fan balloting for the National League's three starting outfielders in the All-Star Game, behind Carlos Beltr치n of the Mets, Ken Griffey Jr. of the Cincinnati Reds and Alfonso Soriano of the Chicago Cubs.</p>
        <p>After the fan balloting, players will vote for three more outfielders. Should Bonds not be chosen by his peers, Manager Tony La Russa of the St. Louis Cardinals could name him among three nonpitchers, in conjunction with the wishes of the commissioner's office.</p>
        <p>This could make things intriguing. Bonds has rarely gone out of his way to charm fellow players, although Boston's David Ortiz greeted him warmly at the batting cage Friday.</p>
        <p>Bonds said that he had never been inside Fenway, although he drove past it during a World Series game in 2004 when visiting his son, who attended a boarding school near here. Bonds once said he would never want to play in Boston because the city was ''too racist.'' But Friday, he spoke only kind words of Boston.</p>
        <p>''I like the city,'' he said. ''It's pretty.''</p>
        <p>As for Fenway and its odd distances and angles, Bonds said: ''I'm trying to see everything. They say the park looks small. This looks bigger than Houston. Looks bigger than Philadelphia. That right field's a long way.''</p>
        <p>Bonds came into the game with 13 home runs, but only 2 since May 8. The last one came Monday night, after Bonds seemed to have trouble running while misplaying two balls in left field. On Friday, he said, slowly and evenly: ''I'm physically O.K. I'm all right.''</p>
        <p>But he also said that he was happy to serve as designated hitter in an American League park.</p>
        <p>''Time starts to work against you, eventually,'' Bonds said. ''So I'm just trying to hang in there the best I can.''</p>
        <p>In his first trip to the plate, in the first, Bonds pulled a pitch by Tav치rez far over the fence in right field that seemed to be a home run as it passed high above the foul pole.</p>
        <p>But the first-base umpire, Charlie Reliford, ruled it foul and Bonds pulled up from his home-run trot, smiled, returned to the batter's box and popped out as people in the stands waved signs that included large asterisks implying that any record he might set will be tainted.</p>
        <p>When asked after the game why he smiled at the umpire, Bonds smiled again and said, ''What am I supposed to do?''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
