<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pests That Bite And Slither? Call Snake Wranglers</title>
    <meta content="16snakes" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/us/16snakes.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854816"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Snakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rattlesnakes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Southern California Snake Removal</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinhauer, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McElroy, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Snakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reptiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E4D7153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="689" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pests That Bite And Slither? Call Snake Wranglers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pests That Bite and Slither? Call Snake Wranglers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER STEINHAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinhauer, Jennifer</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, June 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Snake wrangling business in Southern California is often bustling in spring, when snakes come out to mate, but business is especially booming this year because of extreme drought; thousands of rattlesnakes make their home in hills that surround Los Angeles and are now coming down into canyons and hillside properties in droves; they are in search of prey that have fled parched hills to find food and water in residential gardens; snake wranglers coax snakes from hiding and return them to wild; Jason McElroy, owner of Southern California Snake Removal, comments; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For Sam the Weimaraner, things had been quite grave. A rattlesnake bite to the snout -- the unhappy result of flower bed pursuit -- had left him unconscious, lying in his owner's garage in Topanga Canyon, an IV dangling from his paw.</p>
        <p>It was the second snake bite to the nose in three weeks. Action had to be taken. The snake whisperer was summoned.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Los Angeles, a drought has increased business for people who enjoy removing snakes from the property of others.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For Sam the Weimaraner, things had been quite grave. A rattlesnake bite to the snout -- the unhappy result of flower bed pursuit -- had left him unconscious, lying in his owner's garage in Topanga Canyon, an IV dangling from his paw.</p>
        <p>It was the second snake bite to the nose in three weeks. Action had to be taken. The snake whisperer was summoned.</p>
        <p>Throughout Los Angeles, there are a handful of people who have a deep adoration for limbless reptiles, and are willing, in fact eager, to remove them from the property of others. Armed with cloth gloves, a large plastic bin and a snake hook, which looks like a giant dental tool, they snoop under rocks and peek through piles of wood.</p>
        <p>''We remove them, release them and give them another chance to go on with their lives,'' said Jason McElroy, the owner of Southern California Snake Removal.</p>
        <p>While the snake wrangling business is often bustling in the spring, when snakes come out to mate, business is especially booming this year because of an extreme drought. (Mr. McElroy's usual two calls a day have swelled to roughly nine). Since last July, it has rained 3.21 inches in Los Angeles, almost 12 inches below normal for that period.</p>
        <p>Thousands of rattlesnakes make their home in the many hills that surround the city and are now coming down into the canyons and hillside properties in droves. They are in search of the prey that have fled the parched hills to find food and water in residential gardens.</p>
        <p>Unlike exterminators, who have little use for their prey, Mr. McElroy and his brethren are simpatico with the snakes. ''Rattlesnakes are a very important part of our hillside,'' said Mr. McElroy, who has collected snakes for 22 years. ''Every animal deserves the right to live.'' Snakes that are coaxed from hiding are removed to the wild, never to return to the residence where they were found, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. McElroy, who charges $125 a visit, documents his catches on his Web site, socalsnakeremoval.com. This is where you will find a pair of Southern Pacific rattlesnakes taken from Sherman Oaks, copulating at the time of removal.</p>
        <p>The only downside to the job is getting insurance. ''Most people hang up on you,'' Mr. McElroy lamented. ''I had to go through 20 insurance companies. I think it is because it costs like $200,000 to treat a snake bite.''</p>
        <p>One day this week Mr. McElroy dispatched a part-time worker, Darren Wilson, a fellow snake hunter, owner, admirer and wrangler, to the home of Judith Pierce, owner of the bitten dog, Sam. (Thanks to the quick house call by his veterinarian, Sam, 3, made a hearty comeback.)</p>
        <p>''I've lived here six years, and I've never seen snakes like this year,'' Mrs. Pierce said, noting that her gardener had already done in one rattlesnake with a shovel.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilson arrived and began to turn over stones and poke around in railroad ties in Mrs. Pierce's spectacular garden, which grows up a hill. He searched among the hydrangea, artichokes, sorrel and chives.</p>
        <p>''Uh huh, there is some lizard poop right here,'' he said. ''Sometimes you turn over a can, and you find four at a time.''</p>
        <p>He poked around near a hole in the stone wall. ''No. Just an earthworm and a nice-looking centipede,'' he said, somewhat disappointed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilson then happened upon a little shed full of holes and damp leaves. But all he turned up was a large rodent nest and one dead mouse.</p>
        <p>Deflated, he began to measure Mrs. Pierce's yard for a mesh snake fence, a barrier that would keep the elusive slithering beings at a distance. He glanced around the yard with a look of longing.</p>
        <p>''I wonder how many other species she's got around here?'' Mr. Wilson said.</p>
        <p>Finished, the snake whisperer went back to his brown Volvo and made his way out of the canyons, his plastic snake tub empty beside him.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people are like, 'What's going on with you and snakes?' '' he said. ''But I say, 'Once you get into them, you just can't stop.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
