<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Facing Fears, Up High Or Around the Campfire</title>
    <meta content="16summer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/nyregion/16summer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="SUMMER RITUALS: Into the Woods" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854812"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Summer Rituals | Into the Woods"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Newark (NJ)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E6D7153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1300" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Facing Fears, Up High Or Around the Campfire</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Camp, Conquering Fears and Hearing Cheers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY</byline>
      <dateline>CLARYVILLE, N.Y., June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As her classmates pulled on a rope to raise her above the forest floor in the giant swing, Tanisha Polanco, 15, announced that she needed a hug. And that she wanted to get down. And that she was going to cry.</p>
        <p>Then she told them to go ahead and hoist her all the way to the top, 50 feet in the air, and pulled the cord to release the swing with an unsettling jerk. First came freefall. Then, back and forth above her classmates, Tanisha swung, safely harnessed, hands over her face.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since the early 1970s, when environmental education began to take root, schools have been sending students into the woods to learn about nature  and themselves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As her classmates pulled on a rope to raise her above the forest floor in the giant swing, Tanisha Polanco, 15, announced that she needed a hug. And that she wanted to get down. And that she was going to cry.</p>
        <p>Then she told them to go ahead and hoist her all the way to the top, 50 feet in the air, and pulled the cord to release the swing with an unsettling jerk. First came freefall. Then, back and forth above her classmates, Tanisha swung, safely harnessed, hands over her face.</p>
        <p>''She's crying, she's crying,'' Marlon Sarango, 15, called out from below. He quickly adjusted his tone in the spirit of teamwork, telling Tanisha, ''You got guts, kid,'' and his classmates, ''Clap it up for her.''</p>
        <p>Tanisha's bravery, subsequent motion sickness, and willingness to tackle other high places later were among the life lessons at the Grade 8 Extended Classroom Experience, in which 48 students from the Dr. William H. Horton School in Newark spent three days at the Frost Valley Y.M.C.A. Camp here in the Catskill Mountains.</p>
        <p>Since the early 1970s, when environmental education began to take root, schools around the country, including dozens in and around New York, have been sending students into the woods to learn about nature -- and themselves.</p>
        <p>For the Newark students, whose school playground is a paved courtyard mostly enclosed by walls, the extended classroom in Ulster County provided a chance to taste hemlock needles; watch an owl regurgitate a pellet of indigestible fur and bones, then swallow a dead white mouse whole; and play pickup football in open fields surrounded by high hills, with an orchard, a roaring stream or two, a pond, a lake and a few horses in the distance.</p>
        <p>Horton, a public school for kindergarten through eighth grade in the North Ward, has been sending its oldest students to camp for the past five years.</p>
        <p>At a school where teachers say permission slips are required to visit Branch Brook Park, four blocks from campus, and local soccer fields must be signed up far in advance, the camp is a much-anticipated rite of passage, two weeks before graduation. It is the last hurrah before high school, when the students are dispersed around the city.</p>
        <p>''Once you're used to all your friends around, then you have to separate,'' said Dickson Hernandez, 14. ''Now we're together all the time, and now I want to stay for three weeks, because this is my last time with them.''</p>
        <p>This year, nearly half of Horton's 84 eighth graders did not make it to camp. Some lacked the points to qualify, based on the scoring system used for being on time, earning good grades and wearing tan and blue (the school's attempt to limit gang attire). And some parents were too worried about the unfamiliar experience.</p>
        <p>For those who piled into the 7:30 a.m. bus in Newark on Monday, it was a chance to learn how to adapt to new surroundings. Often, it was with humor.</p>
        <p>While Tanisha was fretting on her way up in the swing, Marlon teased her, saying: ''You can't sue! Remember the permission slip? You signed it!''</p>
        <p>His demeanor changed during his own ascent a few minutes later. ''Oh, God,'' he wailed, ''I don't want to cry in front of the girls.''</p>
        <p>Marlon pulled the cord when he was perhaps about a quarter as high as Tanisha, getting a far tamer ride. He immediately asked, in vain, for a second try.</p>
        <p>''That's part of life,'' said Donna Davis, a camp instructor supervising the swing. ''You only get one shot at things.''</p>
        <p>The first night here, Kier Bowers, a special education teacher, checked on a room in the girls' bunkhouse in the middle of the night, and found all six girls crowded into one bed. They insisted they were comfortable.</p>
        <p>The next morning, the students dug up a time capsule left by last year's Horton campers. Letters to the class of 2007 included rave reviews of the food, with its unlimited helpings -- it was described as either ''rockin','' ''banging'' or ''off the chain'' -- and some advice: ''You should make new friends and say hi to people, because you never know if that person can be your best friend.''</p>
        <p>That night around the campfire, Rakee Merritt, 13, produced the platonic form of toasted marshmallow, uniformly warmly brown.</p>
        <p>''I watched somebody do it on TV,'' he explained.</p>
        <p>It was perfect, until a splat of it landed on Luisa Moran's long black hair.</p>
        <p>Then Brian Smith, the science teacher, began the traditional ghost stories, with a disclaimer.</p>
        <p>''They're all fiction, just so nobody gets too freaked out,'' he said. ''A couple years ago somebody thought it was so scary they passed out. There's no need to pass out.''</p>
        <p>He told about the legend of the giant owl that haunted Frost Valley, and the story of how blood got on the stairs of a climbing tower (hint: it was from a counselor who ''didn't come back this year'' after testing out a giant rope ladder).</p>
        <p>The best story may have been ''How the Hooker Man Went So Very Wrong Last Year.''</p>
        <p>''Hooker Man,'' Mr. Smith explained, is a legendary tale about a man who used to hold a signal lantern for a railroad and lost his hand in a train accident, replacing it with a hook. Now his ghost swings the light in the darkness along the tracks, looking for the lost hand.</p>
        <p>''You can look into the woods and see the glow,'' Mr. Smith said, his face all scary by the campfire's light.</p>
        <p>Last year, Mr. Smith arranged for a student to take a flashlight into the woods and supply that glow, on cue. Only the student slipped on a rock and failed to reveal himself, even when Mr. Smith hollered for him. Campers had to comb the woods, and they all thought Hooker Man had gotten hungry.</p>
        <p>Alonzo Hamlett, 13, was confused by the story, stuck at first on a different meaning of the word hooker. ''What's he doing, standing on the corner with a purse?'' Alonzo said he had wondered. After the story, with a few too many fireflies doing Hooker Man imitations, the students retired to their bunkhouses, some of the girls linking arms for safety.</p>
        <p>Before the bus left on the last day, Jessenia Rodriguez, 14, who had remained resolutely on the ground during each challenge, slid her sneakers slowly across a jittery cable bridge over Pigeon Brook.</p>
        <p>On the way to lunch, Marlon and some friends reviewed their time away. ''I can say I overcame my fears swinging from a big tree,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Shone Nyemah, 14, remarked that for once, one of the girls had not cursed him out. ''If I was the president, I'd make everybody go to Frost Valley,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And even though she had stood at the top of the climbing tower crying for 10 minutes before hurling herself down, Tanisha said she would do it again.</p>
        <p>''I paid good money to come to Frost Valley, $20 for my shirt,'' she said. ''What's the point of paying $20 for a shirt if you don't do anything when you're here? I don't want to regret a lot of things. I came to Frost Valley to have fun. I was like the highest of them all.''</p>
        <p>After a three-hour bus ride, they were back in Newark, where signs near the school on North Seventh Street announce: This Building Under 24-Hour Surveillance, and R.I.P. John, Craig, Ab, Suave, Tripplet and Moofi.</p>
        <p>The only green on the ground grew in small patches behind chain link and wrought iron.</p>
        <p>Summer Rituals</p>
        <p>This article is part of a series, running on Saturdays through Labor Day weekend, on what makes summer special for people in and around New York.</p>
        <p>Summer Rituals | Into the Woods</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
