<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>He Wants to Make It Here, Again</title>
    <meta content="16araton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854839"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E6D6153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="884" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>He Wants to Make It Here, Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Roger Clemens could have been in Boston, in a matchup for the aged, going after Barry Bonds and the Giants with his best friend of his athletic old age, the pitch he calls Mr. Splitty. He could have had a pleasant, commuter-friendly night in Houston after facing the Mariners. But who more than Clemens knows that there is no fiercer and famous interleague baseball than the version played in New York, New York?</p>
        <p>Clemens is a man who lives unapologetically large, who consumes attention the way his beloved Hummers guzzle gas, whose competitive ego was made for the kind of seductions the Yankees do best. We may have kidded ourselves into thinking there was a serious, three-team competition for his partial-season services, but Willie Randolph didn't.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Roger Clemens could have been in Boston, in a matchup for the aged, going after Barry Bonds and the Giants with his best friend of his athletic old age, the pitch he calls Mr. Splitty. He could have had a pleasant, commuter-friendly night in Houston after facing the Mariners. But who more than Clemens knows that there is no fiercer and famous interleague baseball than the version played in New York, New York?</p>
        <p>Clemens is a man who lives unapologetically large, who consumes attention the way his beloved Hummers guzzle gas, whose competitive ego was made for the kind of seductions the Yankees do best. We may have kidded ourselves into thinking there was a serious, three-team competition for his partial-season services, but Willie Randolph didn't.</p>
        <p>''The Yankees pretty much get what they want,'' Randolph, the Mets' manager, said before the Mets finally got a victory last night after five straight defeats. Behind the pitching of Oliver Pérez and the hitting of José Reyes, they broke the Yankees' nine-game win streak, 2-0, in the opener of the Subway Series, Bronx style.</p>
        <p>It wasn't Clemens's fault. In his second start this season, he pitched six and one-third laudable innings, striking out eight Mets, including his former teammate in Toronto, Carlos Delgado, three times. Clemens allowed seven hits and the two runs, but demonstrated that after all the miles, all the calculated maneuvering and king's ransoms commanded, some authority higher than George Steinbrenner still loves him.</p>
        <p>After three years of supposedly coveting more simple pleasures, of reveling in home cooking and comforts in Houston, Clemens has reattached his legendary name to the most illustrious brand in American team sports. As Dale Earnhardt Jr. demonstrated just this week, there comes a time when family must take a back seat to a more appealing professional relationship.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, Earnhardt Jr. announced that he was leaving his late father's company to join Hendrick Motorsports, which is to Nascar what the Yankees were to baseball during the first half of the Joe Torre era. Rick Hendrick's company, run with a similar corporate methodology to Steinbrenner's, has won six Nascar championships and 10 of 14 races this season. While Earnhardt is the sport's richest driver, he has never won its championship, making him Nascar's Alex Rodriguez, by 21st century measures, and hoping to be Clemens, circa the late 20th.</p>
        <p>It was in 1999 that Clemens came to the conclusion that if he was going to win a championship ring, New York was the place to do it. He engineered his way from Toronto to New York, punctuated a four-game World Series takeout of Atlanta, swept away his personal postseason frustrations and has lived a charmed -- some would dare say unbelievable -- baseball life ever since.</p>
        <p>Witness the latest minor miracle as Clemens was working his way back to the majors and making his return last weekend against the Pirates: the rapid halving of the Red Sox' 14 1/2 game lead in the American League East. Until the Yankees' resurgence, Clemens was looking at the possibility of a summer with only one significant date to look forward to, his 45th birthday on Aug. 4.</p>
        <p>''It's been really nice since I've been back, watching these guys do their thing,'' he said after a fine catch by the rookie Carlos Gómez at the left-field wall with two on in the fourth inning against Miguel Cairo resulted in a double play, pulling Pérez through his toughest spot.</p>
        <p>The defeat cost the Yankees a game to the Red Sox, who increased their lead to 8 1/2 games by defeating the Giants. But for now, at least, the death watch is over, the Yankees are solidly in the wild-card race and 97 games remain, time for many more peaks, valleys and opportunities for Clemens to earn his keep as the most spectacularly compensated and celebrated No. 4 starter in the history of the game.</p>
        <p>''Six and a third, two runs, I'll take my chances,'' Torre said, evaluating Clemens. ''Every time.''</p>
        <p>He knows his team will do better with the bats but, recent surge and all, a larger question looms. More than baseball's brand name, can the Yankees be Clemens's chariot to another championship? Can they be the best team, or do they just play one now in those ubiquitous YES Network reruns?</p>
        <p>The last title is seven years behind them. It is eight years since Clemens first slipped into pinstripes to dubious clubhouse glances.</p>
        <p>''As a matter of fact, when he became a Yankee, it took a little while for us to warm to him as a team,'' said Randolph, then a coach on Torre's staff.</p>
        <p>There was the matter of all those confrontations during Clemens's years in Boston and Toronto, so many fastballs under sturdy Yankee chins. Clemens was never the easiest person to like, or figure, whether he was getting himself tossed from a Boston-Oakland playoff game in the second inning after walking Randolph (of all people) in 1990, or firing a fastball and later the jagged edge of a broken at Mike Piazza a full decade later.</p>
        <p>''He's still an excellent pitcher,'' Randolph said, before getting a first-hand look at the 44-year-old version.</p>
        <p>Still a strange Texas dude who recognizes the many bottom-line and potential end-game benefits of working in New York, New York.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
