<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jeter Lets Chance to Know What's Coming Sail On By</title>
    <meta content="16pins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/sports/baseball/16pins.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854833"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Arizona Diamondbacks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Associated Press</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jeter, Derek</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EED7153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="652" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jeter Lets Chance to Know What's Coming Sail On By</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jeter Lets Chance to Know What’s Coming Sail On By</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Derek Jeter had a chance for some authentic, inside information about how another major league team planned to pitch him. But Jeter, the Yankees' shortstop, refused to listen yesterday.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to know,'' Jeter said. ''As far as what pitchers do, I really don't care. All I want to know is what they've got. I don't get into all that stuff. It makes you think too much. I don't want to think.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Derek Jeter had a chance for some authentic, inside information about how another major league team planned to pitch him. Yet the Yankees’ shortstop didn’t want to listen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Derek Jeter had a chance for some authentic, inside information about how another major league team planned to pitch him. But Jeter, the Yankees' shortstop, refused to listen yesterday.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to know,'' Jeter said. ''As far as what pitchers do, I really don't care. All I want to know is what they've got. I don't get into all that stuff. It makes you think too much. I don't want to think.''</p>
        <p>When the Arizona Diamondbacks left Yankee Stadium on Thursday, they left behind their scouting report of the Yankees' hitters. The Associated Press found the report on the floor of the visitors' dugout and published it.</p>
        <p>The Diamondbacks' report said that Jeter struggled with pitches down and in and chased sliders away. The report urged pitchers to mix locations and types of pitches on the first pitch because Jeter is an aggressive hitter.</p>
        <p>Jeter, though, said he never tried to guess along with a pitcher. He said that he looked for a fastball on every pitch and reacted to breaking balls. If he tried to anticipate other pitches, he said, he would be prone to swinging at balls.</p>
        <p>''If you're pitching against me, tell me what's coming,'' Jeter said. ''I wouldn't want to know. If I look for, like, a curveball? As soon as I see it, no matter where it is, I'll swing at it.''</p>
        <p>The report on Johnny Damon said he struggled with soft stuff against right-handers and must be kept honest with fastballs up and in from left-handers. Damon said the report was fairly accurate.</p>
        <p>''It works at times,'' he said. ''Especially when you're struggling, it's real tough to hit certain pitches. It's fair, but it's also something that I'm aware of. They know if they feed me too many fastballs, I'll get 'em.''</p>
        <p>The Diamondbacks lost all three games of the series, and they warned their pitchers to be especially aware of Alex Rodriguez and Bobby Abreu, who each hit safely in all three.</p>
        <p>In the report, BB refers to balls, CH is changeup, FB is fastball and RISP means runners in scoring position. To ladder a fastball means to throw progressively higher to get the hitter to chase a bad pitch. A cripple hitter is one who jumps on a pitch when he is ahead in the count.</p>
        <p>This is what the report said about Rodriguez, Abreu and others:</p>
        <p>Rodriguez: ''HOT right now. Chases a lot of BB's w/2-strikes, both away and in dirt. CH is fine when away. (vs. left-handers) Hard in, soft away. Ladder FB w/2-strikes.''</p>
        <p>Abreu: ''HOT right now. Good guy to crowd once you're ahead. Hammers 1st pitch FB's away w/RISP.''</p>
        <p>Jorge Posada: ''Sits on off-speed when pitcher is ahead. ... Good cripple hitter.''</p>
        <p>Melky Cabrera: ''Need to ladder the FB w/2-strikes. Chases up A LOT! ... Hacker throughout count.''</p>
        <p>IGAWA MAKES PROGRESS -- Kei Igawa pitched well again Thursday for Class AAA Scranton/Wilkes-Barre, allowing one run in six innings to defeat Charlotte. Igawa is 2-2 with a 2.88 earned run average in four starts, with 27 strikeouts and 7 walks in 25 innings, and he could return to the Yankees soon.</p>
        <p>''I don't think he has to accomplish anything else down there,'' said General Manager Brian Cashman, who invested $46 million in Igawa last winter. ''Right now, people need to pitch to hold onto their jobs.''</p>
        <p>That was a reference to starter Tyler Clippard and long reliever Sean Henn, either of whom could be replaced by Igawa. Clippard faces the Mets today.</p>
        <p>DAMON OUT, PHELPS IN -- Johnny Damon was scratched from the lineup last night with a strained abdominal muscle. He was replaced at designated hitter by Josh Phelps, who has essentially lost his spot as the first baseman to Miguel Cairo.</p>
        <p>''Defensively, he's stabilized our infield,'' Joe Torre said of Cairo. ''We're just going to stay with him at this point in time.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
