<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Lower Manhattan Recovers, Many Question Use of Subsidies</title>
    <meta content="16chaseQ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/nyregion/16chaseQ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854830"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEWS ANALYSIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Morgan, J P, Chase &amp; Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEFD7153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Lower Manhattan Recovers, Many Question Use of Subsidies</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">As Lower Manhattan Recovers, Many Question Use of Subsidies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES V. BAGLI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JPMorgan Chase's announcement on Thursday that it would build a $2 billion investment banking headquarters downtown and move 7,000 employees there was only the latest illustration of how far Lower Manhattan has come since the terrorist attack on the World Trade Center.</p>
        <p>But it also raises the question of whether the generous corporate tax breaks and cash grants that once seemed so critical to propping up the beleaguered district are still necessary. Is it time to turn off the public subsidy spigot? Some critics insist that it is.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The generous corporate tax breaks and cash grants that once seemed so critical to propping up downtown are being questioned.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JPMorgan Chase's announcement on Thursday that it would build a $2 billion investment banking headquarters downtown and move 7,000 employees there was only the latest illustration of how far Lower Manhattan has come since the terrorist attack on the World Trade Center.</p>
        <p>But it also raises the question of whether the generous corporate tax breaks and cash grants that once seemed so critical to propping up the beleaguered district are still necessary. Is it time to turn off the public subsidy spigot? Some critics insist that it is.</p>
        <p>A noticeably pleased Gov. Eliot Spitzer, standing in front of Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg, Chase executives and Port Authority officials at a news conference on Thursday, declared that the bank's decision to move to Lower Manhattan ''demonstrates again that downtown is the investment capital of the world.''</p>
        <p>Mayor Bloomberg added that it was a ''tremendous vote of confidence in Lower Manhattan'' and ''evidence that our strategy is working.''</p>
        <p>Sure enough, the stubbornly high vacancy rate for prime downtown office space has fallen to 5.9 percent from 13.7 in 2004, and rents are rising rapidly, according to Cushman &amp; Wakefield, a real estate broker.</p>
        <p>Hermès, Tiffany, Thomas Pink, Hickey Freeman, BMW and other high-end retailers have flocked to Lower Manhattan. In May, the Paramount Group bought the 47-story tower at 60 Wall Street for $1.2 billion, or $750 per square foot, the highest price ever paid for a downtown office building.</p>
        <p>And now Chase will build a 42-story glass tower, designed by Kohn Pederson Fox, at the corner of Greenwich and Cedar Streets. It got a great deal, agreeing to pay the Port Authority $300 million up front for a 92-year lease.</p>
        <p>Jamie Dimon, Chase's chief executive, highlighted the bank's 200-year-old roots downtown, saying: ''We're going back home. We feel good about it.''</p>
        <p>The governor and mayor defended their decision to provide a highly profitable bank with lucrative tax breaks and cash grants by saying those subsidies were ordinary.</p>
        <p>''Virtually all the incentives are off the shelf, available to any employer'' who moves to the trade center area, the governor said. They are ''well within what makes sense for the state and the city.''</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Spitzer only grudgingly dribbled out the dollar value of the subsidies during the conference. After first saying they were worth $20 million, then $100 million, then $160 million, he finally put the total value at ''north of $200 million.''</p>
        <p>Afterward, state officials indicated that the final number was about $240 million. One Chase executive, who requested anonymity, said the governor was low-balling the number.</p>
        <p>State and city officials contend that the Chase deal is far more parsimonious than the extraordinarily generous subsidy package given to Goldman Sachs in 2005 to build a new headquarters at Battery Park City. Critics put the value of that deal, which is now almost universally reviled by public officials, at more than $650 million.</p>
        <p>Unlike Goldman, state officials say, Chase did not receive $1.65 million in tax-free Liberty Bonds. And Chase is paying $300 million for its site, $140 million more than Goldman, and is making bigger payments in lieu of taxes. Besides, they say, the coffers for Chase's $50 million rent subsidy are now empty, and the commercial rent tax exemption expires in 2010.</p>
        <p>Everyone politely forgot about Chase's threats in April to relocate thousands of employees to Stamford, Conn., if it did not receive a bigger incentive package than the city and state were willing to offer. On Wednesday, the mayor of Stamford confirmed that the bank was bluffing, saying Chase officials had never contacted him.</p>
        <p>A Port Authority executive said: ''The deal was always 98 percent about the real estate transaction, not the incentives.''</p>
        <p>Bettina Damiani, director of Good Jobs New York, a private watchdog group, asked: ''Did we get duped? We certainly want to keep JPMorgan in the city. But it's highly questionable whether the bank picked that site downtown because of the subsidies. Historically, corporations make locational decisions based on the availability of public transportation, where their work force lives, any number of other reasons. Subsidies are never at the top of the list.''</p>
        <p>She said, however, that the incentives might have been necessary after Sept. 11. Even a year ago, the district's future as a world financial center was very much in doubt. Lehman Brothers, a downtown stalwart, had long ago fled to Midtown, and many feared that Merrill Lynch would be the next to go. The rebuilding effort was mired in controversy and delays, while the World Trade Center memorial was nearly $500 million over budget. But none of that is true today.</p>
        <p>It is time to turn off the public incentives, Ms. Damiani said. ''But it'll never stop,'' she added, ''because public officials seem so willing to give away our tax breaks for a press conference.''</p>
        <p>Governor Spitzer said yesterday that ''the spigot will be turned off when the benefits expire.''</p>
        <p>''There will always be people who say you paid too much, you paid too little,'' he said. ''Our goal is a booming downtown.''</p>
        <p>NEWS ANALYSIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
