<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blast Destroys Sunni Mosque in Iraq, Raising Fears of Reprisals</title>
    <meta content="16iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/world/middleeast/16iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854754"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sunni Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosques</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Basra (Iraq)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Samarra (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rubin, Alissa J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sunni Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sunni Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E1D9153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blast Destroys Sunni Mosque in Iraq, Raising Fears of Reprisals</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Blast Destroys Sunni Mosque in Iraq, Raising Fears of Reprisals</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISSA J. RUBIN; Iraqi employees of The New York Times contributed reporting from Baghdad, Basra, Najaf and Diyala.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rubin, Alissa J</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, June 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Powerful explosion reduces large Sunni Arab mosque to rubble near Basra; its destruction appears to signal that cycle of revenge violence, following bombing of Shiite shrine in Samarra, has not entirely unfolded; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A powerful explosion that reduced a large Sunni Arab mosque to rubble near the southern city of Basra on Friday morning appeared to signal that the cycle of revenge violence, following the bombing of a sacred Shiite shrine in Samarra on Wednesday, has not entirely unfolded.</p>
        <p>Although there had been scattered reprisal attacks on Sunni mosques in the hours after the Samarra shrine's minarets were demolished Wednesday, strenuous calls for restraint by political and religious figures, and strict security measures, appeared to halt broader violence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An Iraqi official said violence could erupt this weekend when curfews, imposed after an attack on a sacred Shiite shrine, are lifted in Baghdad and other areas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A powerful explosion that reduced a large Sunni Arab mosque to rubble near the southern city of Basra on Friday morning appeared to signal that the cycle of revenge violence, following the bombing of a sacred Shiite shrine in Samarra on Wednesday, has not entirely unfolded.</p>
        <p>Although there had been scattered reprisal attacks on Sunni mosques in the hours after the Samarra shrine's minarets were demolished Wednesday, strenuous calls for restraint by political and religious figures, and strict security measures, appeared to halt broader violence.</p>
        <p>However, there were fears that violence could erupt once curfews were lifted in Baghdad and other areas over the weekend, and that, like last year, the cycle of reprisal killings would unwind over weeks and months. ''We won't see so much right away,'' said an official in the office of Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki. ''It will come later.''</p>
        <p>A United States Air Force F-16 crashed early Friday morning while flying a close air support mission. No information was available on whether the pilot, who was the only crew member, survived. It was one of several recent signs of an intensification in the use of air power to monitor insurgent activities and search for cars rigged as suicide bombs.</p>
        <p>Five American soldiers died in three separate attacks on Thursday, the American military said in a statement. Three were killed by an explosion near their vehicle in Kirkuk Province. One died from small-arms fire in Diyala, and a fifth died from a noncombat injury, the military said.</p>
        <p>While most of the country outside Basra was calm on Friday, clashes continued between Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia and local groups in troubled Diyala Province. Civilians in Diyala, many of whom are in mixed families, said they were deeply distressed by the cycle of bombings and reprisals.</p>
        <p>''Although my family is Sunni, my parents were buried in Najaf, which is holy to Shiites,'' said Sheik Fadhil al-Shammeri, a farmer in Diyala.</p>
        <p>''Samarra has always been in our hearts, but there are extremists who deviated from religion,'' he said. ''Al Qaeda is the head of the snake, and it should be cut in order to keep Iraq safe from any rift.''</p>
        <p>He added that his wife was from a well-known Sunni tribe, but that ''she was crying when she heard the news of the attack on the shrine in Samarra. Why would they want to kill everything inside us? We and the Shiite are brothers; two of my daughters are married to Shiites and I hope my third one will too.''</p>
        <p>The explosion at the Talha Bin al-Zubair mosque, which is in a suburb about 10 miles south of Basra, occurred at dawn, according to reports from residents. Talha Bin al-Zubair was a companion of the Prophet Muhammad, and the mosque was popular among local Sunni Arabs and pilgrims, but had been visited less in recent years because of the security troubles in Basra.</p>
        <p>''We heard two big explosions at dawn,'' said Shaeema Fadel, who is from Zubair, the neighborhood where the mosque is located. ''We didn't know where they were. Then, early in the morning, we discovered where.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''I hold terror cells responsible because they want to divide us.''</p>
        <p>Accounts varied of how the bombers managed to enter the mosque. At about 1,200 square yards, the building would be difficult to destroy without a large explosive charge -- or several of them.</p>
        <p>''Photographers and cameramen entered the mosque asking to take photographs, and they put bombs inside it,'' said Gen. Ali Hamadi, a security official in Basra. However, local residents said they saw uniformed men enter the mosque just before the explosion.</p>
        <p>The Basra area is controlled by several Shiite militias with links to the central government; some are tied to the Badr Organization, which is connected to the Supreme Islamic Iraqi Council, led by Abdul Aziz al-Hakim. Others are allied with the Mahdi Army, the militia of the cleric Moktada al-Sadr.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maliki condemned the Basra bombing, ordering a curfew there until further notice. A curfew in Baghdad that began Wednesday was extended until Sunday morning.</p>
        <p>In Samarra, two civilians were shot to death and four were wounded by Iraqi and American military snipers who were on a joint patrol to enforce the curfew, the Iraqi police said. By nightfall, hundreds of troops from the Interior Ministry and the Iraqi Army had arrived in the city.</p>
        <p>During Friday Prayer throughout the country, Shiite and Sunni clerics generally continued to try to tamp down passions. But leading imams loyal to Mr. Sadr attacked the government, even though members of Parliament loyal to Mr. Sadr have until recently been a crucial component of Mr. Maliki's coalition.</p>
        <p>In Kufa, one of Mr. Sadr's strongholds, Sheik Salah al-Obaidi accused the Maliki government of being captive to the Americans. ''They say, 'When things are quiet, we will rebuild the shrine,' and this is what the occupation wants them to say,'' the sheik said.</p>
        <p>''These are elected governments,'' he said. ''Why this silence? They kept silent to satisfy the occupier and America because the occupation has appointed them and it bans any party that seeks to rebuild the shrine.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
