<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Broad Effort to Get Senate To Return to Immigration</title>
    <meta content="16immig" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/washington/16immig.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854797"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Immigrants</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reid, Harry (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E1D8153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="979" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Broad Effort to Get Senate To Return to Immigration</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Broad Effort to Resurrect Immigration Bill</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roman Catholic Church and many business, labor and Hispanic groups complained about various provisions of immigration bill, but when it appeared that bill might be dying, they mobilized scores of lobbyists and put pressure on Senate and majority leader Harry Reid to revive bill (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At 4:30 p.m. on June 7, the Roman Catholic Church defied the sponsors of a comprehensive immigration bill and urged the Senate not to move toward final passage of the measure without significant changes.</p>
        <p>A few hours later, after the Senate rejected his motion to end debate on the bill, the Senate majority leader, Harry Reid, Democrat of Nevada, pulled it from the Senate floor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Various groups had complained about provisions of a comprehensive immigration bill, but when it appeared to be dying, they were flummoxed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At 4:30 p.m. on June 7, the Roman Catholic Church defied the sponsors of a comprehensive immigration bill and urged the Senate not to move toward final passage of the measure without significant changes.</p>
        <p>A few hours later, after the Senate rejected his motion to end debate on the bill, the Senate majority leader, Harry Reid, Democrat of Nevada, pulled it from the Senate floor.</p>
        <p>His action prompted advocates to rally behind the bill. Within 24 hours, the Catholic Church and many business, labor and Hispanic groups were urging the Senate to resurrect it.</p>
        <p>They had all complained about various provisions of the measure. But when it appeared that the bill might be dying, they were flummoxed. Separately and together, they mobilized scores of lobbyists. They put pressure on the Senate and on Mr. Reid, in particular, to revive the bill.</p>
        <p>''We were not happy with the bill,'' said J. Kevin Appleby of the United States Conference of Catholic Bishops. ''But we did not want it to die.''</p>
        <p>In public, Mr. Reid and the White House blamed each other for the apparent demise of the legislation, while conservative politicians and talk radio hosts criticized it as ''amnesty'' for illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>But behind the scenes, Mr. Reid was inundated with telephone calls, letters, faxes and e-mail urging him to bring the bill back up. The pleas came from groups as diverse as the National Restaurant Association, the National Council of La Raza, the New England Apple Council and the business software company Oracle.</p>
        <p>Farmers and ranchers from coast to coast told the Senate to get the job done.</p>
        <p>''We are tired of the politics, we're tired of the excuses, and we're not going away until Congress reforms the broken immigration system,'' said Maureen J. Torrey, who grows vegetables and raises dairy cows in western New York.</p>
        <p>Unite Here, a union representing apparel, hotel and laundry workers, said the bill could be a boon to illegal immigrants who live in constant fear of being arrested and deported.</p>
        <p>''We are the biggest union in the state of Nevada,'' said Thomas G. Snyder, political director of Unite Here, which has nearly 60,000 members in Las Vegas casinos. ''We have a long relationship with Harry Reid. He knows where we stand on immigration reform. We have been in constant contact with his office.''</p>
        <p>Business trade associations weighed in on Monday, four days after the bill appeared to have collapsed.</p>
        <p>The United States Chamber of Commerce, the National Association of Manufacturers, the National Federation of Independent Business and the Business Roundtable told the Senate to go back to work.</p>
        <p>The impasse could provide a ''cooling-off period,'' they said in a letter to all senators, urging them to pass a comprehensive immigration bill.</p>
        <p>Randel K. Johnson, a vice president of the Chamber of Commerce, said the efforts of business executives, combined with President Bush's visit to Capitol Hill on Tuesday, ''created an echo-chamber effect.''</p>
        <p>The message resonated with the Senate Republican leader, Mitch McConnell of Kentucky, and Senator Jon Kyl of Arizona, the chief Republican architect of the bill, who kept plugging for a deal.</p>
        <p>Laura Foote Reiff, a lobbyist for companies that employ millions of immigrants in the hotel, construction and health care industries, fired off a letter to Senate leaders expressing ''deep concern and distress with the Senate's perceived inability to complete work on the bill.''</p>
        <p>In opposing the effort to limit debate on June 7, the United States Conference of Catholic Bishops said the Senate needed more time to correct ''significant flaws'' in the bill: ''the evisceration of the family preference system'' and a legalization program that ''may well be unworkable.''</p>
        <p>The bishops cited those concerns when it urged the Senate to take up the bill.</p>
        <p>''The issue of immigration is too important for our elected officials to abandon,'' said Bishop Gerald R. Barnes of San Bernardino, Calif. ''It cannot wait for several more years. Human beings are suffering and dying.''</p>
        <p>Hispanic officials echoed that concern in urging Mr. Reid to revive the bill.</p>
        <p>''Immigration is a life and death issue,'' said Representative Luis V. Gutierrez, Democrat of Illinois and chairman of the immigration task force of the Congressional Hispanic Caucus. ''Each day that goes by without action means more people will die in the desert.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush did his part to whip up support for the bill by cajoling Republican senators and giving a speech on the issue. That put pressure on Mr. Reid to respond.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Reid was pummeled in some newspaper editorials and op-ed columns, which said it was shameful for him to let the bill die.</p>
        <p>James P. Manley, a spokesman for Mr. Reid, said the news media criticism had ''zero effect'' on the majority leader. Many have questioned the strength of his commitment, but Mr. Reid insisted, ''I have every desire to complete this legislation.''</p>
        <p>On Friday, Mr. Reid said he would keep the Senate in session on weekends if necessary to complete work on the immigration bill this month.</p>
        <p>Aides to Mr. McConnell, the Republican leader, said he had not promised to deliver any specific number of votes for efforts to shut off debate on the bill.</p>
        <p>Only seven Republicans voted to end debate on June 7. Mr. Reid and the authors of the bill hope that more Republicans will support such a motion if they are allowed to offer amendments.</p>
        <p>One amendment would add $4.4 billion to the bill to increase border security and enforcement of the immigration law. Others would expand a guest worker program for low-skill workers and provide more temporary visas and green cards for high-tech professionals sought by companies like Microsoft, Intel and Google.</p>
        <p>One of the more contentious amendments, proposed by Senator Kay Bailey Hutchison, Republican of Texas, would require illegal immigrants to return to their home countries before they could obtain even temporary legal status.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
