<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Podiums Of London Welcome Newcomers</title>
    <meta content="16orch" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/arts/music/16orch.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854727"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Philharmonia Orchestra</org>
        <org class="online_producer">London Symphony Orchestra</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Barbican Center</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Royal Opera House</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Covent Garden</org>
        <org class="online_producer">English National Opera</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E7D9153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Podiums Of London Welcome Newcomers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Podiums of London Welcome Newcomers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, June 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The three leading orchestras of this major music capital are now going through changes in artistic leadership. All the newcomers have been in action this week. It's as if London had deliberately planned a showcase of the new guard for the benefit of those here for the reopening of the Royal Festival Hall.</p>
        <p>On Monday night, as I reported earlier, Christoph von Dohnanyi, the principal conductor of the Philharmonia Orchestra, conducted works by Ligeti and Beethoven as part of the grand concert to reinaugurate this splendidly renovated hall. But on Tuesday his successor, Esa-Pekka Salonen, who becomes principal conductor next year, took the Philharmonia back to the hall for a formidable program: the English composer Oliver Knussen's Violin Concerto and Mahler's 100-minute Third Symphony.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The three leading orchestras of this major music capital are now going through changes in artistic leadership.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The three leading orchestras of this major music capital are now going through changes in artistic leadership. All the newcomers have been in action this week. It's as if London had deliberately planned a showcase of the new guard for the benefit of those here for the reopening of the Royal Festival Hall.</p>
        <p>On Monday night, as I reported earlier, Christoph von Dohnanyi, the principal conductor of the Philharmonia Orchestra, conducted works by Ligeti and Beethoven as part of the grand concert to reinaugurate this splendidly renovated hall. But on Tuesday his successor, Esa-Pekka Salonen, who becomes principal conductor next year, took the Philharmonia back to the hall for a formidable program: the English composer Oliver Knussen's Violin Concerto and Mahler's 100-minute Third Symphony.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday Valery Gergiev, who became the principal conductor of the London Symphony Orchestra in January, led it in a program of Stravinsky, Debussy and Prokofiev at the Barbican Center. Mr. Gergiev succeeds Colin Davis, whose fruitful 11-year tenure with this self-governing orchestra will surely be regarded as a historic pairing of maestro and musicians.</p>
        <p>The dynamic Russian conductor Vladimir Jurowski, who takes over the London Philharmonic Orchestra this fall from Kurt Masur, left no doubt that he is a musician of consequence in his performances with it during the gala concert on Monday.</p>
        <p>So London's major symphony orchestras have replaced veteran maestros, all in the vicinity of 80, with an exciting roster of much younger artists. Mr. Jurowski is just 35. Mr. Salonen, an ageless dynamo, is about to turn 49. Mr. Gergiev is the oldster at 54.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salonen's compelling concert on Tuesday suggested what audiences here can expect. Impetuous and electric, he is a risk taker. An accomplished composer, Mr. Salonen conducts contemporary music with particular authority, as his riveting account of Mr. Knussen's concerto (2001-2), with the superb violinist Christian Tetzlaff, made clear.</p>
        <p>On its surface this vigorous, smart and pungent 17-minute piece is a modernistic homage to the Baroque violin concerto, with a fantastical first movement, Recitative; a pensive, slow Aria; and a bouncy concluding Gigue. The solo part, especially in the first movement, is wildly frenetic. Mr. Tetzlaff played with breathless energy, myriad colorings and thrilling command.</p>
        <p>In the Mahler Mr. Salonen emphasized the astringent daring of the harmonic language and went for sheer orchestral onslaught during the many moments of exuberance and savagery. Yet he made sense of the score, laying it out with the clarity of a fellow composer.</p>
        <p>There was aching tenderness in the lilting Menuetto and weighty, rich-toned melancholy in the fourth movement (Sehr langsam), with its quietly devastating setting of an elegiac text by Nietzsche, sung with enveloping beauty by the mezzo-soprano Michelle DeYoung.</p>
        <p>In the fifth movement the Ladies of the Philharmonia Voices and the boy choristers of Westminster Abbey sang sweetly in the angelic setting of a poem from ''Des Knaben Wunderhorn.''</p>
        <p>Unlike the exciting yet judicious Mr. Davis, Mr. Gergiev is all instinct, fervor and daring. He can be an erratic interpreter, partly because he maintains such an absurdly punishing schedule. But when he is great, he is really great -- not just exciting but probing and sensitive -- as he was on Wednesday with the London Symphony.</p>
        <p>Stravinsky's Symphony in Three Movements sounded not just like an ingenious Neo-Classical score but also like relentlessly rhythmic music provoked, as Stravinsky explained, by newsreel images of World War II.</p>
        <p>Prokofiev's Violin Concerto No. 1, with Vadim Repin as soloist, emerged as an engrossing fantasy of restless rhythm, shifting moods, bittersweet lyricism and grotesquerie. The impressive Mr. Repin played with his typical combination of Russian intensity and Zenlike calm.</p>
        <p>In three Debussy piano preludes, orchestrated by Colin Matthews, Mr. Gergiev drew lush sonorities from the orchestra. And the dramatically sweeping, incisive and atmospheric account of Stravinsky's ''Petrouchka'' could have come only from someone who, like Mr. Gergiev, conducts this score as regularly in the ballet house as in the concert hall.</p>
        <p>London looks poised to become a model for courageous artistic leadership in the international orchestra world. And with the brilliant 47-year-old English conductor Antonio Pappano, who took over as music director of the Royal Opera House, Covent Garden, in 2002, and the impressive 32-year-old Edward Gardner as the new music director of the English National Opera, the city should be making operatic news as well.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
