<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reports of Forced Labor at Brick Kilns Unsettle China</title>
    <meta content="16china" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/world/asia/16china.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Shanxi Province (China)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">French, Howard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Heng Tinghan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Child Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EED7153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1088" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reports of Forced Labor at Brick Kilns Unsettle China</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Reports of Forced Labor Unsettle China</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">French, Howard W</byline>
      <dateline>SHANGHAI, June 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Unfolding labor scandal in central China involves kidnapping of hundreds of children who reportedly have been forced to work under brutal conditions in brick kilns of Shanxi Province; manhunt has begun for Heng Tinghan, foreman of one of kilns, where 31 enslaved workers were recently rescued; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Su Jinduo and Su Jinpeng, brother and sister, were traveling home by bus from a vacation visit to Qingdao during the Chinese New Year when they disappeared.</p>
        <p>Cheated out of their money when they sought to buy a ticket for the final leg of the journey home, their father, Su Jianjun, said in an interview, they were taken in by a woman who provided them with warm shelter and a meal on a cold winter night. She also offered them a chance to earn enough money to pay their fare by helping her sell fruit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In central China, hundreds of adults and children have reportedly been kidnapped and forced to work under brutal conditions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Su Jinduo and Su Jinpeng, brother and sister, were traveling home by bus from a vacation visit to Qingdao during the Chinese New Year when they disappeared.</p>
        <p>Cheated out of their money when they sought to buy a ticket for the final leg of the journey home, their father, Su Jianjun, said in an interview, they were taken in by a woman who provided them with warm shelter and a meal on a cold winter night. She also offered them a chance to earn enough money to pay their fare by helping her sell fruit.</p>
        <p>The next thing they knew, however, they were being loaded onto a minibus with several other children and taken to a factory in the next province, where they were pressed into service making bricks. Several days later, the boy, 16, escaped along with another boy and managed to reach home. A few days later, Mr. Su was able to rescue his daughter, 18.</p>
        <p>This story and many others like it have swept China in recent days in an unfolding labor scandal in central China that involves the kidnapping of hundreds of children, most in their teens but some as young as 8.</p>
        <p>The children, and many adults, reportedly, have been forced to work under brutal conditions -- scantily clothed, unpaid and often fed little more than water and steamed buns -- in the brick kilns of Shanxi Province.</p>
        <p>As the stories spread across China this week, played prominently in newspaper headlines and on the Internet, a manhunt was announced midweek for Heng Tinghan, the foreman of one of the kilns, where 31 enslaved workers were recently rescued.</p>
        <p>Mr. Su said his children were brought to the factory around midnight of the day they vanished. Once there, they were told they would have to make bricks. ''You will start working in the morning, so get some sleep, and don't lose your bowls, or you will have to pay for them,'' he said the children were told. ''They also charged them 50 renminbi for a blanket.'' That is equivalent to about $6.50.</p>
        <p>Mr. Su managed to recover his children after only a matter of days at the kiln, but many other parents have been less fortunate, losing contact with children for months or years. As stories of forced labor at the brick kilns have spread, hundreds of parents have petitioned local authorities to help them find their children and crack down on the kilns.</p>
        <p>In some cases, according to Chinese news media reports, parents have also come together to try to rescue their children, placing little stock in the local authorities, who are sometimes in collusion with the operators of the kilns. Other reports have said that local authorities, including labor inspectors, have taken children from freshly closed kilns and resold them to other factories.</p>
        <p>The director of the legal department of the Shanxi Province Worker's Union said it was hard to monitor the kilns because of their location in isolated areas.</p>
        <p>''Those factories are located in very remote places and most them are illegal entities, without any legal registration, so it is very hard for people outside to know what is going on there,'' said the union official, Zhang Xiaosuo. ''We are now doing a province-wide investigation into them, both the legal and illegal ones, to look into labor issues there.''</p>
        <p>Liu Cheng, a professor of labor law at Shanghai Normal University, had a different explanation. ''My first reaction is that this seems like a typical example of a government-business alliance,'' Mr. Liu said. ''Forced labor and child labor in China are illegal, but some local governments don't care too much.''</p>
        <p>Zhang Xiaoying, 37, whose 15-year-old son disappeared in January, said she had visited over 100 brick factories during a handful of visits to Shanxi Province in search of him.</p>
        <p>''You just could not believe what you saw,'' Ms. Zhang said in a telephone interview on Thursday. ''Some of the kids working at these places were at most 14 or 15 years old.''</p>
        <p>The local police, she said, were unwilling to help. Outside one factory, she said, they even demanded bribes.</p>
        <p>''We finally got into that place, and I saw people hauling carts of bricks with great difficulty,'' Ms. Zhang said. ''Some of them were very small, and the ropes they pulled left tracks of blood on their shoulders and backs. Others were making bricks, standing by the machines.</p>
        <p>''They had to move the bricks from the belt very quickly, because they were hot and heavy and they could easily get burned or hurt by the machines.''</p>
        <p>By Friday, with the help of Mr. Su, Ms. Zhang finally located her son at a kiln near the one to which Mr. Su's children had been taken.</p>
        <p>Another father, Cai Tianliang, said he had set out to Shanxi Province in May from his native Henan Province in search of his missing 19-year-old son after a local television broadcast had shown a team of television reporters and Henan parents searching the Shanxi kilns for kidnapped children.</p>
        <p>''I thought there was a great possibility that my son was also kidnapped, so I went there twice,'' Mr. Cai said. ''The usual thing is for an owner to have more than one factory, and to shift people without identification from one place to another.''</p>
        <p>On his first trip, which he took with a group of parents, Mr. Cai said he found few clues. On a second visit to the area, he said, he was refused police permits to enter any of the brick factories but persisted anyway.</p>
        <p>''We located a place called the Zhenjie Brick Factory in a town called Chengbei, and at first they would not allow us in,'' he said, ''but we kept negotiating. Finally, they let a few of us in, and they found my son inside.''</p>
        <p>Like many other parents, Mr. Cai said he was dumbfounded by the boy's condition when they were reunited.</p>
        <p>''My son was totally dumb, not even knowing how to cry, or to scream or to call out 'Father,' '' he said. ''I burst into tears and held him in my arms, but he had no reaction. He was in rags and had wounds all over his body. Within three months he had lost over 10 kilos,'' about 22 pounds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cai said he tried to rescue a 16-year-old boy he found there, but was refused by the factory boss. ''He said I could only take my own,'' Mr. Cai said, ''and must leave other people behind at the kiln.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
