<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Performer's Look Back At Her Life, Now Ended</title>
    <meta content="16lid" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/theater/reviews/16lid.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854726"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Puppets</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagrin, Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Twist, Basil</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Behind the Lid (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Puppets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Nagrin, Lee</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Twist, Basil</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Behind the Lid (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E7D9153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1046" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Performer's Look Back At Her Life, Now Ended</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Artist’s Look Back at Her Life, Now Ended</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley reviews Behind the Lid, environmental theater piece by performance artist Lee Nagrin and puppeteer Basil Twist; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has become almost obligatory among those attending memorial services to comment that the departed one seems somehow so present, as if he or she were there looking on, enjoying, even participating. But this observation rarely has the lapel-grabbing force it acquires in ''Behind the Lid,'' a remarkable environmental theater piece by the performance artist Lee Nagrin and the puppeteer Basil Twist.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nagrin died on June 7 at 78. Yet she is indisputably the dominant character, leading lady and chief guide in this walking tour through the landscape of her life and mind. Staged in Greenwich Village at the Silver Whale Gallery, Ms. Nagrin's artistic home for decades, ''Behind the Lid'' is enough to make you believe that this longtime doyenne of experimental theater never left the building.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lee Nagrin was a devoted keeper of the flame of a sensibility that saw theater less as entertainment than as a door to the inexplicable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has become almost obligatory among those attending memorial services to comment that the departed one seems somehow so present, as if he or she were there looking on, enjoying, even participating. But this observation rarely has the lapel-grabbing force it acquires in ''Behind the Lid,'' a remarkable environmental theater piece by the performance artist Lee Nagrin and the puppeteer Basil Twist.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nagrin died on June 7 at 78. Yet she is indisputably the dominant character, leading lady and chief guide in this walking tour through the landscape of her life and mind. Staged in Greenwich Village at the Silver Whale Gallery, Ms. Nagrin's artistic home for decades, ''Behind the Lid'' is enough to make you believe that this longtime doyenne of experimental theater never left the building.</p>
        <p>It is not just that Ms. Nagrin wrote the text of this singular production, which runs through June 28, performed as a movable feast for an audience of 18. Her voice is the first thing you hear when the show begins. And the stooped, broad-backed, white-haired figure, supported by invisible minions, that you are asked to follow down an undulating, fleshlike corridor certainly looks like Ms. Nagrin.</p>
        <p>That figure is the first of many puppets and effigies in the form of Ms. Nagrin that show up throughout the labyrinth of rooms and corridors Mr. Twist and his team have constructed. Ms. Nagrin also appears on videotape, on small monitors. And for the final sequence, video and puppetry are combined in a life-size mannequin, of ceremonial dignity and expressively mobile hands, onto whose face is projected that of Ms. Nagrin, talking with ecclesiastical solemnity of the theater as she knew it.</p>
        <p>In an introduction in the play's program, Ms. Nagrin writes of visiting the cave of the Sibyl of Cuma in Italy and realizing she identified with that mythic storyteller and prophetess. Sibylline is certainly the word for the various avatars of Ms. Nagrin in ''Behind the Lid,'' a work on which she and Mr. Twist began collaborating nine years ago. The entire production might be characterized as a sort of sacred and arcane ritual.</p>
        <p>This is fitting. Ms. Nagrin, a staple of downtown Bohemia for more than half a century, belonged to a tribe now all but extinct in Manhattan, for whom theater was truly a religion, a means of pursuing the ineffable.</p>
        <p>The messiahs of this world included Artaud, Grotowski, Ionesco (whose works Ms. Nagrin was among the first to introduce to New York) and Beckett. Of Beckett's ''Endgame,'' Ms. Nagrin is heard saying, ''When I first saw it, I thought, this is what real life is. I didn't sleep for a week.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Nagrin's own works, interdisciplinary projects that sought to conjure the patterns of dreams, never acquired the renown or cultural acceptance of Beckett's or Ionesco's. But she was a devoted keeper of the flame of a sensibility that saw theater less as entertainment than as a door to the inexplicable.</p>
        <p>It is that spirit of mystical awe that Mr. Twist -- best known as the creator of the ravishing ''Symphonie Fantastique,'' an abstract underwater puppet ballet -- sets out to summon in ''Behind the Lid.'' The show progresses through a series of shape-changing spaces that evoke, among other things, Plato's cave, a suburban backyard, an American Indian graveyard (Ms. Nagrin was much influenced by the time she spent with the Makah tribe of Washington State) and an art gallery.</p>
        <p>The first scenes, which take place in a minitheater that keeps shrinking, will be painful for anyone with even a tinge of claustrophobia. (I came close to blacking out.) But pain is perhaps a suitable response, as what is enacted here includes a concentration-camp drama (written by Ms. Nagrin when she was 14) and the explosion of an atomic bomb.</p>
        <p>''Behind the Lid'' makes a point of defining Ms. Nagrin's art as a response to a troubled chapter in world history. And the relief of leaving that first prisonlike theater becomes a sort of metaphor for art's transcendence of life's horrors.</p>
        <p>Her life, her voice says, was devoted to discovering ''the inside on the outside, the outside on the inside.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Twist appropriately blurs the lines between the real and the representational, between the personal and the universal. He is an active and visible participant in nearly all the scenes -- variously attired as an Indian shaman, as both of Ms. Nagrin's parents and as a barefoot, black-clad master of ceremonies.</p>
        <p>But he makes it clear that it's Ms. Nagrin who is pulling the strings. (One early scene finds a large Nagrin puppet overseeing a miniature theater in which Mr. Twist's head is sandwiched between two tiny dolls.)</p>
        <p>Nearly every aspect of Ms. Nagrin's varied career is embodied here. Her paintings line a white corridor that leads from one theater to another, in a witty re-creation of a downtown gallery opening. (Wine and hors d'oeuvres are served.)</p>
        <p>The visual effects -- from that simulated atomic blast to the apparition of a giant talking totem pole -- are riveting throughout, psyche-roiling combinations of a childlike primitivism and an uberartisan's sophistication. Similarly, the entire enterprise can seem silly, frightening, pretentious, sincere and magnificent, all at the same time.</p>
        <p>Rather like the great experiment that was avant-garde theater in New York for the second half of the 20th century. ''Behind the Lid'' is an evocation not only of Ms. Nagrin but also of an entire theatrical subculture that now has only a flickering existence.</p>
        <p>In a prologue, Ms. Nagrin's voice speaks of the artist as a ''pearl diver'' descending into ''the depths of the past'' and transforming what she finds there into something beyond time. With Mr. Twist's loving assistance, she is plumbing those depths again.</p>
        <p>Behind the Lid</p>
        <p>Created by Lee Nagrin and Basil Twist; directed by Mr. Twist; costumes by Sally Ann Parsons; lighting by Tony Giovannetti; video by Daniel Brodie; sound by Moira MacDonald; produced by Barbara Busackino/Tandem Otter Productions; production stage manager, Ms. MacDonald. Presented by Street Dance Productions at the Silver Whale Gallery, 21 Bleecker Street, at Mulberry Street, Greenwich Village; (212) 868-4444. Through July 13. Running time: 90 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Basil Twist; Oliver Dalzell, Yvette Edery, Jamie Moore, Flora Shepherd, Kirsten Kammermeyer and Randy Ginsburg (puppeteers and puppet builders).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
