<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On West Bank, a Show of Force by Fatah</title>
    <meta content="16westbank" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/world/middleeast/16westbank.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854772"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Bank</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza Strip</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fatah</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hamas</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershner, Isabel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">West Bank</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Fatah, Al</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Hamas</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D8153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On West Bank, a Show of Force by Fatah</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On West Bank, a Show of Force by Fatah</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ISABEL KERSHNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershner, Isabel</byline>
      <dateline>RAMALLAH, West Bank, June 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many Palestinians in West Bank support Fatah day after Hamas seized control of Gaza; two territories that were supposed to make up future Palestinian state have come to resemble enemy countries where opposing ideological powers hold sway; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The preacher at the main mosque here in the Palestinian Authority's administrative capital in the West Bank called for reconciliation during Friday Prayer, a day after Hamas violently seized control of Gaza.</p>
        <p>A few blocks away, dozens of armed and uniformed members of the various security forces loyal to the Palestinian president, Mahmoud Abbas of Fatah, gathered in the city's central Manara Square in an obvious show of force. Every so often they piled into their jeeps and sped off in convoys, screeching through the narrow side streets around the square. Sometimes they stopped and posed for the cameras.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dozens of armed and uniformed men loyal to the Palestinian president, Mahmoud Abbas of Fatah, gathered in Ramallah’s central Manara Square.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The preacher at the main mosque here in the Palestinian Authority's administrative capital in the West Bank called for reconciliation during Friday Prayer, a day after Hamas violently seized control of Gaza.</p>
        <p>A few blocks away, dozens of armed and uniformed members of the various security forces loyal to the Palestinian president, Mahmoud Abbas of Fatah, gathered in the city's central Manara Square in an obvious show of force. Every so often they piled into their jeeps and sped off in convoys, screeching through the narrow side streets around the square. Sometimes they stopped and posed for the cameras.</p>
        <p>Their point was that while Hamas may have taken the Gaza Strip, the West Bank still belongs to Fatah. Many of them donned menacing black masks. Reconciliation did not appear high on their agenda, and local supporters of Hamas lay low.</p>
        <p>Overnight, the two territories that were supposed to make up a future Palestinian state have come to resemble enemy countries where opposing ideological powers hold sway.</p>
        <p>Ziad Abu Ein, a leader of Fatah's young guard in Ramallah, called the Hamas takeover of Gaza ''a coup against the Palestinian Authority.''</p>
        <p>''We will call today or tomorrow for an uprising in Gaza against this fascist military group from Hamas,'' he said.</p>
        <p>One member of the Fatah-dominated Preventive Security apparatus, his blue eyes visible through round peepholes in his mask, said, ''We are here to impose law and order in the streets, and implement the state of emergency declared by the president.'' He said his face was covered so that he couldn't be photographed or identified by ''suspicious'' elements, meaning Hamas.</p>
        <p>The Palestinians have long been distinguished by their social divides, split between the West Bank and Gaza, insiders of those territories and outsiders in exile, refugees and nonrefugees, village and town. But with the conquest of Gaza by the Islamist Hamas complete and the nationalist, secularist Fatah determined to maintain its stronghold in the West Bank, the Palestinian people seem more ruptured than ever.</p>
        <p>''Like there is North Korea and South Korea,'' another security force member said. ''That's what it will be like between Gaza and the West Bank.''</p>
        <p>The West Bank and Gaza have always been distinct geographic areas divided by Israeli territory, and the distance between them has been growing for years. Citing security reasons, Israel started restricting Palestinian travel between the two in the 1990s. A ''safe passage'' arrangement in the Oslo peace accords functioned in a limited manner for a short period before the second Intifada broke out in 2000.</p>
        <p>Since then, Palestinian movement between Gaza and the West Bank has been strictly limited. Israeli security officials explain the restrictions as necessary to stop weapons and explosives, which they say have poured into Gaza through tunnels under the Egyptian border, from reaching the West Bank.</p>
        <p>''Let's admit it, the West Bank and Gaza Strip were already separate to a very large degree,'' said Ghassan Khatib, a former minister in past Palestinian governments and now vice president of Birzeit University in the West Bank. ''They were no longer one market or one social unit. It is no longer the same society. So these latest developments come to complete and consolidate the process that Israel started.''</p>
        <p>The last semblance of cooperation between Fatah and Hamas, and the West Bank and Gaza, collapsed when President Abbas dissolved the three-month-old unity government on Thursday night. Now an emergency government appointed by Mr. Abbas will rule in the West Bank, headed by Salam Fayyad, an internationally respected technocrat and political independent who served as finance minister in the previous government. In Gaza, a Hamas-led government could emerge, and neither one will recognize the other, Palestinian analysts say.</p>
        <p>For Palestinians in the West Bank with family in Gaza, the distance can be agonizing. One man in Manara Square, who is originally from Gaza, was holding a picture of his cousin Samih Madhoun, a senior Fatah leader who was captured and executed by Hamas on Thursday night. Wide-eyed with fright, the man said that two of his brothers were also in the hands of Hamas, and he had no idea if they were still alive. He asked not to be identified, fearing for his relatives' safety.</p>
        <p>Muhammad Tawfiq, a Preventive Security officer from Nablus and the head of a Fatah militia there, said that Hamas had treated fellow Palestinians ''the way that Hitler dealt with the Jews.''</p>
        <p>Most of the stores in downtown Ramallah were shuttered on Friday and the market was unusually quiet. People were unsure whether Fatah would carry out revenge attacks against Hamas in the West Bank, where the group has a much weaker presence than in Gaza.</p>
        <p>One local Hamas leader was killed in Nablus by gunmen of the Fatah-affiliated Al Aksa Martyrs Brigade on Thursday night. But Mr. Tawfiq said that was just ''a reaction'' to the killing of Mr. Madhoun in Gaza. ''Our people couldn't control their emotions,'' he said.</p>
        <p>There were reports of Hamas offices being burned around the West Bank, and Palestinian security forces arrested dozens of Hamas members in a number of cities on Thursday and Friday.</p>
        <p>Still, there was a desire on the Fatah leadership's part to prevent factional violence spreading from Gaza to the West Bank. ''We are calling for no reaction by individuals against Hamas in the West Bank,'' said Mr. Abu Ein, of Fatah. ''We want to keep everything under Palestinian Authority control.''</p>
        <p>Not taking any chances, prominent Hamas figures in the West Bank have gone into hiding; at least those who are not already sitting in Israeli jails. Israel withdrew its soldiers and settlers from Gaza in 2005, but still retains overall control of the West Bank.</p>
        <p>One senior Preventive Security officer, who spoke on condition of anonymity because he was not authorized to talk to the press, said that some Hamas leaders in the West Bank ''may be interested in waking dormant cells.''</p>
        <p>But many Palestinians in Ramallah said they were confident that Hamas would not be able to seize control here. One reason, they said, is that despite the Palestinian Authority's show of force, Israel remains the real power in the West Bank.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
