<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sifting the Palestinian Rubble</title>
    <meta content="l16mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854790"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza Strip</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hamas</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fatah</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Silberman, Daniel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schlenger, Joshua I</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Galal, Khaled</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, Joel D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waxner, Marvin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E2D8153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="726" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sifting the Palestinian Rubble</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Letters from Daniel Silberman, Joshua I Schlenger, Khaled Galal, Joel D Gordon and Marvin Waxner respond to June 15 article and editorial about takeover of Gaza by Hamas; drawing</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Palestinians at War'' (editorial, June 15):</p>
        <p>In its brutal, planned coup, Hamas has at once demonstrated its disdain for Fatah, truces, the rule of law and the disregard it has for the welfare of the Palestinian people. Yet you somehow believe that making more positive overtures can be an effective strategy for addressing the current situation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Palestinians at War'' (editorial, June 15):</p>
        <p>In its brutal, planned coup, Hamas has at once demonstrated its disdain for Fatah, truces, the rule of law and the disregard it has for the welfare of the Palestinian people. Yet you somehow believe that making more positive overtures can be an effective strategy for addressing the current situation.</p>
        <p>Negotiate with President Mahmoud Abbas on a final peace settlement? How can any progress come from that when Hamas has proved how powerless Fatah is in Gaza? Freeze settlements as a good-will gesture? Please! I thought evacuating Gaza would have been sufficient for that purpose, yet we see the outcome of that particular initiative.</p>
        <p>Release revenues to alleviate suffering? As in the past, much of those funds will easily wind up paying for more arms.</p>
        <p>The efforts you advocate will not shore up support for Mr. Abbas, they will not further any aspect of the peace process, and they will not lessen the plight of the Palestinian people. Such a strategy is not ''new and wiser.'' It is old and foolish.</p>
        <p>Daniel Silberman  Hoboken, N.J., June 15, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I found your editorial ''Palestinians at War'' to be a very skewed depiction of Fatah. Yes, in comparison with Hamas, Fatah seems benign, especially since Fatah has recognized Israel's right to exist and has promised to abide by previous Israeli-Palestinian agreements. But Fatah and Hamas differ only in what they say; in terms of what they do, they are very similar.</p>
        <p>Can we forget that during the latest Palestinian intifada, it was a Fatah-affiliated group, Al Aksa Martyrs Brigades, that perpetrated murder and mayhem within Israeli borders through suicide bombings?</p>
        <p>We got to this very low point in the peace process precisely because the Fatah governments that preceded Hamas were very comfortable with double talk: urging peace and conciliation before the international community, while simultaneously inciting the Palestinian population to violence and hatred.</p>
        <p>Joshua I. Schlenger  Flushing, Queens, June 15, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The takeover of Gaza by Hamas should come as a surprise to no one. Israel's reported tolerance of Islamic fundamentalists in the 1970s, its decades of illegal settlement expansion and its strangulation of life in occupied Palestinian territories -- all were aimed at fragmenting and polarizing Palestinian society so that Israel could cloak its naked territorial expansion behind assertions that Palestinians were either incapable or undeserving of self-rule.</p>
        <p>The real surprise is that the United States has allowed itself to play the silent partner in this cynical strategy, which is sure to guarantee unrest and radicalism in the region for decades to come.</p>
        <p>Khaled Galal  San Francisco, June 15, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Amid the Palestinian carnage, you still urge Israel to change its settlement and security policy by restricting the former while relaxing the latter to magically bolster President Mahmoud Abbas.</p>
        <p>If anything, it was the very Israeli policy in Gaza, which you now urge the Jewish state to institute in the West Bank, that gave rise to Hamas these last two years.</p>
        <p>Israel's complete withdrawal of its military presence and checkpoints, as well as the total dismantling of the settlements in Gaza, was greeted with a sweeping victory of Hamas in the ensuing elections, a barrage of rocket attacks against Israeli communities within the Green Line, and now, the Hamas-led savagery resulting in its total control of Gaza.</p>
        <p>Joel D. Gordon  East Brunswick, N.J., June 15, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Palestinian Split Deepens, With Government in Chaos'' (front page, June 15):</p>
        <p>Another foreign policy coup of the Bush administration. Invariably, it finds some way to do the wrong thing. Start an unnecessary and disastrous war in Iraq, and ignore the real problem in the Middle East, the Israeli-Palestinian conflict.</p>
        <p>Having ignored the Israeli-Palestinian conflict, the Bush administration has helped sow the seeds for the renewal of military operations that could very well dwarf the battles between Israel and Hezbollah.</p>
        <p>Being surrounded by Hamas and Hezbollah, both sworn enemies of Israel, and both financed by Iran, does not, to put it mildly, inspire a sense of security for the Israelis. An emboldened jihadist movement could be dangerous to the entire Middle East.</p>
        <p>The ripples of the Bush administration's incompetence go on and on.</p>
        <p>Marvin Waxner  Plainview, N.Y., June 15, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
