<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A 50-Year-Old Time Capsule Sees Daylight, but Will It Start?</title>
    <meta content="16tulsa" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/us/16tulsa.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070619T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854798"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Time Capsules</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Oklahoma</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tulsa (Okla)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Plymouth Division of Chrysler Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Doty, Cate</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Oklahoma</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oklahoma</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Time</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Tulsa (Okla)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Oklahoma</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1D8153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="560" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A 50-Year-Old Time Capsule Sees Daylight, but Will It Start?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A 50-Year-Old Time Capsule Sees Daylight, but Will It Start?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATE DOTY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Doty, Cate</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Muddy, rusty 1957 Plymouth Belvedere is lifted out of Oklahoma earth, 50 years after citizens of Tulsa deposited coupe in underground vault near county courthouse to commemorate state's 50th anniversary; contents of time capsule fared better than car, which resembled shipwreck; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A muddy, rusty 1957 Plymouth Belvedere was lifted out of the Oklahoma earth yesterday, 50 years after the citizens of Tulsa deposited the coupe in an underground vault near the county courthouse to commemorate the state's 50th anniversary.</p>
        <p>At noon with two ceremonial blasts of an air horn and the strains of Henry Mancini's ''Oklahoma Crude'' blaring over the crowd lined up along South Denver Avenue, a blue crane started to lift the car slowly out of its grimy vault and onto a flatbed trailer, spectators said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A muddy, rusty 1957 Plymouth Belvedere was lifted out of the Oklahoma earth, 50 years after the citizens of Tulsa deposited the coupe underground.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A muddy, rusty 1957 Plymouth Belvedere was lifted out of the Oklahoma earth yesterday, 50 years after the citizens of Tulsa deposited the coupe in an underground vault near the county courthouse to commemorate the state's 50th anniversary.</p>
        <p>At noon with two ceremonial blasts of an air horn and the strains of Henry Mancini's ''Oklahoma Crude'' blaring over the crowd lined up along South Denver Avenue, a blue crane started to lift the car slowly out of its grimy vault and onto a flatbed trailer, spectators said.</p>
        <p>''Here she comes!'' Sharon King Davis, the chairwoman of the weekend-long celebration, exclaimed as the car rose. ''She's got one little fin showing, giving us a tease.''</p>
        <p>On the June day the car was buried, onlookers crowded around the hole, craning their necks as the hardtop was lowered by men in shirtsleeves.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, an older crowd still damp from a morning rain was kept a safe distance from the operation, on their feet just to give the car a standing ovation as it was lowered onto the flatbed.</p>
        <p>''Miss Belvedere,'' as Tulsa referred to the hardtop, spent the half-century wrapped in a protective goo and a canvas shroud, its resting place marked by a donated bronze plaque.</p>
        <p>Buried on June 15, 1957, as a publicity stunt to honor 50 years of statehood, the gold-and-white car and its contents -- artifacts like a pack of cigarettes and an unpaid parking ticket -- were to be dug up in another five decades.</p>
        <p>The car was interred with 10 gallons of gasoline, in case fuel would be obsolete in 2007, and a time capsule containing civic records, a prayer and a history of Tulsa churches.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, the excavators found that the structure that was supposedly built to withstand a nuclear blast could not defend its cargo from groundwater. The workers flushed out several feet of mud and, on Thursday, gave the car a test lift and decided that it could withstand being yanked out of the ground. Art Couch, a contractor who led the excavation, said Thursday that the car was structurally sound, although he thought that it was probably filled with mud.</p>
        <p>''Have you ever seen a car that's been in a flood?'' Mr. Couch asked. ''That's what it looks like.''</p>
        <p>After the lift to the flatbed, the car was taken to the Tulsa Convention Center, to be displayed last night. The car resembled a shipwreck, streaked with mud and grime, its windows rimmed with corrosion.</p>
        <p>Workers wearing gloves dug through the trunk, pulling out cans of Schlitz beer, some with the labels still legible.</p>
        <p>The time capsule contents fared better. Aerial photos of 1957 Tulsa were intact, and a vivid 46-star flag was unfurled.</p>
        <p>''Old Faithful survived,'' said John Erling, a volunteer who led the ceremony with Ms. Davis. The planners 50 years ago organized a contest to see who took home the car. Microfilm in the glove box lists all the entries in a contest to guess what the population of Tulsa would be in 2007. Whoever guessed closest to 390,000, the current population, wins.</p>
        <p>Boyd Coddington, a car restorer who flew from California to clean and, possibly, start the car, shook his head when Ms. Lewis asked about its condition.</p>
        <p>''It don't look good,'' Mr. Coddington said.</p>
        <p>The hole that Miss Belvedere left will be filled and planted with grass.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 19, 2007, Tuesday  An article on Saturday about the unearthing of a 1957 Plymouth Belvedere and a time capsule, which had been buried in Tulsa., Okla, to commemorate 50 years of statehood, misidentified one of the items in the capsule. It was a 48-star flag, not a 46-star flag.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 19, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article on Saturday about the unearthing of a 1957 Plymouth Belvedere and a time capsule, which had been buried in Tulsa., Okla, to commemorate 50 years of statehood, misidentified one of the items in the capsule. It was a 48-star flag, not a 46-star flag.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
