<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shunned by Bloomberg, Newsman Is a Gadfly in Exile</title>
    <meta content="16pass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/nyregion/16pass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854811"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">City Hall</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Miller, Gifford</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E6D7153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="954" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shunned by Bloomberg, Newsman Is a Gadfly in Exile</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Gadfly Becomes Persona Non Grata in City Hall</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANE CARDWELL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the publisher of a small independent newspaper, Rafael Martínez Alequin has tormented generations of politicians, raising hackles with pointed -- some say pointless -- questions, often about the interplay of race and class in the city.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani once called him a ''jerk'' and an ''embarrassment,'' and City Council Speaker Gifford Miller asked him in 2005, on Mr. Martínez Alequin's 72nd birthday, if he would consider ''dropping out of this life.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It took Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg to actually bar Rafael Martínez Alequin, the publisher of a small independent newspaper, from City Hall news conferences.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the publisher of a small independent newspaper, Rafael Martínez Alequin has tormented generations of politicians, raising hackles with pointed -- some say pointless -- questions, often about the interplay of race and class in the city.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani once called him a ''jerk'' and an ''embarrassment,'' and City Council Speaker Gifford Miller asked him in 2005, on Mr. Martínez Alequin's 72nd birthday, if he would consider ''dropping out of this life.''</p>
        <p>But it took Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg, the multibillionaire with a reputation for cool-headedness, to actually bar him, beginning in April, from City Hall news conferences.</p>
        <p>''I was surprised that it was this particular mayor because this is the first mayor that I kind of like,'' Mr. Martínez Alequin said last week, after being allowed back into a Blue Room news conference for the first time since his banishment.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, Mr. Martínez Alequin, a City Hall gadfly for the last 20-odd years who now publishes only online, is still in a kind of exile. Mr. Bloomberg has refused to recognize him at news conferences, both in and outside of the Blue Room, and the Police Department has denied him a press pass. He is working with Norman Siegel, the civil rights lawyer, who is contemplating a federal lawsuit over not only the way the city has treated Mr. Martínez Alequin, but also what he says is the unconstitutional way it doles out news media credentials.</p>
        <p>''It allows for too much unfettered discretion on the part of the N.Y.P.D.,'' Mr. Siegel wrote in a letter seeking an appeal of the denial, ''and permits police to deny cards to journalists with viewpoints that are controversial.''</p>
        <p>The Police Department also denied a press pass to Leonard Levitt, who was a longtime police reporter and columnist at Newsday and now writes a widely read online publication, nypdconfidential.com. Lawyers at the New York Civil Liberties Union are also considering a federal lawsuit, contending that the denial was retribution for Mr. Levitt's often critical take on Commissioner Raymond W. Kelly, who once went out to Newsday's Long Island offices to complain about Mr. Levitt's coverage.</p>
        <p>But administration officials say that they denied the applications of both Mr. Martínez Alequin and Mr. Levitt because they did not show a need to cover breaking news for a legitimate news organization.</p>
        <p>''An individual's declaration that they are a news-gathering organization does not make it so,'' said Paul J. Browne, a Police Department spokesman.</p>
        <p>The definition of a news organization appears to be part of the dispute. Reporters who write for online publications, for instance, have generally been recognized only if those publications are divisions of traditional news outlets.</p>
        <p>Stu Loeser, Mr. Bloomberg's chief spokesman, said in an e-mail message that the city was considering updating the guidelines to accommodate the growth of electronic media. But although Mr. Martínez Alequin would be allowed back for news conferences while his appeal is pending, Mr. Loeser said, he was not ''automatically getting the special accommodations and courtesies that are extended to credentialed members of the press anymore.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Martínez Alequin, who at times has been almost a heckler amid the press corps, cuts a singular figure at City Hall. A slight man who said he stands 5 feet 5 1/4 inches (''Don't leave out the quarter,'' he urged), Mr. Martínez Alequin said he was active in civil rights protests before starting an alternative tabloid called The Brooklyn Free Press in 1983.</p>
        <p>Renamed The New York City Free Press, the publication faltered before re-emerging under the same name online. Mr. Martínez Alequin could not provide readership figures for The Free Press, but said Your Free Press (yourfreepress.blogspot.com), his blog, gets about 1,500 hits a month. He said he lives off the savings he amassed with his wife, who died in 2000.</p>
        <p>Over the years, Mr. Martínez Alequin has needled elected officials and other public figures in the Blue Room, once angering Mr. Giuliani by remarking that the police were ''trigger-happy when it comes to blacks and Latinos, eh?''</p>
        <p>His interactions with Mr. Bloomberg and his aides have not been much smoother. Until the April banishment, Mr. Bloomberg had occasionally called on Mr. Martínez Alequin, mainly while rolling his eyes or wondering aloud if he would regret doing so.</p>
        <p>Frequently, the mayor chastised Mr. Martínez Alequin for the content of his questions and for making minor errors like referring to Mr. Bloomberg's autobiography, ''Bloomberg by Bloomberg,'' as ''Bloomberg on Bloomberg.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Martínez Alequin's antics have also irritated other reporters, many of whom have seen his questions as disruptive.</p>
        <p>''What's most interesting to me is that his colleagues in Room 9 did not come to his defense,'' said former Mayor Edward I. Koch. In the past, he said, if anyone sought to reduce the authority of any one publication, the reporters would protest as a group. ''I remember they would even walk out of the room,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At the same time, some veteran reporters say, Mr. Martínez Alequin has asked the questions others feared to ask and gained a following in some corners of the city. Last month, a group of City Council members sent a letter to Mr. Bloomberg protesting Mr. Martínez Alequin's removal from the Blue Room, calling him an ''outstanding and forthright reporter.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Martínez Alequin says that he does not torture officials so much as ask the questions he believes they should answer, especially those related to policies ''that affect poor people.''</p>
        <p>''I do believe that there are many questions that have to be asked to the mayor or to any elected official,'' he said, ''that I think that the mainstream media very seldom asks.''</p>
        <p>For the foreseeable future, it seems, Mr. Martínez Alequin will not be asking them either.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
