<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nest Egg: Nibble Early At Own Risk</title>
    <meta content="16nestegg" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/business/16nestegg.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854821"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR MONEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vanguard Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Internal Revenue Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Duncan, Donald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wesling, Tim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wesling, Colleen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boss, Shira</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Personal Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Personal Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E3D7153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1365" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nest Egg: Nibble Early At Own Risk</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With a Few Exceptions, the Advice Remains: Don’t Touch That Nest Egg</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHIRA BOSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Boss, Shira</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Your Money column on risks of pulling money out of retirement accounts except for actual retirement; says Internal Revenue Service usually charges 10 percent penalty for taking money before retirement age holds more people are choosing to preserve their assets in retirement accounts when they leave their jobs; Vanguard says among workers with 401(k) accounts who left their jobs in 2005, 27 percent took money as lump sum of cash; forty-seven percent kept money in plan, and 24 percent rolled it over into another retirement account; number of workers in their 40s taking cash matches overall average of 27 percent; financial planner Donald Duncan and Tim and Colleen Wesling, who took some money out of their retirement plans early, comment; graph; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Conventional wisdom says not to pull money out of retirement accounts except for actual retirement. Most Americans have enough difficulty building up a nest egg, and cracking it prematurely could mean living on cat food (slang for Social Security) later.</p>
        <p>The Internal Revenue Service usually charges a 10 percent penalty for taking money before retirement age. What rattles financial planners most is that taking money early means investments earmarked for later in life vanish before they ripen through many more years of compounding.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most Americans have enough difficulty building up a nest egg, and cracking it prematurely could mean living on Social Security later.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Conventional wisdom says not to pull money out of retirement accounts except for actual retirement. Most Americans have enough difficulty building up a nest egg, and cracking it prematurely could mean living on cat food (slang for Social Security) later.</p>
        <p>The Internal Revenue Service usually charges a 10 percent penalty for taking money before retirement age. What rattles financial planners most is that taking money early means investments earmarked for later in life vanish before they ripen through many more years of compounding.</p>
        <p>''I would tell someone to work at Starbucks'' before using retirement money to bridge an income gap, said Karen Schaeffer, a financial planner in Rockville, Md. ''This is such a big, huge penalty, you'll give up half this money and you'll never recover it, for the rest of your life.''</p>
        <p>An alternative viewpoint is that money is ultimately a means to an end. An immediate purpose for funds, in select circumstances, might trump squirreling it for retirement.</p>
        <p>Tim Wesling, a financial planner in Alexandria, Va., does not always agree with his peers. ''When you're living the situation,'' Mr. Wesling said, ''it's easier to say, 'We have the money, and we want to spend it.' ''</p>
        <p>One situation for cashing out involves people who tap retirement assets to support themselves through a career change or life transition. Some lose or leave a job; others want to go back to school, be home with children or start a business.</p>
        <p>In those cases, money saved for later in life is being consumed, perhaps detrimentally, in midlife. Although it can be tricky and comes with caveats, there is also a way to draw on retirement assets early without paying the penalty.</p>
        <p>''If it's been their dream to start their business, not to retire on their I.R.A., why not fulfill your dreams,'' Mr. Wesling said. ''That's what it's there for.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wesling and his wife, Colleen, are in this situation. She quit her job as an information technology consultant in March and is willing to take a significant pay cut from her former salary of about $150,000 to start an anticipated career as a bookstore manager.</p>
        <p>In May, the Weslings began taking $7,000 chunks out of her approximately $450,000 I.R.A. to maintain their lifestyle -- which includes tickets to the symphony, $300 dinners on weekends and an annual art-buying vacation to Maine -- while she searches for a job.</p>
        <p>''We decided that for right now, we weren't going to cut back, because we have the money and we don't think it'll be a big deal to get a job,'' Mr. Wesling said. Still, he says, it pains him to pay the penalty, and they would not let the situation go for more than a few months before belt-tightening, which they plan to do anyway once they know the new household budget.</p>
        <p>''We have safety nets others don't have,'' Mr. Wesling said, referring to an estimated $300,000 of home equity and his military retirement pay. ''This is not something I'd recommend for the general public.''</p>
        <p>That is because the general public does not have much money stashed in retirement funds. Among those who have retirement accounts, the median value is $27,900 for a family with a head of household age 35 to 44, and $55,500 for the 45-54 age range, according to Federal Reserve survey data.</p>
        <p>Taking money out before retirement, known as ''leakage,'' most commonly happens when workers change jobs. While still at a company, an employee can take money from a 401(k) account or a similar plan, usually only in cases of hardship, or as a loan, or in select other circumstances.</p>
        <p>When employees leave, though, they have a right to withdraw the money. If rolled over into another retirement account within 60 days, there are no consequences. Taking a cash distribution, however, leads to an income tax payment and the penalty if the person is below the retirement age.</p>
        <p>Among workers with 401(k) accounts who left their jobs in 2005, 27 percent took the money as a lump sum of cash, Vanguard's most recent data showed. Forty-seven percent kept the money in the plan, and 24 percent rolled it over into another retirement account. The number of workers in their 40s taking the cash matches the overall average of 27 percent. Planners say at that age there is perhaps enough money in an account to use for something significant, and enough time to rebuild an account before retirement.</p>
        <p>There are two ways to extract money from a plan. The first is to take a cash distribution. Many people do this without the guidance of a financial planner, who would still generally advise against it.</p>
        <p>''It's pretty much tax suicide to take a lump sum, plus it's subject to a 10 percent penalty,'' said Donald Duncan, a financial planner in Downers Grove, Ill. Distributions are counted by the I.R.S. as regular income and that can push a person into a higher tax bracket.</p>
        <p>The second way is to roll over the assets to an I.R.A., then use some or all of it to set up an income stream, which is taxed but not penalized. The I.R.S. allows this under Section 72(t), and it gives three methods for calculating how much money can be taken penalty-free from the account.</p>
        <p>Denny Gallien of Reynoldsburg, Ohio, used the 72(t) provision four years ago when he was downsized out of an engineering job and wanted to buy a pizza franchise for more than $300,000. Even with his wife working, they could not afford to pay for living expenses, the house they were building, the business and helping two of their sons get through school without having to, as Mr. Gallien says, ''backtrack.''</p>
        <p>He used some of his $450,000 in retirement savings to set up installment payments of $1,500 a month.</p>
        <p>''Is it a scary thing? A little bit, but I was confident that in 10 years I'd be in a pretty good spot, once the banks were paid back,'' Mr. Gallien said.</p>
        <p>His financial planner, Bob Schumann, said: ''What people want is freedom: freedom to work, freedom not to work, freedom to do what they want to do. And taking early distributions from a 401(k) or I.R.A. is a way for them to have that freedom.''</p>
        <p>The hitch in using 72(t) is that although the need for supplementary income might be temporary, the penalty-free income stream is permanent, at least until age 59 and a half (or for five years, if that is longer). So the provision is most commonly used for early retirement.</p>
        <p>''The assumption is that they don't have another source of income,'' said Roger Kruse, a financial planner in Coon Rapids, Minn. ''In most cases, we advise people not to access the retirement funds if they have other resources, virtually any other resources.''</p>
        <p>The need for a nest egg at or near retirement age is likely to be even greater than anticipated. The Center for Retirement Research reported last year that 7 in 10 people, ages 51 to 61 in 1992, experienced a ''negative shock'' in the following decade, through a job loss, health problems, or losing a spouse. Those events ate away at household wealth, with divorce being the most devastating, causing an average 44 percent decline in assets.</p>
        <p>Mr. Duncan, the financial planner, uses his own story as a cautionary tale. By his early 40s he had amassed a $1 million retirement account. He left his job and used the 72(t) provision to set up withdrawals of $48,000 annually, which he said should have sustained him for life.</p>
        <p>But, he said, ''I hit the perfect storm.'' A divorce cleaved the nest egg in half. Then the bear market of the early 2000s shrank it further. A few years after starting withdrawals, the account was down to $100,000.</p>
        <p>The I.R.S. started allowing a once-per-lifetime change to a lesser-withdrawal method, which Mr. Duncan used to recalculate a $4,000 annual distribution, the amount he had originally anticipated for each month.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, he had started his financial planning business and has been able to rebuild. But he now advises: ''Retirement assets are for retirement. Try to find an alternative to fund whatever it is you want to fund.''</p>
        <p>YOUR MONEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
