<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Father and Son Try Sparing The Rod</title>
    <meta content="16outdoors" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/sports/othersports/16outdoors.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854778"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OUTDOORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <org class="online_producer">eBay Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E4D8153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="782" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Father and Son Try Sparing The Rod</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Father and Son Try Sparing the Rod</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY DELANEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sun had begun to set as I stood at the edge of my favorite golf course pond. The slanting rays were warming the northern shore, giving the bass a comfortable place to bask. A foursome was teeing off in the distance, but we were well out of sight, and this was a good thing. I'm sure my party of two would have provided quite a distraction to any unsuspecting golfer. It's odd enough to see someone fishing a water hazard. But instead of fly rods, we wielded what looked like car-vacs with stubby plastic poles attached.</p>
        <p>It all started last winter when an unmarked brown package arrived at my home. Like most anglers, I tend to be secretive about my obsession. Outside of Nascar country and certain parts of Minnesota, most folks regard fishing as an eccentric pastime. And when the topic does come up, perhaps the most predictable question is, ''Have you ever used that Pocket Fisherman thing?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Pocket Fisherman will never replace my #7 fly rod. But it could come in handy for an instant fishing fix, or for stealth fishing applications in quasi-legal locations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The sun had begun to set as I stood at the edge of my favorite golf course pond. The slanting rays were warming the northern shore, giving the bass a comfortable place to bask. A foursome was teeing off in the distance, but we were well out of sight, and this was a good thing. I'm sure my party of two would have provided quite a distraction to any unsuspecting golfer. It's odd enough to see someone fishing a water hazard. But instead of fly rods, we wielded what looked like car-vacs with stubby plastic poles attached.</p>
        <p>It all started last winter when an unmarked brown package arrived at my home. Like most anglers, I tend to be secretive about my obsession. Outside of Nascar country and certain parts of Minnesota, most folks regard fishing as an eccentric pastime. And when the topic does come up, perhaps the most predictable question is, ''Have you ever used that Pocket Fisherman thing?''</p>
        <p>So finally, I gave in and ordered one.</p>
        <p>When I opened the package, the contents were unlike anything I had ever seen. With its star drag and plastic handle, one end bore a nostalgic resemblance to the spin-cast reels of my youth. The business end was a stubby rod with two guides made of some kind of plastic. There was an emblem with a portrait of the inventor, Ron Popeil, molded onto the grip. The whole affair was hinged so that it collapsed to a size small enough for a glove compartment.</p>
        <p>It came with line and a small bobber that fit in a hidden chamber. Best of all, I received two.</p>
        <p>I assumed they were trying to make fishing a family affair. Or maybe they had too much inventory in the warehouse. I stared at the snowy landscape outside my kitchen and wondered when, and if, I would ever have the courage to use this thing.</p>
        <p>When the weather warmed, I had an opportunity. With me was my 15-year-old son. Although he is not an avid fisherman, the sheer novelty of the Pocket Fisherman had convinced him to give it a try. But I could tell that he was having regrets. For him, this was the perfect storm of dorkiness. Dad, with his goofy fanny pack and bizarre fishing gear, did not exactly resemble the prototypical American Sportsman.</p>
        <p>When we arrived at the pond, I rigged our weapons of choice with a bit of worm on a jig head. This seemed a safe bet for anything that swims. I also had my three-piece fly rod in reserve. The lightweight jigs cast surprisingly well, although my son's overly energetic efforts tended to separate the bait from the hook. We waited patiently for something to happen.</p>
        <p>My son soon lost interest and got involved in text messaging, careful not to reveal his location lest one of his entourage should happen by. I eventually began getting nibbles. Finally, I felt a hit and wrestled in a hand-sized bluegill. The spunky critter had given me a pretty good fight and was quickly released. More important, the Pocket Fisherman had survived its first test. But the real contest was yet to come. In minutes I felt a more aggressive tug that I knew had to be a largemouth. Here was the ultimate challenge for the Pocket Fisherman.</p>
        <p>While not particularly acrobatic, the bass did present something of an ordeal. He tried cutting sharply in several directions. The minimal rod of the Pocket Fisherman did not provide much backbone, and I hoped my knot would hold. Finally, I eased the fish to the shore and lipped him out of the water. He was quite healthy and had the brownish color of early spring before the weeds come in. I photographed him with my camera phone and e-mailed the image to myself for posterity.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, my success only increased my son's frustration. He began suggesting that because we had accomplished our mission, perhaps it was time to go. As much as I wanted to stay, the voice of reason prevailed and we packed up to leave. As we walked toward the car, I found myself enjoying this bonding moment, although I felt bad about my son's disappointment.</p>
        <p>''I think I'll take up golf,'' he said. ''If you keep hitting the ball, at least eventually you get it in the hole.''</p>
        <p>As for the Pocket Fisherman, let's just say it will never replace my #7 fly rod. But I may keep one in my car just in case. It could come in handy for an instant fishing fix, or for stealth fishing applications in quasi-legal locations.</p>
        <p>As for that second Pocket Fisherman, well, there's always eBay.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
