<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Criminal in the Suburbs, But With a British Accent</title>
    <meta content="16bell" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/arts/television/16bell.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854720"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Showtime</org>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Meadowlands (TV Program)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DA153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Criminal in the Suburbs, But With a British Accent</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Criminal in the Suburbs, but With a British Accent</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINIA BELLAFANTE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Until the dawn of the 23rd century -- at the very earliest, you suppose -- any new family drama on television seeking to dissect class and criminality will exist in the penumbra of another. The arrival of such a series will call to mind what legendarily came before: its moral inquiries, its occasionally bewildering points of plot. I speak here, of course, of ''Knot's Landing,'' the pioneer of subdivision gothic, a genre whose spigots have leaked ever more ghoulishly since.</p>
        <p>A series on Showtime, beginning tomorrow night, easily represents the most macabre entry in the game. Its title, ''Meadowlands,'' is an invidious tease at this mournful period in television history, as it refers neither to New Jersey nor to the missing Jimmy Hoffa nor to a land patch where asbestos is illegally dumped.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Brogans of “Meadowlands,” a new series on Showtime, are a family in hiding, but it is the show’s prevailing philosophy that corrupt souls cannot mingle among us.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Until the dawn of the 23rd century -- at the very earliest, you suppose -- any new family drama on television seeking to dissect class and criminality will exist in the penumbra of another. The arrival of such a series will call to mind what legendarily came before: its moral inquiries, its occasionally bewildering points of plot. I speak here, of course, of ''Knot's Landing,'' the pioneer of subdivision gothic, a genre whose spigots have leaked ever more ghoulishly since.</p>
        <p>A series on Showtime, beginning tomorrow night, easily represents the most macabre entry in the game. Its title, ''Meadowlands,'' is an invidious tease at this mournful period in television history, as it refers neither to New Jersey nor to the missing Jimmy Hoffa nor to a land patch where asbestos is illegally dumped.</p>
        <p>Such is the fate of the premium-cable viewer that ''Meadowlands'' is set in a housing development somewhere in the marshes of England (proximity to a good soppressata be damned), among the gruesome, the humorless, the irredeemable.</p>
        <p>The great family saga of our television age and some of the merely good ones that have followed are, to varying degrees, essays in the trials of assimilation, their conflict situated between the aspiration to yuppie status and the morally dubious shortcuts deployed to live well.</p>
        <p>Tony and Carmela Soprano strived for a stake in the whole Clintonian boomer universe while they labored far beyond its parameters and ate manicotti on Sunday afternoons. Too young for Woodstock, they named their daughter Meadow, regardless, and sent her to private school and an Ivy League university and fretted over her decision to abandon a career in medicine.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Mary Louise Parker's widowed mother on ''Weeds'' works to keep her career as a drug dealer from interfering with her cul-de-sac life amid the joggers and chrome coffee-cup thermoses somewhere in Orange County, Calif. And on ''The Riches'' a family of con artists assumes a new identity and moves into a gated community in Louisiana, where it is forced to decode and absorb the habits of the freshly well to do.</p>
        <p>The Brogans of ''Meadowlands'' are also a family in hiding, but it is the show's prevailing philosophy that corrupt souls cannot mingle among us. The Meadowlands is a kind of surreal penal colony, a whole village as witness protection program. Everyone who lives there has done something heinous, and no one is trying to become someone he or she is not.</p>
        <p>Complacency makes for dull television. ''Meadowlands'' is David Lynch without his silent laugh track. Nothing seems to bring it to life -- not its obsession with voyeurism, its forays into cross-dressing, its objectification of the obese. Nor that we witness a haggard middle-aged woman sleeping with a teenage boy. There is not a single character in the show who will remind you of a slightly more deranged version of someone with whom you may be vaguely acquainted.</p>
        <p>Danny Brogan (David Morrissey), his wife and his teenage twins have been sent to Meadowlands because he is a killer. This is an aspect of his character about which his wife, Evelyn (Lucy Cohu), remains in extreme denial. They have sex constantly but don't seem to know each other at all. No one in this family has any idea how to talk to anyone else: the couple's son, Mark, chooses to be mute.</p>
        <p>''Meadowlands,'' a co-production with Channel 4 in Britain, is fascinated, above all, with what weirdness looks like: bright houses under unfailingly gray skies; women with chipped, dark nail polish; men with bloodied eyes as swollen as golf balls. It won't teach you a thing, though, about what it feels like to be weird.</p>
        <p>Meadowlands  Showtime, tomorrow night at 10, Eastern and Pacific times; 9, Central time.</p>
        <p>Created by Matthew Alridge and Robert Murphy; Douglas Rae and Mr. Alridge, executive producers; Caroline Levy, producer; Duane Clark, director. The series is produced by Ecosse Films.</p>
        <p>WITH: David Morrissey (Danny Brogan), Lucy Cohu (Evelyn Brogan), Felicity Jones (Zoe Brogan) and Harry Treadaway (Mark Brogan).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
