<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Course Is Hard, No Matter How You Cut It</title>
    <meta content="16golf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/sports/golf/16golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854840"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">United States Golf Assn</org>
        <org class="online_producer">PGA Tour Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Furyk, Jim</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Singh, Vijay</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mickelson, Phil</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Watson, Bubba</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E6D6153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="853" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Course Is Hard, No Matter How You Cut It</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Course Is Hard, No Matter How You Cut It</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa., June 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was the closest thing to a day of misspent golf, a day when the players waded through weeds and crept behind bunkers that looked like benches.</p>
        <p>The best golfers in the world finally met Oakmont Country Club and all of its twisted toughness Friday, leaving the scorecards ugly and the golfers hugging their caddies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The best golfers in the world finally met Oakmont Country Club and all of its twisted toughness on Friday, leaving the scorecards ugly and the golfers hugging their caddies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was the closest thing to a day of misspent golf, a day when the players waded through weeds and crept behind bunkers that looked like benches.</p>
        <p>The best golfers in the world finally met Oakmont Country Club and all of its twisted toughness Friday, leaving the scorecards ugly and the golfers hugging their caddies.</p>
        <p>''It's just a mean golf course,'' Jim Furyk said.</p>
        <p>After the second day of the 107th United States Open, the leader board had been shaken, stirred and turned around, leaving Ángel Cabrera of Argentina with a one-shot lead at par 140 and leaving Phil Mickelson with his first missed cut in the championship since 1992. The cut fell at 150.</p>
        <p>Cabrera, with a one-over-par 71, led Bubba Watson (71) by a shot, and Stephen Ames (69), Aaron Baddeley (70), Justin Rose (71) and Niclas Fasth (71) by two. Tiger Woods (74) trailed Cabrera by five.</p>
        <p>With balls whizzing over greens and bounding into the rough, the officials of the United States Golf Association applauded their handiwork around Oakmont.</p>
        <p>The United States Open has been criticized in the past by players for unfair course setups -- particularly at Shinnecock Hills in 2004. But the golfers almost universally accepted Oakmont as a rugged but fair test.</p>
        <p>Paul Casey of England, after all, shot a four-under 66 to stand three shots off the lead, a message to the field that good scores could be had.</p>
        <p>''The greens are very true,'' Tom Pernice said after shooting a 72 that put him four shots back. ''It's one of the best-conditioned golf courses I've ever stepped on.''</p>
        <p>Rory Sabbatini said, ''This course is going to be challenging any way you do it.''</p>
        <p>Mickelson was less forgiving of the setup. He clung to the cutline until late in the afternoon, when Cabrera nestled an iron shot from 135 yards to 2 feet on his final hole and made a birdie. The putt left Mickelson 11 shots behind -- one too many for him to gain entry into the weekend.</p>
        <p>Cabrera's birdie also bumped out 18 other players, although he did not look at it that way.</p>
        <p>''I did not knock out Mickelson, Mickelson knocked out himself,'' Cabrera said through an interpreter. ''He shot 11 over par.''</p>
        <p>On his way out the door, Mickelson tried to leave an impression nonetheless. He took a jab at the U.S.G.A., describing the difficulty of competing in a championship when ''you're also trying to not end your career on one shot.''</p>
        <p>Mickelson injured his left wrist while practicing in Oakmont's rough May 28 and wore a wrap for two days.</p>
        <p>James Hyler, the chairman of the U.S.G.A.'s championship committee, said that Oakmont was playing as planned.</p>
        <p>''We listen to what he says; it doesn't impact how we set up the course,'' Hyler said of Mickelson's comments. ''We've had tough rough for years.''</p>
        <p>With the conditions at Oakmont drying out and the winds picking up, Hyler did say that the greens would be watered Friday night, which they were not Thursday night.</p>
        <p>He said that the U.S.G.A. officials would pay close attention to the 10th and 12th greens, which can become extra slippery when the wind blows in some directions. A combination of wind and dry conditions rendered the seventh green at Shinnecock nearly unplayable three years ago.</p>
        <p>''We like where we are right now, and we'd like to hold it there for Saturday and Sunday,'' Hyler said.</p>
        <p>Woods normally thrives in difficult conditions, but Oakmont has so far rendered him one of the pack.</p>
        <p>On the second hole, Woods drove into the left rough and hit his second shot into a ditch of grass that was 18 inches high. He slashed at his ball and deposited it long and left into a bunker, then made a bogey.</p>
        <p>On the fourth hole, he hit his tee shot into the Church Pews bunker. With his left foot on the grassy shelf and his ball and right foot in the sand, Woods blasted out of the hazard and back onto the fairway, but he made another bogey.</p>
        <p>''It's just so hard out there,'' said Woods, who had 12 golfers ahead of him on the leader board. ''It's hard to describe, you know?''</p>
        <p>Asked if he felt the U.S.G.A. was letting the course get out of hand, he said: ''It's close. It's right on the edge, I think. The first green, thank God I have spikes on because I think I would have slipped right off the back.''</p>
        <p>Cabrera has had his own experiences on difficult courses and has often fared well.</p>
        <p>A big hitter with a soft putting touch, he has three top-10 finishes at the Masters and a tie for seventh at the 2001 United States Open at Southern Hills. But he has yet to win on the PGA Tour.</p>
        <p>Although he says he would be playing soccer if not for his golf career, he seems to have chosen the right vocation at Oakmont.</p>
        <p>''I was leading in Augusta some years ago and I had a very good chance then,'' he said. ''Now I think I have a good one again.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
