<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Considering The Crime, Not the Suspect</title>
    <meta content="16about" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/nyregion/16about.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854770"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ABOUT NEW YORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/About New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/About New York/About New York - Dwyer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Confessions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EED9153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Considering The Crime, Not the Suspect</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Considering the Crime, Not the Suspect</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM DWYER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Because of the wiring of his brain, Ozem Goldwire must account for every minute in an hour. Asked what happened on the day he came home from work in January 2006 and found his sister dead in bed, Mr. Goldwire reports that his alarm went off at 5 a.m., and he took the B-20 bus at 6:18. ''I got to work at 7:04,'' he says, and so his narrative spools, one precise moment after the next, until he gets off the bus at night and opens the door to his house in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>A man possessed of normal intelligence and above-normal politeness, Mr. Goldwire, 28, has a ''developmental disability with autistic features,'' his school records show. Though he now speaks in the deep tones of an old-time broadcaster, at the age of 6 he had not yet uttered a complete sentence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>How did an innocent man come to confess, and conversely, how has a guilty person gotten away with murder?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Because of the wiring of his brain, Ozem Goldwire must account for every minute in an hour. Asked what happened on the day he came home from work in January 2006 and found his sister dead in bed, Mr. Goldwire reports that his alarm went off at 5 a.m., and he took the B-20 bus at 6:18. ''I got to work at 7:04,'' he says, and so his narrative spools, one precise moment after the next, until he gets off the bus at night and opens the door to his house in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>A man possessed of normal intelligence and above-normal politeness, Mr. Goldwire, 28, has a ''developmental disability with autistic features,'' his school records show. Though he now speaks in the deep tones of an old-time broadcaster, at the age of 6 he had not yet uttered a complete sentence.</p>
        <p>On Jan. 3, 2006, he confessed to strangling his sister, an act of violence that all who know him say would have been completely out of character, had he really done it. Last week, at the request of his lawyer, Gary Farrell, and a Brooklyn assistant district attorney, Robert Lamb, a judge dismissed the case and said Mr. Goldwire was ''actually innocent.''</p>
        <p>How did an innocent man come to confess, and conversely, how has the guilty person gotten away with murder?</p>
        <p>There is no record of the interrogation of Mr. Goldwire. He was in custody for 17 hours and questioned by six detectives before he gave an incriminating statement. Only then was a prosecutor called to videotape him. But on camera, Mr. Goldwire never admitted to hurting his sister, instead beginning his narrative once again with the 6:18 a.m. bus. Asked about his earlier admission, he responded that was just something he said to placate the detectives and was not true.</p>
        <p>In an interview this week, Mr. Goldwire recalled that a detective said to him, ''You think you're a genius,'' perhaps a reaction to his sonorous speaking style.</p>
        <p>''I told her that I was just only human,'' Mr. Goldwire said.</p>
        <p>Some of the detectives later described him as a ''Rain Man'' character, invoking the movie starring Dustin Hoffman. (Instead of fiction, they might try a marvelous new documentary, ''Autism: The Musical,'' that premiered in April at the Tribeca Film Festival.)</p>
        <p>He was asked about his religion, his sex life, and if he had intimate relations with his sister, who was a year older than he was and who also had developmental disabilities. The ordinarily implacable Mr. Goldwire screamed that he had not, records show. Her name is rendered in some records as Shereika Goldwire, but Mr. Goldwire prefers to spell it ''Sherika.''</p>
        <p>At one point, Mr. Goldwire remembered, ''I put my head down into my hands to try to marshall-ize my thoughts.'' A detective sergeant, he said, shoved him upright. ''He was yelling, 'Look at me, look at me!' '' Mr. Goldwire said. Later, two detectives ordered him to stand in a corner and face them.</p>
        <p>Detectives often use psychological pressure on suspects, including outlandish allegations. Criminals will concede that they might be killers, but not perverts.</p>
        <p>Such techniques help solve many crimes. They also snare the wrong people. Among the most startling revelations of the DNA era is the prevalence of false confessions by people who are proven unequivocally innocent. In recognition that the interrogation can be as revealing as the confession, police departments across the country are beginning to tape the questioning of suspects.</p>
        <p>Not in New York City. The police commissioner, Raymond W. Kelly, who has championed widespread police videotaping of public activities, does not see the need for similar documentation of what happens inside interrogation rooms. Mr. Kelly sees enormous logistical problems, a spokesman said yesterday.</p>
        <p>What saved Mr. Goldwire from a murder trial was the willingness of the Brooklyn district attorney's office to hire a psychologist to study the confession. Some victims' families might oppose such a study, creating a political problem for the prosecutors, but Sherika Goldwire's mother -- who is also Ozem's mother -- supported it.</p>
        <p>The psychologist, Kathy Yates, found that even some of the detectives had doubts. She concluded, ''It is likely that the interrogative techniques used by the officers over an extended period of time were coercive in nature for Mr. Goldwire, given his cognitive and developmental disabilities.''</p>
        <p>A tape of the interrogation might have been a special educational tool for everyone involved. Instead, Mr. Goldwire bided his time in jail, awaiting trial. ''One year,'' he said. ''And 11 days.''</p>
        <p>ABOUT NEW YORK E-mail: dwyer@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: dwyer@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
