<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>7 Men Sentenced in Qaeda Bomb Plot in the U.S. and Britain</title>
    <meta content="16britain" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/world/europe/16britain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854756"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Al Qaeda (Terrorist Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tarmohammed, Nadeem</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rehman, Omar Abdul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jalil, Abdul Aziz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barot, Dhiren (Issa Al-Hindi) (Issa Al-Britani)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shaffi, Quaisar</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bhatti, Mohammed Naveed</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feroze, Junade</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haq, Zia Ul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Al Qaeda</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E1D9153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="569" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>7 Men Sentenced in Qaeda Bomb Plot in the U.S. and Britain</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">7 Men Sentenced in Qaeda Bomb Plot in the U.S. and Britain</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, June 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>British court hands down lengthy prison sentences to seven men who served as accomplices to Dhiren Barot, Al Qaeda terrorist planning attacks in US and Britain; Barot is currently serving 30 years in prison; sentences against Qaisar Shaffi, Mohammed Naveed Bhatti, Junade Feroze, Zia Ul Haq, Abdul Aziz Jalil, Omar Abdur Rehman and Nadeem Tarmohamed range from 15 to 26 years; Barot photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A British court handed down lengthy prison sentences on Friday to seven men who served as accomplices to a Qaeda terrorist planning spectacular attacks in the United States and Britain.</p>
        <p>The planned attacks included causing buildings to collapse by detonating explosives packed in limousines and setting off a radiation bomb that would have caused ''fear, panic and widespread disruption,'' Peter Clarke, Britain's senior counterterrorism police officer, said in a statement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Britain’s senior counterterrorism police officer said the planned attacks included causing buildings to collapse by detonating explosives and setting off a radiation bomb.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A British court handed down lengthy prison sentences on Friday to seven men who served as accomplices to a Qaeda terrorist planning spectacular attacks in the United States and Britain.</p>
        <p>The planned attacks included causing buildings to collapse by detonating explosives packed in limousines and setting off a radiation bomb that would have caused ''fear, panic and widespread disruption,'' Peter Clarke, Britain's senior counterterrorism police officer, said in a statement.</p>
        <p>The targets in the United States included the New York Stock Exchange and the Citigroup headquarters in New York City, along with the offices in Washington of the International Monetary Fund and the World Bank, according to prosecutors in a lengthy series of trials.</p>
        <p>The mastermind was Dhiren Barot, 34, a British convert to Islam described by the police as a senior figure in Al Qaeda. Arrested in 2004, he was sentenced to a minimum of 40 years last November, which was later reduced to 30 years because he had not tried to carry out his plans.</p>
        <p>The case drew close attention among counterterrorism and civil liberties specialists, because most of the evidence had come ''not from surveillance but from inquiries carried out after they were arrested,'' Mr. Clarke said.</p>
        <p>''There was painstaking examination of the mass of material found during searches,'' he said. ''A huge amount of this material was on computers, some of it encrypted or deleted.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clarke did not refer specifically to a fiery debate in Britain over whether the period of permissible detention without charge for terrorism suspects should be extended to 90 days from 28.</p>
        <p>But his remarks reinforced previous arguments by the police that modern terrorism inquiries need much more time, to permit the police to carry out complicated investigations that require advanced code-breaking and language skills across international frontiers.</p>
        <p>Of the seven who were sentenced on Friday, only one, Qaisar Shaffi, 28, had denied the charges and stood trial. He was convicted of conspiracy to murder and sentenced to 15 years. Mr. Shaffi was said by prosecutors to have accompanied Mr. Barot to New York on what was depicted as a reconnaissance mission in March 2001.</p>
        <p>The other six men had admitted to charges of conspiracy to cause explosions likely to endanger life.</p>
        <p>''Each one of you was recruited by Barot and assisted him at his request,'' Judge Alexander Butterfield told the defendants. ''Anyone who chooses to participate in such a plan will receive little sympathy from the courts.''</p>
        <p>Any suffering caused to their families, the judge told them, ''is but a tiny fraction of the suffering that would have been experienced had your plans been translated into reality.''</p>
        <p>The sentences against the men -- Mr. Shaffi; Mohammed Naveed Bhatti, 27; Junade Feroze, 31; Zia Ul Haq, 28; Abdul Aziz Jalil, 34; Omar Abdur Rehman, 23; and Nadeem Tarmohamed, 29 -- ranged from 15 to 26 years.</p>
        <p>The British police released detailed summaries of the evidence to support the accusation that the men had helped Mr. Barot.</p>
        <p>''They were the trusted few who researched and carried out reconnaissance and supported Barot,'' said Mr. Clarke, the counterterrorism officer. ''Each had a different role to play. Barot needed minders and drivers, people who could look after him as he carried out his reconnaissance and conducted his meetings.</p>
        <p>''He needed people to carry out research; gain access to specialist libraries; supply vehicles, false identities and travel documents, bank accounts, money and safe houses.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
