<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Washington's Secret Gun Files</title>
    <meta content="16kelly" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/opinion/16kelly.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854768"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smuggling</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelly, Raymond W (Comr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smuggling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04EED9153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="631" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Washington's Secret Gun Files</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Washington’s Secret Gun Files</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Raymond W. Kelly</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelly, Raymond W (Comr)</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Police Comr Raymond W Kelly Op-Ed article urges Congress not to reauthorize Tiahrt amendment, legislation that stops federal government from sharing with local police departments and prosecutors crucial information about guns used in crimes; contends that Congress undermines value of government's data repository by requiring local police departments to investigate illegal gun trafficking rings without this information (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A NARROWLY divided Congress will vote in the coming days on whether to renew legislation that stops the federal government from sharing with local police departments and prosecutors crucial information about guns used in crimes. The Tiahrt amendment, first passed in 2003, prohibits Washington from releasing crime data about guns that used to be provided to state and local law enforcement. If House members reauthorize the measure, they will harm efforts to curtail gun violence in this country.</p>
        <p>When a gun is recovered from a crime scene, the police ask the federal Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives to trace the weapon's provenance. Yet when our officers request the trace data for all gun crimes, the Tiahrt amendment stops us dead in our tracks -- even though this aggregate information would tell us which individuals and dealers are most often involved in buying and selling guns that end up in the hands of criminals. In New York City, about 90 percent of the guns used in crimes come from out of state. Without full access to national trace data, it is far more difficult for our officers to disrupt the ''iron pipeline'' that brings illegal guns to our streets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The reauthorization of the Tiahrt amendment by Congress will harm efforts to curtail gun violence in this country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A NARROWLY divided Congress will vote in the coming days on whether to renew legislation that stops the federal government from sharing with local police departments and prosecutors crucial information about guns used in crimes. The Tiahrt amendment, first passed in 2003, prohibits Washington from releasing crime data about guns that used to be provided to state and local law enforcement. If House members reauthorize the measure, they will harm efforts to curtail gun violence in this country.</p>
        <p>When a gun is recovered from a crime scene, the police ask the federal Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives to trace the weapon's provenance. Yet when our officers request the trace data for all gun crimes, the Tiahrt amendment stops us dead in our tracks -- even though this aggregate information would tell us which individuals and dealers are most often involved in buying and selling guns that end up in the hands of criminals. In New York City, about 90 percent of the guns used in crimes come from out of state. Without full access to national trace data, it is far more difficult for our officers to disrupt the ''iron pipeline'' that brings illegal guns to our streets.</p>
        <p>Trace data combined with other information can be a rich source for police investigations. The firearms bureau acknowledges that numerous traces from a single dealer to guns used in crimes are grounds for suspicion. Yet Congress undermines the value of the government's data repository by requiring local police departments to investigate illegal gun trafficking rings without this information.</p>
        <p>The defenders of the amendment -- including the Republican representative who introduced it, Todd Tiahrt of Kansas -- contend that it protects the anonymity of undercover officers and the confidentiality of law enforcement investigations. But there is no reason we cannot protect the anonymity of undercover officers while at the same time releasing trace data for gun crimes. I oppose unfettered public access to investigative information that may be attached to trace data, like the identities of witnesses and the particulars of active cases. But law enforcement agencies and their partners in state and local government -- the people charged with safeguarding our communities against gun violence -- need broad access to the federal government's data to coordinate interdiction efforts and enforcement strategies.</p>
        <p>By collecting and analyzing our own data, the New York Police Department has developed increasingly sophisticated methods of identifying patterns and trends for assaults, robberies, drug sales, shootings and every other type of crime. Yet Congress prevents us from seeing the national data that would allow us to crack down on the No. 1 public safety threat facing our officers and the American public: illegal gun-trafficking rings.</p>
        <p>My paramount concern is for the safety of the police officers involved in this dangerous work, and I understand the need to preserve the confidentiality of their active investigations. But as a former Treasury under secretary charged with overseeing the firearms bureau, I know the value of this data to inform and advance the crime-fighting agendas of states and localities.</p>
        <p>During my tenure as under secretary, from 1996 to 1998, we routinely shared aggregate gun-crime data in the form of Crime Gun Trace Analysis Reports. These reports, no longer available since 2004, enabled police analysts to identify the nation's illicit gun markets and the major access routes that fed them. We released timely information without jeopardizing investigations and while safeguarding privacy rights.</p>
        <p>We can protect undercover officers and still give our detectives the tools they need to do their jobs. That's why I, along with more than two dozen other law enforcement organizations, including the International Association of Chiefs of Police and a bipartisan coalition of 225 mayors, oppose reauthorization of the Tiahrt amendment. Congress can help save lives by killing this awful law.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Raymond W. Kelly is the police commissioner of New York City.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Raymond W. Kelly is the police commissioner of New York City.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
