<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Aftermath Of Gaza Battle, Grim Realities</title>
    <meta content="16mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/world/middleeast/16mideast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854813"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Looting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza Strip</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hamas</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fatah</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">El-Khodary, Taghreed</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Ian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fayyad, Salam (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abbas, Mahmoud (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haniya, Ismail</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Gaza Strip</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Hamas</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Fatah, Al</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6D7153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1116" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Aftermath Of Gaza Battle, Grim Realities</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Aftermath of Gaza Battle, Grim Realities</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TAGHREED EL-KHODARY and IAN FISHER; Taghreed El-Khodary reported from Gaza, and Ian Fisher from Jerusalem.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">El-Khodary, Taghreed; Fisher, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>GAZA, June 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hamas defeats Fatah in what amounted to five-day civil war in Gaza Strip; there is post-revolutionary feel in Gaza; people are worried not only about daily survival but also about how deadly infighting, which killed reported 116 people, postponed hope for independent and unified Palestinian state; Hamas fighters loot presidential compound of Mahmoud Abbas; Abbas, in West Bank, names Salam Fayyad to be prime minister, replacing Ismail Haniya of Hamas; Hamas officials say that Haniya will remain in office; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This packed, impoverished coastal strip had a postrevolutionary feel on Friday: the green flag of Hamas, victor over Fatah in what amounted to a five-day civil war, flew over public buildings where once the multicolored Palestinian one had been.</p>
        <p>While the violence was largely over, people worried not only about daily survival but also about how the round of deadly infighting -- killing a reported 116 people -- postponed hope for an independent and unified Palestinian state.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>People in Gaza worried about how a round of deadly infighting postponed hope for an independent and unified Palestinian state.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This packed, impoverished coastal strip had a postrevolutionary feel on Friday: the green flag of Hamas, victor over Fatah in what amounted to a five-day civil war, flew over public buildings where once the multicolored Palestinian one had been.</p>
        <p>While the violence was largely over, people worried not only about daily survival but also about how the round of deadly infighting -- killing a reported 116 people -- postponed hope for an independent and unified Palestinian state.</p>
        <p>''These are the darkest days of my life,'' said Ahmad Sawafiri, 47, a taxi driver. ''What comes after all of this?</p>
        <p>''We went backward 100 years.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sawafiri stood in a disgusted crowd in Gaza City watching looters strip the sumptuous villa of Muhammad Dahlan, a former Fatah security chief and bitter rival of Hamas, who was not in Gaza.</p>
        <p>It was, for many Palestinians, a confusing and unaccustomed sight: black-hooded and normally disciplined Hamas fighters, seemingly driven by devotion to God, stripping away chandeliers, carpets, a bathtub -- earthly goods but also symbols of what many see as Fatah's corruption and excess. After the fighters left, poor people with donkey carts arrived, sweeping up stray bits of wood and metal and even uprooting the dapper Mr. Dahlan's garden plants.</p>
        <p>''I will explain it to you,'' said one looter, Mazen Qasas, a vendor. ''I am 34. I am married. I have six children. I am looking for a lamp, anything I can sell or use for my poor house. We are very poor. This is public property. These are corrupt people,'' he said, referring to Fatah leaders. ''They took everything.''</p>
        <p>Abu Muhammad Ashor, a 33-year-old policeman who until recently supported Fatah, looked with amazement and anger at the fine beige tiles that lined Mr. Dahlan's living room. ''Look at these tiles,'' he said. ''With these tiles, we all could have bread every day.''</p>
        <p>Looters also descended on the presidential compound of Mahmoud Abbas and an upscale beach compound used by leading members of Fatah. Hamas, which built its support partly on a reputation for being above corruption, condemned the looting, on television and from the pulpits on the Muslim day of prayer, as ''illegitimate and against religion,'' demanding that the looters return all they took.</p>
        <p>In the West Bank, Mr. Abbas named Salam Fayyad, an independent lawmaker and former World Bank economist who is respected in the West, to be prime minister, replacing Ismail Haniya of Hamas, whom Mr. Abbas dismissed Thursday night. But Hamas spokesmen in Gaza said that Mr. Haniya remained in office.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Abbas faced much criticism among Palestinians for not being able to keep control, the selection seemed aimed at shoring up one possible branch of strength: help from outside. Mr. Fayyad, who served as finance minister in the national unity government Mr. Abbas dismissed, had been trying to drum up support to have international aid sent through a special Palestine Liberation Organization bank account in order to avoid Hamas.</p>
        <p>Now that may not be necessary, with Israel and the West embracing the idea of a non-Hamas government, even if its powers are limited to the West Bank.</p>
        <p>With Israeli and Western powers highly unlikely to start giving money to Hamas, which the United States and the European Union classify as a terrorist group, the Bush administration and other Western governments made clear on Friday that they would continue to work with Mr. Abbas. Over the last day, Israel has also suggested anew it could gradually hand over the remaining Palestinian tax revenues, about $562 million, withheld since Hamas took power a year ago in March.</p>
        <p>Hamas officials immediately dismissed Mr. Abbas's moves to create a new government.</p>
        <p>''No internal formula in the Palestinian territories will hold without national agreement and without respecting the legitimacy of the election,'' Mr. Haniya said before Friday Prayer in Gaza City. He was referring to Hamas's victory in parliamentary elections in January 2006, a surprising victory that underscored deep dissatisfaction with Fatah and set the two parties on a collision course.</p>
        <p>But the prospect of an Islamic state in Gaza under Hamas control -- rising amid similar worries of Islamic extremism in Iraq and Lebanon -- seemed to strengthen the commitment in America and Israel to Mr. Abbas, however weakened he may be internally.</p>
        <p>''No one wants to abandon the hundreds of thousands, if not millions, of people in the Gaza Strip to the mercies of a terrorist organization,'' a White House spokesman, Scott Stanzel, said in Washington.</p>
        <p>The so-called quartet of Middle East peace brokers -- the United States, the European Union, Russia and the United Nations -- held an emergency teleconference on Friday in which they pledged full support to Mr. Abbas and expressed concern about the humanitarian situation in Gaza, Reuters reported.</p>
        <p>Israel has refused to negotiate with Hamas unless it fulfills several conditions, including renouncing violence and recognizing Israel's right to exist, and on Friday Israeli officials suggested that Hamas's takeover of Gaza had not changed that approach.</p>
        <p>''The goal is a two-state solution, or to give the Palestinians their own possibility to fulfill their aspirations in a state of their own,'' the Israeli foreign minister, Tzipi Livni, said Friday in Lisbon, Reuters reported.</p>
        <p>''We are waiting, watching the situation very closely,'' she added. ''But on the other hand we are going to keep this strategy of dialogue with the moderates and to send some hope for those who support their vision.''</p>
        <p>In Israel, the crisis speeded up a key appointment in the government of Prime Minister Ehud Olmert, who is traveling this weekend to Washington to meet with President Bush. At a time of deep concerns about security in Israel, Mr. Olmert, who had planned to make the appointment only after he returned, named Ehud Barak, the former prime minister recently chosen to lead the Labor Party, as defense minister.</p>
        <p>Meantime, Israel kept the borders sealed to Gaza, a thin and densely packed strip of 1.5 million people wedged between Israel, Egypt and the Mediterranean Sea. Poverty has increased markedly since Western governments virtually shut off direct aid to the Hamas government, and humanitarian groups warned of greater suffering if the borders remain shut.</p>
        <p>Amid the confusion and some scattered violence -- two revenge killings were reported Friday in Gaza -- Hamas leaders suggested that their bolstered control in Gaza could help free a BBC reporter, Alan Johnston, kidnapped in Gaza in March.</p>
        <p>''We will not allow for his continued detention,'' a spokesman for Hamas's military wing, Abu Obeidah, said in Gaza on Friday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnston is believed to be held by the Dagmush clan, which has at different times been allied with Hamas and Fatah.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
