<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fans Online Sift for Clues In the 'Sopranos' Finale</title>
    <meta content="16sopr" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/arts/television/16sopr.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854730"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Home Box Office</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Chase, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7D9153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="662" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fans Online Sift for Clues In the 'Sopranos' Finale</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fans Online Sift for Clues in the ‘Sopranos’ Finale</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nearly a week after the HBO series ''The Sopranos'' itself went to black forever, the debate about what its final scene -- in which the screen goes black for 10 seconds as Tony Soprano and members of his family eat in a diner -- might really mean has raged on, especially on blogs. Online, fans have either been railing about the ''cop-out'' of the ending or trying to fill in the blanks of the final episode themselves (or, often, both).</p>
        <p>David Chase, the creator of the series, has done little to clear things up, offering only one potentially relevant comment in an interview he granted to the Newark newspaper The Star-Ledger this week. While declining to say whether the abrupt cut to black meant that Tony Soprano had been killed, Mr. Chase said the meaning of the ending was ''all there'' in the episode.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nearly a week after the HBO series “The Sopranos” itself went to black forever, the debate about what its final scene might really mean has raged on, especially on blogs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nearly a week after the HBO series ''The Sopranos'' itself went to black forever, the debate about what its final scene -- in which the screen goes black for 10 seconds as Tony Soprano and members of his family eat in a diner -- might really mean has raged on, especially on blogs. Online, fans have either been railing about the ''cop-out'' of the ending or trying to fill in the blanks of the final episode themselves (or, often, both).</p>
        <p>David Chase, the creator of the series, has done little to clear things up, offering only one potentially relevant comment in an interview he granted to the Newark newspaper The Star-Ledger this week. While declining to say whether the abrupt cut to black meant that Tony Soprano had been killed, Mr. Chase said the meaning of the ending was ''all there'' in the episode.</p>
        <p>Quentin Schaffer, HBO's chief corporate spokesman, said yesterday that Mr. Chase had wanted an even longer duration of blackness at the show's conclusion. Mr. Chase had wanted as much as 30 seconds of blackness but was talked out of that by HBO executives, Mr. Schaffer said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chase's silence has led theorists to sift though the episode for clues to Tony's fate the way some people watch the Zapruder tape of John F. Kennedy's assassination. Among the wilder speculation on the Web: that the man in the jacket who enters the restaurant and sits at the counter in the last seconds is the cousin of the recently killed mob boss Phil Leotardo, and that the two young African-Americans who walk in are the same two who tried to kill Tony in Season 1.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Schaffer, Mr. Chase dismissed both those points in conversations after the finale was broadcast. Mr. Schaffer added that while Mr. Chase was not talking publicly, he has been monitoring the debate about the final episode closely, calling several times a day this week from his vacation hideaway in France. And Mr. Chase has not dismissed some of the Web chatter about other points in the show.</p>
        <p>Most significant for ''Sopranos'' theorists is the identity of a mystery man at the counter. He is identified in the closing credits as ''Man in Members Only,'' even though, as Mr. Schaffer pointed out, the scene never reveals the brand name of the jacket he is wearing. A previous episode of the series was titled ''Members Only.'' Theorists have speculated that the brand name was meant to suggest that he is a member of the mob, and therefore a hit man.</p>
        <p>The revelation that Mr. Chase had wanted the blackness to extend far longer would seem to further the theory that one of the apparently menacing forces gathering in the restaurant stepped up and turned Tony's lights out.</p>
        <p>Undoubtedly, a longer stretch of darkness would also have fed the now-growing speculation that the final scene was intended to suggest that Tony was about to experience something his late brother-in-law, Bobby Bacala, had prophesized in the very first episode this season: in a scene at Bobby's lake house, he had speculated about what happens when you die -- or get whacked, in ''Sopranos'' terms.</p>
        <p>The scene was reprised in the show's second-to-last episode, though many of the blog speculators have been getting it wrong when claiming Bobby said that at the moment of death ''everything just goes to black.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schaffer said that HBO's own viewing of the scene revealed Bobby's exact quote to be ''You probably don't ever hear it when it happens, right?''</p>
        <p>That does not undercut the overall conclusion that Mr. Chase was hinting at Tony's fate with that final scene, which comes just as a bell rings as the restaurant's door opens for his daughter and the background song ''Don't Stop Believin' '' hits the words ''don't stop.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schaffer said: ''David Chase wanted that black screen moment to be really long. It's certainly plausible to see that as a reference to death.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
