<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FACING SANCTION, DUKE PROSECUTOR SAYS HE'LL RESIGN</title>
    <meta content="16duke" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/us/16duke.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854815"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Duke University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Duff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nifong, Michael B (Dist Atty)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">District Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">District Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Duke University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Nifong, Michael B</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4D7153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FACING SANCTION, DUKE PROSECUTOR SAYS HE'LL RESIGN</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Facing Sanction, Duke Prosecutor Plans to Resign</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DUFF WILSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilson, Duff</byline>
      <dateline>RALEIGH, N.C., June 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Durham County Dist Atty Michael B Nifong announces his resignation as he faces disciplinary charges for his handling of sexual assault prosecution against three former Duke University lacrosse players who were later declared innocent; apologizes to players, their families and North Carolina justice system; his resignation comes as surprise on fourth day of hearing by state bar association; timeline of events in case; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michael B. Nifong, the Durham County district attorney, announced Friday that he would resign, as he faces disciplinary charges for his handling of a sexual assault prosecution against three former Duke University lacrosse players who were later declared innocent.</p>
        <p>Speaking in a barely audible voice in testimony before a disciplinary hearing panel, Mr. Nifong apologized to the players, their families and the North Carolina justice system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At a disciplinary hearing, Michael B. Nifong apologized to three lacrosse players and their families.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Michael B. Nifong, the Durham County district attorney, announced Friday that he would resign, as he faces disciplinary charges for his handling of a sexual assault prosecution against three former Duke University lacrosse players who were later declared innocent.</p>
        <p>Speaking in a barely audible voice in testimony before a disciplinary hearing panel, Mr. Nifong apologized to the players, their families and the North Carolina justice system.</p>
        <p>His resignation came as a surprise on the fourth day of a hearing by the North Carolina State Bar, which has charged him with ''systematic abuse of prosecutorial discretion'' for withholding evidence and making improper pretrial statements.</p>
        <p>''It has become increasingly apparent, during the course of this week, in some ways that it might not have been before, that my presence as the district attorney in Durham is not furthering the cause of justice,'' Mr. Nifong said.</p>
        <p>Joseph B. Cheshire, a lawyer for one of the three former players, said of Mr. Nifong's promise to resign: ''I believe it is a cynical political attempt to save his law license. His apology is far too late.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nifong, 56, still faces the resolution of the ethics charges, perhaps as early as Saturday, which could lead to his disbarment. Mr. Cheshire said defense lawyers planned to file a motion requesting that Mr. Nifong be found in criminal contempt of court for misstatements to the judge and lawyers in pretrial hearings. The charge, if upheld, could result in fines or jail time. The families are also considering civil suits.</p>
        <p>The case stemmed from accusations by a stripper hired for a lacrosse team party in March 2006 that she had been sexually assaulted by three players. It developed into a case that was charged with issues of race and privilege.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nifong, who had declared team members ''a bunch of hooligans,'' eventually dropped the most serious charges against the men and then recused himself from the case when the state bar brought charges against him.</p>
        <p>In April, North Carolina's attorney general, Roy A. Cooper, dismissed all the charges, saying there was no evidence of an attack and calling Mr. Nifong ''a rogue prosecutor.''</p>
        <p>In his testimony on Friday, Mr. Nifong faulted himself for his inflammatory public statements last winter, which he said were intended to pressure witnesses to come forward when the police investigation stalled.</p>
        <p>At one point after the accusation surfaced, Mr. Nifong said, ''I am not going to let Durham's view in the eyes of the world be a bunch of lacrosse players from Duke raping a black girl from Durham.''</p>
        <p>On Friday, he said, ''I think that crossed the line.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nifong said he had made other mistakes in the case but continued to defend himself against charges from the bar that he had intentionally lied and withheld from the defense DNA evidence favorable to the defendants.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nifong, a 29-year veteran of the district attorney's office who had been appointed to the job in April 2005 by Gov. Michael F. Easley, attributed his mistakes to inattention, preoccupation with a political campaign, and what he said was inexperience in handling felony cases in recent years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nifong filed the charges when he was in the middle of a tough campaign for election as district attorney -- during which he touted his experience as a prosecutor -- and as the case faltered, he was accused of pursuing the charges against the white players to bolster his support among Durham's black voters.</p>
        <p>''It is not fair for the people of my community to be represented by someone who is not held in high esteem by either the members of the community or the members of the profession,'' Mr. Nifong said in his statement Friday. ''I will go to my grave being associated with this case. And that's O.K. I don't have a problem with that.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nifong, still on the stand after his statement, faced forceful questioning from the chairman of the three-member ethics panel. During that testimony, he said he still believed that ''something happened'' in the bathroom where the stripper claimed to have been assaulted, although he said it might have been a nonsexual assault or an act of intimidation that resulted in the breaking up of the party.</p>
        <p>Afterward, James P. Cooney III, a lawyer for one of the former defendants, Reade W. Seligmann, condemned Mr. Nifong for criticizing the lacrosse team's behavior at the party. ''For him to apologize,'' Mr. Cooney said, ''and then to continue to slander 46 innocent people about a crime that did not happen, is outrageous.''</p>
        <p>In marked contrast to Mr. Nifong's testimony, earlier in the day Mr. Seligmann, 21, gave emotional testimony about the anguish of facing false charges that interrupted a year of his education and could have sent him to prison for 30 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seligmann choked up and repeatedly wiped back tears as he described hearing the news that he had been indicted and telling his parents.</p>
        <p>''My dad just fell to the floor, and I just sat on the ground,'' Mr. Seligmann said. ''And I said, 'My life is over.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Seligmann recounted how last winter, Mr. Nifong refused to meet with his lawyer who had evidence that he was not even at the party when the assault supposedly occurred. He said that Mr. Nifong had said he was not interested in ''fiction'' and that the district attorney ''smirked'' on another occasion when the evidence was offered.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nifong watched without visible expression Friday morning as Mr. Seligmann described how people in familiar restaurants and on the Duke campus turned against him after the charges were filed. Mr. Seligmann said people in a restaurant he ate in every day and considered friends put up a ''Wanted'' poster showing the entire Duke lacrosse team.</p>
        <p>''The feeling on campus was as lonely as you can imagine,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
