<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Singing! Dancing! Tragedy! Comedy! Resurrecting a 1600s Operatic Spectacle</title>
    <meta content="16lull" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/arts/music/16lull.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854732"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Lully, Jean-Baptiste</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6D9153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="579" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Singing! Dancing! Tragedy! Comedy! Resurrecting a 1600s Operatic Spectacle</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Singing! Dancing! Tragedy! Comedy! Resurrecting a 1600s Operatic Spectacle</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE MIDGETTE</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, June 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Baroque opera was the Busby Berkeley extravaganza of its day. It focused on spectacle and pageantry, and with composers like Jean-Baptiste Lully cranking out an opera a year, it was eminently disposable.</p>
        <p>That aspect can be lost in the haze of scholarly seriousness around informed reconstructions of period works. So it was nice that the Boston Early Music Festival's production of Lully's ''Psyché,'' which opened on Tuesday at the Cutler Majestic Theater, captured some of the antic excess of the era, with a prodigal wealth of singers and dancers in colorful costumes, awash in lace and face powder. Even so, it was more muted, and earnest, than it probably was in the original.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Boston Early Music Festival’s production of Lully’s “Psyché,” which opened on Tuesday, captured some of the antic excess of the era of Baroque opera.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Baroque opera was the Busby Berkeley extravaganza of its day. It focused on spectacle and pageantry, and with composers like Jean-Baptiste Lully cranking out an opera a year, it was eminently disposable.</p>
        <p>That aspect can be lost in the haze of scholarly seriousness around informed reconstructions of period works. So it was nice that the Boston Early Music Festival's production of Lully's ''Psyché,'' which opened on Tuesday at the Cutler Majestic Theater, captured some of the antic excess of the era, with a prodigal wealth of singers and dancers in colorful costumes, awash in lace and face powder. Even so, it was more muted, and earnest, than it probably was in the original.</p>
        <p>New old music is the perennial concern of this fine festival. Held every two years, it is a hub of the American early-music world, at once a trade convention and a cornucopia of concerts built around the performance of a neglected opera.</p>
        <p>The festival's artistic directors, Paul O'Dette and Stephen Stubbs, assembled the performing edition of ''Psyché'' from some 35 sources and brought back much of the same team they used for Lully's ''Thésée'' in 2001, including the choreographer Lucy Graham, who here graciously animated the rhythms of Baroque dance forms through the dancers' bodies.</p>
        <p>Dance was central to ''Psyché,'' which originated in 1671 as a ''tragicomédie et ballet'' -- a new genre -- before Lully reworked it as a more conventional ''tragédie lyrique'' in 1678. Even in this later version, choreography, voices and instruments were balanced as if on a jeweler's scale: strings fell silent during vocal ensembles; singers, during dances; and the whole was supported on a strong continuo fulcrum of theorbos, gamba and harpsichords.</p>
        <p>And the work ended in an extended ''ballet'' to celebrate Cupid and Psyché's wedding. This was actually a pageant of song and dance featuring everyone from Apollo to a Santa-like Silenus: pure entertaining spectacle, somewhat overlong for modern tastes, in which Busby Berkeley would have come into his own.</p>
        <p>For all the pomp, and the Baroque stage machinery suspending gods and demons from the flies, the real engine of the evening was the orchestra, its members facing one another around a kind of library table, playing with the warm, chewy tautness of original instruments, but without the squeaks and squawks that are often their hallmark. The continuo, which included Mr. Stubbs and Mr. O'Dette, was particularly fine.</p>
        <p>Given the emphasis on spectacle, it was odd that here, as in many other early-music productions, the singers tended to be competent and agreeable rather than distinctive. Among the leads, Karina Gauvin was strong as the aggrieved Venus, jealous of Psyché's hold over her son; Carolyn Sampson sang Psyché pleasantly, with a voice both light and warm. An odd interposition of an Italian vocal trio of grieving citizens stood out, thanks to Yulia van Doren and Douglas Williams.</p>
        <p>Works like these occupy such different dramatic territory from that we are used to today that there is no sense in presenting them in anything other than a fine period production like this. Contemporary relevance will out: this was demonstrated by a sitcom marital spat between Venus and Vulcain (Colin Balzer) that, centuries after it was written, still drew laughs.</p>
        <p>''Psyché'' continues through Sunday at the Cutler Majestic Theater at Emerson College, 219 Tremont Street, Boston, and then will be staged at the Mahaiwe Performing Arts Center, 14 Castle Street, Great Barrington, Mass., Friday through June 24; (617) 661-1812 or bemf.org.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
