<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Council Budget Is Adopted, With Members' Pet Projects Identified</title>
    <meta content="16budget" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/nyregion/16budget.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854765"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00EFD9153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="941" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Council Budget Is Adopted, With Members' Pet Projects Identified</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Council Budget Is Adopted, With Members’ Pet Projects Identified</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAY RIVERA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There were the usual earmarks for things like Boy Scouts and churches, Greek-American radio and day care, even some money sprinkled in for fireworks. Only this time, there was a little more explanation of who was responsible for the money.</p>
        <p>The City Council unanimously approved a $59 billion spending package for the city yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The City Council unanimously approved a $59 billion spending package for the city on Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There were the usual earmarks for things like Boy Scouts and churches, Greek-American radio and day care, even some money sprinkled in for fireworks. Only this time, there was a little more explanation of who was responsible for the money.</p>
        <p>The City Council unanimously approved a $59 billion spending package for the city yesterday.</p>
        <p>Most of the budget's highlights, including a 7 percent cut in property tax rates, were revealed days ago.</p>
        <p>But for the first time that anyone at City Hall could remember, the new budget details released yesterday identified which members sponsored the hundreds of discretionary appropriations for pet projects that are inserted into the budget each year. This year there were 1,674 items totaling more than $36 million.</p>
        <p>The disclosures were part of Council Speaker Christine C. Quinn's effort to bring more openness to the typically opaque ritual. So it seemed appropriate that for one of the few times in recent years, the budget vote was taken in the light of the afternoon instead of the usual frenzied late-night rush.</p>
        <p>The earmarks, sometimes termed pork-barrel spending, went to the usual list of nonprofit groups, religious and ethnic organizations and youth programs that council members finance each year to spread a little political good will in their districts. This year, members had to attach their names and say a little bit about what the money was for.</p>
        <p>Understanding the various motivations for the grants, whether altruistic, civic minded or political, could still take months to unravel for anyone intent on trying. But the new budget offers a big head start, government watchdog groups said.</p>
        <p>''In the past, all the public knew after some creative searching of the city budget was the name of the recipient organization and the amount of the grant,'' said Dick Dadey, executive director of Citizens Union. ''Now we know for what purpose the money is intended and which City Council members are responsible for securing the grants.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dadey also praised the overall budget, which presented details of agency budgets in a manner more understandable to the public.</p>
        <p>The $59 billion budget includes a $4.7 billion surplus, a $300 million increase over earlier projections. The budget is 10 percent larger than the budget adopted last year, a fact driven both by rising revenue and increased labor expenses. The budget also puts $2.8 billion toward future debt and expenses and a retirement trust fund for city workers.</p>
        <p>Many of the earmarks were signed by more than one member, but of those signed by a single council member, Leroy G. Comrie Jr. led with 870 items totaling nearly $710,857.</p>
        <p>His earmarks ranged from $5,000 to a group called a Better Jamaica to show movies in parks for Southeast Queens residents, to $45,000 to the Southeast Queens Park Association for sports and youth activities. He also spread out lots of $5,000 and $10,000 gifts to social programs in his district, which includes Jamaica, St. Albans and Queens Village.</p>
        <p>Mr. Comrie was surprised to learn he had the most individual items but said he was proud of the programs he supported, adding, ''I have a high-needs district.''</p>
        <p>Next on the list was Lewis A. Fidler, of Brooklyn, with 40 items totaling $682,625. His projects included $25,000 to the Creative Outlet Dance Theater of Brooklyn to pay for health insurance and to hire staff members. His money also went to various programs for the elderly, health care and youth activities.</p>
        <p>Eighteen members put their names on a $360,000 earmark for the Brooklyn Alliance, the borough's chamber of commerce, for the purpose of ''funding support for fireworks on Coney Island and economic development initiatives.''</p>
        <p>There was also $100,000 for Chess in the Schools Inc., for using ''chess to teach critical thinking and problem solving.'' That item had a dozen signatures, including those of Ms. Quinn, Gale A. Brewer of Manhattan and Eric N. Gioia of Queens.</p>
        <p>David I. Weprin, chairman of the Council Finance Committee, said the disclosure of member items as well other changes ''made this the most open budget in the nation.''</p>
        <p>At least one council member said the changes did not go far enough. Hiram Monserrate of Queens unsuccessfully sponsored a bill last year that would have required each of the Council's initiatives, not just earmarks, to have the sponsoring member's name attached and show which district the money was going into.</p>
        <p>The Council's discretionary spending, including the earmarks, totaled $233 million this year, about the same as last year. The largest chunk of that, $42 million, went to expand branch library hours across the city to six days a week, a service that was lost in cuts after Sept. 11, 2001.</p>
        <p>Other highlights in the initiative list included $6.7 million for programs to give low-level offenders an alternative to jail or prisons, such as community service and substance abuse counseling.</p>
        <p>In many instances, the Council is restoring funds to programs that have been subsidized by the city for years but were either cut out or not included in the mayor's budget, which he unveiled earlier this year. Ms. Quinn said attaching a single name to those programs would be impractical because they are typically widely supported by the council, and the original sponsor may no longer be a member.</p>
        <p>Adding sponsors' names to new initiatives, as Mr. Monserrate suggested, was a good idea, she said, and something the Council might look into when it takes up the budget next year.</p>
        <p>''We're legitimately trying to make the process more transparent,'' Ms. Quinn said. ''We took a major step forward. Now people will suggest how we can make it better and we'll consider all of them.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
