<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reyes Spark Tames Clemens Heat</title>
    <meta content="16yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/sports/baseball/16yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Clemens, Roger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Reyes, Jose</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Pérez, Oliver</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E6D6153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1010" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reyes Spark Tames Clemens Heat</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spark From Reyes Overcomes Heat From Clemens</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Their symbolic subway cars were headed in opposite directions. The Yankees were the hottest team in the majors, the Mets the coldest. The Bronx was up, Queens was down and, last night, both batteries were on.</p>
        <p>The opening act of this weekend's clash at Yankee Stadium was defined by the space between pitcher and catcher. Roger Clemens was even better than he was in his debut last week, but he could not solve José Reyes, whose offense made the sparkling work of Oliver Pérez stand up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oliver Perez limited the Yankees to five hits in 7 1/3 innings to lift the Mets in the opener of the season’s second Subway Series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Their symbolic subway cars were headed in opposite directions. The Yankees were the hottest team in the majors, the Mets the coldest. The Bronx was up, Queens was down and, last night, both batteries were on.</p>
        <p>The opening act of this weekend's clash at Yankee Stadium was defined by the space between pitcher and catcher. Roger Clemens was even better than he was in his debut last week, but he could not solve José Reyes, whose offense made the sparkling work of Oliver Pérez stand up.</p>
        <p>The Mets won, 2-0, ending their five-game losing streak and the Yankees' nine-game winning streak. Pérez blanked the Yankees on five hits through seven and a third innings, and three relievers finished off the shutout.</p>
        <p>''We have some guys swinging the bats pretty good, and he came in and shut us down,'' Derek Jeter said of Pérez. ''You'd like to win because Rocket pitched well, but today he was a little bit better.''</p>
        <p>Clemens, who beat Pittsburgh last Saturday after allowing three runs in six innings, gave up only two over six and a third last night. He struck out eight, walked one and gave up seven hits -- three to Reyes, who drove in a run with a single, homered off the right-field facade and stole three bases.</p>
        <p>Reyes came into the game hitless in six career at-bats against Clemens. But he looked comfortable last night, even if the other Mets hitters did not.</p>
        <p>''It's no secret -- when the team struggles, your main player is in a little bit of a funk,'' Mets Manager Willie Randolph said. ''What happened tonight? He got on base and we won.''</p>
        <p>In the first inning, Reyes led off with a single to right on a high splitter with two strikes. Clemens survived that inning, striking out Carlos Delgado for the first of three times, but the Mets scored in the third.</p>
        <p>Carlos Gómez led off with a bunt single and stole second. Reyes tried to get him over, twice fouling off bunts before swinging away on 2-2. Clemens said he made a good pitch, a splitter tumbling down and away, but Reyes punched it to center for a run-scoring single.</p>
        <p>Reyes came up again with one out in the fifth, hammering a first-pitch curveball off the facing of the third deck in right field. Clemens threw only two other curveballs all game, catcher Jorge Posada guessed, and he would not get a chance to face Reyes again.</p>
        <p>''They were aggressive, and we stayed with our game plan,'' Clemens said. ''Jorge did a tremendous job. We kept guys off-balance, but even when you do that, they get some hits.''</p>
        <p>Still trailing by 2-0 in the seventh, Clemens retired Julio Franco and faced the speedy Gómez again. Gómez , 21, pushed a bunt toward first base, and Clemens, 44, broke off the mound to cover the bag.</p>
        <p>It was not much of a race. Gómez easily beat Clemens for a single, and Manager Joe Torre came to the mound to remove him after 108 pitches. He was not serenaded by Elton John's ''Rocket Man'' this time -- the Yankees were losing.</p>
        <p>The Yankees left seven runners on base in the first four innings against Pérez, looking even more helpless against him than they had in a loss last month.</p>
        <p>Pérez (7-5) has done his best work in showcase games, with a 5-0 record and a 1.26 earned run average this season against the Yankees and the Atlanta Braves.</p>
        <p>''Tonight, we ran into a buzz saw,'' Torre said. ''He shut us down completely. The most important thing is that we won't see him again.''</p>
        <p>After being overpowered by Pérez in the first three innings, striking out five times, the Yankees could blame only themselves in the fourth. Pérez walked the first two hitters before a fly out, and Miguel Cairo then drove a ball to the top of the wall down the left-field line. Gómez leaped for the catch, and Matsui, who had been at second, was nearly to third.</p>
        <p>Base running is normally a strength for Matsui, who rarely makes a fundamental error. But foot speed is not, and he had no time to retreat. By the time he slid into second, he was out on an inning-ending double play.</p>
        <p>''Even though I was positioned there, I was pretty sure I was going to be able to get back,'' Matsui said through an interpreter. ''But Gómez had a stronger arm than I expected.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees would not put another runner on base until the eighth, when Jeter chased Pérez with a double to the right-field corner. But the Yankees could not advance him.</p>
        <p>Abreu drove a pitch from Pedro Feliciano deep to center, where Carlos Beltrán hauled it in, and Rodriguez grounded out to third against Joe Smith.</p>
        <p>Instead of his 350th career victory, Clemens took his 179th career loss. He said his body felt better than it did last Saturday, but he took little solace in that.</p>
        <p>''Like I told Joe, I still think I can give him 110, 115 pitches, and I'm proud of that fact,'' Clemens said. ''But when you come up short, there's really nothing to be happy about.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Johnny Damon was a late scratch from the lineup with a strained abdominal muscle, but Joe Torre said he would play today.  The Mets' lineup included Julio Franco, who was the Cleveland Indians' shortstop when Roger Clemens made his major league debut for Boston on May 15, 1984. Franco went 1 for 3 against Clemens that night and is 19 for 94 against him in his career. Tony Bernazard, a Mets' vice president who watched from the second row last night, was Franco's double-play partner in Clemens's debut. Bernazard was the first player Clemens ever hit with a pitch.  Clemens's and Franco's combined age yesterday was 93 years 246 days. Their meeting was the oldest pitcher-batter matchup since Nick Altrock of the Washington Senators faced pitcher Rube Walberg of the Philadelphia A's in 1933, according to the Elias Sports Bureau.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
