<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Out Amid the Cold Night Air the Devil Dares to Tread</title>
    <meta content="16faus" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/arts/music/16faus.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854731"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Central Park (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Metropolitan Opera</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gelb, Peter</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE7D9153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="464" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Out Amid the Cold Night Air the Devil Dares to Tread</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Out Amid the Cold Night Air the Devil Dares to Tread</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIEN SCHWEITZER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wednesday evening was so unseasonably cold that it felt as if hell had frozen over Central Park during the Metropolitan Opera's concert performance of Gounod's ''Faust,'' which opened its annual free summer series.</p>
        <p>The Met series was scheduled to begin on Tuesday in Central Park with ''La Bohème,'' but the event was canceled because of heavy rain and won't be rescheduled. Given Wednesday's cold weather, it was hardly surprising that only about 12,500 people showed up, according to a police estimate provided by Met officials. (Last summer, more than 30,000 people attended ''La Traviata'' in Central Park.) But the hardy opera lovers who went anyway wrapped themselves in blankets, huddled together and shivered over their picnics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wednesday evening was so unseasonably cold that it felt as if hell had frozen over Central Park during the Metropolitan Opera’s concert performance of Gounod’s “Faust,” which opened its annual free summer series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wednesday evening was so unseasonably cold that it felt as if hell had frozen over Central Park during the Metropolitan Opera's concert performance of Gounod's ''Faust,'' which opened its annual free summer series.</p>
        <p>The Met series was scheduled to begin on Tuesday in Central Park with ''La Bohème,'' but the event was canceled because of heavy rain and won't be rescheduled. Given Wednesday's cold weather, it was hardly surprising that only about 12,500 people showed up, according to a police estimate provided by Met officials. (Last summer, more than 30,000 people attended ''La Traviata'' in Central Park.) But the hardy opera lovers who went anyway wrapped themselves in blankets, huddled together and shivered over their picnics.</p>
        <p>Before the concert, Margaret Juntwait, a host of the Metropolitan Opera radio broadcasts, encouraged the audience to stay warm and praised Peter Gelb's achievements in his first season as general manager, which included successful initiatives like simulcasts in movie theaters. The Met's populism in the parks, however, began long before Mr. Gelb's admirable efforts to bring opera to the masses. (The summer series is now in its 41st year.)</p>
        <p>Maurizio Benini, who conducted Wednesday's concert, had to compete, as usual, with microphones, planes, birds twittering, papers fluttering and people (and teeth) chattering. He led a lively performance that was as nuanced as possible under the circumstances, but unsurprisingly, many of the subtleties of Gounod's score were swallowed by the background noise. There were also a few moments in Act II when the chorus (whose diction was muddled, perhaps by the microphones) was out of sync with the orchestra.</p>
        <p>''Faust'' was the first opera performed at the Metropolitan Opera, on Oct. 22, 1883. Wednesday's performance featured a young cast alongside the veteran bass James Morris, who portrayed Méphistophélès with chilling conviction and naughty menace.</p>
        <p>In the title role, David Pomeroy sang with a powerful, agile tenor and commendable French diction, although his voice sometimes sounded forced in the upper register. His ''Salut demeure'' was heartfelt, but his portrayal was often rather bland, especially next to the dramatically convincing Marguerite of Katie Van Kooten whose warm, gracefully expressive soprano was lively in the ''Jewel'' song and vulnerable in ''Anges Purs! Anges Radieux!''</p>
        <p>The able baritone Hung Yun was admirable as Valentin, her protective brother. The mezzo-soprano Kate Lindsey sang with an attractive voice and was effective as Siébel. Keith Miller as Wagner and Jane Bunnell as Marthe were also strong.</p>
        <p>The musicians and singers must have been almost as frozen as the audience, which predictably, given the plummeting temperature, appeared to have thinned significantly by the end. But a sprinkling of determined listeners braved Faustian frostbite and stayed around for Marguerite's salvation.</p>
        <p>The Metropolitan Opera will present ''Faust'' tonight in Snug Harbor, Staten Island; metopera .org.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
