<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spurs Give Cavaliers a Glimpse at How It's Done</title>
    <meta content="16nba" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/sports/basketball/16nba.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854826"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/San Antonio Spurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">San Antonio Spurs</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Cleveland Cavaliers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Basketball Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Popovich, Gregg</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Duncan, Tim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E1D7153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spurs Give Cavaliers a Glimpse at How It's Done</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spurs Give Cavaliers, and Others, a Look at How It’s Done</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The marketing slogans that accompanied LeBron James and the Cleveland Cavaliers to their first N.B.A. finals lay like discarded signposts the day after the Cavaliers' quick capitulation to the San Antonio Spurs.</p>
        <p>''Rise Up!'' became tumble down when the Spurs completed a four-game sweep Thursday night to capture the franchise's fourth championship in nine years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Spurs’ unassuming hegemony starts with the calculating mind of Coach Gregg Popovich and emanates from forward Tim Duncan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The marketing slogans that accompanied LeBron James and the Cleveland Cavaliers to their first N.B.A. finals lay like discarded signposts the day after the Cavaliers' quick capitulation to the San Antonio Spurs.</p>
        <p>''Rise Up!'' became tumble down when the Spurs completed a four-game sweep Thursday night to capture the franchise's fourth championship in nine years.</p>
        <p>The ''Witness'' campaign turned into the witness protection program. The Cavaliers must figure out how to surround James with better talent.</p>
        <p>And ''All for One and One for All'' seemed more apropos for the Spurs, if only they endorsed the conceit of slogans. Success, they seem to feel, sells itself.</p>
        <p>''You don't need to be flashy,'' said Robert Horry, the role player who collected his seventh championship ring and his second with the Spurs. ''It's all about getting the job done.''</p>
        <p>The Spurs' unassuming hegemony starts with the calculating mind of Coach Gregg Popovich, a one-time Air Force officer in counterintelligence, and emanates from forward Tim Duncan, a peerless All-Star who cares more about his peers than himself.</p>
        <p>With Duncan, 31, healthier than he has been in two seasons, the Spurs do not appear to be slowing down, even in a run-and-gun Western Conference featuring the Phoenix Suns and the Golden State Warriors.</p>
        <p>Duncan and his teammates proved throughout these playoffs that they could diffuse dynamic performers like Denver's Carmelo Anthony and Allen Iverson, run (and bump) with Phoenix and deconstruct a similar hybrid team in Utah before befuddling James.</p>
        <p>It would be easy to say that the Spurs' defense (the Cavaliers averaged 80.5 points a game in the finals) classified them as old school. But they are also an example of the modern N.B.A. as one of the first teams to have mined global talent, which sparkled in this series.</p>
        <p>Tony Parker became the first European named the most valuable player of the finals, a month after Dallas's Dirk Nowitzki was the first European named the regular season M.V.P. As a child in France, Parker, 25, watched Michael Jordan win championships on television at 3 a.m. Late Thursday night, he hoisted the trophy before a new generation.</p>
        <p>''European basketball is improving every year,'' Parker said. ''There's going to be more. I'm on the list now.''</p>
        <p>Manu Ginóbili, the 30-year-old fearless slasher from Argentina, already had an Olympic gold medal with his Spurs teammate Fabricio Oberto. Ginóbili helped clinch his third championship with the Spurs in the fourth quarter of Game 4, when he scored 13 of his 27 points and turned back a late charge by the Cavaliers.</p>
        <p>''Of course you feel very proud and honored to be an important part of this franchise,'' Ginóbili said. ''We know we are probably the best team the last 10, 8 years.''</p>
        <p>There was that Shaquille O'Neal-Kobe Bryant partnership that marked the beginning of the decade, winning three titles for the Los Angeles Lakers from 2000 to 2002. But unlike that team, San Antonio managed to win its third title with the same group of stars intact and hugging, providing a multifaceted model for the league.</p>
        <p>Cleveland's hierarchy -- General Manager Danny Ferry, his assistant Lance Blanks and Coach Mike Brown -- trained under Popovich and desperately wanted to emulate the small-market success of San Antonio. But as the mismatch showed, the Cavaliers have to solve some personnel problems and create an offense that goes beyond giving the ball to James.</p>
        <p>Brown was asked before Game 4 what kind of style of play he wanted next season. ''I want to be an opportunistic fast-break team that attacks,'' he said, even if his players rarely went on the fast break.</p>
        <p>But Brown also talked about playing a grind-out game before concluding, ''I'd like to be a team that can play any style on any given night.''</p>
        <p>The Cavaliers struggled to score 80 points against the Spurs; twice they did not. When the ball was in James's hands for a predictable pick and roll, the Spurs blitzed him, cut off his passing and driving lanes and kept him guessing with their coverages. James often resorted to off-balance jumpers. None of the Cavaliers adjusted, Brown acknowledged.</p>
        <p>After Duncan stepped down from the interview podium Thursday, he and James exchanged congratulations on their seasons.</p>
        <p>''He has a great supporting cast around him,'' James said, almost longingly. ''He definitely brings out the best in his teammates. I think I kind of want to do the same thing.''</p>
        <p>But with Zydrunas Ilgauskas, Drew Gooden, a limping Larry Hughes and an aging Eric Snow, there was only so much James could do.</p>
        <p>A rookie point guard, Daniel Gibson, emerged as James's second-most reliable player. But that was in the Eastern Conference finals, a series victory marked by James's 48-point effort, which gave the Cavaliers an inflated sense of self-worth.</p>
        <p>''After losing the way we lost, it is definitely going to motivate us to get back to this point next year and change the outcome of things,'' Gibson said.</p>
        <p>But Ferry could have trouble making changes this summer. With a payroll exceeding the salary cap, he limited himself by signing ineffective players like Damon Jones and Hughes to long-term contracts. (Hughes signed a five-year, $60 million deal in 2005.) Even if Ferry could package a post player to find a shooter, few teams may want to help the defending Eastern Conference champions improve.</p>
        <p>James was swept in his first trip to the finals, as Shaquille O'Neal was in 1995 with the Orlando Magic. Will James have to go elsewhere to win a title? He signed a three-year, $60 million contract with the Cavaliers last summer that goes into effect next season.</p>
        <p>''I really think the team we have now is good enough to win a championship,'' James said. ''Everybody has to be better coming into next season. I have to be 10 times better.''</p>
        <p>The flip side of James's early success only raised the Cavaliers' expectations. Now, as the Spurs have learned, they are going to have to fulfill them.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
