<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For the Mets, L Is for a Lineup Change to Shake Up the Offense</title>
    <meta content="16mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854844"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E6D6153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For the Mets, L Is for a Lineup Change to Shake Up the Offense</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mets Manager Willie Randolph opened his pregame interview session with a response straight out of ''Sesame Street.'' Asked why Carlos Beltrán was moved up to hit second last night, Randolph said: ''His name starts with a B and it's the second letter in the alphabet. How do you like that?''</p>
        <p>No, he was not serious, although that reasoning could also help to explain why Carlos Delgado returned to the cleanup spot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mets Manager Willie Randolph opened his pregame interview session with a response straight out of ''Sesame Street.'' Asked why Carlos Beltrán was moved up to hit second last night, Randolph said: ''His name starts with a B and it's the second letter in the alphabet. How do you like that?''</p>
        <p>No, he was not serious, although that reasoning could also help to explain why Carlos Delgado returned to the cleanup spot.</p>
        <p>Randolph was in a particularly cagey mood before the game, deflecting questions about lineup changes, the Mets' five-game losing streak and Roger Clemens with a well-timed quip or some graceful ad-libbing. He said that he never left his house on Thursday's day off, and maybe he spent that time thinking of the punch lines.</p>
        <p>''To me, all this stuff going on is nothing,'' Randolph said. ''I'm not tripping. I'm not down on anything.''</p>
        <p>Still, Randolph did not deny that he was looking for some sort of energy infusion, and the lineup change could have been it. Randolph indicated that when Beltrán hits second, behind José Reyes and in front of David Wright, he tends to see better pitches to hit. Mindful of Reyes's speed, pitchers may be less inclined to throw breaking pitches to Beltrán.</p>
        <p>Wright entered the game hitting .357 this month, by far the best average among the Mets' starters, and he can supply protection for Beltrán. In his only other game batting second this season, on April 19 in Florida, Beltrán went 4 for 6 with a home run.</p>
        <p>Reyes went 3 for 3, hit a home run and stole three bases last night in a 2-0 Mets victory, but Beltrán went 1 for 4, Wright went 1 for 3 and Delgado went 0 for 4 with four strikeouts.</p>
        <p>''The way I look at my team is simple,'' Randolph said. ''As my leadoff hitter and my middle-of-the-lineup guys are struggling, and any time that happens, we're going to look how we look right now.''</p>
        <p>Beltrán, who entered the game batting .154 (6 for 39) in June, said that his knee, which he bruised two weeks ago, did not bother him anymore, but that he is still hampered by soreness in his left quadriceps.</p>
        <p>''Whatever's good for the team,'' Beltrán said. ''If you ask me what I prefer, my preference is hitting third. But I don't make the lineup.''</p>
        <p>Delgado served as the Mets' designated hitter, although he did not know about it until told by reporters a few hours before the game. Julio Franco played first base.</p>
        <p>''It's like pinch-hitting four times in a row,'' Delgado said. ''The day I don't want to go out in the field is the day I go home.''</p>
        <p>When the subject turned to Clemens, particularly his history against the Mets, Randolph recalled the moment from Game 2 of the 2000 World Series when Clemens threw Mike Piazza's broken bat in Piazza's general direction. Of those who switched sides in this rivalry, Randolph is the most prominent. He was the Yankees' third-base coach then, but said that if he were managing the Mets, he would have expected more of an angry reaction from Piazza.</p>
        <p>''I would have thought that Mike Piazza should have gone after him,'' Randolph said.</p>
        <p>Just as quickly, Randolph brushed aside a question wondering whether, on a smaller scale, his team could benefit from an event like that. Struggling as they may be, the Mets do not need any fights to motivate them, he said. But what if Clemens would have hit someone?</p>
        <p>''Oh yeah, the whole team would just jump on him,'' Randolph said. ''We'd take turns.''</p>
        <p>BACKING UP THE BACKUP PLAN -- The severity of the Mets' injury situation struck General Manager Omar Minaya during his recent trip to their minor league facility in Port St. Lucie, Fla. Minaya looked in the trainer's room and saw Endy Chávez and Lastings Milledge receiving treatment. They were his backup plan if Moises Alou got injured. All three players have missed significant time with an injury, and none of them are scheduled to return anytime soon.</p>
        <p>''Our C plan was Carlos Gómez and some of our other young guys,'' Minaya said. ''I would think we're going to get back to our A plan or B plan at some point.''</p>
        <p>Of the three, Milledge, who has not played in six weeks because of sprained foot ligaments, may be back sooner, and he is at least two weeks away, Minaya said. Chávez (hamstring strain) could be back within the next five weeks, while Alou (strained left quadriceps) is no closer -- or further away -- from returning.</p>
        <p>Minaya said he doubted Alou would rejoin the team before next month but that he still expected him to play again this season. Minaya also said that Ambiorix Burgos, now a reliever for Class AAA New Orleans, is out indefinitely with elbow discomfort.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Pedro Martínez incorporated breaking balls into his bullpen session yesterday in Port St. Lucie, Fla., for the first time. He threw 53 pitches.  By extending his hitting streak to 15 games on Wednesday night, David Wright became the only player in franchise history with three separate 15-game hitting streaks, according to Trent McCotter of the Society for American Baseball Research. The other Mets with two 15-game hitting streaks are Tommie Agee, Edgardo Alfonzo, Ed Kranepool, Lee Mazzilli, Félix Millán, Mike Piazza, José Reyes, John Stearns and José Vizcaíno.  The Mets are scheduled to face the two-time Cy Young Award winner Johan Santana on Tuesday, in the middle game of their three-game series against the Minnesota Twins at Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
