<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S.G.A.'s Urban Drive Is Well Short</title>
    <meta content="16roberts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/sports/golf/16roberts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854841"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Selena Roberts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">United States Golf Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Dogg, Snoop</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E6D6153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="881" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S.G.A.'s Urban Drive Is Well Short</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S.G.A.’s Urban Drive Is Well Short</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the scene, Snoop Dogg maintained his street cred despite being dressed in an argyle sweater and pink polo as he zipped to a tee box in a customized cart with chrome rims and Lee Iacocca in the passenger seat.</p>
        <p>The odd couple pitched Chrysler cars in the 2005 commercial that ended with Snoop whipping a drive with the most ungainly swing this side of Jim Furyk's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Golf’s caretakers seem complacent with the sport the way it is: safely suburban, affluently anchored. The private politics of the United States Golf Association say so.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the scene, Snoop Dogg maintained his street cred despite being dressed in an argyle sweater and pink polo as he zipped to a tee box in a customized cart with chrome rims and Lee Iacocca in the passenger seat.</p>
        <p>The odd couple pitched Chrysler cars in the 2005 commercial that ended with Snoop whipping a drive with the most ungainly swing this side of Jim Furyk's.</p>
        <p>This about sums up the extent of golf's inner-city outreach: props and camera tricks.</p>
        <p>Where is an urban legend when golf needs one? On an afternoon when putts rolled to another area code on Formica greens, when Oakmont devoured the psyches of he pros, the United States Open could have used a player with a streetwise edge to his wedge, with a little survivor in his driver.</p>
        <p>Curiously, golf has never boarded the Soul Train. After a decade of inner-city initiatives, with Tiger Woods dangled as a shiny lure for coupon-clipping swingers, the United States Golf Association has yet to produce a child prodigy out of its programs for the disadvantaged.</p>
        <p>''If you look at the numbers, they're not very good,'' said David Fay, executive director of the U.S.G.A. ''My view is that we can't throw up our hands and say it's impossible.''</p>
        <p>There is a point when preaching patience becomes a crafty way of forestalling change. Golf's caretakers seem complacent with the sport the way it is: safely suburban, affluently anchored.</p>
        <p>The private politics of the U.S.G.A.'s leaders say so. On the cover of this week's Golf World magazine, the headline reads, ''Can the U.S.G.A. Survive Walter Driver?'' He is the corporate cowboy with luxury tastes who is forcing a Wall Street approach on a nonprofit organization.</p>
        <p>The U.S.G.A.'s grassroots slogan is ''For the Good of the Game.'' Yet Driver projects what's good for him as a member of at least three private clubs with reputations for discriminatory practices: Pine Valley in New Jersey, Augusta National and Peachtree Golf Club in Atlanta. Why join one cabal of bias when you can learn secret handshakes at all three?</p>
        <p>Driver did not respond to a message about his contradiction of conscience. Fay, however, did concede the conflict. To his credit, Fay dropped his membership at Pine Valley, although he pleads guilty to playing the course on occasion.</p>
        <p>There is a game of spin the bottle for U.S.G.A. officials when deciding whether they will A) choose memberships at open clubs or B) give in to the siren song of the great American course, which, as it happens, is often run by prejudiced elites in crested blazers.</p>
        <p>''How do you square it?'' Fay said. ''Everyone has to deal with it on a personal basis. Everyone has to sort it out his own way. I've had to sort it out.</p>
        <p>''It's a struggle. That may sound like a cop-out. I can't argue with that.''</p>
        <p>Fay is honest. But the arbitrary scruples of executives poke holes in the U.S.G.A.'s credibility as a builder of culture clubs for all.</p>
        <p>''Its leadership has never looked like America, with hardly any blacks or Latinos in its top positions, no matter for all the 'Kumbaya' multicultural ads it has run promoting itself with smiling kids of all backgrounds out on the course,'' said the Duke professor Orin Starn, author of ''Caddying for the Dalai Lama: Golf, Heritage Tourism and the Pinehurst Resort,'' who is researching a book on golf and American society. ''The U.S.G.A. has wanted to style itself as upholding a democratic, open-to-all version of golf, including picking public courses like Bethpage and Torrey Pines for the Open and those promos featuring golfers at folksy little starter shacks. The reality is that the U.S.G.A. is just as much about money, big-time profits and corporate connections.''</p>
        <p>Sponsor dollars are precious. There is no desire on golf's part to engage in the cultural and social conundrums faced by the National Football League, the National Basketball Association, Major League Baseball and boxing.</p>
        <p>Let other leagues enforce dress codes banning doo rags, cope with felonious Bengals and handle the taint of steroids. As the P.G.A. commissioner, Tim Finchem, has explained, golf has resisted an anti-doping program because testing would invite the appearance of a problem.</p>
        <p>Keeping up appearances keeps up the revenue stream. But not everyone in golf is threatened by change. Woods has certainly devoted many news conferences to his hope for diversity. But what about players inside the circle of white privilege? There is enlightenment, even ideas for putting a little soul into their sport.</p>
        <p>The First Tee programs that introduce golf to city children are fine. But there needs to be an investment in follow-up support.</p>
        <p>''There will probably have to be another level put in place where there are scholarships for kids to go play lots of junior golf and maybe enter academies,'' the veteran golfer Lee Janzen said, adding, ''The next step is to get kids out of the inner city so they can make it.</p>
        <p>''I'd love to see it happen. Everyone loves the underdog, the guy who came from nowhere, the guy who was never supposed to get there and he got there.''</p>
        <p>Urban legends don't have to arrive on chrome rims. Just as long as they arrive as a reality, not as a commercial prop.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
