<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Government Financial Crisis May Claim Jerusalem Symphony</title>
    <meta content="16symp" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/arts/music/16symp.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854721"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Jerusalem (Israel)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Israel Philharmonic Orchestra</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Israel Broadcasting Authority</org>
        <org class="online_producer">BBC Worldwide Ltd</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Botstein, Leon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03EFDA153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="745" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Government Financial Crisis May Claim Jerusalem Symphony</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Government Financial Crisis May Claim Jerusalem Symphony</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DINA KRAFT</byline>
      <dateline>TEL AVIV, June 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the eve of its 70th anniversary, sharp budget cuts threaten the existence of the Jerusalem Symphony Orchestra.</p>
        <p>Created as a radio orchestra, much in the manner of the BBC Symphony, during the days of British rule, the Jerusalem operates on a modest budget of about $3.6 million a year. Its players, who perform some 40 programs annually, joke that it is one of the world's greatest low-budget orchestras.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the eve of its 70th anniversary, sharp budget cuts threaten the existence of the Jerusalem Symphony Orchestra.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the eve of its 70th anniversary, sharp budget cuts threaten the existence of the Jerusalem Symphony Orchestra.</p>
        <p>Created as a radio orchestra, much in the manner of the BBC Symphony, during the days of British rule, the Jerusalem operates on a modest budget of about $3.6 million a year. Its players, who perform some 40 programs annually, joke that it is one of the world's greatest low-budget orchestras.</p>
        <p>This week the Israel Broadcasting Authority, the public agency that provides most of the orchestra's budget, said it would be cutting its financing of the Jerusalem Symphony by 60 percent, or to roughly $1 million from $2.6 million. If the cut goes through, orchestra officials said that the symphony would be forced to shut down.</p>
        <p>Four years ago Leon Botstein, the president of Bard College in Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y., was brought on as the orchestra's music director and main conductor to help bring it out of debt. At the time Mr. Botstein refused a salary, and the players, many of them immigrants from the former Soviet Union, agreed to take a 20 percent pay cut.</p>
        <p>Mr. Botstein also raised money for the symphony, which has been operating under a court-appointed receivership, in the United States. The orchestra, of some 80 musicians, has been planning an American tour of Chicago and cities on the West Coast later this year.</p>
        <p>''We've paid our debt, and here comes the Israeli politics of the Israel Broadcasting Authority, like an overweight person who decides to lose weight by having a haircut,'' Mr. Botstein said in a telephone interview from Budapest.</p>
        <p>The Israeli government, citing inefficiency and overstaffing at the authority, has slashed the agency's budget by a total of some 40 percent over four years, said Moshe Gavish, the authority's chairman.</p>
        <p>But Yossi Tal-Gan, the orchestra's director general, said the decision would not solve the authority's own financial woes, since its support for the orchestra is less than 2 percent of the agency's total budget.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gavish said the authority could no longer shoulder the cost of the orchestra.</p>
        <p>''We cannot pay for this when we cannot pay for all the other things we are responsible for paying,'' he said, adding that it was unclear if authority employees would be paid on time in July.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gavish suggested that the city of Jerusalem and the culture ministry increase their own small contributions to the orchestra to offset the cuts.</p>
        <p>Orchestra players and officials countered that the symphony was an easy target for budget cuts compared with powerful labor unions, which would battle over salaries. They said with some bitterness that with the Israeli economy thriving, it was sad that money could not be found to support one of the nation's founding cultural institutions.</p>
        <p>The orchestra, which operates in the shadow of the more famous and established Israel Philharmonic Orchestra, sees itself as having two main roles: to play for the radio audience and to be a central force for culture in Jerusalem, an increasingly poor and religious city that has seen its base of secular cultural institutions begin to dwindle.</p>
        <p>The orchestra differentiates itself from the Israel Philharmonic, which celebrated its 70th anniversary in 2006, by playing a more diverse and less traditional repertory. It has been a home for pieces by Israeli composers and lesser-known or more challenging modern works.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Botstein's innovations was to introduce a thematic approach to programs, with one of music written in the aftermath of World War II, for example, or another of music of the late 19th century inspired by Shakespeare.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday and Thursday the orchestra is scheduled to play a program titled ''Music and the Macabre,'' including Aaron Copland's ''Grohg,'' about female vampires, and Bartok's ''Miraculous Mandarin'' (Op. 10), about a prostitute in league with robbers and the otherworldly man they lure to his death.</p>
        <p>Marina Schwartz, a violinist in the orchestra who immigrated to Israel from St. Petersburg, Russia, in the early 1990s said there was a scrappy resourcefulness to the symphony that was part of its charm. ''There are problems all the time, and yet we keep fighting on,'' she said. ''This makes me proud.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Botstein pleads that the fate of the orchestra is linked with Israel's cultural future. ''We as a Jewish people always valued learning and culture,'' he insisted. ''In the end is all that is interesting to the state of Israel soccer? Is this the dream of the founders of the state?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
