<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Specialist in Tough (to) Love</title>
    <meta content="16stew" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/arts/television/16stew.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854718"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dating (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dating (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E1DA153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="517" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Specialist in Tough (to) Love</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Specialist in Tough (to) Love</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN STEWART</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hype and hokiness aside, some reality shows are appealing because they seem real. Buffalo is the setting for ''Confessions of a Matchmaker,'' tonight on A&amp;E. Nobody will confuse that town with Hollywood, Manhattan or the castle on ''The Bachelor.'' Establishing shots show us a gritty, snowy industrial city in the unforgiving north, with a heroine to match.</p>
        <p>Patti Novak, who runs a dating service within spitting distance of Niagara Falls, is a fine representative of Buffalo and a fine character for the reality genre. She's plainspoken but not rude, a classic dispenser of tough love. When Charlie, her first customer comes in, she sizes him up pretty quickly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nobody will confuse the town of Buffalo, the setting for “Confessions of a Matchmaker,” tonight on A&amp;E, with Hollywood, Manhattan or the castle on &amp;#8220;The Bachelor.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hype and hokiness aside, some reality shows are appealing because they seem real. Buffalo is the setting for ''Confessions of a Matchmaker,'' tonight on A&amp;E. Nobody will confuse that town with Hollywood, Manhattan or the castle on ''The Bachelor.'' Establishing shots show us a gritty, snowy industrial city in the unforgiving north, with a heroine to match.</p>
        <p>Patti Novak, who runs a dating service within spitting distance of Niagara Falls, is a fine representative of Buffalo and a fine character for the reality genre. She's plainspoken but not rude, a classic dispenser of tough love. When Charlie, her first customer comes in, she sizes him up pretty quickly.</p>
        <p>''You've made a choice between doughnuts and sex,'' she says.</p>
        <p>''Life takes its toll,'' Charlie responds with a shrug. He's a former Mr. Nude Universe, but those glory days are long gone. Charlie now weighs 346 pounds and was recently kicked out of an all-you-can-eat Chinese buffet. Still, there's hope.</p>
        <p>''I see sensitivity and a great pair of blue eyes,'' Ms. Novak says. She takes him out for a test dinner and cringes as he slurps pasta: ''For God's sake, chew with your mouth closed.''</p>
        <p>Charlie learns his lesson better than another client, Ashley. A cocktail waitress, she refuses to give up her fake tan and layers of makeup. ''He might want to take you home and roll you over,'' Ms. Novak tells her, ''but I bet your bank account he won't want to take you home to Mother.''</p>
        <p>Some reality shows are predicated on cruelty, or at least a survival-of-the-fittest mentality. That ''American Idol'' seems increasingly to fit both those models may be why its ratings are slipping. Sometimes a little kindness is preferable to a freak show. Ms. Novak's clients are not weird enough to be laughable or pathetic enough to pity. They are people with whom a lot of us could identify, at least on a bad day.</p>
        <p>A very bad day, in the case of John. At 41, he says he has never had sex. He blames it partly on the economy. Ms. Novak tells him to get real.</p>
        <p>''It's not cute that you're a virgin at age 41,'' she says. ''It's a red flag the size of Texas.''</p>
        <p>It takes John two dates to figure out his problem. (The viewer may guess it sooner.) Over a shared plate of appetizers, dawn breaks. At least Ms. Novak, who is watching, detects ''chemistry.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Novak's criteria for success may be debatable. I know a lot of happily married couples who would probably fail her chemistry test, but her heart is in the right place. And heart, on a dating show, is what counts.</p>
        <p>Confessions of a Matchmaker  A&amp;E, tonight at 10, Eastern and Pacific times; 9, Central time.</p>
        <p>Created by Penny Benatovich and Patti Novak; Matthew Sharp and Smash Advertising, executive producers; Jerry Kolber, co-executive producer; Trey Nelson and Max Landes, directors; Bob Larson, executive in charge of production for Sharp Entertainment; Robert Sharenow and Colleen Conway, A&amp;E executive producers; Josh Baron, editor. Produced by Sharp Entertainment for A&amp;E Network.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
