<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A 66 on a Tough Course Wows a Tough Audience</title>
    <meta content="16links" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854825"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2D7153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A 66 on a Tough Course Wows a Tough Audience</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa., June 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Englishman Paul Casey holed an 18-inch birdie putt at the ninth hole to complete his round of four-under-par 66, the golfers who were putting on the portion of the ninth green that is set aside for practice stopped what they were doing to applaud his effort.</p>
        <p>Casey had given the late starters an extraordinary target to shoot at. In the end, nobody came close to matching his score. The second-best round on Friday was Stephen Ames's 69.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Englishman Paul Casey holed an 18-inch birdie putt at the ninth hole to complete his round of four-under-par 66, the golfers who were putting on the portion of the ninth green that is set aside for practice stopped what they were doing to applaud his effort.</p>
        <p>Casey had given the late starters an extraordinary target to shoot at. In the end, nobody came close to matching his score. The second-best round on Friday was Stephen Ames's 69.</p>
        <p>Having the added audience of his peers made that last tap-in tricky, Casey said.</p>
        <p>''It's one thing if you're in a group and you're playing with the guys,'' he said. ''But when they stand around and watch, I feel like everybody's critiquing.''</p>
        <p>The feedback was all positive on this day. Nick Dougherty, the first-round leader, walked off the green to begin his round -- he would shoot a 77 -- and gave Casey a thumbs-up sign. Colin Montgomerie and Chris DiMarco shrugged their shoulders at Casey as if in disbelief.</p>
        <p>''And I had a lot of guys say, 'Great round of golf,' when I walked off the green,'' said Casey, who opened with a 77.</p>
        <p>He hit 13 of 14 fairways Friday and needed 26 putts, 7 fewer than in his first round. The only blemish on his round was a bogey at 18.</p>
        <p>''This is right up there in terms of my best round ever,'' Casey said. ''If I had kept the bogey off the card, without a doubt it would have been.''</p>
        <p>THE MICKELSONS' TRAVELS -- Phil Mickelson's wife, Amy, was en route to Pittsburgh from California with the couple's three children when Ángel Cabrera birdied the last hole of his second round to knock Mickelson out of the tournament. Mickelson shot a seven-over 77 and finished 11-over for 36 holes, one shot over the cut.</p>
        <p>It was not a wasted journey for Mickelson's family. Their plan is to spend next week together in Cromwell, Conn., at the Travelers Championship, where Mickelson is a two-time champion.</p>
        <p>Mickelson's spokesman, T. R. Reinman, said Mickelson would show up despite the injury to his left wrist. which clearly hindered his play this week.</p>
        <p>''It's holding up,'' Mickelson said, ''So it's not getting too much worse, so that's a good thing.''</p>
        <p>TEENAGER IN THE ROUGH -- Richard Lee, a 15-year-old amateur and the second-youngest participant in the United States Open, withdrew after 13 holes Friday because of an injury to his right wrist. He appeared to sprain it as he tried to get out of the rough beside the green on the par-4 No. 11. After opening with a 79, Lee was 11 over for the day when he walked off the course.</p>
        <p>''It was a little chip shot, probably 20 feet,'' Lee said. ''The ball was sitting down, so I hit the chip shot. It caught my wrist a little bit. It hurt a lot.''</p>
        <p>DIVIDED LOYALTIES -- Swing coach Butch Harmon had to serve two masters Friday at the U.S. Open. He has been working for several years with Adam Scott, ranked No. 4 in the world, and he began working about two months ago with Phil Mickelson. Just his luck: Mickelson and Scott played together the first two rounds.</p>
        <p>Harmon says his priority was helping Scott, a 26-year-old Australian, win his first major. Still, Harmon didn't arrive until Scott was already about 10 minutes into his warm-up session.</p>
        <p>Mickelson finally arrived and made it easy for the coach. ''Where do you want to go?'' he asked. ''Would you rather have me hit by Adam? Would that be easier?''</p>
        <p>''Wherever you want,'' Harmon replied. ''But that would be easier for me.''</p>
        <p>Mickelson found an opening two spots down from Scott. Harmon, however, headed straight for Scott and spent the next 10 minutes working with him, then switched over to Mickelson.</p>
        <p>Scott took triple bogey on the first hole on his way to an 82. Mickelson shot 40 on the back nine for a 77. (AP)</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
