<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Great Leaders Juggle Ideas</title>
    <meta content="16offline" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Technology; Business; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/16/business/16offline.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854722"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S OFFLINE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Toronto</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Harvard Business Review</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">O (Oprah Winfrey Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">In Character (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Roger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Singer, Thea</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kurzell, Ray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ruhl, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mather, John C (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reader, Garry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tibbetts, Tammy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Paul B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Harvard Business Review</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EEDA153FF935A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Great Leaders Juggle Ideas</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">How Great Leaders Juggle Ideas</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL B. BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Paul B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>What's Offline column; University of Toronto Business School Dean Roger Martin, in Harvard Business Review, says it is mistake to focus on successful leader does as way to improve life at work; says moves that work in one context often make little sense in same company or within experience of single leader; O, the Oprah magazine, asked Nobel Prize winners, MacArthur 'genius' recipients and other who have won top honors in their field how they 'recharge their brains when ideas stop flowing'; Thea Singer writes inventor Ray Kurzell reviews specifics of problem before he falls asleep until they become embedded in his dreams; playwright Sarah Ruhl says reading authors who have particular approach to language can inspire new ideas; John C Mather, winner of Nobel Prize in physics, likes to explain what is stumping him to his wife, ballet teacher; Garry Reader, in In Character, writes honesty and candor are not same thing; says being honest has been downgraded to mere compliance with contracts and laws; adds honesty is not enough because it is demand too easily satisfied; says businesspeople need to be candid, which he defines as bluntly facing facts; Tammy Tibbetts, in Ladies' Home Journal, says there is reason one may get best ideas in shower; says recent research shows warm water running over one's body can stimulate outer layer of skin releasing molecules that 'talk' to nerve endings; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN we look for ways to improve our life at work, how we can make better decisions, for example, or try to figure out the next step in our career, invariably one thing we do is look at what great leaders have done. This is why books like ''Straight From the Gut,'' by John F. Welch Jr., and those by Lee A. Iacocca sell so well.</p>
        <p>But focusing on what a successful leader does is a mistake, according to Roger Martin, dean of the University of Toronto Business School.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When we look for ways to improve our life at work or how we can make better decisions, one thing we do is look at what great leaders have done.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN we look for ways to improve our life at work, how we can make better decisions, for example, or try to figure out the next step in our career, invariably one thing we do is look at what great leaders have done. This is why books like ''Straight From the Gut,'' by John F. Welch Jr., and those by Lee A. Iacocca sell so well.</p>
        <p>But focusing on what a successful leader does is a mistake, according to Roger Martin, dean of the University of Toronto Business School.</p>
        <p>''That's because moves that work in one context often make little sense in the same company or within the experience of a single leader,'' he writes in The Harvard Business Review.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martin contends that the more beneficial thing to do is study how great leaders think.</p>
        <p>He has, and he has concluded that they process information differently than the rest of us do.</p>
        <p>''They have the predisposition and the capacity to hold in their head two opposing ideas at once,'' he writes. ''And then, without panicking or simply settling for one alternative or the other, they're able to creatively resolve the tension between those two ideas by generating a new one that contains elements of the others but is superior to both.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Martin calls this process of consideration and synthesis ''integrative thinking,'' and contends that it is this ability and not a ''superior strategy or faultless execution that is the defining characteristic of most exceptional businesses and the people who run them.''</p>
        <p>Intriguingly, Mr. Martin, who interviewed 50 exemplary leaders in doing his research, says many successful executives aren't aware that this is the way they go about processing information.</p>
        <p>REBOOTING YOUR BRAIN -- O, the Oprah magazine, asked Nobel Prize winners, MacArthur ''genius'' grant recipients and others who have won top honors in their field how they ''recharge their brains when the ideas stop flowing.'' Among the answers:</p>
        <p>Right before he falls asleep, the inventor Ray Kurzweil ''reviews the specifics of a problem -- the background, options context -- until they become embedded in his dreams, a state where taboos relax and the rules of logic evaporate,'' Thea Singer writes.</p>
        <p>The playwright Sarah Ruhl says reading authors who have a very particular approach to language, like Gertrude Stein, can inspire new ideas, ''scrambling the letters around in your head so you starting hearing things differently.''</p>
        <p>John C. Mather, winner of the Nobel Prize in physics, likes to try to explain what is stumping him to his wife, a ballet teacher. ''It makes the problem clearer to me because I have to go back to the beginning and question all the basic assumptions.''</p>
        <p>THE BEST POLICY? ''There is honesty and then there's candor,'' writes Garry Reeder. ''They are not the same thing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reeder, who used to work on Wall Street and is now an M.B.A. candidate at Columbia, thinks being honest, which he says has ''been downgraded to mere compliance with contracts and laws,'' is not enough because ''it's a demand too easily satisfied.''</p>
        <p>Writing in In Character, which describes itself as a ''journal of everyday virtues,'' he says ''there are those who believe for example that Enron executives were technically not guilty of dishonesty and fraud, but nobody doubts that they were less than candid.'' Businesspeople, he says, need to be candid, which he defines as bluntly facing the facts.</p>
        <p>''Candor exhibits the qualities of light in a dark room,'' Mr. Reeder writes. ''Candor cuts through confusion, providing a way forward.''</p>
        <p>FINAL TAKE -- There is a reason you may get your best ideas in the shower, according to Ladies' Home Journal. But credit your skin and not your brain.</p>
        <p>''According to recent research, warm water running over you body can stimulate the outer layer of your skin releasing molecules that 'talk' to your nerve endings,'' Tammy Tibbetts writes. ''These molecules include beta-endorphins which trigger brain activity.''</p>
        <p>Maybe we should replace all the meeting and conference rooms with showers.</p>
        <p>PAUL B. BROWN</p>
        <p>WHAT'S OFFLINE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
