<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Silver Challenges Health Benefits Promised in Manhattan Toll Plan</title>
    <meta content="12silver" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/nyregion/12silver.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853944"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Silver, Sheldon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E2DB173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="788" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Silver Challenges Health Benefits Promised in Manhattan Toll Plan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Silver Challenges Health Benefits Promised in Manhattan Toll Plan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, June 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, in his strongest language yet against Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's plan to charge people who drive into the most congested parts of Manhattan during the day, questioned the health benefits of the proposal yesterday. He also suggested that many of the environmental goals Mr. Bloomberg has outlined could be accomplished without congestion pricing.</p>
        <p>His comments suggested that two hours of testimony by Mayor Bloomberg at an Assembly hearing on Friday had not swayed the Democrats who control the chamber. Mr. Silver even seemed to outline new concerns, saying that the plan could actually hurt areas with high asthma rates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver said that congestion pricing may actually hurt areas with high asthma rates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, in his strongest language yet against Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's plan to charge people who drive into the most congested parts of Manhattan during the day, questioned the health benefits of the proposal yesterday. He also suggested that many of the environmental goals Mr. Bloomberg has outlined could be accomplished without congestion pricing.</p>
        <p>His comments suggested that two hours of testimony by Mayor Bloomberg at an Assembly hearing on Friday had not swayed the Democrats who control the chamber. Mr. Silver even seemed to outline new concerns, saying that the plan could actually hurt areas with high asthma rates.</p>
        <p>''The children of the South Bronx, Bedford-Stuyvesant and Harlem, among others, are the ones who have been exposed to a lot of pollutants,'' he said. Not only would those neighborhoods not benefit from the plan, he said, ''some of those areas will become parking lots with people driving around the neighborhoods looking for parking spots in order to avoid congestion pricing fees.''</p>
        <p>''There is a plan that can be put together that would obviously alleviate the environmental negativism of what takes place in Manhattan right now,'' he said, but added that it could be done ''with or without'' congestion pricing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver's remarks came on the heels of Gov. Eliot Spitzer's endorsement of the mayor's proposal last week. And it followed the Assembly's first hearing on the matter on Friday, at which the mayor offered a lengthy defense of his proposal, though Mr. Silver himself was not present.</p>
        <p>Congestion pricing is the centerpiece of Mr. Bloomberg's wide-ranging plan to ease traffic and improve air quality over the next several decades. His plan would impose an $8 fee on cars and a $21 fee on commercial trucks that enter the part of Manhattan below 86th Street from 6 a.m. to 6 p.m. on weekdays. The mayor has said the measure will reduce asthma problems citywide by taking cars off the road.</p>
        <p>The American Lung Association and many environmental groups support the plan, which is modeled after policies used in London. Opponents worry that it could end up being a tax that weighs heavily on lower- and middle-class citizens and that it would not live up to its promised environmental gains.</p>
        <p>Time is an issue, because the Bush administration said last week that New York City could reap up to $500 million in federal aid if the plan were approved by August.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Silver's remarks underscored that he may once again serve as the mayor's foil in Albany. His opposition doomed the mayor's plan to build a West Side football stadium for the New York Jets. Asked about parallels to that battle, Mr. Silver harked back to the mayor's contention then that a Manhattan stadium would not cause undue congestion.</p>
        <p>The stadium, Mr. Silver pointed out, would have been ''right in the middle of this congested zone.''</p>
        <p>''At that time, a year ago, there obviously was no congestion,'' he added, facetiously. ''We can even put this stadium to attract 100,000 people to come in right in the middle of the zone and there was no problem.''</p>
        <p>John P. Gallagher, a spokesman for the mayor, said of the speaker's comments, ''Congestion pricing will reduce the number of cars and the level of emissions in all neighborhoods of the city, and it will end the practice of toll shopping, which causes increased pollution and congestion in the border neighborhoods the speaker is referring to.''</p>
        <p>Toll shopping refers to the tendency of drivers to gravitate to cheaper or toll-free routes to Manhattan, causing traffic tie-ups. Mayor Bloomberg's plan would effectively equalize the fees.</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver's skepticism partly reflects the wide concern about the plan among the more than 100 Democrats who control the Assembly.</p>
        <p>''I'm sort of torn here,'' said Assemblyman Ruben Diaz Jr., a Bronx Democrat. ''On the one hand, I really want to address the environmental issues,'' he said, but added that he was concerned that congestion pricing could mean ''that folks from other places are going to park their cars in my community'' or that the toll would end up being a tax on his constituents without much benefit.</p>
        <p>''I think in its present state,'' he said, ''there are too many concerns, certainly for us to rush to any judgment.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver said that he was left with ''a lot of questions.'' But he did not say outright that he would reject the plan, and said that it was ''very possible'' that an agreement on some environmental plan for the city could be struck by August.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gallagher said, ''We're encouraged by the fact that the speaker recognizes that we need to act quickly in order to be eligible for the federal funding.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
