<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Top Democrat Plans Advance List of Earmarks</title>
    <meta content="12earmark" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/washington/12earmark.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853957"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Wisconsin</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Obey, David R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE0DB173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="535" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Top Democrat Plans Advance List of Earmarks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Top Democrat Plans Advance List of Earmarks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACQUELINE PALANK; David D. Kirkpatrick contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Palank, Jacqueline</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A top House Democrat delivered a promise -- and a threat -- on Monday about the disclosure of the pet projects known as earmarks.</p>
        <p>Under pressure from Republicans, the Democrat, Representative David R. Obey of Wisconsin, chairman of the House Appropriations Committee, said that this year all earmarks and their sponsors would be listed in The Congressional Record a month before they come up for final approval.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A top House Democrat, Representative David R. Obey of Wisconsin, has delivered a promise and a threat about the disclosure of the pet projects known as earmarks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A top House Democrat delivered a promise -- and a threat -- on Monday about the disclosure of the pet projects known as earmarks.</p>
        <p>Under pressure from Republicans, the Democrat, Representative David R. Obey of Wisconsin, chairman of the House Appropriations Committee, said that this year all earmarks and their sponsors would be listed in The Congressional Record a month before they come up for final approval.</p>
        <p>Lawmakers and the public can raise questions, sponsors can defend their projects, and the Appropriations Committee will make final decisions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Obey warned that he would bar earmarks completely if Republicans attacked individual projects to score political points.</p>
        <p>''If they think they can demagogue the earmarks process all year long and expect Democrats to carry the burden of passing earmarks, they're wrong,'' he said. ''Then there will be no earmarks for anybody.''</p>
        <p>The threat underscores Mr. Obey's determination to preserve the authority of his committee to deliver or withhold earmarks, federal money for bridges, clinics or military contractors that helps endear lawmakers to constituents.</p>
        <p>Earmarks have tripled in volume in the last 12 years, to a total cost of more than $64 billion, straining the ability of Congress to screen each request and tempting lawmakers to abuse their ability to deliver money.</p>
        <p>At the beginning of the year, Democrats passed rules intended to make representatives more accountable by requiring for the first time the disclosure of which lawmakers requested each earmark.</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Obey said earmarks would be disclosed only when House and Senate conference committees worked behind closed doors to prepare bills for final approval. He argued that a crush of work gave the committee staff insufficient time to evaluate the thousands of requests for projects earlier.</p>
        <p>Republicans, still smarting from Democratic accusations of earmark abuse under Republican control, hammered the Democrats as not keeping their promise to open up the process.</p>
        <p>The Republicans criticized Mr. Obey's plan for the disclosure period, which would continue to follow the initial consideration of the bills by the Appropriations Committee and the full House. Under normal procedures, that would be the time to scrutinize the bills.</p>
        <p>''It sounds like Mr. Obey has created a complaints department, not an open and deliberative process that guarantees accountability for the American taxpayer,'' said Representative John A. Boehner, the Ohio Republican who is minority leader.</p>
        <p>Mr. Obey argued on Monday, however, that the new procedures would mean much more accountability than in the past, noting that individual lawmakers had virtually never succeeded in striking individual projects from the bill in open debate.</p>
        <p>Most lawmakers vote to preserve one another's pet projects rather than risk challenges to remove their own.</p>
        <p>The chance of a member's killing an earmark in a House debate ''is hugely remote and largely pro forma,'' Mr. Obey said.</p>
        <p>Steve Ellis, a spokesman for Taxpayers for Common Sense, which tracks earmarks, said that under Mr. Obey's new plan, the final decision on each earmark would be made by the handful of leaders of a House and Senate conference. Mr. Ellis called that ''the proverbial smoke-filled room.''</p>
        <p>''It is not democracy,'' he said. ''It is not the way 'Schoolhouse Rock' told us this was supposed to work.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
