<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rape Suspect Says She Was Fooled Into Confessing</title>
    <meta content="12abuse" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/nyregion/12abuse.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Day Care Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Confessions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Day Care Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06EFDB173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="585" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rape Suspect Says She Was Fooled Into Confessing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rape Suspect Says She Was Fooled Into Confessing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELLEN BARRY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Queens day care worker accused of raping a 4-year-old boy told jurors yesterday that she falsely confessed to the crime on videotape because a detective promised he would release her if she did.</p>
        <p>The worker, Khemwatie Bedessie, testified in broken English that during an interrogation in March 2006, Detective Ivan Borbon showed her a recorder and told her it contained a tape of her having sex with the boy. Ms. Bedessie, who immigrated to the United States from Guyana and has a fifth-grade education, said she resisted at first, telling him: ''Play it. Because I never done nothing to no kids.'' She said she eventually became frightened when he told her that she would be sent to Rikers Island if she did not cooperate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawyers for a Queens day care work accused of raping a 4-year-old boy said her confession was brought about by stress and coercion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Queens day care worker accused of raping a 4-year-old boy told jurors yesterday that she falsely confessed to the crime on videotape because a detective promised he would release her if she did.</p>
        <p>The worker, Khemwatie Bedessie, testified in broken English that during an interrogation in March 2006, Detective Ivan Borbon showed her a recorder and told her it contained a tape of her having sex with the boy. Ms. Bedessie, who immigrated to the United States from Guyana and has a fifth-grade education, said she resisted at first, telling him: ''Play it. Because I never done nothing to no kids.'' She said she eventually became frightened when he told her that she would be sent to Rikers Island if she did not cooperate.</p>
        <p>''I tell him, yes, I will do anything he want so he will send me home,'' said Ms. Bedessie, 39, wiping tears from her face. ''He promised that I'm going to go home and see my mommy and he never let me go.''</p>
        <p>On cross-examination, Dianna Megias, an assistant district attorney, showed Ms. Bedessie clips from her videotaped confession taken at the Special Victims Unit and asked her if she recognized her statements.</p>
        <p>''You want this jury to believe that after you admitted to raping a 4-year-old boy, you would be allowed to go home?'' she asked.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bedessie responded, in a barely audible voice, ''The jury has to judge from their own minds.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Bedessie, who is known as Anita, is charged with rape and six counts of child sexual abuse; if convicted, she could serve up to 25 years in prison. Earlier in the trial in State Supreme Court in Queens, prosecutors played the 30-minute confession in which Ms. Bedessie, in a flat, detached tone, described in detail molesting the boy and, at another time, having sex with him.</p>
        <p>The boy also took the stand, and testified that Ms. Bedessie had molested him. The case will probably go to the jury today.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bedessie's lawyer, Stephen Turano, is making a case that the confession was false and brought about by stress and coercion. That approach has been taken by defense lawyers in other cases in which a defendant's confession was the most crucial piece of evidence.</p>
        <p>The videotape was made about two and a half hours after Ms. Bedessie was informed of the allegation. Detective Borbon testified that her statements were voluntary and spontaneous, and he made no mention of a recording of her and the boy. He said Ms. Bedessie ''felt better getting it off her chest.''</p>
        <p>Asked whether the statements were false, he said no. ''Those were her words,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Bedessie offered a strikingly different account yesterday. She said Detective Borbon began the interrogation by accusing her of the rape and, when she protested, offered the recorder as evidence. Then, she said, he presented her with two options. One was to confess and be released, and the other was to go to Rikers Island, where she would be brutalized by other inmates.</p>
        <p>''I started to get scared,'' said Ms. Bedessie, who added that she had never had any problems with the police. ''I said I will do anything to you to let me go, because I leave my mom home and I'm the one who takes care of my mom.''</p>
        <p>Before her statement was taped, she said, the detective told her: ''This will be between me and you. Accept everything I tell you and you will be able to leave.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
