<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>He's Cornering the Market On Misfit TV Heroes</title>
    <meta content="12lear" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/arts/television/12lear.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853926"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">FX</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Leary, Denis</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Shandling, Garry</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wolf, Dick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E5DB173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1334" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>He's Cornering the Market On Misfit TV Heroes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">He’s Cornering the Market on Misfit TV Heroes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACQUES STEINBERG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Denis Leary would seem an unlikely candidate to become the Dick Wolf of dark, morally muddied TV series about firefighters, cops and lawyers -- and perhaps no more so than on a morning last week on an Upper East Side playground.</p>
        <p>During a break in filming an episode from the fourth season of his firehouse drama, ''Rescue Me,'' Mr. Leary, 49, stripped off the T-shirt he'd been wearing for a street hockey scene, stubbed out a cigarette, placed his palms on the cracked blacktop and began doing push-ups with his ankles suspended several feet above the ground on a nearby barrier.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Denis Leary would seem an unlikely candidate to become the Dick Wolf of dark, morally muddied TV series about firefighters, cops and lawyers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Denis Leary would seem an unlikely candidate to become the Dick Wolf of dark, morally muddied TV series about firefighters, cops and lawyers -- and perhaps no more so than on a morning last week on an Upper East Side playground.</p>
        <p>During a break in filming an episode from the fourth season of his firehouse drama, ''Rescue Me,'' Mr. Leary, 49, stripped off the T-shirt he'd been wearing for a street hockey scene, stubbed out a cigarette, placed his palms on the cracked blacktop and began doing push-ups with his ankles suspended several feet above the ground on a nearby barrier.</p>
        <p>While it would be difficult to imagine the burly Mr. Wolf -- who is a decade older and more than a few pounds heavier than the hockey-stick-thin Mr. Leary -- executing such a maneuver, they do have their similarities. With the season premiere of ''Rescue Me'' at 10 p.m. tomorrow on FX, and the recent pick-up by Fox of ''Canterbury's Law,'' a drama about a troubled criminal defense lawyer shepherded by Mr. Leary's production company, this veteran stand-up comedian is seeking to lay the foundation for a confederation of like-minded series not unlike their New York neighbors on ''Law &amp; Order'' -- albeit more gritty and less formulaic in their plotlines.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't think of 'American Idol' and I'm not making 'According to Jim,' '' Mr. Leary said over a lunch of filet mignon tips, served rare, at a Midtown steak house last week. ''Those kind of premises don't come to me. Our interests, for better or worse, are where they are.''</p>
        <p>Thus, the estranged wife of Mr. Leary's Tommy Gavin on ''Rescue Me'' became romantically involved with his brother last season, and got pregnant, though Tommy's brother, a detective, was killed investigating a drug case before it was determined which man was the father. Last seen, Tommy was in only slightly better shape, engulfed in a fire started by a jilted girlfriend.</p>
        <p>When ''Canterbury's Law'' has its premiere on Fox sometime in the new television season, viewers will first see the main character, a lawyer (played by Julianna Margulies) engaging in an extramarital affair with a client; she later goads a murder suspect to lie on the witness stand, as a trap to ensnare the real killer, which works so well that she is punched in the mouth, hard enough to draw blood, during a cross-examination.</p>
        <p>McCoy, the assistant district attorney played by Sam Waterston on the original ''Law and Order,'' seems like Matlock by comparison.</p>
        <p>But for all the provocativeness that Mr. Leary favors -- his character, Tommy Gavin, appeared to sexually assault his ex last season, and was himself sexually assaulted (while drugged) -- he and his collaborators are always looking for comic relief. And so, early in the new season of ''Rescue Me,'' a rookie firefighter recruited to Gavin's firehouse solely for his prowess on the basketball court extracts any number of concessions, including that he be addressed as Sean (his real name is Bart), even though there is already a firefighter named Sean in the same firehouse. (The original Sean is given little choice but to go by Leslie, his middle name.)</p>
        <p>''What Denis likes to write, and see on the page, is never the expected thing,'' said Peter Tolan, his longtime co-writer on ''Rescue Me,'' who played a similar role alongside Garry Shandling on another iconoclastic series, ''The Larry Sanders Show.'' ''He doesn't write on the nose.''</p>
        <p>In what would have put Mr. Leary in the rarefied territory of Mr. Wolf and Jerry Bruckheimer (as executive producer of at least three law enforcement dramas running in prime time), Mr. Leary nearly got another series on next year's television schedule: ''Fort Pit,'' set in a dysfunctional New York City police precinct. Mr. Leary's production company, Apostle, made ''Fort Pit'' as a pilot at the request of NBC.</p>
        <p>''We gave them what they asked for,'' said Mr. Leary of the pilot, which was written by Mr. Tolan. ''It was a dark, edgy, funny, heartbreaking cop show, like a modern-day 'Hill Street Blues.' ''</p>
        <p>In the end, though, NBC went a different way, with a lineup of new dramas for next fall, including a remake of ''The Bionic Woman,'' that tips more toward the supernatural.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leary and his partners in Apostle, including Jim Serpico, a former comedy tour manager who runs the company for him, and Sony Pictures Television, are already at work preparing pitches in a similar vein for the 2008-9 television season, though none is far enough along to be discussed.</p>
        <p>The origins of Apostle -- its name is drawn partly from Mr. Leary's Roman Catholic school background -- lay indirectly with Robert De Niro, who, along with his partner Jane Rosenthal, produced a movie that Mr. Leary starred in in the mid-1990s titled ''Monument Ave.''</p>
        <p>''He was not shy about feeding me some advice,'' Mr. Leary recalled. ''It was along the lines of: 'Don't just be an actor. Form a production company. That's where the longevity is.' We took it to heart.''</p>
        <p>But where other actors' production companies sometimes exist as little more than vanity credits, Mr. Leary and Mr. Serpico became actively involved in producing films (including ''The Ref,'' in which he starred, in 1994, and ''Blow,'' in which he didn't, in 2001), before turning to television with ''The Job'' (an ABC series) and ''Rescue Me,'' which made its debut in 2004.</p>
        <p>Which poses the question -- what kind of executive is Mr. Leary, whose comedy, including his breakthrough special ''No Cure for Cancer,'' has been known to border on the abusive?</p>
        <p>While it is probably not surprising, he can be forceful in sharing his creative opinions.</p>
        <p>Sony executives, for example, expressed some skepticism early on about a critical plot point of the ''Rescue Me'' pilot -- the appearances of Tommy's dead cousin, a firefighter who died in the Sept. 11 terrorist attacks -- which Sony feared might tag ''Rescue Me'' as science fiction.</p>
        <p>''Probably our biggest debate was, are we going to have ghosts in this or not?'' said Zack Van Amburg, co-president of programming and production at Sony television.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leary was adamant that the ghost of Gavin's cousin, played by James McCaffrey, remain, to serve as a device to show that Tommy and other New York City firefighters were haunted by the losses of so many friends and co-workers.</p>
        <p>''He was 100 percent right,'' Mr. Van Amburg said.</p>
        <p>Asked what it was like to argue with Mr. Leary, Mr. Tolan said he was not crazy like his character, Tommy. ''You can have a conversation with him,'' he said. ''But you better be right when you go in. ''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Tolan said he got a call not long ago from Mr. Leary in which his sole purpose seemed to be to say, ''I love you.''</p>
        <p>''Are you high?'' Mr. Tolan said he asked Mr. Leary.</p>
        <p>''No!'' Mr. Tolan recalled Mr. Leary insisting.</p>
        <p>''So,'' Mr. Tolan said, ''I told him, I love you too.''</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Leary has been known to give the occasional stiff arm to a publicist -- ''In a conversation!'' is how he abruptly brushed off one on the set last week -- he is in many ways beloved by the ''Rescue Me'' crew, several of whom appeared in that street hockey scene.</p>
        <p>''You've got to screw up royally to get them upset,'' Mr. McCaffrey, who is also cast in ''Canterbury's Law,'' said of Mr. Leary and the Apostle team. ''They're obviously very talented, but I think it's a prerequisite you can't get a gig with them if you take things too seriously.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Steven Pasquale, a stage actor who plays the original Sean on ''Rescue Me,'' said he would be forever grateful to Mr. Leary for following the lead of ''Law &amp; Order'' and filming ''Rescue Me'' and ''Canterbury's Law'' in and around New York City instead of Hollywood.</p>
        <p>''The Dick Wolf machine looks like it's winding down a little,'' Mr. Pasquale said, referring to NBC's recent almost-cancellation of the original ''Law &amp; Order.'' ''I'm glad someone's stepping up.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
