<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shelter Closes, Residents Move On and Fortunes Diverge</title>
    <meta content="12camp" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/nyregion/12camp.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853941"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Camp La Guardia</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Department of Homeless Services</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Coalition for the Homeless</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hess, Robert V</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Markee, Patrick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E2DB173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1043" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shelter Closes, Residents Move On and Fortunes Diverge</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shelter Closes, Residents Move on and Fortunes Diverge</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CASSI FELDMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A few weeks ago, the last resident of what was once New York City's largest homeless shelter, Camp La Guardia, packed his bags and left.</p>
        <p>To Robert V. Hess, the commissioner of the city's Department of Homeless Services, the shelter's closing was ''a milestone in the city's history.'' The 1,001-bed facility, 70 miles northwest of Manhattan in a bucolic part of Orange County, is no longer needed because the number of homeless adults is declining, Mr. Hess said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 1,001-bed facility 70 miles outside of Manhattan is no longer needed because the number of homeless adults is declining, the city’s commissioner for the homeless says.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A few weeks ago, the last resident of what was once New York City's largest homeless shelter, Camp La Guardia, packed his bags and left.</p>
        <p>To Robert V. Hess, the commissioner of the city's Department of Homeless Services, the shelter's closing was ''a milestone in the city's history.'' The 1,001-bed facility, 70 miles northwest of Manhattan in a bucolic part of Orange County, is no longer needed because the number of homeless adults is declining, Mr. Hess said.</p>
        <p>Of the 748 men who were at Camp La Guardia in December, 492 moved in with relatives or into other housing, while 256 were transferred to city shelters.</p>
        <p>The shelter had long been a source of contention: Homeless men complained about its location, a 90-minute bus ride from New York City, and residents of the area considered it an unfair burden on their community. Yet the camp also offered its inhabitants a relatively peaceful place to recover from addiction or learn a new skill. Now, most are back in the city, grappling with new responsibilities -- and trying to stay housed.</p>
        <p>Though some former residents have found stable homes, others have moved into housing that has proved inadequate or even dangerous -- thrusting them back into homelessness.</p>
        <p>Gregory Murphy, 43, a longtime resident of Camp La Guardia, knows this firsthand.</p>
        <p>Mr. Murphy, a father of four, lived with relatives and girlfriends before ending up on the street. About seven years ago, he arrived at Camp La Guardia, moving in and out as he wrestled with personal difficulties. At first, Mr. Murphy, who is from Brooklyn, found country life strange, but he soon came to appreciate the clean air and slower pace. ''After a while, you get used to it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But with the shelter closing, Mr. Murphy was moved into a boarding house on Faile Street in the Hunts Point section of the Bronx, where he shared a room with five other men sleeping in bunk beds, not the kind of housing he had hoped for. ''I told them I didn't want to go to no three-quarter house,'' he said, using a common slang term for boarding homes. ''That's no living for a grown man.''</p>
        <p>The house was crowded and, as it turned out, a fire risk. In April, the Fire Department ordered the second floor vacated because of a lack of exits, and Mr. Murphy found himself homeless once again. ''Now I'm back to Square 1,'' he said, as he ate breakfast at a diner across the street from his current home, the 30th Street intake shelter in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Of the numerous group homes that men from Camp La Guardia moved to, 12 have been described as ''problematic'' by the Coalition for the Homeless, an advocacy group that was among the loudest critics of Camp La Guardia. The coalition based its conclusions on things like code violations, lack of services, or unreasonable rules. Residents of two of them -- the Faile Street boarding house and one at 592 Marcy Avenue in Brooklyn -- have been forced to leave, sending at least 11 men back to homeless shelters.</p>
        <p>''By placing Camp La Guardia residents -- including some men living with mental illness and other disabilities -- into hazardous, overcrowded and illegal group homes, the Bloomberg administration is virtually guaranteeing that many of them will end up back in city shelters or on the streets,'' said Patrick Markee, a senior analyst with the coalition.</p>
        <p>The conditions at some of the group homes underscore the city's lack of adequate low-cost housing. In November, the Department of Homeless Services sent a memo to shelter operators, advising them not to send residents to 20 group homes that it said were uncertified or had been closed by the State Department of Health because they did not meet safety or regulatory standards. In an attachment to that memo, the agency added 14 homes to the list.</p>
        <p>''When we learned of a small number of clients being referred from Camp La Guardia to inappropriate housing, we took steps to rehouse those clients and we are refining our instructions to our not-for-profit partners to help clients choose safe housing options going forward,'' said Linda Bazerjian, a spokeswoman for the department.</p>
        <p>Another hurdle for some former Camp La Guardia residents has been finding a job. At Camp La Guardia, most of the residents received welfare benefits and were exempt from work requirements because of its distance from New York City. Once they returned, that exemption ended. While the city has tried to help them find jobs, some men are struggling.</p>
        <p>Mike Stone, 50, a former Air Force budget analyst who moved to New York from Seattle last summer, landed at Camp La Guardia when he could not find an affordable apartment. Once there, he found job hunting nearly impossible. He does not receive welfare benefits, he said, so he left in November to look for work.</p>
        <p>Since then, both a job and a home have eluded him. On a recent weeknight, Mr. Stone was waiting in line at a drop-in center on West 41st Street, clutching a paper ticket that allowed him to sleep in a chair.</p>
        <p>Darrell Winstead, 46, is confident his own future holds something better. He ended up in Camp La Guardia in 2005 after the death of his mother. He was evicted from her public housing apartment in Washington Heights after she died because he was not on the lease, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Winstead describes his two years there as a serene break from urban life. ''It's like you're up in the mountains,'' he said. He took a class in automotive repair and bonded with another resident over their shared love for the Beatles.</p>
        <p>But he was still itching to return to the city. A housing specialist at Camp La Guardia encouraged him to move into a boarding house, he said, but he resisted and eventually got his own place, a tidy studio on Staten Island, using a rental voucher from the city. Now, with his home sparsely furnished and his Beatles poster pinned to the wall, he is looking for a job as a bus or limousine driver.</p>
        <p>At Camp La Guardia, ''you're like a package on a shelf collecting dust,'' he said. ''Now I feel different. I feel like new.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
