<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How to Handle Unruly Students?</title>
    <meta content="l12herbert" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853980"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE6DA173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="399" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How to Handle Unruly Students?</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''School to Prison Pipeline,'' by Bob Herbert (column, June 9):</p>
        <p>Educators and teachers are now in a position in which their only recourse with violent or disruptive children is to expose them to the legal system. While I agree that this is ridiculous in many settings, Mr. Herbert must also accede to the notion that teachers no longer have the legal authority to discipline disorderly kids, leaving only the mechanism of calling the cops.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''School to Prison Pipeline,'' by Bob Herbert (column, June 9):</p>
        <p>Educators and teachers are now in a position in which their only recourse with violent or disruptive children is to expose them to the legal system. While I agree that this is ridiculous in many settings, Mr. Herbert must also accede to the notion that teachers no longer have the legal authority to discipline disorderly kids, leaving only the mechanism of calling the cops.</p>
        <p>Private schools, by contrast, have no obligation to serve violent or disturbed children, but this option does not exist in the public schools.</p>
        <p>James B. Stiehl, M.D.  Milwaukee, June 9, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Throughout history, many of the great human rights and social movements have been energized by the unfettered idealism of youth. I am therefore afraid that introducing black children, some not yet in their teens, to the criminal justice system will destroy that idealism and replace it with ugly cynicism or extreme caution.</p>
        <p>We can no longer ignore these possibilities because the jails and prisons are teeming with young blacks, especially males. The last thing we need in this country is a generation or two of black youths who see abusive enforcement of the law as legitimate representation of the American people.</p>
        <p>Think where our country would be if the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. or Ruth J. Simmons (the president of Brown University) had been driven off the deep end or were satisfied never to rock the boat.</p>
        <p>David L. Evans  Cambridge, Mass., June 9, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Of course calling the police should be a last resort. Unfortunately, it has become the only solution for those who are, for many reasons, afraid to do anything else.</p>
        <p>Teachers and school administrators in particular have become frequent targets of lawsuits by parents and students when they step in to deal with difficult situations. Our litigious society, in which even a good Samaritan can be forced into court and made bankrupt by lawyers' fees, forces all of us to think carefully before we do what in the past would have been the obvious and intelligent thing to do.</p>
        <p>It's wrong and it's regrettable, but when you can see yourself on the receiving end of a lawsuit, you don't hesitate to make that call.</p>
        <p>Susan A. McGregor  North Kingstown, R.I., June 9, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
