<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TV Writers Were Also Watching 'Sopranos'</title>
    <meta content="12sopr" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/arts/television/12sopr.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853919"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Home Box Office</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Chase, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ellin, Doug</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kring, Tim</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Milch, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cuse, Carlton</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lindelof, Damon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E6DB173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="970" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TV Writers Were Also Watching 'Sopranos'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">TV Writers Were Also Watching ‘Sopranos’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After he completed the final episode of ''The Sopranos,'' David Chase told publicity executives at HBO that he was leaving for France and would not take any calls asking him to comment about the ending of his classic television series.</p>
        <p>He also said that he had instructed all of his writers and producers to turn down any requests for information about the decisions that had gone into shaping the show's last chapter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After he completed the final episode of “The Sopranos,” David Chase told publicity executives at HBO that he was leaving for France and would not take any calls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After he completed the final episode of ''The Sopranos,'' David Chase told publicity executives at HBO that he was leaving for France and would not take any calls asking him to comment about the ending of his classic television series.</p>
        <p>He also said that he had instructed all of his writers and producers to turn down any requests for information about the decisions that had gone into shaping the show's last chapter.</p>
        <p>The reason for his resistance became clear on Sunday night when ''The Sopranos'' ended, not with a moment of final summation, but with a literal blank. The reaction to the stunning last shot of an empty screen has been a mix of outrage among some fans at being left sitting on the edges of their seats, where they had been perched for much of the show's last batch of episodes, and awe among others who have always regarded the show as the most ambitious and unconventional of television series.</p>
        <p>Included in the latter group were many people in the same line of work as Mr. Chase, storytellers in the entertainment business.</p>
        <p>Damon Lindelof, one of the creators of the ABC hit show ''Lost,'' another series whose viewers have high expectations about quality, said: ''I've seen every episode of the series. I thought the ending was letter-perfect.''</p>
        <p>Like millions of other viewers, Mr. Lindelof said he was initially taken aback by the quick cut to a blank screen and thought his cable had gone out at that crucial moment. He even checked his TiVo machine and saw that it was still running several minutes beyond the end. When he checked the scene again, he said, he noted ''the scene cut off right as Meadow is coming through the door and right at the word 'stop' in the Journey song.''</p>
        <p>He said: ''My heart started beating. It had been racing throughout the last scene. Afterward I went to bed and lay next to my wife, awake, thinking about it for the next two hours. And I just thought it was great. It did everything well that 'Godfather III' did not do well.''</p>
        <p>In an e-mail message sent right after the final scene, Doug Ellin, the creator of another HBO hit series, ''Entourage,'' said: ''The show just ended, and I'm speechless. I'm sure there is going to be a lot of heated discussion, but that's David Chase's genius. It's what made 'The Sopranos' different from anything that's ever been on TV. It invented a whole new approach to storytelling that isn't afraid to leave things open-ended, and now the biggest open story line in the history of television.''</p>
        <p>For David Shore, creator of the Fox hit ''House,'' one of the best touches was Mr. Chase's own refusal to discuss the ending. Mr. Shore said: ''Obviously he wants us to speculate on what it all means. Obviously that's what we're all doing.''</p>
        <p>David Milch, who has created highly regarded dramas like ''NYPD Blue'' and ''Deadwood,'' said: ''It was a question of loyalty to viewer expectations, as against loyalty to the internal coherence of the materials. Mr. Chase's position was loyalty to the internal dynamics of the materials and the characters.''</p>
        <p>Comedy writers also said they were impressed with Mr. Chase's choices. Chuck Lorre, who created and leads the CBS hit comedy ''Two and a Half Men,'' emerged from screening the final episode and said with a laugh, ''This is what you get when you let a writer do whatever he wants.''</p>
        <p>But he added that he was saying that with admiration. ''People just finished watching that show and immediately talked about it for a half-hour,'' Mr. Lorre said. ''That's just wonderful. What more could you want as a writer?''</p>
        <p>If any shows feel special pressure from the attention ''The Sopranos'' finale is receiving, it is current series looking down the road at their expected finales, even if long in the future.</p>
        <p>Tim Kring, the creator of this year's NBC hit ''Heroes,'' said, ''I have to admit that as soon as it ended, I immediately went there. I don't have an ending for the series yet. I put myself years in the future thinking about what you do when you have viewers with these sorts of expectations. And I think you just have to be true to what you were originally trying to say.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kring said he had only come back to ''The Sopranos'' this season, anticipating the buildup to the ending, and he said he found ''the storytelling in the finale a bit disjointed, so that you lost the cause and effect of some scenes.'' But he said he admired the choices Mr. Chase had made to be true to the nature of his series. ''This was a show that always did everything its own way,'' Mr. Kring said.</p>
        <p>For the producers of ''Lost,'' who have declared an official finale in three more seasons, the conclusion of ''The Sopranos'' carried special weight. ''There was immediate blowback for me,'' said Carlton Cuse, Mr. Lindelof's creative partner on the show. ''A sense of fear ran through my veins, thinking that we are going to be in this position,'' he said, adding, ''we know the end is coming in 48 short episodes.''</p>
        <p>He had admitted to some initial frustration with the ending of ''The Sopranos.'' ''But it settled well with me,'' Mr. Cuse said. ''In that blank screen, there was a certain kind of purity in the choice Chase made to make it the fulcrum of the ending.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lindelof said that as daunting as it is to think of the expectations of ending a popular piece of entertainment, there was also a bit of benefit. ''If you feel that everybody is going to hate it anyway, no matter what you do,'' he said, ''there's a certain liberation in writing it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
