<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'86 Law Looms Over Immigration Fight</title>
    <meta content="12immig" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/washington/12immig.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853948"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Immigrants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Illegal Immigrants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1DB173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'86 Law Looms Over Immigration Fight</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">’86 Law Looms Over Immigration Fight</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR; Carl Hulse contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush will have to contend with bill passed in 1986 that promised to solve problem of illegal immigration when he visits Capitol Hill to push for revival of comprehensive immigration bill; 1986 law prohibited hiring of illegal immigrants, provided new resources for enforcement along Mexican border and offered legal status, or amnesty, to several million illegal immigrants; in current debate, senators of both parties cite 1986 law as example of what not to do; many voice regret at having voted for that measure; Bush and supporters of current Senate bill point out that it puts enforcement first this time; many senators are skeptical; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When President Bush goes to Capitol Hill on Tuesday to push for revival of a comprehensive immigration bill, he will have to wrestle with the ghost of a 1986 law that promised to solve the problem of illegal immigration.</p>
        <p>That law prohibited the hiring of illegal immigrants, provided new resources for enforcement along the Mexican border and offered legal status, or amnesty, to several million illegal immigrants. In the current debate, which stalled last week when the latest legislative proposal failed to clear a procedural hurdle, senators of both parties cite the 1986 law as an example of what not to do.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When President Bush pushes for revival of an immigration bill, he will have to wrestle with the ghost of a law that promised to solve illegal immigration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When President Bush goes to Capitol Hill on Tuesday to push for revival of a comprehensive immigration bill, he will have to wrestle with the ghost of a 1986 law that promised to solve the problem of illegal immigration.</p>
        <p>That law prohibited the hiring of illegal immigrants, provided new resources for enforcement along the Mexican border and offered legal status, or amnesty, to several million illegal immigrants. In the current debate, which stalled last week when the latest legislative proposal failed to clear a procedural hurdle, senators of both parties cite the 1986 law as an example of what not to do.</p>
        <p>Senator Charles E. Grassley, Republican of Iowa, said he regretted voting for the 1986 measure.</p>
        <p>''I thought then that taking care of three million people illegally in the country would solve the problem once and for all,'' Mr. Grassley said. ''I found out, however, if you reward illegality, you get more of it. Today, as everybody has generally agreed, we have 12 million people here illegally.''</p>
        <p>The 1986 law was a product of more than five years' work by Senator Alan K. Simpson, Republican of Wyoming, and Representative Romano L. Mazzoli, Democrat of Kentucky. Both left Congress more than a decade ago.</p>
        <p>Senator Byron L. Dorgan, Democrat of North Dakota, said: ''I was here in Congress in 1986. I heard all the promises of the Simpson-Mazzoli Act. None of them were true, and three million people got amnesty. There was no border security to speak of, no employer sanctions to speak of, and there was no enforcement.''</p>
        <p>Senator John Cornyn, Republican of Texas, said: ''The American people were sold a bill of goods. It didn't work. We got an amnesty, and we got no enforcement. That is why people are so distrustful now.''</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Bush's ''first principles,'' as described in a White House planning document, is, ''Do not repeat the 1986 failure.'' He and other supporters of the current Senate bill say it puts enforcement first this time.</p>
        <p>On Monday, Mr. Bush said he was confident that the bill would move forward and become law, despite the roadblock it hit last week and continued intense opposition from many conservatives in Congress and at the grass-roots level.</p>
        <p>''I'll see you at the bill signing,'' the president told journalists traveling with him in Bulgaria.</p>
        <p>In a letter to Mr. Bush on Monday, Senate Democratic leaders said they were ''committed to Senate passage of an immigration bill this year.'' But they said Mr. Bush must exert stronger leadership and deliver more votes for the legislation.</p>
        <p>The Senate majority leader, Harry Reid, Democrat of Nevada, said he would try again on the immigration bill if the president and Senate Republican leaders showed ''new cooperation and a clear way forward.''</p>
        <p>Supporters of the Senate bill acknowledge that the nation's experience with the 1986 law has made their job harder. Senator Edward M. Kennedy, Democrat of Massachusetts, said the current bill was ''dramatically different from the 1986 act,'' because it places more emphasis on enforcement and more conditions on the granting of legal status to illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>But many senators are skeptical. Under the Senate bill, they note, most new enforcement measures are ''subject to the availability of appropriations,'' meaning Congress would have to provide additional money to finance them.</p>
        <p>Senator Robert C. Byrd, Democrat of West Virginia, said he supported amnesty in 1986 ''based on the very same promises we hear today.'' But that law did not work, Mr. Byrd said, and ''I will not vote to make the same mistake twice.''</p>
        <p>In signing the 1986 measure into law, President Ronald Reagan said, ''Future generations of Americans will be thankful for our efforts to humanely regain control of our borders.''</p>
        <p>The border remains porous.</p>
        <p>Stephen J. Pitti, a professor of history at Yale, said the 1986 law ''did little to slow migration to the United States,'' but made crossing the border more difficult and dangerous. As a result, he said, illegal immigrants, rather than circulating back and forth between the United States and Mexico, are more likely to settle permanently in this country.</p>
        <p>Likewise, Professor Pitti said, the employer sanctions authorized in 1986 did not noticeably deter illegal immigration from Latin America, but ''created a booming market for fake identity cards.''</p>
        <p>Reached Monday in Wyoming, Mr. Simpson said, ''Without a more secure identifier, it was obvious that the 1986 bill could never work.''</p>
        <p>The Senate bill calls for more secure identification documents, with photographs or biometric identifiers. Employers must use a new electronic system to verify that employees are eligible to work in the United States. And the fines for hiring illegal immigrants would be much higher than under the current law.</p>
        <p>But the Senate bill, like the 1986 law, forbids the use of national identification cards.</p>
        <p>Supporters of the 1986 measure freely used the word ''amnesty'' at the time. President Bush insists that the Senate bill ''does not grant amnesty'' because an illegal immigrant would have to pay a fine, pass background checks and hold a steady job to gain legal status.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush will have difficulty persuading senators like David Vitter, Republican of Louisiana. Mr. Vitter said the legalization program and other provisions of the Senate bill ''will inevitably repeat the mistake of 1986, only on a far broader, a far bigger, and far more dangerous scale.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
