<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Mexico, Diabetes Strains Lives and Budgets</title>
    <meta content="12diab" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health&amp;Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/health/12diab.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853910"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CASES WITHOUT BORDERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/Cases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diabetes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Insulin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Diabetes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Insulin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insulin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diabetes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Mexico</location>
        <org class="online_producer">World Health Organization</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E0DC173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1126" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Mexico, Diabetes Strains Lives and Budgets</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Mexico, Diabetes Strains Lives and Budgets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZA BARCLAY</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, June 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ten years after she learned she had Type 2 diabetes, Teresa Sánchez bought her first blood sugar meter, a small, hand-held device that cost $100, a quarter of her monthly pension.</p>
        <p>Before she got the meter, Ms. Sánchez, 52, had to go to a low-cost laboratory or a doctor's office to have her blood sugar tested. Sometimes months passed without a test, and then she would discover that the level had crept to 400 or 500 milligrams per deciliter, two to four times normal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For diabetics in the developing world, the most basic tools necessary to keep their illness in check represent a major expense.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ten years after she learned she had Type 2 diabetes, Teresa Sánchez bought her first blood sugar meter, a small, hand-held device that cost $100, a quarter of her monthly pension.</p>
        <p>Before she got the meter, Ms. Sánchez, 52, had to go to a low-cost laboratory or a doctor's office to have her blood sugar tested. Sometimes months passed without a test, and then she would discover that the level had crept to 400 or 500 milligrams per deciliter, two to four times normal.</p>
        <p>Those years of hyperglycemia, or high blood glucose levels, have led to extensive complications: nerve damage in her legs and feet, feeble vision and glaucoma, and incontinence from the strain on her kidneys and bladder. She also complains of frequent nausea and weakness.</p>
        <p>For diabetics in the developing world, the most basic tools necessary to keep their illness in check represent a major expense. Yet doing without them can be far more expensive in the long run, and harmful to their health.</p>
        <p>Many diabetics in Mexico and other developing countries are finding themselves unable to work, jeopardizing their families' livelihood. Ms. Sánchez once supplemented her pension by selling clothes to her neighbors, but her painful feet now restrict her mobility.</p>
        <p>''I am worried about the future,'' she said. ''I am raising three children and everything has changed in my life because of this disease.''</p>
        <p>Even now, controlling her blood sugar might have remained beyond her reach if not for the intervention of a doctor she met after being hospitalized in December with a bladder infection.</p>
        <p>The doctor, Marco Reynoso, is a rare visionary in Mexico's vast and often inept public health system. An internal medicine specialist, Dr. Reynoso, 49, has intervened in the lives of the scores of working-class diabetics who pass through the Mexican government's Darío Fernández Fierro General Hospital.</p>
        <p>For 23 years, Dr. Reynoso has counseled diabetics like Ms. Sánchez, imploring them to invest in blood sugar meters and keep meticulous daily charts of their levels. He also runs educational courses and fairs for diabetics at the hospital, though he receives no resources or extra pay for his efforts and sometimes has to hold his classes in the hallways.</p>
        <p>''We need to re-educate people and reform their habits, particularly their food and exercise plans,'' he said. ''It's easy to control diabetes, and not that expensive, yet the disease so often becomes problematic.''</p>
        <p>Diabetes is Mexico's leading cause of death, with 138 deaths per 100,000 adults aged 20 to 84 in 2000, compared with 82 per 100,000 in the United States, according to data from the National Institute of Geographic and Statistical Information. And the prevalence rate here is among the world's highest -- 10.7 percent among adults aged 20 to 69.</p>
        <p>The Mexican Diabetes Federation estimates that 6.5 million to 10 million Mexicans have diabetes, and that 2 million of those cases have not been diagnosed. Only 10 percent of diabetics have blood sugar meters and are in good control of their disease, the federation said.</p>
        <p>According to a 2003 study by the World Health Organization, the total combined annual direct and indirect costs associated with diabetes in Latin America and the Caribbean in 2000 were estimated at $65.2 billion. In Mexico, direct and indirect costs were $15.1 billion.</p>
        <p>Diabetes is also impoverishing families at the household level. According to the International Diabetes Federation, families in Latin America pay 40 percent to 60 percent of the cost of diabetes care from their own pockets. In Mexico, where medical care is financed by an amalgam of public and private sources, half the population is uninsured.</p>
        <p>''When diabetics in their 40s and 50s have complications like foot problems or congestive heart failure, they're going to be less productive and their families may go bankrupt taking care of them,'' said Jonathan Brown, a health economist and a senior investigator at the Kaiser Permanente Center for Health Research. ''Instead of the money going toward raising the kids, it goes toward taking care of the parents.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Sánchez, whose husband died several years ago, has three children. Though she has government-paid health insurance, thanks to her former job as a janitor for a state university, she must pay out of pocket for her monitor and some of her medicine, all of which come to about $200 a month.</p>
        <p>While her insurance should cover her insulin, it was out of stock at the hospital pharmacy one recent week, so she had to go to a private drugstore and buy it with her own money. And her insurance does not cover the lancets she uses to prick her finger to draw blood, the blood test strips, the syringes to inject insulin, the rubbing alcohol or the cotton swabs. ''It's very hard economically,'' she said.</p>
        <p>One remedy, experts say, is self-management education, which teaches diabetics how to regulate their blood sugar levels, avoid complications and keep costs down.</p>
        <p>Ms. Sánchez said that in her 10 years with the disease, she rarely received practical advice on what to eat and how to monitor her blood sugar levels.</p>
        <p>''I was told to take my pills and not eat so much bread and tortillas, that was all,'' she said. ''They never told me my levels were far too high, and never explained the risks of complications. I would have taken better care of myself and eaten less had I known what would happen to me.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Reynoso's educational approach is tailored for people with resources stretched thin: he understands they cannot join a gym, so he gives them tips on how to exercise at work. And he advises them on how to find affordable ingredients to prepare low-fat, sugar-free meals.</p>
        <p>Mexico's state-run health institutions are developing educational programs for diabetics.</p>
        <p>''Mexico is making an effort to improve quality of care and educational programs for diabetics,'' said Alberto Barceló, regional adviser for the Pan-American Health Organization's noncommunicable diseases unit. ''There is a lot of effort from the government to prioritize the disease, especially compared with other countries in Latin America.''</p>
        <p>But Enrique Manero, executive director of the Mexican Diabetes Federation, says that fewer than 10 percent of Mexican diabetics are receiving self-management education.</p>
        <p>''Many people don't know the resources exist, but others don't attend the workshops because of indolence or indifference,'' Mr. Manero said. ''They hear about the complications but don't think they will happen to them.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Sánchez says she will attend Dr. Reynoso's diabetes course once her feet improve. And once she can maintain her blood sugar levels over the long term, her costs should go down.</p>
        <p>''For now I can't buy my children shoes or books because the medications are so expensive,'' Ms. Sánchez said. ''But I want to get better and I want to work again.''</p>
        <p>CASES WITHOUT BORDERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
