<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High Court Rules Against Home Aide On Wages</title>
    <meta content="12home" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/nyregion/12home.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853962"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Minimum Wage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minimum Wage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Supreme Court</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Breyer, Stephen G</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EFDB173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="644" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High Court Rules Against Home Aide On Wages</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">High Court Rules Against Home Aide on Wages</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States Supreme Court ruled yesterday against a home care aide from Queens and upheld federal regulations that exempt most home care workers from minimum-wage and overtime protections.</p>
        <p>In a 9-to-0 decision, the court rejected the arguments made by the home care aide, Evelyn Coke, that the Labor Department's regulations should be invalidated because they conflict with Congress's intent to broaden wage protections.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States Supreme Court upheld federal regulations that exempt most home care workers from minimum-wage and overtime protections.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States Supreme Court ruled yesterday against a home care aide from Queens and upheld federal regulations that exempt most home care workers from minimum-wage and overtime protections.</p>
        <p>In a 9-to-0 decision, the court rejected the arguments made by the home care aide, Evelyn Coke, that the Labor Department's regulations should be invalidated because they conflict with Congress's intent to broaden wage protections.</p>
        <p>The ruling upset labor unions and women's groups, which fear that it will push many of the nation's 1.4 million home care workers into worse financial straits. But home care agencies and federal and city officials applauded the ruling, saying it would reduce labor costs for home care, costs that are largely borne by various levels of government.</p>
        <p>The Bloomberg administration filed an amicus brief in the case, arguing that a victory for Ms. Coke could force the city, state and federal governments, which finance home care through Medicaid, to pay $250 million more a year to the 60,000 home care attendants in the city.</p>
        <p>One of Ms. Coke's sons said his mother was too ill to comment.</p>
        <p>The main question in the case was whether several 1974 amendments to the Fair Labor Standards Act exempted home care aides employed by agencies from minimum-wage and overtime protections. In contrast, all sides agreed that those amendments exempted aides hired directly by the elderly or infirm.</p>
        <p>Writing for the court, Justice Stephen G. Breyer acknowledged that the Labor Department had issued conflicting regulations. One says that home care aides employed through agencies or other third parties are exempt from protections under the Fair Labor Standards Act, and another that aides should not be exempt from minimum-wage and overtime protections unless they work in the home of their employer.</p>
        <p>Ms. Coke, 73, initially filed her lawsuit in 2002 against Long Island Care at Home, saying that it often did not give her time-and-a-half pay for overtime even when she worked 24-hour stints at homes in Great Neck, Manhasset and other communities.</p>
        <p>Her lawyers urged the Supreme Court to uphold a decision by the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit, which had invalidated the regulation exempting the aides from wage protections. The circuit court ruled that the regulation clashed with 1974 legislation that broadened minimum wage coverage.</p>
        <p>But the Supreme Court overruled the circuit court, saying that Congress's intent was unclear with regard to home care aides. Justice Breyer noted that Congress had authorized the Labor Department to issue regulations to flesh out the 1974 amendment to the Labor Act.</p>
        <p>In upholding the exemption, Justice Breyer wrote that the court should defer to the department's expertise, and especially to its most recent interpretations, which take the position that the aides should be exempt.</p>
        <p>''The court's ruling is another blow to struggling, low-wage women,'' said Nancy Duff Campbell, a co-president of the National Women's Law Center. ''It means that home care workers, who are overwhelmingly low-income women of color, will continue to be unfairly treated despite providing essential services to our growing elderly and disabled population.''</p>
        <p>MaryAnn Osborne, a vice president of Long Island Care, an agency based in Westbury that employs 80 home care aides, said she was elated by the ruling. ''This decision,'' she said, ''will help us keep our costs down, and it means we will be able to continue to provide service for the elderly and the disabled.''</p>
        <p>Senator Edward M. Kennedy, the Massachusetts Democrat who is chairman of the Senate Health, Education, Labor and Pensions Committee, said he would seek to amend the Fair Labor Standards Act to ensure that home aides were protected.</p>
        <p>He said the court decision highlighted ''a significant gap in the protections of our laws,'' and added that he would work with his colleagues ''on a fair solution that treats these hardworking caregivers with the dignity and respect they deserve.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
