<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3 Plead Not Guilty to String Of New Jersey Bank Thefts</title>
    <meta content="12heist" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/nyregion/12heist.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853942"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E2DB173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="606" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3 Plead Not Guilty to String Of New Jersey Bank Thefts</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">3 Plead Not Guilty to String of New Jersey Bank Thefts</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD G. JONES</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, June 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three men accused of stealing more than $87,000 in a string of bank robberies in New Jersey, including an attempted robbery in April that led to the death of an F.B.I. agent, pleaded not guilty Monday in federal court here to conspiracy and other charges.</p>
        <p>Shortly afterward, a lawyer for one of the men said that a fourth man arrested in the robberies was apparently cooperating with federal prosecutors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A fourth man arrested in the robberies is apparently cooperating with federal prosecutors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three men accused of stealing more than $87,000 in a string of bank robberies in New Jersey, including an attempted robbery in April that led to the death of an F.B.I. agent, pleaded not guilty Monday in federal court here to conspiracy and other charges.</p>
        <p>Shortly afterward, a lawyer for one of the men said that a fourth man arrested in the robberies was apparently cooperating with federal prosecutors.</p>
        <p>''He's talking,'' said F. Kevin Lynch, a lawyer for Wilfredo Berrios, one of the men accused in four robberies that took place in February and March and the attempted robbery of a bank in Readington, N.J., on April 5. During that attempt, Barry Lee Bush, 52, a 19-year veteran of the Federal Bureau of Investigation was fatally shot. The authorities said that he was apparently killed by a bullet from another agent's weapon.</p>
        <p>The three co-defendants have not been charged in Mr. Bush's death, though they could each face more than 100 years in prison if convicted on all counts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lynch said the fourth arrested man, Michael Cruz, was cooperating with federal prosecutors as they prepared their case against the other men.</p>
        <p>Michael N. Pedicini, a lawyer for Mr. Cruz, declined to comment.</p>
        <p>The federal prosecutor handling the case, Charles McKenna, declined to comment on the status of Mr. Cruz, who, despite being arrested, was not named in an indictment handed up in the case on June 1. The indictment does refer to ''a co-conspirator not charged as a defendant.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McKenna would not say whether Mr. Cruz was the unidentified co-conspirator.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't tell you if he was,'' Mr. McKenna said after court.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berrios, 28, and his two co-defendants, Francisco Herrera-Genao, 22, and Efrain Lynn, 21, appeared here before Judge Garrett E. Brown Jr. of United States District Court. During the 15-minute hearing, lawyers for each of the men responded, ''Not guilty,'' when Judge Brown asked how each of them pleaded to the charges.</p>
        <p>The judge set trial for the three men for Sept. 4. Mr. McKenna told Judge Brown that he expected the trial to last about a month and that prosecutors planned to call as many as 40 witnesses.</p>
        <p>The men, each of whom was clad in loose-fitting olive-colored jumpsuits, waved and smiled weakly at family members in the courtroom.</p>
        <p>The men were charged in the robberies of a Commerce Bank in Piscataway, N.J., on Feb. 8, during which $9,609 was stolen; of a Bank of America in East Brunswick, N.J., on Feb. 16 during which $28,980 was stolen; of a Bank of America in Ocean Township, N.J., on March 2 during which $15,960 was taken; and of a Bank of America in South Brunswick, N.J., on March 16, during which $33,066 was stolen.</p>
        <p>The men were arrested on April 5 after the shooting of Agent Bush, which took place during an attempted robbery of a PNC Bank in Readington on April 5. The men also face weapons charges for using an assortment of handguns and rifles in the robberies, including a .380-caliber handgun and an SKS rifle, a weapon that was favored by the former Eastern bloc nations and was a precursor to the AK-47.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lynch said that federal authorities told him they had a surveillance video tape that shows Mr. Berrios holding an assault rifle during one of the robberies. The authorities said Mr. Berrios, who the indictment said was known by the nickname Robo Cop, was one of the drivers during the attempted robbery on April 5.</p>
        <p>''His response is that he was not involved in any of the bank robberies,'' Mr. Lynch said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
