<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Jersey Is Closer to Letting Voters Decide on Property Tax Relief</title>
    <meta content="12trenton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/nyregion/12trenton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070619T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853993"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Roberts, Joseph J Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E3DA173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="527" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Jersey Is Closer to Letting Voters Decide on Property Tax Relief</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Jersey Is Closer to Letting Voters Decide on Property Tax Relief</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, June 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A standoff over a 1-cent property tax increase led to a government shutdown last year. But on Monday, the Assembly voted 79 to 1 to allow voters to decide whether they wanted all of the proceeds of that increase to go toward property tax relief for local governments.</p>
        <p>Last year, when Assembly Speaker Joseph J. Roberts Jr. opposed the 1-cent increase in the state sales tax that Gov. Jon S. Corzine and the State Senate leadership said was needed to close a $4.5 billion budget gap, the government shut down for a week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The state assembly voted overwhelmingly to allow voters to decide whether to use new sales tax revenue to lower local property tax rates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A standoff over a 1-cent property tax increase led to a government shutdown last year. But on Monday, the Assembly voted 79 to 1 to allow voters to decide whether they wanted all of the proceeds of that increase to go toward property tax relief for local governments.</p>
        <p>Last year, when Assembly Speaker Joseph J. Roberts Jr. opposed the 1-cent increase in the state sales tax that Gov. Jon S. Corzine and the State Senate leadership said was needed to close a $4.5 billion budget gap, the government shut down for a week.</p>
        <p>The shutdown was resolved only when a battered Mr. Roberts agreed to support the increase. But it was not an unalloyed victory for the governor and his supporters in the Senate, who agreed to dedicate half of the increased sales tax revenue to property tax relief.</p>
        <p>''Dedicating the remaining half-cent from last year's sales tax increase is vital to achieving the long-term sustainability of property taxes,'' Mr. Roberts said of this year's proposal. ''Promises of property tax relief should not be an annual rite in Trenton, but a permanent right in the state constitution.''</p>
        <p>Governors have no say over proposed constitutional amendments that are put on the ballot. If the Senate approves the measure, which is considered probable, voters will decide in November whether to dedicate all of the proceeds from the sales tax increase to property tax relief. That total is estimated to be $1.5 billion for the 2008-9 fiscal year.</p>
        <p>A crucial difference was that this year Senate President Richard J. Codey -- who stood behind Mr. Corzine last year -- backed Mr. Roberts.</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Corzine, despite his repeated statements opposing such dedication of revenue and the restraints he said it placed on his budgeting flexibility, he chose to not actively oppose the speaker's proposal.</p>
        <p>The state treasurer, Bradley Abelow, frequently noted in recent budget hearings that the state would provide about $16 billion to local property tax relief in the current budget proposal, and that through negotiations -- rather than amending the constitution -- more could be dedicated to that purpose.</p>
        <p>Coming in a year when all 120 legislative seats are up for grabs, passage of the referendum was seen as an exclamation point to the Legislature's effort to portray itself as a champion of property tax relief.</p>
        <p>After a special session of the Legislature in the past year, Democratic majorities in the Assembly and Senate collaborated with Mr. Corzine on a package of bills to provide tax credits of up to 20 percent to most property owners and to place a 4 percent cap on the increases in local property taxes. This was accomplished in the $33.3 billion budget in a year when no new taxes were voted in and school aid was increased, all while working down the state's structural debt.</p>
        <p>One Republican, Assemblyman Richard A. Merkt of Morris County, termed the move to dedicate the entire 1-cent increase to property tax relief ''political theater.'' But in the end, most Republicans voted in favor of the measure, a recognition that they, too, do not want to be portrayed as opposed to property tax relief in this election year.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 19, 2007, Tuesday  Because of an editing error, an article last Tuesday about a vote by the New Jersey General Assembly to allow voters to decide whether all proceeds from a 1-cent tax increase approved last year should go to property tax relief for local governments referred incorrectly at one point to the type of tax that was increased. As noted elsewhere in the article, it was the sales tax, not the property tax.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 19, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article last Tuesday about a vote by the New Jersey General Assembly to allow voters to decide whether all proceeds from a 1-cent tax increase approved last year should go to property tax relief for local governments referred incorrectly at one point to the type of tax that was increased. As noted elsewhere in the article, it was the sales tax, not the property tax.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
