<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giuliani Renews Ties With the Police Chief He Ousted</title>
    <meta content="12bratton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/us/politics/12bratton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853950"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2008 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Santora, Marc</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bratton, William J (Police Chief)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bratton, William J</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE1DB173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="721" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giuliani Renews Ties With the Police Chief He Ousted</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Giuliani Renews Ties With the Police Chief He Ousted</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC SANTORA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Santora, Marc</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rudolph W Giuliani and William J Bratton, police commissioner he fired when he was mayor of New York, meet after not speaking with each other for ten years; rapprochement is latest twist in relationship that says much about Giuliani's leadership style; two men presided over New York City's precipitous drop in crime; Bratton was ousted after capturing some of limelight; now Giuliani is highlighting subject of crime as he seeks Republican presidential nomination; his decision to renew ties to Bratton, now police chief of Los Angeles, comes as he highlights his record in New York and says he would apply tactics from those days to federal government; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The two men, Rudolph W. Giuliani and his former police commissioner William J. Bratton, had not spoken to each other in 10 years. When they had crossed paths at social gatherings, they exchanged little more than icy nods.</p>
        <p>But time, tragedy and a presidential campaign have started to change all that.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tragedy and a campaign changed the relationship between Rudolph W. Giuliani and his former police commissioner, who had not spoken to each other in 10 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The two men, Rudolph W. Giuliani and his former police commissioner William J. Bratton, had not spoken to each other in 10 years. When they had crossed paths at social gatherings, they exchanged little more than icy nods.</p>
        <p>But time, tragedy and a presidential campaign have started to change all that.</p>
        <p>The rapprochement between the two men who presided over New York City's precipitous drop in crime is the latest twist in a relationship that says much about Mr. Giuliani's leadership style. The two had a falling out as Mr. Bratton was capturing some of the limelight for the city's crime drop, and Mr. Bratton was ousted in 1996. Later, he would consult, privately, for Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton, a Democrat, when it looked like she might compete with Mr. Giuliani for the Senate.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Bratton is speaking about his renewed relationship with former Mayor Giuliani, saying it began when people close to Mr. Giuliani reached out to him. The two had a meeting in early March, and it went even further with an extended sit-down on May 31 in Mr. Bratton's office at the Los Angeles Police Department, where he is now chief.</p>
        <p>''It was comfortable,'' Mr. Bratton said. ''It's not social and not friendship in the traditional sense.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bratton, who said he wanted to keep certain aspects of the meeting private out of respect for Mr. Giuliani, said that he did not harbor resentments, and that he sensed a similar change in his former boss.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bratton summed up the falling out in simple terms: a difference in style. He said Mr. Giuliani was ''incredibly smart'' and ''detail oriented,'' but a ''micromanager.'' Mr. Bratton said he was not one to be micromanaged.</p>
        <p>When the two men sat down in Mr. Bratton's Los Angeles office, they reminisced briefly, looking at old photos from the police chief's days in New York and joking about the tricks time plays on the body and the hairline. Mostly, though, they talked about crime, a subject Mr. Giuliani has been highlighting as he seeks the Republican presidential nomination. In their first meeting, which the Giuliani camp suggested, they discussed the growing gang problem in California.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Giuliani and Mr. Bratton felt comfortable enough to get together again last month to discuss the centerpiece of their successful crime-fighting initiative in New York: the Compstat program, which uses statistics to aggressively track and measure progress in fighting crime, so police commanders can then be held accountable.</p>
        <p>John F. Timoney, the chief of police in Miami who has known both men for years, said that when he first heard of their meeting, he could not believe it.</p>
        <p>"A lot of people are surprised," Chief Timoney said. "I was surprised, given their prior relationship."</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani's decision to renew his ties to Mr. Bratton comes at an opportune time politically, as he highlights his record in New York and says he would apply tactics from those days to the federal government. It could also help paper over a potentially embarrassing rift from his days as mayor of New York. And the relationship could help Mr. Bratton, who now has access to Mr. Giuliani, the candidate currently at the top of the Republican presidential pack.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani, at a news conference one day after their most recent meeting, was careful to give Mr. Bratton, and another chief architect of Compstat, Jack Maple, who has since died, credit for developing the strategy. Mr. Bratton said he and the former mayor had met to talk about using Compstat-like programs to track a variety of federal government agencies and hold them accountable.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bratton said Mr. Giuliani's desire to sit down and talk about crime reflected an aspect of his leadership style that has long been present, his hands-on approach to policy.</p>
        <p>''One of his traits is that he is incredibly well researched,'' Mr. Bratton said. ''He really drills down for information.''</p>
        <p>People who know Mr. Giuliani say that three events -- his battle with prostate cancer, his third marriage, to Judith Nathan, and the attacks on Sept. 11 -- all of which occurred in a short period, helped mellow him, a notion Mr. Bratton did not disagree with, adding that he had detected some changes in his former boss.</p>
        <p>''We all soften some on the edges,'' he said.</p>
        <p>THE 2008 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
