<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Close to Deal to Release Frozen North Korean Funds</title>
    <meta content="12bank" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/washington/12bank.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853937"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assets, Frozen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Money Laundering</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Banco Delta Asia</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve Bank of New York</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weisman, Steven R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">North Korea</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E3DB173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="554" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Close to Deal to Release Frozen North Korean Funds</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Close to Deal to Release Frozen North Korean Funds</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN R. WEISMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weisman, Steven R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American officials report that US is close to reaching deal to transfer $25 million in frozen funds to North Korea in hopes of getting North Korea to begin dismantling its nuclear arms program; funds have been frozen for nearly two years at Banco Delta Asia, Macao-based bank which Bush administration has labeled violator of American money laundering laws; many major banks asked to facilitate deal have balked, citing ruling by Treasury Dept that bars American banks from facilitating dollar transactions with Macao bank; Russian bank recently agreed to be vehicle for transaction, provided that it could obtain dollars to carry it out; Federal Reserve Bank of New York will act as intermediary; Bush administration comes under criticism, especially from conservatives, for making deal with North Korea; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States appears to be close to reaching a deal to transfer $25 million in frozen funds to North Korea, with Russia and the Federal Reserve Bank of New York acting as intermediaries, in hopes of getting North Korea to begin to dismantle its nuclear arms program, American officials said Monday.</p>
        <p>The funds have been frozen for nearly two years at a bank that the Bush administration has labeled a violator of American money laundering laws. Because of that label, the bank is barred from doing business with any bank in the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The U.S. hopes to get North Korea to begin to dismantle its nuclear arms program by releasing $25 million in frozen assets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States appears to be close to reaching a deal to transfer $25 million in frozen funds to North Korea, with Russia and the Federal Reserve Bank of New York acting as intermediaries, in hopes of getting North Korea to begin to dismantle its nuclear arms program, American officials said Monday.</p>
        <p>The funds have been frozen for nearly two years at a bank that the Bush administration has labeled a violator of American money laundering laws. Because of that label, the bank is barred from doing business with any bank in the United States.</p>
        <p>The bank, Banco Delta Asia, is based in Macao, a semiautonomous region in China. It has been accused by the United States of helping North Korea finance its nuclear arms program, and carrying out counterfeiting and narcotics activities.</p>
        <p>In February, North Korea agreed to begin dismantling its nuclear program in return for several political and economic concessions, including the return of its frozen funds. It also insisted that the money being routed through an international bank in a transaction be in dollars.</p>
        <p>Major banks that were asked to facilitate the deal balked, however, and the money remained frozen. North Korea then continued to refuse to shut down its main nuclear plant, which the United States says is processing fuel for nuclear bombs.</p>
        <p>Several banks in China and the United States, including Wachovia Bank, refused to carry out the transaction.</p>
        <p>They cited a ruling by the Treasury Department in March that barred American banks from facilitating dollar transactions with the Macao bank.</p>
        <p>Recently, a Russian bank agreed to be the vehicle for the transaction, American officials said, provided that it could obtain dollars to carry it out.</p>
        <p>With American laws barring American commercial banks from supplying the dollars, officials turned to the Federal Reserve Bank of New York to facilitate the deal with North Korea.</p>
        <p>''The United States is working with Russian and Macanese authorities to facilitate the transfer'' of North Korean funds that were previously frozen at Banco Delta Asia, said Molly Millerwise, a Treasury Department spokeswoman. ''We appreciate the willingness of the Russian government to facilitate this transaction and the good cooperation of the Macanese authorities.''</p>
        <p>The Wall Street Journal reported details of the proposed deal on Monday.</p>
        <p>American officials said because the Federal Reserve Bank of New York was not a private bank, but part of the Federal Reserve system, it was not subject to American laws barring commercial transactions involving illicit funds. The system is independent of the government but run by presidential appointees.</p>
        <p>Christopher R. Hill, the assistant secretary of state for East Asian affairs, has said that as soon as the money is transferred to North Korea, the United States would demand that North Korean fulfill the commitments it made in February.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration has come under criticism, especially from conservatives, for making the deal with North Korea. Many of the critics charge that American officials were too trusting of the North's intentions.</p>
        <p>North Korea agreed to disable its nuclear facilities in a deal with the United States, China, Russia, Japan and South Korea. The failure to unfreeze the $25 million has been frustrating to the Bush administration for weeks. In April, a senior Treasury delegation failed to get the money transferred after 13 days of talks in Beijing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
