<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pettersen Adds Mind Game to Her Golf Game</title>
    <meta content="12lpga" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/sports/golf/12lpga.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853998"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ladies Professional Golf Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pettersen, Suzann</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ochoa, Lorena</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DA173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="878" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pettersen Adds Mind Game to Her Golf Game</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pettersen Adds Mind Game to Her Golf Game</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <dateline>HAVRE DE GRACE, Md., June 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The target golf that Suzann Pettersen is playing these days has her taking direct aim at the world's top-ranked female player, Lorena Ochoa.</p>
        <p>After winning her second tournament in less than a month and her first career major here Sunday at the L.P.G.A. Championship, Pettersen is at last able to look at herself and see the same golfer others have: someone for whom the L.P.G.A.'s No. 1 spot is within reach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The target golf that Suzann Pettersen is playing these days has her taking direct aim at the world’s top-ranked female player, Lorena Ochoa.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The target golf that Suzann Pettersen is playing these days has her taking direct aim at the world's top-ranked female player, Lorena Ochoa.</p>
        <p>After winning her second tournament in less than a month and her first career major here Sunday at the L.P.G.A. Championship, Pettersen is at last able to look at herself and see the same golfer others have: someone for whom the L.P.G.A.'s No. 1 spot is within reach.</p>
        <p>''It probably helped with this win,'' Pettersen said after closing with a five-under-par 67 at the Bulle Rock Golf Course to defeat the seven-time major winner Karrie Webb by a stroke.</p>
        <p>The victory was made all the more sweet because of how she clinched it, with clutch approach shots and putts down the stretch. Pettersen birdied four of the last nine holes to hold off Webb and the 18-year-old Na On Min, who made four consecutive birdies on the final nine to finish two strokes back.</p>
        <p>The long, straight drives and crisp irons that Pettersen hit Sunday while playing with Min in the final twosome surprised no one who had watched her on the range. Her rhythmic swing and ball-striking abilities have been the envy of golfers since she turned professional in 2000.</p>
        <p>''Suzann has always had more talent in her little finger than a lot of people out here,'' Webb said. ''It's just been a matter of time before she started playing the way she is.''</p>
        <p>Pettersen, a 26-year-old from Norway, had the game to challenge the best but not the mind game. A person who wears her emotions like a sponsor's patch, Pettersen found it hard to manage her feelings and maintain her focus during rounds.</p>
        <p>If she hit a bad shot, the memory of it was liable to poison her whole day. She might play herself into contention, but her heart would start to race and so would her mind, and she would fall behind.</p>
        <p>That was never more evident than at the Kraft Nabisco Championship in April, when Pettersen, playing in the final twosome, led by four shots with four holes to play only to lose by a stroke to Morgan Pressel.</p>
        <p>Although her final round of two-over-par 74 was widely described as a collapse, Pettersen saw it as something different. To her, it was a steppingstone. ''Teeing off on the last day on the leader board, that's where you want to be in every major in every tournament,'' Pettersen said. ''That's how you build experience, and that's how you build your game.''</p>
        <p>When she studied the tape of those last 18 holes with her coaches, Pia Nilsson and Lynn Marriott, whose emphasis is the mental side of the game, Pettersen noticed that her preshot routine changed as the round went on. She stood over some shots too long and struck others too quickly. ''I looked at it as what I can do different,'' Pettersen said, ''and what I can do stronger when I get to the next tournament and I'm in the same position. You try to find your strong skills and how to use them as often as you possibly can and take whatever happens as a challenge.''</p>
        <p>Losing a major that was hers to win was not the worst thing Pettersen has had to overcome. In 2005, she was sidelined from the Tour for eight months with a career-threatening back injury. She sustained a slipped disk, and it was weeks before she could walk, much less swing a club. ''Yes, there was a doubt if I was ever going to play golf again,'' Pettersen said. ''Now it feels great, and I probably appreciate every day a little bit more being healthy.''</p>
        <p>She returned to the L.P.G.A. in 2006 and made the cut in 21 of 23 events while posting three top-10 finishes.</p>
        <p>Pettersen showed the same resilience in rebounding from the defeat at the Nabisco that she did in putting her back injury behind her. At a tournament in Virginia last month, she came from four shots off the pace in the final round to force a playoff, then won the event.</p>
        <p>The victory bolstered her confidence, but there remained the matter of proving to herself that she could succeed while holding a late lead.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, she accomplished that mission. In her postround news conference, Pettersen marveled at how calm she felt from the first drive to the last putt. ''Every shot came out as I thought and as I could see them,'' she said. ''So that was pretty neat.''</p>
        <p>Pettersen's caddie, James Walton, said her demeanor throughout the day impressed him more than any shot she pulled off. ''She was always in control,'' he said. ''She never got too high, never got too low. Which is great for Suzann'' -- he allowed himself a chuckle -- ''because she's quite an emotional person.''</p>
        <p>Pettersen moved into second place on the money list, behind Ochoa, who is seven months younger and nine L.P.G.A. victories richer.</p>
        <p>''If you look at her, she hits a bad shot, I mean, you would hardly see it on the next shot,'' Pettersen said. ''That's what I'm trying to do.''</p>
        <p>This week, Pettersen moved up eight places in the world rankings, to fourth. From where she stands, she has a clear shot at No. 1.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
