<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mocking an Olympics Logo, but Loving the Attention</title>
    <meta content="12adco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/business/media/12adco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853964"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Logotypes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2012)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">London (Eng)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pfanner, Eric</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Logotypes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">London (England)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEFDB173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mocking an Olympics Logo, but Loving the Attention</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mocking an Olympics Logo, but Loving the Attention</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC PFANNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pfanner, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, June 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Planned 2012 London Olympics logo has drawn range of public reaction and has received much publicity, good and bad, from British press; some of descriptions in British press include 'toileting monkey,' and 'broken swastika'; marketing experts say outcry might be exactly what organizers needed as they sought to raise interest among Britons, especially young, who seem somewhat blase about London Games; logo; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Has any marketer ever gotten more for its money than the London Olympics organizers when they introduced a new logo for the 2012 Games?</p>
        <p>All right, some of the descriptions in the British tabloids -- a ''toileting monkey,'' a ''broken swastika'' -- were less than kind. And the news that a video about the emblem caused epileptic seizures was hardly a public relations dream.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Has any marketer ever gotten more for its money than the London Olympics organizers when they introduced a new logo for the 2012 Games?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Has any marketer ever gotten more for its money than the London Olympics organizers when they introduced a new logo for the 2012 Games?</p>
        <p>All right, some of the descriptions in the British tabloids -- a ''toileting monkey,'' a ''broken swastika'' -- were less than kind. And the news that a video about the emblem caused epileptic seizures was hardly a public relations dream.</p>
        <p>For the most part, however, the logo introduction was a textbook example of marketing in the Web 2.0 era, when gold medals are handed out for achieving maximum brand-building buzz at minimum cost. Why spend a lot of money advertising when media owners and Joe Public do the job for you, free of charge?</p>
        <p>The London papers obliged, splashing the logo across their front pages, in full color, next to giant headlines, for several days last week. The £400,000 (about $800,000) that the London Olympic organizers reportedly spent with Wolff Olins, a brand consulting firm owned by the Omnicom Group, was heavily criticized. Was it actually a bargain?''You could blow that on a couple of phone calls buying the kind of media space they got for free,'' said Adam Smith, futures director at Group M, a media buying agency owned by the WPP Group.</p>
        <p>Free advertising is not all that the organizers got for the new logo, a cartoonlike depiction of the number 2012. The design also prompted strong reactions from the public, a measure of its ability to ''engage with'' it, to use a bit of marketing-speak.</p>
        <p>Like other marketers that have tried to involve consumers, the Olympic organizers created a design template on their Web site so that people could download it and create their own logos; these have been posted on the site.</p>
        <p>But the London 2012 Committee's user generated content plans got an unexpected lift when several newspapers embraced the idea, too, asking readers to send in their own Olympic logos, which they printed.</p>
        <p>An anti-logo group drew 50,000 signatures to a petition seeking to have the design changed -- that's 50,000 people who probably never thought they would feel passionately about an Olympic emblem.</p>
        <p>Marketing experts said the outcry might be exactly what the organizers needed as they sought to raise interest among Britons, especially the young, who seem somewhat blasé about the London Games, at least compared with the Chinese and their excitement over the 2008 Olympics in Beijing.</p>
        <p>''From my perspective it was probably good for them because it got people talking about London and the Games,'' said Paul Kemp-Robertson, the editor of Contagious magazine, which tracks marketing trends in new media.</p>
        <p>The London organizers need to generate awareness because they have set a goal of raising about one-third of the £2 billion-plus operating budget from sponsorships.</p>
        <p>In attracting sponsorship money, the Olympics organizers compete against other sporting events with an international profile, including Formula One auto racing, the World Cup soccer tournament and the America's Cup.So far, the London organizers have announced one major local sponsor, the British banking company Lloyds TSB, in a deal worth a reported £80 million.</p>
        <p>Joanna Manning-Cooper, a spokeswoman for the London committee, declined to comment on reports that EDF Energy, the British unit of the French utility Électricité de France, was poised to announce a similar deal.</p>
        <p>For that kind of money, any marketer would want a bit of flexibility, and Ms. Manning-Cooper said the London 2012 logo was the first Olympics emblem that can be modified by marketers. In newspaper ads that appeared last week, Lloyds TSB used a giant image of the logo, but in its own brand colors -- blue fading to green -- rather than one of the four colors provided by the Games organizers.</p>
        <p>Ms. Manning-Cooper declined to comment on talk that organizers would eventually allow sponsors to rearrange the individual shapes that make up the design, but said the logo would ''evolve over time.''</p>
        <p>With five years left until the 2012 Games, there is plenty of time for the fuss over the logo to die down -- or for it to evolve.</p>
        <p>ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
