<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Work in a Prism, Offering Varied Points of View</title>
    <meta content="12ball" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/arts/dance/12ball.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853918"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E6DB173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="729" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Work in a Prism, Offering Varied Points of View</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Work in a Prism, Offering Varied Points of View</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GIA KOURLAS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>How does a ballerina solve a problem like Aurora? It's no easy task, especially when she is held captive by a production as muddled as American Ballet Theater's busy, dramaturge-heavy version of ''The Sleeping Beauty.'' Still, just as the frequent predicament of ballet in New York has become a variation on the theme of bad show, good dancers, five cast changes last week at the Metropolitan Opera House offered new interpretations -- and glimmers of hope for the work's future.</p>
        <p>In the new ''Sleeping Beauty,'' a group effort by Kevin McKenzie, Gelsey Kirkland and Michael Chernov, at the matinee on June 2 Paloma Herrera did more than deliver an articulate performance. As Aurora she bloomed with lucidity -- from her forceful feet and legs to a noticeably plush upper body -- bursting onto the stage like a tonic of clarity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>How does a ballerina solve a problem like Aurora? It’s no easy task, especially when she is held captive by a production as muddled as American Ballet Theater’s busy, dramaturge-heavy version of “The Sleeping Beauty.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>How does a ballerina solve a problem like Aurora? It's no easy task, especially when she is held captive by a production as muddled as American Ballet Theater's busy, dramaturge-heavy version of ''The Sleeping Beauty.'' Still, just as the frequent predicament of ballet in New York has become a variation on the theme of bad show, good dancers, five cast changes last week at the Metropolitan Opera House offered new interpretations -- and glimmers of hope for the work's future.</p>
        <p>In the new ''Sleeping Beauty,'' a group effort by Kevin McKenzie, Gelsey Kirkland and Michael Chernov, at the matinee on June 2 Paloma Herrera did more than deliver an articulate performance. As Aurora she bloomed with lucidity -- from her forceful feet and legs to a noticeably plush upper body -- bursting onto the stage like a tonic of clarity.</p>
        <p>Ms. Herrera's occasional fault is that she dances only for herself, yet here she seemed to pour her determination into saving Aurora from the production's chaos. Gracious, at once in control and at ease, Ms. Herrera let down her defenses, even during the dogged balances in the Rose Adagio, which she performed with joyful purity.</p>
        <p>As her Prince Désiré, Angel Corella was the best of them all, though, unfortunately, too slight a partner for Ms. Herrera. During the Act II Vision, Mr. Corella, in his indelible way, even managed to rise above its moments of ponderous reverie. Later, in the Wedding Celebration, he was inexhaustible, spinning into double tours en l'air and wrapping up a swift, shooting manège of jumps with the softness of a kitten, one hand on his hip and the barest shadow of a smile.</p>
        <p>In various performances his sister, Carmen Corella, as Carabosse, was equally beguiling, incorporating astute mime and a cane; she led her movement from the hip, creating a cunning silhouette that was somehow crookedly sexy. Hee Seo, long-limbed and poised, was unflappable in roles like the Fairy of Sincerity and Princess Florine. As the Lilac Fairy, Maria Riccetto was indistinguishable, but Stella Abrera was excellent, embracing the beneficent part with magnitude, bearing and, when appropriate, vehemence. In one performance she silenced Carabosse (Martine van Hamel) with a raised arm and, out of the corner of her eye, a brief, withering glance. It was perfection.</p>
        <p>As the leads at Wednesday's matinee, Irina Dvorovenko, her dark hair caked with silver glitter, and Maxim Beloserkovsky were less magnetic yet, for the most part, refreshingly restrained. That evening Diana Vishneva, sparklingly feminine, was seamless in the first act, delivering a Rose Adagio so euphoric that her unsupported balances etched a portrait of Aurora: a young woman learning how to stand on her own in an infectious celebration of independence.</p>
        <p>Ms. Vishneva was paired with the young principal dancer David Hallberg, who, despite his relative inexperience, possesses a natural dramatic instinct full of regal flavor. Yet for all his attempts at ardor, the two dancers lacked connection. In both the Vision and the Wedding Celebration, Ms. Vishneva's buoyant lightness shone through, but she was mired by reserve. Strangely, the harder Mr. Hallberg tried to achieve a bond, the more distant she became.</p>
        <p>Filling in for an injured Julie Kent on the evening of June 2, Gillian Murphy made her Aurora debut opposite Ethan Stiefel, whose Prince Désiré was full of amplitude in his romantic characterization and vibrant dancing. On Saturday afternoon, however, Mr. Hallberg reprised his Prince with Ms. Murphy. (It was the only show for which the two were scheduled.) As they have demonstrated earlier this season in ''Othello'' and ''The Dream,'' they share a generous performing nature, prodigious technique and a perceptible yearning to take their roles further than they imagined they could.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hallberg -- tall, blond and fetchingly noble -- highlights, in Ms. Murphy, an appealing fragility, like that of an orchid, as George Balanchine once described his ballerinas. Her ability to whip off piqué and chaîné turns with demon speed tells only half the story. She came alive as Aurora, aided in part by the production's magnificent lighting, which seemed to be designed for her arresting, redheaded glamour. Dancing within the lustrous, autumnal setting, which shifted from a fiery mango to the deepest rose, Ms. Murphy was more than pretty in pink. She glowed.</p>
        <p>American Ballet Theater continues performances through July 7 at the Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000 or abt.org.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
