<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Women Behind Bars, Real or Imaginary</title>
    <meta content="12kaku" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/books/review/12kaku.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853899"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Moore, Susanna</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E2DC173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1018" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Women Behind Bars, Real or Imaginary</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Women Behind Bars, Real or Imaginary</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Big Girls  By Susanna Moore  224 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $24.</p>
        <p>Susanna Moore writes about women in search of an identity, women who are, more often than not, self-destructive, victimized, conflicted and desperate to escape or transcend an oppressive past. And she writes about these women in two utterly different modes: 1) the lyrical and nostalgic, which she used to enormous effect in her 2003 novel, ''One Last Look,'' and her early novels set in Hawaii (''My Old Sweetheart,'' ''The Whiteness of Bones,'' ''Sleeping Beauties''); and 2), the transgressive and graphic, which she used jarringly in her 1995 erotic thriller, ''In the Cut.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Susanna Moore's latest novel, set in a New York women’s prison, is brutal and troubling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Big Girls  By Susanna Moore  224 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $24.</p>
        <p>Susanna Moore writes about women in search of an identity, women who are, more often than not, self-destructive, victimized, conflicted and desperate to escape or transcend an oppressive past. And she writes about these women in two utterly different modes: 1) the lyrical and nostalgic, which she used to enormous effect in her 2003 novel, ''One Last Look,'' and her early novels set in Hawaii (''My Old Sweetheart,'' ''The Whiteness of Bones,'' ''Sleeping Beauties''); and 2), the transgressive and graphic, which she used jarringly in her 1995 erotic thriller, ''In the Cut.''</p>
        <p>Her latest novel, ''The Big Girls,'' set in a New York women's prison named Sloatsburg, is very much in the latter vein. It is a brutal, troubling, often stomach-turning portrait of the denizens of that terrible place -- in particular, Helen, a woman who has been sentenced to life for murdering her two small children, and Louise, a prison psychiatrist who suffers from her own demons and who begins to identify with her patients.</p>
        <p>The novel is told, in alternating takes, from the point of view of four narrators, none of whom is Paris Hilton. The four are the aforementioned Helen and Louise, along with a prison guard named Ike, with whom Louise begins an affair, and Angie, a Hollywood starlet who is dating Louise's ex-husband, Rafael, and who may or may not be Helen's long-lost sister.</p>
        <p>The novel is keenly observed -- a lot of reporting seems to have gone into its writing -- and succeeds in giving the reader a harrowing view of the elaborate social rules and rituals that inform prison life. But Ms. Moore's willful focus on the brutality that goes on there and the brutality that has shaped so many of these women's lives begins to feel both sensationalistic and numbing as the book progresses.</p>
        <p>In fact, were it not for the sympathetic depiction of Helen, the litany of violent and demeaning events that make up the bulk of this novel's narrative would have the formulaic, voyeuristic feel of a women-behind-bars exploitation film: ''Big Girls Behaving Badly in the Big House.''</p>
        <p>Though Sloatsburg does not seem to be a maximum-security prison -- there is a garden where the women grow beans, and a bakery where some of them work -- most of the characters there seem to have committed horrific crimes.</p>
        <p>Darla has dismembered her boyfriend's wife. Aida stabbed her cousin at school. Jessie is serving 15 years for third-degree murder, aggravated assault, the unauthorized practice of medicine and animal cruelty. (''At the time of her arrest, a dead dachshund was found hanging from the back porch of her mobile home.'') LizAnn kept her newborn son in her closet -- he died when an ice skate fell on him. Jo permanently disabled her husband by attacking him with an electric knife. And so on and so on.</p>
        <p>Friendships and alliances develop among the women, but they also commit savage acts against one another. One woman throws scalding water on Keesha for passing a new girl a plate of noodles. Darla cuts off the finger of a woman named Ahnjanoo, using a piece of her plastic hand mirror ''broken and sharpened for that purpose.''</p>
        <p>And Helen is assaulted with a pair of scissors by a woman named Larissa who says she wants ''to cut her face so the world would always know she was the Devil incarnate.''</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, most of these women come from nightmarish backgrounds. Like characters in earlier Moore novels, many have been abused -- raped or molested or, in one woman's case, pimped out at the age of 9 by her grandmother.</p>
        <p>Helen's story is especially gruesome: she was raped for years by her stepfather, while her mother punished her for being ''a natural-born liar'' by making her eat hot jalapeño peppers -- so many that her face once broke out in blisters.</p>
        <p>As an emotional defense, Helen developed an alter ego named Ellie in whom she could confide, and she also began to hear voices -- the voices of God's messengers, she says, who told her to save her own children by killing them. To pass the time in prison, she measures everything in her cell with a measuring tape, writing down the measurements in a little notebook.</p>
        <p>Louise, who has problems with her own son, Ransom -- he tells his father that his mother's lover, Ike, has exposed himself to him -- identifies with Helen and takes a special interest in her case. She urges Helen to accept the fact that Ellie is not a real person but a projection of Helen's own subconscious, and she presides over Helen's move from protective custody out into the general prison population.</p>
        <p>Louise realizes that therapy is full of hazards for Helen: ''The tension between her conscious self and the self that she has so long kept hidden is so delicate that I am frightened for her. I always knew how dangerous knowledge would be to her, but must I still hold to the belief that her ignorance is equally dangerous?''</p>
        <p>Using the empathy for outsiders that she's demonstrated in earlier books, Ms. Moore does a powerful job of conveying Helen's state of mind, at once self-righteous and grief-stricken, fearful and angry and oddly detached.</p>
        <p>Louise, however, remains an enigmatic and sketchily drawn character: we're told that she was abused as a child, and suffered a breakdown when her son was born. But her past, like that of the narrator of ''In the Cut,'' feels oddly disembodied and vague, and the reader keeps wondering how she ever became a psychiatrist and why she hasn't gained greater insight into her own neuroses and needs.</p>
        <p>Worse, Ms. Moore dwells so insistently on the terrible childhood abuse and neglect her characters have suffered -- just as she dwells relentlessly on the violent or deeply dysfunctional trajectory of their lives -- that their stories all have a way of bleeding into one another. As a result, all these women, with the notable exception of Helen, tend to blur together, leaving the reader feeling horrified and benumbed rather than genuinely moved.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
