<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Politicians in Britain, the Post-Blair Era Has Already Begun</title>
    <meta content="12britain" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/world/europe/12britain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853934"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Gordon (Chancellor of the Exchequer)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Labor Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Blair, Tony</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE4DB173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="737" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Politicians in Britain, the Post-Blair Era Has Already Begun</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Politicians in Britain, the Post-Blair Era Has Already Begun</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, June 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Six British politicians are vying to be chosen by Labor Party as its deputy leader to Gordon Brown, who already knows he will be party leader and prime minister when Tony Blair departs on June 27; interregnum in weeks since Blair announced his departure has brought forth some ferment across British politics; Brown is trying to distance himself from some of most contentious aspects of Blair's leadership, notably way Britian goes to war, which it did twice under Blair; Brown has indicated he will give Parliament more powerful role in such decisions; says he wants greater parliamentary oversight of intelligence; he declines to discuss most onerous issue for him: timing of withdrawal of remaining 5,500 British troops from Iraq (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the past few weeks, like a wannabe rock band on provincial tour, a clutch of British politicians has been crisscrossing the land, from Glasgow to Cardiff to Oxford.</p>
        <p>Six are vying to be chosen by the Labor Party as its deputy leader. Another, Gordon Brown, knows already that he will be party leader and prime minister when Tony Blair finally loosens his grip on June 27. ''It's not his fault,'' the columnist Ann Treneman wrote of Mr. Brown in The Times of London, ''but the fact that he is running against no one inevitably makes the entire affair seem slightly North Korean.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The interregnum in the weeks since the prime minister announced his departure has coaxed forth some ferment across British politics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the past few weeks, like a wannabe rock band on provincial tour, a clutch of British politicians has been crisscrossing the land, from Glasgow to Cardiff to Oxford.</p>
        <p>Six are vying to be chosen by the Labor Party as its deputy leader. Another, Gordon Brown, knows already that he will be party leader and prime minister when Tony Blair finally loosens his grip on June 27. ''It's not his fault,'' the columnist Ann Treneman wrote of Mr. Brown in The Times of London, ''but the fact that he is running against no one inevitably makes the entire affair seem slightly North Korean.''</p>
        <p>While the competition has been limited to the inner conclaves of the Labor Party, the interregnum in the weeks since Mr. Blair announced his departure has coaxed forth some ferment across British politics.</p>
        <p>For one thing, David Cameron, the leader of the opposition Conservatives, has suffered his sharpest setback as he seeks the same center ground Mr. Blair has dominated.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Brown has embarked on a process to distance himself from some of the most contentious aspects of Mr. Blair's leadership, notably the way Britain goes to war, which it did twice under Mr. Blair.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown has indicated that he will give Parliament a more powerful role in such decisions.</p>
        <p>''I have already said Parliament should have a more formal role in issues of war and peace,'' Mr. Brown said during a visit to Baghdad on Monday that had been kept secret in advance. ''But I think we can go further and learn from what's happened over the last few years.''</p>
        <p>One of the most debated periods of Mr. Blair's leadership came before the invasion of Iraq when the government cited intelligence about illicit weapons to justify the decision to join the United States in the war against Saddam Hussein. No such weapons were found and an official inquiry found that the British government had relied heavily on ''seriously flawed'' intelligence.</p>
        <p>Speaking to reporters in Baghdad, Mr. Brown said he had asked a senior civil servant, Sir Gus O'Donnell, to make ''all security and intelligence analysis independent of the political process.'' At the same time, he said he wanted greater parliamentary oversight of intelligence, in order to ''reassure people both about the information and the use of information.''</p>
        <p>''I think it's important to learn all the lessons, just as Tony Blair has said he acted in good faith but mistakes were made,'' Mr. Brown said. ''I think it's important to learn the lessons, to look forward now.''</p>
        <p>But he declined to be drawn into the most onerous issue for him: when will the remaining 5,500 British troops be withdrawn from Iraq? ''This is not the right time to talk about numbers,'' he said. ''I don't want to get into talking about timetables or numbers.''</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Blair has embarked on a long farewell, visiting the United States and Africa and representing Britain at the Group of 8 meeting last week, as he will at the European Union gathering this month. His opponents have been scathing. ''Tony Blair was elected to be prime minister of our country, not a pop star,'' said Mr. Cameron, the opposition leader.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Cameron has seen his own glitter tarnished in a fight with traditional Conservatives, after he said last month he would build no more grammar schools, selective elementary schools run at government expense for students who qualify. Support for these schools was once seen as a bedrock of the party's belief in educational meritocracy.</p>
        <p>To many political analysts, the revolt among his followers and a consequent slide in opinion polls marked the end of a honeymoon that started when Mr. Cameron became Conservative leader in December 2005.</p>
        <p>''This is a key test for our party,'' Mr. Cameron said. ''Does it want to be a serious force for government and change, or does it want to be a right-wing debating society muttering about what might have been?''</p>
        <p>The maneuvering is important for Mr. Cameron and Mr. Brown, the two men most likely to square off in Britain's next general election, which must be held by 2010.</p>
        <p>On present showings, the contest looks even. ''It will be a battle that either can hope to win,'' John Curtice, a political scientist, wrote in The Sunday Telegraph. ''For while voters clearly regard the two men differently, they are evenly divided about who they prefer.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
