<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Princeton Track Team To Compete In China</title>
    <meta content="12princeton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/sports/othersports/12princeton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853996"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TRACK AND FIELD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ivy League</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DA173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="801" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Princeton Track Team To Compete In China</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Princeton Track Team to Compete in China</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Overseas trips were once common for Ivy League track teams. Until a half-century ago, meets frequently involved the combined teams of Oxford and Cambridge against colleges like Yale, Harvard and Princeton.</p>
        <p>Now it is rare for college teams to venture so far, and ever rarer for a group like the Princeton track team to compete in China. The Tigers leave today for a 13-day trip to China, where they will compete in two meets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Overseas trips were once common for Ivy League track teams. Now it is rare for college teams to venture so far, and ever rarer for a group like the Princeton track team to compete in China.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Overseas trips were once common for Ivy League track teams. Until a half-century ago, meets frequently involved the combined teams of Oxford and Cambridge against colleges like Yale, Harvard and Princeton.</p>
        <p>Now it is rare for college teams to venture so far, and ever rarer for a group like the Princeton track team to compete in China. The Tigers leave today for a 13-day trip to China, where they will compete in two meets.</p>
        <p>Peter Farrell is the women's track coach at Princeton. Fred Samara is the men's coach, and one of his runners in the 1980s was Joe Sinisi. ''We were talking a year ago,'' Farrell said, ''and Joe said: 'Why don't you take your teams to China? Think about it.' ''</p>
        <p>The coaches were intrigued with the idea. Farrell said that when August Wolf, a former Princeton shot-putter and 1984 Olympian, heard about it, ''he jumped out of his skin and quickly started raising money for the trip.''</p>
        <p>When Craig Masback, the chief executive of USA Track &amp; Field, heard about it, he came up with the names of alumni who might help.</p>
        <p>Wolf is now a financial-services executive. Masback was once one of the world's leading milers. Each traveled extensively during and after his track days at Princeton. But China?</p>
        <p>A total of 51 Princeton track team members, 28 men and 23 women, will arrive tomorrow in Beijing. They will spend five days there and compete Saturday against an all-star team from Beijing City University.</p>
        <p>They will also spend three days in Xian, known for its archaeological sites, before training and competing at an invitational meet in Shanghai.</p>
        <p>''I was leaning toward rekindling Oxford-Cambridge, but this is so much more exciting,'' Farrell said. ''The prospect of going to an Olympic site the year before the Olympics turned me on. It's pretty exotic for a track team. When would we ever get a chance to make an official trip to China, compete there and be treated like guests?''</p>
        <p>The athletes found out about the trip when they returned to Princeton in the fall, and, as Farrell said, ''their mouths dropped.'' They were told they would have to place high in the Ivy League Heptagonal championships to qualify for the trip.</p>
        <p>That became a great motivator. The men's team finished first indoors and second outdoors, and the women's team placed fourth indoors and second outdoors.</p>
        <p>Andrew Park, a pole-vaulter from Fairport, N.Y., and a co-captain of the men's team, said he had two fears. He was afraid that graduating seniors would not be eligible for the trip. He was assured they would be. Then he worried about the cuisine.</p>
        <p>''I like Chinese food, but I'm not sure what we get here is what they get there,'' he said in a telephone interview. ''We worked with a travel agent to make sure we would like it.''</p>
        <p>Catha Mullen, a middle-distance runner from Bronxville, N.Y., and a women's co-captain, said she would be happy just to get there. She graduated last Tuesday morning, then flew that afternoon to Sacramento to compete in the N.C.A.A. track and field championships. On Wednesday night, she ran in the 5,000-meter semifinals, then finished 10th in the final on Friday.</p>
        <p>''It's no bother,'' she said before her rushed schedule unfolded last week. ''Track has always been about balancing different things.''</p>
        <p>The trip is being financed mainly by the Friends of Princeton Track, an organization made up primarily of former athletes and the parents of current athletes. About 70 people, including coaches, trainers and administrators, will make the trip. The original budget was $180,000 to $200,000, but that has grown.</p>
        <p>Dan Biederman, a sprinter for Princeton in 1972 and 1973 and the president of the Friends, said the trip to China was the first of its kind for a college team. The N.C.A.A. said it did not track international trips.</p>
        <p>''The N.C.A.A. allows a college to take trips like this only once every four years, so we wanted to do it right,'' he said. ''We asked our track alumni to raise their contributions so we could make this trip. Each trip costs about $2,400, and we asked the kids who could pay to put up $750 each. We asked the alumni and friends to pay for two-thirds or three-quarters of one trip, and they came through.''</p>
        <p>There were many other needs.</p>
        <p>Samara said: ''We had to find a tour operator who could handle a large party and customize the tour to our needs. We're not going to do heavy training, but we needed training facilities. We needed special visas. We needed a Chinese liaison, and we found him in James Li, the head cross-country coach at Arizona.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''I love the whole idea. Our athletes can't believe it, and I can't believe it, either.''</p>
        <p>TRACK AND FIELD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
