<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As the Cheering of Tony Night Fades, Broadway Still Faces a Summer of Closings</title>
    <meta content="12dark" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/theater/theaterspecial/12dark.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853925"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/New York Theater Workshop</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Tony Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">League of American Theaters and Producers</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E5DB173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="831" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As the Cheering of Tony Night Fades, Broadway Still Faces a Summer of Closings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">As the Cheering of Tony Night Fades, Broadway Still Faces a Summer of Closings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAMPBELL ROBERTSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just about everyone along Broadway knew that ''Spring Awakening'' would do well at Sunday night's Tony Awards, but there was still some surprise heard at the after-parties: Few thought it would do quite as well as it did.</p>
        <p>The eight wins -- for best musical, book, score, direction and choreography, among other things -- came, among other things, as a relief to the producers of the show, which began its Broadway life struggling for survival and has inched its way forward since then. Its huge roster of producers, which has become a running gag around Broadway, is a testament to just how hard it was to raise money for the show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although this past season was crowded, a sizable chunk of Broadway is going to be dark by the end of the summer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just about everyone along Broadway knew that ''Spring Awakening'' would do well at Sunday night's Tony Awards, but there was still some surprise heard at the after-parties: Few thought it would do quite as well as it did.</p>
        <p>The eight wins -- for best musical, book, score, direction and choreography, among other things -- came, among other things, as a relief to the producers of the show, which began its Broadway life struggling for survival and has inched its way forward since then. Its huge roster of producers, which has become a running gag around Broadway, is a testament to just how hard it was to raise money for the show.</p>
        <p>''We struggled; it was clear that we struggled,'' said Ira Pittleman, one of its lead producers. ''Even I thought it was too risky a proposition for Broadway.''</p>
        <p>But as of early yesterday afternoon, according to the show's producers, ''Spring Awakening'' had taken in more than $750,000 since the beginning of Sunday night's broadcast; if things continue at this clip, the advance for the show could easily top $4.5 million by the end of the week.</p>
        <p>The uptick of fortune for ''Spring Awakening'' stands out even more because few of the other awards given out on Tony night will make even a negligible impact on the immediate Broadway landscape.</p>
        <p>Of the winners of the four top awards, two -- ''Journey's End,'' winner of the best play revival, and ''The Coast of Utopia,'' a record breaker for most awards won by a play, with seven -- have already closed and have no current plans to tour. Another -- ''Company,'' winner of best musical revival -- has been in critical condition at the box office for weeks.</p>
        <p>In fact, although this past season was crowded (at one point in late April, shows were playing in every theater but one), a sizable chunk of Broadway is going to be dark by the end of the summer.</p>
        <p>''A Moon for the Misbegotten'' and ''Journey's End'' closed on Sunday; by the end of August, 10 more shows are scheduled to fold, including ''The Pirate Queen,'' ending its run on June 17 at a loss of at least $16 million.</p>
        <p>Several shows with open-ended runs have been looking shaky. In addition to ''Company,'' August Wilson's ''Radio Golf,'' nominated for best play, has been struggling. There have even been whispers about the fates of ''Rent'' and ''Avenue Q,'' given their moderate ticket sales, but Kevin McCollum, a lead producer on the two shows, insists that neither is leaving anytime soon.</p>
        <p>In another sign that this year was notable more for critical than financial success, three of the four shows nominated for best musical were being sold at the TKTS discount booth the week before the Tony ceremony (''Mary Poppins'' being the exception). Producers are hoping that the Tonys will help change that situation.</p>
        <p>''We're certainly seeing an effect,'' said Michael Rosenberg, the executive producer of ''Grey Gardens,'' speaking the morning after the Tonys. Since the play won three awards but has a hurting box office, its future could lie in the balance. ''We'll just keep watching to see what to do,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The contract for Christine Ebersole, who won the leading-actress Tony for her performance, ends in September, and she has already agreed to join a production of ''Grey Gardens'' in London at some point next season. Whether the show can make it to September, and find a replacement when Ms. Ebersole does leave, is up to ticket buyers.</p>
        <p>With all these closings and potential closings, what's to come?</p>
        <p>As usual, the summer agenda is skimpy. ''Xanadu'' opens in two weeks. A revival of ''Grease'' begins performances at the end of July. A planned production of ''Treasure Island'' that was originally scheduled for this summer has been postponed.</p>
        <p>The fall is lining up to be a big one with ''Young Frankenstein,'' ''The Little Mermaid'' and a few other buzzed-about plays on the docket, but none are opening before October.</p>
        <p>The Tony ceremony, broadcast on CBS, came out bruised once again in the ratings battle, but you must consider what it was up against -- you don't really have to ask at this point, do you? According to preliminary Nielsen ratings, the ceremony drew a meager 6.24 million viewers, down nearly 20 percent from last year (and a lower number than most episodes of the reality casting show ''Grease: You're the One That I Want''). If the final numbers agree, they would make this the lowest-rated Tony broadcast ever.</p>
        <p>Still, CBS came out on top Sunday night among the networks -- but that was largely thanks to a strong ratings performance by ''60 Minutes.''</p>
        <p>''On one hand, I'm pleased that CBS ended up No. 1 for the night,'' said Charlotte St. Martin, the executive director of the League of American Theaters and Producers, accentuating the positive. ''Of course, nobody ever wants to hear you lost viewers because, after all, we need those viewers.'' But, she added: ''We suspect our loyal viewers were there.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
