<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>British Company To Investigate Its Own Deal With the Saudis</title>
    <meta content="12bae" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/world/europe/12bae.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853933"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arms Sales Abroad</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Saudi Arabia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Werdigier, Julia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Sales Abroad</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Saudi Arabia</location>
        <org class="online_producer">BAE Systems Plc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E4DB173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="517" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>British Company To Investigate Its Own Deal With the Saudis</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">British Company to Investigate Its Own Deal With the Saudis</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIA WERDIGIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Werdigier, Julia</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, June 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>BAE Systems, Britain's biggest weapons maker, says it will set up independent commission to examine its business practices following allegations about payments linked to Saudi Arabian arms deal in 1980s; review would focus on BAE Systems' current policies and processes; it would not try to copy any past work done by Britain's Serious Fraud Office, which looked into allegations of corruption in Saudi arms deal but then abruptly canceled its inquiry after Prime Min Tony Blair said probe would threaten thousands of British jobs and affect diplomatic and intelligence ties with Saudi Arabia; some analysts say setting up independent commission is unlikely to end controversy; BAE has denied allegations of wrongdoing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BAE Systems, Britain's biggest weapons maker, is planning to set up an independent commission to examine its business practices following allegations about payments linked to a Saudi Arabian arms deal in the 1980s, an official at the company said Monday.</p>
        <p>Lord Woolf, the former lord chief justice of England and Wales, has been approached to lead the commission, which is expected to report its findings once an investigation is completed, according to the official, who declined to be identified because the composition of the commission had not been made public.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Britain’s biggest weapons maker is planning to set up an independent commission following allegations about payments linked to an arms deal in the 1980s.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BAE Systems, Britain's biggest weapons maker, is planning to set up an independent commission to examine its business practices following allegations about payments linked to a Saudi Arabian arms deal in the 1980s, an official at the company said Monday.</p>
        <p>Lord Woolf, the former lord chief justice of England and Wales, has been approached to lead the commission, which is expected to report its findings once an investigation is completed, according to the official, who declined to be identified because the composition of the commission had not been made public.</p>
        <p>The review would focus on BAE Systems' current policies and processes and would not try to copy any past work done by the Serious Fraud Office, which looked into allegations of corruption in the so-called Al Yamamah arms deal negotiated with Saudi Arabia in 1985, the official said.</p>
        <p>The Serious Fraud Office in December abruptly canceled its inquiry into the allegations after Prime Minister Tony Blair said the investigation would threaten thousands of British jobs and affect diplomatic and intelligence ties with Saudi Arabia.</p>
        <p>Prince Bandar bin Sultan of Saudi Arabia on Monday denied reports by the British Broadcasting Corporation and The Guardian last week that BAE had paid more than $2 billion into bank accounts in Washington operated by him. Prince Bandar helped to negotiate the Yamamah arms deal, then valued at about $54 billion. At the time, Prince Bandar was Saudi Arabia's ambassador to the United States.</p>
        <p>Prince Bandar, who is currently the secretary general of the Saudi National Security Council, said Monday that the allegations were ''untrue'' and ''grotesque in their absurdity.'' He said that the bank accounts in question belonged to the Saudi government, that BAE ''was not a party to any of these accounts'' and that reviews by the Treasury and other United States authorities had found no wrongdoing ''in relation to the operation or management of the account.''</p>
        <p>Some analysts said the plan to set up an independent commission was unlikely to end the controversy. ''They want to show they have nothing to hide today, but no one accuses them of having done something wrong recently,'' said Andrew Brookes, an analyst at the International Institute for Strategic Studies in London. ''The accusations are about the past, so an investigation into processes today won't change anything.''</p>
        <p>The news reports last week revived calls among some lawmakers to restart the investigation because unresolved allegations of bribery might hurt British business.</p>
        <p>But at the Group of 8 meeting in Germany on June 7, Mr. Blair defended the decision to suspend the fraud investigation, saying he did not ''believe the investigation would have led to anywhere except to the complete wreckage of a vital strategic relationship for our country.''</p>
        <p>Saudi Arabia is one of Britain's allies in the Middle East and one of the biggest markets for British goods in the region.</p>
        <p>Under the Yamamah deal, which was signed by then Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher, Britain supplied Tornado fighters and other weapons to Saudi Arabia.</p>
        <p>BAE has denied allegations of wrongdoing in relation to the deal, saying it was a government-to-government agreement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
