<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dissident Challenges U.N. Role on Kosovo</title>
    <meta content="12kosovo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/world/europe/12kosovo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853932"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kosovo (Serbia)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wood, Nicholas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kurti, Albin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Kosovo (Serbia)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E4DB173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dissident Challenges U.N. Role on Kosovo</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dissident Challenges U.N. Role on Kosovo</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS WOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wood, Nicholas</byline>
      <dateline>PRISTINA, Kosovo, June 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Albin Kurti, ethnic Albanian in Kosovo, is former dissident who was jailed for his opposition to former Yugoslav leader Slobodan Milosevic; he opposes United Nations plan in determining status of Kosovo; says it would leave United States and Europe with too much power, noting that it would allow appointed figure to intervene in Kosovo's police and judiciary matters; he urges that Kosovo's future be decided in referendum rather than in Security Council; most ethnic Albanians see Western plan for Kosovo as their best prospect of gaining independence; Kurti has led series of demonstrations against UN, and was sent to prison in Feb after two people were killed during one violent protest; he is now under house arrest as he awaits trial; he is convinced that charges against him are politically motivated because of his opposition to UN plan; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like countless ethnic Albanians in Kosovo, Albin Kurti spent the weekend glued to his television set, watching President Bush's visit to Albania. He was eager to see what Mr. Bush would say from just across the border about Kosovo's efforts to gain its independence from Serbia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush did say that he supported independence for Kosovo as soon as possible, but Mr. Kurti, who opposes the United Nations' role in determining the status of Kosovo, was unimpressed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The treatment of a former dissident has increased nervousness among Kosovo politicians and international officials as the status of the province remains up in the air.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like countless ethnic Albanians in Kosovo, Albin Kurti spent the weekend glued to his television set, watching President Bush's visit to Albania. He was eager to see what Mr. Bush would say from just across the border about Kosovo's efforts to gain its independence from Serbia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush did say that he supported independence for Kosovo as soon as possible, but Mr. Kurti, who opposes the United Nations' role in determining the status of Kosovo, was unimpressed.</p>
        <p>He says he believes that the United Nations plan for the province would leave the United States and Europe with too much power, noting that it would allow an appointed figure to intervene in Kosovo's police and judiciary matters.</p>
        <p>''This is a typical colonial situation,'' he said in an interview on Saturday. ''Of course it has modern wrapping, but it remains a colonial situation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kurti, a former dissident who was jailed for his opposition to the former Yugoslav leader Slobodan Milosevic, has urged that Kosovo's future be decided in a referendum rather than in the Security Council.</p>
        <p>He has led a series of demonstrations against the United Nations, and was sent to prison in February after one violent protest in which two people were killed and 82 wounded. Last Thursday, he was released and placed under house arrest while awaiting trial.</p>
        <p>The treatment of Mr. Kurti has increased nervousness among Kosovo politicians and international officials here as the status of the province remains up in the air. Under the United Nations plan for independence, Kosovo would be supervised by a European-led mission for three years.</p>
        <p>The plan awaits approval by the Security Council, but the Russians may well veto it on behalf of their ally, the Serbs.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Kurti continues to get his message across. In order for the province to obtain ''true independence,'' Kosovo must be allowed to run all of its own affairs, he argued from his apartment, as two policemen stood guard outside.</p>
        <p>The real reason for the charges against him, he claims, is his opposition to the United Nations plan, and fears among politicians and United Nations officials that the protests will jeopardize Kosovo's independence. Several human rights groups and the province's ombudsman have said that the charges appear to be politically motivated.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kurti's stance has made him deeply unpopular with many of his ethnic group. Most ethnic Albanians, who make up an estimated 90 percent of Kosovo's population, support the Western plan for Kosovo as their best prospect of gaining independence after eight years of rule by a United Nations administration, and seven decades of Serbian domination before that.</p>
        <p>Despite the criticism of the arrest and imprisonment of Mr. Kurti, one political analyst said the sympathies of Albanians generally lay with the United Nations in this case.</p>
        <p>''People do not oppose his detention,'' said the analyst, Besa Shahini, the director of the Kosovar Stability Initiative, a political research group based in Pristina. ''There is a sense of relief that he cannot do anything that would jeopardize the final status process.''</p>
        <p>Yet his group, Vetevendosja -- which means ''self-determination'' in Albanian -- has caught the imagination of the urban youth of Kosovo, who are fed up with the United Nations' presence in the region.</p>
        <p>The group has led numerous eye-catching protests at the United Nations headquarters in Pristina, in one case leading around a donkey bearing a United Nations sign.</p>
        <p>On Feb. 10, violent clashes ensued after Vetevendosja protesters tried to force their way through a police cordon in Pristina. The police responded by firing tear gas canisters and rubber-coated bullets, killing two demonstrators.</p>
        <p>The unrest was the most serious in Kosovo since rioting in 2004; Kosovo's interior minister resigned and the chief of the United Nations police force was asked to step down.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kurti was arrested and accused of leading a demonstration ''that led to the deaths of persons and injury of 82 others.'' He also is accused of preventing United Nations personnel from carrying out their duties and faces a maximum sentence of 10 years.</p>
        <p>A report by the United Nations mission blamed a Romanian police unit serving with the United Nations for the deaths and injuries, but concluded there was insufficient evidence to charge the police officers.</p>
        <p>At another court hearing on May 7, a United Nations prosecutor argued that Mr. Kurti needed to remain in detention in light of ''the danger the defendant represents to the future status of Kosovo,'' according to a transcript of the hearing.</p>
        <p>That comment upset human rights groups monitoring the treatment of Mr. Kurti. ''Regardless of the status of negotiations, the premise of freedom of expression should not be jeopardized,'' said Hilmi Jashari, Kosovo's ombudsman.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
