<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Opening Statements in Case On Autism and Vaccinations</title>
    <meta content="12vaccine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/us/12vaccine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853936"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Autism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Autism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immune System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Autism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E3DB173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Opening Statements in Case On Autism and Vaccinations</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Opening Statements in Case on Autism and Vaccinations</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GARDINER HARRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Harris, Gardiner</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawyers began arguments on Monday in the first of several test cases that may help decide whether the government should pay millions of dollars to parents of autistic children.</p>
        <p>Nearly 5,000 parents claim that vaccinations caused their children to become autistic, and many of their claims have been pending for five years. The hearing was held at the ''federal vaccine court,'' set up by Congress 20 years ago when a series of vaccine scares nearly crippled the industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawyers have begun arguments in a test case that may help decide whether the government should pay millions of dollars to parents of autistic children.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lawyers began arguments on Monday in the first of several test cases that may help decide whether the government should pay millions of dollars to parents of autistic children.</p>
        <p>Nearly 5,000 parents claim that vaccinations caused their children to become autistic, and many of their claims have been pending for five years. The hearing was held at the ''federal vaccine court,'' set up by Congress 20 years ago when a series of vaccine scares nearly crippled the industry.</p>
        <p>Every major study and scientific organization examining this issue has found no link between vaccination and autism, but the parents and their advocates have persisted. Their frustration was evident in the opening statement of the parents' lawyer, Thomas Powers of Portland, Ore.</p>
        <p>''Numerous obstacles have been placed in the path of the petitioners seeking that fair and generous compensation that they are entitled to,'' Mr. Powers said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Powers gave his statement with his back to the three judges who will decide the case, addressing instead a few dozen audience members, many of them lawyers.</p>
        <p>''I felt it was important to address the families and the public,'' he said during a break in the hearing.</p>
        <p>The vaccine court has gone to unusual lengths to convince parents that it will fairly adjudicate their claims, even setting up a conference call where parents can listen in to the hearings, which are expected to run for three weeks.</p>
        <p>At the opening of the hearing, Special Master George Hastings took pains to express his sympathy to the parents of autistic children.</p>
        <p>He pointed to Michelle Cedillo and her parents, Theresa and Michael Cedillo, whose claim for compensation is serving as the first test case. Special Master Hastings said the Cedillos were ''the most important people in the courtroom.''</p>
        <p>''To all such family members, as to the Cedillo family, we special masters pledge to you that we will listen very carefully to the evidence presented at this hearing,'' Special Master Hastings said. ''We realize what an important task that has been assigned to us in this hearing.''</p>
        <p>Michelle Cedillo, 12, was rolled into the courtroom in a wheelchair at the start of the hearing. She wore hearing protection similar to that worn by heavy-machinery operators. She hit herself repeatedly and made loud grunting noises. Her parents soon rolled her out.</p>
        <p>Many parents who claim that vaccines gave their children autism are deeply suspicious of what they see as the government's role in their children's illness.</p>
        <p>Most have dismissed the many government-sponsored studies and panels that found no link between vaccination and autism. A few have even physically threatened some government scientists.</p>
        <p>Parents' lawyers said this case would probably affect only a handful of the other claims. A test hearing for the other claims will be heard next year, said Mike Williams, chairman of a committee of parents' lawyers.</p>
        <p>In Monday's hearing, lawyers argued that the measles, mumps and rubella vaccine gave Michelle a chronic measles infection that damaged her central nervous system. The lawyers also said that a once-common additive to pediatric vaccines, thimerosal, damaged her immune system, making it impossible for her to fight the infection.</p>
        <p>''She had been interacting with her parents, with her cousins,'' said Sylvia Chin-Caplan, who represents the Cedillos. ''She was babbling. She suddenly became silent.''</p>
        <p>The argument represents a patchwork of theories advanced for years, but the more common argument is that thimerosal directly damaged children's brains.</p>
        <p>In hopes of finding more evidence to support their claims, parents' lawyers have for years delayed the cases based on that argument.</p>
        <p>''I think we can win with what we've got,'' Mr. Williams said. ''But I think we'll get better evidence'' by waiting.</p>
        <p>Vincent J. Matanoski, an assistant director in the civil division of the Department of Justice, opened with a brief statement in which he dismissed the parents' cases as ''junk science.''</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately, after five years, you'll find a signal lack of support for their contentions,'' Mr. Matanoski said.</p>
        <p>Thimerosal was almost entirely removed from pediatric vaccines in 2001 after some government scientists expressed concern about the amount of mercury that children who got routine vaccinations would be exposed to. Since then, autism rates in the United States have shown no signs of dropping.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
