<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leaders for the America's Cup Teams Have Different Perspectives</title>
    <meta content="12sailing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/sports/othersports/12sailing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853994"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SAILING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">America's Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sailboats and Sailing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sailboats and Sailing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">America's Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bertarelli, Ernesto</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E3DA173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leaders for the America's Cup Teams Have Different Perspectives</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Leaders for the America’s Cup Teams Have Different Perspectives</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <dateline>VALENCIA, Spain, June 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An edgy America's Cup competition grew edgier Monday, when the head of Alinghi expressed disappointment with the opposition's plans and suggested that its leaders were ungrateful for the financial support he had provided when they were struggling to create a syndicate.</p>
        <p>Alinghi, the defending champion, will defend the America's Cup against Emirates Team New Zealand in a best-of-nine series that begins here June 23. Many New Zealanders view it as a grudge match, but Ernesto Bertarelli, the Swiss billionaire who is president of the Alinghi team, sees it through a different lens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alinghi, the defending champion, will defend the America’s Cup against Emirates Team New Zealand in what many New Zealanders view as a grudge match.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An edgy America's Cup competition grew edgier Monday, when the head of Alinghi expressed disappointment with the opposition's plans and suggested that its leaders were ungrateful for the financial support he had provided when they were struggling to create a syndicate.</p>
        <p>Alinghi, the defending champion, will defend the America's Cup against Emirates Team New Zealand in a best-of-nine series that begins here June 23. Many New Zealanders view it as a grudge match, but Ernesto Bertarelli, the Swiss billionaire who is president of the Alinghi team, sees it through a different lens.</p>
        <p>He views it as the climax of the competition that he and his deputies have reshaped into a more profitable and modern event with a more global approach. And he is upset that Team New Zealand's managing director, Grant Dalton, has said that he intends to reinstate some form of a nationality rule if the Kiwis win back the Cup.</p>
        <p>''If he was to win, that basically would put three-quarters of the people around this harbor out of work,'' Bertarelli said in an interview on the terrace at Alinghi's base. ''And more surprisingly so, they are probably friends of his, since a lot of teams have Kiwis in their ranks.''</p>
        <p>Alinghi scrapped the nationality rule after winning the Cup in 2003 in New Zealand, allowing sailors from any nation to work for a syndicate without having to fulfill a citizenship or residency requirement. Its team is now cosmopolitan to the core, with sailors from 11 nations listed on the roster of its 36-member team.</p>
        <p>''The nationality rule he's speaking about is obviously mainly directed to Alinghi, so I guess that's the thank-you note for helping him get his team together,'' Bertarelli said, referring to Dalton.</p>
        <p>In 2004, when Dalton was unable to attract the sponsorship necessary to start a campaign, Bertarelli made contact with Dalton and eventually provided him with an unsecured multimillion-dollar loan.</p>
        <p>''I felt it was just right to have Team New Zealand in the Cup,'' Bertarelli said. ''They had been a big part of this event over the years.''</p>
        <p>In an interview Monday at Team New Zealand's base, Dalton said that the loan was essential. ''We wouldn't exist without it; there's no buts or maybes about that,'' he said. Dalton, who said the loan had been repaid, traveled to Switzerland to meet with Bertarelli in 2004 at Bertarelli's request.</p>
        <p>Despite comments earlier in the competition about his commitment to revising the nationality rule, Dalton was less definitive Monday. ''We will look at nationality, but we haven't made a final decision, compared to what everybody thinks we have,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Informed of Bertarelli's concerns, Dalton conceded that there were differences in their perspectives. ''You can probably assume we don't share exactly the same view on that, just based on where we come from,'' Dalton said of Bertarelli, a Swiss citizen who was born in Italy. ''But I'm no different from him in the respect that he has done an amazing job as the guardian, and I think he sees himself as the guardian of the tradition as well as the guardian of yachting's biggest prize.''</p>
        <p>He added that ''if we ever get close to that environment, we would take our responsibility very seriously.''</p>
        <p>If the New Zealanders win, they could choose to reinstate a strict nationality rule or require that a certain percentage of a team be made up of citizens of the challenging yacht club's country.</p>
        <p>Either rule would have made it difficult for a syndicate like China Team to take part in this year's Cup challenger series. China Team, a start-up that finished last in the series, was made up mostly of French sailors and officials from a former French syndicate.</p>
        <p>''I think it's important that the emerging countries like China, being just one example of potentially many, are allowed to flourish,'' Dalton said. ''It wouldn't be all that clever to just not help them. Part of being the guardian of the Cup is to promote the sport.''</p>
        <p>Although Team New Zealand has hired some outsiders, including Terry Hutchinson and Kevin Hall of the United States, 15 of the 17 sailors on the boat that won the challengers series are New Zealanders or have New Zealand passports. A significant majority of its shore team are also Kiwis.</p>
        <p>Dalton has emphasized the importance of national identity in developing a team strong enough to shake off its embarrassing performance in the last Cup. Alinghi won that competition, 5-0, with the help of the former New Zealand helmsman Russell Coutts and four other Kiwis.</p>
        <p>Those defections generated angst and animosity in New Zealand, sparking a campaign during the last Cup called ''Blackheart,'' which was directed at Coutts and his Kiwi crewmen; they had been based long enough in Switzerland to fulfill the former nationality requirements.</p>
        <p>Coutts has since left Alinghi, but Bertarelli expressed concern that the mood was turning uglier in Valencia.</p>
        <p>Asked for specifics, Bertarelli said the New Zealanders who were still on his crew had been subjected to insults from the New Zealand fans who had gathered in Valencia. ''The aggression toward our Kiwis, I mean it's seven years now,'' Bertarelli said. ''Let it be. Let it go.''</p>
        <p>The Cup is controlled by the winner, which selects the competition site. Bertarelli said he was undecided where the Cup would be staged if Alinghi were to win again. He said Valencia in 2009 was a possibility. He did not rule out Dubai, but said ''the intention is to race again in Europe.''</p>
        <p>SAILING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
