<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sole U.S. Company That Enriches Uranium Is Struggling to Stay in Business</title>
    <meta content="12nuke" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/business/12nuke.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853988"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Uranium</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Usec Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Welch, John K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Uranium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E4DA173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1130" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sole U.S. Company That Enriches Uranium Is Struggling to Stay in Business</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sole U.S. Company That Enriches Uranium Is Struggling to Stay in Business</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>USEC, sole American uranium enrichment company, is struggling to survive, while nuclear power experts worry that its failure would leave Russians dominant in market for fuel processing; USEC has liquidated some of its valuable uranium inventories to stay afloat, as its income has declined because of changing market conditions; it has also maintained high dividend, bought back stock and spent heavily on severance payments for executives; president John K Welch comments; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seventy years after the United States invented uranium enrichment, the sole American company in the business is struggling to survive, while nuclear power experts worry that its failure would leave the Russians dominant in the market for fuel processing.</p>
        <p>The company, USEC, has liquidated some of its valuable uranium inventories to stay afloat, as its income has declined because of changing market conditions. But it had also maintained a high dividend, bought back stock and spent heavily on severance payments after frequent purges in the executive suite. The company spent more than $100 million on two new technologies for enrichment before abandoning them and embarking on a third.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nuclear power experts worry that USEC’s failure would leave the Russians dominant in the market for fuel processing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Seventy years after the United States invented uranium enrichment, the sole American company in the business is struggling to survive, while nuclear power experts worry that its failure would leave the Russians dominant in the market for fuel processing.</p>
        <p>The company, USEC, has liquidated some of its valuable uranium inventories to stay afloat, as its income has declined because of changing market conditions. But it had also maintained a high dividend, bought back stock and spent heavily on severance payments after frequent purges in the executive suite. The company spent more than $100 million on two new technologies for enrichment before abandoning them and embarking on a third.</p>
        <p>''USEC has been a four-letter word in some circles,'' said its president, John K. Welch, who was hired in October 2005 to save the company. Though he has taken steps to strengthen the company, he said the problem now is to find a way to finance new technology and become competitive in the world market.</p>
        <p>Enrichment means sorting two types of uranium to raise the proportion of uranium 235, a step essential for use in American nuclear reactors. The government is promoting nuclear as a step toward energy independence.</p>
        <p>The United States invented the process and used it to build the bomb that destroyed Hiroshima in August 1945. Later, the United States offered enriched uranium to civil nuclear programs worldwide.</p>
        <p>In the 1990s, the government privatized its antiquated enrichment plants. USEC closed one, in Piketon, Ohio, and still runs the other, in Paducah, Ky.</p>
        <p>But the Paducah plant is a heavy user of costly electricity, which now amounts to more than 70 percent of USEC's costs. Centrifuges, which are used by almost all other enrichment plants, use only 5 percent of the electricity used by the Paducah plant.</p>
        <p>In February, USEC announced that the centrifuges it was developing would cost $2.3 billion, up from a previous estimate of $1.7 billion, and would take an extra year to deploy. The company has already spent about $400 million on the centrifuges and is looking for financing to complete the project, which it is trying to build in Piketon, Ohio.</p>
        <p>''Most people expect that $2.3 billion is going to go up,'' said Paul R. Clegg, a stock analyst at Natexis Bleichroeder Inc.</p>
        <p>The company has been involved in merger talks with several companies in the nuclear business, and the trade press has carried reports of other negotiations. But two people with knowledge of the talks said that they did not appear to be leading anywhere.</p>
        <p>In addition to USEC's Paducah plant and its planned centrifuge project, a European consortium is building a centrifuge plant in Hobbs, N.M., that it calls the National Enrichment Facility, and General Electric is trying to make an Australian enrichment technology called Silex commercially feasible.</p>
        <p>Despite the challenges, and the fact that Mr. Welch eliminated the dividend, the stock price is strong. Market analysts say one reason is that the price of virgin uranium is so high that customers are demanding more enrichment work, thus driving up the price of the service that USEC provides. Some investors also see the company as a takeover target, or a likely beneficiary of government help.</p>
        <p>USEC would like to acquire uranium from the Energy Department on favorable terms, to help provide funds for its centrifuge project. But the Energy Department appears to want a signal from Congress, and the company faces questions there about its previous performance, and about the wisdom of bailing out its stockholders.</p>
        <p>The government still owns the Paducah plant, and could take it over and give it to a contractor to run. Or it could allow USEC to operate in bankruptcy, although that would probably eliminate the company's ability to build a more modern plant.</p>
        <p>The assistant secretary of energy for nuclear energy, Dennis R. Spurgeon, was USEC's executive vice president and chief operating officer until he left in 2003, receiving a payment of more than $5 million, according to Securities and Exchange Commission filings. Mr. Spurgeon, through a spokesman, declined repeated requests for an interview.</p>
        <p>According to people close to the company, Mr. Spurgeon had clashed with the chief executive, William H. Timbers, as had other top officials. Mr. Timbers left the company in December 2004, after disagreements with the board. In February 2006, USEC agreed to pay him $14.5 million, according to S.E.C. filings.</p>
        <p>Some Democrats in Congress are demanding a full explanation of the departures of Mr. Timbers and others before they proceed with a discussion about how to help the company.</p>
        <p>USEC has other problems as well. It also takes in enriched uranium from Russia, left over from Russia's nuclear weapons program, under a program called Megatons to Megawatts. USEC dilutes the material to reactor grade under an agreement in operation since the early 1990s.</p>
        <p>Half of the enrichment that the company sells is done under the terms of that agreement, which were locked in years ago, and it provides a substantial profit to USEC. But the agreement ends in 2013, after which the Russian nuclear enterprise, Rosatom, wants to deal directly with the nuclear utilities. Those utilities would like to do the same.</p>
        <p>Another potential problem for USEC is that a near-total ban on Russian imports beyond those allowed in the Megatons to Megawatts program may be coming to an end.</p>
        <p>The ban dates from a trade case brought by American uranium companies against the Soviet Union. The companies won a ruling that the Soviets were dumping production in this country below cost. As a result, the United States threatened a tariff of more than 100 percent, and reached an agreement that limited the imports allowed under the Megatons to Megawatts program.</p>
        <p>But last month, a similar ruling against a French producer was overturned by the Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit. The court ruled that enrichment was a service, not a product, and thus not subject to import quotas.</p>
        <p>Russian and American officials said that the court decision put pressure on the American side to conclude a deal more favorable to the Russians.</p>
        <p>Russia has vast inventories of enriched uranium and a huge ability to enrich more, according to trade experts. The prospect alarms some on Capitol Hill, who believe that the United States must maintain the ability to enrich uranium.</p>
        <p>The prospect is that without USEC, the United States will rely on others not only for the uranium ore, but also for most of the work needed to convert it into fuel.</p>
        <p>''We import two-thirds of our oil, but 90 percent of our uranium,'' said Jack Edlow, a Washington businessman who deals in uranium and who pointed out that the reliance was for both raw ore and for enrichment. ''I can't say 'energy independence' with a straight face.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
