<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>That Nice Midwestern Mom, the One Who's Handy With a Knife</title>
    <meta content="12seco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/theater/reviews/12seco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853922"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zinoman, Jason</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wegrzyn, Marisa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ivey, Judith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rupp, Debra Jo</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Butcher of Baraboo, The (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Second Stage Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Marsh, Ali</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ivey, Judith</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Butcher of Baraboo, The (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E6DB173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>That Nice Midwestern Mom, the One Who's Handy With a Knife</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">That Nice Midwestern Mom, the One Who’s Handy With a Knife</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON ZINOMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinoman, Jason</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jason Zinoman reviews Marisa Wegrzyn play The Butcher of Baraboo, directed by Judith Ivey; Debra Jo Rupp stars; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's not a good sign when the most exciting moments in a play have to do with cutlery. Center stage in ''The Butcher of Baraboo,'' which incidentally is not about a theater critic in Wisconsin, is a humongous meat cleaver, so ominously prominent in this gothic comedy that at one point it even gets its own spotlight.</p>
        <p>''Baraboo'' is the kind of play in which every character at some point confesses a dramatic secret, and part of the fun is trying to guess what it will be. The playwright, Marisa Wegrzyn, strenuously hints that Valerie (Debra Jo Rupp), a kindly Midwestern mother and owner of very sharp knives, killed her husband, who has mysteriously disappeared. She has an odd habit of swinging deadly kitchen utensils around the room, forcefully enough to make you duck in your seat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It’s not a good sign when the most exciting moments in a play have to do with cutlery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's not a good sign when the most exciting moments in a play have to do with cutlery. Center stage in ''The Butcher of Baraboo,'' which incidentally is not about a theater critic in Wisconsin, is a humongous meat cleaver, so ominously prominent in this gothic comedy that at one point it even gets its own spotlight.</p>
        <p>''Baraboo'' is the kind of play in which every character at some point confesses a dramatic secret, and part of the fun is trying to guess what it will be. The playwright, Marisa Wegrzyn, strenuously hints that Valerie (Debra Jo Rupp), a kindly Midwestern mother and owner of very sharp knives, killed her husband, who has mysteriously disappeared. She has an odd habit of swinging deadly kitchen utensils around the room, forcefully enough to make you duck in your seat.</p>
        <p>To be fair, Valerie is a butcher -- a real one, of meat -- but how to explain the frequency with which she says things like ''sometimes I could kill her'' or blurts threats about throwing acid in the face of her sister-in-law, Gail (Welker White)? Aren't Midwesterners supposed to be nice?</p>
        <p>This joke -- average mom moonlighting as bloodthirsty killer -- grows old quickly, and anyone who has seen a few mysteries should be able to detect misdirection when they see it. But if Valerie didn't kill her husband, who did?</p>
        <p>The other suspects include her gloomy daughter, Midge (Ashlie Atkinson); the oh-so-innocent next-door neighbors (Michael Countryman, Ali Marsh); and Gail, a policewoman who is convinced that Valerie did it.</p>
        <p>Frankly, they all seem suspicious, but that may be because they don't resemble any actual human. Instead they perform increasingly absurd and cruel acts that seem motivated more by the dictates of theatrical structure (you have to put a cliffhanger at the end of Act I) than by plausible psychology.</p>
        <p>That would all be fine if the director, Judith Ivey, a Tony-winning actor, had settled on an appropriately light tone for this production, from Second Stage Theater Uptown. It's a ridiculous play, but Ms. Ivey doesn't seem to realize it. She plays it thuddingly straight, while her actors fly off in all directions. Ms. White shrieks her way through her part, while Ms. Rupp's smilingly modest performance feels as if it should be in a totally different play.</p>
        <p>But the most poignant case has to be that of Ms. Atkinson, the performer who brought such vulnerability and depth to her role as the overweight girlfriend in Neil LaBute's ''Fat Pig.'' Here she struggles vainly to make sense of her character, a pharmacist with a predatory streak, only to be upstaged by a very big knife.</p>
        <p>''The Butcher of Baraboo'' continues through June 30 at the McGinn/Cazale Theater, 2162 Broadway, at 76th Street; (212) 246-4422.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
