<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>She Calls It 'Phenomena.' Everyone Else Calls It Art.</title>
    <meta content="12frankel" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/science/12frankel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853896"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cameras</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Nanotechnology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nanotechnology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cameras</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Frankel, Felice</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3DC173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1297" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>She Calls It 'Phenomena.' Everyone Else Calls It Art.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">She Calls It ‘Phenomena.’ Everyone Else Calls It Art.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CORNELIA DEAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When people call Felice Frankel an artist, she winces.</p>
        <p>In the first place, the photographs she makes don't sell. She knows this, she says, because after she received a Guggenheim grant in 1995, she started taking her work to galleries. ''Nobody wanted to bother looking,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The science photographs of Felice Frankel turn phenomena like water repellance, nanotechnology and magnetism into art.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When people call Felice Frankel an artist, she winces.</p>
        <p>In the first place, the photographs she makes don't sell. She knows this, she says, because after she received a Guggenheim grant in 1995, she started taking her work to galleries. ''Nobody wanted to bother looking,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In the second place, her images are not full of emotion or ideology or any other kind of message. As she says, ''My stuff is about phenomena.''</p>
        <p>Phenomena like magnetism or the behavior of water molecules or how colonies of bacteria grow -- phenomena of nature. ''So I don't call it art,'' Ms. Frankel said. ''When it's art, it's more about the creator, not necessarily the concept in the image.''</p>
        <p>As first an artist in residence and now a research scientist at M.I.T., and now also a senior research fellow at the Institute for Innovative Computing at Harvard, she helps researchers use cameras, microscopes and other tools to display the beauty of science.</p>
        <p>With her help, scientists have turned dull images of things like yeast in a dish or the surface of a CD into photographs so striking that they appear often on covers of scientific journals and magazines. According to George M. Whitesides, a Harvard chemist and her longtime collaborator, ''She has transformed the visual face of science.''</p>
        <p>One of her photographs, a vivid image of an iron-rich fluid under the influence of magnets (center right photo), has been so widely reproduced that she is ''sick of it,'' Ms. Frankel said.</p>
        <p>Her crucial step in making it was typical. She slipped a yellow Post-It note under the slide holding the fluid. In her view, the move did not materially alter the laboratory conditions, but it snapped the image of the fluid into such arresting focus that the National Science Foundation made a poster out of it.</p>
        <p>In her book, ''Envisioning Science'' (M.I.T. Press, 2002), Ms. Frankel instructed researchers, in words and many pictures, in the kind of visual depiction of scientific processes and subjects she and Dr. Whitesides produced in an earlier book, ''On the Surface of Things,'' (Harvard University Press, 1997). Now they are finishing a book about ''small things,'' as Dr. Whitesides put it, things at the limit of what can be seen with light, even through the microscope.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Ms. Frankel has been organizing conferences around the country on ''Image and Meaning,'' and working to establish a program sponsored by the National Science Foundation on the uses of visual imagery in teaching science.</p>
        <p>With colleagues, she is working to set up an online site where researchers can talk across disciplines about the concepts they want to convey in images.</p>
        <p>But she does not feel that her photographs have to explain everything. ''To me the idea is to engage somebody to look at something, and they don't even know it's science,'' she said. ''People are not intimidated by pictures. It permits them to ask questions.''</p>
        <p>To achieve this goal, she sometimes alters the images. For example, when she photographed bacteria growing on agar, ''the agar was cracking,'' she said. ''But I wanted the reader to pay attention to the bacteria pattern. So I digitally deleted the cracks.''</p>
        <p>Another time, she photographed rod-shaped orange bacteria, and her film was somehow unable to reproduce the orange she could see when she looked through the microscope. ''I added it,'' she recalled.</p>
        <p>These practices are acceptable, she said, because their purpose is not to disguise or twist scientific information, but to make it clearer. And when images like this appear in scientific journals, Dr. Whitesides said, the ''untinkered original'' is posted online with supplementary material.</p>
        <p>For Ms. Frankel, the main point is that ''I always tell the reader what I do when I manipulate an image.'' And she negotiates with her research colleagues about how to go.</p>
        <p>''I think this should be part of every scientist's education, the manipulation and enhancement of images,'' Ms. Frankel said. ''To just have a blanket statement -- 'You cannot do anything to your image' -- that does not make sense.''</p>
        <p>''You can get a little crazy with objectivity. If enhancing your image gets you to see something better,'' it's acceptable, she said, ''as long as we indicate what we are doing.''</p>
        <p>That's what publications like Scientific American do when they use her work -- they inform readers that the image in question has been altered, and how, said Mariette DiChristina, its executive editor.</p>
        <p>But journal editors often have another issue with her. As Ms. DiChristina put it, if she gets a suggestion she does not like, ''she has been known to balk forcefully.''</p>
        <p>In the end, Dr. Whitesides said, ''what comes out of it is a result one can be very happy with.''</p>
        <p>For Ms. Frankel, 62, this work is a return to a major interest of her youth, when she studied science and aspired to a career as a chemist. Born Felice Oringel in Brooklyn, she attended Midwood High School and Brooklyn College, where she majored in biology. After graduation, she worked in a cancer research lab at Columbia. ''Science has always been in my soul,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But life intervened. She married Kenneth Frankel. He was sent to Vietnam. When he returned, they moved to western Massachusetts, where he worked as a chest surgeon and they raised two sons.</p>
        <p>But when Dr. Frankel returned from Vietnam, he brought a gift. ''It was a very good camera,'' Ms. Frankel said. ''And that's not trivial, that it was good.''</p>
        <p>She started taking photographs. ''Probably I was good,'' she said, but because the camera was good, too.</p>
        <p>''Technically, it worked,'' she said. ''So I was reinforced to continue taking pictures,'' first as a volunteer at a public television station and then for an architect.</p>
        <p>''I had a knack for it,'' she said. ''I didn't like taking pictures of people that much, because you are too dependent on them to make a good picture. With architecture, you have to rely on your own sense of composition.''</p>
        <p>Soon she began landscape photography, producing magazine photographs and, eventually, a book, ''Modern Landscape Architecture: Redefining the Garden'' (Abbeville Press, 1991). Then she landed a dream assignment, to travel the country photographing landscapes. It was a disaster.</p>
        <p>''They wanted the Technicolor blue sky, the hot pinks, which was not what landscape was to me,'' she said. ''I took pictures of rain so you could see the sensuality of the design.''</p>
        <p>She realized that she was, as she put it, ''in the wrong spot,'' and applied for a Loeb fellowship at the Harvard Graduate School of Design, where she spent the academic year of 1991-2 sitting in on university courses. ''I lived at the Science Center, because I was hungry to get back into science,'' she said.</p>
        <p>One day, someone recommended a course in molecular biology, ''and the fellow presenting the work was a terrific lecturer and very obviously visual in the way he presented the work,'' she said. She introduced herself, and he invited her to his lab.</p>
        <p>The professor was Dr. Whitesides. ''We started talking about how one represented science on the blackboard,'' he recalled, ''and at some point she made the remark that she thought we did it badly and I said, 'Well, you show us how to do it better,' and we were off and running.''</p>
        <p>One of the first photographs she made in his lab, water droplets arrayed on a slide with a water-repellent grid (bottom photo), ended up on the cover of the journal Science.</p>
        <p>Since then, Dr. Whitesides said, ''her impact on scientific communication has been very large, in the way science talks to science and science talks to the world outside science.''</p>
        <p>Beyond that, he added: ''She has a wonderful sense of design and color. It is hard to say she is not an artist.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
