<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Campaigning as Trailblazer, By Proxy and Association</title>
    <meta content="12web" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/us/politics/12web.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854038"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICAL MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E1D9173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Campaigning as Trailblazer, By Proxy and Association</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Campaigning as Trailblazer, by Proxy and Association</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK HEALY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Healy, Patrick</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton is not much of a gambler, in politics or life: She refers to herself as part of the ''sensible center'' in the Senate, and only occasionally has she laid money on the table (blackjack is her game).</p>
        <p>Yet, it would have been easy to imagine her betting on Rags to Riches in the Belmont Stakes on Saturday, had she been inclined to wager.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton tends to note the history-making nature of her candidacy in just a couple of sentences on the campaign trail.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton is not much of a gambler, in politics or life: She refers to herself as part of the ''sensible center'' in the Senate, and only occasionally has she laid money on the table (blackjack is her game).</p>
        <p>Yet, it would have been easy to imagine her betting on Rags to Riches in the Belmont Stakes on Saturday, had she been inclined to wager.</p>
        <p>Rags to Riches was the filly in the field, and lo and behold, she won the 139th running of the race, the first time a girl beat the boys in 102 years.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton, who was in Detroit and Iowa on Saturday rather than at the track, tends to note the history-making nature of her candidacy in just a couple of sentences on the campaign trail, instead of laying it on thick.</p>
        <p>Indeed, given that her race is far longer than the one run by Rags to Riches, with the primary season still seven months away, Mrs. Clinton has been trying to find subtler ways to cast herself as a trailblazer. Lately, it has been to embrace and celebrate other people who have worked to get close to the winner's circle.</p>
        <p>Some of these people -- often women -- are, in fact, role models who can do the talking for Mrs. Clinton. At a Women for Hillary breakfast on June 4, one of the hosts, Michelle Paige Paterson, the wife of New York's first black lieutenant governor, drew a nod from Mrs. Clinton with this life lesson: ''Never let any individualist man or chauvinistic institution get in your way.'' And another host, the tennis trailblazer Billie Jean King, declared Mrs. Clinton ''a winner'' and added, ''This is the century for women.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton herself then told the story of Lilly M. Ledbetter, the lone female supervisor at a tire plant in Alabama, who lost a landmark pay discrimination suit before the United States Supreme Court on May 29. Mrs. Clinton also hailed ''our wonderful New Yorker'' Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg, for reading her dissent from the bench in that case, which was decided in a 5-to-4 ruling.</p>
        <p>''It's important to remember that for many of us, the battles of the Billie Jean Kings, the struggles for equality, the opportunity to fulfill our own God-given potential, seem like something of the past, don't they?'' Mrs. Clinton said. ''And yet I think about Lilly Ledbetter, and I think about all the women I know in New York City, and all the women I know around the country, who are doing the very best they can, often with very little support or recognition.''</p>
        <p>''It is time for us all to say, once and for all, that there are no barriers or boundaries in America,'' she added.</p>
        <p>Two days later, Mrs. Clinton attended one of her campaign fund-raisers and basked in the praise of Senator Barbara A. Mikulski of Maryland, the first female Democrat to be elected to the Senate in her own right, and Katharine McPhee, the runner-up on ''American Idol'' in 2006.</p>
        <p>Celebrities are not the only proxies. At Hostos Community College in the Bronx on Friday, Mrs. Clinton also hailed the working-class Hispanics who made up most of her audience. And she sought to associate her candidacy with those women and men who were aspiring to their own version of a winner's circle, the American middle class, as she discussed the compromise immigration bill in the Senate.</p>
        <p>And on Saturday, as Rags to Riches was preparing for her own race, Mrs. Clinton attended an A.F.L.-C.I.O. forum in Detroit, where she cast herself as an ally of blue-collar workers. Her advisers believe that her agenda and message will particularly resonate with this group.</p>
        <p>''A lot of hard-working people in this country have been invisible to this administration,'' said Mrs. Clinton, according to a story in The Detroit News. ''You won't be invisible to the next president of the United States.''</p>
        <p>The invisibility metaphor debuted as a fixture in her stump speech in New Hampshire in early March, and since then she has used it to cast herself as a barrier-breaker who would take other people over the barrier, too.</p>
        <p>Representing the interests of blacks, women, Hispanics and blue-collar workers is not a trailblazing idea. But her advisers said that if Mrs. Clinton was going to be a history-making candidate, she could not be seen as selfishly making history for herself, but rather for the interests of people who had not always been winners in the annals of history.</p>
        <p>POLITICAL MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
