<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When School Is Out, Getting Good Food In</title>
    <meta content="12brod" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health&amp;Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/health/nutrition/12brod.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL HEALTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/Personal Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Fitness and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Obesity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Obesity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Obesity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Ending the Food Fight (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="online_producer">ABCs of Fruits and Vegetables and Beyond, The (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Sneaky Chef: Simple Strategies for Hiding Healthy Foods in Kids Favorite Meals, The (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E7D9173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1196" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When School Is Out, Getting Good Food In</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When School Is Out, Getting Good Food In</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jane E. Brody</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>No one can dispute that American children are fatter than ever. Much of the blame has been placed on schools -- lunch programs high in calories, snack and soda machines in the schools and curtailed or absent physical activities during the school day.</p>
        <p>Although schools are hardly off the hook, a study published in April in The American Journal of Public Health, which tracked the physical condition of 5,000 children as they passed through kindergarten and first grade, found that the biggest gains in body mass index occurred in the summer when parents had sole responsibility for their children's diets and exercise opportunities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Summer is an ideal time to start children on a wholesome nutritional track and to encourage enjoyable physical activities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>No one can dispute that American children are fatter than ever. Much of the blame has been placed on schools -- lunch programs high in calories, snack and soda machines in the schools and curtailed or absent physical activities during the school day.</p>
        <p>Although schools are hardly off the hook, a study published in April in The American Journal of Public Health, which tracked the physical condition of 5,000 children as they passed through kindergarten and first grade, found that the biggest gains in body mass index occurred in the summer when parents had sole responsibility for their children's diets and exercise opportunities.</p>
        <p>Summer is also an opportunity, an ideal time to start children on a wholesome nutritional track and to encourage enjoyable physical activities, some of which can be pursued even after school resumes next fall.</p>
        <p>Promoting Produce</p>
        <p>A simple and beautifully illustrated new book by Steve Charney and David Goldbeck, ''The ABCs of Fruits and Vegetables and Beyond,'' is one good way to interest youngsters in these most nutritious foods, which are readily available, and tastier, in the summer. Part 1 is a series of easy-reader alphabet poems about common and uncommon produce, from apples to zucchini and including (wild) xemenia for the ''X'' page.</p>
        <p>Part 2 offers a host of enticing food facts, recipes and fun. A simple summer dinner might be zucchini with linguini, a recipe that includes scallions, sweet red pepper, tomatoes, fresh basil and parsley, and, of course, zucchini. Or you could bake Z's Mystery Cake, with whole-wheat flour, low-fat yogurt, chocolate chips and shredded zucchini.</p>
        <p>The goal is to familiarize children with foods that are good for them. In many cases, children can help with the preparation, which often encourages them to taste, if not fully consume, something new and different. With yard space, you might even try growing some of these foods. A friend who has done just that with the help of her very young daughters had no trouble getting them to eat all kinds of vegetables, even before they were cooked.</p>
        <p>Another recently published aid for those parents who have had a hard time introducing their children to wholesome foods is ''The Sneaky Chef: Simple Strategies for Hiding Healthy Foods in Kids' Favorite Meals'' by Missy Chase Lapine. The book includes simple make-ahead purées or clever replacements that can greatly improve the way children eat -- not to mention the rest of the family.</p>
        <p>Of course, unlike the ABC book, ''The Sneaky Chef'' does not introduce children to the wonderful foods that can help them grow up healthy and strong. But it is a way to get them to eat many of these foods, through recipes like spaghetti and meatballs with eight hidden vegetables, cauliflower masked in mac and cheese, and blueberries hidden in cupcakes.</p>
        <p>I confess to using this technique with my own children decades ago. I made muffins and quick breads with puréed and shredded fruits and vegetables. I puréed vegetables in soup broth and left visible only the vegetables I knew they would eat. I shredded vegetables into meatloaf and pasta sauces, and I made blender drinks with a variety of fruits.</p>
        <p>Feeding for a Healthy Weight</p>
        <p>There are three factors to consider when trying to encourage children to eat enough of the good foods and not too much of those snacks and treats that tend to pile on the pounds without providing much in the way of nutrition.</p>
        <p>Factor 1: Don't make an issue of it. Children who are repeatedly told that they cannot eat this or that tend to want those foods in preference to others. A child in my neighborhood whose parents forbid him to eat candy secretly stockpiled it in a friend's house and ate it there. It would have been better to give him a ''candy allowance,'' say a piece of chocolate once a day or a candy bar once a week. Now that we know that dark chocolate may actually be healthful, there is even a good choice.</p>
        <p>Ice cream, too, can be a reasonable treat, especially in the hot summer. But select the reduced-fat brands or frozen yogurt. Check the label for calories per serving -- it should not exceed 150 -- and keep in mind that a serving is half a cup.</p>
        <p>Frozen-fruit ices, which have no fat, are another good choice in hot weather. I worry far less about the sugar content than the amount of fat in a frozen dessert. Or consider making your own fruit ices with your child's help. It's easy, and you can buy popsicle molds and sticks to help matters along.</p>
        <p>Drinks, too, can be a source of pointless calories. Stick to pure fruit juices, water and low-fat or nonfat milk. Avoid fruitlike beverages labeled ''drink,'' because that means most of it is sugar water, not fruit juice. And there is simply no justification for giving children sodas, with or without real sugar. This is a habit best not started in childhood.</p>
        <p>Factor 2: While you should not flatly forbid anything (unless the child is allergic to it), do not keep items like chips, candy, packaged cookies, doughnuts, cakes and sodas in the house if you do not want the children to consume them regularly. If they are not readily available, they will be consumed much less often. I always kept a bowl of fresh fruit on the table and a fruit salad in the refrigerator, and the children could serve themselves.</p>
        <p>Also, rethink the use of sugared cereals. Use them as a garnish on more nutritious and minimally sweetened whole-grain cereals, if at all. My sons grew up eating Wheaties and Cheerios with a sprinkling of granola. Add raisins or sliced banana or blueberries for sweetness. Even slivers of fresh pineapple are a delicious addition to cold cereal.</p>
        <p>Factor 3: When children say they have had enough, don't wheedle and cajole and bribe them into eating more. Children have to learn to recognize their natural satiety and hunger signals, eating when hungry and stopping when satisfied. For those with tiny stomachs, serve very small portions and feed them more often. Don't let them fill up with drinks before they have eaten solid food. For children who tend to overeat, use a smaller dish, serve from the kitchen instead of family style at the table, and dish up reasonable portions. Serve foods that are slow to eat, like shrimp with the shell on, and foods low in caloric density, like salads.</p>
        <p>If a child already has a weight problem, another new book can be helpful, ''Ending the Food Fight'' by Dr. David Ludwig, who directs the Optimal Weight for Life Program at Children's Hospital in Boston. The book spells out a nine-week program (just right for summer break) that focuses on a different weight-related theme each week. It starts with a ''clean sweep'' to get junk out of the house, moves on to breakfast, lunch, dinner, snacks, hunger, dessert, eating out and celebrations, and includes ways to introduce more physical activity into a child's life without having to ''exercise.''</p>
        <p>Next week: Another part of a healthy summer for children is keeping them well protected against sunburn.</p>
        <p>PERSONAL HEALTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
