<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blackstone Founders Due Billions</title>
    <meta content="12blackstone" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/business/12blackstone.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854013"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Blackstone Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwarzman, Stephen A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peterson, Peter G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Jenny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Wall Street (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Blackstone Group</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Fortress Investment Llc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Schwarzman, Stephen A</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Peterson, Peter G</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E6D9173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blackstone Founders Due Billions</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Blackstone Founders Prepare to Count Their Billions</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNY ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Jenny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen A Schwarzman and Peter G Peterson, founders of Blackstone Group that is planning to go public, will receive billions of dollars in offering; Schwarzman will cash out maximum of $677.2 million, and his remaining 24 percent stake in Blackstone will be worth $7.7 billion if shares are offered at $30; Peterson will put his $1.9 billion payoff into charitable trust, but will still control 4 percent of company, worth about $1.3 billion (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Meet Wall Street's soon-to-be $8 billion man, Stephen A. Schwarzman, and his $3 billion partner, Peter G. Peterson.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwarzman, 60, and Mr. Peterson, 81, started the Blackstone Group, the equity firm that is planning to go public, with $400,000 in 1985. Yesterday, the firm updated its prospectus and included the information everyone on Wall Street has been waiting for: how much money the principals will make in the offering.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The giant private equity firm, founded by Stephen Schwarzman and Peter Peterson, is expected to go public in the next few weeks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Meet Wall Street's soon-to-be $8 billion man, Stephen A. Schwarzman, and his $3 billion partner, Peter G. Peterson.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwarzman, 60, and Mr. Peterson, 81, started the Blackstone Group, the equity firm that is planning to go public, with $400,000 in 1985. Yesterday, the firm updated its prospectus and included the information everyone on Wall Street has been waiting for: how much money the principals will make in the offering.</p>
        <p>The numbers did not disappoint.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwarzman will cash out a maximum of $677.2 million from the offering, and his remaining 24 percent stake in Blackstone will be worth $7.7 billion if the shares are offered at $30, the midpoint of the range of $29 to $31 the company has cited (if they trade up, he and others will be worth even more). He earned $398.3 million last year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Peterson will put his $1.9 billion payoff into a charitable trust, but will still control 4 percent of the company, worth about $1.3 billion. He earned $212.9 million last year.</p>
        <p>Blackstone plans to sell 133.3 million shares in the offering, which could come late next week. At the midpoint, the firm would raise $3.8 billion after underwriting costs. Underwriters are expected to sell the overallotment of 20 million shares because of the high demand. In addition, the Chinese State Investment Company will pay $3 billion for a nonvoting stake.</p>
        <p>Other executives listed in the filing include Hamilton E. James, the firm's president, who will get a maximum of $188.5 million and own 4.9 percent; J. Tomilson Hill, who runs the hedge fund business and who will make $22.1 million and own 1.6 percent; and Michael A. Puglisi, the chief financial officer, who will make $13.4 million and own 0.7 percent. Mr. James made $97.3 million last year, Mr. Hill $22.1 million and Mr. Puglisi $17.4 million.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Blackstone, John Ford, declined to comment.</p>
        <p>The value of the ownership stakes are predicated on Blackstone's ability to meet the market's expectations for growth, which could be difficult considering that a number of extraordinary forces have contributed to the recent buyout boom, including strong global growth and widely available cheap debt.</p>
        <p>''Everyone knows this is a cyclical business and that these returns are not going to be sustained and that a downturn is coming,'' said Colin C. Blaydon, director of the Tuck Center for Private Equity, an academic research group. ''Everyone knows that but no one knows when.''</p>
        <p>According to the filing, the Blackstone Group, which has 770 employees and manages $88.4 billion in private equity funds and hedge funds, will have a market capitalization of about $32.4 billion. In contrast, the investment bank Lehman Brothers, which has more than 27,000 employees and a far more diversified business, is worth about $40 billion (Lehman is one of the underwriters).</p>
        <p>Blackstone's planned initial offering is seeking to capitalize on a tidal wave of demand from pension funds, foundations and endowments and wealthy individuals who are looking for alternative assets, specifically private equity, hedge funds and real estate funds.</p>
        <p>Blackstone announced that it was going public in March and is one of the biggest players in private equity, along with Kohlberg Kravis Roberts and Goldman Sachs, which all raised $20 billion funds recently.</p>
        <p>As firms like Blackstone and Kohlberg Kravis Roberts have raised larger funds and skyrocketed in size, so, too, have the fees that the private equity managers earn. Typically private equity funds make 2 percent of the assets they manage in a management fee and then take 20 percent of the profits, or ''carry.'' In 2006, Blackstone earned $2.3 billion, up 77 percent from the previous year.</p>
        <p>Blackstone's decision to go public follows that of the Fortress Investment Group, a diversified alternative asset manager that went public in February at $18.50. The stock closed at $31 on its first day of trading and generated widespread interest among hedge fund and private equity firms contemplating a similar move. It closed at $25.73 yesterday.</p>
        <p>In some ways, there is a certain oddity to private equity firms' going public since their business model is predicated on taking companies private in an effort to recognize value. Many private equity managers, in sync with corporate chief executives, have argued that being a public company in the United States comes with too much regulation, especially from the Sarbanes-Oxley Act, the corporate governance law that was passed in 2002.</p>
        <p>Of course, when market conditions are ripe, private equity firms make their money taking the private companies public again. Now, on top of the fact that they seek public markets for their portfolio companies, they, too, are seeking value -- and a lot of it -- in the public markets.</p>
        <p>Owning shares in an equity firm is not without risk. One is the matter of whether the buyout boom can continue. Another is whether Congress will continue to allow carry fees to be taxed at the 15 percent capital gains rates rather than higher ordinary income tax rates of 35 percent. Congress has undertaken a study to examine the issue and if it acts, the impact would be significant.</p>
        <p>In 2006, there was $3.9 trillion worth of mergers and acquisitions, with buyouts constituting 19 percent or $745 billion worth of the total volume. Through June 8, there have been $500 billion worth of buyouts, or 20 percent of the $2.5 trillion worth of deals, according to Dealogic, a data provider. (For the first five months of 2006, there was $1.6 trillion worth of deals, with $27 billion, or 14 percent of that, coming from buyouts.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
