<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>9 Die in Fierce Palestinian Factional Fighting</title>
    <meta content="12mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/world/middleeast/12mideast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854008"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza Strip</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Egypt</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hamas</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fatah</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershner, Isabel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">El-Khodary, Taghreed</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haniya, Ismail (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jediyan, Jamal Abu al-</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Gaza Strip</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E7D9173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="879" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>9 Die in Fierce Palestinian Factional Fighting</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">9 Die in Fierce Palestinian Factional Fighting</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ISABEL KERSHNER and TAGHREED EL-KHODARY; Isabel Kershner reported from Jerusalem, and Taghreed El-Khodary from Gaza City.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershner, Isabel; El-Khodary, Taghreed</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, June 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Palestinians engage in worst factional fighting in month, with gunmen reportedly firing at home and office of Prime Min Ismail Haniya of Hamas, and violence elsewhere in Gaza leaving at least nine dead; Hamas militants kill most senior Fatah official in northern Gaza, Jamal Abu al-Jediyan; short-lived cease-fire was brokered by Egyptian security delegation stationed in Gaza; bitter power struggle between Hamas and Fatah, which together sit in unity government, has claimed lives of hundreds of Palestinians since Hamas won parliamentary elections 18 months ago; Hamas and Fatah accuse each other of starting latest round of violence (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The worst factional fighting in nearly a month raged among Palestinians on Monday, with gunmen reportedly firing at the prime minister's home and office and violence elsewhere in Gaza leaving at least nine dead.</p>
        <p>The death toll made Monday the bloodiest day since a fierce two-week bout of internal violence ended in mid-May. The fighting erupted despite a cease-fire that was supposed to come into force on Monday morning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The worst factional fighting in nearly a month raged among Palestinians in Gaza, with gunmen reportedly firing at the prime minister’s home and office.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The worst factional fighting in nearly a month raged among Palestinians on Monday, with gunmen reportedly firing at the prime minister's home and office and violence elsewhere in Gaza leaving at least nine dead.</p>
        <p>The death toll made Monday the bloodiest day since a fierce two-week bout of internal violence ended in mid-May. The fighting erupted despite a cease-fire that was supposed to come into force on Monday morning.</p>
        <p>Hamas militants killed Jamal Abu al-Jediyan, the most senior Fatah official in northern Gaza, after attacking his house in Beit Lahiya on Monday afternoon. He was ''executed with 40 gunshots,'' said a Fatah spokesman, Maher Miqdad. Mr. Jediyan's brother was also reported to have been killed.</p>
        <p>Four Fatah loyalists and a member of the Executive Force, a Hamas police militia, were killed in clashes around the hospital in the northern Gaza town of Beit Hanoun, according to Dr. Muawiya Hassanein, head of the medical emergency service in Gaza. And in Gaza City, a member of Hamas and a Fatah intelligence officer were killed, Dr. Hassanein said.</p>
        <p>The office of the prime minister, Ismail Haniya of Hamas, came under fire in Gaza City while a cabinet session was under way and after the cease-fire was supposed to be in effect. Nobody was wounded in the attack or during the firing before dawn on Mr. Haniya's house in the Shati refugee camp, which was reported by news agencies. Gunmen also fired during the day at the Ministry of Culture and Sports, but no one was hurt there either.</p>
        <p>The short-lived cease-fire, the latest of many in recent months, was brokered by the Egyptian security delegation stationed in Gaza and came after a bloody 24 hours in which at least three Palestinians were killed. Both factions had agreed to withdraw their gunmen from the streets in order to allow thousands of high school students to begin their matriculation examinations.</p>
        <p>The Palestinian president, Mahmoud Abbas of Fatah, and Mr. Haniya had called on the gunmen to leave the streets to allow the exams to go ahead. Hamas and Fatah sit together in a unity government but are engaged in a bitter power struggle that has claimed the lives of hundreds of Palestinians since Hamas won parliamentary elections 18 months ago.</p>
        <p>A statement issued Monday by Hamas detailing the killing of two of its loyalists on Sunday, for which it blamed Fatah, appeared indicative of the continuing mood of hostility.</p>
        <p>''Nothing can work with such killers,'' the statement said, ''no agreements and no promises.'' Given that the Palestinian justice system is in ''deep sleep,'' it added, ''the only option that remains is to punish the criminals and the murderers.''</p>
        <p>Hamas and Fatah accused each other of starting the latest round of violence, and the Egyptian mediators said it was difficult to determine who was to blame. The deaths on Sunday were marked by their brutality, with two Palestinians thrown from the roofs of high-rise buildings in Gaza City. One was an officer of the Presidential Guard, loyal to Fatah, and the other a member of the Executive Force, which was set up by Hamas to counter the official, Fatah-dominated security services.</p>
        <p>Also on Sunday, a preacher from a Gaza mosque, Muhammad Rifati, was abducted and killed.</p>
        <p>Intense shooting continued through the night into Monday.</p>
        <p>Abeer Saqa, 40, a mother of six, cried while describing her fear as her daughter Rola, 18, left for school in the morning. ''I was about to go with her and wait until she finished the exam, but I couldn't leave the other children alone,'' Mrs. Saqa said. Instead, Rola asked for her brother to walk her to school.</p>
        <p>According to Mrs. Saqa, both Fatah and Hamas have lost popularity because of the infighting. ''Parents sacrifice all these years for their kids to complete their high schools,'' she said. ''We invest all we have for them. This isn't just.''</p>
        <p>The Saqa family lives between two tall buildings. Fatah has taken up position in one, and Hamas in the other. ''They are shooting at each other, and we are in the middle,'' Mrs. Saqa said. ''We can't sleep. How can Rola focus on studying?''</p>
        <p>Rola said she thought she had done well on her first exam. ''After one hour, we heard intensive shooting,'' she said. ''The teacher asked us not to be afraid.'' In that case, the source of the shooting was mourners firing guns at a funeral, she said.</p>
        <p>Early Monday, Palestinian militants launched seven rockets toward Israel. Four were found in open areas inside Israel, but caused no injuries, an army spokesman said.</p>
        <p>About 70 Israeli high school students from the Israeli town of Sderot, close to the Gaza border, were bused out of rocket range to take an exam in citizenship, according to Yifat Lifner, the Education Ministry spokeswoman for southern Israel. They sat for the exam in the Negev desert town of Ofakim.</p>
        <p>Separately, Ehud Barak, a former prime minister of Israel, and Ami Ayalon, a former Shin Bet internal security service chief, wrapped up their campaigns before second-round voting on Tuesday for the leadership of the Labor party.</p>
        <p>The polls indicate a close race between Mr. Ayalon and Mr. Barak.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
