<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports Briefing</title>
    <meta content="12sportsbriefs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EFDA173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="745" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MARATHON</p>
        <p>RUNNERS SELECTED BY LOTTERY -- Patricia Plasencia was anxious about waiting until today to learn whether a computer chose her in the lottery to run the 2007 New York City Marathon. But at 5:55 a.m. yesterday on the WNBC Today in New York Show, the two-time defending women's champion of the race, Jelena Prokopcuka, drew Plasencia's name in a ceremonial drawing.</p>
        <p>Plasencia, 37, is a physical therapy assistant from Del Rio, Texas, a town on the Mexico border of about 37,000 people. Last year she did not get into the lottery, but ran in New York for the charity Team for Kids. In her first marathon, Plasencia finished in 4:52:20.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MARATHON</p>
        <p>RUNNERS SELECTED BY LOTTERY -- Patricia Plasencia was anxious about waiting until today to learn whether a computer chose her in the lottery to run the 2007 New York City Marathon. But at 5:55 a.m. yesterday on the WNBC Today in New York Show, the two-time defending women's champion of the race, Jelena Prokopcuka, drew Plasencia's name in a ceremonial drawing.</p>
        <p>Plasencia, 37, is a physical therapy assistant from Del Rio, Texas, a town on the Mexico border of about 37,000 people. Last year she did not get into the lottery, but ran in New York for the charity Team for Kids. In her first marathon, Plasencia finished in 4:52:20.</p>
        <p>Prokopcuka also drew two other names, Michael Scoleri of New York and Michael Cohen of Smithtown, N.Y. A list of the accepted entrants will be posted by noon on the New York Road Runners Web site, www.ingnycmarathon.org.</p>
        <p>The New York Road Runners will accept about 49,800 runners and expect a starting field of about 38,300 runners for the Nov. 4 race.</p>
        <p>LIZ ROBBINS</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>MCNABB RETURNS EARLY -- Donovan McNabb took a major step forward in his return from knee surgery when he practiced with the Philadelphia Eagles yesterday, several weeks ahead of schedule. McNabb, a five-time Pro Bowl quarterback, participated in noncontact drills in his first action on the field since he tore the anterior cruciate ligament in his right knee last Nov. 19. (AP)</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASEBALL</p>
        <p>BLOGGER EJECTED FROM GAME -- A reporter was ejected from an N.C.A.A. baseball tournament game for submitting live Internet updates during play. Brian Bennett, a writer for The Courier-Journal of Louisville, Ky., was approached Sunday by an N.C.A.A. representative in the bottom of the fifth inning and told that blogging from an N.C.A.A. championship event was against the N.C.A.A. policy. Bennett had done live blogging during Louisville's super regional games against Oklahoma State in the previous two games of the three-game series.</p>
        <p>The representative revoked Bennett's credential Sunday and asked him to leave the game. The newspaper said it was a First Amendment issue, while an N.C.A.A. memo said blogs were considered a ''live representation of the game'' and blogs containing action photos or game reports were prohibited until the game was over. (AP)</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>PASSENGER IN ACCIDENT DIES -- A New Jersey man who was thrown from the sports utility vehicle of Denver Nuggets guard J. R. Smith when it overturned last weekend died last night in the hospital, state police said. Andre Bell, 21, was sitting in the back seat of the vehicle Smith was driving when it went through a stop sign, collided with another car and flipped over at 5:30 p.m. Saturday in Millstone Township. Bell, who was in a coma, died from head injuries at 6 p.m. at Jersey Shore University Medical Center in Neptune, state police said, Smith, 21, who was also thrown from the vehicle, remained at Jersey Shore with an injured left shoulder and numerous scratches, said the police, who added that neither Smith nor Bell was wearing seat belts at the time of the crash. Smith has been issued two traffic tickets for failure to stop at a stop sign and improper passing, according to the police. (AP)</p>
        <p>HOLDSCLAW TO RETIRE -- Chamique Holdsclaw, a six-time W.N.B.A. All-Star who re-signed with the Los Angeles Sparks in February, stunned the team yesterday by retiring. Holdsclaw, 29, played in the Sparks' first five games this season and averaged 15.8 points, 5.6 rebounds and 3.0 assists. Holdsclaw did not give a reason for ending her professional basketball career but said in a statement released by the team that, ''this was not an easy decision.''</p>
        <p>Before joining the Sparks two years ago, Holdsclaw played seven seasons with the Washington Mystics. She was the 1999 W.N.B.A. rookie of the year after leading Tennessee to three consecutive N.C.A.A. championships. (AP)</p>
        <p>DISAPPEARING ACT COSTS MAGIC -- The Orlando Magic is offering refunds to fans who bought season tickets just after Billy Donovan's hiring. More than 200 packages sold within 24 hours of the announcement that the Magic had lured Donovan away from the University of Florida, where he won two consecutive N.C.A.A. titles. Donovan changed his mind a day after his May 31 introduction, deciding to return to the Gators. The Magic said it was contacting people who bought season seats within 48 hours of the Donovan announcement. (AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
