<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Great Architecture Finds a Home in Indiana</title>
    <meta content="13frugalweb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/travel/13frugalweb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854066"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE FRUGAL TRAVELER | AMERICAN ROAD TRIP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Frugal Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Indiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Indiana</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EEDC103EF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1442" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Great Architecture Finds a Home in Indiana</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Great Architecture Finds a Home in Indiana</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT GROSS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE sign said ''Dining Room,'' and its red Deco neon shone valiantly against the empty blue sky. Below was a whitewashed country diner, with only a few cars and pickups in the parking lot; by this late afternoon hour, everyone in North Vernon, Ind., had long since lunched.</p>
        <p>Food wasn't my reason for stopping, either. I simply wanted to enjoy this gorgeous example of prairie design and artistry -- one of many to come, I hoped.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Columbus, Ind., is a small town that just happens to have the most incredible collection of modern architecture in the Midwest (outside Chicago, of course).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE sign said ''Dining Room,'' and its red Deco neon shone valiantly against the empty blue sky. Below was a whitewashed country diner, with only a few cars and pickups in the parking lot; by this late afternoon hour, everyone in North Vernon, Ind., had long since lunched.</p>
        <p>Food wasn't my reason for stopping, either. I simply wanted to enjoy this gorgeous example of prairie design and artistry -- one of many to come, I hoped.</p>
        <p>That morning, I'd driven up from Louisville, Ky., crossing the Ohio River into a land of utter flatness, where farmhouses fronting Route 3 were backed by endless fields of wheat, corn and hay. But within this placid country landscape, I'd spotted numerous signs like the one in North Vernon: ''Gas and Grocery'' molded into plastic and undulled by the seasons; ''Mail Pouch Tobacco'' stenciled on the side of a forlorn barn.</p>
        <p>All were tantalizing hints of the architectural beauty and preservation that awaited me at the end of the road, in Columbus, Ind.</p>
        <p>Recommended by numerousreaders, Columbus is a small town (population 39,000) that just happens to have the most incredible collection of modern architecture in the Midwest (outside Chicago, of course). Everyone from Eliel Saarinen and his son, Eero, to Deborah Berke and Richard Meier has worked there, designing so many schools, churches and libraries that, at least in theory, you can't walk a single block without stumbling on an elegant glass-and-concrete building or a house of worship soaring like a Euclidean fantasy.</p>
        <p>''You actually have to see it to believe it,'' wrote Christopher Porter, a reader.</p>
        <p>And since architectural tourism can be one of the most affordable forms of travel -- you don't have to pay to wander public spaces and stare at buildings -- I gunned the Volvo north toward Columbus.</p>
        <p>Before I could see it, however, I had to find a place to sleep. The Columbus Inn (445 Fifth Street, 812-378-4289, www.thecolumbusinn.com) seemed like a possibility. An 1895 Romanesque brick structure designed by Charles F. Sparrell, the inn once housed the city's government and a farmers' market, but in 1986 reopened as a bed-and-breakfast with original woodwork, tons of antiques and fairly low rates: $109 and up.</p>
        <p>Still, that was too much for me, so I logged onto www.couchsurfing.com, a Web site for people who enjoy sleeping with strangers. No, nothing kinky here -- just an online community where members freely offer up their floors, couches and spare bedrooms to wanderers, in exchange for the same hospitality when they hit the road themselves.</p>
        <p>CouchSurfing would seem to appeal to the postcollegiate backpacker set, but families dig it, too. Michele and Andrea Signorino, one of two CouchSurfing couples in Columbus, once traveled frequently to places like Belize and Argentina, but now that they have three children, seeing the world is a bit more difficult. CouchSurfing, however, lets them bring the travel home, as the hosts for touring rock bands, teenage Canadian motorcyclists and other frugal travelers.</p>
        <p>The Signorinos' green-gray home lay just west of Columbus, in a neighborhood of small houses, big yards and flapping clotheslines, and when I arrived last Wednesday afternoon, I got the biggest, sweetest welcome I could have imagined. Michele, a 43-year-old artist and stay-at-home dad, handed me a beer, while Renzo, 9, Vincent, 6, and Lucia, 3, crowded around to introduce themselves and learn about their new guest, who'd brought an enormous watermelon ($5 at a farm stand) to win them over.</p>
        <p>Within minutes, cuddly Lucia was sitting on my lap, Vincent was challenging me to a Jedi lightsaber duel on the PlayStation, and Renzo and I were trading neat science tricks, like filling a bowl with water, grinding black pepper on top then dipping a bar of soap into the mess. (Try it and see what happens.)</p>
        <p>By the time I performed the broom dance -- a contortion I learned at skateboard camp decades ago -- any thought of modern architecture was long gone. All afternoon, Michele and I entertained the kids, examined his Lambretta motor scooters and ''creepy clown'' sculptures, and discovered that we shared not only cultural references (Tony Millionaire comics, African pop music) but also certain household items: We own the same toaster, same wine rack, same beach towels.</p>
        <p>Eventually, his wife, Andrea, a doctor, returned from work, made hamburgers and we all ate dinner on the porch, telling stories about countries we had visited and characters we had met. Then we devoured the watermelon and spat seeds as far as we could into the grass in the twilight.</p>
        <p>The next morning, I awoke in the softest bed I'd slept in the entire trip and, after a homemade cappuccino from Michele, set off to see the vaunted architecture of Columbus. (The kids were busy with swimming lessons, anyway.) The 10-minute drive led over a brilliant red cable-stayed bridge, designed by J. Muller International, into the center of town, where next to the copper-roofed Beaux-Arts courthouse stood a minimalist grid of limestone pillars 40 feet high -- a veterans memorial designed by Thompson &amp; Rose.</p>
        <p>The contrast of the two -- one classic, the other unabashedly postmodern -- was inspiring and, I learned at the nearby visitors center (506 Fifth Street, 800-468-6564, www.columbus.in.us), quintessentially Columbus. In the early part of the 20th century, the town had prospered from industry and technology, primarily that of Cummins, which manufactured diesel engines. The town adopted the company's innovative posture and remained forward-looking.</p>
        <p>In 1957, the Cummins Foundation agreed to pay the architects' fees for any new municipal building -- a private-public partnership that resulted in more than 60 buildings designed by prominent architects. All are innovative (like Kevin Roche's use of then-experimental salt-glazed tile in the post office), but more importantly, they sparked a civic pride whereby homeowners feel obliged to keep up their quaint Victorians, and businesses aim for architectural greatness, even without the foundation's largesse.</p>
        <p>After buying a $2 map of walking and driving tours, I wandered around downtown, slipping inside Eliel Saarinen's rigidly geometrical First Christian Church and I. M. Pei's county library, where I relaxed with a copy of The Republic, the local paper. (Lead story: Time capsule discovered during demolition of middle school. Below the fold: Artifacts stolen during demolition of middle school.)</p>
        <p>Then I wandered to the offices of Cummins itself, a careful humanizing of brutal materials: ivy decked the concrete walls, and horizontal window slits connected the interior to the street. Out of curiosity, I asked passersby bearing ID tags if working inside great architecture made a difference.</p>
        <p>''I would say not,'' said one woman.</p>
        <p>''Work's work,'' said her male co-worker.</p>
        <p>''Having worked in lots of places,'' said a third, slightly older employee, ''I find it very helpful, particularly the light.''</p>
        <p>The sun was beating down hard, so I hopped in my Volvo, intending to drive to other architectural wonders, but as soon as I turned the key, the temperature gauge leapt into the red. I was a bit worried, since an overheated engine was the one thing my mechanic had warned me about. I returned to the Signorino house, refilled the radiator and decided to give the car, which had traveled 3,000 miles in three weeks, a well-deserved day off.</p>
        <p>Besides, all those fancy buildings, however gorgeous and creative and soul-stirring, lacked the one thing I had at the Signorinos -- the warm glow of family life. That evening, we watched Renzo's LittleLeague team defeat their opponents, 13 to 7, read books with Lucia and went out for huge $5.95 tenderloin sandwiches at the Columbus Bar (322 Fourth Street, 812-375-8800, www.powerhousebrewingco.com).</p>
        <p>As I prepared for bed that night, I realized that I'd found what every traveler hopes to discover on the road: a home away from home.</p>
        <p>Next stop: Wisconsin and Iowa.</p>
        <p>Share Your Suggestions | Read Comments</p>
        <p>THE FRUGAL TRAVELER | AMERICAN ROAD TRIP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
