<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chance of Yankee Thunder in Forecast at Fenway</title>
    <meta content="12chass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/sports/baseball/12chass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854065"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Chass, Murray</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clemens, Roger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7D8173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="964" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chance of Yankee Thunder in Forecast at Fenway</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Chance of Yankee Thunder at Fenway</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Projections in baseball are overused and meaningless. It's just plain foolish to say or think that because Alex Rodriguez hit 14 home runs in the Yankees' first 18 games that he's going to hit 126 home runs this season. Not even Barry Bonds, in his body-boggling prime, could have done that.</p>
        <p>But here is one projection that could actually have some potential as a barometer. Even better, it could create some fun: At the rate at which the Yankees are slashing into Boston's lead in the American League East, they will pass the Red Sox in the standings by July 4.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This projection could create some fun: At the rate at which the Yankees are slashing into Boston’s lead in the A.L. East, they will pass the Red Sox in the standings by July 4.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Projections in baseball are overused and meaningless. It's just plain foolish to say or think that because Alex Rodriguez hit 14 home runs in the Yankees' first 18 games that he's going to hit 126 home runs this season. Not even Barry Bonds, in his body-boggling prime, could have done that.</p>
        <p>But here is one projection that could actually have some potential as a barometer. Even better, it could create some fun: At the rate at which the Yankees are slashing into Boston's lead in the American League East, they will pass the Red Sox in the standings by July 4.</p>
        <p>If that happens, can you imagine the fireworks in the Red Sox' front office, their dugout, their clubhouse, at Fenway Park? Fenway would become a pyrotechnic pit. Fenway fans, burned once more, might torch their season tickets.</p>
        <p>Impossible, you say? There's no way the Yankees could catch the Red Sox in the next three months, let alone the next three weeks? Curb your skepticism and look at the facts: Only 10 days ago, the Red Sox led the Yankees by 13 1/2 games; today, their lead is 9 1/2.</p>
        <p>Beginning with their stunning 6-5 victory over Boston on June 3, a game that might have turned their season around, the Yankees sliced three games from the Red Sox' lead in four days. Another four days and another game was gone in the standings. Four games in eight days.</p>
        <p>And remember, it wasn't long ago -- May 29, in fact -- that the Red Sox' advantage was 14 1/2 games, half a game larger than the largest lead the Red Sox held over the Yankees in 1978, the year of Boston's unforgettable collapse. Which prompts a thought. Now that the Red Sox have won another World Series and expunged ''1918'' from their vocabulary, perhaps the next time Yankees fans see the Red Sox they can greet them with a new chant: ''nineteen-seventy-eight, nineteen-seventy-eight.''</p>
        <p>On Aug. 28, the day that these teams next meet on the field, fans can adorn Yankee Stadium with signs in big numbers saying 1978. In fact, it's easy to change the old signs that taunted the Red Sox: just make the second 1 in 1918 into a 7.</p>
        <p>Speaking of 1978, the Yankees didn't eradicate their 14-game deficit overnight. They went quickly from 14 to 10 in only four days, then picked up two more games during the following four-day period. But from July 27 on it was a slow process; a month later, the Yankees had sliced only half a game from their deficit, meaning that they lagged seven and a half games behind Boston with five weeks left in the season.</p>
        <p>The point is that even if the Yankees don't continue to slash gobs of games from Boston's lead in the coming days or weeks, it doesn't mean that the Red Sox are safe. Sixteen weeks remain in the season, which is plenty of time for dramatic events to occur.</p>
        <p>This seems to be a good point for a disclaimer. Lest anyone think I am rooting for the Yankees to win the division championship, be assured that I don't care which team wins. The New York Times Company owns 17 percent of the Red Sox, but my continued employment by The Times does not depend on my allegiance to company products.</p>
        <p>Contrary to what any number of Red Sox fans think, I am not a Yankees fan either. I have never been a Yankees fan. As a reporter who covered the Yankees for more than 16 years, I could not have survived had I also been a fan.</p>
        <p>But while I am not a fan of either team, I do root for a good story, and having lightning strike a second time would be a good story.</p>
        <p>Obviously, certain factors would have to contribute to Lightning Strike II. Probably the most critical factor will be the Yankees' pitching. It has to be good enough to sustain winning streaks.</p>
        <p>It wasn't good enough in the first two months, but now the key starters are all healthy, and the rotation has been fortified by the addition of Roger Clemens.</p>
        <p>Clemens, Chien-Ming Wang, Andy Pettitte and Mike Mussina should be good enough to match the Boston starters. That rotation has an unbeaten Josh Beckett (9-0), but it also has two pitchers, Tim Wakefield and Julián Tavárez, who have losing records on a team that has the best record in the major leagues.</p>
        <p>The Yankees' starting pitchers have hardly been overwhelming, but with the hitters now hitting the way they had been expected to hit, maybe the pitchers will be inspired to raise their level of performance.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, having Clemens in the rotation with the Yankees now making a move makes a lot more sense than having him pitch for a team going nowhere. With the Yankees, until recently, looking like a hopeless team, people had begun questioning the wisdom of signing Clemens to a $28 million contract, the richest one-year baseball contract ever. But if it helps produce that second lightning strike, no one will question it.</p>
        <p>Is Clemens worth $28 million, or even the prorated $17.4 million he will earn? Worth is in the mind of the beholder. The Yankees were desperate for an established pitcher. None were available in a trade, and the free-agent market isn't open during the season. Clemens was the only established pitcher available.</p>
        <p>In the economic world of supply and demand, when there is great demand and little supply, the seller has a huge advantage. Clemens's agent said $28 million, and the Yankees said, Where do we sign?</p>
        <p>And if Clemens can keep pitching the way he did last Saturday against Pittsburgh, he will be worth the money and Lightning Strike II might just become a reality.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
