<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hats Off to the Coverage Of the Belmont This Year</title>
    <meta content="12sandomir" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/sports/othersports/12sandomir.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854019"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TV SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">ESPN</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E5D9173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hats Off to the Coverage Of the Belmont This Year</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Belmont Coverage Pays Off This Year</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From the moment that ESPN's ABC Sports went on the air Saturday with the Belmont Stakes, one thing was pleasantly apparent.</p>
        <p>Brent Musburger, the host, did not sport his oversized fedora as he did last year when his silly chapeau was a leading indicator of a dreadful broadcast.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>ESPN’s production of the Belmont Stakes was noticeably better than last year’s, with new producer Jack Graham not carrying two extra races, which created a more coherent show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From the moment that ESPN's ABC Sports went on the air Saturday with the Belmont Stakes, one thing was pleasantly apparent.</p>
        <p>Brent Musburger, the host, did not sport his oversized fedora as he did last year when his silly chapeau was a leading indicator of a dreadful broadcast.</p>
        <p>The production was noticeably better than last year's, with the new producer Jack Graham not broadcasting two extra races, as ABC did last year, which created a more coherent show. The tight focus was on the winning horse, the filly Rags to Riches. And if you missed the first time one of ESPN's announcers mentioned that no filly had won the Belmont since 1905, you heard the same nugget repeated nearly a dozen times (although no one specifically said it was run 102 years ago at a mile and a quarter).</p>
        <p>There was vintage film of Tanya, the last filly to win the third leg of the Triple Crown, and a delightful moment when color video of Rags to Riches changed into an approximation of early 20th-century film.</p>
        <p>The most significant change since last year's Belmont was the camera work during the mile-and-a-half race. ESPN did not mistakenly follow the field of seven from faraway angles, as if the field were headed into the Elmont, N.Y., sunset. Instead, it used a system called GyroCam, essentially two cameras mounted on a Land Rover-like vehicle that was driven inside the rail to produce terrific medium- and tight-action shots of as many as six of the horses.</p>
        <p>My preference would have been to avoid some of the cuts to distant angles, but Graham said yesterday that he used the wider angles to include Imawildandcrazyguy, who was well behind. ''Keep in mind Street Sense's move in the Derby,'' he said by telephone, ''and if Imawildandcrazyguy had done that, we would have been remiss if we didn't show him.''</p>
        <p>ESPN/ABC's biggest problem throughout the race was rampant interference with its radio frequencies, which caused audio outages during Jeannine Edwards's interviews with the actor Jerry O'Connell (who is the star of a coming ABC prime-time program, and whose opinions were unnecessary, especially when they were eventually heard), and with Todd Pletcher, Rags to Riches's taciturn trainer. Most notably, a postrace party line-like comedy ensued when Rece Davis interviewed Curlin's trainer, Steve Asmussen, but viewers heard a TVG reporter interviewing someone else.</p>
        <p>''There was chaos,'' Graham said. ''Some of it was caused when our frequencies were stepped on by R.F. theft in New York, and some of it was gremlins you can't figure out.'' In the break before the Davis-Asmussen interview, Graham said, the microphone tested perfectly. But once the interview began, the other TVG interview intruded. ''I thought, 'Oh my God, should I pull out of the segment or wait for it to end?' '' Graham said.</p>
        <p>The last portion of the Asmussen interview was audible.</p>
        <p>ESPN/ABC sent a slew of on-air people to Belmont (more than the number of horses entered, joked Chris Fowler, who was at the main anchor desk). NBC Sports's group, with fewer people, is more cohesive and smartly uses a former jockey, Donna Barton Brothers, atop a horse, to chat with Kentucky Derby and Preakness jockeys soon after they've won.</p>
        <p>And although the lead analysts (the fine pair of Bailey and Randy Moss, who break down races expertly) were at ease, Fowler seemed tense (citing Street Sense as the winner before correcting himself), as did Edwards, who had a habit of waiting too long to mention the name of the horse connected to her interviewees. And how could Joe Tessitore not ask Mike Smith, Tiago's rider, why he was wearing that teensy-weensy pink bow tie?</p>
        <p>And how could a riveting feature about Robby Albarado, Curlin's jockey, and his various spills not mention that the horse that broke down and threw him in 2000 (causing him multiple injuries) was euthanized?</p>
        <p>''At some point, you have to say the feature is on Robby,'' Graham said. ''How much longer could it go?''</p>
        <p>Back to Musburger. He might be the best known of the Belmont group, but he is a dinosaur and a weird presence who, when looking for an allusion to the New York money that bet Rags to Riches down to 4 to 1, chose Hillary Clinton. He still calls people ''pardner'' and on Saturday he cast himself as a betting maven. He said there was ''no value'' in betting on Curlin at 3-to-2 odds, but incongruously added later that even odds on him were ''not bad.''</p>
        <p>Early on, Musburger provided the useful tidbit about how Secretariat and Seattle Slew were part of Rags to Riches's pedigree, information that ESPN should have expanded into a graphic showing Slew (her grandfather), Secretariat (her great grandfather) and Bold Ruler (her great-great-grandfather). That family tree would have been more visually compelling historically than the graphic that said Curlin was looking to be the first horse to win the Preakness and the Belmont since Afleet Alex in 2005. That far back, huh?</p>
        <p>Largely because the Belmont offered no possibility of a Triple Crown horse, the rating fell 9 percent to a 3.2 from last year. In 2004, Smarty Jones's foiled bid for the Triple Crown at the Belmont produced a 13.1.</p>
        <p>TV SPORTS E-mail: sportsbiz@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: sportsbiz@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
