<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Struggles Continue As Mets Lose Again</title>
    <meta content="12mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854063"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E7D8173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="945" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Struggles Continue As Mets Lose Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, June 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The celebrities came out to Dodger Stadium in droves Monday night to watch two of the most struggling teams in baseball. Wearing their Mets hats, Jerry Seinfeld and Hilary Swank came out to cheer a team with two victories this month, but no amount of star presence could prevent them from falling, 5-3, to the Dodgers for their seventh loss in eight games.</p>
        <p>The Dodgers, who had lost five of six, scored five unanswered runs off Orlando Hernández to exact a slice of revenge against the team that swept them in the division series last October. The Mets' lead over idle Atlanta narrowed to two games with no relief in sight. This series is the second of six in a row against playoff teams from last season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The celebrities came out to Dodger Stadium in droves Monday night to watch two of the most struggling teams in baseball. Wearing their Mets hats, Jerry Seinfeld and Hilary Swank came out to cheer a team with two victories this month, but no amount of star presence could prevent them from falling, 5-3, to the Dodgers for their seventh loss in eight games.</p>
        <p>The Dodgers, who had lost five of six, scored five unanswered runs off Orlando Hernández to exact a slice of revenge against the team that swept them in the division series last October. The Mets' lead over idle Atlanta narrowed to two games with no relief in sight. This series is the second of six in a row against playoff teams from last season.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of a tough spot in the season to scuffle as we have, and play these teams, sometimes you scuffle and get away with playing lower echelon teams,'' David Wright said before the game. ''But when you're playing the best of the best, they're going to exploit your weaknesses, and that's what Detroit did. We're going to have to recuperate quickly or were going to get embarrassed over these next couple weeks.</p>
        <p>Shawn Green, who missed the last 14 games with a broken bone in his right foot, supplied most of the offense, going 2 for 4. He drove in the Mets first run and scored their second, but they hardly threatened after taking a 3-0 lead in the third. The Dodgers trailed, 3-0, heading into the bottom of the fourth, but evened the score at 3-3 before going ahead in the sixth.</p>
        <p>The Dodgers' sixth-inning rally began with a leadoff double by Luis Gonzalez into the right-center field gap. With one out, James Loney doubled off the fence in left-center to drive in Gonzalez, and he reached third when Carlos Beltrán did not pick up the ball in time. The Mets shrewdly called a pitchout as the Dodgers squeezed, and Paul Lo Duca corralled Tony Abreu's bunt and tagged out the charging Loney. In his haste to throw out Abreu, Lo Duca threw wide to first, and Abreu made it to third. The error proved costly when Wilson Betemit, pinch-hitting for starter Randy Wolf, blooped a single to left to drive in Abreu, and the Dodgers led, 5-3.</p>
        <p>When Betemit's hit struck the outfield grass, Hernández slapped his glove against his side and stood off the mound shaking his head. Hernández was then replaced by Scott Schoeneweis. Entering the game, the Mets had scored more than three runs only three times this month. Manager Willie Randolph did not need to search far and wide for the reason. During their June swoon, they had hit .167 (12 for 72) with runners in scoring position, according to the Elias Sports Bureau, and .132 (5 for 38) with runners in scoring position and two outs.</p>
        <p>''There's no need to force things, no need to feel like you own these guys on base,'' Randolph said before the game. Asked to elaborate, Randolph said: ''Don't assume that you have to swing the bat when there's a guy on deck who's just as capable as you are. The ultimate goal is to get the run in.'' The Mets were efficient in the earlier innings, converting two of their first three opportunities in taking a 2-0 lead. Shortstop José Reyes celebrated turning 24 by leading off the game with a sharp single to center and scooting to second on a passed ball during Green's at-bat.</p>
        <p>Before the game, Green said that he was glad to be facing a left-handed pitcher after not playing for so long because it would force him to watch the pitches longer. He watched five of them go by before blooping a single to left, driving in Reyes, and then it was time for the real test: running the bases. Told that the bone will not heal fully for another three to four weeks, Green is wearing a guard for protection but said before the game that his foot did not bother him. On Wolf's first pitch, Green broke for second. It caught the catcher, Russell Martin, off guard, and his throw sailed wide and skittered into the outfield, allowing Green to sprint to third.</p>
        <p>With one out, Wright singled through a drawn-in infield to extend the Mets' lead to 2-0 and his hitting streak to 13 games. They added a run in the third when Carlos Gómez's two-out single drove in José Valentín. Three runs are usually plenty on a night when Hernández pitches. Since missing most of May with bursitis in his right shoulder, he had allowed two runs and seven hits in 19 innings, and he carried a 15-inning scoreless streak into the fourth inning.</p>
        <p>After Juan Pierre led off with a walk and stole second, Martin lined a single past a diving Wright at third to drive in Pierre. It was the Dodgers' first hit.</p>
        <p>Los Angeles tied the score on consecutive one-out hits by Gonzalez (double) and Andre Ethier (single), marking only the second time in nine starts that Hernández had given up more than two runs.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Mets outfielder Moises Alou had a magnetic resonance imaging test in New York on Monday that revealed inflammation and soreness in his left quadriceps. He is scheduled to go to Port St. Lucie, Fla., to continue his treatment, and Willie Randolph said he did not expect Alou to rejoin the team anytime soon. The Mets also shut down the Class AAA New Orleans reliever Ambiorix Burgos with a sore elbow. The organization is concerned that he will need reconstructive elbow surgery.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
