<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN SENATE VOTE, G.O.P. FIGHTS OFF GONZALES REBUKE</title>
    <meta content="12gonzales" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854034"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipton, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gonzales, Alberto R (Atty Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E2D9173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN SENATE VOTE, G.O.P. FIGHTS OFF GONZALES REBUKE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID JOHNSTON and ERIC LIPTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, David; Lipton, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Senate Republicans block symbolic no-confidence vote against Atty Gen Alberto R Gonzales that Democrats sought to intensify pressure on him to resign; effort fails in procedural step that falls seven votes short of 60 needed to end debate and move to vote on resolution; vote is 53 to 38, with 7 Republicans voting with Democrats; Republicans who reject proposal offer little defense of Gonzales, but portray resolution as politically motivated stunt; Gonzales says he intends to serve out remainder of Pres Bush's term, and Bush repeats his support of Gonzales; Democrats are conducting investigations into dismissals of United States attorneys and Gonzales's stewardship of Justice Dept; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senate Republicans blocked a symbolic no-confidence vote against Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales on Monday evening, dismissing the measure as an irrelevant gesture, though Democrats had hoped it might intensify pressure on Mr. Gonzales to resign.</p>
        <p>The Democrats had sought a showdown that would force Mr. Gonzales to retreat or President Bush to abandon his support of the attorney general, who has come under strong criticism from both parties for the dismissals of federal prosecutors and recent disclosures about partisanship in hiring at the Justice Department.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senate Republicans blocked a symbolic no-confidence vote against Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales on Monday evening, dismissing the measure as an irrelevant gesture, though Democrats had hoped it might intensify pressure on Mr. Gonzales to resign.</p>
        <p>The Democrats had sought a showdown that would force Mr. Gonzales to retreat or President Bush to abandon his support of the attorney general, who has come under strong criticism from both parties for the dismissals of federal prosecutors and recent disclosures about partisanship in hiring at the Justice Department.</p>
        <p>Instead, the Democrats' effort failed in a procedural step that fell seven votes short of the 60 needed to end debate and move to a vote on the resolution. The vote was 53 to 38. Most of the Senate's 48 Republicans voted against the motion, but 7 voted to proceed. No Democrats voted against the motion.</p>
        <p>Republicans who rejected the proposal offered little defense of Mr. Gonzales, but criticized the resolution as a politically motivated stunt and a waste of the Senate's time.</p>
        <p>''If I were president, I would have asked Alberto Gonzales to resign as attorney general,'' George V. Voinovich, Republican of Ohio, said in a statement. But he said, ''Today's vote does nothing to rectify the current problem or ensure it doesn't happen again.''</p>
        <p>Democrats claimed a measure of victory. Senator Charles E. Schumer, the New York Democrat who was one of the resolution's chief sponsors, said that because a majority of the Senate had voted to move ahead with the resolution, the result could be interpreted as a no-confidence vote.</p>
        <p>''When a majority of the Senate votes no confidence in a cabinet officer, it says a lot,'' Mr. Schumer said at a news conference after the vote. ''He ought to have the decency himself to resign. Clearly, he is not up to the job.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gonzales, who has said he intends to serve out the remainder of Mr. Bush's term, told reporters on Monday morning that he was paying no attention to the vote.</p>
        <p>''I am not focusing on what the Senate is doing,'' he said at a nuclear terrorism conference in Miami. ''I am going to be focusing on what the American people expect of the attorney general of the United States and this great Department of Justice.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush repeated his support of Mr. Gonzales, a friend and fellow Texan, on Monday at a news conference in Sofia, Bulgaria, as he prepared to return to Washington.</p>
        <p>''They can have their votes of no confidence,'' Mr. Bush said, ''but it's not going to make the determination about who serves in my government. This process has been drug out a long time. It's political.''</p>
        <p>Democrats have been leading investigations into the dismissals of the United States attorneys and Mr. Gonzales's stewardship of the Justice Department, inquiries that remain open but are moving to a close. Democratic Congressional aides said that House and Senate investigators were likely to step up efforts to obtain the testimony of White House officials, including Karl Rove, the president's chief political adviser, who might have been involved.</p>
        <p>Congressional efforts to compel the testimony of Mr. Rove and Harriet E. Miers, the former White House counsel, about their role in the dismissals have been stalled by disagreements between the White House and the Senate Judiciary Committee. So far, the panel has authorized but has not issued subpoenas to force their appearance.</p>
        <p>The events that culminated in the vote have been building since January when Democrats learned that eight United States attorneys had been forced from their jobs without being given a reason, including some who had received favorable performance evaluations.</p>
        <p>In response to Senate and House inquiries, the Justice Department offered differing explanations, at first asserting that the prosecutors had been ousted for performance failings and insisting that the White House had played only a minor role.</p>
        <p>Later, Justice Department officials acknowledged that most of the fired prosecutors had received good evaluations and that the White House had initiated the dismissals after the 2004 election.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Gonzales testified about the dismissals, he said he was involved sporadically in the removal process, but had delegated much of the effort to subordinates. He also said he could not answer or recall many specific details, a response that infuriated many Democrats and dismayed a number of Republicans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gonzales suffered another blow when a former aide, Monica M. Goodling, recently testified that she had considered political allegiance in filling lower-level nonpolitical jobs at the Justice Department, a possible violation of federal employment laws.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gonzales's position seemed to slip further after gripping testimony last month by a former deputy attorney general, James B. Comey. He said that in March 2004, Mr. Gonzales, then White House counsel, and Andrew H. Card Jr., then White House chief of staff, went to the hospital room of John Ashcroft, then attorney general, seeking his authorization to continue the National Security Agency's warrantless eavesdropping program.</p>
        <p>During Senate debate on Monday, the Republican leader, Mitch McConnell of Kentucky, accused Democrats of ''spending our time on a meaningless resolution about giving the president advice about who the attorney general ought to be.''</p>
        <p>Democrats leveled a broad attack on Mr. Gonzales's credibility and leadership and said that lawmakers needed to send a strong message of disapproval to the administration.</p>
        <p>''It is a rare maneuver, I know,'' Mr. Schumer said.</p>
        <p>But the move was justified, he said, asserting that Mr. Gonzales was incompetent and that he had ''misled Congress, misled the American people'' about the dismissals of federal prosecutors and other issues.</p>
        <p>Senator Trent Lott of Mississippi, the Republican whip, said a vote of no confidence would have been inappropriate. ''This is not the British Parliament,'' he said, ''and I hope it will never become the British Parliament.'' Mr. Lott was among those Republicans who questioned whether Mr. Schumer's position as head of the Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee accounted in part for his pursuit of Mr. Gonzales.</p>
        <p>Senator Arlen Specter of Pennsylvania was among the few Republicans to vote to allow the resolution to proceed to a vote. ''There is no confidence in the attorney general on this side of the aisle,'' said Mr. Specter, the ranking Republican on the Judiciary Committee. Even so, he predicted that the push to take the no confidence vote would just increase President Bush's resolve to stand by the attorney general.</p>
        <p>''My own hunch,'' Mr. Specter said, is that the vote ''is going to be a boomerang.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
