<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush, on European Tour, Perfects the Art of Meet and Run</title>
    <meta content="12notebook" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/world/europe/12notebook.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854006"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="REPORTER'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bulgaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bulgaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Bulgaria</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Group of Eight</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7D9173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush, on European Tour, Perfects the Art of Meet and Run</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush, on European Tour, Perfects the Art of Meet and Run</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERYL GAY STOLBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</byline>
      <dateline>SOFIA, Bulgaria, June 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reporter's Notebook vignettes from Pres Bush's eight-day, six-country European tour; describes frenzied pace of trip, with Bush staying in some countries only few hours; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''It's good to be here in your beautiful country,'' President Bush told President Georgi Parvanov of Bulgaria on Monday morning. He would be in the ''beautiful country'' for roughly 20 hours, half of them spent inside his hotel. In the world of White House travel, that is an eternity.</p>
        <p>Being on the road with Mr. Bush invariably invokes comparisons to that old movie ''If It's Tuesday, This Must Be Belgium,'' and his eight-day, six-country European tour was no exception. Mr. Bush is not one to linger or to waste time -- this is, after all, the president who traveled to India and skipped seeing the Taj Mahal -- but the Europe trip may have set some sort of record for speed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Being on the road with President Bush invariably invokes comparisons to that old movie “If It’s Tuesday, This Must Be Belgium.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''It's good to be here in your beautiful country,'' President Bush told President Georgi Parvanov of Bulgaria on Monday morning. He would be in the ''beautiful country'' for roughly 20 hours, half of them spent inside his hotel. In the world of White House travel, that is an eternity.</p>
        <p>Being on the road with Mr. Bush invariably invokes comparisons to that old movie ''If It's Tuesday, This Must Be Belgium,'' and his eight-day, six-country European tour was no exception. Mr. Bush is not one to linger or to waste time -- this is, after all, the president who traveled to India and skipped seeing the Taj Mahal -- but the Europe trip may have set some sort of record for speed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush did stay put in Heiligendamm, Germany, for two full days to attend a meeting of leaders of the world's leading economic powers. And he spent two nights in Rome, staying at the home of the American ambassador, Ronald P. Spogli, an old friend of his from Harvard Business School, who helped raise more than $100,000 for each of Mr. Bush's presidential campaigns before getting his plum assignment.</p>
        <p>Often, though, he was a man on the run. ''I'm proud to be the first American sitting president to visit Albania,'' Mr. Bush told Prime Minister Sali Berisha on Monday. ''It's a great honor to represent my country here. I've really been looking forward to this trip and so has my wife, Laura.'' The Bushes spent eight hours in Albania, sandwiching the stop between Rome and Sofia.</p>
        <p>That was nothing compared with Mr. Bush's visit to Poland, where he had dinner at President Lech Kaczynski''s private retreat, a sort of Camp David by the sea. It was a spectacular landscape, overlooking the glittering Baltic, and Mr. Bush gushed as he spoke to reporters with Mr. Kaczynski by his side. ''This is our third trip to Poland,'' the president said. ''We have never been in this beautiful part of your country, and it's spectacular.''</p>
        <p>Those words were spoken at an airplane hangar in Gdansk, with Air Force One parked outside, so that Mr. Bush could make a hasty exit after his three-hour stay.</p>
        <p>Wheels of One's Own</p>
        <p>Where Air Force One goes, so does ''the beast.''</p>
        <p>The beast is what the Secret Service calls Mr. Bush's limousine, the heavily fortified black Cadillac with the presidential license plates. At the Group of 8 meeting in Germany, the other world leaders arrived for dinner in minivans provided by their German hosts. Mr. Bush arrived in the beast.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush actually travels with two limousines, transported by military jet, either a C-5 or a C-17. They serve not only as his wheels, but as his protection; when he was mobbed by admirers in Albania, he stood on the running board of his limousine to wave at the screaming crowd. The Secret Service promptly drove the backup limo close behind him, to keep him covered from the rear.</p>
        <p>But the beast is not always reliable, as the president discovered in Rome. While traveling from the Vatican to the American Embassy, the limousine stalled, giving the Secret Service a scare and forcing Mr. Bush's motorcade of about two dozen cars to come to a halt for five minutes.</p>
        <p>The car eventually started back up and completed the trip, then had trouble squeezing through the embassy gates. So Mr. Bush got out and walked in.</p>
        <p>The beast was later seen in a shady spot with its hood up, a mechanic poking his head underneath. The small presidential seal was taken off the door, and the backup limousine was pressed into service for Mr. Bush's short ride to his next public appearance that day, with Prime Minister Romano Prodi at Chigi Palace.</p>
        <p>No word from the White House on what the trouble was.</p>
        <p>A Style Like No Other</p>
        <p>By the time Mr. Bush left Sofia for Washington on Monday afternoon, he had already taken six plane flights and at least that many helicopter rides.</p>
        <p>After eight days on the road and a bout with an unspecified stomach ailment that kept him in bed one morning in Germany, he could perhaps be excused for sounding a bit punchy.</p>
        <p>''I call him George,'' the president said of President Parvanov, whose first name is Georgi, as they stood side by side in a grand hall of the Museum of National Archaeology here. Mr. Bush then paused for effect, adding, ''He calls me George.''</p>
        <p>But when the president praised the other George for winning admission to the North Atlantic Treaty Organization, he tripped over his syntax. ''We're proud to stand with you in NATO,'' Mr. Bush said. ''These are big achievements for this country, and the people of Bulgaria ought to be proud of the achievements that they have achieved.''</p>
        <p>Later in the day, Mr. Bush met with 10 current and former students at the Elieff Center for Education and Culture at the American University in Bulgaria. They included several Bulgarians, a Serb, a resident of Kosovo, an Albanian and a young woman from Afghanistan. The event was intended to highlight the benefits that education can bring, not only in economic development but also in cultural understanding.</p>
        <p>During the session, Mr. Bush exhibited some cultural understanding of his own. During a chat with Nita Gojani, a Kosovar with purple-dyed hair, she told him that she had at one point studied in Hawaii.</p>
        <p>''So,'' the president of the United States asked, ''were you one of those surfer chicks?''</p>
        <p>REPORTER'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
