<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tradition Is Renewed At Pocono Raceway</title>
    <meta content="12nascar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/sports/othersports/12nascar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854021"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Pennsylvania</location>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <person class="online_producer">France, William C</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE5D9173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tradition Is Renewed At Pocono Raceway</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tradition Is Renewed at Pocono</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <dateline>LONG POND, Pa., June 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In what has become a tradition, two Nascar officials last Friday walked into the office of Dr. Joseph Mattioli, the longtime owner of Pocono Raceway, and handed him a sheaf of papers known as an annual sanction agreement.</p>
        <p>Doc Mattioli, 82, who was a dentist before he built Pocono in 1968, looked at the two men and asked if he was getting the same deal as other tracks. They said yes. He immediately flipped past all the fine print and signed the back page -- another tradition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pocono Raceway will again play host to not one but two 500-mile Nextel Cup races in 2008, no matter how much grumbling from drivers about how interminable 500-mile races seem to be at Pocono.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In what has become a tradition, two Nascar officials last Friday walked into the office of Dr. Joseph Mattioli, the longtime owner of Pocono Raceway, and handed him a sheaf of papers known as an annual sanction agreement.</p>
        <p>Doc Mattioli, 82, who was a dentist before he built Pocono in 1968, looked at the two men and asked if he was getting the same deal as other tracks. They said yes. He immediately flipped past all the fine print and signed the back page -- another tradition.</p>
        <p>With Mattioli's signature, Pocono will again play host to not one but two 500-mile Nextel Cup races in 2008, no matter how much grumbling from drivers about how interminable 500-mile races seem to be at Pocono.</p>
        <p>Although there was speculation that one or even both races might be pulled from Pocono after the death of Bill France Jr., the former Nascar president and a longtime friend of the Mattioli family, Pocono will keep 2 of the 36 races on the Nextel Cup schedule. ''I think we've always had a great working relationship with Doc,'' said Steve O'Donnell, the Nascar vice president for racing operations, who attended the meeting with Nascar's president, Mike Helton.</p>
        <p>Mattioli, whose track has annually played host to two Nascar races since 1982, is coming off a day in which he said Pocono drew its biggest crowd since 2001, an estimated 100,000.</p>
        <p>Although rain caused the race to start late and end early, the big crowd was noteworthy. Officials at Nascar tracks have had to find ways to keep luring fans to races even though gasoline -- the kind used to fill fans' vehicles -- has cost more than $3 a gallon.</p>
        <p>''There's a little bit of flatness, and sometimes it's hard to tell when you're doing better,'' Denis McGlynn, the president and C.E.O. at Dover International Speedway, said in a recent interview. ''Three-dollar gas prices and rising adjustable-rate mortgages are moderating factors for the whole industry.''</p>
        <p>Jeff Gordon caught a break Sunday by winning a race at Pocono that was shortened to 106 laps, or 265 miles, because of rain and darkness. He will return to Pocono with other drivers on Aug. 5 for another race, this one also scheduled for 500 miles.</p>
        <p>Richard Petty won the Purolator 500 at Pocono on Aug. 4, 1974, and all 58 Nascar races at Pocono since have been scheduled for 500 miles, even though drivers have continued to complain that 200 laps around a flat race track makes for a tedious day.</p>
        <p>''I think the racing would be a little bit more exciting if it was a shorter race,'' Gordon said Sunday. ''But I don't make those calls. I think tradition is extremely important here, and 500 miles is the tradition that we have had here for a long time.</p>
        <p>Kasey Kahne said on Friday that a 500-mile race ''is a long time here.''</p>
        <p>''I think 400 would be plenty for the fans and drivers and teams and Nascar and everybody,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mattioli said he did not necessarily disagree with the drivers, although he did point out that a shorter race would mean less television money and, as a result, a smaller purse for the drivers. Of more importance to Mattioli is that the fans have not complained about 500-mile races.</p>
        <p>The demographics at Pocono, which is the closest Nextel Cup track to New York City, could be part of the reason. By Mattioli's estimate, only about 20 percent of fans attend both races, so a Nextel Cup race, for most, is a once-a-year event.</p>
        <p>About 35 percent of Pocono's fan base is from eastern Pennsylvania, with about 20 percent from northern New Jersey and another 20 percent from upstate New York. The other 25 percent come from farther-flung states like Ohio and Connecticut.</p>
        <p>Some fans do not mind driving long distances to watch a long-distance race. To bolster attendance from within a 100-mile radius of the track (which includes New York City), Mattioli paid for more advertising on billboards and buses this year.</p>
        <p>He also offered a two-for-one ticket coupon. Those who met a May 22 deadline could have purchased two $75 Terrace or $45 Concourse tickets to both races for the price of one. He did not provide specific figures, but said the offer was a success.</p>
        <p>''If I can get my money back, I can feel like we've won,'' Mattioli said.</p>
        <p>And he can get to do it all over again next year, if he wants.</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
