<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Iraqi Parliament Votes to Oust Speaker Who Intimidated Members</title>
    <meta content="12iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/world/middleeast/12iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Samarra (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rubin, Alissa J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mashhadani, Mahmoud Al-</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5D9173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="924" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Iraqi Parliament Votes to Oust Speaker Who Intimidated Members</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Iraqi Parliament Votes to Oust Speaker Who Intimidated Members</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISSA J. RUBIN; Abdul Razzaq al-Saiedi and Khalid al-Ansary contributed reporting from Baghdad, and employees of The New York Times from Mosul, Diyala, Hilla and Salahuddin.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rubin, Alissa J</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, June 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iraqi Parliament approves resolution that would force resignation of speaker Mahmoud Mashhadani, Sunni Arab politician who has done little to build consensus among Iraq's political blocs; those voting to remove him include broad spectrum of Shiites, Kurds and even members of Sunni Arab coalition that has backed him in previous scrapes; agreement on Mashhadani's resignation comes after repeated episodes in which he or his bodyguards physically intimidated members of Parliament, in at least two cases striking them; Mashhadani's removal opens way for Sunni Arab political bloc to nominate new person for post; Parliament is under heavy pressure from American government to move swiftly on overhaul of Constitution and on crucial legislation; photo of burning police vehicle after roadside bomb explodes in Samarra, killing two police officers and wounding three (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Parliament approved a resolution on Monday that would force the resignation of the speaker, Mahmoud Mashhadani. The vote underscored the widespread discontent with Mr. Mashhadani, a Sunni Arab politician who has done little to build consensus among Iraq's political blocs.</p>
        <p>Of the 168 Parliament members present at the session, 113 voted in favor of the resolution, which included a pledge from the Sunni Arab coalition -- which had backed Mr. Mashhadani in previous scrapes -- that the speaker would submit his resignation once a replacement was found. In the meantime, Mr. Mashhadani will be on leave, though he will remain a member of Parliament.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The vote underscored the widespread discontent with a Sunni Arab politician who has done little to build consensus among Iraq’s political blocs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Parliament approved a resolution on Monday that would force the resignation of the speaker, Mahmoud Mashhadani. The vote underscored the widespread discontent with Mr. Mashhadani, a Sunni Arab politician who has done little to build consensus among Iraq's political blocs.</p>
        <p>Of the 168 Parliament members present at the session, 113 voted in favor of the resolution, which included a pledge from the Sunni Arab coalition -- which had backed Mr. Mashhadani in previous scrapes -- that the speaker would submit his resignation once a replacement was found. In the meantime, Mr. Mashhadani will be on leave, though he will remain a member of Parliament.</p>
        <p>Those who voted to remove him included a broad spectrum of Sunni Arabs, Shiites and Kurds. He was not in the chamber during the vote.</p>
        <p>''What happened today made obvious the dynamic of democracy in Iraq,'' said Hassan Sinead, a member of Parliament from the Shiite Dawa Party.</p>
        <p>''The Parliament today had a peaceful, impartial, a democratic operation'' to remove the speaker, he said.</p>
        <p>The military reported that three American soldiers died Sunday when insurgents detonated a bomb under a highway overpass near Mahmudiya, the volatile area just south of Baghdad also known as the triangle of death.</p>
        <p>Although the situation was relatively quiet in Baghdad on Monday, in nearby Diyala Province insurgents destroyed a bridge that linked the provincial capital, Baquba, to the main highway to Baghdad, according to a member of the security forces in Diyala, who requested anonymity because he is not authorized to speak to journalists.</p>
        <p>The bridge linked towns on the eastern side of the bridge, which are Shiite, with those on the western side of to the bridge, which are Sunni Arab. The explosion occurred on the western side of the bridge.</p>
        <p>This was at least the fourth successful attack on a bridge in the last two months. Bridges are crucial in central Iraq, where the broad Tigris and Euphrates rivers and their tributaries wind through the countryside. Each attack has hampered commerce and made daily life more difficult for Iraqis.</p>
        <p>The first was on April 12, when insurgents blew up one of Baghdad's bridges over the Tigris on the same day a suicide bomber detonated inside Parliament. Another bridge in Diyala and a bridge to in Mahmudiya have also been attacked.</p>
        <p>Iraqi security forces have managed to foil several other attempts, said Lt. Col. Christopher Garver, a spokesman for the American military forces in Baghdad.</p>
        <p>''Militarily, for the coalition, knocking down the bridge may or may not have significance, because we have other resources, we have 20,000 troops on each side of the river,'' Colonel Garver said. ''But it's inconvenient for the people who live there, and it's a visible reminder that the insurgents were successful on that day.''</p>
        <p>In Baghdad, Iraqi police officers retrieved 17 bodies, most of them shot in the head, according to the Interior Ministry. Ten of those were found in southwest Baghdad, where there has been a sharp increase in the activities of the Mahdi Army, the militia linked to the anti-American Shiite cleric Moktada al-Sadr.</p>
        <p>At least eight Iraqis were killed in violence in Mosul, including the chief of the Iraq Central Bank in Nineveh Province. Eight bodies were found in Diyala as well, and insurgents there tried to kill the vice governor. In Najaf, security forces intercepted a large truck containing a BMW rigged as a car bomb and a container loaded with explosives. It had crossed the border from Syria and was being driven by a man carrying Syrian documents, said Ahmad Duaibel, chief spokesman for the Najaf governor's office.</p>
        <p>In Samarra, a roadside bomb near a police station killed two policemen and wounded three, the police said, according to Reuters.</p>
        <p>The agreement on Mr. Mashhadani's resignation from Parliament came after repeated episodes in which he or one of his bodyguards physically intimidated members of Parliament, in at least two cases striking them. ''The confrontations and conflicts and tension between Mashhadani and the other members in the Parliament happened over and over,'' Mr. Sinead, the Dawa Party representative, said. He added that the most recent incident, in which one of Mr. Mashhadani's guards struck a member of Parliament, was ''the straw that broke the camel's back.''</p>
        <p>The move opens the way for the Sunni Arab political bloc, known as Tawafiq, to nominate a new person for the post. Since the entire Parliament must vote on the speaker, there is a tacit understanding that while the Tawafiq coalition would nominate a Sunni Arab, it would first obtain approval from the Shiite and Kurdish blocs.</p>
        <p>Under the political bargain struck among Iraq's religious and ethnic groups, the Sunni Arabs hold three leadership positions: one vice presidential slot, one deputy prime minister slot and the speakership.</p>
        <p>The speaker can wield considerable power, delaying or speeding legislation and pressing the Parliament to act. The Parliament is under heavy pressure from the American government to move swiftly on an overhaul of the Constitution and on crucial legislation like that determining the distribution of the country's oil revenues.</p>
        <p>Two of the people said to be under consideration for the job are Usama al-Tikriti and Ayaed al-Sammaraie, both members of the Iraqi Islamic Party, who are respected and viewed as moderates.</p>
        <p>Until a replacement for Mr. Mashhadani is approved, the deputy speaker, Sheik Khalid al-Attiya, a Shiite from the United Iraqi Alliance, will be the acting speaker.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
