<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Forging His Own Way In the Shadow of an Icon</title>
    <meta content="12araton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/12/sports/basketball/12araton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854061"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/San Antonio Spurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Cleveland Cavaliers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">San Antonio Spurs</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pavlovic, Sasha</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Petrovic, Drazen</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E7D8173FF931A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1073" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Forging His Own Way In the Shadow of an Icon</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Forging His Own Way in the Shadow of an Icon</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>People see the number, the short-cropped hair, the stiff-shouldered swagger, the pretty jump shot, and reach a logical conclusion. Sasha Pavlovic must be mimicking Drazen Petrovic, paying tribute to a former countryman, a linchpin on his favorite basketball team before it was Balkanized out of existence, into history.</p>
        <p>''No, no, it's not for Drazen,'' Pavlovic said of the No. 3 on his jersey, adding that he once wore No. 11 for his father, Dusan, a longtime power forward in the old Yugoslavia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tales of Drazen Petrovic, the brash gunslinger who starred for the Yugoslav national team, were legend in the Balkan states, and many were passed down to the Cavaliers’ Sasha Pavlovic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>People see the number, the short-cropped hair, the stiff-shouldered swagger, the pretty jump shot, and reach a logical conclusion. Sasha Pavlovic must be mimicking Drazen Petrovic, paying tribute to a former countryman, a linchpin on his favorite basketball team before it was Balkanized out of existence, into history.</p>
        <p>''No, no, it's not for Drazen,'' Pavlovic said of the No. 3 on his jersey, adding that he once wore No. 11 for his father, Dusan, a longtime power forward in the old Yugoslavia.</p>
        <p>In Cleveland -- where the N.B.A. finals shift tonight with the Cavaliers, trailing the Spurs, 2-0, promising to yet make it a series -- 11 belonged to the Lithuanian center Zydrunas Ilgauskas. As Pavlovic explained, ''So I pick another number I like.''</p>
        <p>Which happens to be the one Petrovic wore when he was a star shooting guard, if not an N.B.A. All-Star, with the Nets.</p>
        <p>It was mentioned to Pavlovic that before Petrovic died at 28 in an accident on a German autobahn in 1993, his return to the N.B.A. was uncertain. He believed his exclusion from the 1992-93 All-Star Game by the coaches was in part an unwillingness to acknowledge that a player not developed by the American system was deserving.</p>
        <p>Petrovic wondered if Europeans would ever be accepted as more than ambassadorial role players, not what he had come here to be.</p>
        <p>This sounded to Pavlovic like the headstrong Petrovic he remembered watching on television with fascination and awe while growing up in Bar, an Adriatic coastal city in Montenegro. Tales of Petrovic, the brash gunslinger who starred for the Yugoslav national team and later for his native Croatia, were legend in the Balkan states, and many were passed down to Pavlovic by his father.</p>
        <p>''Drazen had that winner attitude, that killer instinct, like you say here,'' Pavlovic said. ''I heard that when they went to the Olympics in Barcelona to play against the Dream Team, he was maybe the only one who didn't care about who they were.''</p>
        <p>He heard that right. More than any of the N.B.A.'s early imports, Petrovic arrived with a basketball ego and attitude that seemed to be made in America. Others, Pavlovic included, followed his lead.</p>
        <p>Fifteen years after those watershed 1992 Summer Games, the N.B.A. finals are being beamed to 205 countries in 46 languages, including Arabic by a Jordanian-based network. The series has a record number of international players: nine, if we include, as the league does, Tim Duncan of the United States Virgin Islands. Five are starters, and the Spurs' sixth man, Manu Ginóbili, may as well be.</p>
        <p>What does it mean? How more global can the N.B.A. get? R. C. Buford, the Spurs' general manager, whose draft steals of Ginóbili (Argentina) and Tony Parker (France) have elevated his team to a near-dynastic level, guessed not much more.</p>
        <p>''I think it plateaus at some point,'' Buford said. ''I bet if you charted the curve of international players in the league, it was going like this, and I bet you the last couple years, it's more this.'' He angled his hand upward, left to right, and then in a flat line, explaining how the failure of some international players, perhaps arriving too young, would inevitably affect N.B.A. drafting.</p>
        <p>Then, too, there is the possibility of a backlash reflecting America's anti-immigrant wing and the persistent stereotypes that creep into the language as a result of jobs being taken by outsiders. Beneath the surface, there is still some resentment, some resistance, knee-jerk labels attached to foreign-born players, derisively expressed by commentators as soon as they stumble on the postseason stage.</p>
        <p>Pavlovic, a 6-foot-7 shooting guard in his fourth N.B.A. season, refuses to acknowledge the pejorative ''soft European,'' preferring to frame the discussion as one of stylistic differences, the focus in Europe on passing and shooting, and the challenges of adapting to the faster, more physical N.B.A game.</p>
        <p>The 19th pick of the first round in 2003 by Utah, athletic but not fully N.B.A. acclimated, Pavlovic spent last season and part of this one buried on the bench after responding to Coach Mike Brown's criticism of his defense by saying, ''My defense is my offense.'' This was a joke, Pavlovic said, lost in the translation of his Euro-accented English.</p>
        <p>Another chance resulted in a starting position, and a strong dose of redemption in the second round last month against the Nets, when Pavlovic hustled back and blocked a layup attempt by Jason Kidd, a decisive play in a Cavaliers victory.</p>
        <p>''The thing about Sasha that separates him from most of the young European players that come in here is confidence,'' Ilgauskas said. ''He can miss 10 shots in a row and he'll keep taking them.''</p>
        <p>Pavlovic nodded when Ilgauskas's praise was repeated to him, but he shook his head when told how Drazen-like it was.</p>
        <p>''I'm not trying to be like him,'' he said.</p>
        <p>It's complicated, the icon thing, given the political fallout of the changing European map in the early 1990s, in a way Americans cannot fully comprehend. The Yugoslav national team that featured the Croats Petrovic, Toni Kukoc and Dino Radja; the Serb center Vlade Divac; and Sasha Danilovic from Sarajevo in what is now Bosnia and Herzegovina might have been the best European team ever. Pavlovic was 7 when it fractured with the region.</p>
        <p>''You can just imagine how bad it was,'' he said. ''That team was so good, and basketball was all we had. Then people make it out to be war when they have to play against each other. But it was just basketball.''</p>
        <p>With Montenegro no longer part of Serbia after a referendum last year, Pavlovic can make his own national team choice. As an ethnic Serb, he could represent Serbia, as he did in the 2004 Athens Olympics, next summer in the Beijing Games. But tiny Montenegro now has its own national team, however unlikely it is to survive this summer's qualifying tournament.</p>
        <p>''My family wants me to play for Serbia in Beijing, but I know people in Montenegro won't be happy,'' Pavlovic said.</p>
        <p>He recently told a Serbian sports newspaper that he would play for Serbia in 2008. But in San Antonio last week, Pavlovic said that he was not yet sure. The long playoff run gives him the perfect excuse to play nowhere this summer and decide next year where his basketball roots lie, and who he ultimately is, No. 11 or No. 3.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
