<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Final Test, Clemens Appears Set for Return</title>
    <meta content="07pins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852788"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E6D61E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="767" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Final Test, Clemens Appears Set for Return</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Roger Clemens threw batting practice Wednesday in Tampa, Fla., and he seemed to have passed the final test before he rejoins the Yankees on Saturday against the Pittsburgh Pirates.</p>
        <p>''He is feeling good,'' said Manager Joe Torre, who spoke with Clemens. ''He did a sort of simulated batting practice with the screen in front of it. He said in his estimation, it was better than a side day; he got more out of it. Everything is all systems go for Saturday.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Roger Clemens threw batting practice Wednesday in Tampa, Fla., and he seemed to have passed the final test before he rejoins the Yankees on Saturday against the Pittsburgh Pirates.</p>
        <p>''He is feeling good,'' said Manager Joe Torre, who spoke with Clemens. ''He did a sort of simulated batting practice with the screen in front of it. He said in his estimation, it was better than a side day; he got more out of it. Everything is all systems go for Saturday.''</p>
        <p>Clemens told Torre that he typically exerted himself at about 60 percent of what game conditions would be like, but that Wednesday he pushed himself to 80 percent. He was originally scheduled to start Monday, but postponed the appearance because of a fatigued right groin.</p>
        <p>''Everything today went well,'' Clemens said in a statement released through the Yankees. ''I have a short downhill training session tomorrow, and then I should be locked in and ready to go. The weakness that came from the scar tissue has so far dispersed.''</p>
        <p>Torre said he warned Clemens not to become caught up in the excitement of his return, at Yankee Stadium, and to make sure he was fully healthy. But there seemed to be no lingering issues for him or for Andy Pettitte, who completed a bullpen session at U.S. Cellular Field after leaving his last start with tightness in his lower back.</p>
        <p>''I felt real good, actually, so I'm going to pitch on Friday,'' Pettitte said. ''I heated up and I threw a good pen today. I can't say that I felt restricted at all. It was just a nice, easy pen. I don't want it to act up again. I'll pitch Friday, and I don't want it to give me any problems.''</p>
        <p>FASTBALL ISN'T ALWAYS SO FAST -- The last pitch Mike Mussina threw last Saturday was a fastball to a hitter with a .119 career average against him. But the pitch was only 87 miles an hour, and the hitter, Boston's Jason Varitek, crushed it for a homer.</p>
        <p>In eight starts this season, Mussina is 2-3 with a 6.25 earned run average, with just 19 strikeouts in 401/3 innings. The inconsistency of his fastball has been the main reason.</p>
        <p>''When he's been successful, he's always been throwing 89-90, with a downhill angle, and hitting the corners,'' said Wil Nieves, who is now Mussina's regular catcher. ''Other games, like against Boston, he's been in the mid-80s and everything's tailing back to the middle.''</p>
        <p>Just those few miles an hour make a big difference, Nieves said, because hitters can wait a bit longer before gearing up to swing. Thus, they have a fraction of a second more to recognize the spin of Mussina's breaking pitches.</p>
        <p>Mussina said he did not know from start to start what kind of fastball he would have. But he said it had absolutely been the reason for his slow start, and he hopes that with more innings, the fastball will improve.</p>
        <p>''I'm just searching to be more consistent,'' he said. ''I still know it's in there. Hopefully, I won't have to worry about it in two or three more starts.''</p>
        <p>LINKED BY MORE THAN STRIKEOUTS -- Randy Johnson passed Roger Clemens for No. 2 on the career strikeout list Tuesday when he struck out eight for the Arizona Diamondbacks. Johnson now has 4,605 strikeouts, one more than Clemens but far off Nolan Ryan's 5,714. But do not expect them to pose for pictures next week when the Diamondbacks visit the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Johnson did not pitch at Shea Stadium last weekend when the Diamondbacks visited the Mets, staying at home in Arizona to rest his back. He is not scheduled to pitch next week at Yankee Stadium, and seems unlikely to make that trip, either.</p>
        <p>''It looks as if he'll be 0 for New York,'' Diamondbacks Manager Bob Melvin told reporters at Shea last weekend.</p>
        <p>Since Clemens signed with the Yankees and was given the freedom to leave the team on days he is not pitching, Johnson has gotten the same kind of privileges from the Diamondbacks. He has not accompanied the team to the past two cities in which he was not scheduled to pitch.</p>
        <p>JETER GETS A REST -- Joe Torre said Derek Jeter would have the day off Thursday against the White Sox. Miguel Cairo, who had two hits Tuesday, could start in his place. When Cairo started two double plays as the first baseman Tuesday, he became the first Yankees first baseman to do that since Dale Sveum on May 24, 1998, at Boston.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
