<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Camcorders Dial Down High Definition</title>
    <meta content="07pogue" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/technology/07pogue.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852767"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="STATE OF THE ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Operations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/David Pogue</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Camcorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Camcorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Canon Inc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Panasonic Co</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Sony Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Sanyo Electric Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EFD71E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1312" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Camcorders Dial Down High Definition</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Not-So-High- Definition Camcorders</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID POGUE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Uh-oh, it's started. The electronics industry has begun diluting the term high-definition.</p>
        <p>That phrase once denoted the pristine perfect picture you see in electronics stores on HDTV sets. Unfortunately, the use of that term is slowly becoming a marketing mantra merely meant to move merchandise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two new cameras that take both still photos and high-definition video redefine “high-definition” for the worse. Another new entry is closer to the mark.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Uh-oh, it's started. The electronics industry has begun diluting the term high-definition.</p>
        <p>That phrase once denoted the pristine perfect picture you see in electronics stores on HDTV sets. Unfortunately, the use of that term is slowly becoming a marketing mantra merely meant to move merchandise.</p>
        <p>Already, you may have noticed that not all ''high def'' shows on TV look equally good. This month, though, a line has been crossed. Companies have begun selling ''high definition'' camcorders whose video recordings can actually look worse than standard definition. You can witness this degradation in what ought to be a killer new product category: tiny hybrid machines that take both still photos and high-definition video. Who wouldn't love such a thing?</p>
        <p>You, once you discover the compromises involved.</p>
        <p>Three of the first hybrids to market are Canon's PowerShot TX1 ($475), Sanyo's Xacti VPC-HD2 ($610) and Panasonic's very first consumer high-def camcorder, the HDC-SD1 ($810).</p>
        <p>All three record onto memory cards instead of tape or disks. You might assume that video would fill up a card very quickly, but these camcorders can accommodate a new flavor of SD card called SDHC (for high capacity).</p>
        <p>These cards are now available in 4-gigabyte capacities for about $45 and can theoretically go all the way up to 32 gigabytes. (Few existing card readers and cameras can read SDHC cards.)</p>
        <p>The beauty of memory cards, of course, is that they give you more control over your filmed scenes. You can skip to another scene without rewinding or fast-forwarding. You can't record over something by mistake. And you can delete a scene from the middle of your masterpiece to free space.</p>
        <p>Each model has a flash for still photos, a tripod socket and a joystick the size of a hydrogen molecule. Each lets you snap stills while you're filming, which leaves only a quick black blink in the video. And none have eyepiece viewfinders; the only way to frame your shot is by using the flip-out screen.</p>
        <p>Two of the hybrids are astonishingly tiny. Sanyo's Xacti (3.2 by 4.7 by 1.4 inches) is an improved version of a model that had its debut in 2006. It's still a miniature marvel. It just fits in a pants pocket with a vertical pistol-grip design that resembles a disposable flashlight.</p>
        <p>Canon's radical new TX1, clad in stainless steel, is even smaller (3.5 by 2.4 by 1.1 inches). It looks like the love child of the Terminator and a bar of Ivory soap.</p>
        <p>Alas, what you gain in miniaturization and portability, you lose in comfort. Both cameras are ergonomic disasters. If you try to steady the Sanyo by holding the open screen with your left hand, as you'll do instinctively, you'll muffle or add scraping sounds to your soundtrack because the microphone is hidden in the back of the screen.</p>
        <p>The Canon is about the size of the company's Elph pocket cameras, but you're supposed to hold the TX1 vertically, on edge. That's a real drag, because there's nowhere for your fingers to go without accidentally pushing a button on some surface.</p>
        <p>The vertical orientation also limits the screen size to 1.8 inches diagonally. You probably haven't seen a camera screen that small since ''L.A. Law'' was on the air..</p>
        <p>The Sanyo design, with a 2.2-inch screen, is somewhat better. The buttons are all on the edge facing you, one big shutter button apiece for video and stills, plus the Play/Record toggle and the zoom control. A recorded woman's voice chirps out cheerful status reports and warnings. You can turn her off, but I kind of liked her.</p>
        <p>The screens of both cameras are squarish, like a standard TV screen, rather than wide, as you'd expect on a high-def camera. So when you're filming in high definition, black letterbox bars shrink the image even further. If the Canon's widescreen filming area were any smaller, you'd have to frame your shots by closing your eyes and imagining them.</p>
        <p>Other compromises become apparent when you connect these cameras to your high-def TV. The Canon requires a fussy five-headed cable (three component connectors, two stereo sound). When seated in its dock, the Sanyo lets you connect a single HDMI connector that carries both picture and sound.</p>
        <p>The Canon turns out to be a very good 7.1-megapixel still camera; like the Sanyo, it has a 10X optical zoom. The pictures may not be quite as terrific as Canon's own Elph cameras, but stills are clearly the TX1's forte. Photos look fantastic displayed on a high-def TV.</p>
        <p>The face-recognition software inside the camera calculates focus and exposure based on the faces in the scene; no more shooting two buddies, only to discover that the camera focused on the background between them.</p>
        <p>The Canon's high-def video is a different story. It's razor-sharp and the colors pop, but any movement, either by you or by your subject, results in a weird frame-skipping sort of jitter. Note, too, that the Canon's video format (motion JPEG) is easy to edit in popular computer programs, but it fills up a four-gigabyte card (not included) in about 14 minutes. Yikes.</p>
        <p>The Sanyo's 7.1-megapixel photos aren't quite as good as the Canon's, but they're nothing to be embarrassed about.</p>
        <p>You can't say the same about the video on the Sanyo. It is widescreen, but that's about all it has in common with what most people think of as high definition. Some scenes look great. But in bright light, whites are blown out, and details are often soft and cameraphonelike; in low light, dancing pixels overwhelm the scene.</p>
        <p>At least you get an hour's worth of video on a four-gig card -- four times what you'd get from the Canon. And this footage, too, is easy to work with in popular Mac and Windows video editing programs.</p>
        <p>So what about the third contender: Panasonic's SD1? This camcorder makes no attempt to play ''smaller than thou.'' It is a full-size fits-in-a-coat-pocket camcorder (2.9 by 2.6 by 5.4 inches), probably the coolest-looking one you've ever seen. The sculptured silver-colored cylinder fits in your right hand like a handheld grenade launcher, or a spacecraft left over from ''Star Wars.''</p>
        <p>This time, the high-def video is the real deal: crisp, vibrant, wide and thrilling, with smooth motion. All the features are here: fade-in and fade-out effects, backlight compensation, white balance, manual focus, both component and HDMI connectors for your TV, and even a feature that stops recording if the camcorder is bouncing along filming the ground. (It happens to the best of us.)</p>
        <p>The quality still isn't as good as what you'd get from a high-def tape camcorder like Canon's HV20 ($975), but it comes close.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, the Panasonic's still photos are, to use the technical term, horrible. They're blotchy and grainy, just like the stills from traditional camcorders. In other words, the Panasonic isn't really a hybrid; it's just a very good camcorder.</p>
        <p>The price includes a four-gigabyte memory card, which holds 40 minutes of best-quality video. But with the screen open and plenty of starts and stops, you can expect only 40 minutes of recording time from a single battery charge.</p>
        <p>Another drawback is the format in which video is stored, called AVCHD, which Panasonic developed with Sony. AVCHD is designed to compress high-def video in camcorders that record on something other than tape -- DVDs, hard drives and so on. At the moment, very few computer programs can edit it.</p>
        <p>All three of these high-def hybrids will take you on an emotional roller coaster ride. They're experimental, loaded with breakthroughs, but also saddled by disappointments.</p>
        <p>If you buy a high-definition tape camcorder instead, like the Canon HV20, you'll avoid most of those pitfalls. You'll gain the ability to edit your video in existing editing programs. And you'll get astonishing video quality that, in light of recent developments, we might have to describe with a new term: high high-definition.</p>
        <p>STATE OF THE ART E-mail: Pogue@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: Pogue@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
