<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tentative Deal Reached for Darfur Peacekeeping Force</title>
    <meta content="07nations" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/world/africa/07nations.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852702"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sudan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Darfur (Sudan)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">African Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoge, Warren</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sudan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Sudan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Darfur (Sudan)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
        <org class="online_producer">African Union</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Security Council</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E7D81E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="493" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tentative Deal Reached for Darfur Peacekeeping Force</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tentative Deal Reached for Darfur Peacekeeping Force</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN HOGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoge, Warren</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, June 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Nations and African Union strike tentative deal to end disagreement over command of joint peacekeeping force proposed for Darfur; African Union objected to original accord, which gave clear ultimate command to United Nations; new language eliminates reference and leaves division of power vague (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United Nations and the African Union struck a tentative deal on Wednesday to end disagreement over the command of a 23,000-soldier joint peacekeeping force proposed for Darfur.</p>
        <p>The disagreement arose last week and threatened an accord between the organizations on the details of the peacekeeping force, which is meant to help end the violence that has killed some 200,000 people and driven from their homes 2.5 million others in Darfur, a region of Sudan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Secretary General Ban Ki-moon has declared the crisis in Darfur his international priority, and ambassadors from the 15 Security Council countries will visit Sudan this month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United Nations and the African Union struck a tentative deal on Wednesday to end disagreement over the command of a 23,000-soldier joint peacekeeping force proposed for Darfur.</p>
        <p>The disagreement arose last week and threatened an accord between the organizations on the details of the peacekeeping force, which is meant to help end the violence that has killed some 200,000 people and driven from their homes 2.5 million others in Darfur, a region of Sudan.</p>
        <p>The original accord, which had been endorsed by the Security Council, gave clear ultimate command to the United Nations. But the African Union raised objections and asked for ''clarifications'' in the text.</p>
        <p>The new language, in a revised version delivered to the Security Council and the African Union's Peace and Security Council, eliminates the reference and leaves vague how power will be divided.</p>
        <p>A senior United Nations official who briefed reporters on condition of anonymity said the indeterminate phrasing was aimed at satisfying the Security Council that there was enough United Nations leadership to persuade troop-contributing countries to provide the necessary soldiers and equipment, and to convince the African Union and Sudan that there was enough African input at the top.</p>
        <p>Under the revision, he said, the African Union would have ''operational'' authority and the United Nations ''overall'' authority. He explained that this meant that an African Union commander would make decisions on the ground and that the United Nations would step in only if it disagreed with his decision.</p>
        <p>Secretary General Ban Ki-moon has declared the crisis in Darfur his international priority, and ambassadors from the 15 Security Council countries will visit Sudan this month.</p>
        <p>Getting the force into Darfur has been delayed for months by the Sudanese government's unwillingness to keep to an earlier promise to let United Nations peacekeepers in.</p>
        <p>The revised document must now go before the African Union's Peace and Security Council and the Sudanese government for approval, and the timetable is a rushed one.</p>
        <p>Under the schedule, the Sudanese are expected to discuss the agreement on Monday and Tuesday in Khartoum and give their response in time for the Security Council to discuss it in New York on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The next day the Security Council ambassadors leave on an African trip that will place them in Khartoum on June 17. They will also visit Ghana, Nigeria, Ivory Coast and Congo.</p>
        <p>Deployment of the joint force is the third stage of a United Nations-African Union plan to bolster and eventually replace the existing 7,000-member African Union force that has been overwhelmed by the scale of the conflict in Darfur.</p>
        <p>The second stage, known as the ''heavy support package'' and now under consideration, calls for sending 3,000 military police officers and six attack helicopters and other aviation and logistics support. The official said he hoped that this stage would be complete by the end of the year and that the joint force could be deployed in the first half of 2008.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
