<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Moss Expects to Produce for Patriots</title>
    <meta content="07patriots" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/sports/football/07patriots.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852804"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New England Patriots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New England Patriots</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Moss, Randy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3D61E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Moss Expects to Produce for Patriots</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Moss Expects to Produce for Patriots</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <dateline>FOXBOROUGH, Mass., June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Randy Moss smiled at the suggestion that joining the New England Patriots marked a new beginning.</p>
        <p>''I've had two of those,'' said Moss, referring to his stormy tenures with the Minnesota Vikings and the Oakland Raiders. ''I don't really want to call it a new beginning.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Patriots’ decision to acquire Randy Moss, one of the N.F.L.’s most electrifying but enigmatic players, is perhaps pro football’s most intriguing off-season move.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Randy Moss smiled at the suggestion that joining the New England Patriots marked a new beginning.</p>
        <p>''I've had two of those,'' said Moss, referring to his stormy tenures with the Minnesota Vikings and the Oakland Raiders. ''I don't really want to call it a new beginning.''</p>
        <p>Whatever Moss calls it, people will watch. More than 50 members of the news media engulfed him on Wednesday after the second day of a three-day minicamp. The Patriots' decision to acquire Moss, one of the N.F.L.'s most electrifying but enigmatic players, is perhaps pro football's most intriguing off-season move. It has energized a franchise that has won three recent Super Bowls even as the team artfully tries to avoid distractions with a gifted wide receiver who cannot seem to avoid the limelight.</p>
        <p>Despite his talent, Moss has endured a mercurial career. He has argued with teammates and coaches during his seven seasons in Minnesota and two seasons in Oakland. When the Raiders stumbled to the league's worst record (2-14) last season, Moss seemed to lose interest in playing his best. He posted career lows in receptions (42), receiving yards (553) and touchdowns (3). In his eight previous seasons, Moss never caught fewer than 60 passes. Only in 2004, his final season in Minnesota, did he fail to produce at least 1,000 yards receiving.</p>
        <p>Moss, 30, wanted out of Oakland and the Raiders obliged in April, when they sent him to the Patriots for a fourth-round draft choice. Some believe Moss will be rejuvenated while others believe his skills have diminished. But Coach Bill Belichick and quarterback Tom Brady have established a legacy of excellence to which Moss wants to contribute.</p>
        <p>''Belichick, as you all know, is straight-faced, he don't really joke around a whole lot,'' said Moss, describing his early impressions of the Patriots. ''Brady's the same way. That's something that you appreciate. Everybody's on the same page, even in minicamp.</p>
        <p>''I want to fit in. I still love to play the game.''</p>
        <p>Brady loves coming to work as well, and he is enthused by the off-season influx of talent. In addition to Moss, the Patriots acquired versatile linebacker Adalius Thomas, along with the proven wide receivers Donte' Stallworth and Wes Welker.</p>
        <p>When the Patriots traded wide receiver Deion Branch to the Seattle Seahawks last season after New England refused to meet his contract demands, Brady was upset about losing one of his favorite targets.</p>
        <p>However, the front office has provided Brady with a new bunch to play with, and he is excited about the possibilities.</p>
        <p>''We've got to figure out what Randy's good at, what Donte's good at, and what Wes is good at, and try to adapt our offense to their style,'' Brady said Tuesday. ''When Deion left, there were a lot of things Deion did that were unique to Deion. That's exactly how this offense needs to morph.''</p>
        <p>Brady has heard the critics who expect Moss to bring more baggage to the Patriots than a hotel valet would. But so far, Brady has been impressed, and Moss looked explosive during Wednesday's workout. During one portion of practice, Brady and Moss stood off to the side by themselves, talking and throwing a football, part of the working bond they hope to create.</p>
        <p>''I try not to prejudge people, I just let the relationship develop,'' Brady said. ''The thing I worry about is, do you know what to do, do you try hard, and are you unselfish? It seems like he's all three of those things.''</p>
        <p>Moss left Oakland on poor terms; he said the Raiders' losing ways wore on him. Instead of changing negative perceptions with his words, he hopes to dispel them with his actions.</p>
        <p>''To be honest with you, I don't plan on changing,'' Moss said. ''Anything that you heard about me, good or bad, some's a lie, some is true. Hopefully the true stuff will come out, and hopefully the bad will stay back there.</p>
        <p>''I'm not that open. I really don't like to do interviews, because that's not my job. My job is to catch touchdowns and help the team win.''</p>
        <p>It remains to be seen if Moss can return to being a dominant receiver, the type of player who can change a game with one play. However, the Patriots have taken a chance with Moss, and he wants to reward them for it.</p>
        <p>''Getting back to making plays and showing my versatility,'' said Moss, describing his expectations. ''Now that I'm enthused and energetic to be in the position that I'm in, I want to bring the old Randy Moss.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
