<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yonkers Project Is Approved, Though Council Complains</title>
    <meta content="07yonkers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/nyregion/07yonkers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852792"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Yonkers (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E4D61E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yonkers Project Is Approved, Though Council Complains</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Yonkers Agency Approves Controversial Development</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FERNANDA SANTOS</byline>
      <dateline>YONKERS, June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After three years of divisive debate marred by suspicions of back-room deals and political favoritism, a proposal to build houses, offices and shops on an 81-acre site off the Sprain Brook Parkway cleared its last hurdle here on Wednesday. The Industrial Development Agency, a quasi-governmental body, approved $22 million in mortgage and sales tax exemptions for the developer.</p>
        <p>But the occasion was far from celebratory, and the vote, swift and subdued, did not come without protest. City Council members are incensed by the mayor's decision to pursue the sale of the leasehold on the site to the developer for what they say is a fraction of its value.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A proposal to build houses, offices and shops off the Sprain Brook Parkway in Yonkers has cleared its last hurdle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After three years of divisive debate marred by suspicions of back-room deals and political favoritism, a proposal to build houses, offices and shops on an 81-acre site off the Sprain Brook Parkway cleared its last hurdle here on Wednesday. The Industrial Development Agency, a quasi-governmental body, approved $22 million in mortgage and sales tax exemptions for the developer.</p>
        <p>But the occasion was far from celebratory, and the vote, swift and subdued, did not come without protest. City Council members are incensed by the mayor's decision to pursue the sale of the leasehold on the site to the developer for what they say is a fraction of its value.</p>
        <p>At the meeting, one councilman tried in vain to air his complaint. ''Could I please ?'' Dennis Robertson blurted out from a front-row seat in the audience before he was cut off by the mayor, who said, ''This is a public meeting, not a public hearing.''</p>
        <p>The mayor, Philip A. Amicone, who is chairman of the agency, told Mr. Robertson to sit down and then polled the agency members, who unanimously endorsed the package.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robertson, a Democrat who is challenging Mr. Amicone, a Republican, for the mayor's office in the fall, was among the council members who helped devise a compromise last July in which the developer, Forest City Ratner, committed to paying the city no less than $9.5 million a year once the project is constructed. (Forest City Ratner is the development partner in a new Midtown headquarters for The New York Times Company.) The Council, in return, approved a zoning change for the project.</p>
        <p>Council members, who said they had no knowledge of the sale of the leasehold, threatened to seek a court order to stop the construction, scheduled to start this month, or annul their decision to change the zoning.</p>
        <p>''We feel like we were duped by the administration,'' Councilman Liam McLaughlin, chairman of the Council's budget committee, said in an interview. ''We relied on the mayor and on the developer to make accurate representations to us as to the financial details of this project, but now, at the end of the day, we see there was a lot we did not know.''</p>
        <p>The contract says Forest City Ratner must make annual payments of $6.2 million for 72 years, with a 5 percent increase every five years for inflation. Based on the schedule, the Council's accountant, Nick DeSantis, valued the lease at $150 million.</p>
        <p>But Mayor Amicone's spokesman, David Simpson, said the Council's estimate was flawed because it did not take into account a clause allowing the developer to deduct property tax increases from its annual lease fees. In essence, Mr. Simpson said, when council members demanded minimum property revenue payouts from the developer, they depreciated the long-term value of the lease.</p>
        <p>At $26 million, Mr. Simpson added, the price of the lease reflects the value of an appraisal requested by the city in 2002.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robertson, Mr. McLaughlin and the City Council president, Chuck Lesnick, said they were not aware of the fee-reduction clause in the lease contract.</p>
        <p>''The mayor went to a back room with the developer and gave him a sweetheart deal,'' Mr. Robertson said.</p>
        <p>The mayor insisted, however, that the Council had received copies of the contract two years ago and that the contract had been on file at the city clerk's office for about as long.</p>
        <p>''We're not giving anything away,'' Mr. Amicone said.</p>
        <p>In selling the leasehold, the development corporation will be able to settle an $18 million debt incurred when it bought the site from the state in 2004. The city, in turn, will use the remaining $8 million and a one-time preconstruction fee of $10 million paid by the developer to help close a projected $42 million gap in its 2008 budget, the mayor said. If the sale of the leasehold goes through, the city will disband the agency, Mr. Simpson said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Amicone sent his budget to the City Council on April 16, but it has yet to be adopted. If the Council does not act soon, the city may be unable to mail tax bills when the fiscal year starts on July 1 and thus would be forced to tap into its paltry reserves to finance its operations, he said.</p>
        <p>''They're holding off on adopting the budget because they're trying to make political headway in an election year when one of them is running against me,'' Mayor Amicone said, in an implicit reference to Mr. Robertson.</p>
        <p>The Council president, Mr. Lesnick, attributed the delay in adopting the budget to efforts to calculate future income sources based on the new financial realities of the Ridge Hill project as well as an attempt to rearrange expenses to come up with more money for schools.</p>
        <p>''We just want to make sure we do what's best for the city,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
