<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Connecticut Girl Missing Nearly a Year Is Found in a Closet</title>
    <meta content="07missing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/nyregion/07missing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852771"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EFD71E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="886" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Connecticut Girl Missing Nearly a Year Is Found in a Closet</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Connecticut Girl Missing Nearly a Year Is Found in a Closet</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA W. FODERARO and STACEY STOWE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the police showed up with search warrants yesterday morning at a scruffy house on a busy street corner in West Hartford, Conn., they assumed they were looking for evidence in the possible killing of a 15-year-old girl, missing for almost a year.</p>
        <p>Shortly after she disappeared on June 16, the police thought that the girl, whom they called a habitual runaway, had taken off from her home in nearby Bloomfield yet again. But as the investigation unfolded, they found ''bits and pieces of information that suggested foul play,'' said Capt. Jeffrey Blatter of the Bloomfield Police Department, and detectives kept circling back to a dog trainer who was a business acquaintance of the girl's stepfather.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A business acquaintance of the girl’s stepfather faced charges, along with two women who lived with him in the house where the girl was found.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the police showed up with search warrants yesterday morning at a scruffy house on a busy street corner in West Hartford, Conn., they assumed they were looking for evidence in the possible killing of a 15-year-old girl, missing for almost a year.</p>
        <p>Shortly after she disappeared on June 16, the police thought that the girl, whom they called a habitual runaway, had taken off from her home in nearby Bloomfield yet again. But as the investigation unfolded, they found ''bits and pieces of information that suggested foul play,'' said Capt. Jeffrey Blatter of the Bloomfield Police Department, and detectives kept circling back to a dog trainer who was a business acquaintance of the girl's stepfather.</p>
        <p>Yesterday morning, after entering the house on Newington Road, where the dog trainer, Adam Gault, 41, lived with a woman identified as Ann Murphy, 40, the police pushed aside a large bookcase and discovered a locked door that led to a narrow closet under a staircase. Inside was the girl, crouched and pale but not visibly injured.</p>
        <p>''It was so unexpected,'' Captain Blatter said at a news conference. ''The investigators were shocked and very relieved. We never gave up hope, but when we went to do today's search it was unfortunately under a belief that there may be a victim of homicide.''</p>
        <p>But the details of the case seemed to raise as many questions as they answered in terms of the nature of the girl's relationship with Mr. Gault.</p>
        <p>He was charged with second-degree unlawful restraint, second-degree reckless endangerment, second-degree custodial interference, interfering with an officer, risk of injury to a minor and second-degree forgery, and was held in $500,000 bond.</p>
        <p>Ms. Murphy was charged with conspiracy to commit second-degree reckless endangerment, conspiracy to commit second-degree custodial interference and risk of injury to a minor. She was held in $100,000 bond.</p>
        <p>A second woman who lived in the house, Kimberly Cray, 26, was charged with the same crimes that Ms. Murphy is accused of, and was being held in $500,000 bond, said Lt. Dan Coppinger of the West Hartford Police Department.</p>
        <p>All three suspects were scheduled to appear in Superior Court in Hartford today.</p>
        <p>Captain Blatter described the teenager as a ''good student,'' but a ''child from some troubled circumstances.'' He said that she had not been abducted and in fact had ''found what she believed to be a friend'' in Mr. Gault.</p>
        <p>For the past year, she has had no contact with her parents, and the police said there was no evidence that she had been out in public in all that time. Yet investigators said they did not believe that she was holed up in the closet for long; rather, they said, the couple may have hidden the girl there moments before the police moved in to search for DNA and other evidence that they suspected would lead them to her. They said a teenage boy, possibly the son of Mr. Gault or Ms. Murphy, also lived in the house.</p>
        <p>It was unclear whether the teenage girl, who was examined by doctors, had been held against her will.</p>
        <p>''We just don't know yet,'' Captain Blatter said. ''Even if she were to say that she was comfortable in that environment, many of the things we found during the initial search would suggest that any 14-year-old would not have believed that to be a safe, comfortable environment.''</p>
        <p>Later, Captain Blatter described the two-story aluminum-sided house as ''filthy,'' with no sheets on the beds. Investigators also found the ''possibility of sex toys,'' he said. For now, however, none of the charges relate to sex crimes.</p>
        <p>Also at the news conference, Capt. Lori Coppinger of the West Hartford police said the cases of other missing girls were being revisited to determine whether Mr. Gault may have been involved. ''We don't anticipate any girls now missing, but we are familiar with this individual,'' Captain Coppinger said. ''We've had juveniles associated with this individual.''</p>
        <p>Early yesterday evening, officers were still moving through the house, in the blue-collar Elmwood section of West Hartford. A plastic play set shared the weedy yard with a dog run.</p>
        <p>The police did not reveal the girl's identity, but her name and photograph were immediately posted on news Web sites. Captain Blatter said that she was in protective custody. Asked whether she had been harmed by the adults, Captain Blatter said it was safe to assume that a teenager ''under the influence of a 40-year-old has been harmed in some way.''</p>
        <p>It was unclear what kind of life the girl had with her family or why she had run away in the past; Captain Blatter said they were ''concerned'' and ''have been cooperating with us.'' He did not elaborate on Mr. Gault's business relationship with them, but the girl's mother and stepfather own a dog kennel in Bloomfield.</p>
        <p>Dan Milner, a sophomore at Bloomfield High School and a friend of the girl's older brother, said the two of them used to search for the girl when she disappeared. ''She was young and curious,'' he said outside the school. ''It was always like she'd run away and come back home.''</p>
        <p>Another student, Veronica Foster, who said she and the girl had been close in middle school, said, ''We all thought something happened to her.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
