<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Loving New Orleans, With a Ready Escape</title>
    <meta content="07evac" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/garden/07evac.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852680"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E4D91E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1880" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Loving New Orleans, With a Ready Escape</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Loving New Orleans, With a Ready Escape</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIMI READ</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JOANN CLEVENGER, a New Orleans restaurateur, first came here as a teenager, and she loves the city with the romantic zeal of a convert. She's never felt the need to escape it, even temporarily.</p>
        <p>''New Orleans fuels my creative juices,'' said Ms. Clevenger, 68, who presides over her nouvelle Creole restaurant, the Upperline, with Auntie Mame aplomb. Her hair pinned up and falling down, she stands at the door, greeting diners like long-lost friends, her conversation and carefree cackle drifting through dining rooms jammed with paintings and sculptures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Evacuation houses give city residents a piece of home on the run.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JOANN CLEVENGER, a New Orleans restaurateur, first came here as a teenager, and she loves the city with the romantic zeal of a convert. She's never felt the need to escape it, even temporarily.</p>
        <p>''New Orleans fuels my creative juices,'' said Ms. Clevenger, 68, who presides over her nouvelle Creole restaurant, the Upperline, with Auntie Mame aplomb. Her hair pinned up and falling down, she stands at the door, greeting diners like long-lost friends, her conversation and carefree cackle drifting through dining rooms jammed with paintings and sculptures.</p>
        <p>But a year ago, Ms. Clevenger and her husband, Alan Greenacre, 65, drove through southern Mississippi, making a sweep of small towns like McComb, Magnolia, Tylertown and Columbia, assessing them as candidates for a second-home locale.</p>
        <p>''During Katrina, I stayed in a four-room house in Alexandria, Louisiana, with my sister, three dogs, and three other people, including my first husband,'' Ms. Clevenger said. ''I am not a doggy person. If another hurricane or flood comes, I want us to be safe and comfortable. And I want that safe place to be one that gives us joy to make up for missing the joys of New Orleans.''</p>
        <p>Such is life in the Big Uneasy, where garden-variety small talk now includes the perennial question: Where are you evacuating? To cope with the inevitable, many people affluent or creative enough to do so have recently taken a step unparalleled in the city's history: they have bought evacuation homes.</p>
        <p>Paradoxically, leaving makes staying possible. For people who can't bear to tear up their roots, evacuation houses provide a safety net in case the unthinkable happens again and an evacuation turns into another long-term displacement.</p>
        <p>Hurricane season officially started on June 1 and lasts until Nov. 30. While people in other places are discussing summer vacation plans, New Orleans residents are chitchatting about which car they'll take, what multilevel parking garage they'll leave their second car in so it doesn't flood, and which route they will take out of the city. Evacuations and all the preparations they entail have become an inconvenient, and roundly dreaded, but ultimately accepted concomitant to life here.</p>
        <p>Jessica Hack, 57, a textile conservator, lives in an old grocery store in historic Algiers Point, a neighborhood that didn't flood during Katrina. Even so, this storm season she'll be making frequent forays to her 900-square-foot cottage in Natchez, Miss. She bought it six months ago out of foreclosure, sight unseen.</p>
        <p>''I love it,'' Ms. Hack said. ''It backs up on a bayou and I can sit on my screened porch. I've furnished it with antiques and thrift-store finds.''</p>
        <p>''My real estate agent loves me because three of my friends bought houses right after me,'' she continued. ''We just moved part of New Orleans to Natchez, and that's fine with me.''</p>
        <p>Last year, developers even gave serious consideration to creating an evacuation village two hours outside the city -- a pristine New Orleans of the mind near McComb, Miss., with 100 little prefabricated shotgun and camelback houses, a nine-hole golf course and other amenities. ''It was cute, cute, cute, I'm telling you!'' said Bennett Davis, the commercial realtor who conceived the project with the developers, a partnership called Karlton/I.S.G. ''The houses were geared to middle-class people and were going to be done in typical Uptown New Orleans style, with all the gingerbread, quaintness and high ceilings. 'Evacuation Vacation' was our tagline. I still think it's a great idea!''</p>
        <p>THIRTY years ago, New Orleanians did not flee storms en masse. When a hurricane was brewing in the Gulf of Mexico, ''you got your batteries, water, candles, and you knew it was going to be exciting,'' said Jerry Winsberg, 66, a retired criminal court judge who now owns an evacuation house on a golf course in St. Francisville, La., though neither he nor his wife, Isabel, plays golf.</p>
        <p>Joseph Maselli, 59, a lawyer who grew up here and now has an evacuation house in Baton Rouge, said: ''It was a day off from school, and we'd listen to the trees whipping around. If it flooded a little, we'd go outside with umbrellas and wade through it. It had nothing to do with people dying.''</p>
        <p>Some bons vivants even stocked up on liquor and threw hurricane parties. But since the 1980s, the custom of evacuating has grown widespread, probably because of multiple forces: the city's deteriorating infrastructure; erosion in Louisiana's barrier islands, which allows much more powerful hurricanes to reach land; the barrage of apocalyptic predictions by hurricane and flood experts published every so often in The Times-Picayune of New Orleans; and fear of crime after a hurricane.</p>
        <p>The tragedies of Katrina, of course, vindicated habitual evacuees. And memories of 2005 will probably pry loose many of the remaining stubborn souls who have refused to clear out for hurricanes so far.</p>
        <p>Anne Strachan Eichin, 54, is a jewelry sales representative who lives in an elegantly furnished cottage on a leafy block in the Uptown neighborhood. An old-school, sit-out-the-storm native, she evacuated for the first time for Katrina, giving in to her Yankee husband's pleas and packing up the car at the last minute. Mrs. Eichin now owns a fully furnished and stocked evacuation house, a graceful 1840s center hall cottage in St. Francisville, La.</p>
        <p>''All my life I was a terrible New Orleans snob,'' Mrs. Eichin said. ''But I needed a lifeboat. Now I love St. Francisville. The architecture is magnificent, the people are wonderful, the land is rolling and we have fall foliage. It's not the same old tropical swamp.''</p>
        <p>If Katrina had any silver linings, one might be that it broke the city's hypnotic spell over some of its most fervent devotees long enough for them to appreciate the charms of other places.</p>
        <p>''I knew that Paris, France, existed,'' said Patrick Dunne, the proprietor of a French Quarter antique shop called Lucullus, who declined to give his age. ''I knew that New York and Los Angeles existed. But whatever was north and west of Lake Pontchartrain was very amorphous to me.''</p>
        <p>Not anymore. Three months after Katrina, Mr. Dunne closed one of his two New Orleans shops and opened a new high-style store in an unlikely spot -- Breaux Bridge, La., a winsome little town in Cajun country.</p>
        <p>Then he and his Paris-born partner, Zoubir Tabout, settled on a glamorous hurricane hideaway: a late 18th-century manor house raised on brick piers called Serenity. It sits on a hill 54 feet above sea level in Washington, La., a historic town about 30 minutes from the Breaux Bridge store.</p>
        <p>Seemingly overnight, Mr. Dunne has become someone who extols the beauties of the Louisiana countryside. On weekends, he and Mr. Tabout drive to Serenity, moving books and furniture from their New Orleans house in the Faubourg Marigny neighborhood. Then they drive back with a cargo of roses for their New Orleans house.</p>
        <p>These rituals soothe them both. Like many others, Mr. Dunne and Mr. Tabout have found that having an evacuation house acts as balm to a shattered sense of place and home. With foreboding or foresight or paranoia -- take your pick -- Mr. Dunne and Mr. Tabout have furnished the Washington place so that it echoes their New Orleans house. It's all part of an effort to counterbalance imagined losses that could become real.</p>
        <p>''There's a relationship between the houses like a relationship between people,'' Mr. Dunne said. ''Should we lose either house, a part of both will be there. Who knows what tricks the earth has yet to play on us?''</p>
        <p>Sooner or later, all New Orleans residents must ask themselves, is it worth it? Why live in a city that fills you with dread about something as fundamental as home?</p>
        <p>According to Nick Spitzer, a professor of folklore and the host of public radio's ''American Routes,'' the answer probably has to do with New Orleanians' bonds with the people around them and with a landscape imprinted with a long, colorful history.</p>
        <p>''In the modern world, we are increasingly cut off from community, but in New Orleans, this is much less the case,'' said Mr. Spitzer, 56, who teaches at the University of New Orleans and has lived in Louisiana on and off since 1974. ''Here, the culture is at the center of the civitas; it is not an add-on. A jazz funeral, a carnival parade, a great meal, a crawfish boil and the Jazz Fest are part of communal life, and they inspire a huge attachment.''</p>
        <p>But such loyalty doesn't protect people from mood swings or misgivings, which often arise just after some local politician bungles an aspect of the recovery effort or says something embarrassingly weird in the national press.</p>
        <p>''One day I'll wake up and feel so in love and so happy with New Orleans, and the next day I'll be so fed up I don't think I can stand it another day,'' said Josephine Sacabo, 62, a photographer known for her romantic, introspective images.</p>
        <p>Ms. Sacabo and her husband, Dalt Wonk, 64, a playwright, are long-time New Orleanians who live in an atmospheric French Quarter home. Recently, though, they bought two historic houses they intend to weave together in downtown San Miguel de Allende, Mexico, a carefully preserved colonial town in the mountains north of Mexico City.</p>
        <p>''The whole 'just in case' mentality did not exist for me, but now it does,'' Ms. Sacabo said.</p>
        <p>''I don't feel sad to be away,'' she continued. ''Life down there is beautiful and compelling.'' But whenever she returns to the French Quarter, Ms. Sacabo said, she becomes euphoric: ''I love the plants, the smells, the weather, the architecture.''</p>
        <p>''I think it was Tennessee Williams who wrote that he was always attracted to the humanity of the defeated,'' she said. ''The defeated quality is a problematic thing to be in love with, but it's irresistible.''</p>
        <p>AS for Ms. Clevenger, the restaurateur, she finally did find her evacuation paradise. Passing through Columbia, Miss. (population 6,408), she glanced through a garden gate and spied a bottle tree -- an exemplar of the rural Southern tradition of sticking brightly colored bottles onto the branches of dead trees to capture evil spirits.</p>
        <p>''Back up!'' she said excitedly to her husband. She ended up having an animated conversation with the homeowner, and a few months later, when she and her husband visited Columbia again, the property next door was up for sale. By 5 p.m. the next day, they owned the house, a clapboard cottage with a large front porch, a gabled roof and a garden.</p>
        <p>It wasn't long before Ms. Clevenger and Mr. Greenacre began heading for Columbia every weekend. ''In this small block of this small town in Mississippi, we have this complete world,'' she said. ''People invite us to their porches to drink wine. There's a social worker, a riverboat pilot whose nickname is Hotfoot, and a preacher. Sometimes I go to Hattiesburg and buy books or antiques, and when I get home, people come over to examine what I've bought. In a way, it's just like a neighborhood in New Orleans.''</p>
        <p>But in no way does the new house mean she and Mr. Greenacre would ever give up on New Orleans, she said: ''We go there to refresh ourselves, so that we can come back here and be brave.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
