<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bracing For the Demise Of the Big Guy</title>
    <meta content="07towns" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/nyregion/07towns.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070612T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852790"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OUR TOWNS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4D61E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bracing For the Demise Of the Big Guy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bracing for the Demise of the Big Guy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER APPLEBOME</byline>
      <dateline>CLIFTON, N.J.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Highlights? Where to start? Her role as an extra, shopping for T-shirts in East Newark while Paulie Walnuts gets the cellphone call telling him he has prostate cancer in Season 6, Episode 9? The trip to Harriman State Park in New York, where she somehow found the cast filming the epic Pine Barrens episode?</p>
        <p>Her world-class tchotchkes -- the party favors from Jamie-Lynn Sigler's real-world wedding, the bowling shirt with the autographs of 28 ''Sopranos'' cast members, the key to the City of Miami given to cast members?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“The Sopranos” may not be about real people, but it is about a real place, which is why one woman’s passion for place and show have a logical intersection.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Highlights? Where to start? Her role as an extra, shopping for T-shirts in East Newark while Paulie Walnuts gets the cellphone call telling him he has prostate cancer in Season 6, Episode 9? The trip to Harriman State Park in New York, where she somehow found the cast filming the epic Pine Barrens episode?</p>
        <p>Her world-class tchotchkes -- the party favors from Jamie-Lynn Sigler's real-world wedding, the bowling shirt with the autographs of 28 ''Sopranos'' cast members, the key to the City of Miami given to cast members?</p>
        <p>Or just the pure moments of ''Sopranos'' satori, driving down Kearney Avenue in 1999, delivering blood in her day job and reaching the intersection of Kearney and Duke, and saying, ''Of course. That's Satriale's Pork Store'' -- or at least the old auto parts store they used to film it.</p>
        <p>Yes, Soprano Sue, or Sue Sadik before she became a made woman, has lived the ''Sopranos'' story more than most of us and perhaps more than is good for anyone's mental health. But as the faithful await the rapture, the last days of life as we know it leading up to Sunday's finale, she can serve as one stand-in for the other denizens of the Sopranos-Industrial Complex as they try to channel what they've shared since 1999.</p>
        <p>''Jersey used to be a place that people just saw from a window on the Turnpike,'' said Ms. Sadik, who has become a recurring sidelight in ''Sopranos'' lore through her Web site (sopranosuessightings.com), expert commentary and uncanny ability to locate almost every sign, Turnpike exit, and diner shown. ''Now you've got people from all over the world getting off the tour bus to get their picture taken with the garbage dumpster outside the Bada Bing. I love my state.''</p>
        <p>This is a big week for others as well. Pizzaland, seen in the opening credits, stopped taking orders yesterday so it could ship hundreds of pizzas around the country. The On Location Tour of Sopranos sites (four hours, $40, cannoli included) is sure to sell out Saturday and Sunday.</p>
        <p>As she tells it, Ms. Sadik, who is Dutch (''You're not much if you're not Dutch''), not Italian, had zero interest in some dopey show about some dopey singers until she happened to see the opening credits and realized that she could recognize almost every sight from her job running her delivery company since 1988. Soon picking out the Carteret tank farms, the Route 1/9 truck route bridge crossing the Hackensack River and the Valley Landscaping water tower, wasn't enough. She became an expert for others' Web sites, then her own, then the lady who managed to show up at every shoot.</p>
        <p>We get in her blue 2000 Celica for a quick tour, ''Sopranos'' theme music blaring from the CD player.</p>
        <p>''It's not as prevalent as it was years ago, but organized crime is part of our history,'' she says. ''Organized crime is much better than disorganized crime. Go down to Camden if you want to see disorganized crime.''</p>
        <p>She turns onto Lexington Avenue and stops at the new school, which used to be the construction site where Vito Spatafore was seen committing a homosexual sex act that eventually led to his being whacked. Then it's the Botany Plaza Pathmark, where Carmela and Dr. Melfi ran into each other. She heads south on Route 21, then onto Passaic Avenue past the dock where Christopher got beat up and Dick Barone's son later got his kneecaps broken.</p>
        <p>Then to Kearney for Satriale's, the Irish-American club that was turned into an Italian-American club for the show, the Sip 'n' Dunk, the original Sopranos family church -- St. Cecelia's in real life. And then off to the Bada Bing in Lodi, known to tourists and locals far and wide in real life as Satin Dolls. ''Sopranos'' mania or not, it was as dead as Richie Aprile, who was a dead man before he was a dead man.</p>
        <p>HER phone rings. It's her husband, who is annoyed that she doesn't recognize his voice over the music. ''I'm at the Bada Bing. I can't hear,'' she says grumpily. ''Make your own dinner.''</p>
        <p>''The Sopranos'' may not be about real people, but it is about a real place, which is why her passion for place and show have a logical intersection. ''People here have something real inside them,'' she says. ''It's not like California, land of the fruits and the nuts. I was there for my sister's baby shower. I said 'Who's your best caterer?' and they give me a chain. I mean, who wants to get catered by Applebee's?''</p>
        <p>We get back in the car. The CD player is blasting the ''Peter Gunn'' theme and ''Every Breath You Take'' by the Police.</p>
        <p>Carmela's voice comes on.</p>
        <p>''What kind of animal smokes marijuana at his own confirmation?'' she hollers.</p>
        <p>OUR TOWNS E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 12, 2007, Tuesday  The Our Towns column on Thursday, about Sue Sadik, a woman from Clifton, N.J., who reflected on her passion for all things ''Sopranos'' in advance of the series' final episode, misspelled the name of the real street and town where the fictional Satriale's Pork Store is located. It is Kearny Avenue in Kearny, not Kearney. The article also gave an erroneous spelling in some copies for a restaurant chain that Ms. Sadik referred to in disparaging catering options in California, a state she compared unfavorably to New Jersey. It is Applebee's, not Appleby's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 12, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>The Our Towns column on Thursday, about Sue Sadik, a woman from Clifton, N.J., who reflected on her passion for all things ''Sopranos'' in advance of the series' final episode, misspelled the name of the real street and town where the fictional Satriale's Pork Store is located. It is Kearny Avenue in Kearny, not Kearney. The article also gave an erroneous spelling in some copies for a restaurant chain that Ms. Sadik referred to in disparaging catering options in California, a state she compared unfavorably to New Jersey. It is Applebee's, not Appleby's.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
