<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Brazilian Numbers Game Ties Officials to Mobsters</title>
    <meta content="07brazil" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/world/americas/07brazil.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852700"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brazil</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohter, Larry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brazil</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E7D81E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1287" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Brazilian Numbers Game Ties Officials to Mobsters</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Brazilian Numbers Game Ties Officials to Mobsters</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohter, Larry</byline>
      <dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Raids by Brazilian Federal Police have uncovered big payoffs to judges, police officers and lawyers from bosses who run Brazil's ubiquitous illegal lottery known as 'animal game'; more than 40 people face criminal charges, yet game goes on; game is deeply embedded in Brazilian culture and judicial rulings favorable to game's powerful bosses have blunted effect of prohibition; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The illegal lottery known as ''the animal game'' is as visible a part of the urban landscape here as Ipanema beach or Sugarloaf mountain. On thousands of street corners, vendors sit all day at little wooden booths, pads of paper in hand, taking money from bettors, who return later to check results posted on lampposts or walls.</p>
        <p>The bosses of the billion-dollar industry known in Portuguese as the ''jogo do bicho,'' on the other hand, have long preferred to operate in the shadows. That was, at least, until a burgeoning corruption scandal suddenly thrust them into an uncomfortable national spotlight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A burgeoning corruption scandal has suddenly thrust the bosses of the billion-dollar industry known as “the animal game” into an uncomfortable spotlight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The illegal lottery known as ''the animal game'' is as visible a part of the urban landscape here as Ipanema beach or Sugarloaf mountain. On thousands of street corners, vendors sit all day at little wooden booths, pads of paper in hand, taking money from bettors, who return later to check results posted on lampposts or walls.</p>
        <p>The bosses of the billion-dollar industry known in Portuguese as the ''jogo do bicho,'' on the other hand, have long preferred to operate in the shadows. That was, at least, until a burgeoning corruption scandal suddenly thrust them into an uncomfortable national spotlight.</p>
        <p>Raids by the Federal Police have uncovered big payoffs to judges, police officers, prosecutors and lawyers from the bosses who run the game. More than 40 people face criminal charges, mounds of documents have been seized and $6 million in cash has been confiscated.</p>
        <p>Among those jailed are some of the wealthiest and most powerful of the game's kingpins, as well as judges accused of issuing favorable rulings to keep the game running in return for payoffs, sometime as much as $15,000 a month.</p>
        <p>Yet for all the talk of a crackdown, the game goes on. And to Brazilians, that says a lot about the ambiguous relationship between those who control the game and those who make and enforce the laws.</p>
        <p>''The animal game is a deeply embedded cultural phenomenon with a certain romantic aura, and thus hard to eradicate,'' said Denise Frossard, a crusading former judge who became famous here in the 1990s for sending 14 bosses to jail.</p>
        <p>''But it is also a quintessentially Brazilian way of laundering money,'' she added, ''and contributes greatly to the problem of impunity in this country.''</p>
        <p>Playing the game is complicated but potentially lucrative. Players can bet on any combination of two-, three- or four-digit numbers, the last two digits of which are associated with any one of 25 animals, ranging from the alligator to the turkey. The biggest payoff, $4,000 for a one-dollar bet, is awarded to those who ''hit the thousand,'' or correctly pick a winning four-digit number.</p>
        <p>''If I dream of a rooster, well then of course I'll bet on a rooster,'' said Sílvio Cunha, who works as a doorman at an apartment building here. ''When my mother comes to visit, I bet on her flight number, and when I get my telephone bill I bet on that number too. You need always to be alert to numbers that can bring you luck.''</p>
        <p>The animal game was created in the 1890s by the owner of a zoo here as a way to promote his venture. It became almost instantly popular, which soon led the government, fearing that money would be drained away from official lotteries, to ban it.</p>
        <p>For decades official policy fluctuated between tolerance of the game, fueled by generous payoffs to authorities, and intermittent campaigns to snuff it out. Finally, in 1946, the government outlawed casinos and games of chance, the animal game among them.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless it survives. Today it is played everywhere in Brazil, including remote corners of the Amazon, but continues to be controlled from Rio by about a dozen bosses, called bicheiros.</p>
        <p>Winning numbers are picked twice daily at a downtown building that serves as the syndicate headquarters. The results are immediately sent to the thousands of betting points across the country.</p>
        <p>Brazilian slang is peppered with references to the animal game. Bicheiros recur as characters in Brazilian films, novels and television programs, most recently on an HBO mini-series similar to ''The Sopranos.''</p>
        <p>Numerous sambas have been written about the game. In one of the most famous, ''I Hit the Thousand,'' a lucky bettor exults at fulfilling the poor man's dream: ''I won 500 smackers, and now I'm not going to work anymore.''</p>
        <p>Though many Brazilians are reluctant to acknowledge it, bicheiros also play a central, even essential, role in Carnival here. Not only do they contribute the money that allows the samba ''schools'' to parade with elaborate floats and costumes, but they sometimes act as their ''honorary presidents.''</p>
        <p>This year and last, directors of samba schools were killed shortly before Carnival in what the authorities described as murders related to disputes about control of the animal game.</p>
        <p>Among those jailed in this most recent scandal was Ailton Guimarães, president of the league of samba schools, who is said by authorities to be the animal game's boss of bosses.</p>
        <p>Mr. Guimarães, whose nickname is Captain -- his rank when he took part in military operations against left-wing guerrilla groups in the 1970s -- has declined several requests by The New York Times for interviews in recent years.</p>
        <p>But at a court hearing in April he said that he was active in the animal game only between 1982 and 1993 and that he made his living now as a ''financial consultant,'' earning commissions of as much as $200,000 a month from clients investing in the stock market.</p>
        <p>''He's the one who brought an organizational sense and structure to the game,'' said Ms. Frossard, the former judge, who has been the target of assassination attempts that she attributes to hired guns in the pay of game kingpins. ''He also encouraged the group to try to capture the state, at all three levels of government and all three branches, instead of just paying off the police.''</p>
        <p>Since the beginning of the 1990s bicheiros have sought to expand their activities to bingo parlors, video poker and slot machines, known here as ''nickel hunters.''</p>
        <p>That effort has led indirectly to the latest scandal, which is the third this decade to occur in an administration led by the leftist Workers' Party.</p>
        <p>When the party governed Rio Grande do Sul, the home state of Brazil's justice minister, animal game kingpins donated $500,000 for the purchase of the party headquarters there, a former party official said at a parliamentary inquiry. At one point a tape was played in which a party fund-raiser could be heard urging the chief of police to go easy on numbers runners.</p>
        <p>In 2004 a videotape surfaced in which one of President Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva's top political operatives was seen offering to rewrite an online lottery contract to favor an animal game boss nicknamed Charlie Waterfall. In return, the bicheiro promised to contribute more than $100,000 to the Workers' Party campaign and to pay a one percent commission to the official, who had to resign as a result.</p>
        <p>Shortly afterward, Mr. da Silva, who had originally favored legalizing the animal game, issued a temporary decree outlawing bingo parlors. But the Senate refused to make the measure permanent. Bicheiros and their associates have obtained judicial rulings, many of them issued by judges later taken into custody, that have blunted the effect of the prohibition.</p>
        <p>Mr. da Silva's chief of staff, Dilma Rousseff, has now indicated that the government is considering an about-face and is at least willing to study the possibility of legalizing the animal game.</p>
        <p>''It's not a simple question,'' she said recently, but ''it's obvious that as the investigations deepen, an institutional model for the question of games of chance is going to be delineated in Brazil.''</p>
        <p>Some Brazilians oppose legalization on moral grounds or because they fear that it would attract foreign crime organizations. Others are simply skeptical.</p>
        <p>''I'd wager that legalization is never going to happen,'' Luiz Carlos Menezes de Sá, a waiter, predicted after placing a 50-cent bet on 3568, a number associated with the monkey.</p>
        <p>''Without their bribes from the bicheiros, the politicians, cops and judges wouldn't be able to live high on the hog the way they do,'' he said. ''Why would they want to do away with something that makes so much money for them?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
