<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Duncan Has Parker. James Has Himself.</title>
    <meta content="07nba" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070612T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852823"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EFD61E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="945" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Duncan Has Parker. James Has Himself.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <dateline>SAN ANTONIO, June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Cleveland Cavaliers bumped into their first logistical challenge here Wednesday, on the eve of their first N.B.A. finals: Who takes the microphone at the league-mandated news conference?</p>
        <p>Traditionally, each team sends the coach and two star players to the main interview room. San Antonio Spurs Coach Gregg Popovich was followed on the dais, naturally, by Tony Parker and Tim Duncan. The Cavaliers had Coach Mike Brown and LeBron James and, well, then it got tricky.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Cleveland Cavaliers bumped into their first logistical challenge here Wednesday, on the eve of their first N.B.A. finals: Who takes the microphone at the league-mandated news conference?</p>
        <p>Traditionally, each team sends the coach and two star players to the main interview room. San Antonio Spurs Coach Gregg Popovich was followed on the dais, naturally, by Tony Parker and Tim Duncan. The Cavaliers had Coach Mike Brown and LeBron James and, well, then it got tricky.</p>
        <p>The task ultimately fell to Daniel Gibson, a second-round draft pick nicknamed Boobie, who until last week was virtually anonymous, even in Cleveland. ''Who else are you going to send in there?'' someone wondered rhetorically. Who indeed.</p>
        <p>The answer to that question may have a lot to do with how long this best-of-seven series lasts, and whether the Cavaliers have any chance of pulling an upset in the finals, which open Thursday night. James may be the N.B.A.'s brightest star and its greatest hope, but three of the four best players in this series are wearing silver and black: Duncan, Parker and Manu Ginóbili.</p>
        <p>The Spurs have all of the experience, the three crisp championship banners and a cast of role players who have been there and done that, then done it again. The Cavaliers have James. And James has Boobie.</p>
        <p>''There's no former All-Stars, there's no top 50 players -- he's it,'' Will Perdue, a former N.B.A. center and ESPN Radio analyst, said of James. ''He's got to have an outlet. And the thing is, as well as Gibson has played, they got nobody that's proven, night in and night out.''</p>
        <p>N.B.A. championships are generally built on the backs of dynamic duos. Michael Jordan had Scottie Pippen. Shaquille O'Neal had Kobe Bryant, then Dwyane Wade. Duncan had David Robinson, and later Ginóbili and Parker.</p>
        <p>Cleveland has no Robin to James's Batman, which seems problematic. The only Cavalier with an All-Star appearance on his résumé is center Zydrunas Ilgauskas, and he is on the downside of his career. After James, the Cavaliers have few players who can create scoring chances. Their next most dynamic wing player, Larry Hughes, is limping on an injured left foot and is shooting 36 percent in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>The Cavaliers are powered by the rugged interior play of Anderson Varejão, the occasional low-post scoring of Ilgauskas and the outside shooting of Gibson, Donyell Marshall and Sasha Pavlovic.</p>
        <p>But James carries a heavy load, averaging 25.8 points, 8.3 assists and 8.3 rebounds in the playoffs. The Cavaliers' next best scorer is Ilgauskas, at 13.8 points. In the series clincher against Detroit in the Eastern Conference finals, Gibson, a rookie, scored 31 points -- just 10 points fewer than he had in the first two rounds combined.</p>
        <p>The Cavaliers are possibly the least talented team the Spurs have faced in the postseason. San Antonio beat Denver (featuring Carmelo Anthony, Allen Iverson and Marcus Camby) in the first round, then eliminated multifaceted Phoenix (with Steve Nash, Amare Stoudemire and Shawn Marion) in the conference semifinals. The Spurs advanced to the finals by beating Utah's brilliant inside-out tandem of Deron Williams and Carlos Boozer.</p>
        <p>James presents an incredible package of size and strength, with a deft scoring touch and uncanny passing ability. But if James falters, or is suffocated by the Spurs' vaunted defense, the Cavaliers will have nowhere to turn.</p>
        <p>''We've had different guys step up in different games,'' Ilgauskas said. ''We might not have superstars, but we have a lot of guys that can play good basketball.''</p>
        <p>Cleveland got this far -- beating Washington, the Nets and Detroit -- because of outstanding defense and James's ability to lift those around him. The Cavaliers, however, have not faced a team anywhere near the Spurs' caliber, or with their finals experience. Between them, Duncan, Parker, Ginóbili, Bruce Bowen and Robert Horry have 15 championship rings. The only Cavalier who has even played in the finals is the reserve guard Eric Snow, who lost with Seattle in 1996 and Philadelphia in 2001.</p>
        <p>Eight years ago, it was Duncan who made his finals debut, to considerably less fanfare. But Duncan had a number of advantages that James does not. Robinson was still the face of the franchise, and his quest to win his first championship was the biggest story of the series.</p>
        <p>''I think it was huge, in the sense that he could deflect a lot of the attention,'' said Perdue, who was a Spurs reserve that year. ''Tim back then, I think he was still learning the ropes a little bit.''</p>
        <p>Although he is indisputably the Spurs' focal point now, Duncan said that in 1999 he was ''more a piece of the puzzle,'' whereas James is clearly ''a much bigger piece'' of the Cavaliers' scheme. ''They're asking him to do a lot more,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Aside from Robinson, Duncan had savvy veterans like Avery Johnson, Sean Elliott and Mario Elie to guide him. That atmosphere, Duncan said, ''made it easier for me to play the game and not be so stressed about it.''</p>
        <p>Not that the 22-year-old James is showing any signs of stress. The finals cast an immense spotlight on star players, but James has been skillfully navigating these waters since he was a high school phenom in Akron, Ohio.</p>
        <p>''There's no added pressure for me,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Few expected James to make it this far, this soon. Few now expect him to single-handedly take down the Spurs, even though the Cavaliers just beat a Pistons team that had more talent and finals experience. James shrugged at the thought.</p>
        <p>''We haven't been on the everyone-picks-the-Cleveland-Cavaliers side yet,'' he said with a relaxed smile. ''So it's nothing new for us.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 12, 2007, Tuesday  A sports article in some copies yesterday about Eric Snow's role with the Cleveland Cavaliers in this year's N.B.A. finals misstated the year of a previous trip to the finals by Snow when he was with Seattle. It was 1996, not 1995.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 12, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A sports article in some copies yesterday about Eric Snow's role with the Cleveland Cavaliers in this year's N.B.A. finals misstated the year of a previous trip to the finals by Snow when he was with Seattle. It was 1996, not 1995.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
