<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recalling D-Day, Gates Urges a Stronger Alliance</title>
    <meta content="07gates" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/world/europe/07gates.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852710"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Normandy (France)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mazzetti, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Robert M (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Normandy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Gates, Robert M</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E5D81E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recalling D-Day, Gates Urges a Stronger Alliance</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Recalling D-Day, Gates Urges a Stronger Alliance</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK MAZZETTI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mazzetti, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>COLLEVILLE-SUR-MER, France, June 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sec of Defense Robert M Gates gives speech commemorating World War II Normandy invasion, in which he says indispensable alliances between United States and its European allies must endure; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beside a churning sea and an ocean of white marble crosses, Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates said Wednesday that the United States and its European allies should honor the thousands of Americans buried here by strengthening the alliance that they died defending.</p>
        <p>As light rain descended from a gray Normandy sky, Mr. Gates said that the allied invasion on D-Day was founded on ''the belief that that blood of free men could wash away the stains of tyranny.'' But America's ties to Europe are now threatened, he said, by those who ''believe that the foundations of the alliance forged in places like this have collapsed or outlived their usefulness.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates said that disagreements between the U.S. and France should not overshadow what the two nations had in common.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Beside a churning sea and an ocean of white marble crosses, Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates said Wednesday that the United States and its European allies should honor the thousands of Americans buried here by strengthening the alliance that they died defending.</p>
        <p>As light rain descended from a gray Normandy sky, Mr. Gates said that the allied invasion on D-Day was founded on ''the belief that that blood of free men could wash away the stains of tyranny.'' But America's ties to Europe are now threatened, he said, by those who ''believe that the foundations of the alliance forged in places like this have collapsed or outlived their usefulness.''</p>
        <p>At one point, directly addressing his French counterpart, Minister of Defense Hervé Morin, Mr. Gates said that disagreements between the United States and France that made for an often stormy relationship should not overshadow what the two nations had in common.</p>
        <p>''Let the people of our nations never forget that we are bound by history and values just as we are bound by blood,'' Mr. Gates said. ''The blood for everyone who has ever perished in defense of the lofty ideals that gave rise to and still underpin our great alliance.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates's speech was not typical of many given by Bush administration officials on patriotic days of remembrance. There was no mention either of Iraq or Afghanistan, and no direct attempt to link the sacrifices of the past with America's current military conflicts.</p>
        <p>Instead, the speech's theme was broader and more elemental: that the indispensable alliances of the past must endure in the future.</p>
        <p>America's relations with some of its most important European allies have frayed significantly in the past five years, primarily over the decision to go to war in Iraq. Mr. Gates's predecessor, Donald H. Rumsfeld, further inflamed tensions by occasionally suggesting that alliances like NATO were cold-war relics that needed to be overhauled.</p>
        <p>But the Bush administration more recently has made efforts to heal the trans-Atlantic rift as it seeks allies against Islamic radicalism and European help through NATO for the fighting in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates, who arrived in Paris on Tuesday, was the first American defense secretary to visit France in nearly a decade. He assumed the post in December after being out of government since 1993, and seems puzzled and dismayed at times by the actions of America's European allies.</p>
        <p>Last weekend in Singapore, he expressed frustration that despite a pool of 2.3 million troops, European members of NATO were unable to make up a shortfall of 3,000 soldiers needed to train the Afghan Army and police forces.</p>
        <p>But as a self-described ''cold warrior,'' Mr. Gates seems to believe that despite the occasional headaches, the Atlantic alliance that outlasted the Soviet Union is invaluable for the more complex fight against Islamic extremism that Western nations face today.</p>
        <p>Using vivid and lofty language in his speech at the Normandy American Cemetery, Mr. Gates invoked a day 63 years ago that ''unfolded as if it were a lifetime.'' He quoted an American soldier who recalled that the first men to land on Omaha Beach in 1944 were cut down by enemy fire and tumbled ''just like corncobs off of a conveyor belt.''</p>
        <p>The cemetery is the burial site of 9,387 Americans who died during the Normandy invasion. After his speech, Mr. Gates cut the ribbon on a $30 million visitor center on the cemetery grounds, perched on a bluff overlooking Omaha Beach. The money for the visitor center was authorized by Congress in 2001.</p>
        <p>Such memorial sites are essential, Mr. Gates said, to ensure that the heroism of those who fought is not forgotten, and that ''the passage of time and the thinning of their ranks will never dim the glory of their deeds.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
