<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pull Over, You With the Lead Foot: Your TV Career Awaits</title>
    <meta content="07hale" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/arts/television/07hale.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852667"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Court TV</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6D91E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="524" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pull Over, You With the Lead Foot: Your TV Career Awaits</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pull Over, You With the Lead Foot: Your TV Career Awaits</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE HALE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>True-crime reality shows can be named after the enforcers (''Dog the Bounty Hunter''), the miscreants (''America's Most Wanted'') or both (''Bandits vs. Smokies''). The creators of ''Speeders,'' which makes its debut tonight on Court TV, went with the bad guys -- perhaps because the natural alternative, ''Traffic Cops,'' would have made it just a little too obvious where they got their ideas.</p>
        <p>''Speeders,'' based on the pilot, is ''Cops'' without the guns and the running. The camera rides along with officers as they identify and apprehend the titular lawbreakers; subject them to a mild dose of on-camera humiliation that leaves you amazed, for the millionth time, that people sign releases; and then conduct rueful post-mortem discussions of the imperfections of human nature.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Speeders” is “Cops” without the guns and the running.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>True-crime reality shows can be named after the enforcers (''Dog the Bounty Hunter''), the miscreants (''America's Most Wanted'') or both (''Bandits vs. Smokies''). The creators of ''Speeders,'' which makes its debut tonight on Court TV, went with the bad guys -- perhaps because the natural alternative, ''Traffic Cops,'' would have made it just a little too obvious where they got their ideas.</p>
        <p>''Speeders,'' based on the pilot, is ''Cops'' without the guns and the running. The camera rides along with officers as they identify and apprehend the titular lawbreakers; subject them to a mild dose of on-camera humiliation that leaves you amazed, for the millionth time, that people sign releases; and then conduct rueful post-mortem discussions of the imperfections of human nature.</p>
        <p>Perhaps because of the lack of action -- there's so little actual human movement that you begin to notice the fine points of climbing from a patrol car in traffic -- the series puts more emphasis on personality, with dating-show-style introductions of the officers. And they talk a lot, because otherwise you're watching them point radar guns and walk to and from their cars. It makes you a little nostalgic for the world-weary, taciturn cops of ''Cops.''</p>
        <p>Of course that's all just framing for the real payoff of this kind of show: the self-righteous, clueless, pathetic behavior of the apprehended. And after all these years it's still pretty funny. ''I just got my shoes, man,'' whines a college student pulled over for doing 65 in a 40-mile-an-hour zone. ''I'm on the way to the gym. I swear to God's life.''</p>
        <p>Others get angry; two speeders actually turn to the camera, after the officers have walked away, and refer to them with a term that can't be printed in this newspaper even when uttered by the president. Comedic gold arrives in the form of a drunken-driving suspect in California who admits to having had a couple of drinks of ''modka'' and can't recite the alphabet past H.</p>
        <p>For some reason Officer Darin Germaine of the Laguna Beach Police Department quizzes him on his education level -- you have to wonder whose idea that was -- setting up the episode's best exchange:</p>
        <p>''Did you get a degree?''</p>
        <p>''Yes.''</p>
        <p>''In what?''</p>
        <p>''In ... in ... speech communicama ... speech communications.''</p>
        <p>''That's not working real well for you right now.''</p>
        <p>I'm not sure if that kind of mild amusement will be enough to thrive in Thursday prime time, even during the summer. (One way to stick around for 20 seasons, like ''Cops,'' is to stick to Saturday night.)</p>
        <p>Just for a little insurance the producers of ''Speeders'' tack on their most ''Cops''-like moment at the end of the half-hour: found video of a traffic stop during which two drunk women take off most of their clothes and prance half-naked in the street. They're the only women with speaking roles.</p>
        <p>Speeders  Court TV, tonight at 8, Eastern and Pacific times; 7, Central time.</p>
        <p>John Stevens and Barry Poznick, executive producers; Christine Cavalieri, supervising producer. For Court TV: Robyn Hutt, senior executive producer; Diane Best, executive producer; Ed Hersh, executive in charge of production. Produced by Zoo Productions.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
