<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Belmont Is Curlin's Race to Lose</title>
    <meta content="07draw" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/sports/othersports/07draw.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852769"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EFD71E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="700" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Belmont Is Curlin's Race to Lose</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Curlin Gets His Chance to Become a Big Star</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As good as he is, Curlin has never been the big star. There were 20 horses in the Kentucky Derby, too many for any one to stand out as the one to watch. In the Preakness Stakes, it was all about Street Sense, which was no surprise considering he was dominant two weeks earlier in the Derby.</p>
        <p>Now comes the Belmont Stakes, a race Street Sense will skip and only seven horses will contest. That leaves the talented Curlin alone on top of the heap. This is his show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After seven horses were entered Wednesday for Saturday’s Belmont, Curlin was installed as the 6-5 morning-line favorite, reflective of his status as the nation’s top 3-year-old.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As good as he is, Curlin has never been the big star. There were 20 horses in the Kentucky Derby, too many for any one to stand out as the one to watch. In the Preakness Stakes, it was all about Street Sense, which was no surprise considering he was dominant two weeks earlier in the Derby.</p>
        <p>Now comes the Belmont Stakes, a race Street Sense will skip and only seven horses will contest. That leaves the talented Curlin alone on top of the heap. This is his show.</p>
        <p>After seven horses were entered yesterday for Saturday's Belmont, the final leg of the Triple Crown, Curlin was installed as the 6-5 morning-line favorite, reflective of his status as the nation's top 3-year-old. By post time, his odds could be even lower. He will break from post No. 3 in the mile-and-a-half race, in which post positions will be all but meaningless because of the lengthy distance, the small field and the relatively long run to the first turn.</p>
        <p>''Curlin definitely deserves to be the favorite,'' said Larry Jones, the trainer of the Belmont starter Hard Spun. ''This horse, he very well could be a superhorse.''</p>
        <p>Curlin ran well in the Kentucky Derby, overcoming his lack of experience and some traffic problems to finish third. But he came of age in the Preakness. He seemed beaten when passed by Street Sense near the top of the stretch, but with the type of determination only a few horses have, he regrouped, found another gear and nipped Street Sense at the wire.</p>
        <p>It is possible that the Curlin who shows up in the Belmont will be better than the one who won the Preakness. Having raced just five times during a career that began only four months ago, he may not have peaked.</p>
        <p>Still, a victory by him in the Belmont is not a foregone conclusion. Among those standing in his way is Rags to Riches, the top 3-year-old filly in the nation. Trained by Todd Pletcher, who is 0 for 28 in Triple Crown races, she will attempt to become the first filly to win the Belmont in 102 years. She has won all four of her starts this year, including three straight in Grade I stakes events.</p>
        <p>Rags to Riches will break from post No. 7 and has been made the third choice at 3-1. Entitled to a weight allowance because she is a filly, she will carry 121 pounds, five fewer than her six male rivals. John Velazquez will be aboard her for the first time, taking over for Garrett Gomez, who was committed to ride Hard Spun.</p>
        <p>''Rags to Riches is very intriguing,'' said Steve Asmussen, who trains Curlin. ''She's just another quality horse in the race, and Curlin is going to have to run extremely well to win.''</p>
        <p>At 5-2, Hard Spun is the second choice and has been assigned post No. 6. Second in the Derby and third in the Preakness, he is a consistent horse, but one who may need Curlin to have an off day in order to win. Jones and Hard Spun's owner, Rick Porter, are hoping the switch to a top rider in Gomez will help. Porter fired jockey Mario Pino after the Preakness, saying he felt Pino made a premature and costly move on the backstretch.</p>
        <p>''We've got a guy on him who should know what it takes to get the job done,'' Jones said. ''I hated to change from Mario, but we felt like we needed to do something.''</p>
        <p>Few expect any of the other four horses entered yesterday to win. The fourth choice is Tiago, whose odds are 10-1. He won the Santa Anita Derby but showed little in placing seventh in the Kentucky Derby. He has not run since.</p>
        <p>Coming off his fourth-place finish in the Preakness, C P West will try to give the trainer Nick Zito and jockey Edgar Prado an upset win. They are the same pair who upset Smarty Jones in the 2004 Belmont with Birdstone. Imawildandcrazyguy and Slew's Tizzy round out the field. The former claimer Digger, who was considered for the race by the owner Larry Roman, was not entered.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
