<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Libby and the Scales of Justice</title>
    <meta content="l07libby" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852745"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7D71E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="601" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Libby and the Scales of Justice</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Libby Given 30 Months for Lying in C.I.A. Leak Case'' (front page, June 6):</p>
        <p>I. Lewis Libby Jr. sentenced to 30 months: justice delivered!</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Libby Given 30 Months for Lying in C.I.A. Leak Case'' (front page, June 6):</p>
        <p>I. Lewis Libby Jr. sentenced to 30 months: justice delivered!</p>
        <p>Republicans rushed to throw Bill Clinton out of his presidency over the same allegation: misleading statements. But when it comes to their guy, it's all just a big misunderstanding. And to receive support from the likes of Donald H. Rumsfeld and Paul D. Wolfowitz, well, that just confirms that the scale of justice found balance.</p>
        <p>Paul Bartlett  St. Paul, June 6, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The Libby sentence had barely been announced when we were bombarded by television pundits proclaiming that a real tragedy had occurred. A public servant, a decent man, a loyal man, a person who had made financial sacrifices to serve, had fallen valiantly. Give us a break. This is anything but a tragedy.</p>
        <p>I. Lewis Libby Jr. is an experienced lawyer, highly intelligent, who chose to lie and obstruct justice to protect a few people who still work in the White House. The fact that he chose to protect people devoid of intellectual and moral honesty is his problem, not ours.</p>
        <p>As far as his future is concerned, pardon or no pardon, I see a multimillion-dollar deal for his memoirs and lots of well-paid speaking engagements. And that is a real tragedy.</p>
        <p>Fabio Angeli  Stony Brook, N.Y., June 6, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The whole country now is on a Bush-pardons-Libby watch. Should that happen, that will be the ultimate slap in the face to all law-abiding Americans by this terrible administration.</p>
        <p>Dave Walker  North Dartmouth, Mass.  June 6, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The former chief of staff to Vice President Dick Cheney, I. Lewis Libby Jr., has been sentenced to two and a half years in prison and fined $250,000 for having lied about his role in leaking the identity of a former C.I.A. operative. According to the special prosecutor, Patrick J. Fitzgerald, this perjury impeded a serious investigation.</p>
        <p>Considering that no one was ever charged with that leak and the fact that the original leakers' identity was known to investigators before Mr. Fitzgerald began his investigation, I find it difficult to understand what exactly Mr. Libby is guilty of.</p>
        <p>How is it possible for someone to lie (or tell the truth, for that matter) about his role in a crime that never happened, or at least for which no one has ever been prosecuted?</p>
        <p>I. Bar-Nir  Highland Village, Tex., June 6, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>One of the most absurd talking points that has emerged from the spin machine in the wake of I. Lewis Libby Jr.'s sentencing for perjury and obstruction of justice is that Mr. Libby's conviction and sentence are a travesty because no underlying crime was committed.</p>
        <p>Since the special prosecutor, Patrick J. Fitzgerald, didn't charge anyone with the leak of Valerie Wilson's classified status -- the event that triggered the investigation -- then why should Mr. Libby be punished when no one else was?</p>
        <p>This ignores that the threshold for conviction required proof that the leaker knowingly intended to reveal an agent's status -- a difficult requirement -- and further ignores that Mr. Fitzgerald wasn't able to fully investigate this case because of Mr. Libby's interference.</p>
        <p>The point many are now making, including most of the Republican candidates running for president, is that lying repeatedly to a federal grand jury is allowed if it ultimately turns out that the crime being investigated didn't reach the threshold for indictment.</p>
        <p>John Ariel Murphy  Seattle, June 6, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
