<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vote on New Rules for Jail Inmates Is Delayed</title>
    <meta content="07jail" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/nyregion/07jail.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852696"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907EED91E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vote on New Rules for Jail Inmates Is Delayed</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Vote on New Rules for Jail Inmates Is Delayed</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SEWELL CHAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The board that oversees the city's Department of Correction has put off a final vote on changes to the rules governing the daily lives of city inmates -- the most significant changes since 1978 -- after an outcry by the City Bar Association, the Legal Aid Society and other groups that have called the changes draconian and inhumane.</p>
        <p>The new rules would, in part, reduce the minimum number of square feet guaranteed to inmates in communal dormitories; permit the authorities to read inmate mail and monitor inmate phone calls without court warrants; and allow certain inmates -- not just those who have violated disciplinary rules -- to be confined in a cell up to 23 hours a day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The board that oversees the city’s Department of Correction has put off a final vote on changes to the rules governing the daily lives of city inmates  the most significant changes since 1978  after an outcry by the City Bar Association, the Legal Aid Society and other groups that have called the changes draconian and inhumane.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The board that oversees the city's Department of Correction has put off a final vote on changes to the rules governing the daily lives of city inmates -- the most significant changes since 1978 -- after an outcry by the City Bar Association, the Legal Aid Society and other groups that have called the changes draconian and inhumane.</p>
        <p>The new rules would, in part, reduce the minimum number of square feet guaranteed to inmates in communal dormitories; permit the authorities to read inmate mail and monitor inmate phone calls without court warrants; and allow certain inmates -- not just those who have violated disciplinary rules -- to be confined in a cell up to 23 hours a day.</p>
        <p>After the Board of Correction issued the proposed rules on Jan. 19, advocates for inmates and their families responded with outrage, saying that there had been no real opportunity for public input. A public comment period, including a hearing on April 17, was to have ended on May 21, but on May 10, the board announced that it would continue to receive comments through the end of June.</p>
        <p>The board also agreed to hear some of the concerns of the advocates at its next meeting, on June 14, and to take a vote in the fall.</p>
        <p>At a City Council hearing yesterday, advocates reiterated their concerns about the proposed rules, and drew a sympathetic audience from lawmakers.</p>
        <p>''These proposals, if implemented, have the potential to inflict undue hardship on prisoners and their families, while the board and the Department of Correction have offered little evidence as to why these changes are necessary,'' said Councilman Miguel Martinez, a Manhattan Democrat and the chairman of the Fire and Criminal Justice Services Committee, who led the hearing.</p>
        <p>John M. Brickman, who was executive director of the Board of Correction from 1971 to 1975 and now leads the Correctional Association of New York, a private prison oversight group, said the board had failed to act independently of the Department of Correction.</p>
        <p>John Boston, who directs the prisoners' rights project at the Legal Aid Society, was even more blunt, saying, ''The proposed amendments are overwhelmingly directed toward serving the convenience and enhancing the prerogatives of the Department of Correction while providing no substantial benefits to prisoners, their families or the communities they come from.''</p>
        <p>Alex Jonatowski, a lawyer at the City Bar Association, told the Council, ''The proposed revisions were drafted outside of public view and without contribution from people and groups who will be most affected.''</p>
        <p>In a phone interview, Hildy J. Simmons, the chairwoman of the Board of Correction, said: ''I respectfully disagree. I think six months' worth of public input is a pretty good amount of public input. We've been engaged in a process of reviewing the standards and coming up with new proposals for more than two years.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Simmons declined to discuss the substance of the proposed revisions, since the board is still debating them. But Stephen J. Morello, a deputy commissioner and spokesman at the Correction Department, said its commissioner, Martin F. Horn, has been pushing for changes to the rules since he took office in 2003.</p>
        <p>''The current standards, some of which are outdated, do not provide us with all the tools we need -- tools available to other jails in New York State -- to keep our jails safe for the inmates and the staff,'' Mr. Morello said.</p>
        <p>Among the other changes under consideration, the new rules would require pretrial detainees, who are now allowed to wear their own clothing, to wear jail uniforms, except at trial; prevent inmates from having physical contact with visitors in the first 24 hours after admission; and amend a requirement that the jails have Spanish-speaking staff members and volunteers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
