<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tough Art With a Candy Center</title>
    <meta content="07bien" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/arts/design/07bien.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852675"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Venice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Venice Biennale</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Venice Biennale</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Venice (Italy)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Guggenheim, Solomon R, Museum</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gonzalez-Torres, Felix</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E5D91E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1296" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tough Art With a Candy Center</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tough Art With a Candy Center</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDY KENNEDY</byline>
      <dateline>VENICE, June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The artist Felix Gonzalez-Torres, who died of AIDS in 1996 at 38, did not exactly fit the profile of a secret agent, an infiltrator foiling lines of defense. He was a generous man with a handsome, cherubic face and wicked sense of humor. He loved cats. And some of his best-known art is made of candy, mounds of it, free for the taking and endlessly replenished, a Willy Wonka vision of Post-Minimalism.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gonzalez-Torres also firmly believed that all art was political, whether it intended to be or not. He knew that his was, and for it to be effective he thought it should not preach or proselytize or even too fully show its hand. ''The most successful of all political moves,'' he once said, ''are ones that don't appear to be 'political.' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The artist Felix Gonzalez-Torres undoubtedly would have considered it a huge victory that he is the official representative of the United States at the 52nd Venice Biennale.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The artist Felix Gonzalez-Torres, who died of AIDS in 1996 at 38, did not exactly fit the profile of a secret agent, an infiltrator foiling lines of defense. He was a generous man with a handsome, cherubic face and wicked sense of humor. He loved cats. And some of his best-known art is made of candy, mounds of it, free for the taking and endlessly replenished, a Willy Wonka vision of Post-Minimalism.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gonzalez-Torres also firmly believed that all art was political, whether it intended to be or not. He knew that his was, and for it to be effective he thought it should not preach or proselytize or even too fully show its hand. ''The most successful of all political moves,'' he once said, ''are ones that don't appear to be 'political.' ''</p>
        <p>Such a strategy could be called subversive. You could also say that it worked on many levels: candy as candy; as art object; as a questioning of art objects; as a metaphor for mortality and depletion in the age of AIDS; as a means for his art and ideas literally to be spread, like a virus -- or maybe like joy -- by everyone who took a piece.</p>
        <p>Whichever way his art is seen, Mr. Gonzalez-Torres undoubtedly would have considered it a huge victory that it will be exhibited here beginning Sunday as the official representative of the United States at the 52nd Venice Biennale, the kind of slipping past the gatekeepers that delighted him. And because his work often dealt squarely with the reality of death, including his own, he might have been pleased that he managed to pull off such a coup without even being around, people who knew him say. (He is only the second artist to represent the United States posthumously in the Biennale in its modern history; the work of Robert Smithson was chosen for the 1982 exhibition, nine years after his death.)</p>
        <p>''I was shocked that he was chosen, frankly,'' said Nancy Spector, chief curator of the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, whose proposal was selected last year in an open competition by a committee of curators, museum directors and artists that advises the State Department.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gonzalez-Torres, who was born in Cuba and raised in Puerto Rico before moving to New York, had a complicated but unabashed love of America and the ideals it represented. His work was often a way to express his bitter disappointment when he felt that the country was failing those ideals, during the early days of AIDS, the Gulf War and the administrations of Presidents Ronald Reagan and George H. W. Bush, a time when he feared that civil liberties and other democratic protections were eroding.</p>
        <p>Ms. Spector, the curator of the exhibition at the Palladian-style United States pavilion here, said she chose Mr. Gonzalez-Torres as her Biennale candidate partly because his work had become more influential since his death, inspiring many prominent young artists like Pierre Huyghe, Rirkrit Tiravanija and Tino Sehgal.</p>
        <p>And, Ms. Spector said, the work seems more relevant now, with the war in Iraq and domestic battles over government eavesdropping, gay marriage and the concentration of wealth in America.</p>
        <p>''I feel pretty confident that he would have felt this was the right time and the right place,'' she said, ''because it would have signaled that notion of both total infiltration and of really arriving at the center and being able to speak the narrative that he wanted to.''</p>
        <p>As excoriating and critical of the United States as his work can be, she said, she thinks he would have seen his selection as a sign of ''total acceptance'' by his adopted country and would have been ''overjoyed, a very proud American.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gonzalez-Torres made the short list for the 1995 Biennale, a year before his death, and at that time, even as he was becoming more ill, he spoke of wanting the work in the exhibition to be ''tough.'' The work that Ms. Spector chose includes many of his greatest hits: a candy spill; cubelike stacks of paper, also free for the taking and replenished to an ideal height; cascading strings of 15-watt frosted light bulbs that can be arranged however the curator sees fit. But many of the pieces here are also tough, among his most stridently polemical.</p>
        <p>One paper stack, with blank pieces edged in black like funeral announcements, is called ''Untitled (Republican Years),'' from 1992. Two other stacks, from 1989, bear the typed words ''Memorial Day Weekend'' and ''Veterans Day Sale.'' (Mr. Gonzalez-Torres, who thought of such stacks as anti-monuments, said he came up with the idea for the two phrases after reading the paper and thinking ''that in our culture we no longer celebrate historical events at the public plaza -- we go shopping.'')</p>
        <p>While some of his signature spills and piles are composed of silver-wrapped chocolates or brightly colored hard candy, the carpetlike one that covers the floor in one wing of the American pavilion, called ''Untitled (Public Opinion),'' is made with grayish licorice pieces vaguely shaped like missiles.</p>
        <p>The largest work in this exhibition, conceived by Mr. Gonzalez-Torres during his lifetime but not made until now, does not appear to have political overtones at all. Commanding the courtyard in front of the pavilion, it is two shallow circular reflecting pools, touching to form a figure eight. The pools, weighing 8 to 10 tons each, are made of solid pieces of Carrara marble, the same kind Michelangelo used. (They are the largest pieces taken intact from a particular quarry in northern Tuscany since 1523, according to the exhibition's stone supplier.)</p>
        <p>The pools arrived at the pavilion on Monday, caught up in some characteristically Italian-style traffic and paperwork problems on their way to Venice. ''We were starting to get pretty worried,'' Ms. Spector said. As she and assistants made the last adjustments to the exhibition on Tuesday afternoon, the pools were filled for the first time, and the water almost spilling over their edges caught the sunlight as yellow flowers from a Linden tree floated down onto the surface.</p>
        <p>But the pools are more than simply beautiful, echoing other doubled objects that Mr. Gonzalez-Torres made as expressions of homosexual affinity and togetherness, like a pair of round mirrors or a pair of synchronized clocks, also touching, called ''Untitled (Perfect Lovers).'' He said he thought such works were more powerful because they refused to engage critics by playing on their terms.</p>
        <p>''Two clocks side by side are much more threatening to the powers that be than an image of two men'' performing oral sex, he wrote (though he used a much more descriptive phrase).</p>
        <p>Of course many of the art pilgrims and tourists who file past the pools from now until Nov. 21, when the Biennale ends, will not think of sex or politics when seeing them. ''They're beautiful, and I think people will probably throw coins in them, or might actually get into them if it's hot,'' Ms. Spector said, smiling. ''I wouldn't mind.</p>
        <p>Andrea Rosen, the dealer who represented Mr. Gonzalez-Torres from 1990 until his death and who now oversees his estate, said she did not think he would mind either. He would probably jump in himself. As he once said, he did not want his art to be just for people who read postmodern theory but also ''for people who watch 'The Golden Girls.' ''</p>
        <p>Ms. Rosen said: ''His work has the ability to change with people's intentions and to be read through the filter of any given moment. I'm proud that he was chosen. And I'm proud that Nancy has chosen to do a show that is darker and more political. But I think different people are going to come away from this with very different experiences. That's Felix's magic.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
