<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Decisively, One Women's Team Earns Itself a Trip to Shanghai</title>
    <meta content="07card" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/crosswords/bridge/07card.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852666"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cards and Card Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cards and Card Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE7D91E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="617" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Decisively, One Women's Team Earns Itself a Trip to Shanghai</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Decisively, One Women’s Team Earns Itself a Trip to Shanghai</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Phillip Alder</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first team has qualified for the world championships from the trials taking place in Schaumburg, Ill.</p>
        <p>Hansa Narasimhan, Irina Levitina, Jill Levin, Jill Meyers, Debbie Rosenberg and JoAnna Stansby will be the U.S.A.-1 team in the Venice Cup, starting in late September in Shanghai. In the final they defeated Kathleen Sulgrove, Candace Griffey, Cindy Bernstein, Sally Wheeler, Laurie Kranyak and Linda McGarry, 218 international match points to 129. Sulgrove led by 36 imps after 48 of the 96 boards, but Narasimhan took the second half by an impressive 169 imps to 44.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first team has qualified for the world championships from the trials taking place in Schaumburg, Ill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first team has qualified for the world championships from the trials taking place in Schaumburg, Ill.</p>
        <p>Hansa Narasimhan, Irina Levitina, Jill Levin, Jill Meyers, Debbie Rosenberg and JoAnna Stansby will be the U.S.A.-1 team in the Venice Cup, starting in late September in Shanghai. In the final they defeated Kathleen Sulgrove, Candace Griffey, Cindy Bernstein, Sally Wheeler, Laurie Kranyak and Linda McGarry, 218 international match points to 129. Sulgrove led by 36 imps after 48 of the 96 boards, but Narasimhan took the second half by an impressive 169 imps to 44.</p>
        <p>The diagramed deal was Board 84.</p>
        <p>After three passes Rosenberg (South) opened with a weak two-bid in the fourth position, a rare beast indeed. (If her suit had been hearts, she probably would have passed.) This presented Bernstein (West) with a predicament. It is well known that making a takeout double with a two-suited hand is dangerous. But her only logical alternative, to use Leaping Michaels, bidding four diamonds to show a red two-suiter, would have been inconsistent with her initial pass, and bold vulnerable opposite a passed partner, especially one who did not open in the third position, where a degree of latitude is permitted.</p>
        <p>But when Bernstein chose to double, Wheeler (East) understandably passed.</p>
        <p>West led her singleton club. To defeat the contract East had to give West a club ruff, but that was nigh impossible to find, West's double having in principle announced support for all three unbid suits.</p>
        <p>After taking dummy's club king with her ace, East led her diamond king and continued with her second diamond. West won with her ace, cashed the heart ace and played back a diamond, East ruffing dummy's queen. South overruffed and drove out the spade queen to make her doubled contract.</p>
        <p>In the other room Meyers (West) opened two hearts, a weak two-bid. This is an unusual specimen too, with only a five-card suit, a longer side suit and two aces. But it worked well here. Levin (East) responded two no-trump, an inquiry bid that is usually chosen with a hand worth a game-try in partner's suit.</p>
        <p>Griffey (South) debatably intervened with three spades. West rebid four diamonds, which North doubled. East retreated to four hearts, North doubling again.</p>
        <p>This contract was unbeatable. South won the first trick with her spade ten and continued with the spade king, declarer (West) ruffing with her heart seven and North overruffing with the nine. After winning the club-king shift with East's ace, West played a heart to her ace, led a diamond to dummy's king, returned a diamond to her ace and ruffed a diamond on the board.</p>
        <p>The heart queen lost to North's king, but declarer ruffed the club queen, drew trumps and ran the diamonds. She conceded only one spade and two hearts.</p>
        <p>Plus 670 and plus 790 gave the Narasimhan team 16 imps on the board.</p>
        <p>The two losing semifinalists simultaneously played a 96-board match, Shawn Quinn, Sue Picus, Hjordis Eythorsdottir and Rozanne Pollack defeating Lynn Baker, Karen McCallum, Kerri Sanborn, Lynn Deas and Beth Palmer by 185 imps to 184.</p>
        <p>In the second 96-board final, to select the U.S.A.-2 team, at halftime yesterday afternoon, Quinn led Sulgrove 115 imps to 31.</p>
        <p>In the open trial the three quarterfinal matches finished last night. After 75 of 120 boards, Russ Ekeblad's team led Martin Harris's by 226 imps to 134, Richard Schwartz led Lou Ann O'Rourke 146 imps to 104, and Seymon Deutsch led Rose Meltzer 166 imps to 155. The winners were joined by the Nick Nickell team for 120-board semifinals finishing tomorrow night, with the 120-board final being played on Saturday and Sunday. Details can be found at usbf.org.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
