<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Dark, Rock 'n' Roll Oasis In the Shine of the Hamptons</title>
    <meta content="07CRITIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/fashion/07CRITIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852652"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Critical Shopper"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Hamptons (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5DA1E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="964" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Dark, Rock 'n' Roll Oasis In the Shine of the Hamptons</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Dark, Rock ’n’ Roll Oasis in the Shine of the Hamptons</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alex Kuczynski</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you are not acquainted with the oeuvre of John Varvatos, the first things you need to know are the following: he invented the boxer brief for Calvin Klein and, in partnership with Converse, the laceless Chuck Taylor.</p>
        <p>The first constitutes a contribution to male comfort, even if the International Male catalog, in the pre-Varvatos era, might have beat him to something similar; the second, a contribution to sociology. The laceless Chuck Taylor combines nostalgia (practically everybody wore Chuck Taylors when they were little, no matter how old they are now) and gangsta chic (the no-laces look symbolizing recent prison release). The first time I saw a pair, they adorned the feet of a Hamptons-hopping Beverly Hills money manager. You see what I mean. They're not just sneakers; they are the footwear equivalent of the white man's overbite.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Varvatos comes to the Hamptons. Stash the laces.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you are not acquainted with the oeuvre of John Varvatos, the first things you need to know are the following: he invented the boxer brief for Calvin Klein and, in partnership with Converse, the laceless Chuck Taylor.</p>
        <p>The first constitutes a contribution to male comfort, even if the International Male catalog, in the pre-Varvatos era, might have beat him to something similar; the second, a contribution to sociology. The laceless Chuck Taylor combines nostalgia (practically everybody wore Chuck Taylors when they were little, no matter how old they are now) and gangsta chic (the no-laces look symbolizing recent prison release). The first time I saw a pair, they adorned the feet of a Hamptons-hopping Beverly Hills money manager. You see what I mean. They're not just sneakers; they are the footwear equivalent of the white man's overbite.</p>
        <p>Mr. Varvatos designs chiefly for the guy in his 20s and 30s who is learning how to spend money on his clothing; Mr. Varvatos has also recently, bravely, begun to row his boat into the treacherous waters of women's fashion.</p>
        <p>His men's clothes are clean and fitted in the European sense but slightly rumpled, as if you took a well-dressed wealthy young Italian, got him drunk and let him sleep on the beach overnight. He and his shirt arrive for breakfast appropriately sandblasted but trying to look respectable. It's kind of retro-preppy meets pop star, which makes sense, considering that Mr. Varvatos spent the early part of his career at Ralph Lauren but is also a major collector of rock 'n' roll vinyl.</p>
        <p>The laceless Chuck Taylor is now Converse's second-biggest seller, just behind the classic Chuck Taylor. (You pay a little more than twice as much for the privilege of going lace-free.) Mr. Varvatos now produces his own line, the Converse line and Star USA, his more affordable secondary collection, which includes women's clothing. He likes to dress rock stars and told a reporter last year that when Iggy Pop posed for one of his ad campaigns, it was the one time the famously muscular rock star specifically asked to keep his clothes on during a shoot.</p>
        <p>Mr. Varvatos has been on something of a tear in the last few years, opening stores in Los Angeles, Las Vegas and New York and in a few choice malls. Over Memorial Day weekend, he opened an 1,800-square-foot boutique in East Hampton, a space that mixes industrial, rock 'n' roll and vintage elements with some intriguing design pieces. (He plans to sell antique furniture.)</p>
        <p>Black-and-white photographs of Michael Stipe, Elvis Costello and Iggy Pop hang on exposed brick walls. Over a large wooden table of T-shirts at the front of the store hangs a homage, unintentional or not, to Ralph Ellison's ''Invisible Man'': a tangle of scores of light bulbs, strung together and hanging from an iron rack, the electric wires braided together. It resembled, in fact, a photograph by the artist Jeff Wall titled ''After 'Invisible Man,' by Ralph Ellison, the Prologue, 1999-2000.''</p>
        <p>In the book, Ellison used light to define his identity: ''Perhaps you'll think it strange that an invisible man should need light, desire light, love light. But maybe it is exactly because I am invisible. Without light I am not only invisible, but formless as well; and to be unaware of one's form is to live a death.'' Mr. Varvatos, it is clear, is trying to do the same: on sale at the table are T-shirts that read, ''Who the hell is John Varvatos?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Varvatos has cited influences that range from military to preppy to punk rock, but he has often strayed from those motifs, such as when he designed wide-wale corduroy slippers for men in 2005, which to me signifies something like early retirement. But he can pull off a relaxed classic look, neat and New Wave as the '80s, but with a tie askew or a cuff slightly frayed.</p>
        <p>RELATIVELY speaking, it is a dark store in a sunny place, and it looks especially dark considering that it is smack next door to the Nines, a specialty golf shop for women, which on the last two weekends had a display of hot-pink golf bags in its front window. Isn't there some aesthetic continuity charter in East Hampton that requires that all mommies own a pair of Tory Burch flats and all stores have pink in their window display?</p>
        <p>Over Memorial Day weekend, the Varvatos store was bustling with curious visitors. Last weekend, a sunny Saturday found the place deserted, two staff members discussing exactly how Jimi Hendrix died. (Neither of them knew.)</p>
        <p>Perhaps it is a welcome blast of shadow and sullenness in the otherwise happy-all-the-time land of the Hamptons. While the store is not yet fully stocked in women's apparel, there was a rack in the back where I found a heavy satin peasant blouse in opal green and several ribbed cotton tanks and cargo pants in varying lengths. A vintage apothecary cabinet held Mr. Varvatos's skin care line (Even Tone Skin Cream, Pore Refining Mattifier, Concealer).</p>
        <p>There were no men's laceless sneakers in sight; there were, however, boots, moccasins and lace-up oxfords. On their own table, several pairs of sandals were on display. It may be time for East Hampton to bid farewell to the laceless Chuck Taylor and say hello to the man sandal.</p>
        <p>John Varvatos  54 Newtown Lane, East Hampton; (631) 324-4440</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- High-end Abercrombie &amp; Fitch, with quieter music.</p>
        <p>SERVICE -- Good-natured.</p>
        <p>PRICES -- T-shirts questioning identity of Mr. Varvatos, $50; distressed leather jacket, $1,695; man-purse, $495; laced calf duffel bag, $1,595.</p>
        <p>KEY LOOKS -- Imagine if Peter Fonda were 25 years old and living off his parents' trust fund in East Hampton.</p>
        <p>Critical Shopper</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
