<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wang Shows Effectiveness Good Pitching Can Have</title>
    <meta content="07yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/sports/baseball/07yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852819"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago White Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Chicago White Sox</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wang, Chien-Ming</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Abreu, Bobby</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0D61E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wang Shows Effectiveness Good Pitching Can Have</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Wang Shows Effectiveness Good Pitching Can Have</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The signs of life are hard to miss now. The Yankees have won five of their last seven games, with dormant bats stirring and a defense that is starting to make a difference.</p>
        <p>But it is pitching that controls the game, Manager Joe Torre often says, and only strong pitching can lead the Yankees into a pennant race. On Wednesday night, the Yankees' ace was at his best.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees scored in only two innings, but with starter Chien-Ming Wang in control, the outcome never seemed to be in doubt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The signs of life are hard to miss now. The Yankees have won five of their last seven games, with dormant bats stirring and a defense that is starting to make a difference.</p>
        <p>But it is pitching that controls the game, Manager Joe Torre often says, and only strong pitching can lead the Yankees into a pennant race. On Wednesday night, the Yankees' ace was at his best.</p>
        <p>Chien-Ming Wang throttled the Chicago White Sox over nine innings in a 5-1 victory at U.S. Cellular Field. It was the first complete-game victory for the Yankees in 119 games, since Wang tossed a shutout against Tampa Bay last July 28.</p>
        <p>If the Yankees win Thursday, they will win consecutive series for the first time this season. Their record is 26-31, still far back in the standings but improving bit by bit.</p>
        <p>''We're starting to stack some blocks here, and that's what we need to do,'' Torre said. ''It's a long season, and we certainly need to climb back to .500 and see how good we are.''</p>
        <p>Wang (5-4) walked one, struck out four and gave up no extra-base hits, throwing 105 pitches, fewer than he did in his previous start, when he beat Boston despite lasting just five and two-thirds innings.</p>
        <p>Johnny Damon doubled twice for the Yankees, and Melky Cabrera went 2 for 4 and threw out a runner at the plate. Bobby Abreu also reached base twice, the sixth game in a row he has done that. Since Torre gave him a start off May 30, Abreu is 10 for 21.</p>
        <p>Abreu had a walk in the Yankees' four-run third inning off the White Sox' Javier Vázquez, who gave up no other runs over six innings.</p>
        <p>In Vázquez and Thursday's starter, José Contreras, the Yankees are facing two pitchers they had hoped would be cornerstones of their rotation. Earlier this decade, the Yankees committed $77 million to them, only to trade them for pitchers since departed -- Vázquez for Randy Johnson, Contreras for Esteban Loaiza.</p>
        <p>Since leaving the Yankees after his failure in the 2004 American League Championship Series, Vázquez has continued to tease. He is fourth in the majors in strikeouts since 2000, trailing only Johnson, Pedro Martínez and Curt Schilling. Yet in the last four seasons, with four different teams, he had a record of 49-49.</p>
        <p>Naturally, he entered Wednesday's game with an even record, at 3-3. Naturally, too, his pitches sparkled at times, but he could not win.</p>
        <p>Vázquez struck out the side in the first inning after a leadoff double by Damon, and later caught Alex Rodriguez looking on a nifty curveball to end the fifth. But Rodriguez had a crucial blow in the third inning, which began with a single by Miguel Cairo, who made his second straight start at first base.</p>
        <p>Cairo scored on Damon's second double, and after a single and a walk, Rodriguez ripped a long hit to the center-field wall to make it 3-0. Rodriguez was thrown out at second on a close play, and after a walk to Jorge Posada, Hideki Matsui scored Abreu with a sacrifice fly to center.</p>
        <p>Posada drew the throw from center and was thrown out on the bases, ending the inning with the Yankees leading, 4-0. Base-running problems would stifle Yankees rallies in the sixth and seventh innings, but with Wang in control, it hardly mattered.</p>
        <p>''You see a pitch in a zone you want to hit it in, you swing, and by the time your bat gets to the ball, the pitch is in a different place because of how much it moves,'' said the White Sox' leadoff hitter, Jerry Owens, who was 1 for 4.</p>
        <p>''It's tough to adjust to, especially because of the velocity -- 93 or 94 miles an hour. He kept the ball down and got a lot of ground balls. He pitched to his strengths really well.''</p>
        <p>But Owens said he saw more than the sinker from Wang. He also saw a slider, changeup, splitter and four-seamer, proof that Wang has continued to diversify his repertory.</p>
        <p>''It helps me a lot to change timing for hitters,'' Wang said.</p>
        <p>The White Sox scored their only run in the third inning on a single, a wild pitch and two groundouts. Owens tried to score from second on a single in the sixth inning, but Cabrera cut him down with a one-hop throw from center.</p>
        <p>Last week's foot injury to designated hitter Jason Giambi has finally put Damon and Cabrera in the right place. Damon is refreshed as the designated hitter, where his legs stay strong to give him better balance at the plate, and Cabrera helps the defense immensely in center.</p>
        <p>''I'm not sure there's anybody who has a better arm in the game,'' Damon said. ''There's not too many center fielders who can stop a running game. He's been incredible.''</p>
        <p>Owens played against Cabrera and said he knew about his strong arm. But he admitted he did not expect to be out by so much at the plate.</p>
        <p>''When I get on second base, I feel I can score on any base hit,'' Owens said. ''He made a great throw, and Posada blocked the plate perfectly. I really had nowhere to go. The ball got there a lot quicker than I thought it was going to. It was a perfect throw.''</p>
        <p>Cabrera made one perfect throw, and Wang made many more. The Yankees are coming to life.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
