<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After the Fight, Booker's Top Antagonist Is Still Standing</title>
    <meta content="07elect" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/nyregion/07elect.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852791"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICAL MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Newark (NJ)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Booker, Cory A</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E4D61E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1005" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After the Fight, Booker's Top Antagonist Is Still Standing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After the Fight, Booker’s Top Antagonist Is Still Standing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW JACOBS</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was the kind of triumph that would fill any up-and-coming political force with glee. Mayor Cory A. Booker, who took City Hall in a landslide here last year, threw his newfound heft behind six legislative candidates in Tuesday's Democratic primary and found himself celebrating victory with five of them.</p>
        <p>''Five out of six ain't bad,'' Mr. Booker crowed as he swept through the Robert Treat Hotel lobby to a ballroom full of flushed and exhausted campaign workers. ''We went from having zero people supporting our agenda in Trenton to having five, which makes this a tremendous day.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Cory A. Booker of Newark will have to find a way to live with a powerful opponent in the State House for another four years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was the kind of triumph that would fill any up-and-coming political force with glee. Mayor Cory A. Booker, who took City Hall in a landslide here last year, threw his newfound heft behind six legislative candidates in Tuesday's Democratic primary and found himself celebrating victory with five of them.</p>
        <p>''Five out of six ain't bad,'' Mr. Booker crowed as he swept through the Robert Treat Hotel lobby to a ballroom full of flushed and exhausted campaign workers. ''We went from having zero people supporting our agenda in Trenton to having five, which makes this a tremendous day.''</p>
        <p>But even as supporters bounced to Kool and the Gang's ''Celebration'' and emptied the complimentary bowls of Fritos, there was quiet hand-wringing over that sixth race, which was for the seat occupied by State Senator Ronald L. Rice, a 20-year incumbent who has long been one of the mayor's most well-placed and vocal opponents.</p>
        <p>To a few of his allies and many of his enemies, Mr. Booker's loss highlighted a glaring gap between his growing national star power and a gravitational pull that, in local elections at least, is less potent than was widely assumed. Last month, the mayor's political muscle was slightly bruised when the school board candidates he was backing here won office citywide but fared poorly in the South Ward, his home base.</p>
        <p>''Considering this is the first time he's testing his political leadership, I think he did pretty well,'' said Ingrid W. Reed, an analyst at Eagleton Institute of Politics at Rutgers University. ''But insiders might read the results differently.''</p>
        <p>A few campaign strategists who worked for the Booker slate said they underestimated the senator's appeal and overestimated the mayor's prowess. ''Maybe he hasn't paid enough dues yet; maybe the foundation isn't there yet,'' one worker said. ''And maybe, based on the landslide he had last year, he thought he was bigger than he really is.''</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Rice's challenger, D. Bilal Beasley, a councilman in neighboring Irvington, lost by fewer than four percentage points, the defeat means that Mr. Booker will have to find a way to continue to live with a powerful opponent in the State House for another four years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rice, a Vietnam veteran who earned his political stripes during the Black Power movement of the 1960s and '70s, has grown increasingly strident since last May, when he was badly stomped by Mr. Booker in the mayoral race and a post-election rapprochement failed to take place. In recent months, the two men have traded insults and both claim the other has refused to sit down and talk.</p>
        <p>The venom, at least on Mr. Booker's side, melted away on Tuesday night when it was clear the game had been lost. When he took the stage, he pledged to stand behind Mr. Rice in November -- largely an empty gesture in a solidly Democratic city -- and in an interview on Wednesday he added that he hoped the two might bridge their differences.</p>
        <p>''We're hoping we can appeal to his better angels, not the bitter ones,'' Mr. Booker said.</p>
        <p>But as of Wednesday evening, Mr. Rice's mean-spirited angels appeared to be ascendant. ''I'm not going to be so nice anymore,'' he said, after pairing the mayor's name with an expletive and criticizing him for collecting contributions from people who live outside Newark.</p>
        <p>He said, however, that he would be willing to work with Mr. Booker. ''But don't think I'm going to run around and kiss his behind to get a meeting,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In a text message later Wednesday night, Mr. Booker said the two had finally spoken, and he described the exchange as ''a good conversation.''</p>
        <p>Despite the longstanding conflict with Mr. Rice, the mayor tried to keep the focus on his five primary victories, four of which involved unseating incumbents who, he said, did not share his vision for grappling with Newark's problems. In the fifth race -- for the Senate seat from the 29th District once occupied by former Mayor Sharpe James -- Teresa Ruiz, an aide to the county executive, was uncontested.</p>
        <p>Mr. Booker also gave his support to a handful of other candidates around the state, and said he expected the six victors to become allies in Trenton. ''We need all the friends we can get in the State Senate,'' he said, explaining why he had spent time campaigning and raising money for the Senate candidacy of Sandra Bolden Cunningham, who defeated an incumbent assemblyman in Hudson County.</p>
        <p>While most of Tuesday's winners will face negligible opposition in November, the Senate seat in the 29th District is not a sure thing. Even though Ms. Ruiz has the backing of Mr. Booker and Stephen N. Adubato Sr., a political power in Newark's North Ward whose get-out-the-vote operation is considered the best in the state, she faces two opponents who have considerable name recognition. One of them is Assemblyman William D. Payne, scion of a political family in Newark who was bumped off the Booker-Adubato ticket; the other is Luis Quintana, a former Booker ally on the Newark Municipal Council whose candidacy, announced last week, has irked Mr. Booker.</p>
        <p>Their main worry is that Mr. Quintana will split the district's large Latino vote with Ms. Ruiz and leave Mr. Payne the winner. Mr. Adubato criticized both men, saying it was disloyal to run against the Democratic nominee. ''It's sacrilegious,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In an interview on Wednesday, Mr. Payne had similar thoughts about Mr. Adubato as well as Mr. Booker's decision to back insurgents who effectively ended the careers of several colleagues, including a nephew, Assemblyman Craig A. Stanley.</p>
        <p>''It's a sad day, a travesty, when tenured legislators with seniority are thrown out by inexperienced people backed by outside interests,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Asked about the widespread conjecture that Mr. Quintana's candidacy was intended to split the Hispanic vote and benefit him, Mr. Payne laughed gently and said: ''I hope he stays in because it will make for an interesting race. And if it benefits my candidacy, that's fine with me.''</p>
        <p>POLITICAL MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
