<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Pucker and Pout to Hip-Hop Hit</title>
    <meta content="07skin" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/fashion/07skin.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852649"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Skin Deep"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rap Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beauty</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beauty</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rap Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EFDC1E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="678" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Pucker and Pout to Hip-Hop Hit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From Pucker and Pout to Hip-Hop Hit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOLA OGUNNAIKE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RUN-D.M.C. had its Adidas, Busta Rhymes had his Courvoisier and Lil' Kim, the fashion plate turned convicted perjurer, has used her couplets to praise the work of everyone from Marc Jacobs to Jacob the Jeweler.</p>
        <p>Lil Mama is rap's newest product placer. But instead of promoting cars or clothes or cocktails, she is glorifying something a little more innocuous in her hit song, ''Lip Gloss.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Lip Gloss” is not just a catchy song, it’s a rapper’s signature.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RUN-D.M.C. had its Adidas, Busta Rhymes had his Courvoisier and Lil' Kim, the fashion plate turned convicted perjurer, has used her couplets to praise the work of everyone from Marc Jacobs to Jacob the Jeweler.</p>
        <p>Lil Mama is rap's newest product placer. But instead of promoting cars or clothes or cocktails, she is glorifying something a little more innocuous in her hit song, ''Lip Gloss.''</p>
        <p>Lip gloss.</p>
        <p>Over a spare, double-Dutch-friendly beat, Lil Mama, a Brooklyn-bred 17-year-old with sass to spare, rhymes: ''I said my lip gloss is cool/My lip gloss be poppin/I'm standing at my locker/And all the boys keep stoppin.''</p>
        <p>The song's video opens with her smearing a dollop of sparkling-pink gloss across her lips. Moments later, she is dancing down the hallways of a high school. Her lip gloss is popping. And the boys? They are indeed stopping. The song has not only become a radio mainstay, but the video (filmed at Lil Mama's former high school, Edward R. Murrow in Brooklyn) has also become a favorite on YouTube (more than two million hits), MTV and BET.</p>
        <p>There were no boys jockeying for Lil Mama's attention one afternoon last month when she met a reporter for a shopping expedition at the Sephora in Times Square, but she was nearly swamped by a gaggle of young girls who were more eager for autographs than makeup tips. Still, they couldn't help commenting on the rapper's watermelon-pink lip gloss (L'Oreal's watermelon crush Colour Juice, $7.49, drugstore.com). ''That's mad cute,'' said one girl who had yet to shed her baby fat. Strolling through Sephora, Lil Mama pointed out must-haves, potential purchases and items that she regarded with a sniff.</p>
        <p>L'Instant de Guerlain perfume ($52, one-ounce eau de parfum spray)? ''This smells like something my grandmother would wear,'' she said. Urban Decay's glitter-drenched Heavy Metal eye gels -- two of which are named, appropriately, Roadie and Rockstar ($18)? ''Definitely too much,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She reached for a more subtle gloss by Urban Decay called Guys Love Betsy (XXX Shine Lip Gloss, $16). The packaging described it as ''extra, extra shiny, a little tacky, super sexy.''</p>
        <p>''Guys love this,'' Lil Mama said with a playful wink as she dabbed a bit on her lips. ''It draws attention to how white my teeth are, but it's not overboard.''</p>
        <p>Cargo's Oceania Lip Gloss Quad, a compact with four shades of berry-colored glosses ($24), was another of her favorites. ''I like this a lot, because you can share it with your friends of all different complexions,'' she said. She also likes Pout's Pop My Bubble lip gloss ($16), but a publicist for the brand said it had been discontinued and instead recommended Pout's Plump lip glosses.</p>
        <p>Lil Mama said she owns at least 15 glosses. ''Hot-pink sparkly, light pink non-sparkly, clear Lipglass by MAC, you name it,'' she said. ''I own tons.''</p>
        <p>Growing up in Brooklyn, Lil Mama, whose birth name is Niatia Kirkland, began painting her face early. ''I wanted to be a model, to look like the people in the magazines,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She began writing poetry and dancing in talent shows in elementary school, and by middle school discovered a love for singing and rapping. Her father, known as True, who founded an independent record label, Familiar Faces, more than a decade ago, started releasing his daughter's recordings on underground mix tapes. The song ''Lip Gloss'' came to her while she was recording another track for her coming album, tentatively titled ''Voice of the Young People,'' which is scheduled for a September release. Meanwhile, she appears to be enjoying the attention since the release of ''Lip Gloss.''</p>
        <p>''Kids on the street are happy to see me and I'm happy to see them, too,'' she said after ordering a late lunch of French fries and chicken nuggets at a McDonald's. Her food arrived but Lil Mama was short on cash. ''Who is going to pay for this?'' she asked her publicist, who hovered nearby.</p>
        <p>She then playfully pursed her lips. ''I'm just supposed to order and look cute,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Skin Deep</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
