<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Goals Are Both Met and Missed in Clinton Fund-Raising</title>
    <meta content="07clinton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/us/politics/07clinton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852798"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E3D61E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1021" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Goals Are Both Met and Missed in Clinton Fund-Raising</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Goals Are Both Met and Missed in Clinton Fund-Raising</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK HEALY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Healy, Patrick</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Clinton presidential campaign raises money this spring, Hillary and Bill Clinton have had many ups and a few downs. Gov. Jon Corzine of New Jersey is delivering at least $1 million, and their friend Warren Buffett an additional $500,000. And Mrs. Clinton's brother Tony kept the peace in the family by coming through with $175,000 at a Pennsylvania fund-raiser -- right after his daughter's baptism.</p>
        <p>But a West Coast swing by Mr. Clinton has come up short thus far: It has raised barely half of the $600,000 in ''high goal'' commitments the campaign had hoped for. (Donations can always come in late.) And Mrs. Clinton's cocktail party in Columbus, Ohio, was pretty modest: Her ''low goal'' for the event was $100,000, and actual commitments totaled $98,100 recently.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A confidential document provided to The Times provides a glimpse of Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton’s successes and failures in fund-raising.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the Clinton presidential campaign raises money this spring, Hillary and Bill Clinton have had many ups and a few downs. Gov. Jon Corzine of New Jersey is delivering at least $1 million, and their friend Warren Buffett an additional $500,000. And Mrs. Clinton's brother Tony kept the peace in the family by coming through with $175,000 at a Pennsylvania fund-raiser -- right after his daughter's baptism.</p>
        <p>But a West Coast swing by Mr. Clinton has come up short thus far: It has raised barely half of the $600,000 in ''high goal'' commitments the campaign had hoped for. (Donations can always come in late.) And Mrs. Clinton's cocktail party in Columbus, Ohio, was pretty modest: Her ''low goal'' for the event was $100,000, and actual commitments totaled $98,100 recently.</p>
        <p>These details are among a trove of fund-raising data in a confidential document about the 90-odd lunches, dinners and receptions that the campaign planned from April 1 to June 30, as the Clintons escalate a pitched battle with Senator Barack Obama of Illinois for the Democratic war chest (not to mention the party's nomination).</p>
        <p>On paper, the breadth of the Clinton fund-raising operation is apparent in minute splendor: how the campaign courted lawyers in Chicago and bankers in California, and how it has relied particularly heavily this spring on money from gay men and lesbians and Asian-Americans, with two separate fund-raisers involving Fujianese-Americans.</p>
        <p>The document, dated May 17, was provided to The New York Times by an uncommitted Democrat who is not affiliated with any presidential campaign. The Clinton campaign said the document was authentic, and declined to say how it got out, or even if the campaign had leaked the information as a way to set fund-raising expectations for the June 30 deadline for campaign finance reporting.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton raised $26 million in the first quarter of 2007. According to the data, she has received commitments of at least $23.2 million for the second quarter. Several top donors said yesterday that they would take in more checks than they had predicted, at least one by more than $100,000. And with the campaign expecting to raise at least $4 million through the Internet and direct mail, Mrs. Clinton is poised to raise more than her first-quarter total -- perhaps considerably more.</p>
        <p>''They were expecting only $325,000 in actual commitments from me because I had promised as much as $500,000, but I'm on track to deliver all $500,000,'' said Jay Jacobs, a prominent Democratic fund-raiser and party leader on Long Island, who held a dinner with Mr. Clinton on May 5. ''I'm not going to be embarrassed and explain that I tried but didn't succeed with $500,000.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton's top fund-raising lieutenants say that the goal of the Clintons -- who are described as deeply involved and deeply competitive on the fund-raising front -- is to exceed the first quarter's $26 million by a comfortable margin. Doing so, these donors and her political advisers say, would telegraph to party insiders, the news media and voters that Mrs. Clinton is building political momentum after her performances in two televised debates and her campaign appearances this spring.</p>
        <p>''We are on target to have the largest second-quarter fund-raising total in Democratic Party history,'' said Howard Wolfson, a Clinton campaign spokesman. ''There were many questions raised about whether we would be able to match our first-quarter effort. We will.''</p>
        <p>Those questions have stemmed from the Obama threat; potential fatigue among Clinton donors; Mrs. Clinton's ability to devote more time to fund-raising (which some of her donors said was badly needed); and general uncertainty about her candidacy, given the steady criticism from her political rivals and some voters over her initial support for the war in Iraq (which she now opposes).</p>
        <p>The document shows that Mrs. Clinton has stepped up her own activity, usually attending a few fund-raisers each weekend, and has also relied more on her husband, who is scheduled to attend at least 20 fund-raisers this quarter. (He attended 16-odd events in the first quarter.) She is also relying on friends and allies who are close to Mr. Clinton, like the businessmen Ron Burkle and Vernon E. Jordan Jr., who are each organizing fund-raisers this month. (Mr. Burkle is a co-host of a $500,000 dinner in Manhattan tonight, with both Clintons expected.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Obama raised nearly $26 million in the first quarter of 2007, almost beating Mrs. Clinton, and he did raise more money than she did for the 2008 primary campaign. (Candidates raise money for both the primary and general elections.) An Obama aide said yesterday that the campaign would be ''thrilled'' to raise $20 million in the second quarter. But last night, the Huffington Post blog, citing anonymous sources close to both candidates, said Mr. Obama would out-raise Mrs. Clinton in the second quarter. An Obama spokesman denied the report.</p>
        <p>The document is the second confidential Clinton campaign file to leak in the last two weeks; the first, which was also provided to The New York Times, was a memorandum by the deputy campaign manager recommending that Mrs. Clinton skip the Iowa caucuses in 2008. Costas Panagopoulos, a political science professor at Fordham University who studies fund-raising, said the Clinton operation was so strategic that it probably leaked the data to influence fund-raising expectations. Recalling that some Clinton donors were surprised by Mr. Obama's strong first quarter, Mr. Panagopoulos said he believed the campaign would want to have a record-breaking second quarter, as Mr. Wolfson signaled.</p>
        <p>''It looks like they're kicking it up a notch, and I'm sure their initial pie-in-the-sky fund-raising number has been augmented,'' Mr. Panagopoulos said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton's biggest events this quarter, according to the document, are a $1 million fund-raiser by Mr. Corzine on June 18 and another $1 million dinner by her South Asian committee on June 24. Mr. Corzine is in the early stages of rehabilitation from severe injuries suffered in a car accident in April, but he is still aiding Mrs. Clinton, whom he endorsed this spring. Two events by Fujianese-American groups are expected to yield $600,000; and two Indo-American receptions have a total of $450,000 in commitments.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
