<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amid Calls for Changes, a Voice for Small Business Is Confident</title>
    <meta content="07preston" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/business/smallbusiness/07preston.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852726"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SMALL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Careers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Small Business Administration</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Preston, Steven C</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E2D81E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amid Calls for Changes, a Voice for Small Business Is Confident</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Voice for Small Business</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RON NIXON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Steven C. Preston, 46, a former executive vice president at ServiceMaster, became administrator of the Small Business Administration in July 2006. He sat down recently in his Washington office to discuss his efforts and those of Congress to overhaul the agency, which has been hit with budget and staff cuts. Following are excerpts:</p>
        <p>Q. There have been some proposals in the Senate and House for reforming various programs at the agency. Do you think those are necessary?</p>
        <p>A. I think it's important to acknowledge that in the absence of progress, Congress is going to feel the need to take action. So I respect the fact that many people on the Hill are working hard to think about how to improve the performance of the S.B.A. On the other side, there are policies that we're not a fan of. I am not in favor of subsidizing our loan programs. I think we should be focusing on expanding those programs by making them more effective in reaching small business. But frankly, for the amount of fee that they pay, I don't think that that's an inhibitor to our getting capital in their hands.</p>
        <p>Q. You've said that you felt that the agency had the budget to actually fulfill its statutory requirements. And you stand by that?</p>
        <p>A. The budget we have allows us to fulfill our mission, and within that budget we are going to be a much more effective and much more efficient agency at performing what we do. So I think we're going to build capacity to perform our mission that exceeds our growth in the budget. So I think there's a great opportunity for us to be a lot better at what we do, be much more responsive to customers, improve our turnaround times, improve the quality of what we do.</p>
        <p>Q. What are your staff levels at this point?</p>
        <p>A. With the passage of the '07 budget, we have now begun to hire a number of critical positions. We were sort of in a five-month period where we were in this continuing resolution, which means you really don't know how much money you're going to have, and so we were hesitant to begin hiring some of those jobs. But we have hired a number -- either hired or begun to post -- mission-critical jobs in the guaranteed-lending operations, much of which is in the processing center, where we need some people.</p>
        <p>Q. The impression in the small-business community is that people tend to like you. But they still see a lot of the programs being inefficient, or they think that the staff is not as responsive as they've been in the past, or they don't have the knowledge that they've had in the past.</p>
        <p>A. When I talked about these initiatives that we're driving, the reason that we formed these initiatives in part was the fact that I've met with hundreds of small-business owners, legislators, because they hear from their constituencies, and trade associations. And what we consistently hear is we're tough to do business with, a lot of our regulations are confusing, a lot of our people aren't trained the way that they need to be. And I'd agree with all of that. The flipside is that I think we've got a couple thousand people that are incredibly dedicated, work very hard and have done excellent work.</p>
        <p>Q. Let's talk about your impact on small businesses and supplementing the private sector. I'm seeing this number thrown out quite a bit, that the agency's program only helps about 1 percent of all small businesses.</p>
        <p>A. Well, you know, our resource partner network touched 1.5 million people last year. So that's 1.5 million out of 25, so that's more than 1 percent -- that's 6 percent. We made 100,000 small-business loans. I have to say, I think it's a larger percentage than that, when I just look at the sheer numbers. So I think our impact is greater.</p>
        <p>Q. Final question: Where would you like to see the agency at the end of the current administration?</p>
        <p>A. When I leave, if our employees don't say this is a much better place to work, I have a much greater ability to serve small business and the quantity of work I do is significantly greater than where it was, you know, two and half years ago, I will be very disappointed. That will drive the effectiveness of our operations, how well we serve small businesses, how well we're partnering with banks -- that covers everything because it all has to start with how well we're supporting our employees to be able to extend the hand of service to small business and to our partners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Steven C. Preston, the administrator of the Small Business Administration, discusses his efforts and those of Congress to reform the agency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Steven C. Preston, 46, a former executive vice president at ServiceMaster, became administrator of the Small Business Administration in July 2006. He sat down recently in his Washington office to discuss his efforts and those of Congress to overhaul the agency, which has been hit with budget and staff cuts. Following are excerpts:</p>
        <p>Q. There have been some proposals in the Senate and House for reforming various programs at the agency. Do you think those are necessary?</p>
        <p>A. I think it's important to acknowledge that in the absence of progress, Congress is going to feel the need to take action. So I respect the fact that many people on the Hill are working hard to think about how to improve the performance of the S.B.A. On the other side, there are policies that we're not a fan of. I am not in favor of subsidizing our loan programs. I think we should be focusing on expanding those programs by making them more effective in reaching small business. But frankly, for the amount of fee that they pay, I don't think that that's an inhibitor to our getting capital in their hands.</p>
        <p>Q. You've said that you felt that the agency had the budget to actually fulfill its statutory requirements. And you stand by that?</p>
        <p>A. The budget we have allows us to fulfill our mission, and within that budget we are going to be a much more effective and much more efficient agency at performing what we do. So I think we're going to build capacity to perform our mission that exceeds our growth in the budget. So I think there's a great opportunity for us to be a lot better at what we do, be much more responsive to customers, improve our turnaround times, improve the quality of what we do.</p>
        <p>Q. What are your staff levels at this point?</p>
        <p>A. With the passage of the '07 budget, we have now begun to hire a number of critical positions. We were sort of in a five-month period where we were in this continuing resolution, which means you really don't know how much money you're going to have, and so we were hesitant to begin hiring some of those jobs. But we have hired a number -- either hired or begun to post -- mission-critical jobs in the guaranteed-lending operations, much of which is in the processing center, where we need some people.</p>
        <p>Q. The impression in the small-business community is that people tend to like you. But they still see a lot of the programs being inefficient, or they think that the staff is not as responsive as they've been in the past, or they don't have the knowledge that they've had in the past.</p>
        <p>A. When I talked about these initiatives that we're driving, the reason that we formed these initiatives in part was the fact that I've met with hundreds of small-business owners, legislators, because they hear from their constituencies, and trade associations. And what we consistently hear is we're tough to do business with, a lot of our regulations are confusing, a lot of our people aren't trained the way that they need to be. And I'd agree with all of that. The flipside is that I think we've got a couple thousand people that are incredibly dedicated, work very hard and have done excellent work.</p>
        <p>Q. Let's talk about your impact on small businesses and supplementing the private sector. I'm seeing this number thrown out quite a bit, that the agency's program only helps about 1 percent of all small businesses.</p>
        <p>A. Well, you know, our resource partner network touched 1.5 million people last year. So that's 1.5 million out of 25, so that's more than 1 percent -- that's 6 percent. We made 100,000 small-business loans. I have to say, I think it's a larger percentage than that, when I just look at the sheer numbers. So I think our impact is greater.</p>
        <p>Q. Final question: Where would you like to see the agency at the end of the current administration?</p>
        <p>A. When I leave, if our employees don't say this is a much better place to work, I have a much greater ability to serve small business and the quantity of work I do is significantly greater than where it was, you know, two and half years ago, I will be very disappointed. That will drive the effectiveness of our operations, how well we serve small businesses, how well we're partnering with banks -- that covers everything because it all has to start with how well we're supporting our employees to be able to extend the hand of service to small business and to our partners.  SMALL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
