<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TB Patient Gives His Account to Congress</title>
    <meta content="07tb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/us/07tb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852729"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Tuberculosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Epidemics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tuberculosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel Restrictions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tuberculosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Epidemics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Speaker, Andrew</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E1D81E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="911" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TB Patient Gives His Account to Congress</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">TB Patient Gives His Account to Congress</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN and JACQUELINE PALANK; Lawrence K. Altman reported from New York, and Jacqueline Palank from Washington.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Palank, Jacqueline; Altman, Lawrence K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a Senate hearing, Andrew Speaker yesterday contradicted some accounts by government officials about the timing of who knew what and when about his plans to travel abroad after being told that he had extremely drug-resistant tuberculosis.</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, 31, who is now in isolation at a Denver hospital, created an international health scare by taking commercial flights for his wedding in Greece and honeymoon in Europe last month. He spoke by telephone from his room at the National Jewish Medical and Research Center in Denver to a Senate Appropriations subcommittee that oversees the Public Health Service.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a Senate hearing, Andrew Speaker contradicted some accounts by government officials about the timing of who knew what and when about his plans to travel abroad.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a Senate hearing, Andrew Speaker yesterday contradicted some accounts by government officials about the timing of who knew what and when about his plans to travel abroad after being told that he had extremely drug-resistant tuberculosis.</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, 31, who is now in isolation at a Denver hospital, created an international health scare by taking commercial flights for his wedding in Greece and honeymoon in Europe last month. He spoke by telephone from his room at the National Jewish Medical and Research Center in Denver to a Senate Appropriations subcommittee that oversees the Public Health Service.</p>
        <p>After statements by Dr. Julie L. Gerberding, director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, about her agency's role in detecting the extremely drug-resistant form of the disease and then notifying Mr. Speaker about it, he told the committee, ''A few of things you were told are simply not accurate.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker gave his version of events after Dr. Gerberding left to appear at another hearing, before the House Homeland Security Committee.</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker said the diagnosis of tuberculosis, initially suspected in January, was confirmed in early to mid-April. He said he and his doctor met with officials of the Fulton County Health Department in Atlanta on April 25, when tests had not shown that his case was drug resistant.</p>
        <p>At that time, Mr. Speaker said, the disease centers and Fulton County Health Department in Atlanta knew of his wedding and honeymoon travel plans. They met again on May 10 when, he said, he was told that he had multiple drug-resistant tuberculosis but was ''not a threat to anyone.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Gerberding had just told the committee that her agency learned on May 18 that Mr. Speaker had left the country. The agency has not provided an official timeline of the events in the case.</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker said agency, Fulton County officials and his doctors knew of the resistance problem before the May 10 meeting at the Health Department.</p>
        <p>''They were all discussing this, because of the fact that there was resistance,'' Mr. Speaker said, ''and talking about getting me out to Denver.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Gerberding said that her agency did not determine that Mr. Speaker had the extremely resistant form of tuberculosis until May 22 and that it then started searching for him in Europe.</p>
        <p>Senator Tom Harkin, Democrat of Iowa and chairman of the subcommittee, said he suspected ''some bureaucratic mismanagement'' in how several government agencies handled Mr. Speaker's case, and announced that he would hold another hearing, but did not set a time.</p>
        <p>At a separate hearing before the House Homeland Security Committee, members pressed the agencies on the timeliness of their alerts, the ability of their computer systems to track Mr. Speaker's travels and the ability of the United States to protect itself from a biological threat.</p>
        <p>Officials from the Department of Homeland Security and its Customs and Border Protection agency, as well as the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, said the case had prompted some changes in how they operated. But Homeland Security Department officials said they could not describe those changes for security reasons.</p>
        <p>Among the difficulties in interrupting Mr. Speaker's movements was that current systems made it impossible to prevent him from boarding a commercial airliner after he had left Italy. An existing passenger-tracking system that the Customs and Border Protection uses does not flag completely new reservations with a final destination outside the United States, said Jayson P. Ahern, assistant commissioner in the Customs Office of Field Operations.</p>
        <p>The system tracks changes made to existing reservations. He said that this system might be improved, but that an expansion of its abilities brought up legal questions like passengers' privacy rights.</p>
        <p>Border officials for the most part defended their actions and said a border agent was to blame for failing to stop Mr. Speaker when he re-entered the United States on May 24 in Champlain, N.Y. The agent had received the warning sent to all United States ports of entry directing agents to mask Mr. Speaker, place him in isolation and contact the disease centers. Yet the agent, who did not think that Mr. Speaker looked sick, let him proceed.</p>
        <p>W. Ralph Basham, commissioner of Customs and Border Protection, said the agent exhibited ''clear and blatant disregard'' for the warning. The agent is the subject of an internal investigation and has been put on administrative leave.</p>
        <p>Customs will re-evaluate its National Targeting Center, Mr. Basham said, which conducts twice-daily sweeps of its systems to check the status of suspected terrorists. This system did not discover that Mr. Speaker had entered the United States until six hours after the fact.</p>
        <p>Representative Ed Perlmutter, Democrat of Colorado, asked how the disease centers could have missed so many opportunities to catch Mr. Speaker. Dr. Gerberding said, ''We make decisions based on the theory that the patient will cooperate.''</p>
        <p>When asked whether exposure to the drug-resistant tuberculosis presented a threat similar to a threat from a terrorist, Dr. Gerberding said: ''There is a difference between a terrorist and an infected person. Our medical approach is to give the patient the benefit of the doubt.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Gerberding said her agency would evaluate its ability to help local and state officials prevent patients from leaving the country, as well as the speed of its notifications to the Homeland Security Department and the World Health Organization.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
