<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kiwis to Face Rival in Cup Rematch</title>
    <meta content="07sailing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/sports/othersports/07sailing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852730"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="YACHT RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain/Valencia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">America's Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">America's Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Valencia (Spain)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Prada</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Clarey, Christopher</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Barker, Dean</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Dalton, Grant</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Coutts, Russell</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E1D81E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kiwis to Face Rival in Cup Rematch</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kiwis Earn Cup Rematch Against Their Top Rival</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clarey, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>VALENCIA, Spain, June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Bring it home,'' read the T-shirts of the New Zealanders who have turned this distant harbor into a sunny enclave of their cloudier land.</p>
        <p>They do not have the America's Cup back yet, and the hardest part may still be to come. But Emirates Team New Zealand will now have a chance to sail for the Cup against Alinghi, the Swiss syndicate that raided its talent and pried the Auld Mug away with surprisingly little resistance in 2003.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Emirates Team New Zealand will now have a chance to sail for the America’s Cup against Alinghi, the Swiss syndicate that raided the Kiwis’ talent and pried the trophy away in 2003.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Bring it home,'' read the T-shirts of the New Zealanders who have turned this distant harbor into a sunny enclave of their cloudier land.</p>
        <p>They do not have the America's Cup back yet, and the hardest part may still be to come. But Emirates Team New Zealand will now have a chance to sail for the Cup against Alinghi, the Swiss syndicate that raided its talent and pried the Auld Mug away with surprisingly little resistance in 2003.</p>
        <p>Team New Zealand qualified for the Cup on Wednesday by completing a sweep of Luna Rossa Challenge with a 22-second victory that gave the Kiwis their fifth victory in five races over a competitor that was expected to provide much greater resistance in the best-of-nine series.</p>
        <p>''I don't think we thought it would be a 5-0 series,'' Dean Barker, New Zealand's helmsman and skipper, said. ''But we're so thrilled we managed to win, and now we look forward to the next step.''</p>
        <p>Barker has been looking forward since Alinghi swept his team in the last Cup in his home waters off Auckland. Barker was the helmsman that year, too, and he ended up having to steer through a variety of misfortune, as Team New Zealand's boat, which featured an avant-garde hull appendage, proved to be unreliable.</p>
        <p>There was initially doubt about whether New Zealand would run another campaign because of the cost of keeping up with the billionaires from countries with larger populations and sponsorship bases. But the government and Barker decided to push ahead with a new team leader: Grant Dalton, one of the most successful ocean racers in the world.</p>
        <p>''You can't compare the two teams, even though we share the same name,'' Barker said. ''This team is much stronger. I think going through the Louis Vuitton series makes you a lot more race-hardened. Now the challenge is to take the momentum forward.''</p>
        <p>The race against Alinghi will not quite be the grudge match it could have been. The crucial figure in the last Cup was Russell Coutts, the helmsman for New Zealand's Cup victories in 1995 and 2000 before defecting to Alinghi with several of his crew members from New Zealand.</p>
        <p>Coutts's design knowledge and match-racing skills proved critical in 2003, but he left Alinghi acrimoniously in 2004. Because Switzerland is landlocked, Alinghi had to find a location outside the country to stage the Cup. Coutts reportedly disagreed with the choice of Valencia, preferring the stronger winds in Cascais, Portugal. He left the team shortly after the decision to come to Valencia was announced.</p>
        <p>The rest of Alinghi's team has remained intact, and it is now led by Coutts's longtime sidekick and tactician, Brad Butterworth. But Alinghi will have another helmsman when it faces Team New Zealand in the best-of-nine match that will begin here June 23. The new helmsman is expected to be either Ed Baird of the United States or Peter Holmberg of the U.S. Virgin Islands, neither of whom has had that responsibility in an America's Cup.</p>
        <p>''Alinghi's boat is a really refined piece of machinery,'' said Terry Hutchinson, Team New Zealand's American tactician. ''The thing I like is our guy driving the boat has been there. Their guy hasn't.''</p>
        <p>Alinghi will not, however, have the classic disadvantage of a defender. In the past, there was little chance for a defender to race against its future opponents during the lead-up to the Cup. Because of a new format in which there are a series of prerace regattas over a two-year period, Alinghi has had ample opportunity to test itself against the challengers and has had consistent success.</p>
        <p>It raced in training against New Zealand as recently as last week, although neither team used its newest racing boat.</p>
        <p>But New Zealand's newest yacht certainly proved too complete for Luna Rossa. ''That series was as much a credit to the design team as anyone,'' Hutchinson said. ''The boat got us out of a lot of tight spots.''</p>
        <p>This Vuitton Cup final began with a tight race in midrange winds. But the Kiwis took command after that and produced the first sweep in Vuitton finals history. The race Wednesday was tighter than the three that preceded it, although the Kiwis led around every mark.</p>
        <p>''It's obviously pretty disappointing,'' James Spithill, Luna Rossa's helmsman, said. ''But I think full credit has to go to the Kiwis.''</p>
        <p>Luna Rossa's crew members were certainly sporting in defeat. They docked their yacht first Wednesday, and when Team New Zealand docked a few minutes later, the Italians stood on deck and applauded.</p>
        <p>Still, it was the latest unhappy ending in the Cup for Patrizio Bertelli, Luna Rossa Challenge's president, who is the chief executive of Prada and has invested hundreds of millions of dollars and thousands of hours in his three challenges.</p>
        <p>His most successful attempt is his first, in 2000, when his team won, 5-4, in the Vuitton finals against America One before being overwhelmed by Coutts and the Kiwis in the Cup. ''I'm still interested in trying again,'' he said. ''But we will have to see where the competition will be held and under what conditions.''</p>
        <p>If Alinghi were to defend successfully, the Cup could stay in Valencia. But there is no doubt where the Cup is heading if the Kiwis win, and there is no doubt what is driving the thousands of New Zealanders who have come here.</p>
        <p>''It's a grudge match,'' said Brent Evil, a 49-year-old from Kawau Island, near Auckland.</p>
        <p>YACHT RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
