<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A 17-Year-Old Turns Pro And Looks to Be the Man</title>
    <meta content="07golf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/sports/golf/07golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852716"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4D81E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A 17-Year-Old Turns Pro And Looks to Be the Man</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A 17-Year-Old Turns Pro and Looks to Be the Man</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is a touch of Paul Bunyan in the story of Tony Finau, a 17-year-old golfer who stands 6 feet 4 inches, weighs 205 pounds and carries only one wood, 12 irons and a putter in his bag.</p>
        <p>Finau, who is of Samoan and Tongan descent, grew up in Salt Lake City with nine brothers and sisters. Days before graduating from high school May 30, he decided to forgo his amateur status for life as a professional.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tony Finau, a long hitter off the tee who won the 2006 Utah State Amateur title, is one of countless golfers opting to start a career at a young age instead of competing in college.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is a touch of Paul Bunyan in the story of Tony Finau, a 17-year-old golfer who stands 6 feet 4 inches, weighs 205 pounds and carries only one wood, 12 irons and a putter in his bag.</p>
        <p>Finau, who is of Samoan and Tongan descent, grew up in Salt Lake City with nine brothers and sisters. Days before graduating from high school May 30, he decided to forgo his amateur status for life as a professional.</p>
        <p>Beginning today, he will be among 12 players competing for a $2 million first prize at the Ultimate Game at Wynn Las Vegas, a tournament featuring long-shot players, hard-luck cases and various professionals culled from the country's minitours.</p>
        <p>''I think I'll have a lot of people in the actual golf world that will tell me I've made the wrong choice,'' Finau said recently of his decision to turn professional. ''I'm willing to handle that and prove them wrong.''</p>
        <p>Finau, a long hitter off the tee who won the 2006 Utah State Amateur title, is opting to start a career at a young age instead of competing in college. Although he was recruited by several top college programs, Finau has chosen a route more aligned to Michelle Wie, Sean O'Hair and Morgan Pressel, who each turned professional as teenagers.</p>
        <p>In fact, Finau is not the only golfer in his family. His younger brother, Gipper, 16, also turned professional at the Ultimate Game, but he failed to advance to the final 12.</p>
        <p>''They know how tough it is, with Michelle Wie and Ty Tryon,'' said Kelepi Finau, the boys' father, referring to the two young golfers who have struggled as professionals. ''They understand the only way to validate when you turn pro is if you go out and win something.</p>
        <p>Woods has provided a blueprint for young golfers and their families, though not always to a successful end. Although Woods attended Stanford for two years and won three consecutive United States Amateur titles before turning professional at age 20, others have taken a faster path to varied results.</p>
        <p>Wie, who turned professional at 16, has had a short career marked by ballooning scores and growing resentment among her peers. Tryon, who earned his PGA Tour card nearly six years ago at 17, has bounced around satellite tours in the United States and overseas.</p>
        <p>Like Woods, Wie and Tryon signed lucrative endorsement deals when they turned professional and were promoted as big hitters and can't-miss stars. Although both are still young, neither has reached the potential once predicted for them.</p>
        <p>''The big thing with Ty is more his organizational skills than anything else,'' said David Leadbetter, the swing teacher who has worked with Tryon and Wie. ''He's a kid who everything was done for him as a junior and he just didn't have the discipline. On Tour, there are certain things you have to do -- be consistent in your routines and so on. That's the thing that he has to do.''</p>
        <p>Tony Finau and his brother have built strong credentials, despite their youth. Gipper became the youngest player, at 16 years 20 days, to make the cut in a Nationwide Tour event last year. Finau, as a sophomore in 2004, won medalist honors at the 4A Utah State High School championship by shooting a 63 to win by six shots.</p>
        <p>To compete in the Ultimate Game, whose 36-hole, two-day final will be held at the Wynn Las Vegas Golf Course, Finau and his brother had to put up $50,000 apiece. They were sponsored by Dieter Esch and Brad Krassner, the owners of Wilhelmina Models, and Molonai Hola, a Utah businessman.</p>
        <p>''We live in Park City and have observed them in and around Utah,'' Esch said of Finau and Gipper in a telephone interview. ''When they turned pro, Wilhelmina decided to sign both to a contract.''</p>
        <p>While his brother lost his second-round preliminary match, Finau won both of his matches, including one against Rick Rhoden, the former major league pitcher who has competed in several Champions Tour events. The two victories allowed Finau to earn back his $50,000 entry fee plus an additional $50,000.</p>
        <p>Whether or not he wins the $2 million first-place prize, Finau will soon set off on a professional career, a gamble that he says he can win.</p>
        <p>''As long as I have the strong support of my family, I'll be all right,'' Finau said. ''Go out there and win, and there's nothing they can say about it.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
