<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sorenstam Strives to Become What She Was</title>
    <meta content="07annika" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/sports/golf/07annika.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852715"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Sorenstam, Annika</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E4D81E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="943" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sorenstam Strives to Become What She Was</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sorenstam Strives to Become What She Was</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At times, Annika Sorenstam broke into the kind of giddy smile that would rarely be coaxed from her in the middle of a competitive round. This occasion, she said, was worth letting a little joy break through her usual focused facade.</p>
        <p>''I'm just happy to be back,'' she said last weekend in Mount Pleasant, S.C., where she was the official host of the Ginn Tribute tournament. ''When you've been home, away from competition, you just appreciate it when you're back. I enjoyed the break, but I also miss it. I miss the competition.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Annika Sorenstam lost her No. 1 L.P.G.A. world ranking to Lorena Ochoa after two injured disks in her neck cost her playing time and disrupted her usual ferocious fitness routine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At times, Annika Sorenstam broke into the kind of giddy smile that would rarely be coaxed from her in the middle of a competitive round. This occasion, she said, was worth letting a little joy break through her usual focused facade.</p>
        <p>''I'm just happy to be back,'' she said last weekend in Mount Pleasant, S.C., where she was the official host of the Ginn Tribute tournament. ''When you've been home, away from competition, you just appreciate it when you're back. I enjoyed the break, but I also miss it. I miss the competition.''</p>
        <p>Sorenstam, 36, had not played since the beginning of April because of two injured disks in her neck. She abandoned her usual ferocious fitness routine for six weeks and watched her No. 1 world ranking slip away to Lorena Ochoa.</p>
        <p>Although she dialed back her swing -- and her expectations -- considerably while she cajoled her body back into playing form, Sorenstam said she surprised herself with her performance in her return. She was one under par after two rounds before ending up five over for the tournament, tied for 36th, a showing she considered encouraging entering this week's L.P.G.A. Championship at Bulle Rock Golf Course in Havre de Grace, Md. ''I'm not 100 percent and probably won't be for a while,'' she said. ''Give me a few weeks, and I hope to be up there again.''</p>
        <p>Sorenstam, though, has reached a crossroads in her career. After dominating the L.P.G.A. for so long, winning 69 tournaments and finishing No. 1 on the money list eight times, she hit a rough patch over the past year -- for her. She won three tournaments, including the United States Open, her 10th career major. But Ochoa won six times and overtook her as the Tour's hottest player.</p>
        <p>Sorenstam has also gone through a divorce, is opening a golf academy in Orlando, Fla., and has begun a new business designing golf courses. The first opened recently in China. Another is in the works in South Africa, and she has been hired to redesign Patriots Point Links in Mount Pleasant, not far from last week's tournament.</p>
        <p>She also has a new romantic relationship, with Mike McGee, who is the managing director of her company.</p>
        <p>''I think it's going well,'' Sorenstam said. ''I love my life. I love the stuff I'm doing. Things are going well on the course and off the course. So far, so good.''</p>
        <p>The biggest question is whether she can regain the form that made her the face of women's golf for so long. It is a high bar to reach, because she placed it so high in the prime of her career.</p>
        <p>Sorenstam's success changed the game. She was so fit, she prompted other players to take fitness more seriously. She hit the ball so far, she forced others to add strength to their games.</p>
        <p>''I admire her so much and respect her so much,'' Ochoa said. ''She's the one that made us better players, just to be in good shape, work hard, hit the ball farther, really raise the level of golf. I want to say thank you to her for that.''</p>
        <p>When she was dominating the game, Sorenstam managed to foster many of those feelings among the younger players who are now vying to knock her from the top.</p>
        <p>''She's just fabulous all the way around,'' said Brittany Lincicome, a 21-year-old from Seminole, Fla., who won her second pro tournament this year. ''Her golf game, the way she's played. If she wants to hit a draw, she hits a draw, and if she wants to hit a cut, she hits a cut. The shots she has are phenomenal.</p>
        <p>''Off the course, some people think she's mean or whatever, but when you talk to her, you find out that she's just very shy. If you can get her talking, she's awesome to talk to.''</p>
        <p>As she has grown older, Sorenstam has talked much less reluctantly. She was the host for a tournament in Sweden the past few years and decided to take on that role on the L.P.G.A. Tour this season. She laughed about the odd feeling of driving into RiverTowne Country Club with ''Hosted by Annika'' flags flying everywhere. She was involved in organizing the tournament, a role she took to heart.</p>
        <p>''I think I look at things a little differently than just kind of walking down the fairway,'' she said. ''Now I want to make sure we all have drinks on the tees. You look around, making sure the spectators are having a good time.''</p>
        <p>As she clearly stakes out some territory for her career after she stops playing golf, Sorenstam said she did not think about retiring. She said even her recent injury did not dampen her competitive drive.</p>
        <p>Last week, she told herself to treat her first tournament like a warm-up. She vowed not to swing too hard. She was driving nowhere near her usual length. She said she did not care about her score; she was focused on patiently working herself back into shape.</p>
        <p>But in the second round, she holed a chip shot for an eagle on the third hole, after a birdie on the previous hole. She found herself with a familiar feeling.</p>
        <p>''I hadn't really been looking at the leader board, but here I am, two under par, and all of a sudden I'm staring the leader board down,'' Sorenstam said, laughing. ''I had to tell myself, 'Go back and play your game and see what happens.' ''</p>
        <p>But, she said, ''It was a fun feeling.''</p>
        <p>She is happy to be back, but she will probably not settle for that much longer.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
