<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why Give Away The Airwaves?</title>
    <meta content="l07airwaves" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852742"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E7D71E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="418" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why Give Away The Airwaves?</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The fine F.C.C. commissioner Michael J. Copps (''The Price of Free Airwaves,'' Op-Ed, June 2) argues that broadcasters, in return for their longtime free use of the public airwaves, should be required, as a condition of their license renewal, to serve the public interest in worthy programming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The fine F.C.C. commissioner Michael J. Copps (''The Price of Free Airwaves,'' Op-Ed, June 2) argues that broadcasters, in return for their longtime free use of the public airwaves, should be required, as a condition of their license renewal, to serve the public interest in worthy programming.</p>
        <p>Denying renewals of licenses was a very rare and cumbersome process, even when the Federal Communications Commission was modestly responsive years ago to challengers claiming violations of the 1934 Communications Act, which obliges broadcast stations to meet the ''public interest, convenience and necessity'' criteria.</p>
        <p>Another approach, based on the public's being the landlord and the stations' being the tenant, is for Uncle Sam to charge the stations rent for what Commissioner Copps estimates is a half trillion dollars' worth of public airwaves. Some of the rental income could adequately finance studios, reporters and producers for audience networks created by legislation.</p>
        <p>Such a law would require reversion of, say, one hour prime time and one hour drive time daily from the control of the broadcasters to these public institutions. In this manner, the people would have their own station time, free of commercialism and advertising myopias, to meet a broad array of the public's information needs.</p>
        <p>Ralph Nader  Washington, June 4, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Michael J. Copps, an F.C.C. commissioner, discusses my colleagues' and my research showing that only 8 percent of local television newscasts covered a local political campaign in the month before the 2004 presidential election. In this and other ways he mentions, stations are not living up to their obligation to serve the public interest.</p>
        <p>While I applaud Mr. Copps's efforts to strengthen the license renewal system, no one can ensure that television stations are serving the public interest unless there is an effective system for monitoring their aggregate output.</p>
        <p>Currently, various academic and citizen groups struggle every year to finance research that can measure the quantity and nature of public affairs programming. But we lack the resources to capture all the programming we would like to.</p>
        <p>To put real teeth back into the license renewal system, stations should be required to create an online searchable database of their news, public affairs and children's programming. Unless the public has access to such a database, stations can easily continue to skirt their duty to serve the public interest.</p>
        <p>Matthew Hale  South Orange, N.J., June 3, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is an assistant professor at the Center for Public Service, Seton Hall University.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
