<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Selig Wants Giambi's Help in Steroid Inquiry</title>
    <meta content="07giambi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/sports/baseball/07giambi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Giambi, Jason</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Selig, Bud</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mitchell, George</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E0D61E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1069" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Selig Wants Giambi's Help in Steroid Inquiry</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Before Punishing Giambi, Selig Wants His Help</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY; Tyler Kepner contributed reporting from Chicago.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After Jason Giambi of the Yankees tacitly admitted last month to using steroids, Commissioner Bud Selig was placed in an awkward position. Selig wants to show that he is tough on steroid users, but punishing Giambi is problematic because if he used steroids, it occurred before Major League Baseball punished players for using performance-enhancing substances.</p>
        <p>Would Selig try to fine or suspend Giambi? What would other players think if Giambi was punished for being honest about the past? How would it look if Selig did nothing?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees’ Jason Giambi created new problems for himself by indicating publicly that he had used steroids.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After Jason Giambi of the Yankees tacitly admitted last month to using steroids, Commissioner Bud Selig was placed in an awkward position. Selig wants to show that he is tough on steroid users, but punishing Giambi is problematic because if he used steroids, it occurred before Major League Baseball punished players for using performance-enhancing substances.</p>
        <p>Would Selig try to fine or suspend Giambi? What would other players think if Giambi was punished for being honest about the past? How would it look if Selig did nothing?</p>
        <p>Selig took a calculated approach yesterday when he asked Giambi, the Yankees' designated hitter, to cooperate, within the next two weeks, with the investigation into the use of illegal performance-enhancing substances being conducted by the former Senator George Mitchell. If Giambi agrees to speak with Mitchell, it is believed he would be the first active player to do so.</p>
        <p>In a statement, Selig strongly hinted that any possible punishment of Giambi would be influenced by whether he cooperated with Mitchell. Selig noted that his decision about Giambi would not be completed until after Giambi had a chance to meet with Mitchell.</p>
        <p>''It is in the best interests of baseball for everyone, including players, to cooperate with Senator Mitchell in his investigation so that Senator Mitchell can provide me with a complete, thorough report,'' Selig said. ''Discipline for wrongdoing is important, but it is also important to create an environment so players can feel free to honestly and completely cooperate with this important investigation.''</p>
        <p>By asking Giambi to cooperate with Mitchell, Selig is apparently trying to appear to be a disciplinarian while also offering Giambi a way to avoid a possible punishment. If Selig announced a stern punishment yesterday, it would have in effect told players that they could be disciplined for being candid. It might have also ruined the slim chance Mitchell has of getting players to speak with him in an investigation that is now 15 months old.</p>
        <p>Several agents have said they have advised their clients not to talk with Mitchell. Mike Myers, a teammate of Giambi's, said he doubted Giambi would cooperate. Selig has no power to compel anyone to testify.</p>
        <p>Arn Tellem, Giambi's agent, said in an e-mail message that he would not comment on Selig's statement until he could speak with Giambi and lawyers for the players union. Giambi, who is on the 15-day disabled list with a torn plantar fascia in his left foot, was not with the Yankees in Chicago yesterday and was unavailable to comment. He is expected to be out for several weeks.</p>
        <p>After reviewing Selig's statement, Michael Weiner, the general counsel for the players union, released a statement saying that Giambi would consult with his lawyer and union lawyers before responding to Selig. Weiner said it would be Giambi's decision whether to meet with Mitchell.</p>
        <p>Giambi created problems for himself last month by suggesting publicly that he had used steroids. In an article in USA Today, Giambi discussed the subject of steroids in baseball and the mistakes he had made.</p>
        <p>''I was wrong for doing that stuff,'' Giambi said. ''What we should have done a long time ago was stand up -- players, ownership, everybody -- and said, 'We made a mistake.' ''</p>
        <p>But Weiner, in the statement, stressed that he did not think Giambi did anything for which he could be punished.</p>
        <p>''We do not believe that grounds exist for disciplining Jason Giambi based upon the newspaper article, anything which sprang from it, or his decision whether he will meet with Senator Mitchell,'' Weiner said.</p>
        <p>While the Yankees offered a one-sentence release saying they supported Selig, some players were annoyed by Selig's request. Myers, a reliever and a former player representative, called the Mitchell investigation ''a freight train without brakes'' and wondered what Selig was trying to achieve.</p>
        <p>''They just let Mitchell loose and have no control about what he does,'' Myers said. ''Selig doesn't have any control of him. The Senate doesn't have any control of him. He can pretty much do whatever he wants to do, and as far as Jason talking to Mitchell to determine what kind of punishment should be done, Jason didn't do anything to be penalized for, so that is a joke in itself.''</p>
        <p>Pitcher Mike Mussina, the Yankees' player representative, was asked if he thought Selig's approach would work.</p>
        <p>''To say either help us or you're suspended? No,'' Mussina said. ''But Bud thinks he can do whatever he wants, so we'll find out.''</p>
        <p>Johnny Damon, who is one of Giambi's closest friends on the Yankees, seemed more confused than anything.</p>
        <p>''I'm still trying to figure out what he's in trouble for: freedom of speech?'' Damon said. ''You can always go back and get someone for something they did in the past, whether it's stealing a pack of gum or whatever. I guess they think it's pretty serious, what he's saying. I'm not sure what they're trying to get out of him.''</p>
        <p>Before Selig's request, it was highly unlikely Giambi would have agreed to talk with Mitchell. And, even now, that is in doubt. Even if Mitchell promised Giambi immunity from being punished, Mitchell cannot promise him immunity from being asked to testify in any ongoing or future investigations involving steroids. The potential to be called to testify is a deterrent to Giambi and any player.</p>
        <p>After Giambi made his remarks to USA Today, he and Tellem met with three Major League Baseball lawyers May 23 to discuss his comments to the newspaper. The lawyers gave a report to Selig, who has been deliberating since then how to treat Giambi's case.</p>
        <p>According to an article in The San Francisco Chronicle in 2004, Giambi's testimony to a federal grand jury investigating the Balco steroid distribution case included an admittance of steroid use. Giambi, the article said, told the grand jury that he had used steroids and human growth hormone before signing a seven-year, $120 million deal with the Yankees in December of 2001 and while with the team in 2002 and 2003. Baseball's testing policy began in 2003, but players were not disciplined for a first offense until 2005.</p>
        <p>If Giambi was to give similar testimony to Mitchell, it would put the information on the public record and would prove useful to Mitchell's investigation. Because Giambi's testimony was leaked to a newspaper, it is not a matter of public record.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
