<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Student Play About Iraq War, Banned in School, Curtains Finally Go Up in Connecticut</title>
    <meta content="07play" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/nyregion/07play.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852810"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Wilton High School</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2D61E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Student Play About Iraq War, Banned in School, Curtains Finally Go Up in Connecticut</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Student Play About Iraq War, Banned in School, Curtains Finally Go Up in Connecticut</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON LEIGH COWAN</byline>
      <dateline>FAIRFIELD, Conn., June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three months after their principal canceled a school production they had prepared on the war in Iraq, a group of Wilton High School students staged a dramatic reading of the play Wednesday night to a packed house at a nearby theater.</p>
        <p>Sixteen cast members clutched their scripts and captivated a standing-room-only audience of 225 people. At several points during the 50-minute performance of the play, called ''Voices in Conflict,'' at the Fairfield Theater Company, audience members gasped, laughed and whistled appreciatively.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The play, called “Voices in Conflict,” attempts to portray the views of soldiers and others on the Iraq war in their own words.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three months after their principal canceled a school production they had prepared on the war in Iraq, a group of Wilton High School students staged a dramatic reading of the play Wednesday night to a packed house at a nearby theater.</p>
        <p>Sixteen cast members clutched their scripts and captivated a standing-room-only audience of 225 people. At several points during the 50-minute performance of the play, called ''Voices in Conflict,'' at the Fairfield Theater Company, audience members gasped, laughed and whistled appreciatively.</p>
        <p>''We've been talking about the play so long, it's just consumed our lives for so long, and now we're finally doing it,'' Erin Clancy, a cast member, said in the dressing room of the theater before the show. ''It's almost unfathomable.'' She plays Sgt. Lisa Haynes, with the Army Reserve.</p>
        <p>The play, which had been assigned as part of an advanced drama class, had been conceived as a series of monologues. Students helped their teacher, Bonnie Dickinson, assemble materials from film, books, blogs and other sources in an effort to portray the views of actual soldiers and others on the conflict in their own words. By tackling a topical play, Ms. Dickinson said she had hoped to deliver a more worthwhile experience for her students than usual high school fare like ''Grease.''</p>
        <p>But the production ran into trouble in Wilton, a town of about 18,000 about an hour's drive from Manhattan, when the principal canceled the production in March, weeks before it was to be staged on school grounds.</p>
        <p>Among the reasons for the cancellation, the principal, Timothy H. Canty, cited his concern that the production might be seen as biased against the war and might ruffle feelings in the community, which had lost one recent graduate to the war. He also said he did not think there was enough classroom and rehearsal time to ensure ''a legitimate instructional experience.''</p>
        <p>After an article in The New York Times about the cancellation prompted furious debate, the school district's lawyer ruled that the production could go forward as long as it was not presented as a school-sponsored event. That ruling cleared the way for the cast, half of whom are graduating, to accept offers from a number of high-wattage theaters to stage the play at no cost.</p>
        <p>''I'm glad the play was banned, in a way, because we would never have gotten to see it otherwise,'' said John Simon, a former head of the Connecticut branch of the American Civil Liberties Union, who had come to Fairfield to lead a panel discussion after the show.</p>
        <p>Included on the panel was Yvonne Latty, an author of ''In Conflict: Iraq War Veterans Speak Out on Duty, Loss and the Fight to Stay Alive,'' a book that provided inspiration and source material for the students' play. She said she was moved by the performance, especially seeing 18-year-old Erin Clancy thoroughly inhabit the ''40-year-old black woman in Oklahoma with post-traumatic stress,'' whom she had profiled in her book.</p>
        <p>Ms. Dickinson said, ''It's a wonderful feeling to know people are going to see this play, when I imagined we were going to be tossing it aside and never working on it again.''</p>
        <p>Miles Marek, the producing director for the Fairfield Theater Company, said, ''What attracted us to this project was the fact that the students were trying to tackle some challenging material and were being shut down and censored. We're sending troops all around the world to liberate Iraq and Afghanistan, and yet we're having to defend our own freedom of speech back home. It doesn't seem right as the lesson we're teaching our children in schools.''</p>
        <p>Wilton school administrators were in short supply in the opening night crowd, but Ms. Clancy said Mr. Canty tapped her on the shoulder at school earlier that day and wished her luck.</p>
        <p>Elliott Landon, the superintendent of nearby Westport's public schools, said he thought the play was ''very well done.'' Asked if he thought it ought to have been canceled by the Wilton school, Dr. Landon said, ''Not on the basis of what was presented tonight.''</p>
        <p>The production returns to the Fairfield Theater at 7:30 p.m. Friday. That night's panel will include the playwright Willy Holtzman.</p>
        <p>The student production will then be performed at the Vineyard Theater in New York City at 5 p.m. on Saturday; at the Culture Project at 8 p.m. on Sunday, followed by a panel featuring the filmmaker and actor Stanley Tucci; and at the Public Theater at 7 p.m. on Friday, June 15. The Vineyard is offering its 100 seats free on a first-come-first-served basis. All other sites are already sold out.</p>
        <p>There were the predictable opening-night glitches on Wednesday. One cast member, Mike Ward, was told he had to step in because another cast member, Chris Kozlowski had a conflict. ''He had a lacrosse game that got moved because of rain and his mom said he couldn't leave,'' said Devon Fontaine, 16, a fellow cast member. In the end, Mr. Kozlowski raced in on time.</p>
        <p>The students also had to juggle rehearsals between last Saturday's prom at the Maritime Aquarium in Norwalk, Conn. and next week's finals.</p>
        <p>On June 12, Ms. Dickinson will begin auditions at the high school for the fall play, selected she says with an eye toward generating minimal fuss: Shakespeare's ''Twelfth Night.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
