<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Feud Over Land Parcel Shadows Plans for a Permanent Memorial to United Flight 93</title>
    <meta content="07memorial" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/us/07memorial.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852795"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Park Service</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE4D61E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="722" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Feud Over Land Parcel Shadows Plans for a Permanent Memorial to United Flight 93</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Feud Over Land Parcel Shadows Plans for a Permanent Memorial to United Flight 93</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SEAN D. HAMILL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hamill, Sean D</byline>
      <dateline>SHANKSVILLE, Pa., June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two employees of the National Park Service used a garbage bag and duct tape on Wednesday to cover an unauthorized box erected to receive donations at a temporary memorial where visitors pay homage daily to the 40 victims of United Flight 93.</p>
        <p>The development was the latest in a strained relationship pitting the Park Service and a group representing the victims' families against the owner of the most critical piece of land for what is to become a permanent Flight 93 National Memorial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The National Park Service has demanded that the owner of the land where United Flight 93 crashed remove a box erected to receive donations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two employees of the National Park Service used a garbage bag and duct tape on Wednesday to cover an unauthorized box erected to receive donations at a temporary memorial where visitors pay homage daily to the 40 victims of United Flight 93.</p>
        <p>The development was the latest in a strained relationship pitting the Park Service and a group representing the victims' families against the owner of the most critical piece of land for what is to become a permanent Flight 93 National Memorial.</p>
        <p>''It's really sad we have to do this,'' Joanne Hanley, memorial superintendent, said after helping cover the box, which, bearing a drawing of an American flag and the words ''Flight 93 National Memorial,'' was thought by visitors to belong to the Park Service. ''But we need to protect the public interest and to be able to tell the story in a dignified manner.''</p>
        <p>United 93 was on its way from Newark to San Francisco on Sept. 11, 2001, when it was hijacked and then crashed in a field near this western Pennsylvania town. The following year Congress authorized the Park Service to create a permanent memorial but stipulated that the government could not invoke eminent domain for it; all sales of property were to be voluntary.</p>
        <p>The most crucial property is 273 acres where both the crash site and the temporary memorial, which overlooks the site and is less than an acre in all, are situated. It is owned by Michael Svonavec's family mining company.</p>
        <p>Mr. Svonavec, who put up the donation box last Saturday, says the dispute surrounding it has less to do with confusion on the part of visitors than with an effort to bring him bad publicity and so pressure him to sell cheaply. He says he sought the donations as a way to pay the $10,000-a-month bill for security he has provided since March, when the federal money that was paying the county sheriff to patrol the crash site and the temporary memorial ran out.</p>
        <p>Though the Park Service says it does not need security there -- just two cases of vandalism have been reported in the last five years -- Mr. Svonavec says that with thousands of visitors a week, he has liability concerns. Whatever the case, the Park Service, which controls the temporary memorial site under an agreement with him, has given him until Friday to remove the box.</p>
        <p>The Park Service has been working for more than four years on a $58 million memorial plan involving about 2,000 acres. It is expected that up to 1,300 acres will be bought by the government or the families, with the rest protected by easements that restrict development.</p>
        <p>Two small parcels totaling 60 acres have already been bought. But about a dozen landowners have not reached final agreement, including Mr. Svonavec, whose family has owned its parcel, former mining land, since 1961.</p>
        <p>Mr. Svonavec says he began negotiating with the Park Service to sell most of his property -- he intends to donate the several acres that are the crash site -- about three years ago. The Park Service made an initial offer of an undisclosed sum last year, but he refused to even look at it, he says, because it was not based on an appraisal that the agency had obtained. The agency has not explained why it rejected the appraisal.</p>
        <p>Families of Flight 93 then entered negotiations, ready to spend much of the $1 million that Universal Studios had donated to the group after release of the movie ''United 93.'' Patrick White, vice president of the organization, says it was during these talks that Mr. Svonavec said he thought the land was ''worth $50 million, but you can have it for $10 million'' -- much more than the half a million the group had contemplated.</p>
        <p>Mr. Svonavec denies making that remark. In fact, he says, he does not know what the land is worth because he has not obtained an appraisal himself, though he is preparing to do so. Now, he says, he is refusing to negotiate with the families group and is waiting for the Park Service to obtain a second appraisal of its own so he can sell the property and put it all behind him.</p>
        <p>''I'm not a public relations person, I'm a mining engineer,'' he said. ''It hasn't been fun.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
