<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Partisan Battles Mark End Of Regular Hartford Session</title>
    <meta content="07conn" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852731"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E0D81E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Partisan Battles Mark End Of Regular Hartford Session</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER MEDINA</byline>
      <dateline>HARTFORD, June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the state legislature prepared to end its regular lawmaking session on Wednesday, there were times when the political leaders could not even agree to disagree.</p>
        <p>After months of wrangling, the governor, M. Jodi Rell, a Republican, and Democratic legislative leaders were still at loggerheads over the state budget Wednesday night, making it all but certain that a special session would be needed in the coming weeks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the state legislature prepared to end its regular lawmaking session on Wednesday, there were times when the political leaders could not even agree to disagree.</p>
        <p>After months of wrangling, the governor, M. Jodi Rell, a Republican, and Democratic legislative leaders were still at loggerheads over the state budget Wednesday night, making it all but certain that a special session would be needed in the coming weeks.</p>
        <p>Although talks were expected to continue late into the night, Mrs. Rell said she thought it was ''very unlikely'' that she could come to an agreement with the General Assembly, which is controlled by Democrats, over her proposed $17.5 billion budget at a time when the state has a surplus of $918 million.</p>
        <p>''It's a terribly frustrating process, to say the least,'' Mrs. Rell said during an afternoon news conference in her office. ''The majority party is utterly intent on increasing spending and raising taxes, neither of which as governor I will allow to happen.''</p>
        <p>But minutes later, the Democrats Mrs. Rell said she was fighting convened their own news conference, saying that her chief negotiator was going over budget numbers at that very moment.</p>
        <p>''This is really crazy,'' James A. Amann, the House speaker, said outside the chamber around 2 p.m. ''We've got 10 hours to go.''</p>
        <p>He called the most recent budget meeting -- held at 3 a.m. Wednesday -- ''very cordial'' and added, ''We are so close to a deal it's ridiculous.'' But the governor's remarks at her own news conference threatened to ''blow it all up,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The impasse apparently centered on the Democrats' persistence in trying to overhaul the state's income tax structure by increasing the tax rate for those who earn more than $272,000 a year. The Democrats have long favored such a change, which they say makes the income tax progressive, rather than the relatively flat structure the state now has.</p>
        <p>Both houses of the legislature passed the tax plan bill last week. But Mrs. Rell has adamantly blocked the plan, vetoing the bill shortly after the legislative vote and railing against it again on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Although producing a budget is the main priority of the legislative session, the state has until the end of the fiscal year, June 30, to do so without passing any emergency spending bills.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, Mrs. Rell called for a special session to begin on Tuesday. But legislative leaders had already acknowledged earlier in the week that a special session would be needed to vote on the budget bills, and accused Mrs. Rell of grandstanding.</p>
        <p>''We don't need the governor to wag her finger and call us into special session,'' said Donald E. Williams Jr., the Senate president pro tempore. ''We know what we have to do. It's simply an attempt for her to pre-empt us, to get one more headline.''</p>
        <p>The renewed sparring came a day after the state's nonpartisan Office of Fiscal Analysis increased its estimate for the budget surplus by $71 million, bringing the total to $918 million. The state also has nearly $1 billion in its so-called rainy-day fund.</p>
        <p>The incomplete budget has left several other items unsettled. The legislature has passed a health care bill that would broaden eligibility for the state's health insurance program for children and increase Medicaid reimbursements for hospitals and doctors, among other things. But Mrs. Rell has said she will veto the bill because it is akin to passing a ''piecemeal'' spending plan.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, she used the same rationale to issue a line-item veto on legislation meant to encourage energy conservation. That veto incensed Democrats, who had battled internally for more than two years to come to an agreement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams and Mr. Amann both said Mrs. Rell was being disingenuous, pointing out that in previous years, she signed spending legislation before a budget agreement had been reached.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
