<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Buyout, the Isles Have Finally Seen the Back of Yashin</title>
    <meta content="07islanders" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/sports/hockey/07islanders.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852752"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Islanders</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Yashin, Alexei</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E4D71E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="751" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Buyout, the Isles Have Finally Seen the Back of Yashin</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Buyout, the Isles Have Finally Seen the Back of Yashin</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The quirky Islanders conceded perhaps their biggest business blunder in franchise history yesterday when they gave up on Alexei Yashin, buying out the last four years of his weighty 10-year contract.</p>
        <p>Yashin, the Islanders' underachieving and unpopular center and captain, will receive $17.63 million, in essence, to walk away. General Manager Garth Snow made it clear in a conference call with reporters that the Islanders needed to cut their losses with Yashin to continue their makeover.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The quirky Islanders conceded perhaps their biggest business blunder in franchise history Wednesday when they gave up on Alexei Yashin, buying out the last four years of his 10-year contract.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The quirky Islanders conceded perhaps their biggest business blunder in franchise history yesterday when they gave up on Alexei Yashin, buying out the last four years of his weighty 10-year contract.</p>
        <p>Yashin, the Islanders' underachieving and unpopular center and captain, will receive $17.63 million, in essence, to walk away. General Manager Garth Snow made it clear in a conference call with reporters that the Islanders needed to cut their losses with Yashin to continue their makeover.</p>
        <p>''It's obviously a new beginning for Alexei, and it's a new beginning for the Islanders organization,'' Snow said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The Islanders are jettisoning Yashin in an effort to hold on to other top players, including forwards Ryan Smyth and Jason Blake. Smyth, 31, a fearless, playmaking left wing acquired from Edmonton this season at the league's trading deadline, becomes an unrestricted free agent July 1. Blake, 32, who had a career-high 40 goals this season, can also become a free agent.</p>
        <p>Yashin, who turns 34 on Nov. 5, helped the Islanders make the playoffs in four of the five seasons he was with the team. But he never scored more than 32 goals in a season, and he was hampered by a sprained knee this past season after he got off to a good start.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately, he got hurt and just couldn't get back to where he was before,'' Coach Ted Nolan said of Yashin, who had 18 goals and 32 assists in 58 regular-season games.</p>
        <p>After the Islanders acquired Smyth, he quickly became the conscience of the team -- a blunt, passionate spokesman that Yashin never was in two seasons as the Islanders' captain.</p>
        <p>Don Meehan, Smyth's agent, said yesterday that he and the Islanders had had preliminary discussions about a new contract. But he said the team's decision about Yashin would not be critical in determining whether Smyth would re-sign.</p>
        <p>Smyth, whose nickname is Captain Canada, scored only 5 goals in 18 games for the Islanders, but he helped them win their last four regular-season games to squeeze into the playoffs. They lost to the Buffalo Sabres in five games.</p>
        <p>''We're going to do everything we can to keep him,'' Snow said of Smyth, who would most likely become the team's captain if he stays with the Islanders.</p>
        <p>The money the Islanders save on Yashin could help re-sign Smyth, Blake or other free agents.</p>
        <p>Although Snow and Nolan were careful not to criticize Yashin yesterday, it was obvious they had deliberated for a while before determining that he was too expensive to keep.</p>
        <p>Had Yashin played for the Islanders until the end of his contract, he would have earned $26.45 million. Under the collective bargaining agreement, the Islanders could buy him out at two-thirds of that total. He will be paid $17.63 million over eight years.</p>
        <p>''This decision was not based on a month's play or one game,'' Nolan said. ''It was a thought-out process.''</p>
        <p>Charles Wang, the Islanders' owner, is not bashful about writing big contracts in an effort to improve his team; last September, he signed goaltender Rick DiPietro to a 15-year, $67.5 million contract. (The length of the contract was a league record.)</p>
        <p>Yashin signed an $87.5 million contract after the Islanders acquired him in June 2001 from the Ottawa Senators for the hulking defenseman Zdeno Chara and a first-round draft choice that the Senators used to pick the talented center Jason Spezza.</p>
        <p>The length of Yashin's contract, then a record, was questioned by Gary Bettman, the N.H.L. commissioner. (The value of the contract was cut by 24 percent after a new collective bargaining agreement was signed in 2005.)</p>
        <p>During a conference call with reporters in October 2001, Bettman said: ''I don't understand the Alexei Yashin contract. I don't understand why it's 10 years, but it's not my team and not my money. Time will tell whether it was the correct move on their part.''</p>
        <p>Pleasant and well liked, but often playing with an icy indifference, Yashin lost favor with Nolan, who was in his first year as the team's coach, and who attempted to build his team on grit and guile.</p>
        <p>Yashin played sparingly in the playoffs and did not record a goal or an assist.</p>
        <p>''I've always believed in the vision Charles Wang has for the organization, and although I won't be a part of it, I believe that the team is headed in the right direction,'' Yashin said in a statement released by the team.</p>
        <p>''I'm looking forward to this new chapter in my life.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
