<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TODAY IN BUSINESS</title>
    <meta content="07biztoday" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852733"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EFD81E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="894" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TODAY IN BUSINESS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WARNING FOR TWO DIABETES DRUGS -- The Food and Drug Administration has called for the toughest safety warning on two diabetes drugs, Avandia and Actos. The decision comes a year after the agency's safety reviewers strongly recommended just such a step. It also occurs during a Congressional inquiry into why the agency delayed its warnings about Avandia. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>A medical researcher told a House hearing about name-calling and a veiled threat of a lawsuit by a drug company executive after the researcher had criticized Avandia. [A30.]</p>
        <p>CHINA TO OVERHAUL FOOD LAWS -- China said that it was overhauling its food and drug safety regulations and would introduce nationwide inspections. The announcement was a response to growing international concerns about tainted food and counterfeit drugs. [A1.]</p>
        <p>A BOOMING BUSINESS IN AUTO PARTS -- China's auto parts exports have increased more than sixfold in the last five years, nearly topping $1 billion in April, and are part of a broader shift as China moves up from basic goods like textiles and shoes toward higher-value industrial goods that compete directly with countries like the United States. [C1.]</p>
        <p>AUTOMAKERS OPPOSE ENERGY BILL  -- The chief executives of General Motors, Ford and Chrysler met with Senate lawmakers, less than a week before Democrats plan a vote on a sprawling energy bill, and asserted that the bill's proposed increase in mileage requirements would be impossible to meet and would gravely damage the industry. [C1.]</p>
        <p>BUILDING A BETTER PATENT SYSTEM -- The Bush administration wants to revamp the nation's patent system, requiring better information from inventors and allowing public scrutiny of applications, according to the patent office's chief. The goal, said Jon W. Dudas, above, the director of the United States Patent and Trademark Office, is to improve the quality of patents and curb the rising wave of patent disputes and lawsuits. [C3.]</p>
        <p>LESSONS FROM LONDON -- The Bancroft family, owners of a controlling interest in Dow Jones, is trying to learn from the lessons of The Times of London as they attempt to come up with a system for keeping The Wall Street Journal's newsroom independent of Rupert Murdoch, the head of the News Corporation who has bid to buy the company. [C1.]</p>
        <p>INTEREST RATE JITTERS -- For the second consecutive day, Wall Street recoiled at the prospect that inflation would not settle down enough to suit the Federal Reserve. And investors appeared to worry not only that interest rates will stay where they are, but that the Fed could raise them even higher. [C1.]</p>
        <p>RABBIT EARS WILL NEED SOME HELP -- A broadcasters group unveiled two versions of devices that television viewers will need beginning Feb. 17, 2009, if they use rabbit ears or rooftop antennas to receive their television signal. On that date, stations must switch from traditional analog signals to digital broadcasting. [C3.]</p>
        <p>ASTRAZENECA EXECUTIVE LEAVING -- AstraZeneca, Britain's second-largest drug maker after GlaxoSmithKline, said that its chief financial officer was leaving to join to Goldman Sachs, one of AstraZeneca's corporate brokers, as a managing director. Jon Symonds, who joined Zeneca from KPMG in 1997 and was instrumental in the $30 billion merger with Astra of Sweden a year later, will step down at the end of July. [C5.]</p>
        <p>BUSH OPPOSES EMISSION TARGETS -- The White House said it would hold firm against concrete long-term targets for reducing greenhouse gas emissions, a major priority for Chancellor Angela Merkel of Germany, the host of this week's Group of 8 meeting. [A14.]</p>
        <p>EUROPEAN RATE GOES UP -- The European Central Bank raised borrowing costs to their highest level in nearly six years, pointing to a humming economy that, while welcome, raised the risk of higher inflation. European stock markets fell. [C5.]</p>
        <p>ORIENTING ELECTRONICS TO WOMEN -- Making a consumer electronic product more appealing to women no longer means offering a pink or pastel version. More manufacturers are discovering that feminizing technology is more about a product's fundamentals, often expressed in its ease of use. [C7.]</p>
        <p>PRUDENTIAL CLOSES RESEARCH UNIT  -- Prudential Financial decided to close its small, struggling equity research and sales business. About 420 people will be laid off. [C3.]</p>
        <p>CITIGROUP TO PAY $15 MILLION FINE -- NASD, a regulator of brokerage firms, said that Citigroup will pay $15.2 million to settle claims that its brokers had coaxed employees of the BellSouth Corporation into retiring early on exaggerated projections for investment returns. [C4.]</p>
        <p>FENDI SETTLES WAL-MART SUIT -- Fendi, the Italian fashion designer and maker of luxury products, settled a lawsuit against Wal-Mart Stores that contended the retailer had sold counterfeit handbags and wallets in its Sam's Club stores. [C9.]</p>
        <p>CBS RELENTS AFTER SERIES PROTEST -- CBS reversed course three weeks after canceling the apocalyptic drama ''Jericho,'' and ordered seven new episodes after a sustained and creative protest by fans of the series. The new episodes are for broadcast late this year or early in 2008. [C4.]</p>
        <p>PHONE BOOKS ON A DIET -- The fat phone book is losing some of its girth as more people give up their land lines for cellphones. In Manhattan, despite population gains in recent years, the 2007 Verizon White Pages was 142 pages smaller than the 2006 edition. [B1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WARNING FOR TWO DIABETES DRUGS -- The Food and Drug Administration has called for the toughest safety warning on two diabetes drugs, Avandia and Actos. The decision comes a year after the agency's safety reviewers strongly recommended just such a step. It also occurs during a Congressional inquiry into why the agency delayed its warnings about Avandia. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>A medical researcher told a House hearing about name-calling and a veiled threat of a lawsuit by a drug company executive after the researcher had criticized Avandia. [A30.]</p>
        <p>CHINA TO OVERHAUL FOOD LAWS -- China said that it was overhauling its food and drug safety regulations and would introduce nationwide inspections. The announcement was a response to growing international concerns about tainted food and counterfeit drugs. [A1.]</p>
        <p>A BOOMING BUSINESS IN AUTO PARTS -- China's auto parts exports have increased more than sixfold in the last five years, nearly topping $1 billion in April, and are part of a broader shift as China moves up from basic goods like textiles and shoes toward higher-value industrial goods that compete directly with countries like the United States. [C1.]</p>
        <p>AUTOMAKERS OPPOSE ENERGY BILL  -- The chief executives of General Motors, Ford and Chrysler met with Senate lawmakers, less than a week before Democrats plan a vote on a sprawling energy bill, and asserted that the bill's proposed increase in mileage requirements would be impossible to meet and would gravely damage the industry. [C1.]</p>
        <p>BUILDING A BETTER PATENT SYSTEM -- The Bush administration wants to revamp the nation's patent system, requiring better information from inventors and allowing public scrutiny of applications, according to the patent office's chief. The goal, said Jon W. Dudas, above, the director of the United States Patent and Trademark Office, is to improve the quality of patents and curb the rising wave of patent disputes and lawsuits. [C3.]</p>
        <p>LESSONS FROM LONDON -- The Bancroft family, owners of a controlling interest in Dow Jones, is trying to learn from the lessons of The Times of London as they attempt to come up with a system for keeping The Wall Street Journal's newsroom independent of Rupert Murdoch, the head of the News Corporation who has bid to buy the company. [C1.]</p>
        <p>INTEREST RATE JITTERS -- For the second consecutive day, Wall Street recoiled at the prospect that inflation would not settle down enough to suit the Federal Reserve. And investors appeared to worry not only that interest rates will stay where they are, but that the Fed could raise them even higher. [C1.]</p>
        <p>RABBIT EARS WILL NEED SOME HELP -- A broadcasters group unveiled two versions of devices that television viewers will need beginning Feb. 17, 2009, if they use rabbit ears or rooftop antennas to receive their television signal. On that date, stations must switch from traditional analog signals to digital broadcasting. [C3.]</p>
        <p>ASTRAZENECA EXECUTIVE LEAVING -- AstraZeneca, Britain's second-largest drug maker after GlaxoSmithKline, said that its chief financial officer was leaving to join to Goldman Sachs, one of AstraZeneca's corporate brokers, as a managing director. Jon Symonds, who joined Zeneca from KPMG in 1997 and was instrumental in the $30 billion merger with Astra of Sweden a year later, will step down at the end of July. [C5.]</p>
        <p>BUSH OPPOSES EMISSION TARGETS -- The White House said it would hold firm against concrete long-term targets for reducing greenhouse gas emissions, a major priority for Chancellor Angela Merkel of Germany, the host of this week's Group of 8 meeting. [A14.]</p>
        <p>EUROPEAN RATE GOES UP -- The European Central Bank raised borrowing costs to their highest level in nearly six years, pointing to a humming economy that, while welcome, raised the risk of higher inflation. European stock markets fell. [C5.]</p>
        <p>ORIENTING ELECTRONICS TO WOMEN -- Making a consumer electronic product more appealing to women no longer means offering a pink or pastel version. More manufacturers are discovering that feminizing technology is more about a product's fundamentals, often expressed in its ease of use. [C7.]</p>
        <p>PRUDENTIAL CLOSES RESEARCH UNIT  -- Prudential Financial decided to close its small, struggling equity research and sales business. About 420 people will be laid off. [C3.]</p>
        <p>CITIGROUP TO PAY $15 MILLION FINE -- NASD, a regulator of brokerage firms, said that Citigroup will pay $15.2 million to settle claims that its brokers had coaxed employees of the BellSouth Corporation into retiring early on exaggerated projections for investment returns. [C4.]</p>
        <p>FENDI SETTLES WAL-MART SUIT -- Fendi, the Italian fashion designer and maker of luxury products, settled a lawsuit against Wal-Mart Stores that contended the retailer had sold counterfeit handbags and wallets in its Sam's Club stores. [C9.]</p>
        <p>CBS RELENTS AFTER SERIES PROTEST -- CBS reversed course three weeks after canceling the apocalyptic drama ''Jericho,'' and ordered seven new episodes after a sustained and creative protest by fans of the series. The new episodes are for broadcast late this year or early in 2008. [C4.]</p>
        <p>PHONE BOOKS ON A DIET -- The fat phone book is losing some of its girth as more people give up their land lines for cellphones. In Manhattan, despite population gains in recent years, the 2007 Verizon White Pages was 142 pages smaller than the 2006 edition. [B1.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
