<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Lifetime Spent Fleeing The Savagery That Follows</title>
    <meta content="07gree" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/books/07gree.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852662"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Oates, Joyce Carol</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">The Gravediggers Daughter (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E7D91E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="931" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Lifetime Spent Fleeing The Savagery That Follows</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Lifetime Spent Fleeing the Savagery That Follows</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELLE GREEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Gravedigger's Daughter  By Joyce Carol Oates  582 pages. Ecco. $26.95.</p>
        <p>Born in filth on a ship full of German refugees in New York harbor in 1936, Rebecca Schwart, like so many of Joyce Carol Oates's heroines, will live a life touched by enough violence to supply a slasher movie. At 13 she is cornered by her shotgun-wielding father, the eponymous gravedigger, who has killed a man and blown his wife into a headless heap inside their hovel near the cemetery gates. Instead of murdering his daughter too, he sends himself into oblivion, showering her with gore. ''She'd wiped that face off her own damn face!'' Ms. Oates writes of Rebecca. ''She'd picked that face out of her hair.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Though clearly meant to have an epic sweep, “The Gravedigger’s Daughter” feels like a four-hour film that should have been cut by 90 minutes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Gravedigger's Daughter  By Joyce Carol Oates  582 pages. Ecco. $26.95.</p>
        <p>Born in filth on a ship full of German refugees in New York harbor in 1936, Rebecca Schwart, like so many of Joyce Carol Oates's heroines, will live a life touched by enough violence to supply a slasher movie. At 13 she is cornered by her shotgun-wielding father, the eponymous gravedigger, who has killed a man and blown his wife into a headless heap inside their hovel near the cemetery gates. Instead of murdering his daughter too, he sends himself into oblivion, showering her with gore. ''She'd wiped that face off her own damn face!'' Ms. Oates writes of Rebecca. ''She'd picked that face out of her hair.''</p>
        <p>But this is just the prologue. The author also places her protagonist into the path of a murderer who butchers at least six young women. And she will throw her into the clutches of a minor mobster who beats her child into unconsciousness and her into near-oblivion.</p>
        <p>Yes, this is the sort of sanguinary stuff in which Ms. Oates has been buried to the elbows for four decades; ripped-from-the-headlines crimes have fueled her work since her short story ''Where Are You Going, Where Have You Been?'' (inspired by a prolific killer in Tucson) appeared in 1966. And yes, there is much to admire in this bittersweet tale of one woman's triumph of the will.</p>
        <p>At 582 pages, however, Ms. Oates's 36th work of fiction begins to sink under its own dolorous weight. Though clearly meant to have an epic sweep, ''The Gravedigger's Daughter'' feels like a four-hour film that should have been cut by 90 minutes.</p>
        <p>Flip to the overheated scene on Page 548: By now well off and no longer in peril, Rebecca enters ''a state of suspended panic'' when her teenage son takes the stage in a piano competition. As ''vivid crystalline notes exploded in the air with hurtful volume,'' his performance becomes ''a tortuous spectacle'' capped by a vision of her dead parents (who had sung arias to each other in Munich). ''Blurred with distance as with time, their faces hovered at the rear of the concert hall.  They were stunned, disbelieving.''</p>
        <p>Dedicated to Ms. Oates's grandmother Blanche Morgenstern (''the gravedigger's daughter'') and set in rural New York, where the author was raised and much of her fiction is set, the novel is strongest when Ms. Oates is describing the poverty and shame that sends Rebecca clawing her way into the world: Jacob Schwart works 12 hours a day digging and weeding graves, emerging hunched and filthy, like ''a troll.'' Terrorized by vandals and taunted by shouts of ''Gravedigger! Kraut! Nazi! Jew!,'' he and his family shrink into a dank caretaker's cottage whose water supply is poisoned by what his wife, Anna -- a frightened rabbit of a woman -- believes to be seepage from the graves.</p>
        <p>Though she sinks into a kind of fugue state after a refugee boat carrying her sister's family is turned away from New York harbor, Anna has a disturbingly seductive quality that in Ms. Oates's hands seems to mark her for destruction. Blowsy and bovine, she excites jealousy in her ruined husband.</p>
        <p>Her daughter, however, is infused with the energy -- and the moxie -- of the New World. In a nagging interior refrain that is an echo of Jacob's voice, Ms. Oates makes it clear that, though the Schwarts and their two sons (all born in Germany) will never hold their heads above water, Rebecca will be allowed to forge an identity because: ''You -- you are born here. They will not hurt you.'' Over and over his words sift into Rebecca's consciousness as she scrabbles up the social ladder: ''In animal life the weak are quickly disposed of,'' Jacob says. ''So you must hide your weakness, Rebecca.''</p>
        <p>And hide it she does. The most compelling aspect of this story is the manner in which the gravedigger's daughter creates a new persona, remaining tense and watchful even as she launches herself into the role of an American whom she christens Hazel Jones. Rootless, gullible, on the run from the creep who has fathered her child, she knows that smart women don't put all their cards on the table. Like others in the Chautauqua Valley town where she takes a soul-deadening factory job, Rebecca understands that ''a married woman saves in secret, not in a bank but somewhere in her house, for that day of reckoning worse-come-to-worst.''</p>
        <p>On the lam, the daughter of doomed immigrants becomes a mutable creature who only partly swallows her survivor guilt. In the beginning she takes her cues from movie culture; working as an usher, she styles herself as a peppy, eye-catching version of Rita Hayworth. Later, as a salesclerk in a music store, she thinks of Hazel as a neat, exaggeratedly feminine ''other,'' realizing that she has ''established for herself a personality distinct as a comic strip character: Olive Oyl, Jiggs-and-Maggie, Dick Tracy, Brenda Starr Girl Reporter.''</p>
        <p>In the land of second acts she could do worse. Of course Ms. Oates will not allow poor Hazel to rest easy: A last-minute plot twist (''the most fantastical revelation of her life'') literally sends her into a faint. For a moment she considers waking her longtime lover -- a jazz musician and journalist who knows nothing of Rebecca and her bloody past -- to deliver a histrionic confession. ''I will tell him my life has been a lie,'' she declares. A bit of a whopper, yes, and often schmaltzy, but engaging enough for those who don't cling to every word.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES Michelle Green, a book critic, is the author of ''The Dream at the End of the World: Paul Bowles and the Literary Renegades in Tangier'' (HarperCollins).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Michelle Green, a book critic, is the author of ''The Dream at the End of the World: Paul Bowles and the Literary Renegades in Tangier'' (HarperCollins).</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
