<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Through Erik Satie's Music, a Trip Back in Time to the Soundless and the Surreal</title>
    <meta content="07sati" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/arts/music/07sati.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852672"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">McDonell, Nick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E6D91E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="451" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Through Erik Satie's Music, a Trip Back in Time to the Soundless and the Surreal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Through Erik Satie’s Music, a Trip Back in Time to the Soundless and the Surreal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIEN SCHWEITZER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''It's so intense I can't stand it,'' the pianist Bruce Levingston said laughingly after playing Erik Satie's Sarabande No. 2, Gnossienne No. 4 and Gymnopédie No. 1 to open his concert at the French Institute Alliance Française's Florence Gould Hall on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The intensity Mr. Levingston clearly felt was transmitted in his introspective, dreamy performance, very different from the mood of Satie's playful ''Sports et Divertissements'' (1914), which came next.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The highlight of the evening was a performance of Satie’s music to “Entr’acte,” Rene Clair’s brilliant (and still enjoyably trippy) 1924 silent Surrealist film.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''It's so intense I can't stand it,'' the pianist Bruce Levingston said laughingly after playing Erik Satie's Sarabande No. 2, Gnossienne No. 4 and Gymnopédie No. 1 to open his concert at the French Institute Alliance Française's Florence Gould Hall on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The intensity Mr. Levingston clearly felt was transmitted in his introspective, dreamy performance, very different from the mood of Satie's playful ''Sports et Divertissements'' (1914), which came next.</p>
        <p>The publisher of that work initially approached Stravinsky about writing music to accompany a book of Charles Martin's prints. But Stravinsky scoffed at the fee, and the publisher turned to Satie. A genuine bohemian, Satie thought the fee obscenely high and became surely the only poor artist ever to insist on a reduced paycheck.</p>
        <p>Martin's Art Deco prints depicting leisure activities, for which Satie's short, programmatic movements provide a whimsical soundtrack, were projected on a screen.</p>
        <p>But the composer instructed that his quirky texts be narrated between the 21 short movements, not over the music, as Nick McDonell did here. Some of Satie's musical quotations, like ''Frère Jacques'' in ''The Awakening of the Bride,'' and other details were therefore harder to discern.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Levingston and Mr. McDonell were lively partners, and Mr. McDonell, a novelist, narrated Virgil Thomson's translations with confidence and charm, although without an essential element of whimsy.</p>
        <p>The concert opened a René Clair film series, and the highlight of the evening was a performance of Satie's music to ''Entr'acte,'' Clair's brilliant (and still enjoyably trippy) 1924 silent Surrealist film. It was shown that year in Paris during the intermission of Satie's ballet ''Relâche.'' Mr. Levingston played as the film was shown.</p>
        <p>Satie's score (called ''Cinéma'') is remarkably synchronized with the action and is one of the earliest examples of music matched to film. In one scene he parodies Chopin's Funeral March, then accompanies shots of mourners bounding in slow motion after a camel-drawn hearse with short, rhythmic figures whose accents mirror people's feet hitting the ground. Surreal indeed.</p>
        <p>Carnival music is heard as the quirky crowd circles a mini-Eiffel Tower, and the tempo quickens when the throngs race after the hearse.</p>
        <p>Satie appears in the film alongside Marcel Duchamp and Francis Picabia, looking utterly bourgeois in a suit and bowler, his uniform from 1905 on, despite his anti-materialism and slobbish living conditions.</p>
        <p>Satie was certainly eccentric but was an influential innovator with a razor-sharp wit. This unusual program and the comments from Satie's contemporaries that Mr. Levingston read offered lively insights into Satie's surreal worlds and fascinating artistic collaborations.</p>
        <p>The film series ''The Surreal Delicacy of René Clair'' runs through July 31 at Florence Gould Hall, 55 East 59th Street, Manhattan; schedule: fiaf.org.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
