<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2012 Olympic Logo: Sparks Precede the Flame</title>
    <meta content="07olympics" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/world/europe/07olympics.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852685"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2012)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Logotypes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">London (Eng)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">London (England)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E0D91E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2012 Olympic Logo: Sparks Precede the Flame</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">2012 Olympic Logo: Sparks Precede the Flame</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, June 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rollout of London's new logo for 2012 Olympics has become front-page news and provoked sharp criticism; organizing committee insists that it will not withdraw logo, which is composition of jagged-edged cutouts roughly denoting figures 2012 in pink and yellow; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was said to provoke epileptic seizures. Someone compared it to a broken swastika or ''some sort of comical sex act between 'The Simpsons.' '' The mayor was not amused.</p>
        <p>The rollout of London's new logo for the 2012 Olympics, in other words, has not been an unalloyed triumph.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The rollout of London’s new logo for the 2012 Olympics, which has become front-page news, has not been an unalloyed triumph.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was said to provoke epileptic seizures. Someone compared it to a broken swastika or ''some sort of comical sex act between 'The Simpsons.' '' The mayor was not amused.</p>
        <p>The rollout of London's new logo for the 2012 Olympics, in other words, has not been an unalloyed triumph.</p>
        <p>Two days after it was introduced on Monday, the logo -- a composition of subway-graffitilike, jagged-edged cutouts roughly denoting the figures 2012, in pink and yellow -- has become front-page news. One newspaper, The Sun, ran a competition to discover whether amateur designers -- two of whom it identified in its pages as a monkey and a blind woman -- could do better.</p>
        <p>An online petition gathered 35,000 signatures to protest the logo and demand that it be replaced. But perhaps the brouhaha evoked some other considerations, most notably concerning Britons' ambivalent attitude not just to winning the right to stage the Olympics, but also to dealing with innovation, design and success itself.</p>
        <p>The logo ''is not simple, it is not memorable, it is not beautiful,'' the columnist Magnus Linklater wrote in The Times of London. ''It is bound to be a success.''</p>
        <p>To the 2012 Organizing Committee, ''the new emblem is dynamic, modern and flexible.''</p>
        <p>An animated version on a Web site was withdrawn after advocacy groups representing people with epilepsy said that flashing lights provoked more than 10 seizures among the estimated 23,000 people vulnerable to a photo-sensitive form of epilepsy.</p>
        <p>The display was withdrawn, but the mayor of London, Ken Livingstone, who had reportedly refused to endorse the logo, also took issue with the $800,000 tab for designing it without a study of its impact.</p>
        <p>''If you employ someone to design a car and it kills you, you're pretty unhappy about that,'' he said. ''If you employ someone to design a logo for you and they haven't done a basic health check, you have to ask what they do for their money.''</p>
        <p>On Web sites, critics registered sharp opposition. ''It resembles a swastika and looks like graffiti -- two things London is not about and should not aspire to,'' said an opponent, Peter Donovan.</p>
        <p>The organizing committee insisted that it would not withdraw the logo. Indeed, Sebastian Coe, the committee chairman, called it ''an invitation to take part and be involved.''</p>
        <p>It was an invitation that British newspapers accepted with glee.</p>
        <p>Most newspapers said Wednesday that their readers had sent in their own versions. The Sun published a display of five alternative designs, one painted by a macaque monkey named Katie. Another was reported as having come from Deborah Jones, 36, who was said to be blind.</p>
        <p>As a columnist, Jane Moore, wrote in The Sun, the Olympic organizers say, ''It'll grow on us.''</p>
        <p>''So does foot fungus,'' she added.</p>
        <p>But might the response have said more about a conservative nation's resistance to newness? Or could the reaction have touched also on a deep-seated and curmudgeonly reluctance to play host to a venture like the Olympics without forecasting its doom well in advance?</p>
        <p>''When something is so swingingly attacked as the 2012 logo has been, it tells you more about the people doing the attacking, and their taste, than about the design in question,'' said Michael Wolff, the co-founder of Wolff Olins, the branding agency that designed the logo. ''Prejudice is comfortable and lazy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolff, who has since formed a separate company, went on to say in The Evening Standard, ''I think this petulant reaction will subside and pride will take its place.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
