<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If Only The Drama of the Single Child</title>
    <meta content="l07child" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E7D71E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="511" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If Only The Drama of the Single Child</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Company for an Only Child, and for Parents, Peace of Mind'' (news article, June 3):</p>
        <p>You write that parents of only children fear the persistent stigma in spite of studies that find that only children turn out fine. In collecting personal stories by only children, we found that for every only child who was ever lonely, there is another who is ambivalent about depriving his multiple children of the joys of being ''the one.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Company for an Only Child, and for Parents, Peace of Mind'' (news article, June 3):</p>
        <p>You write that parents of only children fear the persistent stigma in spite of studies that find that only children turn out fine. In collecting personal stories by only children, we found that for every only child who was ever lonely, there is another who is ambivalent about depriving his multiple children of the joys of being ''the one.''</p>
        <p>For every singleton who wishes she had a sibling, there is a bitter sister who faults her sibling for shirking filial duty. And for every adult only child who finds his aging parents a burden, there is another who feels a pride of ownership in seeing his devoted caretakers through to their end.</p>
        <p>Indeed, sibling status has little to do with determining happiness.</p>
        <p>Daphne Uviller  Deborah Siegel  New York, June 3, 2007</p>
        <p>The writers are the editors of ''Only Child: Writers on the Singular Joys and Solitary Sorrows of Growing Up Solo.''</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>You correctly cite the evidence that only children do just fine. In all my decades as a psychotherapist I never had a client wail, ''Woe is me, I am an only child.'' I did have myriad clients complain about their favored brother, their teasing sister, their bratty younger sib, their spoiled older sib and the unfairness of it all.</p>
        <p>Roberta Temes  Scotch Plains, N.J., June 3, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As an only child, I appreciate your article about support groups for singletons and their parents. But I am a bit surprised by a variable omitted by the ''trend experts'' you mentioned who cited some reasons for the increase in the number of only children.</p>
        <p>While I was growing up in the 1950s, many people in my Brooklyn neighborhood practiced birth control as one way to help them make the transition to the middle class.</p>
        <p>Although my parents were college educated, my father's salary barely covered the necessities, and my mother did not go back to work full time until I was 11. A second child was not an affordable option.</p>
        <p>Day care expenses and college tuition have skyrocketed in recent years. At least in part, many people today may choose to have only one child for financial reasons, as my parents did.</p>
        <p>Amy Laiken  Chicago, June 4, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As an only child now entering my senior years, I read your article with interest. While there was never any group like Mothers of Only Children while I was growing up, as an adult I have never lost the chance to exchange ideas with other only children.</p>
        <p>The best analysis of our plight came from a Belgian friend who told me that a lot of the negative view of only children is due to the fact that in English ''only'' rhymes with ''lonely.'' Ever since, I now agree with her that I am an ''enfant unique.''</p>
        <p>Edward Apuzzo  Sleepy Hollow, N.Y., June 4, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
