<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giuliani and McCain Say They Will Skip August Straw Poll in Iowa</title>
    <meta content="07giuliani" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/us/politics/07giuliani.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852694"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Iowa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Iowa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McCain, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFD91E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="949" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giuliani and McCain Say They Will Skip August Straw Poll in Iowa</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Giuliani and McCain to Skip Straw Poll in Iowa</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC SANTORA; Michael Luo contributed reporting from New York, and Jeff Zeleny from Des Moines.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Santora, Marc; Zeleny, Jeff; Luo, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>NEW CASTLE, N.H., June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bucking a ritual for Republican presidential candidates, Rudolph W. Giuliani and Senator John McCain announced Wednesday that they would skip participation in what has been a significant early test of candidate strength, the straw poll in Ames, Iowa, this summer.</p>
        <p>Their decision was the clearest indication of how much the changing primary calendar is upending presidential politics this year, as candidates grapple with the prospect of huge primaries in crucial states like Florida on Jan. 29 and California, New York and Texas a week later.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The decisions were a clear indication of how much the new primary calendar is upending politics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bucking a ritual for Republican presidential candidates, Rudolph W. Giuliani and Senator John McCain announced Wednesday that they would skip participation in what has been a significant early test of candidate strength, the straw poll in Ames, Iowa, this summer.</p>
        <p>Their decision was the clearest indication of how much the changing primary calendar is upending presidential politics this year, as candidates grapple with the prospect of huge primaries in crucial states like Florida on Jan. 29 and California, New York and Texas a week later.</p>
        <p>Both campaigns said they would still compete in the Iowa caucuses, scheduled for January. But the Giuliani campaign cited the high cost of participating in the poll, which they estimated at $3 million, as the reason for pulling out. Hours later, the McCain campaign followed suit, raising the prospect that the event would lose its import in the road to the nomination.</p>
        <p>''This type of campaign has never been waged before,'' said Michael DuHaime, the Giuliani campaign manager. Mr. DuHaime said the need to spend in states like Florida and California was forcing the campaign to make tough choices about where to allocate resources.</p>
        <p>Terry Nelson, Mr. McCain's campaign manager, said the senator, of Arizona, still intended to compete vigorously in the caucuses.</p>
        <p>Mitt Romney, who lags far behind Mr. Giuliani in national polls but is doing well in polls in Iowa, will still participate in the straw poll, hoping to use a strong showing both there and in the caucus to propel his candidacy in the primaries that follow.</p>
        <p>The Ames straw poll started in 1979, initially conceived as a way to raise money for the caucuses. It has been criticized as a poor test of support because the candidates essentially buy the tickets for the attendees who do the voting. Campaigns are expected to buy thousands of $30 tickets for supporters, provide them transportation and then pamper them during the carnival-like event, which is scheduled to be held on Aug. 11 at Iowa State University.</p>
        <p>George W. Bush used a straw poll victory in 1999 as evidence of his campaign's legitimacy and strength. The poll has also proved important in helping thin out the field, with lesser-known candidates who perform poorly dropping out of the race.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain's decision to bypass the poll took Iowa Republican Party officials by surprise, because he has been competing aggressively in the state. But party officials said they still intended to hold the event and that the developments did not lessen the importance of the Iowa caucuses, which are tentatively scheduled for Jan. 20, but could be held even earlier as other states move up their primaries.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani's announcement irritated some Iowa Republicans, who for nearly three decades have jealously guarded their tradition of opening the nation's race for the White House. But it also underscored the reality that advisers to Mr. Giuliani believe that his best prospects for winning the nomination could rest in appealing to moderate voters in the crush of primaries in California, Florida and New York, which will require costly advertising campaigns.</p>
        <p>The 2008 political calendar has already been far from orderly, although the basic rituals of Iowa, New Hampshire and South Carolina as early testing grounds have remained. But the decision by Mr. Giuliani, who currently leads in many polls, to downscale in Iowa could have wider repercussions.</p>
        <p>His advisers insisted Wednesday that they were in Iowa to win and took great care to explain the decision to bypass the straw poll. First, campaign officials disclosed the news to The Des Moines Register. Then, other Iowa reporters were invited to participate in a conference call with a senior adviser to Mr. Giuliani, former Representative Jim Nussle of Iowa, who ran unsuccessfully for governor last year.</p>
        <p>''The straw poll actually could in fact take away Iowa's significance, if we're not careful,'' Mr. Nussle told reporters. ''It's not a serious event in the grand scheme of picking a nominee. And at this time in our history, with the war on terror and economic challenges facing our country, we need to have a serious conversation about our nominee and not just have, you know, these kind of fund-raising straw polls.''</p>
        <p>While Ames has at times been a good barometer, it has also been notably wrong, like in 1995 when Phil Gramm of Texas invested large sums of money and tied for first there, only to see his campaign fizzle.</p>
        <p>Steffen W. Schmidt, a professor of political science at Iowa State University, said that the importance of the Iowa straw poll appeared to be fading. While the caucuses will remain important to candidates, Mr. Schmidt said, the compressed schedule does not allow the luxury of spending so much money in one place in August.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of a phony event,'' he said. ''It diverts energy and resources from the bigger states. It's a metaphor for the entire way the race is going.''</p>
        <p>The Romney campaign, which has already spent hundreds of thousands of dollars advertising in the state and reaffirmed its decision to take part in the straw poll, was quick to criticize the decisions to pull out.</p>
        <p>Christopher Rants, the Iowa House Republican leader who is an adviser to the Romney campaign, said, ''It sure looks to me that Giuliani is trying to avoid having to compete for conservative votes.''</p>
        <p>The Giuliani campaign, hoping to reassure Iowa voters, announced that it would open its official campaign headquarters in the state on Thursday. Mr. Giuliani, however, will not be there. He is campaigning in Michigan that day, before heading off for events in Washington, D.C.; Missouri; and California.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
