<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge Rejects Main Argument of Effort to Stop Atlantic Yards Project in Brooklyn</title>
    <meta content="07yards" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/nyregion/07yards.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852697"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Forest City Ratner Companies</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EED91E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge Rejects Main Argument of Effort to Stop Atlantic Yards Project in Brooklyn</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Judge Rejects Main Argument of Effort to Stop Atlantic Yards Project in Brooklyn</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS CONFESSORE; Andy Newman contributed reporting.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal judge yesterday dismissed the most significant lawsuit against the Atlantic Yards project near Downtown Brooklyn, dealing a major setback to opponents of the $4 billion project.</p>
        <p>The decision by the judge, Nicholas G. Garaufis of United States District Court in Brooklyn, centered on the looming condemnation of about a dozen businesses and homes to make way for the 22-acre complex, which state officials approved late last year. It was among the most significant eminent domain cases to unfold since the United States Supreme Court's much-disputed Kelo v. City of New London decision in 2005, which held that public officials may transfer condemned property to another private interest if doing so would create a superior benefit to the public.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The decision dealt a major setback to opponents of the $4 billion project.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal judge yesterday dismissed the most significant lawsuit against the Atlantic Yards project near Downtown Brooklyn, dealing a major setback to opponents of the $4 billion project.</p>
        <p>The decision by the judge, Nicholas G. Garaufis of United States District Court in Brooklyn, centered on the looming condemnation of about a dozen businesses and homes to make way for the 22-acre complex, which state officials approved late last year. It was among the most significant eminent domain cases to unfold since the United States Supreme Court's much-disputed Kelo v. City of New London decision in 2005, which held that public officials may transfer condemned property to another private interest if doing so would create a superior benefit to the public.</p>
        <p>The plaintiffs argued that any public benefit of the project was incidental, and the true purpose was to enrich the developer, Forest City Ratner Companies, and its investors.</p>
        <p>The plaintiffs include residents and business owners who have refused to sell their properties to Forest City. They say the project originated with Forest City rather than with city and state officials, and that Forest City planners had selected the properties that needed to be condemned</p>
        <p>But Judge Garaufis rejected their reasoning. ''Plaintiffs have not set forth facts supporting a plausible claim of an unconstitutional taking,'' he wrote. ''Nowhere in the amended complaint or their briefs do plaintiffs sufficiently allege any purpose to confer a private benefit.'' He also said any claim that the condemnations would not benefit the public were ''baseless.''</p>
        <p>Forest City has already begun preparing the property. The plans for the complex include a basketball arena for the New Jersey Nets, more than 6,000 apartments and office space. Supporters of the project say that it will generate thousands of new jobs, hundreds of millions of dollars in new tax revenue and badly needed units of subsidized housing. The project is being overseen by the Empire State Development Corporation, which would exercise eminent domain.</p>
        <p>In a statement, Bruce Ratner, the chief executive of Forest City, said that the decision was ''an important victory not only for Atlantic Yards but for Brooklyn as well.''</p>
        <p>Forest City Ratner Companies is also the development partner for the new Midtown headquarters for The New York Times.</p>
        <p>The plaintiffs said they would appeal the decision. ''We will continue to pursue every single legal option available to the plaintiffs, wherever they lead us, to stop what we believe is a private taking in violation of the U.S. Constitution,'' said Candace Carponter, a lawyer and a member of Develop Don't Destroy Brooklyn, a coalition of groups and individuals opposed to the project.</p>
        <p>A federal magistrate judge had earlier recommended that the eminent domain lawsuit be dismissed from federal court on procedural grounds and moved to state court. But Judge Garaufis said the case was appropriate for federal court.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit is not the only one associated with Atlantic Yards.</p>
        <p>A suit filed in January by a group of tenants living in rent-stabilized apartments on the site claimed that the state's offers to relocate them were inadequate. A separate suit by the same tenants charged that the state had failed to go through the required steps to cancel their leases. A judge ruled last month that the case had been filed in the wrong court, but a lawyer for the tenants said it would be refiled.</p>
        <p>Still another lawsuit, filed in April, challenged the environmental impact statement that the state used in evaluating the project, on the grounds that it did not fully address the traffic and security problems the project would create.</p>
        <p>But the case dismissed yesterday was the most significant, both for the hope opponents had invested in its potential to stop Atlantic Yards -- the arena, for example, could not have been built if the case had succeeded -- and for the weighty constitutional issues it raised.</p>
        <p>Matthew D. Brinckerhoff, a lawyer for the plaintiffs, said Judge Garaufis had erred both in his assessment of the lawsuit's merits and in the test he chose to apply in dismissing the case. At this stage of the lawsuit, before discovery and a trial, he said, the judge should have considered whether the case could succeed if all the plaintiffs' claims were true, rather than decide whether he thought the claims were plausible.</p>
        <p>''Not only is what we believe plausible, but all of the evidence that is undisputed points to our conclusion being correct,'' Mr. Brinckerhoff said. ''And that is why we are appealing, and that is why we will win.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
