<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Above Midtown, A Lilliputian Universe</title>
    <meta content="07garden" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/garden/07garden.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852674"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE GARDEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE6D91E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1108" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Above Midtown, A Lilliputian Universe</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Above Midtown, a Lilliputian Universe</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I'VE never really loved miniature worlds because the real thing always seemed so much more compelling. Why put little teacups around a tiny table, when you can have a tea party with real cake? Why stick moss and ferns in a glass box, when you can go wading in the stream where they grow wild along the banks?</p>
        <p>But the charm of the miniature became obvious to me on an intensely hot day two weeks ago as I stood on a terrace in the middle of New York City. I was flushed with heat and thirsty. But as I scanned the troughs arrayed down the center of the long terrace, the plants, many of them small versions of trees, looked perfectly comfortable. The blinding sun and humidity didn't seem to be hurting the dwarf conifers and miniature crape myrtles, and desert plants, like cacti and succulents, were as happy as the silver saxifrages nestled in the tufa.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alpine plants help make a roof terrace into its own small realm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I'VE never really loved miniature worlds because the real thing always seemed so much more compelling. Why put little teacups around a tiny table, when you can have a tea party with real cake? Why stick moss and ferns in a glass box, when you can go wading in the stream where they grow wild along the banks?</p>
        <p>But the charm of the miniature became obvious to me on an intensely hot day two weeks ago as I stood on a terrace in the middle of New York City. I was flushed with heat and thirsty. But as I scanned the troughs arrayed down the center of the long terrace, the plants, many of them small versions of trees, looked perfectly comfortable. The blinding sun and humidity didn't seem to be hurting the dwarf conifers and miniature crape myrtles, and desert plants, like cacti and succulents, were as happy as the silver saxifrages nestled in the tufa.</p>
        <p>Susan Keiser, who owns her own design company, Greystone Gardens in Ossining, N.Y., designed this diverse landscape for the offices of Rockefeller &amp; Company, a wealth management group, on the third floor of 10 Rockefeller Plaza. Dealing with a beating sun on the south terrace and shade on the north and with protection from the wind by surrounding buildings, Ms. Keiser has built a miniature world -- of desert, mountain and woodland -- all in containers.</p>
        <p>''I've tested thousands of plants here over the years,'' Ms. Keiser said. She chose 700 different kinds of plants that could survive life in a trough and arranged them down the middle of the two very long terraces along the north and south sides of the building. Many of these plants are alpines, meaning they are native to mountainous areas, not necessarily the Alps, but rocky places battered by sun and wind. Many pines, junipers, cedars and spruces are also tolerant of heat if given enough water, which Ms. Keiser supplies painstakingly with a hand-held hose.</p>
        <p>On the sunny south terrace, I stared down at a collection of troughs devoted to evergreens, none of them more than two feet high. Some were soft golden mounds, others blue-green or chartreuse; some crept like serpents along stones arranged in the troughs. And because the troughs are rectangles and squares in five different sizes, and three different heights, a geometric, mathematical rhythm is set up. The precision lends order to all these fluffy, spiky, rambling plants.</p>
        <p>Ms. Keiser has some fun with color here, too: blues and greens and silver-blues are on one side; grassy greens and chartreuse and lemon on the other.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of a reverse image,'' she said, as we looked down, two Gullivers in this Lilliputian world.</p>
        <p>I was transfixed by a monkey puzzle tree, about 18 inches tall, which held its dark green spiky-needled branches high, like outstretched arms, over a weathered rock. I'd seen one before -- a 17-footer in the New York Botanical Garden's conifer collection -- but this one was adorably small, casting miniature shadows over a Raoulia australis, a little alpine plant grown for its silvery foliage, which makes a nice ground cover.</p>
        <p>One of the joys of a trough garden filled with miniature plants is the perspective it provides. It's impossible to see these trees whole, standing on the ground, surrounded by normal-size evergreens. You have to crane your neck up, or face some big spruce broadside. There's no way to get the gestalt of the entire plant, or to see what lies behind it, unless you go around and look.</p>
        <p>And in real life, some big golden Chamaecyparis can seem just too big, too gold.</p>
        <p>''They look like cheap tarts to me,'' Ms. Keiser said. ''Gold mop cypress, blue spruce and red barberry, and the red bark mulch. That's how the cheapest of landscapers pump up color.''</p>
        <p>But somehow, looking down on a gold mop cypress, it doesn't look so garish. You can appreciate its filigreed golden needles, its billowy shape.</p>
        <p>''It's not just one big golden blob,'' she said. ''It's not like you're being attacked by this big gold thing.''</p>
        <p>The raised troughs, which are nine inches deep, appear to be slate, but are actually fiberglass, cast over rock. Ms. Keiser designed them herself, and had them custom-made by Roundbush Castings in Glen Head, N.Y. The ''boulders,'' too, placed here and there in the rock gardens, are fiberglass.</p>
        <p>''These were cast from real rocks,'' she said, hefting a feather-light fake. ''I hand-selected them from piles of rocks, choosing ones that I could fit together in combinations.''</p>
        <p>There are weight restrictions on rooftops and terraces, of course, and fiberglass is a lot lighter than tufa, the limestone rock used in alpine gardens, or the mix of cement, peat and sand that makes up hypertufa, the artificial stone used for troughs.</p>
        <p>''The largest of these planters weighs 250 pounds, and that's with real tufa and soaking wet,'' said Ms. Keiser, who uses some tufa for her choice alpines. ''But once you use fake rocks, it's almost nothing.''</p>
        <p>I was beginning to see the charm of these succinct raised gardens, and I could picture watering a controlled group of them. It would clearly be more satisfying than watching a larger landscape wither in the drought. I imagined myself wielding my pruners over a grove of tiny crape myrtles, rather than struggling to control the giant lilacs and mock oranges that now grow way over my head.</p>
        <p>Rock gardening is a bit like bonsai: plants must be pruned to a miniature scale, and nutrients withheld to discourage growth. Ms. Keiser has pruned crape myrtles, mountain laurel, yews, arborvitae and bulky cypress into multi-trunked trees, cutting off branches, from the bottom up, to reveal the shape of the trunks, the color of the bark.</p>
        <p>This careful pruning makes these plants more sculptural, so that they stand apart yet relate to one another, like works of art in a courtyard.</p>
        <p>Ms. Keiser also plants things at the base of these raised planters -- carpets of thyme beneath the alpine gardens, coppery grasses beneath the conifers -- and uses columnar junipers and barberries to draw the eye up to the surrounding skyscrapers. There may be conduits running along the building and stained tiles beneath your feet, but walking down these gardens is a journey through another world.</p>
        <p>Though this garden is not open to the public, the North American Rock Garden Society (nargs.org), which has a very active Manhattan chapter, is the best source for anyone interested in alpines, dwarf conifers and the art of container gardening.</p>
        <p>Sources for rock garden plants include Arrowhead Alpines in Fowlerville, Mich. (arrowhead-alpines.com) and Oliver Nurseries in Fairfield, Conn. (olivernurseries.com).</p>
        <p>IN THE GARDEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
