<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cuomo Plans to Broaden Student-Lending Inquiry</title>
    <meta content="07loan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/us/07loan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Civil Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Cuomo, Andrew M</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E4D61E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="800" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cuomo Plans to Broaden Student-Lending Inquiry</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cuomo Plans to Broaden Student-Lending Inquiry</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANA JEAN SCHEMO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schemo, Diana Jean</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Attorney General Andrew M. Cuomo of New York, whose scrutiny of student loans has exposed ties between universities and lenders, said Wednesday that he was broadening his inquiry to examine the criteria lenders use when making loans, and whether they violate civil rights statutes.</p>
        <p>Testifying at a Senate Banking Committee hearing on private student loans, which do not carry federal guarantees, Mr. Cuomo said he was examining whether lenders were discriminating against students based on the institutions they attended or other factors not directly related to their credit history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Attorney General Andrew M. Cuomo of New York said that he was broadening his investigation to examine whether the criteria lenders use when making loans violate civil rights statutes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Attorney General Andrew M. Cuomo of New York, whose scrutiny of student loans has exposed ties between universities and lenders, said Wednesday that he was broadening his inquiry to examine the criteria lenders use when making loans, and whether they violate civil rights statutes.</p>
        <p>Testifying at a Senate Banking Committee hearing on private student loans, which do not carry federal guarantees, Mr. Cuomo said he was examining whether lenders were discriminating against students based on the institutions they attended or other factors not directly related to their credit history.</p>
        <p>''What criteria are they using in the underwriting of these loans?'' Mr. Cuomo asked. ''Parental income? Student income? Student creditworthiness? How about the school you attend? How is that weighted?''</p>
        <p>While lenders have the right to consider a borrower's credit record, he said, ''there are also civil rights and legal ramifications to what criteria they use, and that's what we're looking at.''</p>
        <p>He suggested that students at historically black institutions were sometimes charged higher interest rates and fees than other students.</p>
        <p>Senator Christopher J. Dodd, the Connecticut Democrat who is committee chairman and is running for president, likened the practice to redlining, in which banks rule out mortgage loans based not on the credit record of potential homeowners but by whether urban neighborhoods are predominantly black.</p>
        <p>The market in private student loans has soared in recent years, tripling to $17.3 billion in the last five years. Such loans carry variable interest rates, unlike government-backed loans, which have fixed rates.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo, whose student-loan ''code of conduct'' bans secret gifts from lenders to universities became a model for legislation the House passed overwhelmingly last month, called private student loans the Wild West of consumer lending because they are largely unregulated and the level of disclosure pales next to that required of the mortgage industry.</p>
        <p>Regulations that the federal Education Department issued last week on student lending apply only to loans carrying federal guarantees. Mr. Cuomo urged Congress to clean up the private loan industry, but said new legislation was probably not needed. Rather, he said, the federal agencies charged with oversight, the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency, the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation and the Federal Trade Commission, have not used the authority they already have.</p>
        <p>A number of lenders, including Sallie Mae, which holds more private loans than any other company, consider the institution a student is attending in determining the interest rate, fees and other terms of loans they extend to students, said Barry W. Goulding, a Sallie Mae senior vice president who testified.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Goulding justified the practice, saying Sallie Mae considered ''our experience with the borrowers attending that school'' to only ''a nominal extent,'' which could result in interest rates up to one percentage point higher. More important, he said, is the credit history of the borrower and the co-signer, usually the students' parents.</p>
        <p>He said Sallie Mae had looked at the rates it charges students at six historically black colleges and universities: three received the best rates; three received higher rates.</p>
        <p>In setting interest rates, Mr. Goulding said, Sallie Mae also considers the ''competitive landscape,'' how aggressively colleges and universities seek the best deal for their students. Those that put together their preferred-lender lists by soliciting companies for their best terms, he said, typically get up to one percentage point lower interest rates.</p>
        <p>That disclosure suggested that colleges and universities that relied on perks to choose which lenders to recommend had hurt their students.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo testified that 90 percent of all students select their lenders from their college's preferred-lender lists. Asked how common the perks and revenue sharing agreements were, Mr. Cuomo said, ''On the private loan side, it's rampant.''</p>
        <p>Executives from two other major student lenders, First Marblehead Corporation and Bank of America, said they did not weigh an institution's default history in setting loan terms. Rather, they said, they only make loans to a list of about 6,500 institutions, determined by factors like accreditation. The executives said they were providing a valuable service, investing in human capital and giving students with no credit history or collateral a chance to attend college.</p>
        <p>Luke Swarthout, the higher education advocate at the United States Public Interest Research Group, a nonpartisan consumer group, disagreed, saying many lenders did not readily disclose the terms of loans.</p>
        <p>The Associated Press reported that two universities announced Wednesday that financial aid directors had left their posts. Capella University said it had fired its financial aid director, Tim Lehmann, for accepting consulting fees from a student lender, and Widener University of Pennsylvania said its financial aid dean, Walter Cathie, had retired.</p>
        <p>The two had been on administrative leave since Mr. Cuomo accused them in April of accepting improper payments from a lender that they recommended to students.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
