<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Immigration Compromise Divides Republican Senators</title>
    <meta content="07opposition" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/washington/07opposition.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852812"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Sessions, Jefferson B III</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kyl, Jon</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McCain, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bunning, Jim</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Vitter, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Thune, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E1D61E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Immigration Compromise Divides Republican Senators</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Immigration Compromise Divides Republican Senators</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARL HULSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hulse, Carl</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Jeff Sessions, a conservative former federal prosecutor from Alabama, says he is anything but anti-immigration. But he is dead set against what he says is a misguided and flawed immigration proposal he says will not secure the nation's borders while rewarding those who have sneaked across them.</p>
        <p>''I just don't think that all 12 million people, including single people who broke the border last December, need to be put on a guaranteed path to citizenship,'' Mr. Sessions, a Republican, said Wednesday as the Senate neared a pivotal vote on its immigration overhaul.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A small group of Senate Republicans is leading the charge against immigration legislation championed by some of their closest Congressional comrades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator Jeff Sessions, a conservative former federal prosecutor from Alabama, says he is anything but anti-immigration. But he is dead set against what he says is a misguided and flawed immigration proposal he says will not secure the nation's borders while rewarding those who have sneaked across them.</p>
        <p>''I just don't think that all 12 million people, including single people who broke the border last December, need to be put on a guaranteed path to citizenship,'' Mr. Sessions, a Republican, said Wednesday as the Senate neared a pivotal vote on its immigration overhaul.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sessions is part of what might be called the disloyal opposition, a small but determined group of Senate Republicans leading the charge against legislation championed not only by President Bush, but by some of their closest Congressional comrades -- notably Senator Jon Kyl, Republican of Arizona. ''On this deal, I can't be with him,'' Mr. Sessions said ruefully of his partner in past immigration battles.</p>
        <p>The sharp split has created tensions in the usually united Republican ranks and led to occasional harsh words as lawmakers who typically train their fire on Democrats take shots at one another.</p>
        <p>''They either don't know about the bill or understand it, either one,'' said Senator John McCain, the Arizona Republican and presidential contender who has been defending the legislation against what he says are distortions and demagogic attacks.</p>
        <p>Despite such complaints and suggestions that opponents of the bill are motivated by bigotry, Mr. Sessions and Republican colleagues like Jim DeMint of South Carolina, Jim Bunning of Kentucky and David Vitter of Louisiana have dug in against what they describe as a travesty. Others, including Senators John Cornyn of Texas and John Thune of South Dakota, both Republicans, have raised serious objections as well.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sessions, who refers jokingly to the negotiators as the ''masters of the universe,'' distributed a list of what he says are 20 serious loopholes, including the prospect that an illegal immigrant convicted of child sexual abuse could qualify for residency if the crime occurred before the bill becomes law.</p>
        <p>Backers of the measure say they have already moved to restrict eligibility for those who commit serious crimes and that the opponents of the bill are making sensational but unsupported claims to stir up opposition.</p>
        <p>Outgunned on the floor against some of the most skilled legislators of both parties, the opponents have suffered a steady string of defeats in trying to reshape the bill, most recently on Wednesday as the bipartisan coalition behind the measure beat back a series of conservative amendments. Late in the evening, Mr. Sessions finally won a victory with approval of his proposal to limit income tax benefits for illegal immigrants who qualify for residency, and Mr. Cornyn scored a victory as well. But even as they lose most of the bigger fights, the opponents say they are exposing fundamental problems with the measure and building a broader case against it.</p>
        <p>''This outnumbered handful of senators has done amazing work in forcing both the other senators and America to see what is in this bill,'' said Rosemary Jenks, director of government relations for Numbers USA, a group opposed to the bill. ''They take a lot of heat from their colleagues, but they are on the side of the American people.''</p>
        <p>The opponents have tried to highlight what they see as glaring inadequacies in the legislation, working with outside interest groups to point out problems, potential costs in social services and the fact that it was drafted in closed negotiations by the administration working with about a dozen senior lawmakers.</p>
        <p>''There is always the possibility and the likelihood that people will misrepresent what is in the bill and then differ with it,'' said Senator Edward M. Kennedy, Democrat of Massachusetts and one of the legislative veterans shepherding the measure. ''It's an old technique. I have used it even myself.''</p>
        <p>Supporters of the legislation have also accused their foes of being callous in their push to deny residency to illegal immigrants. ''If you want to be the person who keeps families apart, bring this bill down,'' Senator Lindsey Graham, Republican of South Carolina and another of its architects, said Wednesday on the floor.</p>
        <p>Opponents of the measure say that while such criticism, particularly coming from fellow Republicans, can sting, it will not deter them.</p>
        <p>''It is not helpful, and I don't think it reflects where a lot of people are,'' said Mr. Thune, who noted his grandfather came to the United States from Scandinavia. ''We have an appreciation that we are a welcoming country, but coupled with the fact that we are a nation of laws and have to respect those laws.''</p>
        <p>In addition to the Republicans, there are a handful of certain Democratic votes against the immigration bill but lawmakers in both parties say there has been little coordination or effort to mount a bipartisan effort to defeat the measure.</p>
        <p>''I was here in 1986 and heard all the promises about border security and am hearing the same things now,'' said Senator Byron L. Dorgan, Democrat of North Dakota. ''But I am just voting and offering amendments on my own.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sessions is hopeful that a critical mass can be achieved against the measure, particularly on the procedural vote set for Thursday to cut off debate, a move that would require 60 votes to avert a threat by Senator Harry Reid of Nevada, the Democratic leader, to put the measure aside and move on to other issues.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sessions is calling for a national dialogue on the volatile issue. ''I do not oppose immigration,'' he said. ''I just think we ought to create a system that serves our national interest, that allows talented people from around the world to apply and come here, those persons most likely to flourish.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
