<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Is the Yankees' Real First Baseman?</title>
    <meta content="07anderson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/sports/baseball/07anderson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852787"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gehrig, Lou</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mattingly, Don</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Giambi, Jason</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Skowron, Bill</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mientkiewicz, Doug</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mantle, Mickey</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Anderson, Dave</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE7D61E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Is the Yankees' Real First Baseman?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Where Is the Yankees’ Real First Baseman?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While the Yankees hold their breath waiting for Roger Clemens to rescue their rotation, they continue to suffer from the absence of a real Yankee first baseman.</p>
        <p>In winning 26 World Series, the Yankees almost always had a feared power hitter at what is considered a power position. Lou Gehrig was the original real Yankee first baseman, the ideal. Wally Pipp, Nick Etten, George McQuinn, Tommy Henrich, Johnny Mize, Joe Collins, Bill Skowron, Chris Chambliss and Tino Martinez were also real Yankee first basemen, power hitters who earned Series rings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In winning 26 World Series, the Yankees almost always had a feared power hitter at what is considered a power position. But this season there is no real Yankee first baseman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While the Yankees hold their breath waiting for Roger Clemens to rescue their rotation, they continue to suffer from the absence of a real Yankee first baseman.</p>
        <p>In winning 26 World Series, the Yankees almost always had a feared power hitter at what is considered a power position. Lou Gehrig was the original real Yankee first baseman, the ideal. Wally Pipp, Nick Etten, George McQuinn, Tommy Henrich, Johnny Mize, Joe Collins, Bill Skowron, Chris Chambliss and Tino Martinez were also real Yankee first basemen, power hitters who earned Series rings.</p>
        <p>His last two seasons, limping but always a threat, Mickey Mantle was a real Yankee first baseman. Without a Series ring, so were Don Mattingly and Jason Giambi. But this season there is no real Yankee first baseman.</p>
        <p>Remember the slogan ''Real men don't eat quiche''? Well, a real Yankee first baseman doesn't bat eighth or ninth, as Josh Phelps and the injured Doug Mientkiewicz often have; a real Yankee first basemen doesn't bunt for a base hit, as Miguel Cairo did Tuesday night; a real Yankee first baseman doesn't usually platoon; and a real Yankee first baseman isn't learning defensive footwork in midseason, as Johnny Damon is doing with Mattingly as his tutor.</p>
        <p>In the Yankees' 26-31 record that included last night's 5-1 victory over the White Sox, their starting first basemen combined for a decent .278 average, but only 6 homers and only 27 runs batted in. Hardly the numbers of a real Yankee first baseman.</p>
        <p>In 36 starts before breaking his wrist, Mientkiewicz batted .241 with 4 homers and 16 R.B.I.; in Phelps's 17 starts, he had a .316 average but only 1 homer and 9 R.B.I.; in Giambi's 2 early-season starts before injuries limited him to being the designated hitter, then put him on the disabled list, he was 2 for 5 with 1 homer; in Cairo's 2 starts, he was 4 for 8 with 1 R.B.I.</p>
        <p>If Manager Joe Torre has had to juggle four players there, it means he doesn't have one he trusts, much less one real Yankee first baseman. It also means the Yankees will probably pursue the Rangers' Mark Teixeira, who hit 33 homers last year, in a midseason trade or as a free agent.</p>
        <p>This isn't meant to defame Mientkiewicz, Phelps, Cairo and certainly not Damon, who are what they are: Mientkiewicz primarily a flashy fielder with an occasional bat, Phelps a decent batter without much power, Cairo a versatile and valuable utility infielder, Damon a sore-legged center fielder who might have filled the Yankees' crater at first base if he had been transferred there in spring training.</p>
        <p>But not one of them is a real Yankee first baseman.</p>
        <p>Not that any past or future Yankee first baseman is likely to be compared to the legendary Gehrig, the Iron Horse who played in 2,130 consecutive games from 1925 to 1939 after replacing the injured Pipp at first base. Pipp is remembered jokingly and unfairly for losing his job, but he had been the Yankees' established first baseman for a decade, leading the American League in 1916 with 12 homers and 93 R.B.I., and driving in 108 and 114 runs the two seasons before Gehrig arrived.</p>
        <p>After Gehrig contracted the disease that is named for him and ended his career early in the 1939 season, the Yankees went on to win the Series twice with relatively light-hitting successors at first base: Babe Dahlgren (.235, 15 homers, 89 R.B.I.) in 1939 and Johnny Sturm (.239, 3 homers, 36 R.B.I.) in 1941.</p>
        <p>When the Yankees won the 1943 Series during World War II, Etten was at first base after having driving in 107 runs that season. McQuinn, an All-Star with the St. Louis Browns during the war, batted .304 with 13 homers en route to the 1947 Series victory. During the Yankees' record run of five straight Series from 1949 to 1953, the Old Reliable Henrich was the first baseman the first year, and Mize and Collins the next four.</p>
        <p>In Game 7 of the 1956 Series at Ebbets Field, the bases were loaded when, as Skowron recalled, Manager Casey Stengel told him, ''Take two shots to right.'' Swinging early, Skowron lined Roger Craig's first pitch into the left-field stands for a grand slam. On his return to the dugout, Stengel told him, ''That's the way to pull the ball, big fella.'' Skowron was also the first baseman on the 1958, 1961 and 1962 Series champions.</p>
        <p>Chambliss's pennant-winning home run lifted the Yankees into the 1976 Series; the next two years he helped them win it. When Mattingly, Donnie Baseball himself, retired after the 1995 season, Tino Martinez contributed to four Series rings in five years. Giambi hasn't played on a Series winner, but he was a real Yankee first baseman with 41 homers twice and later 32 and 37 until sidelined by injuries.</p>
        <p>Now there is no real Yankee first baseman. And until one arrives, there probably won't be any Yankee World Series rings.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
