<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Stumble As Outfield Absorbs Another Hit</title>
    <meta content="07mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/sports/baseball/07mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852822"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Philadelphia Phillies</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Chavez, Endy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Alou, Moises</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EFD61E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1037" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Stumble As Outfield Absorbs Another Hit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mets Stumble as Outfield Absorbs Another Hit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets' night got off on the wrong foot, so to speak, when Damion Easley took himself out of the lineup with an injured right knee. David Newhan, like Easley a natural second baseman, replaced him in left field, and if he had not been available, General Manager Omar Minaya and his staff may have started combing the streets of Flushing for anyone with outfield experience.</p>
        <p>With every day that passes, the Mets miss Moises Alou and Shawn Green more and more. And now they may be facing life without their spark plug outfielder, Endy Chávez, who injured his left hamstring while trying to beat out a ground ball in the seventh inning of the Mets' 4-2 loss to the Philadelphia Phillies last night at Shea Stadium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Endy Chávez injured his left hamstring while trying to beat out a ground ball in the seventh inning of the Mets’ loss to the Philadelphia Phillies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Mets' night got off on the wrong foot, so to speak, when Damion Easley took himself out of the lineup with an injured right knee. David Newhan, like Easley a natural second baseman, replaced him in left field, and if he had not been available, General Manager Omar Minaya and his staff may have started combing the streets of Flushing for anyone with outfield experience.</p>
        <p>With every day that passes, the Mets miss Moises Alou and Shawn Green more and more. And now they may be facing life without their spark plug outfielder, Endy Chávez, who injured his left hamstring while trying to beat out a ground ball in the seventh inning of the Mets' 4-2 loss to the Philadelphia Phillies last night at Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>For the first time all season, the Mets have lost three consecutive games, but the sting of this defeat will most likely evaporate by morning. The loss of Chávez may haunt them as long as their outfield remains banged up.</p>
        <p>Chávez will have a magnetic resonance imaging exam today, and if the results are as discouraging as Chávez looked afterward, the Mets will put him on the disabled list. They will probably replace him with second baseman José Valentín, who is scheduled to rejoin the team today after missing the past six weeks with a partly torn knee ligament.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't look too good,'' Manager Willie Randolph said of Chávez's injury.</p>
        <p>Nor, for that matter, do the Mets, who have not played with their opening-day lineup since April 28, largely because of injuries to Alou, Green and Valentín. In losing five of their past seven games, the Mets have scored 17 runs. They had six hits last night and went 0 for 8 with runners in scoring position, culminating with the at-bat that led to Chávez's injury.</p>
        <p>After Jimmy Rollins hit a three-run homer against Aaron Heilman with two outs in the seventh to put the Phillies ahead, 3-2, the Mets put pressure on reliever Geoff Geary in the bottom of the inning. Rubén Gotay hit a chopper off the plate that Geary flubbed, and Newhan fouled off two bunt attempts before doubling down the left-field line. Pinch-hitter Julio Franco ripped a grounder toward first base that Ryan Howard dived to stop. Somewhat inexplicably, Gotay did not charge home as Howard got the out.</p>
        <p>''I just didn't have a good read on it,'' Gotay said.</p>
        <p>José Reyes was then walked intentionally to set up a potential double play. On a 3-2 pitch, Chávez grounded sharply into the double play the Phillies were hoping for, but a few steps before first base, he pulled up lame, clutching the back of his left leg before falling to the grass.</p>
        <p>Chávez could not put any weight on his left leg and had to be helped off the field by the head trainer Ray Ramirez and the assistant trainer Mike Herbst. Afterward, Chávez had trouble sitting down, and he limped slowly out of the clubhouse.</p>
        <p>''I was a little surprised and scared about it because I had no idea how it's going to be,'' Chávez said. ''It hurts when I move.''</p>
        <p>In place of the Mets' injured outfielders, Chávez has filled in nicely, but Carlos Gómez and Ben Johnson, in their brief time with the team, have offered only an occasional spark. With Lastings Milledge, Alou's insurance policy, out for the past six weeks with sprained ligaments in his foot, the Mets' options at Class AAA New Orleans consist of Ricky Ledee and Chip Ambres.</p>
        <p>No surprise, but the Mets are counting the days until Green and Alou can return, and one is much, much closer than the other. Green, sidelined since May 26 with a broken right foot, was cleared by a doctor yesterday to start jogging, and he said he expected to be activated for Sunday's series finale in Detroit. Alou, however, is running out of patience with his ailing left quadriceps. He even tried rubbing the muscle with an ointment that he gives to his horses. It did not work. His chances of playing this weekend are remote.</p>
        <p>''It's just the way it is,'' Randolph said. ''We just have to keep picking each other up.''</p>
        <p>Before they keep doing it, the Mets would settle to do it just once. The time-tested tonic for an offense struggling to score runs is a pitcher who does not give up any. In tossing six scoreless innings last night, Orlando Hernández has allowed only two runs in his three starts since coming off the disabled list May 25.</p>
        <p>For the third consecutive game, Hernández allowed a single to the first hitter of the game. And for the third consecutive game, Hernández allowed little else afterward. Just two more soft singles and four walks, and those were mitigated by the Mets' turning two double plays.</p>
        <p>They led through six, 2-0, on Carlos Beltrán's fourth-inning homer and Delgado's sixth-inning run-scoring groundout off Adam Eaton, until Hernández said he had grown tired after throwing 99 pitches.</p>
        <p>Heilman came in for the seventh and quickly gave up the lead. The first two runners reached, but with two outs, Rollins turned on a hanging 1-2 changeup and sent a fly ball that kept carrying until it dropped over the right-field fence.</p>
        <p>''It's very tough,'' said Heilman, who allowed his fourth homer of the season. He allowed five last year.</p>
        <p>Not as much, perhaps, as losing yet another outfielder, this time the versatile, do-everything Chávez.</p>
        <p>''I joke with the guys all the time that I don't have a hamstring,'' said Chávez, who said he had never had a hamstring injury. ''Now I know I do.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Scott Schoeneweis has pitched the entire season with a severed tendon behind his left knee, near the hamstring, which, he said reluctantly, has weakened his push-off leg. Schoeneweis was loath to offer the injury as an excuse for his 6.00 earned run average and 18 walks in 21 innings.  The Tigers scratched Nate Robertson (tired arm) from Sunday's start and have replaced him with Andrew Miller, the No. 6 pick from last year's draft, who will make his second major league start. He is scheduled to face Tom Glavine.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
