<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Shutter Clicks to a Corner's Parade of Poets and Punks</title>
    <meta content="07street" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/nyregion/07street.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852793"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="EAST VILLAGE JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sociology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sociology</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">East Village (NYC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E4D61E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Shutter Clicks to a Corner's Parade of Poets and Punks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On a Corner, a Shutter Clicks as Poets and Punks Pass in Review</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COLIN MOYNIHAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was getting close to midnight when a man who goes by the name Swami taped a hand-lettered placard reading ''Pearls Before Swine'' to a phone booth on the west side of Avenue A in Lower Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Near the stroke of 12, he began reading his poetry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Tompkins Square Park is the living room of the East Village, then the crossroads of East Seventh Street and Avenue A is its front stoop.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was getting close to midnight when a man who goes by the name Swami taped a hand-lettered placard reading ''Pearls Before Swine'' to a phone booth on the west side of Avenue A in Lower Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Near the stroke of 12, he began reading his poetry.</p>
        <p>Without a proper lectern, he improvised, resting his elbows on the seat of a bicycle locked to a parking meter near East Seventh Street as he declaimed verses dedicated to F. Scott Fitzgerald and Zelda Sayre. After a couple of poems, the owner of the bike indicated his desire to depart.</p>
        <p>But Swami was not quite done, so he continued leaning on the seat as he read:</p>
        <p>Can you dig yourself, across the street?  Do you dig the people that you meet?  And is goodness just another pill  We swallow with the bitter swill?</p>
        <p>Eventually, Swami surrendered his spot and the bicyclist rode off. The poet then refreshed himself with a bottle of Corona, but the taste of the beer turned sour when a police officer handed him an $80 ticket for drinking in public.</p>
        <p>This is the East Village on the first Saturday night of June: street preachers, pensioners, summer punks and poets. Nighttime tipplers congregate. Adventurers from surrounding suburbs rush by in groups, and park bench veterans hobble slowly past.</p>
        <p>If Tompkins Square Park is the living room of the East Village, then the crossroads of East Seventh Street and Avenue A is its front stoop, where neighbors gather to gossip, debate and watch the nightly sidewalk parade.</p>
        <p>''A lot of what I do here is what you'd call social science,'' said Bob Arihood, a photographer who spends many nights on the corner. ''I observe and watch.''</p>
        <p>If it happened on or near Avenue A within the past 12 or 13 years, chances are that he saw it through his camera lens. A year ago, Mr. Arihood began a neighborhood blog(neithermorenorless.blogspot.com) with pictures and commentary.</p>
        <p>Over the last several months he has posted photographs of a red-tailed hawk that lives in Tompkins Square and documented the demise of the Cave Inn, a crumbling building on St. Marks Place, where longtime East Village dwellers like Biker Bill and Jim Power, also known as Mosaic Man, squatted before they were kicked out last spring.</p>
        <p>But much of Mr. Arihood's work illustrates the lives of people who frequent the stretch of sidewalk in front of Ray's Candy Store, on Avenue A just north of East Seventh Street. And few of those figures go by the names that were issued on their birth certificates.</p>
        <p>There's L. E. S. Jewels, who wears a pirate's eye patch and carries a striped cane, and there's Outlaw, who has been known to leave messages scrawled with a marker inside a phone booth on the corner for his girlfriend, Spike.</p>
        <p>There's also Loan Shark Bob, a money lender who used to sell shots of liquor for a dollar and whose collection of bicycles, chained to a pole, were set on fire one night a few years back, possibly by a disgruntled debtor.</p>
        <p>''This is a locus where so many paths cross,'' Mr. Arihood said of the corner. ''You get the opportunity to step into people's lives and explore.''</p>
        <p>It was getting close to last call, in the wee hours, and the bar drinkers began asking the sidewalk drinkers where to catch a cab or how to find the F train.</p>
        <p>Biker Bill stopped by the corner for a while. So did Chris Flash, who runs a messenger service and an underground newspaper called The Shadow.</p>
        <p>Swami prepared to read another poem by announcing, ''You have to have a high I.Q. to understand what this one is all about.''</p>
        <p>A man known as Rock 'n' Roll tap-danced in front of a restaurant, and passers-by gave him tips. Another character who is called Santa Claus, because of his generous white beard, crossed over from Tompkins Square and arranged himself comfortably on the sidewalk in front of the Odessa Bar. Mr. Arihood clicked the shutter of his Leica camera.</p>
        <p>Firecrackers echoed from the darkness beyond the memorial mural to the prince of political punk, Joe Strummer, across the avenue, where a motto next to his image reads, ''The future is unwritten.''</p>
        <p>An air-conditioner in a tenement window started with a guttural stutter, and droplets fell onto a steamy sidewalk. Spare-change seekers mingled with big spenders.</p>
        <p>As the night grew longer, the conversation on the corner turned toward the metaphysical. The crowd discussed how people can become alienated when a society is based on greed. Swami cited Bertolt Brecht, then asked a man in a double-parked black sedan to turn up a song on the radio.</p>
        <p>''I cheated myself, like I knew I would. I told ya, I was troubled, you know that I'm no good,'' Amy Winehouse sang.</p>
        <p>Swami closed his eyes, grinned, then started dancing as a man and a woman walked by holding hands.</p>
        <p>EAST VILLAGE JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
