<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pro Scouts Go Diamond Mining At Los Angeles-Area Powerhouse</title>
    <meta content="07draft" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/sports/baseball/07draft.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852821"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Major League Baseball</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EFD61E30F934A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pro Scouts Go Diamond Mining At Los Angeles-Area Powerhouse</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pro Scouts Go Diamond Mining at Los Angeles-Area Powerhouse</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEE JENKINS</byline>
      <dateline>CHATSWORTH, Calif., June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Chatsworth High School baseball team walked single file through the campus quad Wednesday, one future millionaire after another.</p>
        <p>The first future millionaire, Mike Moustakas, chatted with the second, Matt Dominguez. Then they asked their head coach for one more favor before graduation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If all goes as projected, Mike Moustakas and Matt Dominguez will both be drafted in the first round Thursday, making Chatsworth High School the official capital of prep baseball.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Chatsworth High School baseball team walked single file through the campus quad Wednesday, one future millionaire after another.</p>
        <p>The first future millionaire, Mike Moustakas, chatted with the second, Matt Dominguez. Then they asked their head coach for one more favor before graduation.</p>
        <p>''How about throwing us a little batting practice today?'' Moustakas said.</p>
        <p>''How about tomorrow?'' replied the head coach, Tom Meusborn.</p>
        <p>Moustakas bowed his head. Dominguez looked off in the distance. ''I don't think we can do it tomorrow,'' Moustakas said.</p>
        <p>They have a previous commitment, and Meusborn knows it.</p>
        <p>Since Major League Baseball established its amateur draft in 1965, only six high schools have produced two first-round picks in the same year. If all goes as projected, Moustakas and Dominguez will both be drafted in the first round Thursday, and Chatsworth will become the official capital of prep baseball.</p>
        <p>''I just hope we don't pull a Brady Quinn,'' said Moustakas, referring to the Cleveland Browns' quarterback who tumbled down the N.F.L. draft board this year.</p>
        <p>Even before Chatsworth started drawing 30 major league scouts to every game, it was not your typical high school baseball program. The Chancellors have five different uniforms, a 72-page media guide and a clubhouse inside a trailer. The field has stadium seating, surround-sound speakers and a concession stand that sells steak sandwiches.</p>
        <p>''We want everything to be the best,'' Meusborn said.</p>
        <p>When Moustakas and Dominguez came to Chatsworth, the team was ranked No. 1 in the nation, in the middle of a 54-game winning streak. Moustakas wrote his first English paper about all the reasons he thought he would start right away.</p>
        <p>His teacher was not impressed.</p>
        <p>''I thought he had no chance,'' said Mike Immken, the English teacher who is also the school's athletic director. ''No one starts here right away.''</p>
        <p>But Moustakas and Dominguez were unique. As freshmen, Moustakas started at shortstop, Dominguez started at third base, and they helped Chatsworth to a 35-0 record. Hitting cleanup, Dominguez batted .461, overshadowing everyone else in the lineup.</p>
        <p>Moustakas eventually caught up to Dominguez, and maybe even surpassed him. Moustakas set the California record this spring for home runs in a season (24) and in a career (52). He can also throw a 97-mile-an-hour fastball.</p>
        <p>Moustakas and Dominguez spent Wednesday afternoon in a health careers class, even though their careers are already determined. Moustakas will likely go in the top 10 picks Thursday, Dominguez in the top 20. Just in case anyone questions Chatsworth's depth, outfielder Bobby Coyle may also be picked in the first five rounds.</p>
        <p>''It's weird to think that everyone else at school is going to college or junior college,'' Dominguez said. ''And we're going to the middle of nowhere to play ball.''</p>
        <p>During lunch break Wednesday, Chatsworth players were honored on the quad for their latest city championship, won Saturday at Dodger Stadium. Some of the students around the quad paid attention to the ceremony. Most of them did not.</p>
        <p>Unlikely many high school stars, Moustakas and Dominguez are rarely approached for autographs or asked about the draft. They acknowledge that the baseball team gets perks, but players raise most of the money, selling Christmas trees every year.</p>
        <p>''We're just like regular kids,'' Moustakas said. ''I think people here are used to having good baseball players around.''</p>
        <p>Moustakas and Dominguez are certainly used to it. Dominguez's older brother, Jason, is the closer at Pepperdine. And Moustakas's uncle Tom Robson used to be the hitting coach for the Mets.</p>
        <p>Whenever Robson swung through Los Angeles for games against the Dodgers, Moustakas would work as the Mets' batboy. He became such a good-luck charm for the team that Bobby Valentine, the former manager, once took Moustakas along to San Diego.</p>
        <p>Moustakas and Dominguez are best friends and former Little League teammates, but their personalities are much different. Moustakas is casual and outgoing, wearing his wraparound sunglasses and flip-flops. Dominguez blends into the background.</p>
        <p>Jeff Davis, the Chatsworth principal, said neither player had ever been in trouble, but he called both of them into his office this spring. He wanted them to read a note that was sent to him by Freddy Sánchez, the National League batting champion.</p>
        <p>Sánchez, an infielder for the Pittsburgh Pirates, played for Davis at Burbank High School and expressed his gratitude for everything he learned.</p>
        <p>''I think Matt and Mike both got something out of it,'' Davis said. ''They saw that Freddy did not forget where he came from. They saw that he cared.''</p>
        <p>Since Meusborn became the head coach at Chatsworth 18 years ago, the team has been to the city championship game 11 times, won 6 city titles and finished with the No. 1 national ranking twice. Next week, the Chancellors will be honored at Los Angeles City Hall. But there is one accomplishment that keeps eluding him.</p>
        <p>''I have never had a player make the major leagues,'' Meusborn said. ''That's what I really want right now.''</p>
        <p>Four Chatsworth alums are currently in the minor leagues. Three players will be drafted Thursday. Next year, the team will have two top prospects, first baseman James Wharton and catcher Carlos Escobar Jr.</p>
        <p>Meusborn should not have to wait much longer.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
