<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Contemporary Solar Systems, With Some Classical Moons</title>
    <meta content="13pier" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/arts/music/13pier.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854132"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">St Paul Chamber Orchestra</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Aimard, Pierre-Laurent</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Colman, Ronald</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Stefanovich, Tamara</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E6D7173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="598" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Contemporary Solar Systems, With Some Classical Moons</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Contemporary Solar Systems, With Some Classical Moons</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD HOLLAND</byline>
      <dateline>OJAI, Calif., June 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Ojai Valley, an hour and a half north of Los Angeles, was filmdom's original Shangri-La: a fictional Himalayan pocket of natural luxury imagined by the writer James Hilton and made palpable for the screen by Hollywood cameras brought here on location. With the 1937 movie ''Lost Horizon,'' Shangri-La entered the vocabulary, evoking welcome, secrecy and unexpected beauty.</p>
        <p>I suspect that musicians invited to the Ojai Music Festival each June share with Ronald Colman and friends that same delighted disbelief, not so much at the place -- soft hills, cooling breeze and towering eucalyptus notwithstanding -- but for the audience that comes to hear them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mozart happens at the Ojai Music Festival, but as accent color.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Ojai Valley, an hour and a half north of Los Angeles, was filmdom's original Shangri-La: a fictional Himalayan pocket of natural luxury imagined by the writer James Hilton and made palpable for the screen by Hollywood cameras brought here on location. With the 1937 movie ''Lost Horizon,'' Shangri-La entered the vocabulary, evoking welcome, secrecy and unexpected beauty.</p>
        <p>I suspect that musicians invited to the Ojai Music Festival each June share with Ronald Colman and friends that same delighted disbelief, not so much at the place -- soft hills, cooling breeze and towering eucalyptus notwithstanding -- but for the audience that comes to hear them.</p>
        <p>No arm's-length tolerance of new music here. Upscale locals, Los Angeles intelligentsia and out-of-towners crowd Libbey Bowl's near-primitive outdoor facilities for four days and devour music normal audiences might greet with bewilderment.</p>
        <p>Mozart happens at Ojai too, but as accent color. This year's event, last Thursday through Sunday, was planned by Pierre-Laurent Aimard, a French pianist of eclectic curiosity who likes to trace the line of music history from Bach to Elliott Carter. But there is another argument: that one history of music ended around 1910, and a new one started.</p>
        <p>Bartok and Stravinsky, not Beethoven, then become the new standard repertory, and current composers like Peter Eotvos, this year's special guest here, feed from the bosoms of Varèse or Messiaen, not Haydn. My experience is that most music written after 1920 sounds best in its own company and not as the ''effect'' end of historical cause and effect.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, to the appreciative comments of a nearby crow, Mr. Aimard played Schumann's late and little-heard ''Gesänge der Frühe,'' and on Sunday evening he offered a Mozart concerto. Both were lovely, yet a solar system away from Ives's ''Concord'' Sonata.</p>
        <p>Only Bach proved interplanetary; excerpts from the ''Art of Fugue'' and Mr. Carter's ''Intermittences'' and ''Caténaires'' shared a stony sound world, the first awesomely put together (and played), the second willfully virtuosic.</p>
        <p>Between an old history and a new one was Mahler's ''Lied von der Erde,'' done by the St. Paul Chamber Orchestra in Schoenberg's cut-down arrangement. Mahler is the author of languid, lingering 20-minute codas that touch the heart but hate to say goodbye. The two healthy sounding voices were those of Monica Groop and Sean Panikkar. Douglas Boyd conducted to good effect.</p>
        <p>You can enjoy Mr. Eotvos's music without trusting it. His three-movement ''Chinese Opera,'' brightly done on Saturday night by the St. Paul players, is a construction of many moving parts and brilliant sound effects. Yet you feel at the gun-end of a sales pitch. Innovation has been left to fill the holes that lack of wholeness and substance creates.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eotvos had stiff competition all week, and on Sunday the Ligeti Piano Concerto added to it, with the ever active Mr. Aimard and Mr. Boyd's St. Paul players. Ligeti embraces shrillness, abrasion and loose-limbed syncopation, and creates a paradox of complex movement so transparent that the ear sees through it.</p>
        <p>Later Mr. Carter's ''Dialogues for Piano and Large Ensemble,'' with the intrepid Tamara Stefanovich, reinvented the Romantic concerto in the composer's stern, somber terms.</p>
        <p>After Ravel's G major Concerto, everyone went home. Mr. Aimard, who works harder than is good for him, might think about a rest. Libbey Bowl's live oaks and sycamores will now have only themselves to listen to, or maybe our crow, who returned on Sunday and regularly entered on the music's second beat. Next week Ojai has its lavender festival. Life may be short and art long, but nature wins out in the end.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
