<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lamb With a Pesto that Packs a Wallop</title>
    <meta content="13pair" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854106"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PAIRINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E4D8173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="592" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lamb With a Pesto that Packs a Wallop</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AUSTRIAN red wines are not the stuff of everyday drinking. That's mainly because they are not front and center in wine shops and on wine lists. But they should be.</p>
        <p>The wines in our tasting were generously food-friendly and also, at typically $20 a bottle or less, mostly wallet-friendly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AUSTRIAN red wines are not the stuff of everyday drinking. That's mainly because they are not front and center in wine shops and on wine lists. But they should be.</p>
        <p>The wines in our tasting were generously food-friendly and also, at typically $20 a bottle or less, mostly wallet-friendly.</p>
        <p>They offered aromas and tastes of mint, pepper, earth and, especially in the blaufränkisch group, rich suggestions of sour cherries.</p>
        <p>They could provide harmonious drinking with plates of charcuterie, sautéed mushrooms, substantial fish like tuna and salmon, gamey birds like quail, and the gamut of meat preparations, from veal stews to steak.</p>
        <p>Glancing at the map, I saw that a goulash or Wiener schnitzel were obvious choices, as would be specialties of northeastern Italy, the Alto Adige, which nudges the Tyrol and where all manner of dishes are flavored with speck, a kind of smoked ham, and horseradish.</p>
        <p>I came up with a lamb dish done schnitzel-style. Coating thin slices of lamb in successive layers of seasoned flour, egg and bread crumbs was the easy part. The challenge was to cook the lamb medium to medium rare, a concern that is not an issue when schnitzel is made with veal.</p>
        <p>So I asked my butcher to pound the slices of top round of lamb, from the leg, only lightly, resulting in pieces that were about a half-inch thick, to provide enough tolerance so the meat could brown without overcooking. Refrigerating the coated slices before frying them helps, too.</p>
        <p>To pick up some of the herbal and pepper flavors in the wine, I devised a pesto sauce, made with mint leaves and zapped with horseradish, to accompany the schnitzel.</p>
        <p>A dollop of sour cream enhanced its Austrian accent. Warm potato salad in a vinaigrette dressing with dicings of speck was a felicitous choice alongside.</p>
        <p>Lamb Schnitzels with Mint-Horseradish Pesto  Time: 40 minutes</p>
        <p>1/2 cup flour  Salt and ground black pepper  1/4 cup freshly grated horseradish  1 large egg  3/4 cup dry bread crumbs  1 1/2 pounds top round of lamb, in four pieces lightly pounded to 1/2 -inch thick  1/2 cup (packed) fresh mint leaves  1/3 cup extra virgin olive oil  2 lemons  2 tablespoons sour cream  2/3 to 1 cup vegetable oil, preferably grape seed.</p>
        <p>1. Spread flour on a dinner plate and season with salt, pepper and 2 teaspoons horseradish. In a shallow bowl, beat egg with 1 tablespoon water. Spread bread crumbs onto a dinner plate. Dip lamb pieces first in flour, shaking off excess, then in egg, then in crumbs. Place on a platter. Refrigerate.  2. Place mint leaves and remaining horseradish in food processor and process until mint is minced. Slowly drizzle in olive oil through feed tube. Transfer to a serving bowl, stir in juice of 1 lemon and sour cream, season with salt and pepper and set aside.  3. Heat vegetable oil to a depth of about 1/2 inch in a 12-inch skillet to very hot. Add 2 slices of lamb and cook over medium-high heat until browned, turning once, about 2 minutes a side. Try to keep oil and lamb moving in pan by gently sliding pan on burner in a circular motion. When done, place lamb on several thicknesses of paper towel to drain. Repeat with remaining lamb. Lamb will be medium-rare. If you want it more well done, reduce heat to medium so it takes longer to cook.  4. Transfer to a platter, and serve, with sauce and remaining lemon in wedges.  Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>PAIRINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
