<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Earnhardt Will Announce His Decision and May Join Nemesis</title>
    <meta content="13nascar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/sports/othersports/13nascar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854258"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Earnhardt, Dale Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hendrick, Rick</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bernstein, Viv</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E3DE143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Earnhardt Will Announce His Decision and May Join Nemesis</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Earnhardt Will Announce His Decision and May Join Nemesis</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIV BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Viv</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dale Earnhardt Jr., the most popular driver in Nascar, will announce this morning what team he will race for beginning in 2008 amid indications that he will sign with the powerhouse Hendrick Motorsports.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Earnhardt confirmed that a news conference had been scheduled to name Earnhardt's new Nextel Cup home. Jesse Essex, a spokesman for Hendrick, said in an e-mail message that his team had no comment regarding Earnhardt. A person involved in Nascar racing, who spoke on condition of anonymity because no official announcement had been made, said Earnhardt would sign with Hendrick.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dale Earnhardt Jr., the most popular driver in Nascar, will announce Wednesday morning what team he will race for beginning in 2008.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dale Earnhardt Jr., the most popular driver in Nascar, will announce this morning what team he will race for beginning in 2008 amid indications that he will sign with the powerhouse Hendrick Motorsports.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Earnhardt confirmed that a news conference had been scheduled to name Earnhardt's new Nextel Cup home. Jesse Essex, a spokesman for Hendrick, said in an e-mail message that his team had no comment regarding Earnhardt. A person involved in Nascar racing, who spoke on condition of anonymity because no official announcement had been made, said Earnhardt would sign with Hendrick.</p>
        <p>Earnhardt, 32, announced on May 10 that he would leave Dale Earnhardt Inc., the team built by his father and the only team for which he has raced in Cup competition. He said he wanted to drive for a team that would afford him a better chance to compete for championships. Earnhardt, who has not won a race in more than a year in his red No. 8 Chevrolet, also said he strongly preferred to remain with the same manufacturer.</p>
        <p>After that news conference, Earnhardt's sister and chief negotiator, Kelley Earnhardt Elledge, mentioned Hendrick, Joe Gibbs Racing, Richard Childress Racing and Ginn Racing among the possible destinations. All four teams are affiliated with Chevrolet.</p>
        <p>But spokesmen for Joe Gibbs Racing and Ginn Racing said in phone interviews yesterday that their teams were not involved in the announcement. A person with knowledge of Richard Childress Racing who was not authorized to speak for the organization said Earnhardt was not expected to sign there, either. In fact, Childress, who won six Cup championships with Earnhardt Jr.'s father, has been traveling in New Zealand with his family this week.</p>
        <p>Hendrick Motorsports is the dominant team in the series. Hendrick drivers have 10 Nextel Cup victories in 14 races so far, including 4 by Jeff Gordon and 4 more by Jimmie Johnson.</p>
        <p>The owner Rick Hendrick told The Associated Press in May that his team was not in a position to sign Earnhardt. Hendrick Motorsports has four drivers under contract: Gordon, Johnson, Kyle Busch and Casey Mears. Nascar limits Nextel Cup teams to four drivers.</p>
        <p>But Hendrick could buy out a driver's contract and replace him. Beyond Gordon and Johnson, who have won championships for Hendrick and are signed to long-term deals, the only possibilities are Busch and Mears. Each has won one race this season. Mears was signed to a multiyear deal beginning in 2007 and is close friends with Johnson. Busch, 22, is considered one of the best young talents in the sport, but has been a source of consternation at times in his two-plus seasons racing the No. 5 Chevrolet. His contract expires in 2008.</p>
        <p>Elledge, who did not respond to phone or e-mail queries yesterday, said last month that she and her brother would consider many factors in seeking the right fit. Among the concerns she raised in an interview after the May 10 press conference was fan reaction to a move by Earnhardt to Hendrick Motorsports. Joining Hendrick would make him a teammate of Gordon, who has been viewed as the archenemy among the Earnhardt faithful.</p>
        <p>''If you choose to go to Hendrick, they're kicking everybody's butt right now and there's a lot of people that don't like that,'' Elledge said in May. ''But if given the opportunity for Dale to kick everybody's butt, would they?''</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
