<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bad Month Gets Worse For Maine and the Mets</title>
    <meta content="13mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/sports/baseball/13mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854259"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Los Angeles Dodgers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Maine, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Randolph, Willie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E3DE143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bad Month Gets Worse For Maine and the Mets</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bad Month Gets Worse for Maine and the Mets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, June 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Willie Randolph won two World Series rings by age 24, played for demanding managers like Billy Martin and Lou Piniella, and was hired after 12 failed managerial interviews. He says he has seen it all, done it all, in his 35 seasons in professional baseball, and that includes enduring slumps like the one the Mets are in right now.</p>
        <p>This is not their first tailspin during Randolph's three seasons as manager, but it has come at a most inopportune time. Their 4-1 loss against the Dodgers on Tuesday night was their eight in nine games and dropped them to 36-27, the first time the Mets have been fewer than 10 games over .500 in a month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Starter John Maine had the indignity of allowing home runs on three consecutive pitches, to the Dodgers’ Nos. 7-8-9 hitters, in the second inning, and the Mets never recovered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Willie Randolph won two World Series rings by age 24, played for demanding managers like Billy Martin and Lou Piniella, and was hired after 12 failed managerial interviews. He says he has seen it all, done it all, in his 35 seasons in professional baseball, and that includes enduring slumps like the one the Mets are in right now.</p>
        <p>This is not their first tailspin during Randolph's three seasons as manager, but it has come at a most inopportune time. Their 4-1 loss against the Dodgers on Tuesday night was their eight in nine games and dropped them to 36-27, the first time the Mets have been fewer than 10 games over .500 in a month.</p>
        <p>John Maine (6-4) had the indignity of allowing home runs on three consecutive pitches, to the Dodgers' Nos. 7-8-9 hitters, in the second inning, and the Mets never recovered. They managed one run and five hits in seven innings against the left-hander Hong-Chih Kuo, whose mammoth homer off Maine capped the Dodgers' rare feat. It was the first time the Mets had allowed three consecutive home runs since Pete Harnisch gave up three to San Diego on April 1, 1997.</p>
        <p>Even if losing 9 of 11 this month makes Mets fans antsy, especially with the team's schedule growing more daunting every day and the Braves (two games back) and Phillies (three) closing in, it is just baseball to Randolph.</p>
        <p>''It's what I know about winning baseball and the season, its ebbs and flows,'' he said.</p>
        <p>His composure does not reduce the sting of losing. The Mets are assured of dropping their fourth consecutive series and need Jorge Sosa, who has won their only two games this month, to outduel the Dodgers ace Brad Penny on Wednesday night to avoid the sweep.</p>
        <p>When the Mets took a 1-0 lead in the second inning Tuesday, scoring first for the fifth consecutive game, the omens were plentiful.</p>
        <p>David Wright's leadoff single, the 500th hit of his career, extended his hitting streak to 14 games, and he promptly stole second, his 14th stolen base in 14 attempts. The next batter, Carlos Delgado, drove him home with a single, snapping his 0-for-17 slide with runners in scoring position, to give Maine a run to play with.</p>
        <p>That lead lasted, oh, about three minutes. With one out, Wilson Betemit crushed an 0-1 pitch into the seats in left-center to tie the score at 1-1. The next batter, Matt Kemp, had barely been introduced when he hit the first pitch 447 feet down the left-field line, becoming the first player to reach the loge level here since July 2005.</p>
        <p>With Kuo, who had one career hit, up next, there was no way the Dodgers would hit three in a row, right? Not so fast. Maine threw a first-pitch fastball that Kuo clobbered into the right-center-field stands. The moment Kuo made contact, he knew. He tossed the bat to the grass with the nonchalance of a slugger and broke into a trot around the bases.</p>
        <p>The Dodgers had hit four consecutive home runs before, last Sept. 18, and the crowd was still standing when Rafael Furcal came to the plate. The first pitch popped into Paul Lo Duca's glove for a strike, drawing a chorus of boos, and Furcal lined out to José Valentín. Even if the Mets were not laughing, the public-address announcer showed his sense of humor by playing ''It's easy as 1-2-3'' from the Jackson Five song ''ABC.''</p>
        <p>Throughout this slide, Randolph has spoken generally about themes that discourage him. Until Tuesday, there had rarely been specific moments that irked him. He had at least three to choose from.</p>
        <p>In the fourth, José Reyes pulled his glove back on Kemp's steal of second, letting the throw sail into center and Kemp scoot to third. In the fifth, Maine popped out on a bunt attempt. And in the sixth, in relief of Maine, Joe Smith allowed his 10th consecutive inherited runner to score, as the Dodgers went ahead, 4-1.</p>
        <p>Randolph draws on his experiences with the people he considers his mentors, people like Martin and Piniella, Dick Howser and Yogi Berra, to form his distinct managerial style. That usually does not entail team meetings, but he felt it was worth it to give a pep talk before Monday's game. It was not to motivate his players, he said, because this stretch should be reason enough to motivate them.</p>
        <p>''We feel that when the dust clears, we'll be where we want to be,'' Randolph said. ''If not, that's life. We've just got to keep getting better and better. We're not as good as we want to be.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Moises Alou, originally scheduled to fly Tuesday to Port St. Lucie, Fla., to continue receiving treatment for his strained left quadriceps, remained in New York to be evaluated by the team's medical director, Dr. David Altchek. ''He's not going to play anytime soon, so it doesn't matter where he goes or where he stays,'' Manager Willie Randolph said.  The Class AAA reliever Ambiorix Burgos was examined in New York and placed on the minor league disabled list with elbow discomfort. The organization remained concerned that he would require reconstructive elbow surgery.  Pedro Martínez threw 50 pitches off a mound in Port St. Lucie.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
