<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Hectic Chronicles</title>
    <meta content="13webhunt" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854271"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE HUNT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EEDA1E31F930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1048" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Hectic Chronicles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRENT BOWERS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HEY, all you work addicts out there, get a life.</p>
        <p>It took a nervous breakdown to force Timothy Ferriss to take that advice. But before I tell you his story, let me toss out a sampling of comments -- boasts, really -- that I've garnered recently from entrepreneurs about their hectic schedules.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HEY, all you work addicts out there, get a life.</p>
        <p>It took a nervous breakdown to force Timothy Ferriss to take that advice. But before I tell you his story, let me toss out a sampling of comments -- boasts, really -- that I've garnered recently from entrepreneurs about their hectic schedules.</p>
        <p>From a corporate executive who runs several businesses on the side: ''I get up at 3:30 a.m. I put in a full day at the office. In the evening, I do my personal paperwork.''</p>
        <p>From the owner of an office-equipment company: ''I didn't take a vacation for four straight years, and I was working 60 to 70 hours a week. I don't need anybody to encourage me to be in the office at 7 a.m. I'm there.''</p>
        <p>From the founder of a clothing store that is now defunct: ''Throughout my career, I'd wake up at 2 a.m. and not be able to get back to sleep. I'd say to myself: I should have bought green blouses instead of blue blouses. I worked all day, every day.''</p>
        <p>And my favorite, from William Kluckas, the 71-year-old founder of WFK Associates, who retired for good in 2003:''Almost every night, I dream I'm working. It isn't a replay of the past; the situations are all brand-new. I'm still solving problems. The only difference is that I'm not billing anybody anymore.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ferriss, founder of BrainQuicken, a maker of a dietary supplement  in San Jose, Calif., that is supposed to increase brainpower and physical performance, used to be like them. (His product is just the ticket for unrepentant workaholics, come to think of it.)</p>
        <p>The revelation that fast footwork can lead to a bigger payoff than a slow slog came to Mr. Ferriss when he was a student at Princeton University in 1998 and began holding seminars on how to cram for exams. The $1,500 he made for a few hours of hustle sure beat the $8 an hour he was pulling down at his job in a library attic.</p>
        <p>After starting BrainQuicken in 2001 at age 23, though, he fell into the classic trap of the start-up maven. ''I worked from 7 a.m. to 9 p.m.,'' he recalled. ''I'd get up early to call wholesalers, distributors and customers in the U.K. and Europe, and would call Asia at the end of the day. I spent four or five hours every Saturday and Sunday reading e-mail.''</p>
        <p>He remembers the day his recovery began: June 14, 2004. He was visiting an entrepreneur friend in Brooklyn who had gone down an identical path, and said to himself, ''Enough is enough.''</p>
        <p>He took a cab to John F. Kennedy International Airport with just his backpack and bought a one-way ticket to London, where he crashed at a friend's pad. ''I envisaged waking up slowly, stretching like a cat in a Spanish villa and relaxing over a book,'' he said. ''Instead, I bolted upright in bed. I had this compulsion to check my e-mail.</p>
        <p>''I wandered the city for three days in a daze, visiting museums, unable to think about anything except work. I couldn't walk past an Internet café without an upsurge of anxiety that I was missing out on something. I felt compelled to draw up lists of things to do, including 'go to dinner' and 'go to sleep,' just so I could check them off.''</p>
        <p>Pretty pathetic, huh? If you can top that one, please let me know at the e-mail address below.</p>
        <p>I'll probably get a lot of e-mails. Ted Zoller, executive director at the Center for Entrepreneurial Studies at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, says burnout is an intrinsic peril for entrepreneurs because they become so caught up in their vision that ''they can't restrain themselves, they can't monitor themselves.''</p>
        <p>His advice for avoiding the workaholic pitfall: pace yourself, set milestones and scale them back if you fall short, and have an exit plan. Also, make an inventory of the important things in your personal life, and get in the habit of reading obituaries. ''You'll quickly realize that in the grand scheme of things, your venture isn't going to matter all that much,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ferriss says it took him two months to cast off his workaholic chains. He began checking his e-mails once every 10 days. He discovered the magic of the 80-20 Pareto principle, named after an Italian economist, which states that 80 percent of consequences stem from 20 percent of causes. He began ignoring the 80 percent of his customers who accounted for just 20 percent of his business, and even jettisoned one of his top five buyers, who was creating more trouble than he was worth. His workload shrank, his revenue rose and his profit margin shot up by 30 percent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ferriss even applied the 80-20 rule to his personal life, spending more time with the 20 percent of his friends who gave him 80 percent of the pleasures of companionship and avoiding the 20 percent who contributed 80 percent of the frustrations.</p>
        <p>He even wrote a book, out seven weeks  and already a best seller, titled ''The 4-Hour Workweek'' (Crown Publishers), spelling out how to stop wasting time and start enjoying yourself. By four-hour workweek, he says, he means the time you devote to distasteful tasks. By all means, put in 50 hours on product development or schmoozing with clients, if that turns you on, he says. But if your preferences run to having fun, you could also travel, write a screenplay, go hiking on the Appalachian Trail or take up flying.</p>
        <p>In his own case, he says, his laid-back philosophy has allowed him to become a world-champion cage fighter, the first American to hold a Guinness world record in tango, a Princeton University lecturer, an actor on a hit TV series in China and a whole litany of other adventures.</p>
        <p>I recommend ''The 4-Hour Workweek'' because it's fast-paced and witty. His account of how he won the gold medal at the Chinese Kickboxing National Championship, for example, is hilarious. I'd tell you more but I promised myself I wouldn't spend any more than 3 hours and 59 minutes on this column (yes, Tim, I'm beating you at your own game) and my time is up.</p>
        <p>IN THE HUNT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
