<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>And Now, the Authentic Candidate</title>
    <meta content="l13krugman" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854198"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DF143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="648" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>And Now, the Authentic Candidate</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Authentic? Never Mind'' (column, June 11):</p>
        <p>Once again, Paul Krugman gets to the heart of the style-over-substance nature of today's political campaigns. But he didn't mention one important problem this need for ''authenticity'' causes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Authentic? Never Mind'' (column, June 11):</p>
        <p>Once again, Paul Krugman gets to the heart of the style-over-substance nature of today's political campaigns. But he didn't mention one important problem this need for ''authenticity'' causes.</p>
        <p>As presidential campaigns increasingly require astronomical sums of money, most candidates have personal fortunes that allow them to run. Does this mean that we can never have a national discussion about poverty? Yes, he's wealthy, but John Edwards has proved over and over that he genuinely cares about the plight of the poor.</p>
        <p>Let's forget the mansion and the $400 haircuts and remember that style-over-substance got us where we are today: Iraq, the environment, the Justice Department, Katrina -- need I go on?</p>
        <p>Christina Ferrari  Brooklyn, June 11, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Paul Krugman maintains that voters should not consider the ''authenticity'' of a candidate when deciding whom to support. Unfortunately, his argument rests on a rather skewed definition of the term.</p>
        <p>While I don't expect John Edwards to sell his mansion before talking about the problems of the poor, I do expect candidates to live up to the ideals to which they subscribe.</p>
        <p>How can a politician who lives in a 20-room home that must be heated and cooled year round ask Americans to cut down on their own energy use? How does a leader ask a 20-year-old to sacrifice his life in Iraq when he used political connections to avoid service? How does a politician call for health care reform when he made a fortune suing health care providers?</p>
        <p>The time has come for a leader who makes the same personal sacrifices that he or she asks of the public.</p>
        <p>Michael Sclafani  Spring Lake, N.J., June 11, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Authenticity, as defined by politics today, is nothing more than an illusion; men who were raised with everything acting as if they had nothing. But that's simply a symptom of the times.</p>
        <p>We've become an extraordinarily shallow country of voters, where the big question in 2004 was not Iraq, not health care, but which candidate would be more amiable over a beer. And even now, more than a year before ballots are cast, we're focused on John Edwards's haircut and Mitt Romney's hunting habits.</p>
        <p>It was this inattention to (important) details that gave us the most destructive president in our history, and it is this ignorance that could very well lead to another mistake.</p>
        <p>Matt Lurrie  Forest Hills, Queens, June 11, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Paul Krugman's column was right on. We have witnessed the tragic result of the G.O.P. right wing's efforts to make the Republican Party the dominant (most powerful) party for eternity at the expense of the interests of the entire nation. We must guard against this ever happening again.</p>
        <p>Jean Gelder  Rocky River, Ohio, June 11, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Lies, Sighs and Politics'' (column, June 8):</p>
        <p>Paul Krugman exposes a deep flaw in the way the media cover candidates for office in this country. The most trivial and superficial gets primary attention while issues of substance are left for the viewer or the reader to ascertain.</p>
        <p>The immaturity and character flaws of George W. Bush were there from the beginning, and should have been a disqualification for office in a more attentive, mature society. But it wasn't, because the media chose not to do their job of challenging his views and uncovering the truth about him but chose to pass off his comic conviviality as the attributes voters were looking for in a president.</p>
        <p>Until the seriousness of the highest job in the land is covered as such, we will have flawed candidates running for the office of the presidency in this country and mediocrity determining who is qualified to run.</p>
        <p>Hendrik E. Sadi  Yonkers, June 8, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
