<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Sends Second High Official to Baghdad This Week to Press Premier for Action</title>
    <meta content="13iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/world/middleeast/13iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854236"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Maliki, Nuri Kamal al-</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Negroponte, John D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EEDF143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="711" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Sends Second High Official to Baghdad This Week to Press Premier for Action</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Second U.S. Official Presses Iraqi Premier for Action</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMIEN CAVE; Khalid W. Hassan, Ali Adeeb and Karim Hilmi contributed reporting from Baghdad, and Iraqi employees of The New York Times from Ramadi and Diyala Province.</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, June 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Department of Defense confirms deaths of three service members in Iraq</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Deputy Secretary of State John D. Negroponte visited Baghdad on Tuesday to press Iraq's Shiite-led government to complete a series of political reforms intended to reconcile the country's warring sects.</p>
        <p>It was the second visit Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki received this week from a high-profile American official; on Sunday, the top military commander for the Middle East, Adm. William J. Fallon, warned that the Iraqi government needed to make tangible political progress by next month to counter opposition to the war in Congress.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The deputy secretary of state urged the Shiite-led government to complete political reforms intended to reconcile Iraq’s warring sects.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Deputy Secretary of State John D. Negroponte visited Baghdad on Tuesday to press Iraq's Shiite-led government to complete a series of political reforms intended to reconcile the country's warring sects.</p>
        <p>It was the second visit Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki received this week from a high-profile American official; on Sunday, the top military commander for the Middle East, Adm. William J. Fallon, warned that the Iraqi government needed to make tangible political progress by next month to counter opposition to the war in Congress.</p>
        <p>Mr. Negroponte, the former ambassador to Iraq, met with Mr. Maliki at his office in the fortified Green Zone and emphasized the need for accommodation and compromise among Iraq's combative factions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maliki, in a statement after the meeting, said Iraq's government was determined to persuade Parliament to approve several proposals that the Americans had identified as benchmarks, including an oil law that could more evenly distribute revenues to provinces and among Sunnis, Shiites and Kurds. He emphasized, however, that the country's priority should be developing its security forces to fight insurgents.</p>
        <p>''We have many tasks ahead of us,'' he said. ''On top of them is developing our security forces to handle their national roles in fighting the Al Qaeda terrorist group, Saddamists and militias to impose law and order in all the country.''</p>
        <p>Although sectarian violence continues in Iraq every day, he said, ''We have eliminated the danger of sectarian war.''</p>
        <p>The visit and Mr. Maliki's statement seemed to underscore the increasingly tense relationship between Mr. Maliki and the Americans.</p>
        <p>Many American officials now blame a lack of firm leadership by senior politicians like Mr. Maliki for the lack of progress in Iraq. He and other Iraqi officials, including Sunnis and Kurds, say the Americans are mistakenly focused on individuals rather than the broader forces of sectarian distrust, corruption, violence and interference from Iran and Syria, which they contend have conspired to sabotage stability.</p>
        <p>Iraq's quarrelsome political climate has been on public display lately as Parliament has sought to unseat its speaker, Mahmoud Mashhadani, a Sunni, who has done little to build consensus among political blocs and whose guards were accused of assaulting a Shiite lawmaker on Sunday.</p>
        <p>In a vote on Monday, 113 of the 168 Parliament members who were present voted to force Mr. Mashhadani's resignation, and his own bloc, the Iraqi Consensus Front, has agreed to replace him. But in some of his first public comments on Tuesday, he told reporters that he did not intend to leave and would try to sue if forced to give up his position.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Iraq's sectarian violence continued.</p>
        <p>In Baghdad, the authorities found 26 bodies scattered throughout the city, many showing signs of torture, an Interior Ministry official said. Three roadside bombs in the capital killed three people and wounded at least 12, news services reported.</p>
        <p>To the west, in Anbar Province, a suicide car bomber killed at least four people at a checkpoint west of Ramadi, witnesses said.</p>
        <p>And in Diyala Province, increasingly the site of Iraq's most extreme violence, bombs and gun battles continued to tear through communities. The police said that gunmen attacked the house of a local official outside Muqdadiya, kidnapping his elderly father and three sisters.</p>
        <p>Gaps in Iraq May Prolong U.S. Stay</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON, June 12 (Bloomberg) -- Iraq's security forces have gaps in leadership, logistics and combat power that could tie down United States troops for years, the departing Army general in charge of Iraqi training said Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The most serious problem is a lack of majors, lieutenant colonels and brigadier generals to lead military forces set to exceed 190,000 by the end of the year, Lt. Gen. Martin Dempsey told a House Armed Services Committee panel. That force level would be larger than the total American troops now in Iraq.</p>
        <p>Finding competent leaders has been difficult, he said, because the pool of qualified officers recalled from Saddam Hussein's army after the United States disbanded the force in May 2003 ''is beginning to thin out, and many fine military and police leaders have been killed and wounded in the ongoing fight.''</p>
        <p>THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
