<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Socrates as a Woman, and Other Twists on the Ancients</title>
    <meta content="13target" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/theater/13target.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854113"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Target Margin Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Herskovits, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Greenspan, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05EFD8173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="932" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Socrates as a Woman, and Other Twists on the Ancients</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Socrates as a Woman, and Other Twists on the Ancients</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEXIS SOLOSKI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Socrates didn't much care for the theater, or so Plato insists in ''The Republic.'' ''All poetical imitations are ruinous to the understanding of the hearers,'' Socrates declares at one point.</p>
        <p>But beginning tomorrow, the Target Margin Theater company will make Socrates not only the lead character in a play, but also its co-author, with an adaptation of Plato's ''Symposium'' retitled ''Dinner Party.'' If that is not a sufficiently unlikely theatrical combination, the adaptation will run in tandem with Aristotle's ''Poetics,'' here called ''The Argument,'' by David Greenspan, the actor and director.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Target Margin Theater company’s productions of “Dinner Party” and “The Argument” represent the culmination of a season devoted to the Greeks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Socrates didn't much care for the theater, or so Plato insists in ''The Republic.'' ''All poetical imitations are ruinous to the understanding of the hearers,'' Socrates declares at one point.</p>
        <p>But beginning tomorrow, the Target Margin Theater company will make Socrates not only the lead character in a play, but also its co-author, with an adaptation of Plato's ''Symposium'' retitled ''Dinner Party.'' If that is not a sufficiently unlikely theatrical combination, the adaptation will run in tandem with Aristotle's ''Poetics,'' here called ''The Argument,'' by David Greenspan, the actor and director.</p>
        <p>Target Margin's artistic director, David Herskovits, founded this experimental theater company in 1991. From its first production -- a bloody version of ''Titus Andronicus'' set in a Lower East Side basement -- Target Margin has focused on neglected classics like Dorothy and DuBose Heyward's ''Mamba's Daughters'' and the plays of Gertrude Stein. Mr. Herskovits said he started the company because ''there wasn't a place in the institutional theater that would be naturally welcoming and supportive of me; I wanted to do things that were a little further outside the mainstream.'' And he has. The company has produced more than 30 works in which large casts, boisterous design and frenetic action have crowded small downtown stages.</p>
        <p>Over matzo-ball soup and corned-beef sandwiches, Mr. Herskovits explained why he enjoyed turning philosophical treatises into theatrical shows. One reason, with the current productions in particular, he said, is that ''The Symposium'' and ''Poetics'' actually do lend themselves to drama.</p>
        <p>''Both make room for theatrical experience,'' he said, and are ''set in a particular scene with a particular group of characters and a high level of contradictory and overlapping motivations, agendas, ironies and confusions.'' He added, ''What the theater can do, it can dramatize those things.'' Mr. Herskovits, like any good follower of Socrates, will often claim that he knows nothing. ''I don't know what a play is,'' he'll say, or, ''Believe me, I could be a total idiot about all this stuff.'' But with degrees in classics from Yale and Cambridge, postgraduate work in Greek and 20 years as a director, he is not exactly adrift.</p>
        <p>''Dinner Party'' and ''The Argument'' represent the culmination of a season devoted to the Greeks. They follow productions of Euripides' ''As Yet Thou Art Young and Rash'' and Sophocles' ''Women of Trachis.'' His plan for the season, he said, was ''to really mount a broad-ranging theatrical investigation of classical Greek culture,'' and to do so by looking ''beyond the canon of classical drama'' to sources that might not immediately be seen as theatrical experiences.</p>
        <p>Richard Foreman, founder of the Ontological-Hysteric Theater and Mr. Herskovits's first employer in New York, said he applauded his ''dedication to plays from the repertory that no one else dares to perform.''</p>
        <p>And Mr. Herskovits acknowledged an attraction to ''material that many theaters will resist because it's large, because it's obscure, because it's very literary.''</p>
        <p>Such material -- which he characterized as having ''a high resistance'' to audiences, as well as to himself -- appeal to him because they contain ''situations we cannot fathom easily, tonal problems, opaque language.''</p>
        <p>Martin Puchner, a theater professor at Columbia University, said that more than 100 plays, beginning in the 17th century, have featured Socrates as a character. But Target Margin's latest offering, he said, may well be the first one in which a young African-American woman plays the part.</p>
        <p>She is Stephanie Weeks, but during ''Dinner Party'' all the actors use their first names. So Stephanie, Han Nah and Steven replace Socrates, Agathon and Aristophanes.</p>
        <p>The setting is a contemporary loft, and the music comes from a D.J. offering Lauryn Hill, Gotan Project and Seu Jorge. And, significantly, women invade the formerly all-male precincts of ''The Symposium.''</p>
        <p>Much of the conversation in ''The Symposium'' involved pederasty, but Mr. Herskovits's production instead features both homosexual and heterosexual relations between adults. The play's dramaturge, Kathleen Kennedy Tobin, defends this choice, arguing: ''The classical dynamic of man-youth love doesn't exist today. There's no equivalent in modern society for this accepted power-education-desire dynamic. You'd have to set it in ancient Greece, with a long program note.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Herskovits said that he chose to ''sacrifice an allegiance to that bit of history in order to favor what I believe are the deep truths about love and human relationships.''</p>
        <p>Neither Ms. Tobin nor Mr. Herskovits said they wanted to create a show requiring a philosophy degree to understand. Using contemporary settings and actors' own names was intended to make the proceedings clearer, Ms. Tobin said. She and Mr. Herskovits have walked the cast through the original Greek and several translations to help them create an improvised, idiomatic script.</p>
        <p>Mr. Herskovits said that ''the decision to improvise language is a choice in tension with the literary qualities of the speeches,'' but he felt that ''the idiomatic freedom and instantaneous texture of the performances make the game worth the candle.''</p>
        <p>He described Plato's language as so much ''smoke.'' He encouraged the actors to clutch at ''the core of thought'' behind it, to ''scrape away all of the encrustation of scholarship and translation and expectation.''</p>
        <p>The theme and tension in ''Dinner Party'' come from asking, what is love, and how does it differ from sexual desire?</p>
        <p>''Plato really is interested in getting beyond human erotic relationships, but he always remembers that that's what's driving us all,'' Mr. Herskovits said. ''It isn't either-or. It's both. That's why it's a Target Margin show.''</p>
        <p>''Dinner Party'' and ''The Argument'' open tomorrow and run together through June 30 at the Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea; (212) 255-5793, Ext. 11.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
