<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Memorial Services Remember David Halberstam and Kitty Carlisle Hart; A Writer Dedicated To Conveying Truth</title>
    <meta content="13halberstam" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/nyregion/13halberstam.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854151"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pulitzer Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Halberstam, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFD7173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="621" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Memorial Services Remember David Halberstam and Kitty Carlisle Hart; A Writer Dedicated To Conveying Truth</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">David Halberstam Remembered as Writer Dedicated to Conveying Truth</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Halberstam, the Pulitzer Prize-winning journalist and author who was killed in a car crash in California on April 23, was remembered yesterday as a gifted storyteller who was determined to tell his readers the truth.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of people attended a memorial service for Mr. Halberstam at Riverside Church in Manhattan: well-known writers and editors who had known him when he was a war correspondent lugging a portable typewriter and filing stories by teletype, and people who had read Mr. Halberstam's books or heard him on radio or seen him on television. Among the speakers were the historian Doris Kearns Goodwin; the writers Gay Talese, Michael Arlen and Anna Quindlen; and Representative John Lewis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hundreds of people attended a memorial service for Mr. Halberstam at Riverside Church in Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>David Halberstam, the Pulitzer Prize-winning journalist and author who was killed in a car crash in California on April 23, was remembered yesterday as a gifted storyteller who was determined to tell his readers the truth.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of people attended a memorial service for Mr. Halberstam at Riverside Church in Manhattan: well-known writers and editors who had known him when he was a war correspondent lugging a portable typewriter and filing stories by teletype, and people who had read Mr. Halberstam's books or heard him on radio or seen him on television. Among the speakers were the historian Doris Kearns Goodwin; the writers Gay Talese, Michael Arlen and Anna Quindlen; and Representative John Lewis.</p>
        <p>Neil Sheehan, who was a correspondent with United Press International in Saigon when Mr. Halberstam was posted there by The New York Times, talked about how Mr. Halberstam's dispatches infuriated policymakers in Washington and military commanders in Saigon. On occasion, so did Mr. Halberstam.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sheehan described a day when an outpost north of Saigon fell to a Vietcong assault and the military would not let reporters fly there on military aircraft. That evening, Mr. Halberstam called the United States military commander, Gen. Paul D. Harkins, at his villa to complain.</p>
        <p>The briefing for reporters the next day was given by a brigadier general who began, Mr. Sheehan said, ''by lecturing us lowly reporters for having had the temerity to disturb the commanding general at home.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Halberstam did not let that pass, Mr. Sheehan said. '' 'General,' David boomed in his great loud voice,'' Mr. Sheehan said, '' 'we are not corporals. We do not work for you. We work for our editors. If you have any complaints, complain to our editors. We will disturb the commanding general at home any time we have to do so in order to get our job done. The American public has a right to know what's going on here. Is that clear?'</p>
        <p>''I suspect no one had given that man a dressing-down like that since his plebe year at West Point,'' Mr. Sheehan said. But he said one general at the briefing winked at Mr. Halberstam, ''and the rest of us had to work hard to suppress a smile.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Halberstam was also remembered as a best-selling author whose telephone number was listed in the Manhattan directory. Mr. Talese said Mr. Halberstam would answer, usually on the first ring, ''and talk to you, whether he knew you or not.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Halberstam, 73, died when a car slammed into the one in which he was riding and pushed it into a third vehicle in Menlo Park, Calif.</p>
        <p>Among those at the service were Joseph Lelyveld, a former executive editor of The New York Times; Seymour Topping, a former Times managing editor; Benjamin C. Bradlee, a former executive editor of The Washington Post; David Remnick, the editor of The New Yorker magazine; and Richard C. Holbrooke, the former United States ambassador to the United Nations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Halberstam, who wrote more than 20 books, was perhaps best known for writing about Vietnam in ''The Best and the Brightest'' or about media dynasties in ''The Powers That Be.'' But, Ms. Goodwin said, Mr. Halberstam's books on sports and athletes opened a window onto the larger canvas of American life.</p>
        <p>The singer Peter Yarrow, a neighbor in Mr. Halberstam's building, said Mr. Halberstam had ''brought light and clarity and determination to all of us'' by concentrating on issues of fairness and decency.</p>
        <p>Dexter Filkins, who covered the war in Iraq for The Times, said Mr. Halberstam had set an example. ''We reporters in Iraq were the running backs,'' he said. ''David went first, a long time ago, and cleared the way.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
