<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mayor and Council Agree on Budget, Providing Breaks on Property and Sales Tax</title>
    <meta content="13city" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/nyregion/13city.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854231"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEFDF143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1008" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mayor and Council Agree on Budget, Providing Breaks on Property and Sales Tax</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mayor and Council Agree on Budget, Providing Breaks on Property and Sales Tax</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAY RIVERA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City taxpayers would get a larger-than-expected break on their property taxes under a deal announced last night by city leaders on a $59 billion budget. The pact would also use a record $4.4 billion surplus to eliminate taxes on clothing and shoes and increase library service to six days a week.</p>
        <p>The agreement, sealed by Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg and the City Council speaker, Christine C. Quinn, with a handshake and a kiss in the City Hall rotunda, comes weeks earlier than usual and was the earliest since Mr. Bloomberg took office in 2002. The highlight is a 7 percent across-the-board cut in the property tax rate, 2 percentage points more than the mayor proposed in January.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The highlight is a 7 percent across-the-board cut in the property tax rate, more than Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg proposed in January.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York City taxpayers would get a larger-than-expected break on their property taxes under a deal announced last night by city leaders on a $59 billion budget. The pact would also use a record $4.4 billion surplus to eliminate taxes on clothing and shoes and increase library service to six days a week.</p>
        <p>The agreement, sealed by Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg and the City Council speaker, Christine C. Quinn, with a handshake and a kiss in the City Hall rotunda, comes weeks earlier than usual and was the earliest since Mr. Bloomberg took office in 2002. The highlight is a 7 percent across-the-board cut in the property tax rate, 2 percentage points more than the mayor proposed in January.</p>
        <p>While the rate cut may not mean lower tax bills for everyone, it will help offset soaring property assessments, officials said.</p>
        <p>The early budget agreement allows the cuts to be reflected in the property tax bill for the first quarter of the fiscal year 2008, which begins July 1, providing an immediate dose of political good will for the mayor and the Council. The bills will be sent out within the next week.</p>
        <p>It also allows the mayor to focus on other pressing items of his agenda, including winning legislative approval for his congestion-pricing plan.</p>
        <p>In a joint announcement, Mr. Bloomberg called the early agreement ''a tribute to the cooperative relationship we've developed with the City Council leadership, members and the budget staff. Together we've reached a budget that we think is good for the entire city and one that will carry us over and keep us from making some of the mistakes of the past.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Quinn said the budget ''balances fiscal responsibility with the need to provide essential city services to New Yorkers.''</p>
        <p>The deal, which the Council is all but sure to approve in a vote scheduled for Friday, adds about $230 million to the formal budget proposal the mayor unveiled in April.</p>
        <p>In addition to the property tax cuts, the budget would renew the $400 property tax rebates for homeowners, which total about $256 million a year. It would also provide about $110 million in sales tax relief by eliminating city sales taxes that now apply to clothing and shoe purchases of over $110, and by providing $75 million in tax breaks for small businesses and S-corporations, a type of partnership. The tax cuts total about $1.3 billion.</p>
        <p>The business and sales tax cuts will require legislative approval from Albany, which approved renewal of the rebates for homeowners last week.</p>
        <p>The mayor's office had proposed about $110 million in business tax breaks in January but trimmed the number by about $35 million in an agreement with the Council to increase property tax cuts, according to administration officials.</p>
        <p>The cut in the property tax rate was intended to soften the impact of rising property values, which will lead to higher tax bills for many property owners. According to the city's estimates, market values grew by 19 percent in 2006, double the increase of the previous year.</p>
        <p>The mayor and the Council said yesterday that the 7 percent cut would effectively offset the rising property values, meaning that the average home owner's tax bill would not rise.</p>
        <p>According to Council figures, the average yearly tax bill for condominiums in the coming fiscal year, with the rise in assessments combined with the lower tax rate, would be $6,061. Compared with fiscal year 2007's average bill of $6,476, that would be a savings of $415.</p>
        <p>Co-op owners, who are assessed differently, would pay about $3,975 in the new fiscal year, compared with fiscal year 2007's average of $3,944, an increase of $31.</p>
        <p>And owners of single family homes would pay $2,964 in the new fiscal year, compared with an average $2,977 in the current fiscal year, a $13 savings.</p>
        <p>For Ms. Quinn, the budget included some victories and defeats. She won approval to have all public libraries returned to being open at least six days a week, a service that was lost in cuts after 9/11. And under the agreement, the expanded hours would begin right away, not over three years, as she originally proposed.</p>
        <p>But she did not win a $300 tax credit for renters, the highlight of the budget priorities she announced in April. Ms. Quinn said she would continue to press for the renters' credit with the mayor and in Albany, which would also have to approve it.</p>
        <p>She said the Council was successful in restoring $21 million in financing that will allow City University of New York to retain full-time faculty and hire more professors. The budget also includes more money for full-day prekindergarten slots.</p>
        <p>The budget would provide for bulletproof vests for auxiliary police officers and improvements to the 311 system. It would also include $200 million for mass transit initiatives called for in the mayor's environmental blueprint for the city, PlaNYC, and $28 million for 9/11 health programs.</p>
        <p>The early budget agreement is a stark signal of how the city's financial picture has improved over the last five years. When Mr. Bloomberg took office, he and the Council were forced to raise property taxes 18 percent in addition to cutting government services in the face of the economic downturns after 9/11. Budget negotiations then were filled with histrionics, each side accusing the other of overspending or shortchanging essential services.</p>
        <p>The process has become positively cordial by comparison over the last two years, especially since Ms. Quinn took over as speaker in 2006.</p>
        <p>But the mayor and the Council warned that the city's financial fortunes could turn in the next few years. For that reason, the budget includes $2.3 billion to pay down future expenses and debt in 2009 and 2010. They also made the 7 percent tax reduction a one-year cut with a promise to extend it if the economy remains strong.</p>
        <p>''In the months ahead, we'll keep a close eye on the city's finances as we weigh whether to extend this property tax cut next year,'' Mr. Bloomberg said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
