<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Left Wrist, Meet Right Wrist</title>
    <meta content="13roberts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/sports/golf/13roberts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854246"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Selena Roberts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Wie, Michelle</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mickelson, Phil</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7DE143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Left Wrist, Meet Right Wrist</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Left Wrist, Meet Right Wrist</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He tweaked his wrist last month by muscling practice balls out of a rough as thick and tangled as pompoms on the United States Open course at Oakmont Country Club.</p>
        <p>She played with one injured wrist as she muscled drives against the brutes of the PGA Tour in January, then hurt the other wrist in a tumble while running weeks later.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michelle Wie has been filleted for her wrist versus reward shenanigans as an entitled teen while Phil Mickelson has been treated with reverence for his trouper’s mentality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He tweaked his wrist last month by muscling practice balls out of a rough as thick and tangled as pompoms on the United States Open course at Oakmont Country Club.</p>
        <p>She played with one injured wrist as she muscled drives against the brutes of the PGA Tour in January, then hurt the other wrist in a tumble while running weeks later.</p>
        <p>He withdrew from the first round of the Memorial Tournament on May 31 after 11 holes and a two-over-par effort when his inflamed wrist couldn't cock for another swing.</p>
        <p>She withdrew from the first round of the L.P.G.A.'s Ginn Tribute on the same afternoon after 16 holes and a 14-over-par fiasco, citing a sore wrist that could not generate another 280-yard drive.</p>
        <p>She didn't dare miss the next major, though, playing in the L.P.G.A. Championship over the weekend with wrapped wrists.</p>
        <p>He didn't sit home, either, preparing for this week's United States Open with a brace on his left wrist.</p>
        <p>He is the beloved Pooh of golf, Phil Mickelson. She is the alienating princess of Nike, Michelle Wie. What does the popularity disparity have to do with it?</p>
        <p>The fabulously wealthy Wie has been filleted for her wrist-versus-reward shenanigans as an entitled teenager. The handsomely paid Mickelson has been treated with reverence for his trouper's mentality.</p>
        <p>The difference in fallout would illuminate the gimme putts of double standards -- the cattiness of gals versus the camaraderie of men -- if Wie's credibility wasn't in a singular free fall.</p>
        <p>With three majors and more than 30 Tour wins, Mickelson may well be a closet Narcissus with a devilish side behind his affable veneer, but he has a reservoir of good will that provides a buffer to skepticism.</p>
        <p>Why is Mickelson teeing it up this week? Out of his sponsors' interest or self-interest? The reason is not a divisive issue because Mickelson is not a polarizing figure.</p>
        <p>''I probably won't be pain-free like I had hoped,'' said Mickelson at a news conference after his practice round in Oakmont, Pa., yesterday. ''But I should be able to have it be manageable as long as I don't aggravate it -- or hit in the rough.''</p>
        <p>He had to laugh. Avoiding the rough at any United States Open is like expecting to walk on water without getting your feet wet. An impossibility -- especially for Mickelson. Who doesn't remember his collapse at last year's United States Open when he couldn't find the fairway but did hit a hospitality tent?</p>
        <p>His flaws only foster more endearment. Wie's hiccups invite scorn.</p>
        <p>Whether it comes from Wie or her stage parents or management team, there is no comprehension of debt service. Golf doesn't owe them. They owe golf.</p>
        <p>Her recent bouts of entitlement -- with her curious scheduling and medical mysteries -- have tested the patience of even the most diplomatic L.P.G.A. caretakers, including Annika Sorenstam. As host of the Ginn Tribute, Sorenstam offered an exemption to Wie and to MacKinzie Kline, a 15-year-old wonder with a congenital heart defect who was permitted to use a cart.</p>
        <p>To Kline, the day was a gift. To Wie, it was a given.</p>
        <p>Kline opened her invite via a cellphone message after class at her high school in Encinitas, Calif.</p>
        <p>''I heard my phone vibrating in my backpack,'' Kline said last week as she sat in the dining room during a fund-raising event at the Mountain Ridge Country Club in West Caldwell, N.J., for the Children's Heart Foundation. ''I looked after class and it was her. I held the phone to my ear and she said, 'This is Annika.' I was like, right.</p>
        <p>''I kept pressing the button to hear it again. Then, finally once I thought, this is really Annika, I had to hear it again to understand what she was telling me. It's still saved in my phone.''</p>
        <p>Kline, whose condition can leave her sapped by the end of a round, finished the Ginn Tribute with an 89 -- or one shot over the L.P.G.A.'s 88 rule. Posting an 88 makes any non-Tour member ineligible to play another event within the year.</p>
        <p>Wie might have faced the same fate if her handlers hadn't apparently warned her about the pending number. She walked away from her round before her score ballooned to an 88. Sorenstam later questioned her class when Wie materialized at the L.P.G.A. Championship. A withdrawal never entered Kline's mind.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it matters what you shoot,'' Kline said. ''I think you have to keep playing and finish the tournament. I definitely wouldn't have wanted to quit. I felt a responsibility.''</p>
        <p>Whom was the Wie camp indebted to? The sponsors who would have coughed up a platinum card if Wie had been barred the rest of the L.P.G.A. season? A family that already looks attention starved for entering Wie in a men's event next month despite her injuries?</p>
        <p>Mickelson's wrist saga may be every bit as curious as Wie's when drawn on its parallel paths, but he has a wealth of credibility. This isn't a double standard. Just a second look at how the career of Wie is dangerously close to fizzling out as a novelty act.</p>
        <p>She hasn't broken par in a year. She is only drifting farther off the fairways and further down the leader board in every event she plays -- PGA or L.P.G.A.</p>
        <p>Enough of the free passes. Enough of the exemptions. Wie and her entourage need lessons in debt service. Everything -- even the benefit of the doubt -- should be earned.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
