<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Math Lesson on College Loans</title>
    <meta content="13kunin" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/opinion/13kunin.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854230"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kunin, Madeleine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Education Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EFDF143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Math Lesson on College Loans</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Math Lesson on College Loans</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Madeleine May Kunin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kunin, Madeleine</byline>
      <dateline>Burlington, Vt.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Madeleine May Kunin, secretary of education during Clinton administration, holds that expanding direct lending program, which allows government to give student loans directly, is cost-effective, ethical way to provide student loans; says direct loan system is rare case in which federal government is more streamlined than private sector; maintains that it also saves borrowers money and would allow more grants for needy students; contends that direct lending eliminates corruption or favoritism and ensures lowest costs for students; notes that direct lending also offers income-contingent repayment options; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Department of Education's proposed new standards for overseeing student loans -- a response to the growing scandal involving kickbacks from lending institutions to university student-aid officials -- are a step in the right direction. But the department and the Bush administration could go further in making student loans cheaper, less cumbersome and, most important, not susceptible to corruption.</p>
        <p>In fact, the method for achieving this is already on the books: the William D. Ford Federal Direct Loan Program, which omits the middleman and allows the government itself to give loans to students. It needs to be expanded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Expanding the direct lending program is a sensible and cost-effective way for Congress and the Department of Education to help more of our young people realize the American Dream.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Department of Education's proposed new standards for overseeing student loans -- a response to the growing scandal involving kickbacks from lending institutions to university student-aid officials -- are a step in the right direction. But the department and the Bush administration could go further in making student loans cheaper, less cumbersome and, most important, not susceptible to corruption.</p>
        <p>In fact, the method for achieving this is already on the books: the William D. Ford Federal Direct Loan Program, which omits the middleman and allows the government itself to give loans to students. It needs to be expanded.</p>
        <p>Since 1994, the Education Department has given universities a choice between the traditional Federal Family Education Loan Program, under which the government guarantees loans from 3,500 eligible banks and other lenders, and the Ford direct loan system.</p>
        <p>This direct loan program was one of the first education initiatives of the Clinton administration; we thought it would save taxpayers money and simplify the lending process for both students and universities. Indeed, as anyone who has ever tried to negotiate his way through the paperwork involved in the traditional loan program will attest, the direct loan system has proved to be one of those rare cases in which the federal bureaucracy is far more streamlined than the private sector.</p>
        <p>It also saves taxpayers a lot of money. According to President Bush's 2007 budget, the government will pay a subsidy of 1.7 percent on the dollar value of its direct loans, as opposed to the 7.5 percent it will pay on guaranteed loans by private lenders. (There are many reasons for this disparity -- which changes from year to year -- including variations in expected loan volumes and the extra monetary rewards needed to attract private lenders to the guaranteed loan program.)</p>
        <p>The Office of Management and Budget projects that students and parents will borrow $76 billion this year from the guaranteed loan program. If all these loans were direct loans, the O.M.B. found, the Treasury would save nearly $4.5 billion.</p>
        <p>Even if only a small percentage of borrowers moved into the direct loan program, the savings could be enough to provide more grants for needy students. Democratic leaders in the House and Senate have proposed bills to create such a redistribution, and they deserve support.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, direct lending has a troubled history in Congress. Back in the early '90s, lending institutions, which see student loans as easy money, lobbied strongly against creating the direct loan program. It survived only because Democrats tucked it into the 1993 budget agreement.</p>
        <p>Although the law permitted up to 60 percent of American universities and colleges to move to direct lending, the number participating has never topped one-third and it is now down to about 25 percent. Why? When Republicans took control of Congress in 1994, they passed a law that prohibited the Education Department from encouraging or requiring colleges to switch to the direct loan program.</p>
        <p>While this might seem a good way to ensure competition, it has not worked in practice. According to a study by the New America Foundation, lenders ''profiting from the guarantee system could use their substantial resources to lure or retain colleges and universities, while the direct loan program was not allowed to make its own case.''</p>
        <p>This very idea -- that banks ''lure'' universities into doing business -- brings us to perhaps the best argument on behalf of direct lending: it eliminates any possibility of corruption, favoritism or abuse. The traditional bank loan program will always depend on volume for its earnings. No matter how many regulations are issued by Washington, there will always be an incentive for lenders to win over financial aid officers by any means possible.</p>
        <p>Another advantage of direct lending is that universities do not have to try to sort out which of the thousands of private lenders would be best for their students. With direct loans, the government can ensure the lowest costs for taxpayers and students.</p>
        <p>An additional benefit for students (and the nation) is that the direct loan program offers income-contingent loan repayment options, which can lower premiums, and that after 25 years of repayment, loans are forgiven. These features make it easier for debt-ridden students to take lower-paying jobs that serve the public interest without having to worry about defaulting on their loans.</p>
        <p>More than ever, achieving the American Dream depends on access to a good, affordable college education. Expanding the direct lending program is a sensible and cost-effective way for Congress and the Education Department to help more of our young people realize it.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Madeleine May Kunin, a former governor of Vermont, was the deputy secretary of education from 1993 to 1996.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Madeleine May Kunin, a former governor of Vermont, was the deputy secretary of education from 1993 to 1996.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
