<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Doing the People's Business, In All Its Somnolent Glory</title>
    <meta content="13wise" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/arts/television/13wise.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854130"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Public Broadcasting Service</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wiseman, Frederick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7D7173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="829" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Doing the People's Business, In All Its Somnolent Glory</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Doing the People’s Business, in All Its Somnolent Glory</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIRGINIA HEFFERNAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Frederick Wiseman's documentaries were famous for having integrity, and then, quick as a flash, they became famous for being boring. ''State Legislature,'' a two-part, billion-minute program about, well, you know what it's about, is set in the state capital building in Boise, Idaho. It appears tonight on PBS.</p>
        <p>The clattery, shuffly, all-too-real documentary opens with some Idahoan legislators telling teenagers, at length, what average and ordinary guys they are as members of a so-called citizen legislature. One even proposes, in a workaday monotone, that the first hundred people in any Idaho phonebook could do just as well as the legislators at making decisions in the capital.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Frederick Wiseman’s clattery, shuffly, all-too-real documentary, “State Legislature,” set in the state capital building in Boise, Idaho, appears tonight on PBS.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Frederick Wiseman's documentaries were famous for having integrity, and then, quick as a flash, they became famous for being boring. ''State Legislature,'' a two-part, billion-minute program about, well, you know what it's about, is set in the state capital building in Boise, Idaho. It appears tonight on PBS.</p>
        <p>The clattery, shuffly, all-too-real documentary opens with some Idahoan legislators telling teenagers, at length, what average and ordinary guys they are as members of a so-called citizen legislature. One even proposes, in a workaday monotone, that the first hundred people in any Idaho phonebook could do just as well as the legislators at making decisions in the capital.</p>
        <p>If the title of ''State Legislature'' doesn't grab you, then these claims of absolute banality surely will.</p>
        <p>It's going to be another long, yawning, integrity-jammed Wiseman haul. If you're inclined to complain about so-called jump-cuts in contemporary television, Mr. Wiseman's films are a chance to see if you really do miss the old film editor's eye: the one that doesn't blink, tire of long shots or wimp out when some yammerer is speechifying on anything from judiciary minutiae to how seriously he pledges his allegiance to the flag of the United States of America and to the Republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, with liberty and justice for all.</p>
        <p>What becomes plain -- and either refreshing or deadening, depending on the viewer -- is that a contemporary character is absent here, the trickster who controls nearly all viewing experiences these days. This is the capricious digital editor -- the one with the Avid or, better yet, the Final Cut Pro, who can't resist cutting and jumping and wiping and cutting again.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wiseman, who believes his art is in his editing, eschews that wanton, good-time cutty style, choosing instead to manipulate images like a traditional celluloid editor. This type is understandably parsimonious with incisions, knowing they're hard to undo on film; Mr. Wiseman, let's say, is trigger-unhappy. His films are long, and they often look like tape simply rolling, C-Span-style.</p>
        <p>But even security cams catch good stuff from time to time. And Mr. Wiseman, whose choices are apparent in the selection of scenes and sequence if not in the internal editing of scenes, offers subdued intellectual pleasures and gentle ironies for those faithful enough to wait for them.</p>
        <p>During a presentation by a police officer before the Legislature on the dangers of perverts with camera phones, for example, the contradiction between the film's monotone and the sexual and technological panic it exhibits comes into focus.</p>
        <p>''This is a big issue we've had lately,'' says the officer, with considerable reserve, in his gun-metal-colored suit, ''of the ladies in particular, that are unaware that someone is coming up from behind them and sticking one of these new videos -- or, excuse me, cellphones with the cameras on it -- up behind them and actually doing what we call 'upskirting' and taking pictures up their skirt, and they're not even aware of it.''</p>
        <p>In the Hollywood version of ''State Legislature'' this man's speech would either be excessively sanctimonious or excessively salacious. What's striking here is that it's neither, even with that aggressive word ''sticking.'' The officer speaks with measured frustration about prosecuting the new crime and seems as vexed and discomfited by the new technology as he is by the voyeurism.</p>
        <p>''The Internet is just really getting to a point where people want to put some images out there,'' he says, shaking his head. ''And we have no way to address it at this time.''</p>
        <p>''Upskirting,'' in other words, trips off his tongue as a coinage, whereas ''camera phone'' continually eludes him.</p>
        <p>From there, watching the movie begins to feel like being in a giant, well-organized meeting that never ends, where you never get to talk and where the issues -- unless you live in Idaho -- don't have anything directly to do with you. After video voyeurism, subjects move to matters educational, agricultural, jurisdictional, procedural, soporifical, sleeperal, ambieneral, losttrainofthoughteral. What, huh? No, I'm awake. I'm just dozing.</p>
        <p>Look, is that police officer who couldn't say ''camera phone'' a stand-in for Mr. Wiseman's own anxieties? The filmmaker, who began his prolific and genre-defining career with ''Titicut Follies'' in 1967, has been in far rougher, raunchier places than this Legislature, and even ones that require more patience.</p>
        <p>But, like the rest of us, he has never lived in a more digital era, with such small cameras and so many opportunities for so many people both to shoot and stage-manage images. To someone who is used to running the show, there's something much scarier about that than upskirting, even. Maybe that's what this film is really about.</p>
        <p>State Legislature  On most PBS stations tonight (check local listings).</p>
        <p>Directed, produced and edited by Frederick Wiseman; Stephen Segaller, executive producer for Thirteen/WNET; Sally Jo Fifer, executive producer for ITVS; John Davey, photography; sound by Mr. Wiseman. Produced by Idaho Film Inc. and Thirteen/WNET New York in association with ITVS.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
