<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spitzer Expects Federal Funds for Congestion Plan; Lawmakers' Doubts Remain</title>
    <meta content="13albany" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/nyregion/13albany.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854252"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Albany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Albany (NY)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E5DE143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="803" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spitzer Expects Federal Funds for Congestion Plan; Lawmakers' Doubts Remain</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spitzer Expects Federal Funds for Congestion Plan; Lawmakers’ Doubts Remain</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, June 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer expressed optimism on Tuesday about the chances of getting federal funds to carry out Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's congestion-pricing plan, even as lawmakers continued to question its wisdom. The lawmakers also said it was unlikely to come up for a vote before the end of the regular legislative session next week.</p>
        <p>The mayor's proposal would impose fees on vehicles driving into the most congested parts of Manhattan on weekdays as part of an overall plan to improve air quality and ease traffic. Hanging in the balance is as much as $500 million in federal money that the Bush administration has said can be awarded if the state approves the mayor's plan by August.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALBANY, June 12  Gov. Eliot Spitzer expressed optimism on Tuesday about the chances of getting federal funds to carry out Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg’s congestion-pricing plan, even as lawmakers continued to question its wisdom. The lawmakers also said it was unlikely to come up for a vote before the end of the regular legislative session next week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer expressed optimism on Tuesday about the chances of getting federal funds to carry out Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's congestion-pricing plan, even as lawmakers continued to question its wisdom. The lawmakers also said it was unlikely to come up for a vote before the end of the regular legislative session next week.</p>
        <p>The mayor's proposal would impose fees on vehicles driving into the most congested parts of Manhattan on weekdays as part of an overall plan to improve air quality and ease traffic. Hanging in the balance is as much as $500 million in federal money that the Bush administration has said can be awarded if the state approves the mayor's plan by August.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer said on Tuesday that his understanding was that the state could qualify for federal assistance money even if all the details of the plan were not spelled out in any legislation that was passed. He said the United States transportation secretary, Mary E. Peters, had been ''very clear that she wanted to be confident that there would be a move towards congestion pricing if she were going to make those grants.''</p>
        <p>But, he added, ''it doesn't mean we need to resolve every last detail about implementation -- where the stoplights or the cameras would go, or what technology necessarily would be used.''</p>
        <p>His comments came as the mayor and the Assembly speaker, Sheldon Silver, a Democrat, continued to differ in their views, judging from comments the men made in separate interviews on radio station WROW in Albany on Tuesday morning.</p>
        <p>The mayor said the Legislature should move swiftly to pass the proposal by the end of the regular Legislative session on June 21.</p>
        <p>''If you can't do it by the 21st, or whenever they finish up this session, I don't know why you think you could do it later on,'' Mr. Bloomberg said. ''You're not going to learn anything else in a week or two.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Silver appeared to rule that out, saying ''I think it's unlikely that we can take action within the next week.''</p>
        <p>The governor has said that the issue would probably be taken up in a special session that he would call during the summer. Mr. Silver has not said that he would reject the proposal outright, and said he was open to taking it up in a special session.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Silver has already outlined a number of concerns, including the boundaries of the toll zone, the use of hundreds of cameras, and his fear that some neighborhoods would become commuter parking lots.</p>
        <p>He mentioned new worries on Tuesday, including doubts about whether the idea of using residential parking permits in some neighborhoods would be enough to prevent commuters from turning parts of the city into parking lots.</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver said that would just move the problem to neighborhoods without the residential permits.</p>
        <p>''I'm not trying to be negative,'' he added. ''I believe those are questions that ought to be considered.''</p>
        <p>In another sign of the uncertainty over the plan in Albany, the Senate deputy majority leader, Dean G. Skelos, a Long Island Republican, also said he did not think there was enough time left in the session to take the issue up in his chamber, either. That was something of a blow to Mr. Bloomberg, who has strong ties to Senate Republicans and is one of their biggest contributors. The Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, had the mayor's proposal introduced last week.</p>
        <p>''I think that there are a lot of questions,'' Mr. Skelos said. ''Obviously, the speaker has indicated that he has many concerns, as our conference does.''</p>
        <p>The mayor's plan, which is supported by a broad coalition of environmental groups, would impose an $8 fee on cars and a $21 fee on commercial trucks entering the part of Manhattan below 86th Street from 6 a.m. to 6 p.m. on weekdays.</p>
        <p>The mayor rebutted some of the speaker's concerns on Tuesday but was largely diplomatic in his comments.</p>
        <p>''I don't think the speaker or the majority leader have ever said they're against this; I think they said they have questions, and that's fine,'' Mr. Bloomberg said. ''That's their job.''</p>
        <p>The governor has endorsed the plan but has concerns about some of the details.</p>
        <p>''There are some implementation issues that have to be dealt with by the Legislature, should be dealt with, do not necessarily need to be dealt with in a piece of legislation that would be passed by the August or so deadline that the secretary of transportation has set,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The notion of approving the plan but leaving the details to be worked out later was rejected by one prominent opponent of the proposal.</p>
        <p>''We don't enact press releases and concepts,'' Assemblyman Richard Brodsky, a Westchester County Democrat, said. ''We enact laws.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
