<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Iraqis Are Failing to Meet Benchmarks Set by U.S.</title>
    <meta content="13benchmarks--iht" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/world/middleeast/13benchmarks-iht.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cave, Damien</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EEDF143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Iraqis Are Failing to Meet Benchmarks Set by U.S.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Iraqis Are Failing to Meet U.S. Benchmarks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMIEN CAVE; Reporting was contributed by Richard A. Oppel Jr., Abdul Razzaq al-Saiedi, Alissa J. Rubin and Michael R. Gordon.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cave, Damien</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, June 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iraq's leaders have failed to reach agreements on nearly every law that Americans have demanded as benchmarks and officials of both countries question whether any substantive laws will pass before end of year; Iraq's central government has become increasing irrelevant as competing groups within each faction work locally to obtain control; Iraq's political limitations complicate American mission, whose troop surge was to help promote political reconciliation; some question whether current benchmarks can ever halt cycle of violence; two stalled laws, regarding constitutional review and political purge of Baathists, highlight distrust undermining process; constitutional review committee soon gridlocked and said that disputes must be settled by political leadership; law designed to rehire low- to midlevel Baathists in effort to halt insurgency support has also stalled; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Iraq's political leaders have failed to reach agreements on nearly every law that the Americans have demanded as benchmarks, despite heavy pressure from Congress, the White House and top military commanders. With only three months until progress reports are due in Washington, the deadlock has reached a point where many Iraqi and American officials now question whether any substantive laws will pass before the end of the year.</p>
        <p>Kurds have blocked a vote in Parliament on a new oil law. Shiite clerics have stymied an American-backed plan for reintegrating former Baathists into government. Sunnis are demanding that a constitutional review include more power for the next president.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just three months before progress reports are due, Iraq’s leaders have failed to agree on nearly every key law.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Iraq's political leaders have failed to reach agreements on nearly every law that the Americans have demanded as benchmarks, despite heavy pressure from Congress, the White House and top military commanders. With only three months until progress reports are due in Washington, the deadlock has reached a point where many Iraqi and American officials now question whether any substantive laws will pass before the end of the year.</p>
        <p>Kurds have blocked a vote in Parliament on a new oil law. Shiite clerics have stymied an American-backed plan for reintegrating former Baathists into government. Sunnis are demanding that a constitutional review include more power for the next president.</p>
        <p>And even if one or two of the proposals are approved -- the oil law appears the most likely, officials said -- doubts are spreading about whether the current benchmarks can ever halt the cycle of violence gripping Iraq's communities.</p>
        <p>For the handful of party leaders with the power to make deals, the promise of compromise now carries less allure than the possibility for domination. Long-suppressed Shiites and Kurds now see total victory within their grasp. Previous American benchmarks like elections have failed to bring peace and, after four years of unfulfilled promises, bloodshed and sprawling chaos, once wary glances have become cold, unblinking stares.</p>
        <p>The same forces of entropy and obstinacy have also severed links between the party leaders and their constituencies. In Shiite areas of southern Iraq, Sunni areas of the west and for Kurds in the north, Iraq's central government has become increasingly irrelevant as competing groups within each faction maneuver at the local level for control of public money and jobs. In many cases, especially through mosques, Iran and other foreign powers often provide more institutional support than Baghdad.</p>
        <p>As Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki told an American military commander on Monday, ''There are two mentalities in this region, conspiracy and mistrust.''</p>
        <p>Iraq's political limitations raise difficult questions for the American project here. The initial mission for the increase of American troops was to create an atmosphere for political reconciliation. If broad-based compromises among the country's factions fail to emerge or have little impact, what comes next?</p>
        <p>Most Western political officials in Iraq and Washington publicly refuse to discuss a Plan B, but Iraqi leaders and some of those who work with them admit that their days are often filled with angst and frustration. Many have turned their attention toward risky local alliances with insurgents or former insurgents who say they will fight Al Qaeda. Even among the most hopeful, expectations have diminished.</p>
        <p>''Being here, you can't be optimistic until things happen,'' said Ashraf Qazi, the United Nations special representative for Iraq. He said that while a broad national reconciliation program based on a series of new laws might still be possible this year, a ''passing grade'' would be signs of building momentum.</p>
        <p>''There are no guarantees,'' he said. ''In fact, it would be overambitious to say all these things can be solved.''</p>
        <p>The challenges to reconciliation include the personal, the sectarian and the systemic. Two of the stalled laws -- regarding a constitutional review and de-Baathification -- highlight the distrust over the petty and profound disputes that have undermined the process.</p>
        <p>The Constitution</p>
        <p>The current Constitution is a product of the last ambitious American effort to inspire a grand compromise among Iraq's belligerent factions. Approved by a referendum in October 2005, it set the stage for elections and was widely praised by the White House, but it also failed to address many vital issues.</p>
        <p>There was so little agreement on how to share revenues -- with minority Sunnis fearing they would be left out -- that the charter even failed to give the government a right to collect taxes.</p>
        <p>Iraq's government formed a constitutional review committee in October to address potential amendments. The group was given four months to come up with recommendations for changes.</p>
        <p>Nicholas Haysom, a constitutional expert with the United Nations, worked closely with the committee. He said the group's 31 participants met regularly.</p>
        <p>''We felt there is an ethical commitment,'' said Sheik Humam Hamoudi, one of three committee chairmen and a member of the Supreme Islamic Iraqi Council, an influential Shiite group. ''We have a mission to accomplish.''</p>
        <p>The discussions soon turned to gridlock over a number of issues, including many of the same problems that arose during the last constitutional effort. Sunnis, Shiites and Kurds, for example, initially could not agree on how to divide revenues and responsibilities between the federal government and the regions. The future of oil-rich Kirkuk was left in limbo, with Kurds holding out for a referendum scheduled for the end of this year that they hope will grant them control.</p>
        <p>There were also bitter disputes over whether the Constitution should define Iraq as an Arab country, and whether the powers of the presidency should be expanded.</p>
        <p>As was the case with the original Constitution, the conflicts involved existential questions of Iraq's identity and more immediate struggles for power.</p>
        <p>Sunni demands for presidential strength have been particularly strong, lawmakers said, because with a Kurd, Jalal Talabani, currently president, Sunnis expect that the next president will be one of their own. Sunnis say broadening the executive branch would help Iraq when the prime minister fails to produce results.</p>
        <p>''Putting all the authorities in one hand, in one man, will be more dangerous than spreading it out,'' said Hussein al-Falluji, an attorney and member of Parliament with the Iraqi Consensus Front, the main Sunni bloc.</p>
        <p>The prime minister, not surprisingly, has interpreted the Sunni position as an affront. An aide to Mr. Maliki, who declined to be named because he was not authorized to speak to reporters, said the prime minister resented the way that Tariq al-Hashimi, the Sunni vice president, was undermining the country's parliamentary system by trying to secure additional power for the presidency, an unelected position.</p>
        <p>He said the prime minister's refusal to compromise was ''constitutional'' and ''practical.''</p>
        <p>With neither the presidency debate nor the question of Kirkuk resolved, the committee missed its original four-month deadline and a two-month extension. When it finally delivered a draft in May, it essentially passed the buck, saying that the disputed provisions must be handled by ''the political leadership in the country, to settle them for the interest of the nation and to guarantee rights to all parties.''</p>
        <p>Nearly a month later, the heads of Iraq's major political parties still have not met to discuss the Constitution.</p>
        <p>''Maybe they do not care about their responsibilities,'' Mr. Falluji said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Haysom and Mr. Qazi at the United Nations emphasized that the committee had made progress. They said there was widespread support for provisions establishing the primacy of the federal judiciary and a federal right to collect taxes and regulate ports, transportation and other national resources. But two major issues are outstanding, and other laws depend on a census that could assign revenues according to population, so no quick end is in sight.</p>
        <p>''We have not committed to doing it by September,'' Mr. Hamoudi said. ''Maybe the American Congress has made such a commitment, but we have not.''</p>
        <p>De-Baathification</p>
        <p>Ever since the Americans purged former members of the Baath Party of Saddam Hussein from Iraq's government soon after the 2003 invasion, they have been trying to reform their policy.</p>
        <p>Some changes were made in 2004, bringing back teachers and others with technical expertise, but the hope has been that a broader plan to rehire low- to midlevel Baathists would woo disaffected Sunni Arabs and drain the Sunni-led insurgency of support.</p>
        <p>The latest effort began this spring with the grandly titled Reconciliation and Accountability Law, a proposal backed by Ambassador Zalmay Khalilzad, the senior American envoy in Iraq until April. The draft decreed that all former Baathists who had worked in the government could collect their pensions. It opened government jobs to thousands more, and set a three-month time limit for Iraqi citizens to bring lawsuits against former members of the Baath Party.</p>
        <p>Sunnis supported the overhaul, and Shiites and Kurds were expected to fall in line after the Shiite prime minister and the Kurdish president announced the plan on March 26.</p>
        <p>But the law was stymied by Ahmad Chalabi, who headed Iraq's de-Baathification commission. Mr. Chalabi, the former Pentagon protégé, relies on the commission for an official role in Iraq's government. Having just renovated a spacious office in the Green Zone, he has strongly opposed any effort to weaken his position or the country's policy on former Baathists.</p>
        <p>According to a senior official with the commission, Mr. Chalabi and members of his organization sabotaged the American-backed plan by rallying opposition among Shiite government officials in southern Iraq, then taking their complaints to Grand Ayatollah Ali al-Sistani, Iraq's most powerful Shiite cleric.</p>
        <p>On April 1, Mr. Chalabi visited the ayatollah's office in Najaf. He later appeared at a news conference, declaring that Ayatollah Sistani told him the law was incomplete and that ''there would be other drafts.''</p>
        <p>A day later, an aide to the reclusive cleric confirmed that there was ''a general feeling of rejection'' about the proposal.</p>
        <p>Since then, the original draft has gone nowhere. The Americans have met with several groups responsible for additional drafts that address de-Baathification. Iraqi officials said they were working on a compromise law combining various elements of the American law and other proposals, primarily a softer alternative backed by Mr. Chalabi.</p>
        <p>But without clear support from Ayatollah Sistani, a final draft of the law has not been completed or introduced in Parliament.</p>
        <p>It remains unclear how much support the proposal could attract. Mr. Falluji, the Sunni lawmaker, said the prime minister did not fully support reconciliation with former Baathists -- a suspicion also harbored by some American officials. Some Sunnis currently in government have fallen afoul of Baathists and may not be eager to bring back members of the former government.</p>
        <p>Even if the law passes, it may not be enforced. In many provinces, officials have little respect for laws passed in the capital. In the southern city of Basra, the various Shiite parties have already divvied up the spoils of government: the Fadhila Party controls much of the oil industry and the border police are tied to the Supreme Islamic Iraqi Council, the party of Abdul Aziz al-Hakim.</p>
        <p>The Americans are seeking to hold provincial elections by the end of the year, but the proposal is also stalled, with some fearing that it would lead to more violence. Meanwhile, similar concerns about the weakness of the central government are hampering progress on other laws, particularly those involving government revenues.</p>
        <p>At one point during discussions over the constitutional review, the Americans offered a suggestion: that every check be signed by a Sunni, a Shiite and a Kurd, said Jabir Habeeb, a Shiite member of the constitutional review committee.</p>
        <p>The proposal, he said, was immediately dismissed as unworkable.</p>
        <p>THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
