<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Finally Admitting Killing, Man Finally Goes Free</title>
    <meta content="13mob" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/nyregion/13mob.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854175"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E4D6173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="828" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Finally Admitting Killing, Man Finally Goes Free</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Finally Admitting Killing, Man Finally Goes Free</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL BRICK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Carmine Carini had a decision to make. He was 47 years old. Nearly half that time he had spent in prison for the murder of a Brooklyn record shop owner, a man shot three times to the head and dumped from a car in the watermark style of a Mafia execution.</p>
        <p>In those 23 years, Mr. Carini's infant son had grown to a young man. His cousins, well-known Mafia assassins, had been murdered for bungling a job. Vigorous prosecution had diminished the city's organized-crime families. Halley's Comet had passed the Earth, a Democrat had held the White House for eight years and several new methods had been invented for the packaging of toothpaste. Through it all, Mr. Carini had failed on eight attempts to contest his sentence on procedural grounds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Carmine Carini had a decision to make. He was 47 years old. Nearly half that time he had spent in prison for the murder of a Brooklyn record shop owner, a man shot three times to the head and dumped from a car in the watermark style of a Mafia execution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Carmine Carini had a decision to make. He was 47 years old. Nearly half that time he had spent in prison for the murder of a Brooklyn record shop owner, a man shot three times to the head and dumped from a car in the watermark style of a Mafia execution.</p>
        <p>In those 23 years, Mr. Carini's infant son had grown to a young man. His cousins, well-known Mafia assassins, had been murdered for bungling a job. Vigorous prosecution had diminished the city's organized-crime families. Halley's Comet had passed the Earth, a Democrat had held the White House for eight years and several new methods had been invented for the packaging of toothpaste. Through it all, Mr. Carini had failed on eight attempts to contest his sentence on procedural grounds.</p>
        <p>But when a judge vacated the murder conviction last month, ruling that new testimony from two Mafia cooperating witnesses would most likely change the outcome of a new trial, prosecutors offered a deal.</p>
        <p>''If he confesses, he goes free,'' said Mr. Carini's lawyer, Ronald L. Kuby. ''If he maintains his innocence, he goes back to jail and faces life in prison.''</p>
        <p>After thinking it over for a month, Mr. Carini chose yesterday to confess and go free. In State Supreme Court in Brooklyn, he pleaded guilty to manslaughter and accepted a sentence of 7 to 21 years in prison, time he had already served. But before he was allowed to leave, Mr. Carini was required to acknowledge his role in the crime. For this he swore to tell the truth, a common though not universal condition in a plea-bargain hearing.</p>
        <p>In all his years in prison, Mr. Carini had maintained that he played no role in the killing. Prosecutors have said that the record shop owner, Verdi Kaja, had business dealings with Mr. Carini's cousins, Vincent and Eddie Carini. Mr. Kaja was summoned to a car and shot dead on Nov. 18, 1983. Carmine Carini was convicted of murder, described by prosecutors as being both the gunman and driver. Prosecutors said he later warned the victim's family not to talk to the police.</p>
        <p>After his efforts to contest the case on technicalities failed, Mr. Carini received a windfall in 2004. Two Mafia witnesses under federal protection told their handlers that Vincent Carini had confessed to the killing, lamenting his cousin's conviction. Federal prosecutors passed on that information to state prosecutors, who passed it on to Mr. Carini, who renewed his efforts, aided by Mr. Kuby; his assistant, David Pressman, and a private investigator, Lawrence Frost. Last month, a judge overturned the conviction, ordering Mr. Carini held in $500,000 bail to stand trial again.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors were not convinced of Mr. Carini's innocence, but impugning the federal cooperating witnesses seemed a delicate proposition. The case fell to an assistant district attorney, Anna-Sigga Nicolazzi, who was admitted to the bar more than a decade after Mr. Carini was admitted to state prison.</p>
        <p>In court, Ms. Nicolazzi said she was ready to retry the murder charge, arguing that no matter who had pulled the trigger, the state's eyewitnesses still placed Carmine Carini in the car.</p>
        <p>In court yesterday, Ms. Nicolazzi thumbed through a gossamer yellow sheaf of papers, an indictment that appeared well-acquainted with the inside of a filing cabinet. Mr. Carini, his hair gray and thinning, his hands cuffed behind his back, grinned and winked at his family.</p>
        <p>He sat and listened as other defendants considered their guilty pleas. A man acknowledged practicing law without a license. A woman declined to admit beating her child, choosing instead to face trial.</p>
        <p>''Added to the calendar,'' called the clerk, reciting an indictment number ending with the year 1984.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carini stepped forward, as did his prosecutor.</p>
        <p>''We are ready to proceed,'' Ms. Nicolazzi said. ''We have spoken to the witnesses, who still maintain their position strongly.''</p>
        <p>But to spare the victim's family a new trial, she said, prosecutors would accept a guilty plea for the negotiated sentence.</p>
        <p>Then Justice Neil Jon Firetog asked Mr. Carini: ''What kind of weapon did you use?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Carini hesitated. His lawyer, Mr. Kuby, chose this language: ''The record indicates a handgun was used.''</p>
        <p>The judge told him that was not good enough, saying: ''Are you taking the plea?''</p>
        <p>Asked again what kind of weapon he had used, Mr. Carini said: ''Ah, a handgun.''</p>
        <p>That was that.</p>
        <p>''The defendant is released at this time,'' Justice Firetog said. ''Good luck to you. Next case.''</p>
        <p>After a round of applause from his family in the gallery and four hours of paperwork, Mr. Carini emerged from the courtroom in jeans and a white T-shirt, revealing a flower tattoo inscribed ''Mother'' and ''Father.''</p>
        <p>He posed for pictures, declared himself ready for a home-cooked meal and said he felt ''very good.''</p>
        <p>''A lot of things,'' he said, had factored into his decision, including ''probably the legal fees and just waiting to get out of jail and get it over with.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
