<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Loser, Loser Burning Bright In the Grim Helsinki Night</title>
    <meta content="13dusk" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/movies/13dusk.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854125"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaurismaki, Aki</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hyytiainen, Janne</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Lights in the Dusk (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Finland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Finland/Helsinki</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Finland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Helsinki (Finland)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Kaurismaki, Aki</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Lights in the Dusk (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E7D7173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Loser, Loser Burning Bright In the Grim Helsinki Night</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Loser, Loser Burning Bright in the Grim Helsinki Night</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews film Lights in the Dusk, written and directed by Aki Kaurismaki; Janne Hyytiainen stars; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A mood of cosmic desolation seeps like late autumn sunlight filtered through clouds in ''Lights in the Dusk,'' the Finnish filmmaker Aki Kaurismaki's haunting meditation on the downward spiral of a solitary loser in contemporary Helsinki. This hapless everyman, Koistinen (Janne Hyytiainen), a night watchman for a security company, patrols a block of stores that include a fancy jewelry shop ripe for burglary.</p>
        <p>Koistinen, who dreams of running his own security operation, leads a life of continual humiliation. His colleagues ridicule him for not having a girlfriend. He receives suspicious, hostile glances when shopping in the supermarket. When seeking a bank loan, he shows his trade school diploma and the officer sneers, ''Are you some sort of comedian?'' before dismissing him as ''trash.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A mood of cosmic desolation seeps like late autumn sunlight filtered through clouds in Aki Kaurismaki’s “Lights in the Dusk.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A mood of cosmic desolation seeps like late autumn sunlight filtered through clouds in ''Lights in the Dusk,'' the Finnish filmmaker Aki Kaurismaki's haunting meditation on the downward spiral of a solitary loser in contemporary Helsinki. This hapless everyman, Koistinen (Janne Hyytiainen), a night watchman for a security company, patrols a block of stores that include a fancy jewelry shop ripe for burglary.</p>
        <p>Koistinen, who dreams of running his own security operation, leads a life of continual humiliation. His colleagues ridicule him for not having a girlfriend. He receives suspicious, hostile glances when shopping in the supermarket. When seeking a bank loan, he shows his trade school diploma and the officer sneers, ''Are you some sort of comedian?'' before dismissing him as ''trash.''</p>
        <p>An obvious mark for sharp-eyed predators, Koistinen is spotted in a bar one evening by Lindholm (Ilkka Koivula), a lean, slick-haired gangster in cahoots with Russian mobsters. Observing Koistinen being rebuffed by a woman at the bar, then bullied by her date, Lindholm recognizes him as a type: ''a sentimental fool,'' as he puts it, with the loyalty of a dog.</p>
        <p>He sics his girlfriend, Mirja (Maria Jarvenhelmi), a blond bombshell with a resemblance to Gwen Stefani, on Koistinen with instructions to flirt with him and gain the jewelry store's security codes. Lindholm theorizes that even after Mirja has betrayed Koistinen, the sucker will remain loyal to her out of some quaint sense of chivalry.</p>
        <p>This buffeted nobody suggests a contemporary version of Chaplin's Little Tramp. Koistinen accepts the cruelties dished out by life with taciturnity, almost as if they were his due. On the rare occasions that he ineptly lashes back, he is immediately slapped down, and several times he is beaten up.</p>
        <p>''Lights in the Dusk'' is too hard-headed a movie to be a sentimental tribute to the persecuted little guy with integrity in a cold, corrupt world. To some degree it shares Lindholm's opinion that Koistinen is a fool. Like all of Mr. Kaurismaki's films, it tempers its lyricism with an undertone of gallows humor, more muted here than in earlier films, but still palpable.</p>
        <p>This movie is the third of a series the director has called his ''Loser Trilogy.'' The first film, ''Drifting Clouds,'' focused on unemployment, and the second, ''The Man Without a Past,'' examined homelessness. ''Lights in the Dusk'' is a portrait of loneliness. A sense of aching distance and isolation is palpable in every frame of the film, which portrays Helsinki as a bleak, shadowy Edward Hopper cityscape. (Specific visual reference is even made to Hopper's 1942 painting ''Nighthawks.'')</p>
        <p>The actor playing Koistinen resembles the young Mickey Rourke with the stuffing knocked out of him. But under his blank facade, his hope never dies. His yearning is expressed on the soundtrack by old recordings of the great Swedish tenor Jussi Bjoerling singing Puccini arias.</p>
        <p>This spare, minimalist film is not realistic. It has the simplicity of a silent movie, and the blocking of the actors, especially in the scenes with Koistinen and Mirja, emphasizes the distances between them. In one scene they are photographed silently sitting side by side, gazing blankly in front of them. When he takes her to an action-adventure film, she stares impassively at the screen while he turns his head and gazes at her like a shy, worshipful fan.</p>
        <p>Timo Salminen's exquisite cinematography renders Helsinki a place of endless sadness, in which the sun, grazing the horizon far to the south, casts snaking shadows on the streets, and the warehouses and factories around the harbor suggest a labyrinthine fortress of gloom. The entire city seems peopled with cold, unsmiling sadists like the loan officer, who will seize any opportunity to step on those below them on the social ladder.</p>
        <p>The most sympathetic figure, Aila (Maria Heiskanen), is a plain young woman, as isolated as Koistinen, who operates a mobile food van near his shabby apartment. In their conversations she subtly indicates her longing for him, but he doesn't notice.</p>
        <p>When he shows up drunk at the van one evening, she patiently helps him home. Under her poker-faced stoicism is the rarest quality to be found in Helsinki: a reservoir of kindness.</p>
        <p>Lights in the Dusk  Opens today in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Written (in Finnish, with English subtitles), produced, directed and edited by Aki Kaurismaki; director of photography, Timo Salminen; set design, Markku Patila; released by Strand Releasing. At the IFC Center, 323 Avenue of the Americas, at Third Street, Greenwich Village. Running time: 78 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: Janne Hyytiainen (Koistinen), Maria Jarvenhelmi (Mirja), Maria Heiskanen (Aila) and Ilkka Koivula (Lindholm).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
