<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Europe Plans A Quieter And Cleaner Passenger Jet</title>
    <meta content="13air" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/business/worldbusiness/13air.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854180"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Airbus Industrie</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rolls-Royce Plc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Saab Ab</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Thales</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dassault Systemes</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Eurocopter</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Castle, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <org class="online_producer">European Union</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE1D6173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="539" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Europe Plans A Quieter And Cleaner Passenger Jet</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Europe Plans a Quieter and Cleaner Passenger Jet</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN CASTLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Castle, Stephen</byline>
      <dateline>BRUSSELS, June 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>European Union is planning 1.6 billion-euro public-private partnership to help its aviation industry develop generation of greener and quieter aircraft; European officials say project, known as Clean Sky and costing equivalent of $2.1 billion, will bring vast economic benefits and offset impact of huge growth in air travel by cutting jet carbon emissions by 20 percent to 40 percent in coming decades and reducing jet noise; most of leading European aviation companies have agreed to contribute to project, including Airbus, Rolls-Royce, Saab, Thales, Dassault and Eurocopter, along with universities and research institutes; public contribution will require approval from European Union member states (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Driven by concerns that it is falling behind on airplane development, the European Union is planning a 1.6 billion-euro public-private partnership to help its aviation industry develop a generation of greener and quieter aircraft.</p>
        <p>European officials say the project, known as Clean Sky and costing the equivalent of $2.1 billion, will bring vast economic benefits and offset the impact of huge growth in air travel by cutting jet carbon emissions by 20 percent to 40 percent in the coming decades and reducing jet noise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The European Union is planning a public-private partnership to help its aviation industry develop greener and quieter aircraft.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Driven by concerns that it is falling behind on airplane development, the European Union is planning a 1.6 billion-euro public-private partnership to help its aviation industry develop a generation of greener and quieter aircraft.</p>
        <p>European officials say the project, known as Clean Sky and costing the equivalent of $2.1 billion, will bring vast economic benefits and offset the impact of huge growth in air travel by cutting jet carbon emissions by 20 percent to 40 percent in the coming decades and reducing jet noise.</p>
        <p>The use of 800 million euros in European Union money, however, may revive tensions with Washington, which, on the behalf of Boeing, has fought a long-running battle at the World Trade Organization over charges of illegal public support to the aircraft maker Airbus.</p>
        <p>A document, likely to be approved Wednesday by the European Commission, states that the European Union needs to provide public financing if it is not to fall behind other markets.</p>
        <p>''Not launching Clean Sky soon will put the European industry in a position of competitive disadvantage, with negative repercussions not only for the industry itself but also for the E.U. as a whole,'' it says.</p>
        <p>The paper emphasizes that the United States has a similar effort, the National Aeronautics Research and Development Policy, and that it is likely to continue unabated.</p>
        <p>''At the same time,'' the paper said, ''other competitors have emerged in recent years, such as Brazil, Russia, China and India.''</p>
        <p>Under the European Union plan, the industry would contribute 800 million euros for Clean Sky from 2008 to 2014. Most of the leading European aviation companies have agreed to contribute to the project, including Airbus, Rolls-Royce, Saab, Thales, Dassault and Eurocopter, along with universities and research institutes.</p>
        <p>The public contribution will require approval from European Union member states. The project has support from countries like Britain, which is usually skeptical about big European Union projects, like the troubled satellite navigation program Galileo.</p>
        <p>The money will go to six main projects, including development of a greener engine, creation of a ''smart'' fixed wing that will change position during flight to make it more energy efficient, and use of lighter materials as substitutes for metal.</p>
        <p>The European Union says ''market failures'' make public money essential. It argues that aeronautics programs are a high risk commercially and technically because they deliver returns long after the original investment.</p>
        <p>''The United States are going through with the same thing,'' said Marco Brusati, project officer at the European Commission, ''and we have to keep up the pace, but the areas we have focused on most are the development of environmental technologies.''</p>
        <p>Though Airbus will stand to gain around 12 percent of the budget, most of the money will be spent on the development of technologies, not of specific models, Mr. Brusati said.</p>
        <p>''This will contribute to a new generation of aircraft which will have a more environmentally friendly approach,'' he added.</p>
        <p>According to projections by the European Commission, the new technology could cut airline carbon by 20 to 40 percent, leading to a reduction of two billion to three billion tons from 2015 to 2050. Nitrogen oxide emissions could be cut by 40 to 60 percent and ''perceived aircraft noise'' could be halved.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
