<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giuliani Sets Forth a Dozen Priorities for His Presidency</title>
    <meta content="13giuliani" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/us/politics/13giuliani.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854162"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2008 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE7D6173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="624" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giuliani Sets Forth a Dozen Priorities for His Presidency</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Giuliani Sets Forth a Dozen Priorities for His Presidency</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC SANTORA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Santora, Marc</byline>
      <dateline>BEDFORD, N.H., June 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rudolph W. Giuliani on Tuesday outlined what he said would be the 12 major priorities of his presidency, among them fighting terrorism, cutting taxes, achieving energy independence and, in a new theme for him, overhauling the education system.</p>
        <p>''These are the 12 things that I believe will change the way we look at this campaign,'' Mr. Giuliani said in a speech to a group of New Hampshirites in this Manchester suburb, where he accused Democrats of wanting to ''look in the rearview mirror'' and take the country back to the 1990s. ''We are going to lay out a mission of reform and change,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Among the priorities of Rudolph W. Giuliani were achieving energy independence and, in a new theme for him, overhauling the education system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rudolph W. Giuliani on Tuesday outlined what he said would be the 12 major priorities of his presidency, among them fighting terrorism, cutting taxes, achieving energy independence and, in a new theme for him, overhauling the education system.</p>
        <p>''These are the 12 things that I believe will change the way we look at this campaign,'' Mr. Giuliani said in a speech to a group of New Hampshirites in this Manchester suburb, where he accused Democrats of wanting to ''look in the rearview mirror'' and take the country back to the 1990s. ''We are going to lay out a mission of reform and change,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani has often been faulted for the turmoil and lack of progress in the New York school system during his years as mayor. And while in New Hampshire several months ago, he acknowledged that education was one area where he had not achieved the kind of change he had hoped.</p>
        <p>The clearest indication of what is wrong in the educational system, he said Tuesday, can be seen in the failure of primary and secondary education when compared with college education. Higher education, he said, is driven by the choices of students and parents, while public education is based on a ''monopoly model.''</p>
        <p>''This system is overwhelmed with bureaucrats,'' he said, adding that in coming months he would more clearly define how parents can be given more choice.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, fighting terrorism was at the top of the list that Mr. Giuliani offered Tuesday. But noticeably absent from the speech was any mention of the war in Iraq, likely to be the central challenge for any new president.</p>
        <p>Asked afterward about the omission, the candidate said Iraq must be viewed in the context of a broader fight against terrorism. It was not dealt with singly in the speech, he said, because the fluid situation there makes it hard to speak in specifics about the war.</p>
        <p>''What I was trying to do was to look at the things, as best as you can predict it now, that are going to be there a year and a half from now,'' he said. ''Iraq may get better; Iraq may get worse. We may be successful in Iraq; we may not be. I don't know the answer to that. That's in the hands of other people. But what we do know for sure is the terrorists are going to be at war with us a year, a year and a half from now.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani also detailed some of his thoughts on health care -- a central issue for Democrats -- saying his goal was to try to give more control to consumers. Instead of employer-based insurance or, as some Democrats have proposed, government-mandated insurance, he favors a $15,000 tax exemption that taxpayers would use toward the purchase of their own policies. (Those too poor to benefit from the exemption would receive some kind of voucher from the government.)</p>
        <p>The consumer could decide how much to spend on the insurance policy, keeping anything left over for either a health savings account or investment in a retirement fund. Critics have said this incentive to buy cheap policies offering little coverage for preventive care would lead patients to visit the doctor only after becoming very ill and would therefore ultimately place a greater burden on the health care system.</p>
        <p>The other priorities that Mr. Giuliani listed in his speech were ending illegal immigration, restoring fiscal discipline, improving accountability in Washington, increasing the number of adoptions as a way of reducing abortions, reforming the legal system and appointing ''strict constructionist'' judges, preparing the nation for natural disasters as well as terrorist attacks, and making America more competitive in the global marketplace while improving its image.</p>
        <p>THE 2008 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
