<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Chinese Company Fights Its French Partner</title>
    <meta content="13danone" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/business/worldbusiness/13danone.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854181"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Groupe Danone</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wahaha Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barboza, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kanter, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zong Qinghou</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Groupe Danone</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Wahaha Group</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE1D6173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1173" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Chinese Company Fights Its French Partner</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Chinese Company Fights Its French Partner</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARBOZA and JAMES KANTER; David Barboza reported from Hangzhou, and James Kanter reported from Paris.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barboza, David; Kanter, James</byline>
      <dateline>HANGZHOU, China, June 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dispute between Groupe Danone and Wahaha Group's chairman Zong Qinghou has escalated into battle for control of country's largest beverage maker; fight started in 2005, when executives at Danone say they noticed something peculiar in financial figures coming from their joint venture in China with Wahaha; Danone discovered that Zong was operating series of secret companies outside joint venture, companies that were mimicking joint venture and siphoning off millions of dollars; Danone has filed lawsuit in California against company controlled by Zong's relatives; analysts say Wahaha dispute is reminder of pitfalls that foreign companies face when doing business in China; case detailed; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A dispute between Groupe Danone, the French multinational company, and a brash Chinese executive has escalated into a battle for control of the country's largest beverage maker.</p>
        <p>The fight started in 2005, when executives at Danone say that they noticed something peculiar in the financial figures coming from their joint venture here with the Wahaha Group.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A dispute between Groupe Danone and a Chinese executive has escalated into a battle for control of China’s largest beverage maker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A dispute between Groupe Danone, the French multinational company, and a brash Chinese executive has escalated into a battle for control of the country's largest beverage maker.</p>
        <p>The fight started in 2005, when executives at Danone say that they noticed something peculiar in the financial figures coming from their joint venture here with the Wahaha Group.</p>
        <p>After a long investigation, Danone officials concluded that their closest partner in China, Wahaha's longtime chairman, Zong Qinghou, was operating a series of secret companies outside the joint venture -- companies that were mimicking the joint venture and siphoning off millions of dollars.</p>
        <p>Last week, after months of negotiation between Danone and Mr. Zong had failed to resolve the dispute over those companies and who has the rights to the Wahaha brand, Danone filed a lawsuit in California against a company controlled by Mr. Zong's relatives.</p>
        <p>That lawsuit has escalated the quarrel into nasty and, at times, bizarre territory.</p>
        <p>Analysts say that the Wahaha dispute is a reminder of the pitfalls that foreign companies face when doing business in China.</p>
        <p>''This is a cautionary tale,'' says Steve Dickinson, a lawyer in Shanghai at Harris &amp; Moure. ''This is not a message that you can't do business in China. But if you come to China and let the Chinese run the business without supervision, they can do this kind of thing.''</p>
        <p>Of course, Danone officials acknowledge that they took a risk on Mr. Zong, who is known for his brash management style. But they also say that the 61-year-old entrepreneur helped transform Wahaha into one of China's most successful beverage makers, a company that had sales of more than $1.5 billion last year.</p>
        <p>Now, however, Danone is trying to figure out how to deal with what suddenly looks like a corporate revolt at Wahaha.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zong, who founded Wahaha in the 1980s and is one of China's wealthiest businessmen, angrily resigned as chairman last Wednesday, disputing Danone's contentions about secret companies. He said that he could no longer deal with what he called Danone's harassment and smear campaign against him and his family.</p>
        <p>Two days later, Wahaha -- 51 percent of it owned by Danone -- released a series of harshly worded letters from employees that accused Danone officials of ignorance and bullying.</p>
        <p>In one of the letters, which Wahaha said represented large groups of employees, the workers vowed to standby ''Chairman Zong'' and to punish Danone's ''evil deeds.''</p>
        <p>And then, over the weekend, Wahaha issued a statement saying the company's management and staff ''strongly disapprove'' of two directors appointed by Danone.</p>
        <p>Wahaha officials declined to comment.</p>
        <p>But at a press conference in Shanghai on Tuesday, Danone officials defended their actions and said that they were working to resolve the dispute.</p>
        <p>Emmanuel Faber, the head of Danone's Asia operations, said he was worried that Mr. Zong might attempt to destroy the Wahaha brand and start his own competing company, absorbing Wahaha units.</p>
        <p>Danone said in a statement, ''We think that it is inappropriate for anyone to seek to leverage employees, business partners and the public to support their goal of maximizing their own personal wealth while endangering the business continuity of the company.''</p>
        <p>The series of statements raises another question: who is running Wahaha? Mr. Zong has run the company with for more than 20 years, controlling many aspects of the business.</p>
        <p>Danone says it still has contact with Wahaha. But the French company also acknowledges that it does not have a single executive based at Wahaha's headquarters in Hangzhou and that Danone officers never played a role in the day-to-day operations of the joint venture.</p>
        <p>The boardroom drama has cast a dark cloud over Wahaha, a beverage company known for its popular children's drinks, fruit juices and bottled water.</p>
        <p>According to Danone, most of the problems are tied to Mr. Zong. Danone says that he and several of his family members began operating a series of parallel companies sometime after 2003.</p>
        <p>In 2005, Danone says, illegal Wahaha-related companies began expanding aggressively, manufacturing a growing share of the company's products.</p>
        <p>In late 2006, after Danone says that it discovered the parallel companies, Mr. Zong agreed to sell a majority stake in those companies to Danone, which intended to fold them into the joint venture.</p>
        <p>But after signing the agreement, Danone says that Mr. Zong pulled out of the deal and then began creating more mirror companies, including his own separate sales division.</p>
        <p>Those moves, Danone say, prompted the company to file a lawsuit in California last week against a group of corporations in the British Virgin Islands that were registered by Mr. Zong's wife and daughter, who have run some of the mirror companies and list California as their residence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zong has fought back in public. In a letter posted on the Internet last week, Mr. Zong said that Danone officials were fully aware of the outside companies, that they were partly financed by company employees and that Danone wanted to acquire them cheaply.</p>
        <p>Whether the local Hangzhou government, which owns a stake in Wahaha, will step in is unclear.</p>
        <p>But analysts who follow Danone are worried about how the dispute will affect the company's bottom line and its future growth in China.</p>
        <p>''If this was settled over a period of months, then it would have been all right for Danone,'' said Cedric Lecasble, an analyst with Kepler Equities in Paris. ''But things have been going in the wrong direction. The situation has turned out to be tougher than I could have imagined.''</p>
        <p>Some analysts are even questioning why Danone did not have better supervision of Mr. Zong and Wahaha if it thought Mr. Zong was stealing from the company.</p>
        <p>''This was a great business Danone had in China, and over time it was going to give them an awful lot of growth, perhaps 10 to 15 percent each year over the next five years,'' said Jeremy Fialko, an analyst at ABN Amro bank in London. ''The joint venture is a very practical business model, but you've got to be cognizant of the risks involved.''</p>
        <p>However, Mr. Faber, the head of Danone's Asia operations, suggested that the fraud began slowly and picked up in 2005 and then accelerated again after the negotiations with Mr. Zong broke down last December. In February, Danone says, it discovered that even more secret companies had been established.</p>
        <p>Asked whether Danone's oversight of the joint venture was typical, Mr. Faber called it a ''fairly unusual or unique case.''</p>
        <p>But, Mr. Faber added: ''Wahaha is what it is today because Danone was able to take the risk of letting Mr. Zong run the show. This man created a great company. But he has not been very rational recently.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Faber says that Danone is hoping to find a solution that allows both sides to benefit now.</p>
        <p>''At the end of the day, we want a fair share of the pie,'' he said. ''We don't want to destroy the pie.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
