<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kibbe Raw (Good) and Cooked (Better)</title>
    <meta content="13appe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854104"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="A GOOD APPETITE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE5D8173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="905" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kibbe Raw (Good) and Cooked (Better)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Melissa Clark</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOST of the time, my husband, Daniel, is an eager accomplice when it comes to my more outré culinary cravings. He has gamely sampled braised chicken feet in Chinatown, crispy tripe tacos in Hell's Kitchen and even the deep-fried Gummi octopuses I made one afternoon in an oil-ridden frenzy. But when it came to raw lamb kibbe for dinner, he put the kibosh on my plan.</p>
        <p>''I was actually hoping for something cooked,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOST of the time, my husband, Daniel, is an eager accomplice when it comes to my more outré culinary cravings. He has gamely sampled braised chicken feet in Chinatown, crispy tripe tacos in Hell's Kitchen and even the deep-fried Gummi octopuses I made one afternoon in an oil-ridden frenzy. But when it came to raw lamb kibbe for dinner, he put the kibosh on my plan.</p>
        <p>''I was actually hoping for something cooked,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Having already bought the ingredients for kibbe -- freshly ground lamb, bulgur, onions and spices -- I'll admit that I wasn't prepared for the veto. But isn't marriage often about compromise?</p>
        <p>The easiest thing, of course, would be to simply fry up the mixture. According to my prime source, ''The Arab Table'' by May S. Bsisu (William Morrow, 2005), kibbe, the national dish of both Lebanon and Syria, is as malleable as Silly Putty. It can be served raw or cooked, hot or cold. It can be formed into sheets, patties, balls or miniature footballs and broiled, grilled, baked, fried or poached. You can stuff it with pine nuts and fried onions. You can drizzle it with yogurt sauce or hummus.</p>
        <p>Since I didn't have any pine nuts, I decided to skip the stuffing entirely. Besides, once I came to terms with the idea of cooking the lamb mixture, my heart was set on forming it into football shapes. Stuffing the footballs seemed like too much to undertake on a weeknight. Ditto the hummus, though a yogurt sauce seemed possible.</p>
        <p>I chose broiling as a cooking method since it was the easiest and least messy way to attain a crisp golden crust. If I couldn't have soft, supple, raw lamb, crunchy seemed like the next best way to go.</p>
        <p>After reading through myriad recipes, both from Ms. Bsisu's book and online, I realized that if raw kibbe is the steak tartare of the Middle East, cooked kibbe is the meatball (with bulgur replacing the bread crumbs).</p>
        <p>But here's where the recipes diverged. Some called for soaking the bulgur in water for hours before mixing with the meat, some called for a quick soak, and still others called for rinsing it in several changes of water. I opted for a quick soak; all that rinsing seemed fussy.</p>
        <p>The bulgur soaked while I chopped the onion and stirred up the yogurt sauce. Then I drained the bulgur in a fine sieve and mixed it into the meat.</p>
        <p>The last addition was the salt and spices. This was the fun part. Usually, when you're working with ground meat you don't taste it raw, especially when pork and beef are involved. But since I had planned to eat the kibbe uncooked in the first place, I figured tasting was not only perfectly fine, but a well deserved hors d'oeuvre. So I nibbled away, tweaking the balance of salt, sweetness from the cinnamon and allspice, muskiness from the cumin and heat from the chili powder. Once the meat was seasoned to perfection, I kept tasting because I couldn't quite make myself stop.</p>
        <p>But remembering that my husband wanted dinner too, I formed what was left of the pink meat into footballs and ran them under the broiler. They emerged mahogany brown with crackling crusts. We devoured what precious few I hadn't eaten as tartare, dipping them in the garlicky, herb-flecked yogurt sauce. Much as I loved the raw kibbe, the broiled were even better -- rich, brawny and deeply fragrant from the warmed spices.</p>
        <p>''These are amazing,'' Daniel said, licking his fork. ''But how come you made such a small batch?''</p>
        <p>Lamb and Bulgur Kibbe With Garlic Yogurt Sauce  Time: 40 minutes</p>
        <p>1 cup bulgur  2 cups plain Greek yogurt  2 tablespoons chopped dill or basil or cilantro, more for garnish  1 large garlic clove, minced  1 3/4 teaspoons kosher salt, more to taste  2 pounds ground lamb or beef  1 onion, chopped  1 teaspoon ground cumin  3/4 teaspoon ground allspice  3/4 teaspoon ground cinnamon  1/2 teaspoon freshly ground black pepper  1/8 teaspoon Aleppo pepper or a pinch of cayenne  4 tablespoons olive oil  Rice or pita or other bread, for serving  Sliced tomatoes and cucumbers (optional).</p>
        <p>1. Put bulgur in a bowl and cover with plenty of cold water. Let soak for 20 minutes.  2. Meanwhile, in a bowl, stir together the yogurt, herbs, garlic and 1/4 teaspoon salt. Chill. Position a broiler rack about 3 inches from heat source and preheat broiler.  3. In a large bowl, combine lamb, onion and spices and remaining 11/2 teaspoons salt. Drain bulgur in a fine sieve, pressing down hard and squeezing to eliminate as much water as possible. Add to lamb mixture and mix very well with your hands.  4. Pour oil onto a large jellyroll pan or rimmed baking sheet. Using your hands, form lamb mixture into 2-inch-long footballs and rest each one on baking sheet. When all footballs are formed, roll them in oil, coating them all around.  5. Broil kibbe until well browned on one side, about 8 minutes. Roll them over and broil until browned on other side, 4 to 6 minutes longer.  6. Taste yogurt sauce and add more salt if needed. Serve kibbe with sauce (drizzle it on top, or dip kibbe into it) and rice or bread, and tomatoes and cucumbers if desired. Garnish with more herbs.  Yield: 4 to 6 servings.</p>
        <p>A GOOD APPETITE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
