<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. Tribunal Sentences Serb To 35 Years For War Crimes</title>
    <meta content="13hague" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/world/europe/13hague.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854146"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia and Montenegro</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Krajina (Croatia)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simons, Marlise</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martic, Milan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Croatia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Croatia/Zagreb</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Croatia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Croatia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Zagreb (Croatia)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Serbia</location>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Martic, Milan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06EFD7173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="482" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. Tribunal Sentences Serb To 35 Years For War Crimes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">War Crimes Tribunal Sentences Serb to 35 Years</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Simons, Marlise</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Nations war crimes court established to hear cases from former Yugoslavia finds Milan Martic, former henchman of president Slobodan Milosevic, guilty of multiple war crimes and sentences him to 35 years in prison; Martic was important political figure of Serbian ministate of Krajina (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United Nations war crimes court established to hear cases from the former Yugoslavia found a former henchman of president Slobodan Milosevic guilty on Tuesday of multiple crimes while leading a Serbian separatist rebellion and handed down a sentence of 35 years.</p>
        <p>Milan Martic, 52, listened motionless as the three judges called him ''one of the most important and influential political figures'' of the Serbian ministate of Krajina, which broke off from Croatia in the early 1990s as Yugoslavia fell apart.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Judges in The Hague found Milan Martic, who led a Serbian separatist rebellion in Croatia in the early 1990s, guilty of multiple crimes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United Nations war crimes court established to hear cases from the former Yugoslavia found a former henchman of president Slobodan Milosevic guilty on Tuesday of multiple crimes while leading a Serbian separatist rebellion and handed down a sentence of 35 years.</p>
        <p>Milan Martic, 52, listened motionless as the three judges called him ''one of the most important and influential political figures'' of the Serbian ministate of Krajina, which broke off from Croatia in the early 1990s as Yugoslavia fell apart.</p>
        <p>They convicted Mr. Martic of crimes against humanity, including murder, persecution and torture of Croatian civilians, and of war crimes, including plunder and wanton destruction of civilian sites, churches, schools and entire villages. The campaign to drive non-Serbs out of Krajina caused hundreds of deaths and created tens of thousands of refugees.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martic was also found guilty of ordering an unjustified two-day rocket attack on the Croatian capital, Zagreb, in 1995. In the days after the attacks, Mr. Martic boasted to reporters that he had given the orders.</p>
        <p>The defense had demanded an acquittal and described Mr. Martic as a hero and a protector of the Serbian population, while prosecutors had pressed for a life sentence.</p>
        <p>The 35-year prison term is high by the standards of the tribunal, which has completed proceedings against more than 100 of those accused. Mr. Martic has already been in detention for five years, since he surrendered to the tribunal in 2002. But the judges gave him little credit for turning himself in, because by then he had been on the run for seven years, they wrote.</p>
        <p>During his 13-month trial, Mr. Martic, a former policeman and an ardent Serbian nationalist, showed no remorse. He tried to justify the violent actions of the police and paramilitary groups he directed as minister of defense and minister of the interior and eventually as president of the self-styled republic of Krajina.</p>
        <p>The ministate, which occupied one-third of Croatia, lasted from 1991 to 1995, when the Croatian military, backed by American advisers, restored Zagreb's control.</p>
        <p>The judgment also cited the Serbian leadership in Belgrade for planning a Greater Serbia to include all ethnic Serbs, of which Krajina was to have been a part. Belgrade sent funds, supplies and forces to the Krajina separatists.</p>
        <p>Evidence had established that Slobodan Milosevic, who died shortly before his four-year trial at the tribunal ended, ''covertly'' intended to seize control of swaths of land in Bosnia and Croatia, the judgment said, by using paramilitary groups to provoke violence, after which the Belgrade army would intervene to secure and unify the territories.</p>
        <p>The plan eventually failed after intervention from the West. But the judgment said Mr. Martic was a key part of that plan. It quoted Mr. Martic as saying in 1994 that he would ''speed up the process of unification'' and ''pass on the baton to our all-Serbian leader Slobodan Milosevic.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
