<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Setting So Romantic They're Now Married to It</title>
    <meta content="13rest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/dining/reviews/13rest.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854109"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">SoHo (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E1D8173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1269" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Setting So Romantic They're Now Married to It</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Setting So Romantic They’re Now Married to It</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank Bruni</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF looks alone could make a restaurant, Provence would have nothing to worry about.</p>
        <p>It turns the sweetest of faces to the world. The front of the restaurant is mostly glass, latticed with strips of wood painted the lulling blue of a Mediterranean sky, and on a warm night whole sections of this transparent wall open, erasing the division between inside and out, letting gentle breezes and the faint bustle of a narrow SoHo street wash over you.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The fare at Provence, the SoHo favorite, which changed ownership recently and reopened two months ago, is inconsistent and sometimes dull.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF looks alone could make a restaurant, Provence would have nothing to worry about.</p>
        <p>It turns the sweetest of faces to the world. The front of the restaurant is mostly glass, latticed with strips of wood painted the lulling blue of a Mediterranean sky, and on a warm night whole sections of this transparent wall open, erasing the division between inside and out, letting gentle breezes and the faint bustle of a narrow SoHo street wash over you.</p>
        <p>No wonder Marc Meyer and Vicki Freeman, the restaurateurs behind Five Points and Cookshop, snapped this gem up last fall when, after two decades, its original owner closed it. Their decision made sense even without added sentiment: about 11 years ago they became engaged here.</p>
        <p>Back then Provence was the romantic setting of many dates, a suggestion of the French countryside in the middle of a city far away. Time and neglect later got the better of it, but for a good long while, it had sophistication without ever straining for it and warmth to burn.</p>
        <p>The Meyer-Freeman redo of the restaurant, unveiled two months ago, aims for those same qualities, and on a cosmetic level it achieves them. To the couple's credit, they haven't tried to turn Provence into something snazzier or snootier than it should be.</p>
        <p>Within wood-paneled walls and under a wood-beamed ceiling, they've preserved an essentially homey atmosphere, with a raft of refinements. They've added a marble bar in the front room and gold-and-crimson banquettes in the middle room, beyond which the enclosed garden lies.</p>
        <p>Much of the credit for these flourishes goes to the designers Melissa Hamilton and Christopher Hirsheimer. In a city where almost every possible restroom design has been tapped, they managed to come up with an approach that's literally novel. The women's room is wallpapered with columns of text from ''The Hunchback of Notre Dame,'' while the men's gets ''The Three Musketeers.'' I bet a dozen theories could be hatched, and jokes made, about those literary assignments.</p>
        <p>But looks can get a restaurant only so far, and nostalgia can't cover the rest of the distance. The food has to do its part, and Provence's is inconsistent and sometimes dull.</p>
        <p>On the surface, at least, the restaurant's bistro-plus menu is smartly calibrated. The ratio of hearty to lighter fare, of sausages to sea bass, is just right. Some dishes honor the French region for which the restaurant is named; others could appear at any New York restaurant without an obvious ethnic compass.</p>
        <p>Provence's prices show commendable restraint. More of a dozen or so entrees on a recent dinner menu fell below the $25 mark than above it, and only three of about a dozen appetizers were more than $10.</p>
        <p>The terrific all-French wine list, rife with interesting selections from small producers, follows suit. With a ceiling of $50 a bottle you'd still have plenty of choices, though you'd miss an appealing roster of Bandols.</p>
        <p>Still, I'd trade one or two of those virtues for a crisper skin on the underseasoned rotisserie chicken; for a lamb cutlet that tasted more like lamb and less like its Parmesan-flecked breading; for sautéed calamari and baby octopus that didn't rely so heavily on pine nuts and currants for personality.</p>
        <p>On an early visit, a deep-fried soft-shell crab was greasy. On a later visit, the greasiness was gone, but the crab had seemingly vanished with it: I could almost have been eating deep-fried shape-of-crab.</p>
        <p>There's been improvement since early April, and there are definite pleasures to be had. But the strides haven't been steady enough to dispel my impressions of a kitchen -- directly supervised by Lynn McNeely, who cooked at Barbuto -- that can't fully get its act together.</p>
        <p>Some of what I liked best didn't require Mr. McNeely's kitchen to exert much effort. A platter of cured meats from Salumeria Biellese was first-rate. Oysters, fresh and briny, could be ordered individually or in a luxurious two-tier seafood array with mussels, shrimp, crab (irreproachable in this iteration), bay scallops and razor clams (outstanding).</p>
        <p>Among starters -- including calamari and baby octopus; fine salt cod fritters; excessively chewy escargot brochette; asparagus under a shower of bread crumbs and chopped egg; and a more memorable chilled asparagus and spring garlic soup -- my favorite was a gooey gratin of wild mushrooms, artichoke and tangy goat cheese. It packed the kind of punch that other dishes lacked.</p>
        <p>Grilled porgy needed something brighter and sharper than the herb mayonnaise that accompanied it, though perhaps nothing as aggressive as the olive-almond tapenade that jousted with grilled daurade.</p>
        <p>House-made pork sausage and braised pork shoulder over white beans lacked the richness and gusto it promised, and the sauce verte with it didn't register. It was like a cassoulet that had lost its nerve.</p>
        <p>You'd be wiser to go with a deftly grilled hanger steak, provided you get a side of the regular frites, crunchy on the outside and soft within, and not the chalky chickpea frites. You'd be wiser still to get the sea scallops, plump and juicy, with baby beets and vine beans. Mr. Meyer and Ms. Freeman have always been finicky about their produce, and for the most part that commitment showed.</p>
        <p>They don't take big chances with desserts, which don't make a big impact. Bypass the chocolate mousse for a lemon-rhubarb tart that squarely hit its sour notes.</p>
        <p>As a neighborhood haunt -- the kind of familiar French bistro you pop into almost by default, knowing what's good and what's what -- Provence has enough going for it.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Meyer and Ms. Freeman are positioning this restaurant, which has 110 seats in all, to be more than that. The 15 well-chosen wines by the glass, including four rosés, seek the approval and affection of savvy gourmands, as do the artisanal cheese selections, which change regularly.</p>
        <p>And the blue paint was purchased in Provence, so that the shade was just so. If the restaurateurs get as obsessive about the food, they may be able to celebrate their anniversary here for years to come.</p>
        <p>Provence  * [Rating: One Star]  38 MacDougal Street (Prince Street), SoHo; (212) 475-7500.</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE An enclosed back garden and a largely glass facade that opens to the street are just two points of charm in a romantic but homey restaurant freshly brimming with it.  SOUND LEVEL Moderately loud in the front room, quieter toward the back.  RECOMMENDED DISHES Oysters; seafood platter; cured meats; pork pâté; asparagus soup; artichoke and mushroom gratin; prawns with citrus salad; scallops with baby beets; hanger steak; frites; lemon-rhubarb tart.  WINE LIST A principled, thoughtful, all-French selection of wines from small producers that puts regions other than Bordeaux and Burgundy front and center and takes chances -- for example, presenting as many rosés by the glass (four) as whites and reds. A half dozen unconventional beer selections as well.  PRICE RANGE Lunch appetizers, $8 to $12. Entrees, $15 to $23. Dinner appetizers, $8 to $12. Entrees, $18 to $27. Desserts, $8.  HOURS Lunch noon to 3 p.m. Monday through Friday, 11:30 a.m. to 3 p.m. Saturday and Sunday. Dinner 5:30 to 11:30 p.m. Monday through Saturday, to 10 p.m. Sunday.  RESERVATIONS For prime dinner times, call at least 10 days ahead.  CREDIT CARDS All major cards.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS Small step to the entrance; inaccessible restrooms.  WHAT THE STARS MEAN Ratings range from zero to four stars and reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.  PAST REVIEWS from The Times, with additional capsule reviews by Times critics: nytimes.com/dining</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
