<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scrutiny on Tax Rates That Fund Managers Pay</title>
    <meta content="13tax" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/business/13tax.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854228"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Credits, Deductions and Exemptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capital Gains Tax</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brookings Institution</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rubin, Robert E (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Jenny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Summers, Lawrence H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Gains Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Rubin, Robert E</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904EFDF143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scrutiny on Tax Rates That Fund Managers Pay</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Scrutiny on Tax Rates That Fund Managers Pay</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNY ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Jenny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Backlash against tremendous wealth being created by managers of hedge funds and private equity funds may be gaining strength; former Treasury Sec Robert E Rubin makes case for why private equity and hedge fund managers should pay more than double low rate in taxes they now enjoy; Rubin, chairman of executive committee at Citigroup, responds to questions posed to him about whether 20 percent fee on profits that most private equity firms charge should continue to be taxed on lower capital gains rate of 15 percent or changed to top ordinary income tax rate of 35 percent; Rubin in panelist at tax reform conference run by Hamilton Project, policy group initiated mostly by moderate Democrats from business and academia that is housed at Brookings Institution; another area of interest to committee is ability of hedge fund managers and private equity managers to defer large portions of their income offshore, where it can increase tax free; photo of Rubin and Lawrence H Summers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The backlash against the tremendous wealth being created by managers of hedge funds and private equity funds may be gaining strength.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Robert E. Rubin, a former Treasury secretary in President Bill Clinton's administration, made the case for why private equity and hedge fund managers should pay more than double the low rate in taxes they now enjoy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The backlash against the wealth being created by managers of hedge funds and private equity funds may be gaining strength.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The backlash against the tremendous wealth being created by managers of hedge funds and private equity funds may be gaining strength.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Robert E. Rubin, a former Treasury secretary in President Bill Clinton's administration, made the case for why private equity and hedge fund managers should pay more than double the low rate in taxes they now enjoy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rubin, now the chairman of the executive committee at Citigroup, was responding to a question posed to him about whether the 20 percent fee on profits that most private equity firms charge should continue to be taxed at the lower capital gains rate of 15 percent or changed to the top ordinary income tax rate of 35 percent. Mr. Rubin, who said he was expressing his own views and not that of his employer, was a panelist at a tax reform conference run by the Hamilton Project, a policy group initiated mostly by moderate Democrats from business and academia that is housed at the Brookings Institution.</p>
        <p>''It seems to me what is happening is people are performing a service, managing peoples' money in a private equity form, and fees for that service would ordinarily be thought of as ordinary income,'' Mr. Rubin said. He made clear that he was not a tax expert but said the issue should be looked at ''with great seriousness'' by the appropriate tax committees in Congress.</p>
        <p>The compensation of private equity and hedge fund managers has become a hot button issue as their pay has skyrocketed. James Simons, chairman of Renaissance Technologies, earned $1.7 billion last year while the average compensation of the top 25 managers was $570 million, according to Institutional Investor's Alpha magazine.</p>
        <p>Stephen A. Schwarzman, the co-founder of the Blackstone Group, which is in the process of going public, made $400 million last year. He plans to cash out up to $677.2 million after the initial public offering and will own a stake worth $7.5 billion if the offering is priced in the range the company's underwriters have planned.</p>
        <p>Congress, searching for alternate sources of revenue, has taken notice. A few months ago, staff members of the Senate Finance Committee started to examine taxes on the 20 percent fee on profits, which private equity firms call ''carry'' and hedge funds call performance fees, as well as other tax issues involving hedge funds and private equity.</p>
        <p>Another area of interest to the committee is the ability of hedge fund managers and private equity managers to defer large portions of their income offshore, where it can increase tax free (they pay taxes when they bring it back into the United States). The chairman of the Senate Finance Committee, Max Baucus, Democrat of Montana, recently said the committee was not close to doing anything.</p>
        <p>Private equity firms and hedge funds are generally structured as partnerships, which means they have ''flow-through'' accounting: every owner receives his or her share of the profits and pays taxes on it. No corporate entity is taxed.</p>
        <p>Most private equity funds and hedge funds receive two kinds of fees: a 2 percent management fee (2 percent of the assets they manage), and a 20 percent incentive fee, or a 20 percent cut of the profits.</p>
        <p>There are crucial differences though. Many hedge funds trade in and out of liquid securities, like stocks, very rapidly, so their gains are taxed as ordinary income (because they do not hold them for more than a year). Private equity funds, by contrast, borrow money to buy companies, strive to improve the company's operations in the private market and take it public or sell it, generally in five to seven years (though that time has recently been shrinking).</p>
        <p>The dispute does not center on whether the income generated by the transaction should be treated as a long-term capital gain, but whether private equity managers, who are not risking significant amounts of their own money, but managing money for others, should get the lower capital gains tax treatment.</p>
        <p>Jason Furman, director of the Hamilton Project, framed the issue this way: ''Is it an employee doing a service and getting a fee, or is it more like a business owner selling their business at a profit?'' (The Hamilton Project is not an advocacy organization and does not have a view).</p>
        <p>While the tax treatment of so-called carried interest focuses more directly on private equity managers, many hedge funds are getting more involved in buying and selling more illiquid assets, including companies, which would bring the issue closer to home for them. At the same time, private equity funds and hedge funds are increasingly getting into each other's business.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
