<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Budget Agreement Is Near, New Jersey Officials Say</title>
    <meta content="13budget" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/nyregion/13budget.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854238"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EEDF143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="708" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Budget Agreement Is Near, New Jersey Officials Say</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Budget Agreement Is Near, New Jersey Officials Say</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, JUNE 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine and the Democratic leaders of the Assembly and Senate said Tuesday afternoon that they had reached ''broad agreement on the framework'' for a new state budget and expected its official adoption well before the statutory June 30 deadline.</p>
        <p>The blueprint calls for ''a slightly bigger'' budget than the $33.3 billion plan proposed by the governor in February, according to Bradley Abelow, the state treasurer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRENTON, JUNE 12  Gov. Jon S. Corzine and the Democratic leaders of the Assembly and Senate said Tuesday afternoon that they had reached “broad agreement on the framework” for a new state budget and expected its official adoption well before the statutory June 30 deadline.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine and the Democratic leaders of the Assembly and Senate said Tuesday afternoon that they had reached ''broad agreement on the framework'' for a new state budget and expected its official adoption well before the statutory June 30 deadline.</p>
        <p>The blueprint calls for ''a slightly bigger'' budget than the $33.3 billion plan proposed by the governor in February, according to Bradley Abelow, the state treasurer.</p>
        <p>The agreement preserves Governor Corzine's goal of a balanced budget with no new taxes or fees for the first time in five years, Mr. Abelow said, and includes increases in education aid and income-tax credits for the vast majority of the state's property owners.</p>
        <p>Spending increases include aid to hospitals to care for patients who do not have health insurance and raises for employees of a number of state-supported nonprofit agencies, most of them health-related.</p>
        <p>Neither Mr. Abelow nor aides to the legislative leaders, who met earlier Tuesday with Mr. Corzine, would give specifics on how much money had been added to these or other areas. But all those involved were eager to praise the early agreement, a sharp contrast from last year, when differences between the Democratic leaders and the governor pushed the process past June 30 and led to a seven-day shutdown of state government.</p>
        <p>''Broad agreement of the parameters of where we expect to be puts us in the position to complete the budget well before the June 30 deadline,'' Mr. Abelow said in a briefing here about 90 minutes before a joint written statement by Mr. Corzine and the legislative leaders. ''Our unity of purpose has made this easier.''</p>
        <p>One lawmaker familiar with the budget talks, who spoke on the condition of anonymity for lack of authorization, said that the hospital aid, known as charity care, would be increased by $129 million -- short of the nearly $300 million sought by hospitals -- for a total of $716 million. The workers at the nonprofit agencies will get cost-of-living increases without adding a small fee for their patients, as had been proposed by the governor, the lawmaker said.</p>
        <p>In addition, the lawmaker said that some of the nearly $7 million for cancer research and treatment that had been cut under Mr. Corzine's original budget proposal would be restored, along with half the $18 million reduction in aid to municipalities.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the lawmaker said, school districts would be required under the agreement to collectively dedicate $10 million to adult education programs. In an effort to make the much-criticized secretive budget process of the past more transparent, both houses of the Legislature plan to hold public hearings in the next week or so to discuss the changes to the governor's original proposal. Staff members in the Assembly said on Tuesday that a vote on the new budget might be scheduled as early as June 21.</p>
        <p>While the Corzine administration and legislative leaders have gone to greater than usual lengths over the last two weeks to stress their general agreement on budget matters rather than their differences, the timing of Mr. Abelow's briefing, in advance of the joint statement on Tuesday, ruffled some legislative feathers.</p>
        <p>Officials in the governor's office said they called the briefing after The Star-Ledger of Newark posted a report online heralding a final budget agreement. The online report led to a frenzy of calls to the treasurer's office, officials said.</p>
        <p>But the staffs of the legislative leaders were unaware of Mr. Abelow's plans to make a statement on his own. For a brief time, the plan for a joint statement was ''on life support,'' said a staff member who spoke on the condition of anonymity because the staff member was not authorized to talk about the budget negotiations.</p>
        <p>State Senator Joseph M. Kyrillos Jr., a Republican from Middletown, attributed Tuesday afternoon's confusion to continuing nervousness after what he called last year's ''budget chaos.''</p>
        <p>''Clearly the governor won't allow the level of chaos that took place last year,'' Mr. Kyrillos said. ''It behooves him to reassure the public that he has a steady hand on the process, and I believe he wanted to make his statement early in order to prevent any 'one more thing' meetings with legislative leaders looking for something else.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
