<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New TV Campaign Stars Bronx as a Tourist's Delight</title>
    <meta content="13bronx" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/nyregion/13bronx.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854173"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E4D6173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="824" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New TV Campaign Stars Bronx as a Tourist's Delight</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A New Television Campaign, Starring the Bronx as a Tourist’s Delight</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANNY FERNANDEZ</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Television viewers in the New York region will learn about a new and intriguing tourist destination this month. It is an exotic land the size of Paris, an urban retreat that gave the world not only hip-hop but also Billy Joel, and is home to a zoo, a baseball stadium and a jeer disguised as a cheer.</p>
        <p>The Bronx.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A series of television commercials promoting the borough of 1.3 million will be on the airwaves starting June 25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Television viewers in the New York region will learn about a new and intriguing tourist destination this month. It is an exotic land the size of Paris, an urban retreat that gave the world not only hip-hop but also Billy Joel, and is home to a zoo, a baseball stadium and a jeer disguised as a cheer.</p>
        <p>The Bronx.</p>
        <p>A series of television commercials promoting the borough of 1.3 million will be on the airwaves starting June 25. The 30-second spots, the first television advertisements the Bronx has used to sell itself, are part of a marketing campaign called ''We're Talking the Bronx,'' starring Adolfo Carrión Jr., the borough president.</p>
        <p>In the nine commercials, Mr. Carrión boasts of the borough's Zagat-rated restaurants (there are 25 of them, he says), its booming residential and commercial development, its physical beauty and its many attractions, like the Bronx Zoo and Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>The $200,000 campaign was paid for by several Bronx institutions and companies featured in the ads, including the Yankees, Fordham University and North Fork Bank.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carrión unveiled the ads yesterday at a news conference at Fordham Preparatory School. Though the image of the Bronx as a burning, dangerous place is outdated by several decades, he said people outside the borough still needed to be reminded not so much of what the Bronx is, but what it is not.</p>
        <p>''The Bronx has risen from the decades of the '70s and '80s to a place that many people didn't imagine that it could,'' Mr. Carrión said after the event. ''It is a great American story of a community that refused failure, that embraced success and opportunity.''</p>
        <p>The ads will run for nine weeks on cable networks including CNN and ESPN in parts of the Bronx, Manhattan and Westchester County. They could be seen by roughly one million viewers, according to Weinrib &amp; Connor, the White Plains advertising agency that produced the ads.</p>
        <p>The spots promoting one of New York City's grittier boroughs give the place a rather old-fashioned, small-town feel. A fiddle plays pleasantly in the background as Mr. Carrión and others smile at the camera, though the borough's homegrown musical legacies include hip-hop, doo-wop and salsa.</p>
        <p>In one ad, an unidentified representative of Woodlawn Cemetery, one of the financial sponsors of the campaign, stares into the camera and says: ''Whether preplanning or at a time of need, come talk with us.''</p>
        <p>In others, viewers are whisked from the borough's Little Italy on Arthur Avenue to the blue-backed seats of Yankee Stadium to the interior of North Central Bronx Hospital, ''the hospital of choice for the Norwood community.'' There are shots of Mike's Deli on Arthur Avenue and the eager staff of a Ridgewood Savings Bank branch.</p>
        <p>The ads were shot throughout the borough in four days in May. The focus is on the big picture, and the little one, too. Mr. Carrión says in one scene that in the past five years, $2.4 billion has been invested in housing in the Bronx. In others, he points out the borough's efforts to reduce traffic congestion in neighborhoods and rebuild playgrounds.</p>
        <p>''More than 7,500 families have bought homes and are living the great American dream right here in the Bronx,'' Mr. Carrión says at one point, referring to the period since 2002. ''We're talking the Bronx.''</p>
        <p>Naturally, the ads put a nice gloss on life in the borough. There is no mention of the borough's high unemployment and poverty rates, and no mention that it lacks a major hotel.</p>
        <p>The ads are part of a marketing campaign that is now in its fourth year. The promotional push has included radio spots, newspaper ads and billboards, and now TV commercials. Past ads featured celebrity Bronxites, including the television host Regis Philbin and the mystery writer Mary Higgins Clark.</p>
        <p>Lloyd Ultan, the borough historian, said a little boosterism was necessary for a borough often overshadowed by Manhattan and still stereotyped by the fires, crime and abandonment of the 1970s and 1980s.</p>
        <p>''When you say 'the Bronx' to many people, it conjures up images of Jimmy Carter walking on the plains of Charlotte Street,'' said Mr. Ultan, 69, referring to the former president's visit to rubble-strewn lots in the South Bronx in October 1977. ''But that's 30 years ago. People must realize that there are no longer any devastated areas in the Bronx, that crime in the Bronx has dropped to the lowest levels in 40 years.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Carrión said the goal of the campaign was to generate more tourism to the borough, which attracted about seven million visitors last year. The ads also raise the profile of Mr. Carrión, who is considered a possible candidate for mayor in 2009.</p>
        <p>When asked if the ads would help his political future, he said yesterday: ''Every time I wake up in the morning and do my job right, it helps me to do whatever I'm going to do next.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
