<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Named for Piety, Laced With Profanity</title>
    <meta content="13golf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/sports/golf/13golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854218"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE1DF143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Named for Piety, Laced With Profanity</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Named for Piety, Laced With Profanity</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa., June 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are 20 benches in the middle of Oakmont Country Club where no golfer wants to stop and take a rest.</p>
        <p>The benches are made of grass and hold some of the best views on the course, but should a player hit his ball there during this week's United States Open, it may cost him the championship.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Of all the distinctive wrinkles of Oakmont, the home of this week’s U.S. Open, the club’s Church Pews bunker between the third and fourth holes have come to represent the course’s toughness, charm and eclectic soul.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are 20 benches in the middle of Oakmont Country Club where no golfer wants to stop and take a rest.</p>
        <p>The benches are made of grass and hold some of the best views on the course, but should a player hit his ball there during this week's United States Open, it may cost him the championship.</p>
        <p>''Everyone looks forward to seeing the Church Pews in person, but they certainly don't want to get too close,'' said Bob Ford, Oakmont's head professional, referring to the 26,000-square-foot bunker between the third and fourth holes, and a smaller version to the left of No. 15.</p>
        <p>Of all the distinctive wrinkles of Oakmont -- from its 288-yard par-3 eighth hole to its slippery, undulating greens -- the club's Church Pews have come to represent the course's toughness, charm and eclectic soul.</p>
        <p>Like the Road Hole bunker at St. Andrews and the Postage Stamp at Royal Troon, Oakmont's Church Pews are landmarks unto themselves.</p>
        <p>The United States Golf Association, which runs the tournament, has graced its official program and pairing guide brochure with a picture of the Church Pews.</p>
        <p>The Pittsburgh Tribune-Review splashed photos of the bunkers to kick off its championship coverage.</p>
        <p>The largest bunker -- with 12 pews -- is tucked between the 428-yard par-4 third and the 609-yard par-5 fourth and punishes drives hit too far left.</p>
        <p>Many players said that a drive into the Church Pews would all but force them to hit a wedge shot sideways back into the fairway, especially if a ball comes to rest against the grassy lip of a pew.</p>
        <p>Bogeys and higher will be inevitable. Scores will skyrocket. But, man, those pews are pretty, Phil Mickelson said.</p>
        <p>''Some of the coolest bunkers in the game,'' he said. ''I certainly don't plan on going in them, but it is something that I would look at as a possible architectural feature in some of my design work.''</p>
        <p>While sand makes up most of the Church Pews bunkers, the large strips of grass cutting across them create a hazard that is arresting and maddening.</p>
        <p>In the days leading up to the event, which begins Thursday, the golfers have taken different approaches to preparing for them. Some have used their practice rounds to hit shots out of the bunkers, so they can be better prepared for any situation.</p>
        <p>Tiger Woods, though, has avoided them altogether, refusing even to drop a ball in them to test them out.</p>
        <p>''I don't really think that you should be practicing negativity,'' he said Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Sergio García agreed. When he drove into the Church Pews from the fourth tee during his practice round, he rescued his ball from the bunker and did not think twice about doing so.</p>
        <p>''That's the neat thing about practice rounds,'' García said Tuesday. ''You can pick it up and put it back in the fairway.''</p>
        <p>Zach Johnson, the Masters champion, and Ernie Els, who won the United States Open here in 1994, disagreed with Woods and García.</p>
        <p>Both said they had spent parts of their practice rounds dreaming up any possible situation in the Church Pews. They have tried hitting out of good lies, and bad lies, and lies in between -- the better to be prepared.</p>
        <p>''I've done it already,'' Johnson said. ''Whether it's a sand shot or a wedge, that's pretty much what you're limited to. To an extent, they kind of remind you of links golf across the pond. They are treacherous.''</p>
        <p>Els said of dropping several balls in the pews: ''That's why we play practice rounds. You never know what's going to happen under pressure. We kind of lose it sometimes. You need to play all kinds of different shots.''</p>
        <p>On the road to winning his championship at Oakmont in a playoff over Loren Roberts and Colin Montgomerie, Els said he did not recall landing in either of the Church Pews bunkers.</p>
        <p>''I remember on 3, I was just hitting a 2-iron down the fairway, laying back,'' he said. ''And on 4, I made sure I kept it right.''</p>
        <p>This year, though, the largest bunker has been increased in yardage to 30 by 100, compared with 25 by 70, making it more difficult to skirt on the way to the green.</p>
        <p>Johnny Miller, who won the 1973 event at Oakmont with a blistering final-round 63, also avoided the Church Pews for four rounds. He speculated that others might not be so lucky this year.</p>
        <p>''Guys are going to be thinking about it,'' he said. ''If it rolls up into a bank, you've got to probably go out sideways. These bunkers are great, great bunkers. You don't want to go in them, though.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
