<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cavaliers Let Opportunity Pass Them By</title>
    <meta content="13nba" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854262"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E3DE143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="956" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cavaliers Let Opportunity Pass Them By</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <dateline>CLEVELAND, June 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LeBron James drove desperately to the basket with just under 15 seconds remaining and his Cleveland Cavaliers trailing by a basket. Running into San Antonio's best two defenders, Bruce Bowen and Tim Duncan -- the savvy veterans who have confronted him at every turn in these N.B.A. finals -- James spun to pass the ball to Anderson Varejao.</p>
        <p>Fans in Quicken Loans Arena let out a groan, as if their city's long history of sports suffering had led them to this inescapable moment of defeat. Wasn't James supposed to be over his unselfish passing phase at the end of games?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LeBron James drove desperately to the basket with just under 15 seconds remaining and his Cleveland Cavaliers trailing by a basket. Running into San Antonio's best two defenders, Bruce Bowen and Tim Duncan -- the savvy veterans who have confronted him at every turn in these N.B.A. finals -- James spun to pass the ball to Anderson Varejao.</p>
        <p>Fans in Quicken Loans Arena let out a groan, as if their city's long history of sports suffering had led them to this inescapable moment of defeat. Wasn't James supposed to be over his unselfish passing phase at the end of games?</p>
        <p>James would later say he thought Varejao would get him the ball back. Instead, Varejao flung up an awkward layup in the lane. And missed.</p>
        <p>Manu Ginóbili, who had not made a shot from the field all night, made three of his four free throws in the final 10 seconds as the Spurs squeezed a 75-72 victory Tuesday night in Game 3 of the N.B.A. finals.</p>
        <p>Even without Tim Duncan and Ginóbili at their best in a ragged game, the Spurs are one victory away from clinching their fourth title in nine years and solidifying their dynasty status. Tony Parker hit a clutch 3-pointer with one minute remaining and led the Spurs with 17 points. Duncan had 14.</p>
        <p>When James missed a wild 3-pointer before the buzzer and did not draw a foul from Bowen, the fans who were furiously waving their white towels to support the Cavaliers' first finals appearance dropped them in near-surrender. No team has come back from a 3-0 deficit in the finals.</p>
        <p>''We can't live on history,'' James said. ''But at the same time we have dug ourselves a big hole.''</p>
        <p>There have been seven sweeps in N.B.A. finals history, but the past two teams to suffer such ignominy were franchises making their first appearance on the league's biggest stage. The Los Angeles Lakers swept the Nets in the 2002 finals and the Houston Rockets swept Shaquille O'Neal's Orlando Magic in 1995.</p>
        <p>''You know, the experience factor, we don't like to make any excuses, but it definitely played a part in this finals against a world power team, a great team, in the Spurs,'' James said.</p>
        <p>James has committed 17 turnovers in the first three games of the finals (he had five in Game 3), and he has shot 36.3 percent, appearing to be unable to impose his will as he did at the end of the conference finals.</p>
        <p>''I think he's trying, he's definitely trying,'' Duncan said. ''We're a pretty good defensive team. Whether he tries to impose his will or not, we're going to be standing in front of him.''</p>
        <p>Unlike Michael Jordan, Magic Johnson and Larry Bird, who all won a championship in their first trip to the finals, James, however, cannot rely on a talented supporting cast.</p>
        <p>James scored a game-high 25 points in this Game 3, but the Cavaliers' rookie guard Daniel Gibson, starting for the injured Larry Hughes, missed nine of his 10 shots in his first playoff start. Center Zydrunas Ilgauskas, the longest tenured Cavalier, grabbed 18 rebounds and scored 12 points.</p>
        <p>James has not been the same since his eye-popping Game 5 performance in the conference finals, where he scored 48 points against the Detroit Pistons and 29 of his team's final 30 points in the double-overtime victory.</p>
        <p>''I kind of envisioned it being tough,'' James said. ''I think the Eastern Conference finals was tough and I knew it was going to pick up another level. I think our team senses that, too.''</p>
        <p>As James drove to the fateful basket in the closing seconds, Cavaliers Coach Mike Brown was yelling furiously for a timeout.</p>
        <p>''I'm more tired from yelling timeout 18 times in a row then from the game,'' Brown said. ''It was so loud, nobody heard me.''</p>
        <p>Instead, James raced up court, and the next thing Brown saw was Varejao's miss.</p>
        <p>''I definitely wanted to try to get a good look at it or give my teammate a better look at it, but it was just miscommunication,'' James said.</p>
        <p>The Spurs, on the verge of winning their third title in five years, are past that playoff novice stage. San Antonio Coach Gregg Popovich preaches perfection and consistency in every practice. The result?</p>
        <p>''I can honestly say these three games is the best defense we've played all season,'' Popovich said, giving special credit to Bowen's work on James and complimenting Bowen's 4-for-5 shooting night from 3-point range.</p>
        <p>''I thought Timmy and Tony and Manu would have to be great to win these games, but that's not going to happen all the time,'' Popovich added. ''That's why I think Bruce picked up a lot of slack.''</p>
        <p>The game was not one for the highlight reel, full of sloppy play, missed shots and turnovers. The teams combined for four fast-break points. Cleveland shot 3 for 19 from 3-point range. Even the officials made a mistake on a call.</p>
        <p>At the start of the second quarter, with James driving to the basket, the officials called a foul on Jacque Vaughn but put Gibson on the line. He made both free throws.</p>
        <p>Then the officials reversed the call, erased the 2 points and put James on the line. James made the first, missed the second. It was that kind of night for the Cavaliers, and that kind of series.</p>
        <p>If the first half was difficult to watch the third quarter, when the Spurs outscored the Cavaliers, 15-12, was forgettable.</p>
        <p>''It was 40-38 at halftime, we set the western world of offensive basketball back 10 years,'' Popovich said.</p>
        <p>In the process, however, the Spurs are on the verge of advancing into the hallowed territory of a dynasty.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
