<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turkish Premier Opposes Move on Militants in Iraq</title>
    <meta content="13turkey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/world/europe/13turkey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854160"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kurds</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Turkey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tavernise, Sabrina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erdogan, Recep Tayyip (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kurds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kurds</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Turkey</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Erdogan, Recep Tayyip</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E7D6173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="522" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turkish Premier Opposes Move on Militants in Iraq</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Turkish Premier Opposes Move on Militants in Iraq</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SABRINA TAVERNISE; Sebnem Arsu contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tavernise, Sabrina</byline>
      <dateline>ISTANBUL, June 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tayyip Erdogan, prime minister of Turkey, takes strong public stance against military incursion into northern Iraq, indicating that he would not back military's request for major offensive; military has already increased its presence along Iraq border and has been conducting operations against Kurdish militants inside Turkey; Erdogan says Turkey should continue to fight militants on Turkish soil, where majority of them are (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan took a strong public stance against a military incursion into northern Iraq on Tuesday, in an indication that he would not back the military's request for a major offensive.</p>
        <p>For weeks, the Turkish Army has been pushing for a broad military response to attacks by the Kurdistan Workers' Party, a militant separatist group that takes refuge in northern Iraq. The military has already increased its presence along the border and has been conducting operations against the militants in Turkey. On Tuesday, Mr. Erdogan said Turkey should first continue to fight the militants on Turkish soil before fighting them in Iraq, slowing the movement toward an incursion. He said far more militants were in Turkey than in Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Recep Tayyip Erdogan took a strong public stance against his own country’s military incursion into northern Iraq to fight Kurdish rebels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan took a strong public stance against a military incursion into northern Iraq on Tuesday, in an indication that he would not back the military's request for a major offensive.</p>
        <p>For weeks, the Turkish Army has been pushing for a broad military response to attacks by the Kurdistan Workers' Party, a militant separatist group that takes refuge in northern Iraq. The military has already increased its presence along the border and has been conducting operations against the militants in Turkey. On Tuesday, Mr. Erdogan said Turkey should first continue to fight the militants on Turkish soil before fighting them in Iraq, slowing the movement toward an incursion. He said far more militants were in Turkey than in Iraq.</p>
        <p>The Turkish Parliament would need to approve a major military action, and Mr. Erdogan's party controls the legislature, so his view on the wisdom of an invasion is important.</p>
        <p>''Has the struggle against 5,000 terrorists inside Turkey come to a close, so that we can now start dealing with the 500 in northern Iraq?'' Mr. Erdogan said in Ankara, according to the state-run Anatolian News Agency.</p>
        <p>It was the first time a cautious tone had been struck in weeks of sharp language, and Mr. Erdogan's message will likely be welcomed by the United States, which is trying to navigate a position between its two allies: Turkey, a NATO member, and Iraqi Kurds, the most reliable partner in Iraq.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the Kurdish group also struck a conciliatory note on Tuesday, saying that it would stop attacks against the Turkish military as long as Turkey reciprocated, according to a report by The Associated Press that quoted Abdul Rahman Chaderchi, a Workers' Party official in northern Iraq.</p>
        <p>Mr. Erdogan's stance on Tuesday differed sharply from his remarks after a bombing in Ankara last month, in which he supported the military's push for an incursion. The bombing, which killed eight people, was blamed on the Kurdish group.</p>
        <p>Politically, Mr. Erdogan opposes the military, which stood against him and his party, Justice and Development, as he began pushing his choice for president in April. The military said then that Mr. Erdogan's government had strayed too far from secularism and warned that it could take action if the trend continued.</p>
        <p>Some critics of the military, a powerful force that has deposed elected governments it considers dangerous to Turkey, argue that it wants to move against the Kurdish militants simply to remain relevant at a time when democracy in Turkey has reached its most sophisticated state in the nation's history.</p>
        <p>Funerals for Turkish soldiers killed by Kurdish militants have been highly publicized in recent weeks, with emotional photographs of the soldiers splashed across the front pages of Turkish newspapers.</p>
        <p>At one recent funeral, mourners booed government ministers and accused Mr. Erdogan's government of murder, Reuters reported.</p>
        <p>Mr. Erdogan countered that accusation angrily on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''The people who shout 'killer government' will have to pay for it,'' he said, according to Reuters. ''Nobody has the right to call a 'killer' a government which governs the country day and night with self-sacrifice.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
