<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City Students Lead Big Rise On Math Tests</title>
    <meta content="13math" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/education/13math.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854237"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syracuse (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Medina, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloomberg, Michael R (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Finger Lakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Finger Lakes/Syracuse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EEDF143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1279" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City Students Lead Big Rise On Math Tests</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">City Students Lead Big Rise on N.Y. Math Tests</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER MEDINA; Ford Fessenden and David Herszenhorn contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Medina, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Math scores for students in New York State improve significantly in every grade tested, driven by sizable gains in New York City, according to results of annual statewide math exam; New York City's increases are larger than those in any other big-city school district except Syracuse and show city nearing statewide performance average; Mayor Michael R Bloomberg cites results as evidence of success of his education policies; some say city was so far behind it could only improve; one of most impressive achievements for city was that students improved as they moved from grade to grade, defying historic trend of proficiency levels dropping as students age; graph of math achievements in New York State and New York City (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Math scores for students across New York State improved significantly in every grade tested this year, powered by sizable gains in New York City, according to results of the annual statewide math exam released by education officials yesterday.</p>
        <p>The city's increases were larger than those in any of the other big-city school districts except Syracuse and showed the city nearing the statewide performance average. In every grade tested -- third through eighth -- New York City had jumps, in most cases in the double digits, in the proportion of students performing at grade level or above.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In every grade tested, the city had jumps, often in double digits, in the proportion of students scoring at grade level.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Math scores for students across New York State improved significantly in every grade tested this year, powered by sizable gains in New York City, according to results of the annual statewide math exam released by education officials yesterday.</p>
        <p>The city's increases were larger than those in any of the other big-city school districts except Syracuse and showed the city nearing the statewide performance average. In every grade tested -- third through eighth -- New York City had jumps, in most cases in the double digits, in the proportion of students performing at grade level or above.</p>
        <p>The improvement in the city's students' math performance, which brought 65.1 percent of students to grade level or above, now makes it more comparable to some racially and economically mixed suburban school districts, like Peekskill in Westchester County or the South Country Central School District in mid-Suffolk County, than to other urban centers like Buffalo, where just 35.9 percent of students met the standards. Syracuse, despite its improvement this year, has just 39.4 percent of students at grade level or above.</p>
        <p>Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg, who has made education a priority and won mayoral control of the school system, seized on the numbers as evidence of success. ''I'm happy, thrilled -- ecstatic, I think, is a better word,'' Mr. Bloomberg said during a news conference at City Hall, standing next to a monitor showing bar and line graphs of the results. ''The hard work going on in our schools is really paying off.''</p>
        <p>This was the second year in which New York State used new tests and new math standards devised to bring more rigor to the system, and some of the statewide gains could be attributed to teachers and students becoming more accustomed to the exams and the curriculum. When the new test was first used last year, scores across the state generally fell from the previous year.</p>
        <p>This year, across the state, 72.7 percent of students in Grades 3 through 8 showed they were proficient at grade level or above in math, an increase from 65.8 percent the year before. But the gains were not universal.</p>
        <p>In Yonkers, student performance dropped slightly. In New York City, improvement was widespread, but hundreds of schools showed no improvement.</p>
        <p>The state's results mirrored national trends, which, according to the National Assessment of Educational Progress, show steady improvement in recent years in fourth-grade math, but much more modest gains in the eighth grade. Because there are no national standardized tests, it is also difficult to compare students from one state to another.</p>
        <p>A study by the federal government last week showed that two years ago, before the tests were changed, New York State's fourth-grade math test was easier than most others, ranking below 28 of 32 other states in difficulty in that grade. The state's test in eighth-grade math was ranked below 12 other states'.</p>
        <p>This year New York City students' gains outpaced those statewide at every level. In seventh grade, for example, 55.5 percent of New York City students were at grade level or better, an increase of more than 11 percentage points from the year before. The state recorded 66.4 percent of seventh graders at grade level or above, only a 4.9 point jump.</p>
        <p>The state education commissioner, Richard P. Mills, said at a news conference in Albany that the city, like other districts, had focused heavily on teacher training and paid careful attention to the shortcomings revealed by past test scores. Mr. Mills said teachers were becoming more adept at working toward the new standards.</p>
        <p>''It is quite evident to me that teachers are teaching the curriculum," he said, and added that teachers were able to determine where students had trouble.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Mills singled out New York City for its climb in scores, he stopped short of crediting mayoral control of the schools for it. The Regents chancellor, Robert M. Bennett, who also spoke at the news conference, said that New York City is ''quite obviously on the right track.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mills tempered his praise yesterday with the acknowledgment that this year again, the performance of eighth-grade students was persistently low throughout the state. In New York City, only 45.6 percent of eighth graders were proficient in math.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to get much higher than that, but this clearly shows a step in the right direction,'' Mr. Mills said. ''There is considerable work ahead.''</p>
        <p>Over the years, the tests have shown that there is a stubborn drop-off as students get older. For example, 85 percent of third-grade students statewide met the standards, but that number fell to 58 percent in the eighth grade. New York City has been trying to improve its students' math performance for many years, beginning in 2000, when the schools chancellor then, Harold O. Levy, made it a primary focus.</p>
        <p>In explaining the scores yesterday, Mr. Bloomberg put heavy emphasis on teachers and on a contract agreement that had allowed the city to extend the school year by an extra two days and also add 150 minutes to the school week for struggling students.</p>
        <p>''Each year, that will build on what was done before, because in the past children went from one grade to another and they kept falling further and further behind,'' the mayor said. ''If they have the skills to go into the next year and understand what the wonderful teacher at the front of the room is saying, then they are not going to fall behind or at least they won't fall behind as fast or as far.''</p>
        <p>Others said that the city had been so far behind that it had nowhere to go but up. ''It all depends on whether you take a half-full or half-empty approach -- if your scores are lower than others, then of course you have so much room for improvement,'' said Alfred S. Posamentier, the dean of the education school at City College. ''There is constant pressure, at the cost obviously of the arts and social studies and other subjects.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most impressive achievement for New York City was that students improved as they moved from grade to grade, mostly defying the historic trend of proficiency levels dropping consistently each year as students aged.</p>
        <p>For instance, 55.5 percent of the city's seventh graders scored proficiently this year, up from 52.7 percent when they were sixth graders last year. New York State only recently began testing students in Grades 3 through 8 rather than in just fourth and eighth grade.</p>
        <p>''There is recognition now that youngsters have to grow year by year, whereas in the past we just had two snapshots,'' Mr. Mills said in an interview. ''There is no place to hide.''</p>
        <p>Some of the most significant gains in New York City and elsewhere came in middle-school grades.</p>
        <p>For instance, nearly 64 percent of the city's sixth-grade students met the state standards, up from 53 percent last year. Mr. Mills also said there were impressive gains from high-poverty, traditionally low-performing schools. Mr. Mills also said the gap between the performance of black and Hispanic students compared with whites was narrowing.</p>
        <p>That was true also in New York City, where, the mayor said, the largest gains on this year's test were achieved by black and Hispanic students, who posted improvements of about 9 percentage points.</p>
        <p>The city's school chancellor, Joel I. Klein, was not in the city to join the festivities. Instead, he was in Washington, where he attended a news conference with Mayor Adrian M. Fenty for the announcement of the appointment of Michelle Rhee, who ran a New York City education group that trained teachers, as the new schools chancellor.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
