<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sudan Relents on Peacekeepers in Darfur</title>
    <meta content="13darfur" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/world/africa/13darfur.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854145"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sudan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Darfur (Sudan)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">African Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Polgreen, Lydia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoge, Warren</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sudan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Sudan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Sudan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EFD7173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sudan Relents on Peacekeepers in Darfur</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sudan Relents on Peacekeepers in Darfur</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYDIA POLGREEN and WARREN HOGE; Lydia Polgreen reported from Dakar, and Warren Hoge from the United Nations.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Polgreen, Lydia; Hoge, Warren</byline>
      <dateline>DAKAR, Senegal, June 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sudan agrees to joint United Nations and African Union force of 20,000 peacekeepers in Darfur, after resisting for months; African Union officials hail announcement, but others note that Sudanese government has made similar pledges and then reversed itself; Sudan says majority of soldiers must be African, which may hamper efforts to raise force to full strength (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After resisting for months, Sudan has agreed to a joint United Nations and African Union force of nearly 20,000 peacekeepers in Darfur, its western province and the site of one of the world's worst humanitarian crises, the African Union said Tuesday.</p>
        <p>African Union officials hailed the announcement as a breakthrough, but others cautioned that the Sudanese government had made similar pledges only to reverse itself. Sudan has also set conditions for the deployment, including an insistence that a majority of the soldiers be African and that non-Africans be used only as a last resort, which may hamper efforts to raise the force to full strength.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sudan set conditions for the deployment, insisting that a majority of the soldiers be African, which may hamper efforts to raise the force to full strength.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After resisting for months, Sudan has agreed to a joint United Nations and African Union force of nearly 20,000 peacekeepers in Darfur, its western province and the site of one of the world's worst humanitarian crises, the African Union said Tuesday.</p>
        <p>African Union officials hailed the announcement as a breakthrough, but others cautioned that the Sudanese government had made similar pledges only to reverse itself. Sudan has also set conditions for the deployment, including an insistence that a majority of the soldiers be African and that non-Africans be used only as a last resort, which may hamper efforts to raise the force to full strength.</p>
        <p>Still, African Union officials said that the agreement offered the clearest hope yet that an enlarged and strengthened peacekeeping force would be deployed in Darfur, where the conflict pitting the government and its allied militias against rebel groups has driven 2.5 million people from their homes and killed at least 200,000.</p>
        <p>''It is a breakthrough moment,'' said Noureddine Mezni, a spokesman for the African Union in Sudan. ''We are hopeful.''</p>
        <p>The agreement was reached after two days of negotiations in Addis Ababa among the Sudanese government, the African Union and the United Nations over thorny issues, including where the troops would come from and whether the force would be under the command of the African Union or the United Nations.</p>
        <p>Difficult questions also arose about how long the force would be in place. Sudan relented only after the three sides agreed that the need for the force would be periodically reviewed, though their joint statement did not indicate how often.</p>
        <p>At the United Nations, Zalmay Khalilzad, the American ambassador, said more details on the agreement were needed, especially on whether non-African troops would be restricted.</p>
        <p>''If this is an unconditional acceptance, this would be a positive step that we would welcome,'' he said. ''But if it is conditional, as we hear, that there will be only African troops involved and no non-Africans, that is putting a condition on the acceptance, and that would be unacceptable.'' The Security Council announced that it would discuss the plan on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>A 7,000-troop African Union force has been working in Darfur since 2004, monitoring a long discarded cease-fire. With insufficient personnel or matériel to handle an area the size of France and a mandate that limits its authority to protect civilians, the force has been derided as ineffective.</p>
        <p>A peace agreement signed last May by the government and one of the rebel factions was supposed to lead to the deployment of a United Nations force, something government negotiators at the peace talks said they would accept.</p>
        <p>But Sudan's president, Omar Hassan al-Bashir, later denounced the idea of non-African troops in Darfur, contending that they would be considered occupiers and neo-colonialists. A large United Nations peacekeeping force is operating in southern Sudan, which emerged from nearly two decades of civil war in 2005.</p>
        <p>At a news conference in Addis Ababa, the African Union's Peace and Security Commissioner Said Djinnit said that Sudan had agreed to the deployment of a force of 17,000 to 19,000 troops, and that the command of the force would remain with the African Union. The United Nations would play a supporting role, and a majority of the troops would come from Africa.</p>
        <p>''We agreed that priority should be given to finding troops from Africa,'' Mutrif Siddig, the leader of the Sudanese negotiation team, told Reuters. ''If there are not enough contributions from Africa, then troops can be brought in from elsewhere.''</p>
        <p>Such formulations allow for unacceptable delay, said John Prendergast, a Sudan expert who helps lead Enough Project, an initiative of the Center for American Progress and the International Crisis Group to abolish genocide and mass atrocities.</p>
        <p>''The gulf between the rhetoric of acceptance and the reality of deployment is huge,'' he said, adding that haggling over the composition of the force ''is putting a condition on the deployment which ensures its failure.''</p>
        <p>Michèle Montas, the spokeswoman for Secretary General Ban Ki-moon, said she did not know whether there were any conditions on the composition of the force, but she did not rule out the possibility that all its members might end up being Africans.</p>
        <p>''We have always said consistently that we would be trying to get as many African troops as we could possibly get,'' she said, adding, ''if we can get enough African troops, it will be essentially African troops.''</p>
        <p>International pressure on the Sudanese government has built recently as the United States has called for additional sanctions, France's new president, Nicolas Sarkozy, has pledged a greater commitment to finding a solution and China has gone on the defensive as a result of increasing attempts by peace advocates to link the 2008 Olympics in Beijing to the crisis in Darfur. China has been criticized for its diplomatic and financial involvement with the government of Sudan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khalilzad added that American proposals for new sanctions were ''very much still under consideration,'' particularly if Sudan's announcement was conditional.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
