<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Place to Go If You Like It Hot</title>
    <meta content="13unde" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/dining/reviews/13unde.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854110"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="$25 AND UNDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/$25 and Under</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">East Village (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E1D8173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="764" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Place to Go If You Like It Hot</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Place to Go if You Like It Hot</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Meehan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MA la, the uppercut combo of chili heat and the peculiar numbing effect of the Sichuan peppercorn, is the flavor profile most associated with Sichuan eating.</p>
        <p>But while ma la is definitely the marquee attraction, Sichuan cuisine is no one-trick pony.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Grand Sichuan St. Marks in the East Village, one of four related restaurants in Manhattan, offers a way to deepen your understanding of Sichuan cuisine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MA la, the uppercut combo of chili heat and the peculiar numbing effect of the Sichuan peppercorn, is the flavor profile most associated with Sichuan eating.</p>
        <p>But while ma la is definitely the marquee attraction, Sichuan cuisine is no one-trick pony.</p>
        <p>In fact, it's a 23-trick pony: according to Fuchsia Dunlop's count in her excellent Sichuan cookbook ''Land of Plenty'' (W. W. Norton, 2003), that is the number of flavor profiles in the Sichuan canon.</p>
        <p>Grand Sichuan St. Marks in the East Village, one of four related Grand Sichuan restaurants in Manhattan, is a good place to deepen your understanding of several of them.</p>
        <p>For ma la, there are few pleasures as reliable as Sichuan dan dan noodles, room-temperature noodles tossed with minced pork, a few stalks of pickled greens and a villainously oily and spicy sauce that renders each slurp more punishing.</p>
        <p>Grand Sichuan's sliced pork with ''home special sauce'' is a great way to try some jia chang, which ''Land of Plenty'' translates as ''homestyle flavor.'' It gets sweetness from a miso-like bean paste and its depth and complexity are magnified by a few fermented black beans that dot the thin slices of pork, almost floral-tasting Chinese celery and big pieces of spicy green pepper (which taste positively timid after a bit of one of those little red Sichuan peppers in the dry and spicy chicken).</p>
        <p>One caveat: eat it hot. Like most dishes forged in the intense heat of a wok, its allure fades as it cools.</p>
        <p>Score some yan xiang, or smoked flavor, from tea-smoked duck, a staple of all the Grand Sichuan restaurants.</p>
        <p>And the Chong Qing dry and spicy chicken definitely has some hu la, or ''scorched chili pepper flavor,'' going on. I gave up counting the peppers on the plate after my 60th (I doubt I was even halfway done). I plunged my chopsticks into the red and black mountain of wok-toasted dried chilies, searching for the nuggets of fried chicken skin, meaty slices of barely cooked ginger or a bit of well-charred scallion hidden inside.</p>
        <p>Even though the order I overheard most often from neighboring tables was sesame chicken with brown rice (one of 30 mostly ho-hum lunch specials at $6.50 or less), the kitchen doesn't go gringo on dishes that should be truly, terrifyingly spicy. Egg the cooks on at your tongue's peril.</p>
        <p>Of the dishes that will get you sweating like you're in a sauna, the best is sliced fish with spicy sauce soup, nearly the most expensive thing on the menu at $16.95. It comes in a broad bowl capped with few handfuls of those little red Sichuan peppers atop a layer of spice-infused oil two fingers deep. (Fat is not a four-letter word in Sichuan.)</p>
        <p>Below, there are gently cooked slices of some anonymous white fish; sturdy ribs and wilted leaves of Napa cabbage; bean sprouts; Sichuan peppercorns; and scads of minced garlic, all coated in a red cloak of oily, spicy goodness. For a few dollars more you can add noodles and have a dish that would feed three people.</p>
        <p>But one dish alone would never do. Anyway, for a reprieve from the spicy onslaught, it's good to have a few vegetables on hand.</p>
        <p>Cold chopped cucumber with scallion sauce isn't a revelation, but it offers reliable relief. (As do the waiters and waitresses: water glasses are refilled with remarkable frequency, and beers are brought to the table seconds after they're ordered.)</p>
        <p>If you're fine with everything blazing like a wildfire, though, one of the best vegetable dishes is the sautéed spicy Chinese broccoli. A jumble of woody, just-cooked stems is punctuated with -- yeah, yeah, I know you saw it coming -- chili after chili.</p>
        <p>At the end of the meal, as we crushed through our fortune cookies, we winced at empty truism after empty aphorism until we got to the last cookie, which held this note: ''Ignore previous cookie.''</p>
        <p>Wry humor and good Chinese food in the East Village.</p>
        <p>We headed out into the harsh summer sun, beads of perspiration already dotting our faces.</p>
        <p>Grand Sichuan St. Marks  19-23 St. Marks Place (Third Avenue), East Village; (212) 529-4800.</p>
        <p>BEST DISHES Sliced pork with home special sauce; Chong Qing dry and spicy chicken; sliced fish with spicy sauce soup; Sichuan dan dan noodle; sautéed spicy Chinese broccoli.  PRICE RANGE Small dishes, $1.60 to $6.95; larger dishes and main courses, $5.95 to $17.50.  CREDIT CARDS All major cards.  HOURS 11:30 a.m. to 11 p.m. daily.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS Up a flight of stairs.</p>
        <p>$25 AND UNDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
