<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Village Takes a More Hospitable Approach to Day Laborers</title>
    <meta content="13labor" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/nyregion/13labor.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070627T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854233"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Day Laborers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805EEDF143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="961" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Village Takes a More Hospitable Approach to Day Laborers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Mamaroneck, Taking a More Hospitable Approach to Day Laborers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FERNANDA SANTOS</byline>
      <dateline>MAMARONECK, N.Y., June 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The placard, about the size of a record cover, was perched on the sidewalk outside a church on Old White Plains Road, so discreet it could have easily escaped the notice of drivers passing by. Steel-blue type on a white background offered a modest invitation to contractors used to trolling the streets here in search of help: Hire Workers!</p>
        <p>The new day-laborer hiring site opened its doors on Tuesday morning, hours after a long, contentious meeting in which a divided Board of Trustees accepted a court-mandated settlement forbidding police officers from asking such workers about their immigration status. The settlement stems from a federal judge's ruling over a lawsuit filed against the village in April 2006 by six day laborers who accused the police of harassment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new hiring site and an unrelated settlement herald what could be a big change in the way Mamaroneck deals with Hispanic day laborers who usually seek work from contractors at local streets and parks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The placard, about the size of a record cover, was perched on the sidewalk outside a church on Old White Plains Road, so discreet it could have easily escaped the notice of drivers passing by. Steel-blue type on a white background offered a modest invitation to contractors used to trolling the streets here in search of help: Hire Workers!</p>
        <p>The new day-laborer hiring site opened its doors on Tuesday morning, hours after a long, contentious meeting in which a divided Board of Trustees accepted a court-mandated settlement forbidding police officers from asking such workers about their immigration status. The settlement stems from a federal judge's ruling over a lawsuit filed against the village in April 2006 by six day laborers who accused the police of harassment.</p>
        <p>Though the new church-sponsored site and the settlement are unrelated, they herald what could be a momentous change in the way this village of 28,000 deals with the Hispanic day laborers who have for years solicited work from contractors at local streets and parks.</p>
        <p>''We have to try to put the ugly disputes of the past behind us and give the hiring site a chance,'' said Toni Pergola Ryan, one of the four trustees on the board.</p>
        <p>The site at the Strait Gate Church, which has a largely black congregation of about 1,300 families, is unusual. Though many churches have been welcoming to day laborers, Pablo Alvarado, director of the National Day Laborer Organizing Network, said only a handful of the country's approximately 65 hiring sites are associated with black congregations.</p>
        <p>''It's an unusual gesture, and it's a beautiful one, particularly because we know there have been tensions between African-Americans and Latinos in places where they compete against one another for these types of jobs,'' Mr. Alvarado said.</p>
        <p>The project got off to a slow start, attracting seven workers on Tuesday -- about a quarter of the number that typically gather near Columbus Park, a few blocks away. Two of them were hired.</p>
        <p>The church, founded in 1932 by Elder John Brown and now led by his grandson, Bishop Wayne L. Powell, has a history of community outreach. In the 1970s, the church opened a homeless shelter, the first in Westchester County's Long Island Sound shore, and faced intense protest (the shelter has since closed). The church has also financed a school for disadvantaged children in the Dominican Republic, and sent Bishop Powell to Kenya to help dig wells for the nomadic Masai tribe.</p>
        <p>''Our first responsibility is to humanity, and it doesn't matter the color, the education or the financial situation,'' said Bishop Powell, who has been pastor of the church since 1984. ''We're here to help people however we can, and we're not afraid to ruffle some feathers.''</p>
        <p>The opening of the hiring site, as well as the vote on the settlement, inspired nearly two hours of heated debate at the trustees' meeting Monday night, with at least a dozen residents taking turns at the microphone to voice concerns about traffic and becoming a magnet for illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>''I'd like to know who is going to check if these workers are illegal,'' Donna Dickerson, 39, a mother of two who lives within steps of the site, said at the meeting. ''Rest assured that we'll be taking photographs, taking down license plates and forwarding them to the authorities.''</p>
        <p>In the end, the trustees voted 3-1 to approve the settlement, with the village's mayor, Philip J. Trifiletti, casting the dissenting vote. Because of the timing of the settlement vote and the opening of the hiring center, the village counsel recommended that one of the trustees, Tony Fava, recuse himself from the vote. Mr. Fava once held a financial interest on property owned by the Strait Gate Church.</p>
        <p>Under the settlement, Mamaroneck will pay $550,000 in fees to the plaintiffs' lawyers, bringing the total cost of the litigation to more than $1.2 million. In addition, the village agreed not to assign officers to patrol places where day laborers assemble, except to respond to complaints, and to post signs on nearby streets for a year directing workers and contractors to the church site.</p>
        <p>''This agreement is a milestone, and we hope it will serve as a cautionary example to other communities engaged in battles to remove immigrants who are seen as undesirables these days,'' said Cesar Perales, president of the Puerto Rican Legal Defense and Education Fund, which filed the lawsuit on behalf of the day laborers.</p>
        <p>The Hispanic Resource Center, a local advocacy group financed by grants and donations, will operate the hiring site, which opens at 6 a.m. Monday to Saturday. It will also offer English and citizenship classes, on-the-job safety courses and nutrition workshops at the church to laborers who are not hired on any given day.</p>
        <p>The workers will assemble inside the smaller of the church's two worship rooms, a space of wood-paneled walls and stained-glass windows. Contractors can pull into the church's parking lot and tell a site employee how many workers they want to hire; the employee will then summon the workers, in the order in which their names were drawn in a lottery held each morning.</p>
        <p>''This is a work in progress, but we hope the day laborers will have confidence in us and come to the site to look for work,'' said Mariana Boneo, the resource center's executive director. ''And we hope the people of this town will eventually come to our side.''</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, one of the residents who raised questions about the site at the trustees' meeting extended an olive branch. The resident, Glenn Tippett, stopped by the church and dropped off jugs of coffee and trays of bagels to the site's staff and the few day laborers who had shown up looking for work.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 27, 2007, Wednesday  An article on June 13 about a more hospitable approach to day laborers taken by the village of Mamaroneck, N.Y., referred imprecisely to the number of hiring sites in the country. According to the National Day Labor Organizing Network, there are approximately 65 formal sites, like the one at the Strait Gate Church in Mamaroneck. But there are hundreds more informal gathering places for day laborers, including street corners and parking lots. (The first nationwide study of day laborers, released in 2006, counted more than 500 sites.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 27, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article on June 13 about a more hospitable approach to day laborers taken by the village of Mamaroneck, N.Y., referred imprecisely to the number of hiring sites in the country. According to the National Day Labor Organizing Network, there are approximately 65 formal sites, like the one at the Strait Gate Church in Mamaroneck. But there are hundreds more informal gathering places for day laborers, including street corners and parking lots. (The first nationwide study of day laborers, released in 2006, counted more than 500 sites.)</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
