<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TODAY IN BUSINESS</title>
    <meta content="13biztoday" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854204"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE4DF143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="911" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TODAY IN BUSINESS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GIFTS FOR FAITH-BASED GROUPS -- Over the past 20 years Congress has given almost 900 grants to faith-based groups through the use of provisions called earmarks, including two decommissioned Coast Guard cutters that were given to a mission group in California. But rather than use the vessels to provide medical care, as Congress had directed, the group sold them both. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>YIELDS RISE, DRIVING SHARES DOWN -- The cost of borrowing headed higher as yields on the 10-year Treasury note, a key benchmark, hit a five-year high, and that drove the stock market down sharply. [C1.]</p>
        <p>NEW SERVINGS AT CONAGRA -- ConAgra Foods was built from dozens of acquisitions with brands that struggled to keep up with their competitors. But a new chief executive, Gary M. Rodkin, is trying to revive its brands with new products like Healthy Choice dinners that do not become mushy when microwaved, Orville Redenbacher popcorn that is low in sodium but still has a salty taste, and Chef Boyardee microwave-ready macaroni and cheese. [C1.]</p>
        <p>WOOING ASIAN GAMBLERS -- Casino operators in Las Vegas have become much more aggressive in wooing Asians both domestically and abroad, aiming not just at the newly wealthy from China, who in recent years have emerged as Las Vegas's best customers, but also Asian-Americans and recent immigrants from the Pacific Rim. [C1.]</p>
        <p>SIGNS OF A BACKLASH -- Robert E. Rubin, a Treasury secretary in President Bill Clinton's administration, made the case for private equity and hedge fund managers' paying more in taxes, a sign that the backlash against the tremendous wealth being created by managers of hedge funds may be gaining strength. [C3.]</p>
        <p>CHANGES IN JOURNAL'S NEWSROOM -- The Wall Street Journal, already roiled by a proposed takeover by Rupert Murdoch, will announce a major newsroom shake-up, including the reassignment and replacement of several top editors, officials there say. [C1.]</p>
        <p>A PHONE WITHOUT A KEYBOARD -- If there is a billion-dollar gamble underlying Apple's iPhone, it lies in what the cellphone does not have: a mechanical keyboard. The absence of a keyboard allows for a bigger screen, but the downside is that typing is done by pecking on the screen with thumbs or fingers. [C1.]</p>
        <p>FUTURE OF JAGUAR AND LAND ROVER -- Ford said that it was working with financial advisers to sort out the future of Jaguar and Land Rover, the two British brands that have been rumored to be up for sale for more than a year. [C3.]</p>
        <p>PROFIT GROWTH AT LEHMAN  -- Lehman Brothers reported that its profit in the second quarter rose 27 percent, a record for the investment bank and potentially auguring a good week for Wall Street earning reports. [C4.]</p>
        <p>ENERGY BILL DEBATED IN SENATE -- The Senate began debate on a sprawling bill to reduce oil consumption, with top Democrats circulating a proposal to provide $10 billion in loans for plants that make diesel fuel from coal. [A16.]</p>
        <p>A DANONE DISPUTE IN CHINA -- A dispute between Groupe Danone, the French multinational company, and a brash Chinese executive has escalated into a battle for control of China's largest beverage maker. [C8.]</p>
        <p>INFLATION, BUT NO OVERHEATING -- Inflation in China reached a 27-month high of 3.4 percent in May, but the increases in consumer prices were heavily concentrated in food while figures for growth in the money supply and in loans suggested that the broader economy was not yet overheating. [C8.]</p>
        <p>GREENER PLANES, FROM EUROPE -- The European Union is planning a 1.6 billion-euro public-private partnership to help its aviation industry develop a generation of greener and quieter aircraft. [C8.]</p>
        <p>VOTE CRITICAL OF EXECUTIVE PAY -- Yahoo said that about a third of its shareholders had voted against the re-election of one or more company directors. The vote against some directors had been recommended by three Wall Street advisory firms that had criticized the compensation committee for awarding bonus and retention pay in the form of 6.8 million stock options to Terry S. Semel, Yahoo's chief executive, in a year when the company's shares dropped nearly 35 percent. [C3.]</p>
        <p>SAVING WEB SEARCH HISTORIES -- Google announced that it would cut back on how long it keeps the Web search histories of users, to 18 months from 24. [C3.]</p>
        <p>ART IMITATING ADVERTISING -- A coming television series about Madison Avenue, set in the days when sponsors' products were regularly woven into the plots of shows, is -- yes -- getting a sponsor whose product will be regularly woven into the plot of each episode. The series, ''Mad Men,'' will run on AMC, and be sponsored by the Jack Daniel's brand of Tennessee whiskey sold by the Brown-Forman Corporation. Advertising: Stuart Elliott. [C5.]</p>
        <p>MOVIE TRAILERS FOR ADULTS -- Hollywood is retrofitting its rating system to give studios a chance to show racier trailers for movies online. [E1.]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>Business Briefing  Articles on these developments are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>RESTITUTION IN CA FRAUD -- Stephen Richards, former sales chief of the software maker CA, agrees to pay more than $29 million in restitution for an accounting fraud. (DOW JONES/AP)</p>
        <p>BLOCKBUSTER RENTAL PLAN -- Blockbuster is offering a lower-priced plan for online movie rentals as it competes with Netflix. It said it would cut prices $1 a month for customers who order movies online only. (AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GIFTS FOR FAITH-BASED GROUPS -- Over the past 20 years Congress has given almost 900 grants to faith-based groups through the use of provisions called earmarks, including two decommissioned Coast Guard cutters that were given to a mission group in California. But rather than use the vessels to provide medical care, as Congress had directed, the group sold them both. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>YIELDS RISE, DRIVING SHARES DOWN -- The cost of borrowing headed higher as yields on the 10-year Treasury note, a key benchmark, hit a five-year high, and that drove the stock market down sharply. [C1.]</p>
        <p>NEW SERVINGS AT CONAGRA -- ConAgra Foods was built from dozens of acquisitions with brands that struggled to keep up with their competitors. But a new chief executive, Gary M. Rodkin, is trying to revive its brands with new products like Healthy Choice dinners that do not become mushy when microwaved, Orville Redenbacher popcorn that is low in sodium but still has a salty taste, and Chef Boyardee microwave-ready macaroni and cheese. [C1.]</p>
        <p>WOOING ASIAN GAMBLERS -- Casino operators in Las Vegas have become much more aggressive in wooing Asians both domestically and abroad, aiming not just at the newly wealthy from China, who in recent years have emerged as Las Vegas's best customers, but also Asian-Americans and recent immigrants from the Pacific Rim. [C1.]</p>
        <p>SIGNS OF A BACKLASH -- Robert E. Rubin, a Treasury secretary in President Bill Clinton's administration, made the case for private equity and hedge fund managers' paying more in taxes, a sign that the backlash against the tremendous wealth being created by managers of hedge funds may be gaining strength. [C3.]</p>
        <p>CHANGES IN JOURNAL'S NEWSROOM -- The Wall Street Journal, already roiled by a proposed takeover by Rupert Murdoch, will announce a major newsroom shake-up, including the reassignment and replacement of several top editors, officials there say. [C1.]</p>
        <p>A PHONE WITHOUT A KEYBOARD -- If there is a billion-dollar gamble underlying Apple's iPhone, it lies in what the cellphone does not have: a mechanical keyboard. The absence of a keyboard allows for a bigger screen, but the downside is that typing is done by pecking on the screen with thumbs or fingers. [C1.]</p>
        <p>FUTURE OF JAGUAR AND LAND ROVER -- Ford said that it was working with financial advisers to sort out the future of Jaguar and Land Rover, the two British brands that have been rumored to be up for sale for more than a year. [C3.]</p>
        <p>PROFIT GROWTH AT LEHMAN  -- Lehman Brothers reported that its profit in the second quarter rose 27 percent, a record for the investment bank and potentially auguring a good week for Wall Street earning reports. [C4.]</p>
        <p>ENERGY BILL DEBATED IN SENATE -- The Senate began debate on a sprawling bill to reduce oil consumption, with top Democrats circulating a proposal to provide $10 billion in loans for plants that make diesel fuel from coal. [A16.]</p>
        <p>A DANONE DISPUTE IN CHINA -- A dispute between Groupe Danone, the French multinational company, and a brash Chinese executive has escalated into a battle for control of China's largest beverage maker. [C8.]</p>
        <p>INFLATION, BUT NO OVERHEATING -- Inflation in China reached a 27-month high of 3.4 percent in May, but the increases in consumer prices were heavily concentrated in food while figures for growth in the money supply and in loans suggested that the broader economy was not yet overheating. [C8.]</p>
        <p>GREENER PLANES, FROM EUROPE -- The European Union is planning a 1.6 billion-euro public-private partnership to help its aviation industry develop a generation of greener and quieter aircraft. [C8.]</p>
        <p>VOTE CRITICAL OF EXECUTIVE PAY -- Yahoo said that about a third of its shareholders had voted against the re-election of one or more company directors. The vote against some directors had been recommended by three Wall Street advisory firms that had criticized the compensation committee for awarding bonus and retention pay in the form of 6.8 million stock options to Terry S. Semel, Yahoo's chief executive, in a year when the company's shares dropped nearly 35 percent. [C3.]</p>
        <p>SAVING WEB SEARCH HISTORIES -- Google announced that it would cut back on how long it keeps the Web search histories of users, to 18 months from 24. [C3.]</p>
        <p>ART IMITATING ADVERTISING -- A coming television series about Madison Avenue, set in the days when sponsors' products were regularly woven into the plots of shows, is -- yes -- getting a sponsor whose product will be regularly woven into the plot of each episode. The series, ''Mad Men,'' will run on AMC, and be sponsored by the Jack Daniel's brand of Tennessee whiskey sold by the Brown-Forman Corporation. Advertising: Stuart Elliott. [C5.]</p>
        <p>MOVIE TRAILERS FOR ADULTS -- Hollywood is retrofitting its rating system to give studios a chance to show racier trailers for movies online. [E1.]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>Business Briefing  Articles on these developments are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>RESTITUTION IN CA FRAUD -- Stephen Richards, former sales chief of the software maker CA, agrees to pay more than $29 million in restitution for an accounting fraud. (DOW JONES/AP)</p>
        <p>BLOCKBUSTER RENTAL PLAN -- Blockbuster is offering a lower-priced plan for online movie rentals as it competes with Netflix. It said it would cut prices $1 a month for customers who order movies online only. (AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
