<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clemens Joins Teammates; Johnson Stays in Desert</title>
    <meta content="13pins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070615T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854239"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEEDF143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="837" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clemens Joins Teammates; Johnson Stays in Desert</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Roger Clemens is not a scheduled starter against the Arizona Diamondbacks this week, yet he was at Yankee Stadium yesterday, roaming the clubhouse and the field like any other teammate. The Yankees have told Clemens he can come and go as he pleases on the days he does not start, but Clemens is here now.</p>
        <p>''Because it's in your contract and it gives you certain privileges, I think everybody assumed it was going to be on a regular basis,'' Manager Joe Torre said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Roger Clemens is not a scheduled starter against the Arizona Diamondbacks this week, yet he was at Yankee Stadium yesterday, roaming the clubhouse and the field like any other teammate. The Yankees have told Clemens he can come and go as he pleases on the days he does not start, but Clemens is here now.</p>
        <p>''Because it's in your contract and it gives you certain privileges, I think everybody assumed it was going to be on a regular basis,'' Manager Joe Torre said.</p>
        <p>''That's why my stance was, 'Let's see what problems, if any, it causes, and then we'll deal with it,' '' Torre said. ''He certainly has the right to exercise it, and I don't know what's going to happen. But him being here, I think, indicates he certainly wants to be here, and his kids are a little bit older, too, than they were in Houston.''</p>
        <p>While Clemens is here this week, another 4,000-strikeout pitcher is not. The Arizona left-hander Randy Johnson is not scheduled to pitch in this series, and Diamondbacks Manager Bob Melvin and General Manager Josh Byrnes told him to do his between-starts work at home, as he has done since he began recovery from back surgery.</p>
        <p>''It just makes sense, at least for right now,'' Melvin said. ''It just limits another trip for him. He's got to put a back brace on to fly. There are a lot of things he has to do to get himself comfortable on a flight. If we can alleviate some of that, we're going to do it. He actually wanted to come here.''</p>
        <p>Johnson, a former Yankee, is 4-2 with a 3.52 earned run average in nine starts for Arizona. He has 70 strikeouts in 53 2/3 innings and will make his next start in Baltimore on Friday.</p>
        <p>DAMON STAYING IN THE OUTFIELD -- Five years ago, when the Yankees visited Coors Field in Denver, Joe Torre gave first baseman Nick Johnson his first career start in left field. Johnson slipped in the outfield in pursuit of a line drive, and Torre still remembers the play.</p>
        <p>''It wasn't very comfortable for him, or for me, either,'' he said.</p>
        <p>To that end, Torre said it was unlikely that he would give Johnny Damon his first career start at first base next week when the Yankees play in Denver and San Francisco, two National League parks where the designated hitter is not used.</p>
        <p>Torre said he would keep Melky Cabrera in center field, but might use Damon in a corner outfield spot to rest Hideki Matsui or Bobby Abreu. But Damon has been working out at first base, and said he would be confident there.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of guys who have played first base that I think I could move around better than,'' Damon said.</p>
        <p>TORRE REASSURES MUSSINA -- Mike Mussina was upset to be removed from his last start in the seventh inning after only 79 pitches. He said after the game that he had probably lost Joe Torre's trust because of his uneven season, but Torre met with Mussina and assured him that was not true.</p>
        <p>''I trust him, and I told him that,'' Torre said, adding later, ''He has enough in the bank not to have to audition.''</p>
        <p>POSADA JR. PROVIDES INSPIRATION -- Joe Torre said he was touched by Jorge Posada Jr.'s appearance at his father's charity dinner on Monday. The boy, who is 7, was born with craniosynostis, in which the bones in the skull fuse together before the brain grows.</p>
        <p>Posada's foundation raises money for the disease.</p>
        <p>''Jorge Jr. got up there and welcomed the people there,'' Torre said. ''It was incredible stuff. You talk about wanting to cry. He was like a little man when he was being interviewed on the video, talking about the problem that I can't pronounce.''</p>
        <p>Posada said his son was not inhibited in any way by the condition, which is checked once a year.</p>
        <p>As Torre surmised, he is comfortable with a microphone, too. ''He's not shy,'' Posada said.</p>
        <p>MATCHUPS FROM OCTOBERS PAST -- Except for the Houston Astros, every team that has won a National League pennant has faced the Yankees at least once in the World Series. Thus, nearly every interleague matchup is a rematch of a past Series, including the classic Yankees-Diamondbacks series in 2001.</p>
        <p>There were many memorable moments in that Series, but Bob Melvin, then an Arizona coach, shared an unusual one.</p>
        <p>''The three-foot rat over in that corner that we had to get rid of,'' Melvin said, while sitting in the visiting dugout yesterday. ''That got a lot of people's attention. When I first saw it, I thought it was a cat. They had to come in here and make it extinct. I can't believe they got the blood stain out.''</p>
        <p>A rat the size of a cat? Really?</p>
        <p>''As the seasons go by, I might embellish it a little bit,'' Melvin said, smiling. ''By next year, it'll be a dragon.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 15, 2007, Friday  A report in the Yankees notebook on Wednesday about catcher Jorge Posada's 7-year-old son, Jorge Jr., misspelled the name of a condition that the boy was born with in which the bones in the skull fuse prematurely. It is craniosynostosis, not craniosynostis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 15, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>A report in the Yankees notebook on Wednesday about catcher Jorge Posada's 7-year-old son, Jorge Jr., misspelled the name of a condition that the boy was born with in which the bones in the skull fuse prematurely. It is craniosynostosis, not craniosynostis.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
