<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Returning to a Favorite Role for an Almost-Final Goodbye</title>
    <meta content="13mano" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/arts/dance/13mano.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854126"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">American Ballet Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ferri, Alessandra</person>
        <person class="online_producer">MacMillan, Kenneth</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E7D7173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="594" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Returning to a Favorite Role for an Almost-Final Goodbye</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Returning to a Favorite Role for an Almost-Final Goodbye</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROSLYN SULCAS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alessandra Ferri has given many riveting performances in the title role of Kenneth MacMillan's ''Manon,'' a near-perfect vehicle for the dramatic intelligence and physical gifts that have made her one of the great ballerinas of the last two decades.</p>
        <p>When American Ballet Theater gave its premiere of this ballet in 1993, the Italian-born Ms. Ferri -- already closely identified with MacMillan's work during her early career at the Royal Ballet -- danced the title role. On Monday night, with the same company, Ms. Ferri danced the first of her performances in ''Manon'' before retiring from the stage next week with a final appearance in MacMillan's ''Romeo and Juliet.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alessandra Ferri gave a no-holds-barred performance of Kenneth MacMillan’s “Manon” that is likely to remain unforgettable for those lucky enough to be there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Alessandra Ferri has given many riveting performances in the title role of Kenneth MacMillan's ''Manon,'' a near-perfect vehicle for the dramatic intelligence and physical gifts that have made her one of the great ballerinas of the last two decades.</p>
        <p>When American Ballet Theater gave its premiere of this ballet in 1993, the Italian-born Ms. Ferri -- already closely identified with MacMillan's work during her early career at the Royal Ballet -- danced the title role. On Monday night, with the same company, Ms. Ferri danced the first of her performances in ''Manon'' before retiring from the stage next week with a final appearance in MacMillan's ''Romeo and Juliet.''</p>
        <p>Dancing with the Italian guest artist Roberto Bolle, making his debut with Ballet Theater (and at the Met) as her hapless lover, Des Grieux, Ms. Ferri gave a no-holds-barred performance that is likely to remain unforgettable for those lucky enough to be there.</p>
        <p>Erotic chemistry onstage, just as in life, is an unpredictable thing. Without it, there's little in ''Manon'' to hold the attention or explain the young girl's initial impulsive flight with the young student -- and her subsequent return to him after becoming mistress to the wealthy Monsieur G. M. (Macmillan based his ballet on Abbé Prévost's 18th-century romantic novel rather than on the Massenet or Puccini operas, although a patchwork of Massenet pieces constitute the score.)</p>
        <p>Ms. Ferri and Mr. Bolle, who have frequently danced together, have chemistry in spades, and their first-act bedroom pas de deux, with its ecstatic lifts and rapturous embraces, made a seamless and moving poem of the choreography. (At the end, both dancers fell flat to the floor after the final embrace, exhausted and exhilarated.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolle also gave a remarkable account of his character's opening solo, an extremely difficult series of adagio extensions, almost academic in their demand for perfect body placement and control. But nothing seems to hold much fear for Mr. Bolle, a dancer of Greek-god proportions and virile intensity who also has a plush, feline grace and a beautiful line -- that perfectly aligned fingertip-to-toetip stretch of the body so important to ballet.</p>
        <p>There's not much to do with the character of Des Grieux; he may be corrupted into theft and murder by his love for Manon, but he essentially remains blandly decent. Manon, however, remains prime dramatic ballerina territory, and Ms. Ferri made the most of every moment.</p>
        <p>From her astonishingly convincing entrance as a fresh but already manipulative 16-year-old (we immediately see her kinship to her dissolute brother, ready to sell her to the highest bidder) to the moral degeneracy that accompanies her decision to leave Des Grieux, she shows her character as fundamentally flawed, almost blameless in her amoral vacuity.</p>
        <p>Through her gorgeously cambered feet, the supple arch of her back and her beautiful arms, Ms. Ferri used every step as an expression of character, exulting in her sexual power at the beginning, despairing in an extraordinarily powerful rendering of the finale.</p>
        <p>The evening rightly belonged to Ms. Ferri and Mr. Bolle, but Ethan Stiefel's debut as the dastardly Lescaut and Gillian Murphy as his mistress deserve their own plaudits.</p>
        <p>Louche, cunning and funny, Mr. Stiefel lent his beautiful classical form to a role that can often look deadly dull or simply silly, and his rapport with Ms. Ferri made something believable of their dissolute choices. All in all, this was just about as perfect a ''Manon'' as there is likely to be.</p>
        <p>American Ballet Theater performs ''Manon'' through Saturday at the Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center; (212) 362-6000 or abt.org.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
