<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Sinkerball Night, Yankees Keep Rising</title>
    <meta content="13yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/sports/baseball/13yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854260"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Arizona Diamondbacks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wang, Chien-Ming</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Abreu, Bobby</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E3DE143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="924" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Sinkerball Night, Yankees Keep Rising</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On Sinkerball Night, Yankees Keep Rising</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a bad night to be a worm, a lonely night to be an outfielder and -- as always, these days -- a great night to be a Yankee.</p>
        <p>Two of the major leagues' pre-eminent sinkerballers faced each other at Yankee Stadium last night in Brandon Webb of the Arizona Diamondbacks and Chien-Ming Wang of the Yankees. The result was predictable: a steady flow of ground balls and another victory for the surging Yankees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chien-Ming Wang worked seven innings, riding a Bobby Abreu homer to beat Arizona and bring the Yankees’ record to .500 for the first time since May 9.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was a bad night to be a worm, a lonely night to be an outfielder and -- as always, these days -- a great night to be a Yankee.</p>
        <p>Two of the major leagues' pre-eminent sinkerballers faced each other at Yankee Stadium last night in Brandon Webb of the Arizona Diamondbacks and Chien-Ming Wang of the Yankees. The result was predictable: a steady flow of ground balls and another victory for the surging Yankees.</p>
        <p>Wang worked seven innings, riding a Bobby Abreu homer to beat Arizona, 4-1, and bring the Yankees' record to .500 for the first time since May 9. With a 31-31 record, the Yankees have 100 games to see if they can make the playoffs for the 13th season in a row.</p>
        <p>''When you win, you don't feel you're ever going to lose,'' Manager Joe Torre said. ''Tonight you knew we were going to have our hands full because of who we were facing, but pitching is the only way.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees, who have won seven in a row and 10 of 12, trail the Boston Red Sox by nine and a half games in the American League East but stand five and a half back in the wild-card race, with Detroit and Cleveland tied atop the A.L. Central at 37-26.</p>
        <p>''It feels good to be back at .500,'' said Mariano Rivera, who earned the save and has not allowed a run in his last nine appearances. ''But we can't stop there. We have to keep going and fighting hard.''</p>
        <p>Wang had the lowest home run rate in the majors last season, allowing .5 homers every nine innings. Webb was second, at .57. Only Derek Lowe of the Dodgers allowed fewer fly balls, on average, than Webb and Wang.</p>
        <p>Through six innings last night, neither team's center fielder or right fielder had made a putout. Wang actually generated fewer than half his outs on the ground (9 of 21), but the Diamondbacks still could not do much with him.</p>
        <p>''Today, I left my ball high; they hit it hard,'' said Wang, who was working with an extra day of rest. ''Maybe too strong.''</p>
        <p>Wang had not allowed a homer since May 5, when Ben Broussard of Seattle connected to ruin Wang's perfect game with one out in the eighth inning. Chad Tracy lined a homer into the right-field seats with one out in the fourth last night, but by then Wang already had a lead.</p>
        <p>Johnny Damon led off the first inning with a grounder to second that Orlando Hudson, a Gold Glove winner last season, threw away for an error. Webb fell behind Derek Jeter on a 3-1 count, and Damon took off for second.</p>
        <p>Because Jeter hits to the opposite field so often, it was the shortstop, Stephen Drew, who was covering the bag. Drew darted to second, only to see Jeter's grounder skitter through the spot he vacated. Instead of a double play, it was a single that put runners on the corners.</p>
        <p>''That was the key play of the whole game for us,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Abreu made it so by hitting a flat sinker over the fence in right-center field for his fourth home run of the season. Abreu is 20 for 41 in June, with 12 runs batted in over 11 games. It has been a swift turnaround for a hitter whose May average (.208) was the worst of any calendar month of his career.</p>
        <p>''I don't think too much at the plate,'' Abreu said. ''In the past, I was thinking -- taking some good pitches to hit and swinging at bad pitches. But now I feel good.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees were mostly punchless after the home run, with Webb, last season's Cy Young award winner in the National League, retiring 10 of the next 11 hitters. But Abreu's home run was all Wang needed.</p>
        <p>Through six innings, the Diamondbacks had Tracy's homer and five singles, and two of their hardest hits were line drives by Drew that were snagged by first baseman Miguel Cairo.</p>
        <p>It was a meager output until the seventh, when Tony Clark led off with a single to center and the next two hitters slammed the ball to center field. Melky Cabrera had gotten no chances all night, but he caught both balls for outs.</p>
        <p>Up stepped the No. 9 hitter, Chris Snyder, and Wang hit him with a pitch. That brought up Chris Young, who lined a shot toward left field that Jeter snared for the final out.</p>
        <p>Two fly outs and a line out made for an unusual sequence for Wang, who had recorded at least one ground out in each of his last 27 innings. His night was finished, and he made sure to say something to Jeter after the catch.</p>
        <p>''Good job,'' Wang said he told Jeter, and he could have repeated that to all his teammates. The Yankees are rolling, and they are not surprised.</p>
        <p>''The thing we continue to remind them is this isn't happening by coincidence,'' Torre said. ''This is happening because they're working hard, and they're not going to be denied. It's a great attitude to have.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>First baseman Doug Mientkiewicz had a screw inserted in his right wrist yesterday, nine days after his injury in Boston. Mientkiewicz hopes to return by Aug. 1.  Pitcher Darrell Rasner, who broke his right index finger May 19, had two pins removed from his knuckle last Wednesday but said he has not begun throwing. Rasner still cannot curl the finger into his palm.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
