<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blair Compares News Media to 'Feral Beast' in Angry Parting Shot</title>
    <meta content="13britain" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/world/europe/13britain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854148"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">London (England)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EFD7173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="606" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blair Compares News Media to 'Feral Beast' in Angry Parting Shot</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Blair Compares News Media to ‘Feral Beast’ in Angry Parting Shot</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, June 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>British Prime Min Tony Blair uses one of his last speeches before he leaves office to settle scores with press corps he holds responsible for attacking him; he compares press to 'feral beast' and says that advent of 24-hour news cycle has made media slave to 'impact'; Blair has long had complicated relationship with press; some media organizations have accused Blair administration of relying on spin to court public favor (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the land that produced ''Scoop,'' Evelyn Waugh's comic novel of journalistic mischief, it would barely seem surprising for politicians to let rip at reporters. But was it going too far for Prime Minister Tony Blair to call the press a ''feral beast''?</p>
        <p>Up to a point, some reporters might have said, borrowing the expression from ''Scoop'' that mid-ranking editors used to contradict all-powerful proprietors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tony Blair used one of his last speeches before he leaves office to settle scores with a press corps he holds responsible for hounding him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the land that produced ''Scoop,'' Evelyn Waugh's comic novel of journalistic mischief, it would barely seem surprising for politicians to let rip at reporters. But was it going too far for Prime Minister Tony Blair to call the press a ''feral beast''?</p>
        <p>Up to a point, some reporters might have said, borrowing the expression from ''Scoop'' that mid-ranking editors used to contradict all-powerful proprietors.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, Mr. Blair was not in an ''up to a point'' mood. He seemed more in full-throated roar, using one of his last speeches before he leaves office in 15 days to settle scores with a press corps he holds responsible for hounding, badgering, blustering and bludgeoning the nation's leaders since he came to power 10 years ago.</p>
        <p>''The fear of missing out means today's media, more than ever before, hunts in a pack,'' he declared in the speech, at the Reuters headquarters here. ''In these modes it is like a feral beast, just tearing people and reputations to bits. But no one dares miss out.''</p>
        <p>He quoted a past prime minister, Stanley Baldwin, who berated the news media for having ''power without responsibility -- the prerogative of the harlot through the ages,'' a charge that borrowed from Kipling.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair also evoked the memory of Gladstone and Disraeli to note that he was not the first prime minister to face ''extraordinarily brutal treatment'' in the newspapers.</p>
        <p>And he acknowledged that his speech might ruffle feathers among the very people responsible for relaying his words to the world. ''I've made this speech after much hesitation,'' he said. ''I know it will be rubbished in certain quarters. But I also know this has needed to be said.''</p>
        <p>His targets were quick to respond. ''I think by and large the British press is pretty good,'' said Trevor Kavanagh, the former political editor of the top-selling tabloid, The Sun. ''I think it does its best to be level accurate and sensitive to the requirements of both the people it writes about and the people it writes for. This was a very strange speech.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair cited changes in reporting -- the impact of the Internet on traditional newspapers and broadcasters, and the advent of a 24-hour news cycle -- to say that ''the media are facing a hugely more intense form of competition than anything they have ever experienced before.''</p>
        <p>''They are not the masters of this change, but its victims. The result is a media that, increasingly and to a dangerous degree, is driven by 'impact.' Impact is what matters. It is all that can distinguish, can rise above the clamor, can get noticed. Impact gives competitive edge. Of course, the accuracy of a story counts. But it is secondary to impact.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair's relationship with the British news media has long been complicated. At first, his government paid ''inordinate attention'' to ''courting, assuaging and persuading the media,'' he said. He became known as much for courting the News Corporation of Rupert Murdoch, who owns The Sun, as for the aggressive policies toward news media of his onetime communications director, Alastair Campbell. But that did not spare Mr. Blair from criticism. While he has been credited with a talent for the telling phrase, the deft sound bite and impassioned oratory, his administration has been accused by media organizations of relying on spin to court public favor.</p>
        <p>''This government is paying the price for trying to triple count and mislead the public,'' Mr. Kavanagh told the BBC. ''A rather benign media has allowed this government to get away with political murder.''</p>
        <p>Of late, British journalists have seemed increasingly aggressive in questioning Mr. Blair.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
