<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bond Yields Soar, Driving Shares Down</title>
    <meta content="13bond" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/business/13bond.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854220"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Industrial Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bank of England</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenspan, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bajaj, Vikas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Greenspan, Alan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E0DF143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1036" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bond Yields Soar, Driving Shares Down</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bond Yields Soar, Driving Shares Down</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIKAS BAJAJ; Keith Bradsher contributed reporting from London.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bajaj, Vikas; Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Yields of 10-year Treasury note hit five-year high, climbing to 5.248 percent, up from 5.154 percent late June 11 as investors sell off notes and bonds; Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index closes down 1.07 percent, or 16.12 points, to 1,493 points; Dow Jones industrial average drops 1 percent, or 129.95, to 13,295.01; bond prices start falling after top official of Bank of England signals that policy makers in London might continue to raise interest rates; sell-off intensifies after Federal Reserve's former chairman Alan Greenspan says borrowing costs will climb, particularly for developing countries; investors' expectations of inflation, which traditionally drive bond yields higher, do not appear to be prime reason for move; economists and market specialists say recent sell-off suggests that investors have become more disenchanted with low rate of return from bonds at time when global economy is continuing to expand at robust pace; stock market rally and rising interest rates in Europe and Asia may also be pressuring American government debt; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The cost of borrowing headed higher yesterday and drove the stock market down sharply.</p>
        <p>Yields on the 10-year Treasury note -- a key benchmark that influences nearly all long-term interest rates, including home mortgages -- hit a five-year high, climbing to 5.248 percent yesterday, up from 5.154 percent late Monday as investors sold off notes and bonds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The cost of borrowing headed higher as yields on the 10-year Treasury note hit a five-year high, climbing to 5.248 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The cost of borrowing headed higher yesterday and drove the stock market down sharply.</p>
        <p>Yields on the 10-year Treasury note -- a key benchmark that influences nearly all long-term interest rates, including home mortgages -- hit a five-year high, climbing to 5.248 percent yesterday, up from 5.154 percent late Monday as investors sold off notes and bonds.</p>
        <p>Treasury yields, which have been rising steadily since the end of April and have started to weigh on the stock market, quashed an early afternoon stock rally. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index, a broad gauge of the market, closed down 1.07 percent, or 16.12 points, to 1,493 points; and the Dow Jones industrial average dropped 1 percent, or 129.95, to 13,295.01 points. [Page C10.]</p>
        <p>Bond prices, which move in the opposite direction from yields, started falling yesterday after the top official at the Bank of England signaled in a speech late Monday that policy makers in London might continue to raise interest rates.</p>
        <p>The sell-off intensified after Alan Greenspan, the former chairman of the Federal Reserve, said in a speech that he thought that borrowing costs would climb, particularly for developing countries.</p>
        <p>But investors' expectations of inflation, which traditionally drive bond yields higher, do not appear to be the prime reason for the move. Though inflation continues to run above the upper limit of the Federal Reserve's comfort level of about 2 percent, there has been little to suggest it is picking up pace.</p>
        <p>''This is not about inflation in my view,'' said Jane Caron, chief economic strategist at Dwight Asset Management, a bond firm based in Vermont. Yields ''got down to a level that were not particularly compelling.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the price of gold, which is widely seen as a hedge against inflation, has fallen in recent weeks, and the yields on inflation-protected securities have been rising.</p>
        <p>Instead, economists and market specialists said, the recent sell-off suggested that investors had become more disenchanted with the low rate of return from bonds at a time when the global economy is continuing to expand at a robust pace. The stock market rally and rising interest rates in Europe and Asia may also be pressuring American government debt</p>
        <p>Ms. Caron said there were also some indications that investors in Asia, including the region's central banks that are big purchasers of United States government debt, may be scaling back. In the past, Asian investors have bought Treasuries as yields approach 5 percent.</p>
        <p>This time, however, ''there is not a lot of buying coming in from Asia,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Officials in China, one of the biggest holders of American government debt, have said repeatedly that they have not and will not sell or reallocate to different currencies their existing foreign exchange reserve, currently at around $1.2 trillion. But officials of the People's Bank of China have publicly suggested on several occasions that they would seek to improve returns on new investments as money continued to pour into the reserves.</p>
        <p>The Chinese government has already distinguished itself from other governments in its willingness to take somewhat greater credit risk on foreign reserves, most notably through its purchase of an estimated $100 billion worth of American mortgage-backed securities.</p>
        <p>Since Chinese foreign exchange reserves are rising at more than $300 billion a year as a result of widening trade surpluses and net foreign investment, a decision by officials in Beijing to allocate a greater portion to other currencies could potentially cause ripples in the international currency markets.</p>
        <p>But the Chinese tend to move very gradually in any economic or financial policy decision, particularly regarding the currency, so most experts think it is unlikely that they are shifting sharply away from dollar-denominated purchases even with new money coming into their reserves.</p>
        <p>''They want to own dollars,'' said Harold S. Woolley, a managing director at Bessemer Trust, an investment firm in New York. ''Nobody forces them to sell goods to us and take dollars.''</p>
        <p>Another explanation for the rise in yields, economists suggest, is that investors are realizing that they had been wrong about the direction of interest rates in the last year or two.</p>
        <p>In the United States, investors had believed the slowing housing market would prompt the Fed to cut short-term interest rates. Not only has that not happened, but policy makers have steadfastly signaled that they would not do so until inflation expectations fell more significantly.</p>
        <p>That could explain, analyst said, why yields on long-term securities are rising faster than yields on short-term securities. For much of the last year, yields have been inverted or flat so shorter-term debt paid just as much, if not more, than longer-duration notes and bonds.</p>
        <p>In Europe and Asia central bankers have been raising rates in response to strong growth and worries about inflation -- and indicating that they are not done.</p>
        <p>''We are seeing increases in foreign interest rates, and there is lot of evidence that global economy is doing very well,'' said David Kelly, an economist at Putnam Investments, the mutual fund company based in Boston. He noted that many economists were even forecasting a pickup in the American economy, which slowed notably in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>There is some risk, however, that the higher yields and accompanying higher borrowing costs could put a damper on any resurgence.</p>
        <p>As of last week, the national average rate for a 30-year fixed mortgage was at 6.53 percent, up from 6.18 percent at the start of the year, according to Freddie Mac.</p>
        <p>Though that is still low by historical levels, rising rates would mean consumers who are refinancing or buying a home will have to spend more of their disposable income on monthly house payments than they have been. That could hurt consumer spending and the broader economy.</p>
        <p>Businesses will probably fare somewhat better, according to Mr. Kelly and others, because interest costs tend to have a relatively small impact on corporate profit. Also, business credit remains widely available and at good terms.</p>
        <p>''I don't see how this will shut anything off,'' said James W. Paulsen, chief investment strategist with Wells Capital Management. He said that yields would have to climb to 6 percent or more before borrowing costs start to hurt businesses.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
