<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Casting a Ballot Overseas Is Sometimes No Sure Bet</title>
    <meta content="13overseas" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/washington/13overseas.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854227"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2008 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Absentee Voting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Voter Registration and Requirements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Voter Registration and Requirements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Defense Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EFDF143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1373" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Casting a Ballot Overseas Is Sometimes No Sure Bet</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Casting Ballot From Abroad Is No Sure Bet</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN URBINA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Urbina, Ian</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over the last six years, the Defense Department has spent more than $30 million trying to find an efficient way for American soldiers and civilians living abroad to vote in elections back home.</p>
        <p>But with the presidential primaries approaching, the Pentagon's system, which is Web-based, remains slow, confusing and plagued with security and privacy problems. And that has left many of the five million Americans overseas uncertain that their vote will be counted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Pentagon’s system for allowing citizens living abroad to vote is plagued with security and privacy problems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over the last six years, the Defense Department has spent more than $30 million trying to find an efficient way for American soldiers and civilians living abroad to vote in elections back home.</p>
        <p>But with the presidential primaries approaching, the Pentagon's system, which is Web-based, remains slow, confusing and plagued with security and privacy problems. And that has left many of the five million Americans overseas uncertain that their vote will be counted.</p>
        <p>Fewer than 20 local election officials in the United States have said they want to use the military's Web system in the coming election. Just 63 voters used it in the 2006 election to request and return ballots over the Internet, according to a Defense Department study.</p>
        <p>Civilians are not given access to the system, even though the Defense Department is responsible for assisting all overseas voters. Security experts and Congressional auditors say the system is vulnerable to undetectable vote tampering and hacking. The Election Assistance Commission, which is responsible for creating guidelines to enable secure Internet voting, is years away from doing so.</p>
        <p>''A system should be in place, regardless of the cost, to make sure that the very defenders of our democracy have the opportunity to take part in it,'' wrote Sgt. James Mowrer, an Iowa National Guardsman deployed in Iraq who helped organize voters in his unit in 2006, in an e-mail message.</p>
        <p>But the traditional paper ballot system for overseas voters -- the one the Pentagon is trying to improve -- has also had problems for years.</p>
        <p>Typically, voters mail paper forms back and forth across continents as they try to register to vote, request a ballot and then return the ballot before the polls close. But the forms are often lost or delayed in the mail.</p>
        <p>Voters often wait until the last moment or get confused because rules and deadlines vary state to state. Poor planning, legal challenges or technical problems often lead local election officials to send ballots abroad too late.</p>
        <p>As a result, anywhere from a quarter to half of overseas voters fail in their attempt to vote, say voting experts at the National Defense Committee  and the Overseas Vote Foundation .</p>
        <p>Supporters of the military say that if national secrets and banking transactions are conveyed overseas electronically, it should be possible to do so with votes.</p>
        <p>''At a minimum, we need a means to transmit the unmarked ballot to service members, and that method needs to be user-friendly, secure and private,'' said Bob Carey, a senior fellow with the National Defense Committee, a private group that advocates for military voting rights. ''Right now the Pentagon's system does not do that.''</p>
        <p>Under the current paper system, overseas ballots are often contested because they arrive late, or without postage or postmark, as occurred on a wide scale in Florida in 2000.</p>
        <p>For the nearly three million military service members and their eligible dependents, the voting challenges are even greater because frequent redeployments move them around the world before election officials can send them unmarked ballots.</p>
        <p>Finding the proper mailing address, resolving whether the voted ballot must be notarized and determining the right size paper and envelope can be bewildering because each state has different rules.</p>
        <p>Many of the estimated two million civilians overseas who are eligible to vote -- especially missionaries, Peace Corps volunteers and other Americans working far from urban centers -- also complain of ballots arriving late or not at all.</p>
        <p>Military officials say their voting system is meant only to expand options beyond the use of regular mail, and the Pentagon has also tried to help soldiers by placing voting assistance officers in military units worldwide. Stewart Upton, a spokesman for the Defense Department, did not answer questions about the system except to say that the Pentagon was seeking suggestions from the private sector on ways to improve it before the next election.</p>
        <p>But Sergeant Mowrer said that during the midterm election last year, his unit's voting assistance officer was located at another base, so he took on the responsibility of organizing the voting for the 22 soldiers in his unit. He and a majority of his detachment sent in requests for absentee ballots, and while he received and returned his ballot, half of the other soldiers never received their ballot on time, he said.</p>
        <p>''There should be some kind of accountability in place to ensure that their votes reach their destination and are counted,'' he wrote.</p>
        <p>Part of the difficulty for military officials has been that they cannot force local election officials to standardize the rules, forms and due dates that apply to overseas voters. Each state has different rules.</p>
        <p>Local election officials are also partly to blame for the confusion, according to a draft report from the Government Accountability Office in April. It cited 18 states or territories that had inconsistent or misleading information instructing overseas voters how to cast their ballot.</p>
        <p>''It's red tape and hurdles,'' said Kent Deitemeyer, 58, a businessman who spends 10 months each year living in Christchurch, New Zealand, and the rest of the time at his home in Glen Allen, Va. He said that when he received his absentee ballot before the 2006 election, it came with a piece of paper with instructions how to fold it into an envelope that was to be used for mailing the ballot back.</p>
        <p>Though he said he was certain he folded it exactly as instructed, he received a notice weeks after the election with a handwritten box that was checked to inform him that his vote had not been counted because he had used an improper envelope.</p>
        <p>''When you're a military dad with a kid in Iraq you kind of want your vote to count,'' he said, explaining that he has a 24-year-old son serving in the Army.</p>
        <p>Many election officials say they have been reluctant to direct overseas voters to the Pentagon's Web page because it was too difficult to navigate. Instead they have encouraged overseas voters to consult more user-friendly Web sites like that of the Overseas Vote Foundation.</p>
        <p>In the 2006 election, the Defense Department used a Web-based system that cost more than $830,000 to design and operate. But election officials in only nine states permitted their voters abroad to use it, and just 63 voters used it to request and return ballots over the Internet during that election, according to a Defense Department report given to the Senate Armed Services Committee in May.</p>
        <p>''Do the math,'' said Representative Carolyn B. Maloney, Democrat of New York. ''In terms of those who actually tried to vote using the system in the 2006 election, that's more than $13,000 per vote.''</p>
        <p>''We could have flown their ballots back and forth first class for less money,'' she added.</p>
        <p>Security concerns also remain. In April, the G.A.O. said the method used to convert faxes to e-mail messages as voting documents that are sent between voters and election officials did not meet security requirements.</p>
        <p>Asked about the system the Defense Department is likely to use in 2008, three of the four computer scientists and electronic voting experts previously hired by the Defense Department to review the system in 2004 issued a report expressing concern. They concluded that the system was vulnerable to vote tampering or hacker attacks that could occur in undetected fashion and that therefore it should not be used.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, more than three-quarters of service members surveyed in a focus group conducted by the Defense Department in September said they were likely to vote over the Internet if security were adequate, according to the Government Accountability Office.</p>
        <p>Some local officials dismiss the security concerns as overblown.</p>
        <p>''Once doctors look at naked women long enough they say, who cares?'' said Pat Hollarn, elections supervisor for Okaloosa County, Fla., who favors Internet voting. ''We're the same way. We see ballots here often enough that we don't care. We're not interested in how people voted. We just want to be sure that they are allowed to vote and that their vote is counted.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Hollarn added that voters also hold an important responsibility. In the 2006 midterm election, 30 percent of all ballots she sent to voters overseas were returned because their mailing information had not been updated, she said.</p>
        <p>THE 2008 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
