<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Before Fourth Season, a Chat With Fifth and Sixth Graders</title>
    <meta content="13giants" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/sports/football/13giants.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854203"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Manning, Eli</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Barber, Tiki</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E5DF143FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Before Fourth Season, a Chat With Fifth and Sixth Graders</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Before Fourth Season, a Chat With Fifth and Sixth Graders</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, June 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eli Manning sat in the principal's office Tuesday, waiting to address a group of fifth and sixth graders.</p>
        <p>''I always get a little nervous when I'm sent in here,'' Manning said in jest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the running game a question mark after the retirement of Tiki Barber, more of the offensive load could fall on quarterback Eli Manning as he enters his fourth N.F.L. season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Eli Manning sat in the principal's office Tuesday, waiting to address a group of fifth and sixth graders.</p>
        <p>''I always get a little nervous when I'm sent in here,'' Manning said in jest.</p>
        <p>Manning is a long way from grade school, but as an N.F.L. quarterback, he is still on the hot seat. After his appearance at Hedgepeth-Williams Elementary School on Tuesday, Manning was headed to three days of minicamp, where his growth as a quarterback remains the most important piece of the Giants' offensive puzzle.</p>
        <p>With the running game a question mark after the retirement of Tiki Barber, more of the offensive load could fall on Manning as he enters his fourth N.F.L. season.</p>
        <p>Manning is well aware that this has been characterized as a make-or-break season, both for him, and for Giants Coach Tom Coughlin. But he said he has no regrets about his decision three years ago to shun the San Diego Chargers and engineer a trade to the Giants.</p>
        <p>''You appreciate playing in a town that's serious about their football,'' Manning said. ''You can go to other towns where if you lose, it doesn't really matter. That wouldn't be any fun. They might not be as hard on you, but at least here, you're in an organization and a town that expects to win. That's what you want to be a part of. I'm looking forward to a long future here.''</p>
        <p>Far from becoming the franchise quarterback the Giants envisioned, Manning's play leveled off last season, with 24 touchdowns, 18 interceptions and a 77.0 passer rating -- numbers that were similar to those of 2005, when he had 24 touchdowns, 17 interceptions and a 75.9 passer rating. The two other quarterbacks drafted the same year have enjoyed more success -- Ben Roethlisberger of the Pittsburgh Steelers, who has won a Super Bowl; and Philip Rivers of the Chargers, who made the Pro Bowl last season.</p>
        <p>The Giants took steps to help Manning by hiring Chris Palmer as quarterbacks coach in January. Palmer has made Manning's footwork a point of emphasis, with the goal of improving Manning's passing accuracy.</p>
        <p>''He's got a lot of different drills, mechanics stuff with footwork,'' Manning said. ''I can see a difference just from moving in the pocket and having your feet set ready to throw. When you avoid somebody or move around, you can still be mechanically sound.''</p>
        <p>Asked the most difficult thing about playing quarterback for the Giants, Manning paused before answering.</p>
        <p>''Trying to live up to the expectations that everyone has,'' he said. ''You try so hard, but especially in New York, you can have six great games, and all of sudden you have a bad one and they make you feel like you're a total failure. You've got to learn to trust yourself, and to trust your coaches. You can't get down after a few things go the wrong way.''</p>
        <p>Manning made his appearance at Hedgepeth-Williams as part of the What Moves U program organized by the National Football League and the American Heart Association, an initiative to encourage youngsters to become more active and physically fit.</p>
        <p>Some of the questions from fifth and sixth graders were ones that Manning expected, like ''What was it like watching your brother Peyton win the Super Bowl?''</p>
        <p>''I was excited for Peyton,'' he said. ''I know how hard it is to get there, how hard he's worked. So many things have to go your way. He was thrilled. I was excited for my mom. Between 14 seasons with my dad, and 9 with Peyton, that's 23 long years of rooting for a team to try and win a Super Bowl. It was a good experience, but I don't want to be watching too many more from the seats.''</p>
        <p>Other questions were more offbeat, like, ''Do you ever get hounded by the paparazzi?''</p>
        <p>''No,'' Manning said, smiling. ''That's for the celebrities.''</p>
        <p>Manning expects to be hounded by more questions, like whether he is ready to become a more consistent quarterback, and more of a vocal leader. None of those questions will be answered for certain at minicamp this week, but Manning said he saw no reason not to be optimistic.</p>
        <p>''We've been to the playoffs the last two years, and although we haven't finished the way we've wanted to, we have the ability to win games,'' he said. ''Last year going into the season, there were more expectations of us doing well. This year we're kind of under the radar, which can be nice. We can just focus.</p>
        <p>''The quarterback is always the leader. When you lose a veteran like Tiki, you lose some leadership. From a leadership standpoint, I'm going to have to do more, although when you look great teams, it's not just one guy. Yes, I'll probably do some more things. But I'm looking forward to that, and everything else.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
