<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Day Care Worker Is Convicted Of Raping a 4-Year-Old Boy</title>
    <meta content="13abuse" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/nyregion/13abuse.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854172"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E4D6173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="586" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Day Care Worker Is Convicted Of Raping a 4-Year-Old Boy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Day Care Worker Is Convicted of Raping a 4-Year-Old Boy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELLEN BARRY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Queens jury, forced to render a stark judgment on a videotaped confession, yesterday found a day care worker guilty of raping and sexually abusing a 4-year-old boy in her care.</p>
        <p>The prosecution relied heavily on a recording in which the worker, Khemwatie Bedessie, gave a detailed account of abusing and having intercourse with the boy. The defense then put her on the stand, where she tearfully testified that she had been intimidated into telling lies before the camera.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Queens jury, forced to render a stark judgment on a videotaped confession, yesterday found a day care worker guilty of raping and sexually abusing a 4-year-old boy in her care.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Queens jury, forced to render a stark judgment on a videotaped confession, yesterday found a day care worker guilty of raping and sexually abusing a 4-year-old boy in her care.</p>
        <p>The prosecution relied heavily on a recording in which the worker, Khemwatie Bedessie, gave a detailed account of abusing and having intercourse with the boy. The defense then put her on the stand, where she tearfully testified that she had been intimidated into telling lies before the camera.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bedessie, 39, a Guyanese immigrant with a fifth-grade education, looked numb as the verdict was delivered.</p>
        <p>''I'm not sure she really understands what's going on,'' said her lawyer, Stephen Turano, who said she intends to appeal the verdict. Ms. Bedessie's confused performance on the witness stand, he added, ''wasn't malingering. That's really her.''</p>
        <p>The Queens district attorney, Richard A. Brown, hailed the decision. ''The defendant's actions represent a disturbing betrayal of trust to the 4-year-old child at the heart of this case, his parents and the school that employed her,'' he said. ''Hopefully, the terrible experience that the child suffered at the hands of the defendant will not have any long- reaching effects or leave him emotionally scarred for life.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Bedessie was questioned last spring after one of her 4-year-old charges told his mother she had molested him. About three hours after she was brought to the Special Victims Unit, Ms. Bedessie gave her confession, saying, at one point, ''I felt bad about it, because I don't know how it came about. I felt somebody was doing it with the child, because I felt he was doing it before.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Turano tried to argue that the taped confession provided incomplete information, since the hours of questioning that proceeded it were not recorded. On the witness stand, Ms. Bedessie said that the detective promised to release her if she admitted to raping the boy, and that the alternative was brutal treatment on Rikers Island.</p>
        <p>''He promised that I'm going to go home and see my mommy and he never let me go,'' she said, beginning to cry. It was the single moment during the trial when she showed any emotion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Turano said his client was naïve and acquiescent during the police interview.</p>
        <p>''No doubt about it, ladies and gentlemen, this is a very simple woman,'' Mr. Turano said. ''This is a very unsophisticated woman. Evaluate for yourselves whether it is credible to believe that she is unaware of her rights.''</p>
        <p>Before the jury went into deliberations after lunch yesterday, an assistant district attorney, Dianna Megias, played excerpts from the videotaped confession for jurors for the second time. She asked them to use common sense to judge which of Ms. Bedessie's performances was more believable.</p>
        <p>''Look at the mannerisms and gestures in this video,'' Ms. Megias said. ''Ladies and gentlemen, the details, the emotion, the mannerisms were the defendant's and only the defendant's.'' She asked the jurors if they could spot instances in the taped confession when Ms. Bedessie turned to the detectives for cues, or when the detectives' faces suggested that they were coaching her. ''No,'' she said, ''because there was no script.''</p>
        <p>She dismissed the defense's witnesses as ''fluff'' and urged jurors to rely on life experience.</p>
        <p>''You don't have to accept what doesn't make sense,'' she said. ''You were here. You heard it.''</p>
        <p>After the verdict, several of Ms. Bedessie's relatives wiped away tears.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bedessie will be sentenced on July 25 and faces up to 25 years in prison.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
