<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>5 Children Die in Pittsburgh House Fire</title>
    <meta content="13blaze" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/13/us/13blaze.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070615T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854142"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Pittsburgh</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Pittsburgh (Pa)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E0D7173FF930A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="456" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>5 Children Die in Pittsburgh House Fire</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">5 Children Die in Pittsburgh House Fire</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SEAN D. HAMILL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hamill, Sean D</byline>
      <dateline>PITTSBURGH, June 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five young children from two families died Tuesday in an early morning fire after their mothers left them in the home overnight with a teenage baby sitter who has not been found, the police said.</p>
        <p>Neighbors in Larimer, an impoverished neighborhood in the city's East End, called 911 at 1:23 a.m. after two 8-year-old boys managed to get out of the house and scream for help.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five children died Tuesday in a fire after their mothers left them in the home overnight with a teenage baby sitter who has not been found.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Five young children from two families died Tuesday in an early morning fire after their mothers left them in the home overnight with a teenage baby sitter who has not been found, the police said.</p>
        <p>Neighbors in Larimer, an impoverished neighborhood in the city's East End, called 911 at 1:23 a.m. after two 8-year-old boys managed to get out of the house and scream for help.</p>
        <p>But the three-story brick home was fully engulfed by the time firefighters and several neighbors arrived. Fire Chief Michael Huss said the fire began when some of the children were playing with matches.</p>
        <p>''I heard the two little boys on the front steps screaming, 'Can somebody help us?' '' said Sontaya Perry, 22, one of the neighbors who responded to the fire. ''I tried to go in there at first, but the steps were on fire and the heat from the fire stopped me.''</p>
        <p>Initially, she said she could hear screaming from the children on the second floor. A minute later the screaming stopped.</p>
        <p>Emergency crews arrived moments later and used a ladder to get to a second-story window and the five children were pulled unresponsive from a bedroom.</p>
        <p>Two of the children -- Dezekiah Holyfield, 3, and Andre Rankin, 6 -- were pronounced dead at the scene. Three others -- Daekia Holyfield, 7, Cedano Holyfield, 4, and Azquel Rankin, 5 -- died at the hospital or on the way there.</p>
        <p>Police Chief Nate Harper said investigators were trying to locate the 17-year-old baby sitter that one of the mothers said was watching the children. Both mothers had been interviewed, but Chief Harper would not discuss what they said or where they were when the fire broke out.</p>
        <p>The Allegheny County medical examiner's office determined that all five died from carbon monoxide poisoning and smoke inhalation.</p>
        <p>''This is certainly one of the most emotionally draining incidents for us in some time,'' said Robert J. McCaughan, chief of the city's Emergency Medical Services, which oversees paramedics.</p>
        <p>Fire Chief Huss said the blaze started on the second floor and spread to houses on either side, including a vacant home that was badly damaged. One nonfunctioning smoke detector was found in the home.</p>
        <p>Neighbors said the mother of the four Holyfield children -- including one of the 8-year-old boys who survived -- worked nights.</p>
        <p>The three Rankin children -- including the other 8-year-old boy -- had been brought to the home Monday evening from their home in the city's Homewood neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Once a middle-class bastion with a mix of neat brick and wooden-sided homes built in the early 1900s, the neighborhood has been missed by other redevelopment efforts in the East End, and has more than its share of vacant lots and boarded up homes and businesses.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 15, 2007, Friday  An article on Wednesday about a house fire that killed five children in Pittsburgh incorrectly described the building. It was wood and shingles, not brick.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 15, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>An article on Wednesday about a house fire that killed five children in Pittsburgh incorrectly described the building. It was wood and shingles, not brick.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
