<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-Businessman Wins Runoff for Dallas Mayor</title>
    <meta content="18dallas" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/us/18dallas.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Dallas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Dallas (Tex)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E2DC123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="513" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-Businessman Wins Runoff for Dallas Mayor</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ex-Businessman Wins Runoff for Dallas Mayor</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRETEL C. KOVACH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kovach, Gretel C</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS, June 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Voters here on Saturday chose a retired businessman as their next mayor, ending a bid by a three-term city councilman who if elected would have become the first openly gay elected leader of a major American city.</p>
        <p>The retired businessman, Thomas C. Leppert, former chief executive of one of the world's largest construction firms, was elected on Saturday in a runoff against the city councilman, Ed Oakley, who owns a small construction contracting business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dallas voters on Saturday chose Thomas C. Leppert, former chief executive of one of the world’s largest construction firms, as their next mayor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Voters here on Saturday chose a retired businessman as their next mayor, ending a bid by a three-term city councilman who if elected would have become the first openly gay elected leader of a major American city.</p>
        <p>The retired businessman, Thomas C. Leppert, former chief executive of one of the world's largest construction firms, was elected on Saturday in a runoff against the city councilman, Ed Oakley, who owns a small construction contracting business.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leppert, 53, a Republican, received almost 58 percent of the 85,600 votes cast in the runoff.</p>
        <p>It was the most expensive political race in Dallas history. Mr. Leppert's campaign spent ''well over $2 million,'' a campaign aide said, including a $600,000 loan from Mr. Leppert himself, who retired from the Turner Corporation in December and serves on the boards of the Washington Mutual Bank and other businesses. Mr. Oakley spent about $1.8 million on his campaign.</p>
        <p>''We clearly brought new leadership, and the people of Dallas were looking for that,'' Mr. Leppert said Sunday in a telephone interview. ''We did it in a way that was positive and bridged some of the divides. I don't think Dallas has seen anything like it.''</p>
        <p>Dallas, with a population of about 1.2 million, is the ninth-largest city in the United States.</p>
        <p>This is Mr. Leppert's first elected political office. His promise of a fresh start at City Hall, his business leadership background and his efforts to reach out to minority and poor residents in the city's southern section resonated beyond the traditional voting stronghold of the business elite in affluent north Dallas.</p>
        <p>Several prominent black religious and political leaders endorsed the Leppert campaign, including Frederick D. Haynes III, head of the Friendship-West Baptist Church with more than 8,000 members, and Don Hill, the mayor pro tem, who finished third in the general election on May 12, behind Mr. Leppert and Mr. Oakley.</p>
        <p>''I believe he will use his connections to not only lure development to the southern sector,'' said Dr. Haynes, ''but also there is a genuine interest on his part to address the problems of poverty, which bears so many negative fruits, including crime and drugs and violence.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Oakley, 55, said on Sunday that while he had to spend campaign time fund-raising, Mr. Leppert made significant inroads in his base of south Dallas and minority voters. He said his loss probably spelled the end of his tenure in public office.</p>
        <p>Mr. Oakley said he was proud that a gay man had made it so far politically in one of the country's biggest cities. During the campaign, automated telephone calls to voters arranged by groups opposing Mr. Oakley referred to his sexuality.</p>
        <p>''I really thought in this day and age that we've moved beyond all of that,'' Mr. Oakley said. ''But I'm very proud, if you look at my support base from conservatives to liberals, it was an amazing coalition of people who never would have gotten behind an openly gay candidate.</p>
        <p>''I hope I will set the stage for someone down the road,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
