<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Capos' Taut Smiles At HBO</title>
    <meta content="18carr" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/business/media/18carr.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855359"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA EQUATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Home Box Office</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Albrecht, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nelson, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Plepler, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kessler, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Akselrad, Harold</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lombardo, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carr, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sopranos, the (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Home Box Office</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Albrecht, Chris</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E6DD123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1114" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Capos' Taut Smiles At HBO</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Capos’ Taut Smiles at HBO</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CARR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carr, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Media Equation column discusses future of HBO cable network after The Sopranos program ends and long-time chief executive and programmer in chief Chris Albrecht leaves company; network takes new leadership approach with Bill Nelson named chairman and chief executive and Richard Plepler, Eric Kessler and Harold Akselrad all named as co-presidents; Michael Lombardo, president of programming group, rounds out collaborative Hollywood-type team (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The keening that followed the 11 seconds of inky blackness at the end of ''The Sopranos'' finale has finally begun to die down. But the executives at HBO could be forgiven for feeling like they are still staring into that dark place.</p>
        <p>The last episode of ''The Sopranos'' wasn't HBO's only recent loss. Chris Albrecht, long the chief executive and programmer in chief, has also been whacked -- taken out by his own hand after being charged with assaulting a female companion after a boxing match in Las Vegas last month. (Mr. Albrecht pleaded no contest.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the denouement of “The Sopranos” and the departure of former chief executive Chris Albrecht, HBO has a big case of the “now what’s?”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The keening that followed the 11 seconds of inky blackness at the end of ''The Sopranos'' finale has finally begun to die down. But the executives at HBO could be forgiven for feeling like they are still staring into that dark place.</p>
        <p>The last episode of ''The Sopranos'' wasn't HBO's only recent loss. Chris Albrecht, long the chief executive and programmer in chief, has also been whacked -- taken out by his own hand after being charged with assaulting a female companion after a boxing match in Las Vegas last month. (Mr. Albrecht pleaded no contest.)</p>
        <p>The loss of two bosses of the HBO family is significant. But with 30 million subscribers, profit of $1.2 billion on $3.4 billion in revenue last year and a string of lavishly praised programs, the cable channel is not in any kind of trouble. Still, with the denouement of ''The Sopranos,'' one of the most lauded television series ever, and Mr. Albrecht's departure, HBO has a big case of the ''now what's?''</p>
        <p>In an effort to ensure continuity and soothe jangled nerves, Richard D. Parsons, chief executive of the parent Time Warner, and Jeffrey L. Bewkes, its president and a former head of HBO, decided to keep it in the family when it came time to replace Mr. Albrecht. And unlike the North Jersey clan, this is a family that knows how to share, perhaps to a fault.</p>
        <p>Last week, Bill Nelson, the former chief operating officer, was named chairman and chief executive, while Richard Plepler, Eric Kessler and Harold Akselrad -- all longtime lieutenants at HBO -- were named co-presidents, with Michael Lombardo also being promoted to president of the programming group and head of HBO's West Coast office.</p>
        <p>To a certain extent, all the roles are an extension of previous responsibilities, but the four- or five-headed arrangement (depending on how you count) means that everyone will get to dip their beak in.</p>
        <p>Mr. Plepler, who had been the top corporate communications officer, will now be in charge of programming, while Mr. Kessler will be in charge of marketing, distribution and international efforts. Mr. Akselrad will manage business and legal affairs, in addition to supervising acquisitions and the company's technology group.</p>
        <p>Michael Speck, of the media consultant Heidrick &amp; Struggles, said that given the people involved, this all made sense.</p>
        <p>''You have a centerpiece in Bill Nelson,'' Mr. Speck said. ''There are people who have already proven to work well together, and I don't see how this new structure is going to affect that.''</p>
        <p>Still, the co-presidency seems far more like a Hollywood sort of solution, where titles are handed out like bonbons, than an effort to maintain a network's reputation for artistic and commercial decisiveness. In a telephone interview on Friday afternoon, Mr. Bewkes seemed amazed that people who watch the company would assign so much meaning to titles.</p>
        <p>''Given the clear responsibilities that each of the three co-presidents have and the long working relationship that all four of them have,'' he said, ''I have no doubt that this will be a streamlined and effective decision-making team.''</p>
        <p>But no matter how it is spun, HBO is confronting midlife crisis with a great deal of thickness around the middle.</p>
        <p>And there are some real problems to fix. ''Entourage'' is having a nice moment, and ''Flight of the Conchords'' is already getting a thorough face-licking from the critics, but neither will own the conversation the way that ''The Sopranos'' did. Like ''Sex and the City'' before it, ''The Sopranos'' gave HBO the kind of cachet that made people feel smart, not dumb, in parting with $15 or so every month for television programming.</p>
        <p>Last Thursday, I was on the Forbes boat on the Hudson River for a fund-raiser for St. Jude's Hospital with the cast of ''The Sopranos.'' The departure from the dock of the wildly popular crew served as an easy metaphor -- that ship has sailed.</p>
        <p>For the time being, HBO will content itself with aggregating a series of niche tastes: the kids who tune in to see ''Entourage,'' young marrieds who find ''Big Love'' riveting. Other new series like ''The Comeback'' and ''Lucky Louie'' have been canceled as HBO -- a source of patience in an industry of attention deficit disorder cases -- has developed a quicker trigger finger.</p>
        <p>''Deadwood,'' a show that seemed to define the idiosyncratic glory of the network, was mismanaged out of existence under Mr. Albrecht. Now David Milch, the creator of the series, is starting over with ''John From Cincinnati.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Milch said he would continue to rely on the same people at the network he always has.</p>
        <p>''The foundation for all the work that I have done there and the people I have done it with are still in place, and I am very comfortable with that,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But the new organization chart creates an additional tier between the chief executive and many leading programmers at the network -- including Colin Callender, who is in charge of HBO original films like ''La Vie en Rose'' and ''Bury My Heart at Wounded Knee,'' and Carolyn Strauss, long an innovator who is in charge of series. Both said after the announcement that they were satisfied with the state of things.</p>
        <p>''The most important thing is that all of the creative heads get to maintain their sovereignty and their autonomy,'' Mr. Callender told The Los Angeles Times.</p>
        <p>That may seem like a high level of prerogative, but HBO's business model is built on finding and making long-term bets on creative talent. HBO sees itself in a sort of permanent political campaign, working to maintain its base while trying to bring the undecideds inside the tent.</p>
        <p>Political campaigns, though, need more than a platform: they need a leader, like Mr. Albrecht was, and Mr. Bewkes before him (and come to think of it, like Michael Fuchs before him). Perhaps Mr. Nelson will be The Guy, but the current arrangement seems like a way of deciding by not deciding.</p>
        <p>''In terms of maintaining morale, it's a very good move,'' said Jimmy Schaeffler of the Carmel Group, a media consulting firm, about HBO's new ruling class. ''But it counterintuits a lot of how entertainment companies usually run, with one or two kingpins making the decisions. Human nature and common sense suggest it probably won't last for the long term.''</p>
        <p>HBO is a genuine family, much more so than the Sopranos ever were, so for now, all the guns will remain well hidden. Still, everyone from Charles Darwin to Paulie Walnuts will tell you that there are only so many seats at the table. And when push comes to shove -- or worse -- well, it won't be personal, just business.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA EQUATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
