<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Holding a Mirror Up to Israeli Destiny, the Past and the Prologue</title>
    <meta content="18bron" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/books/18bron.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855357"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Segev, Tom</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">1967 (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E6DD123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1212" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Holding a Mirror Up to Israeli Destiny, the Past and the Prologue</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Holding a Mirror Up to Israeli Destiny, the Past and the Prologue</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ETHAN BRONNER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>1967  Israel, the War, and the Year That Transformed the Middle East  By Tom Segev  Translated by Jessica Cohen. Illustrated. 673 pages. Metropolitan Books. $35.</p>
        <p>Tom Segev, an Israeli columnist and historian, sums up the meaning for Israel of the 1967 war with two jokes. The first, heard in the months before the war, when Israelis feared a second Holocaust at the hands of their Arab neighbors, is of a sign hanging near the boarding gate at the national airport, asking the last one out of the country to turn off the lights. The second, told after the six days in which Israel defeated the armies of Egypt, Syria and Jordan and quadrupled the territory under its control, involves two officers talking about how to spend their day. '' 'Let's conquer Cairo,' one proposes. The other replies, 'But what will we do after lunch?' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“1967” is a fascinating and devastating portrait of an Israel filled with self-doubt, then suddenly with power and messianic fervor. Missing from the compelling and damning narrative are the Arabs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>1967  Israel, the War, and the Year That Transformed the Middle East  By Tom Segev  Translated by Jessica Cohen. Illustrated. 673 pages. Metropolitan Books. $35.</p>
        <p>Tom Segev, an Israeli columnist and historian, sums up the meaning for Israel of the 1967 war with two jokes. The first, heard in the months before the war, when Israelis feared a second Holocaust at the hands of their Arab neighbors, is of a sign hanging near the boarding gate at the national airport, asking the last one out of the country to turn off the lights. The second, told after the six days in which Israel defeated the armies of Egypt, Syria and Jordan and quadrupled the territory under its control, involves two officers talking about how to spend their day. '' 'Let's conquer Cairo,' one proposes. The other replies, 'But what will we do after lunch?' ''</p>
        <p>The Israelis quickly named the June 1967 event the Six-Day War to echo biblical creation. Like many historical watersheds, its origins and consequences have been intensely analyzed and debated, especially in recent weeks as its 40th anniversary was marked. Mr. Segev illuminates his two jokes with more than 600 pages of social history. His argument, in the end, is this: Anxiety, much of it Holocaust related, was so overpowering that Israel went to war against saber-rattling Egypt and Syria when diplomacy might have sufficed, and the rout of its neighbors caused such irrational exultation in Israel that it foolishly became an occupier, a role that continues to drag it and the region down.</p>
        <p>Mr. Segev is part of the new historians of Israel, as they are known, who have challenged what they consider their country's founding myths, largely with newly released or uncovered archival material. Young (and not-so-young) societies tell heroic stories of themselves, and Israel's new historians seek to reshape those stories, not only to make them more accurate, but also to help Israelis see themselves as outsiders do and thereby find a way to compromise.</p>
        <p>If you are weak and noble and your enemy strong and evil, there is little to discuss. But if it turns out you are more powerful and your neighbor weaker than you had understood, and your actions less high-minded than you believed, you may rethink your next move.</p>
        <p>Mr. Segev has been engaged in this activity for years. He has written excellent books on the country's first year of existence, 1949, as well as on the pre-World War I British mandate in Palestine and on the embarrassed neglect that Israel showed Holocaust survivors. For years his column in the newspaper Haaretz was called ''Katav Zar,'' or foreign correspondent, even though it was about Israel and he reported from home.</p>
        <p>This book follows on those earlier endeavors. But unlike his book on the British mandate, ''One Palestine Complete,'' ''1967'' lacks a certain sweep. It does not tell the whole story of the war, barely focusing on Arab activity. He leaves that to the many other histories of the war, simply taking note of the Syria-based Palestinian terrorist attacks and the bellicosity coming from Egypt. What interests Mr. Segev is Israel: its moods, debates, generation gaps and anxieties.</p>
        <p>Drawing on hundreds of unpublished letters, diaries and minutes of cabinet meetings, as well as newspapers and extensive interviews with participants, Mr. Segev paints a deliciously detailed portrait of Israel at the time, including the cost of refreshments at high school dances, sartorial habits of officials, the design of a typical apartment and the quirks of leaders like Moshe Dayan.</p>
        <p>Israel was an isolated state without television reception and few telephones. Traumatized by the past and the growing threats from Arab leaders, officials ordered thousands of graves prepared in public parks. The editor of a major daily declared, ''There will be no Treblinka here.''</p>
        <p>You need not agree with Mr. Segev's conclusions on how things could have been done differently to benefit from his research and narrative. If you plan to read only one book on the 1967 war, this is not it. It is too narrowly focused. At the same time Mr. Segev makes a compelling and fresh case that the war was at least partly a result of a delicate and vulnerable moment in Israeli history, and his exploration of that moment is -- while too long -- persuasive and engaging.</p>
        <p>In essence he argues that in 1966 many Israelis felt lost, their 18-year experiment in statehood foundering, their first days of heroism and vision gone, their economy plummeting, and some of their best citizens emigrating. The nation's founding prime minister, David Ben-Gurion, had been replaced with the hesitating Levi Eshkol (asked if he wanted coffee or tea, the joke went, he replied, ''half and half''); the Jews of Middle Eastern countries had begun to arrive in large numbers, and they made the founders nervous because of their Eastern ways; and Palestinian terror, based mostly in Syria, was escalating. The newspapers were filled with headlines like ''The Crisis'' and ''Death of a Vision.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile there was talk that in its independence war of 1948 Israel should have taken the historic, biblical parts of the land of Israel: Old Jerusalem, Hebron, Jericho, Gaza. In addition Egypt and Syria, egged on by the Soviet Union, expressed deep hostility to Israel and vowed to return the land to the dispossessed Palestinians. The first generation of native-born military leaders -- Dayan, Yitzhak Rabin, Ariel Sharon, Ezer Weizman -- felt contempt for the European-born political leaders like Eshkol, a gap of generation and culture that also pushed Israel to war.</p>
        <p>When speaking to his lieutenants, General Rabin used to refer to Eshkol and his ministers as ''the Jews,'' while Eshkol called the generals ''Preissn'' (''Prussians,'' in Yiddish). The army was trained for war, and as Dayan put it in April 1967, ''Aggression is in its bones and its spirit.''</p>
        <p>All of this meant, Mr. Segev argues, that when Israeli jet fighters knocked out the Egyptian air force in just over an hour, and King Hussein of Jordan foolishly joined in, Israel found itself unable to think clearly about the risk of taking the Gaza Strip and West Bank with their biblical locales and hundreds of thousands of Palestinians. Jewish destiny seemed blindingly clear.</p>
        <p>Israel was turning its victorious military into a kind of cult, certain that it would carry out an ''enlightened occupation.'' Dayan went so far as to tell a Palestinian poet that the relationship between Israel and the Palestinians would be like that between a Bedouin man and a young girl he takes against her wishes: Their children would not recall the rape but would view the man as their father.</p>
        <p>''1967'' is a fascinating and devastating portrait of a society filled with self-doubt, then suddenly with power and messianic fervor. Missing from the compelling and damning narrative are the Arabs, with their own considerable delusions and failures. It is quite right that the Israeli occupation has been cruel and counterproductive, greatly delaying the chances of peaceful coexistence. It is less clear, however, how the Middle East would have turned out if Israel had restrained itself in 1967. In a region devoid of good government, economic development and individual opportunity, militant Islam could have built its army of the faithful even without Israeli occupation.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
