<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Things Going Right for Red Sox, But for All the Wrong Reasons</title>
    <meta content="18redsox" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/sports/baseball/18redsox.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855459"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <org class="online_producer">San Francisco Giants</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Varitek, Jason</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wakefield, Tim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E4DB123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1059" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Things Going Right for Red Sox, But for All the Wrong Reasons</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Things Going Right for Red Sox, but for All the Wrong Reasons</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, June 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An hour before the Red Sox played the Giants in the middle game of their weekend series, Boston catcher Jason Varitek jumped up in front of his locker, knocked over his chair, kicked one of his shoes across the room and shouted as he dived on the floor of the Fenway Park clubhouse.</p>
        <p>Varitek was imitating a play last season in which pitcher Julián Tavárez ran to second base to tag out a wandering runner as Varitek was returning to home plate from a conference on the mound. ''But there was time out!'' Varitek said, adding that the trick to working with Tavárez was to ''keep him away from thinking.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>People are hearing the Red Sox loudly and clearly this season while watching them succeed in somewhat unorthodox ways.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An hour before the Red Sox played the Giants in the middle game of their weekend series, Boston catcher Jason Varitek jumped up in front of his locker, knocked over his chair, kicked one of his shoes across the room and shouted as he dived on the floor of the Fenway Park clubhouse.</p>
        <p>Varitek was imitating a play last season in which pitcher Julián Tavárez ran to second base to tag out a wandering runner as Varitek was returning to home plate from a conference on the mound. ''But there was time out!'' Varitek said, adding that the trick to working with Tavárez was to ''keep him away from thinking.''</p>
        <p>As Varitek spoke and onlookers laughed, Tavárez walked behind him, listening with one ear while the other ear was pressed to a cellphone. ''Can you hear me now?'' Tavárez shouted, repeating it several times with increasing volume. The day before, Tavárez retired a batter by fielding a grounder on the first-base line and intentionally rolling a throw to first base as if bowling.</p>
        <p>People are hearing the Red Sox loudly and clearly this season while watching them succeed in somewhat unorthodox ways. They beat the Giants, 9-5, on Sunday behind the knuckleball pitcher Tim Wakefield and a home run and three runs batted in from Manny Ramírez.</p>
        <p>This completed a weekend sweep and raised their record to 44-24, the best in the major leagues. They led the American League East by eight and a half games over the Yankees. But there is something counterintuitive about these 2007 Red Sox, who play in a hitters' ballpark and are generally thought of as a power team.</p>
        <p>Their success goes beyond their starting pitchers, Wakefield (7-7), Josh Beckett (9-1), Daisuke Matsuzaka (8-5), Curt Schilling (6-3) and Tavárez (4-4), and beyond their bullpen, whose setup man, Hideki Okajima, has an earned run average of 1.04 in 34 2/3 innings and closer, Jonathan Papelbon, who has 16 saves.</p>
        <p>The curious numbers for the Red Sox involve the hitting. Although Ramírez, the left fielder, homered for the second consecutive game Sunday, he has only 10 this season, far off his pace from last season, when he hit 35, and from 2005, when he hit 45, and 2004, when he hit 43.</p>
        <p>David Ortiz, the Red Sox' other big bopper, has just 11 homers. He hit 54 last season, 47 in 2005 and 41 in 2004.</p>
        <p>Ortiz spent much of the weekend complaining that umpires were calling too many strikes against him. He was ejected from Friday night's game for throwing his helmet after taking a third strike.</p>
        <p>Ortiz said Saturday, ''I bet it gets better now,'' but he walked angrily to the dugout when called out again on strikes. Afterward, he discussed umpiring in profanity-laced terms.</p>
        <p>Terry Francona, the manager, in discussing the lack of power, said home runs ''are not the end-all, be-all for us.'' In their place, the Red Sox have been getting consistent hitting from their infielders.</p>
        <p>Kevin Youkilis, the first baseman, had two hits Sunday to raise his average to .332. Dustin Pedroia, the rookie second baseman, had one hit Sunday and is batting .322. Mike Lowell, the third baseman, had a hit Sunday and is batting .305.</p>
        <p>Lowell leads the team in home runs with 12. He also made a savvy, veteran play Friday night to keep a pivotal inning alive.</p>
        <p>It occurred after Julio Lugo got picked off first base with two outs. Lowell danced off third to draw a throw. This let Lugo escape to second as Lowell skidded back safely into third with a hook slide ahead of the tag. The Red Sox then scored three runs to break open a close game in what became a 10-2 victory.</p>
        <p>''You've got to take pride in the little things,'' Lowell said Sunday. He mentioned two details from Sunday's game: a surprise bunt single by Pedroia that helped ignite a five-run rally in the third, and a run scored by Youkilis from first base on a Lowell double despite a hard carom off the left-field wall.</p>
        <p>''A lot of players wouldn't score on that,'' Lowell said. ''Little things like that are big.'' He also said it was better to have ''starting pitching that can dominate'' than to have ''a team that scores a million runs and doesn't have pitching.''</p>
        <p>Wakefield, who allowed five runs and eight hits in five and two-thirds innings, including Barry Bonds's 748th career home run, says the Red Sox have gotten good pitching when they have not scored score a lot and have hit well when their pitching has been poor.</p>
        <p>''We're deep through the lineup, we're deep in our pitching staff and, obviously, the defense is very good,'' Wakefield said. ''All pistons of the engine are working.''</p>
        <p>But other aspects of the lineup might tempt General Manager Theo Epstein to make a move before the July 31 nonwaiver trading deadline.</p>
        <p>Lugo, the latest in a long line of shortstops to replace Nomar Garciaparra, is batting .207 after going 0 for 4 Sunday. Center fielder Coco Crisp, who replaced Johnny Damon in center field last season, is hitting .233 after hitting .264 last season following a trade from Cleveland.</p>
        <p>Right fielder J. D. Drew, signed as a free agent from the Dodgers, perked up this weekend as a leadoff hitter with three hits Friday, one Saturday and one Sunday. But he is hitting just .242.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if content is the right term,'' Drew said. ''I'm trying to grind out some at-bats.''</p>
        <p>The batting order will be an issue now that the Sox are to play nine road games in the next 10 days -- three each in Atlanta, San Diego and Seattle. Because the first six games are in National League ballparks, they will not be able to use a designated hitter, who is usually Ortiz.</p>
        <p>Should Ortiz play first base, Francona would have to bench either Youkilis, who plays there regularly, or Lowell, who plays third base but could be replaced there by Youkilis, who has experience at that position.</p>
        <p>Has Francona thought about what he will do to solve this problem?</p>
        <p>''No,'' he said, adding that he would figure it out on the flight to Atlanta and discuss it with the players involved. He did not seem overly concerned. No doubt, 29 other managers would love to have his problems.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
