<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Classic Qualities Have Role In Contemporary Sound</title>
    <meta content="18mann" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/arts/music/18mann.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855368"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New School</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Xenakis, Iannis</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lerdahl, Fred</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Narucki, Susan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E5DD123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Classic Qualities Have Role In Contemporary Sound</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Classic Qualities Have Role in Contemporary Sound</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE SMITH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Few composers represent the shock of the new as convincingly as Iannis Xenakis, who transmuted the impersonal logic of higher mathematics into sounds of elemental power and daunting ferocity. Xenakis hardly reinvented music from scratch: the precision of Bach, the feeling of inevitability associated with Beethoven, Chopin's poetry and Debussy's painterly quality can all be heard in his 1980 piano work, ''Mists.'' But when Marc Ponthus opened the first concert of the Institute and Festival for Contemporary Performance on Friday night with an exhilarating account of that piece, it seemed to herald a radical break from convention, along with a compelling embrace of the new and unexpected.</p>
        <p>The primary function of the institute, presented annually by Mannes College the New School for Music, is to provide young performers with direction in the specialized skills required by contemporary composers. Evening concerts, open to the public, offer the players a chance to put what they have learned to use.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The primary function of the institute, presented annually by Mannes College the New School for Music, is to provide young performers with direction in the specialized skills required by contemporary composers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Few composers represent the shock of the new as convincingly as Iannis Xenakis, who transmuted the impersonal logic of higher mathematics into sounds of elemental power and daunting ferocity. Xenakis hardly reinvented music from scratch: the precision of Bach, the feeling of inevitability associated with Beethoven, Chopin's poetry and Debussy's painterly quality can all be heard in his 1980 piano work, ''Mists.'' But when Marc Ponthus opened the first concert of the Institute and Festival for Contemporary Performance on Friday night with an exhilarating account of that piece, it seemed to herald a radical break from convention, along with a compelling embrace of the new and unexpected.</p>
        <p>The primary function of the institute, presented annually by Mannes College the New School for Music, is to provide young performers with direction in the specialized skills required by contemporary composers. Evening concerts, open to the public, offer the players a chance to put what they have learned to use.</p>
        <p>Sadly, the audiences are small and seem to consist primarily of participants and faculty. In a way the institute seems like a throwback to the Society for Private Musical Performances, the group Arnold Schoenberg organized in 1918 to provide competent accounts of modern music for a small circle of Viennese devotees. (Stravinsky, Debussy and Bartok were among the composers whose works were performed.)</p>
        <p>Fred Lerdahl's Duo for Violin and Piano introduced another of the institute's most invaluable assets: Rolf Schulte, a remarkable violinist who combines clarity with intense feeling in even the thorniest scores. The first movement, ''Disputation,'' traced an arc of increasing and decreasing agitation; the second, ''Elegy,'' contained poignant laments for three friends. The pianist Stephen Gosling was Mr. Schulte's eloquent partner.</p>
        <p>Atonality and aggression were set aside for the premiere of ''Burnt Counterpoint,'' by Keith Fitch. In the outer movements Michael Ibrahim, a saxophonist, and Matthew Gold, a percussionist, played bright, racing patterns that shifted in and out of sync; in between, Mr. Ibrahim blew high, keening melodies and murmured multiphonics over Mr. Gold's quiet tam-tam taps and brittle glockenspiel outbursts.</p>
        <p>Two works by the Russian composer Vladimir Tarnopolski were scheduled, but one was postponed. Its replacement was a bracing performance by Mr. Ponthus of two movements from Pierre Boulez's Sonata No. 2. Mr. Tarnopolski's ''Scenes From the Real Life'' featured four settings of poetry by Ernst Jandl, performed by the soprano Susan Narucki with Mr. Gosling, the flutist Jill Sokol and the French horn player Stewart Rose.</p>
        <p>In ''My Own Song'' Ms. Narucki was surrounded by clamorous figures that echoed the turbulent insistence of her words. The performers affected blurry intonation and a pronounced wobble in the genuinely otherworldly ''Inhalt'' (''Gist''). All moaned, barked and otherwise intoned the words of the absurdist ''Chanson,'' as Ms. Narucki rolled Rs at length and gargled other syllables. ''Ins Theater'' (''To a Theater'') featured rushing Minimalist rhythms that occasionally stammered like a needle stuck in a vinyl groove.</p>
        <p>Ms. Narucki was an arresting presence throughout. And Mr. Tarnopolski's clever cycle, for all its challenges, amounted to serious fun.</p>
        <p>Photo: Mathew Gold (percussion) and Michael Ibrahim (saxophone) perform ''Burnt Counterpoint'' at Mannes College the New School for Music. (Photo by Nan Melville for The New York Times)</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
