<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Debate Over Cause of Autism Strains a Family and Its Charity</title>
    <meta content="18autism" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Front Page; Health; U.S.; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/us/18autism.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855460"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Autism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mercury (Metal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Autism Speaks (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gross, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strom, Stephanie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wright, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wright, Suzanne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wright, Katie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirby, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Oprah Winfrey Show (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Evidence of Harm (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Autism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pediatrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Autism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mercury (Metal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Autism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Wright, Bob</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E4DB123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1349" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Debate Over Cause of Autism Strains a Family and Its Charity</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Autism Debate Strains a Family and Its Charity</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE GROSS and STEPHANIE STROM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strom, Stephanie; Gross, Jane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Debate over cause of autism causes rift in family that formed charity dedicated to curing that disorder; some think autism is genetic and best treated with intensive therapy, while others blame preservatives in vaccinations and swear by supplements and diet to cleanse body of heavy metals; Bob and Suzanne Wright founded their mega-charity, Autism Speaks, with hope of curing dreaded neurological disorder that affects one of every 150 children in American, including their grandson; their daughter Katie, mother of Christian, says her parents are not giving enough support to people who believe, as she does, that synthetic mercury preservative in vaccines is to blame; no major scientific studies have linked pediatric vaccination and autism, but many parents are convinced of it; family rift began in April when Katie put herself on side of 'The Mercurys,' as that faction is known, on Oprah Winfrey, and lashed out at 'old guard' scientists in Web interview with David Kirby, author of controversial book Evidence of Harm: Mercury in Vaccines and Autism Epidemic; Bob and Suzanne Wright then repudiated their daughter on charity's Web site; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A year after their grandson Christian received a diagnosis of autism in 2004, Bob Wright, then chairman of NBC/Universal, and his wife, Suzanne, founded Autism Speaks, a mega-charity dedicated to curing the dreaded neurological disorder that affects one of every 150 children in America today.</p>
        <p>The Wrights' venture was also an effort to end the internecine warfare in the world of autism -- where some are convinced that the disorder is genetic and best treated with intensive therapy, and others blame preservatives in vaccinations and swear by supplements and diet to cleanse the body of heavy metals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fissures in the autism community over the cause of the disorder have made their way into the Wright family, founders of the charity Autism Speaks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A year after their grandson Christian received a diagnosis of autism in 2004, Bob Wright, then chairman of NBC/Universal, and his wife, Suzanne, founded Autism Speaks, a mega-charity dedicated to curing the dreaded neurological disorder that affects one of every 150 children in America today.</p>
        <p>The Wrights' venture was also an effort to end the internecine warfare in the world of autism -- where some are convinced that the disorder is genetic and best treated with intensive therapy, and others blame preservatives in vaccinations and swear by supplements and diet to cleanse the body of heavy metals.</p>
        <p>With its high-powered board, world-class scientific advisers and celebrity fund-raisers like Jerry Seinfeld and Paul Simon, the charity was a powerful voice, especially in Washington. It also made strides toward its goal of unity by merging with three existing autism organizations and raising millions of dollars for research into all potential causes and treatments. The Wrights call it the ''big tent'' approach.</p>
        <p>But now the fissures in the autism community have made their way into the Wright family, where father and daughter are not speaking after a public battle over themes familiar to thousands of families with autistic children.</p>
        <p>The Wrights' daughter, Katie, the mother of Christian, says her parents have not given enough support to the people who believe, as she does, that the environment -- specifically a synthetic mercury preservative in vaccines -- is to blame. No major scientific studies have linked pediatric vaccination and autism, but many parents and their advocates persist, and a federal ''vaccine court'' is now reviewing nearly 4,000 such claims.</p>
        <p>The Wright feud has played out in cyberspace and spilled into Autism Speaks, where those who disagree with Katie Wright's views worry that she is setting its agenda. And the family intent on healing a fractured community has instead opened its old wounds and is itself riven.</p>
        <p>The rift began in April when Katie put herself squarely on the side of ''The Mercurys,'' as that faction is known, on Oprah Winfrey, where she described how her talkative toddler turned unresponsive and out-of-control after his vaccines and only improved with unconventional, and untested, remedies.</p>
        <p>In a Web interview with David Kirby, author of the controversial book, ''Evidence of Harm: Mercury in Vaccines and the Autism Epidemic,'' Ms. Wright lashed out at the ''old guard'' scientists and pioneering autism families. If the old-timers are unable to let go of ''failed strategies,'' she said, they should ''step aside'' and let a new generation ''have a chance to do something different with this money'' that her parents' charity was dispensing.</p>
        <p>Complaints poured in from those who said Ms. Wright's remarks were denigrating.</p>
        <p>So, in early June, Bob and Suzanne Wright repudiated their daughter on the charity's Web site. ''Katie Wright is not a spokesperson'' for the organization, the Wrights said in a brusque statement. Her ''personal views differ from ours.'' The Wrights also apologized to ''valued volunteers'' who had been disparaged. Told by friends how cold the rebuke sounded, Mrs. Wright belatedly added a line saying, ''Katie is our daughter, and we love her very much.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Wright called the statement a ''character assassination.'' She said she had not spoken to her father since. Ms. Wright continues to spend time with her mother, but said they had not discussed the situation.</p>
        <p>''I totally respect if her feelings were hurt,'' Mrs. Wright said. ''But a lot of feelings were hurt. A lot.''</p>
        <p>Now other autism families who hoped to put their differences aside are shouting at each other in cyberspace. ''Our struggle is not and should not be against each other,'' said Ilene Lainer, the mother of an autistic child and the executive director of the New York Center for Autism.</p>
        <p>The big tent approach of Autism Speaks appealed to Mel Karmazin, chief executive of Sirius Radio and an early board member and contributor. ''If you look at what projects Autism Speaks has funded, we are agnostic,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Karmazin, who also has an autistic grandson, added, ''I never wanted to look my grandson in the eye and tell him I'm taking just one viewpoint or that I think it had to be genetic.''</p>
        <p>Bob and Suzanne Wright are sympathetic to Katie's plight, having witnessed Christian's sudden regression and his many physical ailments, mostly gastrointestinal, which afflict many autistic children.</p>
        <p>The boy did not respond to behavioral therapies, the Wrights said, leading to their daughter's desperate search for anything that might help. ''When you have that sense of hopelessness, and don't see results, you do things that other people think is too risky,'' Mr. Wright said. ''The doctors say, 'Wait for the science.' But you don't have time to wait for the science.''</p>
        <p>The Wrights agreed to disagree with most of Katie's views. But her public attack on other parents crossed a line, Mr. and Mrs. Wright said in separate telephone interviews.</p>
        <p>''I know my daughter feels deeply that not enough is being done,'' Mr. Wright said. ''The larger issue is we want to be helpful to everyone, and to do that we need information, data, facts.''</p>
        <p>Some in the traditional scientific community worry that Autism Speaks has let Ms. Wright's experience shape its agenda. She scoffs at the notion. Her parents, she said in a telephone interview, are ''courageous'' and ''trying very hard,'' but have been slow to explore alternative approaches.</p>
        <p>''You can say it and say it and say it,'' she said. ''Show me evidence that they're actively researching vaccines.''</p>
        <p>The Wright family's fight has captured the attention of the bloggers, who are now questioning everything from its office lease to how it makes grants. The charity rebutted the bloggers' accusations of improprieties in interviews with The New York Times, which examined its IRS forms and read relevant sections to Gerald A. Rosenberg, former head of the New York State attorney general's charities bureau. He said nothing he reviewed was untoward.</p>
        <p>The most distinctive aspect of Autism Speaks is its alliance with Autism Coalition for Research and Education, an advocacy group; the National Alliance for Autism Research, devoted to scientific research into potential genetic causes, with high standards for peer review; and Cure Autism Now, which has championed unconventional theories and therapies.</p>
        <p>Which wing of the merged charity is ascendant? Some establishment scientists and parents now fear it is The Mercurys. They point to Cure Autism Now's having more seats than the National Alliance does on the board of directors and the growing number of research projects that focus on environmental causes.</p>
        <p>At a recent benefit gala, featuring Bill Cosby and Toni Braxton, some in the audience were surprised when Mr. Wright announced that all proceeds would go toward environmental research, which generally includes vaccines.</p>
        <p>But a list of current research grants on the Autism Speaks Web site suggests that the Wrights, while walking a fine line, are leaning toward genetic theories.</p>
        <p>From 2005 to 2007, the charity sponsored $11.5 million in grants for genetic research (compared with $5.9 million by all its partners between 1997 and 2004). It sponsored $4.4 million in environmental research (down from $6 million granted by the partners in the previous seven years). And many of the environmental studies explore what is known as the double-hit hypothesis: That the genes for autism may be activated in some children by exposure to mercury or other neuro-toxins.</p>
        <p>Bob and Suzanne Wright say their two-year immersion into the world of autism has been an eye-opener, especially the heated arguments worthy of the Hatfields and McCoys.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Wright is aware that the marriage of the Alliance and Cure Autism Now, for instance, could fall apart over opposing ideologies. ''I'm not going to let it,'' she said. ''The truth will rise to the top.''</p>
        <p>She is also aware that the rift in her own family needs repair: On Friday, her daughter posted a message on an autism Web site questioning their ''personal denouncement of me.''</p>
        <p>Yet Mrs. Wright is confident that ''we'll work our way through this.'' Autism, she said ''has done enough damage to my family. I'm not letting it do any more.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
