<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Beginning, Even Jeter Doubted Jeter</title>
    <meta content="18jeter" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/sports/baseball/18jeter.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855468"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jeter, Derek</person>
        <person class="online_producer">DiMaggio, Joe</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ledee, Ricky</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3DB123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="808" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Beginning, Even Jeter Doubted Jeter</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Beginning, Even Jeter Doubted Jeter</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This was before the 2,242 hits, before the four World Series rings, before he became the captain of the Yankees and before he attracted comparisons to Joe DiMaggio. This was Derek Jeter in Tampa, Fla., 15 years ago. This was Jeter's first day playing professionally for the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Ricky Ledee was there starting for Class A Tampa, waiting to see the first-round draft choice who would immediately become the starting shortstop. Ledee's first impression of Jeter was that he was really skinny. Ledee held up his left pinky to show how thin he thought Jeter looked as an 18-year-old.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before he became an iconic player, simply putting the ball in play was an accomplishment for Derek Jeter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This was before the 2,242 hits, before the four World Series rings, before he became the captain of the Yankees and before he attracted comparisons to Joe DiMaggio. This was Derek Jeter in Tampa, Fla., 15 years ago. This was Jeter's first day playing professionally for the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Ricky Ledee was there starting for Class A Tampa, waiting to see the first-round draft choice who would immediately become the starting shortstop. Ledee's first impression of Jeter was that he was really skinny. Ledee held up his left pinky to show how thin he thought Jeter looked as an 18-year-old.</p>
        <p>Jeter teased Ledee, his former minor league and major league teammate, behind the batting cage before the Yankees silenced the Mets, 8-2, at Yankee Stadium last night. Jeter is still playing shortstop for the Yankees while Ledee, who helped the Yankees win two titles, is hanging on with the Mets, his seventh team.</p>
        <p>Jeter singled in the first inning off Orlando Hernández and trotted home on Alex Rodriguez's two-run homer. Once again, Jeter did something, even if it was a little something, to aggravate the Mets. Ledee did not play in the three-game series.</p>
        <p>Every time Ledee shared a memory about Jeter, he stressed that he revered him.</p>
        <p>Still, Ledee, the journeyman outfielder who never fulfilled his promise with the Yankees, smiled when he discussed the early days of watching a raw Jeter, the player who has developed into an icon here.</p>
        <p>''He stunk,'' Ledee said. ''In the beginning, he stunk.''</p>
        <p>Reminded of the beginning, Jeter acknowledged that, for a while, he did stink. In Jeter's debut, he went 0 for 7 with five strikeouts in a doubleheader and also made a throwing error that lost one of the games. Jeter, who had only one strikeout in 59 at-bats in his senior year in high school, was exasperated after several hours as a Yankee.</p>
        <p>''I think I was 0 for 8 with seven strikeouts,'' said Jeter, who embellished it into an even worse day.</p>
        <p>Maybe Jeter exaggerated because the first bad day bled into a second and a third; Jeter did not get a hit until his 15th at-bat.</p>
        <p>Ledee said Jeter was so flummoxed as a hitter that simply putting the ball in play was an accomplishment. Was this the talented player from Kalamazoo, Mich., the Yankees gave an $800,000 signing bonus?</p>
        <p>''It was bad,'' Ledee said. ''The first couple of days were tough.''</p>
        <p>The first time Jeter met his teammates at a Gulf Coast League game, he was driven there by a Yankees executive.</p>
        <p>Ledee, who had taken the one-hour bus ride with the team, said some players grumbled about how the new player had received preferential treatment.</p>
        <p>Ledee said they were moaning even more once Jeter actually played a day later.</p>
        <p>''First, he didn't travel with us,'' Ledee said. ''Then, in the first game, he blew the game. We were like, 'He got all that money?' It was rookie league stuff.''</p>
        <p>Statistically, Jeter did struggle with his first minor league team. He hit .202 with 3 homers, 25 runs batted in and 12 errors in 47 games. Ledee, who batted only .229 in his third stint at Tampa, said Jeter's first hit was a bloop single to right field.</p>
        <p>But while Jeter looked overwhelmed, Ledee said the skinny prospect had skills. Ledee explained how minor leaguers never know if they are going to make it to the majors, so they study everyone around them as if they are competitors. When teammates analyzed the young Jeter, Ledee said they spotted someone who was soon going to handle Class A and keep advancing. Jeter made it to the majors in 1995 and was with the Yankees for good by 1996.</p>
        <p>''You could see that everything was there,'' Ledee said. ''The bat speed was there. He stayed inside the ball and hit the ball the other way. The Jeter that I see now, he was the same then.''</p>
        <p>Ledee said that he never saw Jeter get depressed about his problems. No matter how much Jeter struggled, Ledee said he stayed focused.</p>
        <p>''You don't know if, in his room, he was fighting himself,'' Ledee said. ''But, on the field, you never saw that.''</p>
        <p>While Jeter made sure that no one saw him sweat, he did have some long nights when he returned to the Radisson Bay Harbor Inn in Tampa. Jeter sat on the balcony and watched the cars breeze by, anything to take his mind off his troubles.</p>
        <p>''Back in the hotel, I might have gotten down,'' Jeter said. ''But not in front of anybody.''</p>
        <p>Fifteen years later, Jeter is one of the leading hitters in the American League. Ledee said he played with many minor leaguers who had better starts than Jeter, but none who have had the kind of finish that Jeter is fashioning.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
