<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pigs With Cellphones, But No Condoms</title>
    <meta content="18adcol" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/business/media/18adcol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855362"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Condoms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Condoms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Fox Broadcasting Co</org>
        <org class="online_producer">CBS Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Kaplan Thaler Group</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Joanou, Phil</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E6DD123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1060" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pigs With Cellphones, But No Condoms</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pigs With Cellphones, but No Condoms</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ADAM NEWMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a commercial for Trojan condoms that has its premiere tonight, women in a bar are surrounded by anthropomorphized, cellphone-toting pigs. One shuffles to the men's room, where, after procuring a condom from a vending machine, he is transformed into a head-turner in his 20s. When he returns to the bar, a fetching blond who had been indifferent now smiles at him invitingly.</p>
        <p>Directed by Phil Joanou (''State of Grace''), with special effects by the Stan Winston Studio (''Jurassic Park''), the commercial is entertaining. But it also has a message, spelled out at the end: ''Evolve. Use a condom every time.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fox, which along with CBS rejected a Trojan commercial, said that “contraceptive advertising must stress health-related uses rather than the prevention of pregnancy.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a commercial for Trojan condoms that has its premiere tonight, women in a bar are surrounded by anthropomorphized, cellphone-toting pigs. One shuffles to the men's room, where, after procuring a condom from a vending machine, he is transformed into a head-turner in his 20s. When he returns to the bar, a fetching blond who had been indifferent now smiles at him invitingly.</p>
        <p>Directed by Phil Joanou (''State of Grace''), with special effects by the Stan Winston Studio (''Jurassic Park''), the commercial is entertaining. But it also has a message, spelled out at the end: ''Evolve. Use a condom every time.''</p>
        <p>''We have to change the perception that carrying a condom for women or men is a sign they're on the prowl and just want to have sex,'' said Linda Kaplan Thaler, chief executive of the Kaplan Thaler Group, the New York advertising agency that created the ''Evolve'' campaign. ''It's a sign of somebody being prepared -- if the opportunity arises -- to think about their own health and the health and safety of their partner.''</p>
        <p>But the pigs did not fly at two of the four networks where Trojan tried to place the ad.</p>
        <p>Fox and CBS both rejected the commercial. Both had accepted Trojan's previous campaign, which urged condom use because of the possibility that a partner might be H.I.V.-positive, perhaps unknowingly. A 2001 report about condom advertising by the Henry J. Kaiser Family Foundation found that, ''Some networks draw a strong line between messages about disease prevention -- which may be allowed -- and those about pregnancy prevention, which may be considered controversial for religious and moral reasons.''</p>
        <p>Representatives for both Fox and CBS confirmed that they had refused the ads, but declined to comment further.</p>
        <p>In a written response to Trojan, though, Fox said that it had rejected the spot because, ''Contraceptive advertising must stress health-related uses rather than the prevention of pregnancy.''</p>
        <p>In its rejection, CBS wrote, ''while we understand and appreciate the humor of this creative, we do not find it appropriate for our network even with late-night-only restrictions.''</p>
        <p>''It's so hypocritical for any network in this culture to go all puritanical on the subject of condom use when their programming is so salacious,'' said Mark Crispin Miller, a media critic who teaches at New York University. ''I mean, let's get real here. Fox and CBS and all of them are in the business of nonstop soft porn, but God forbid we should use a condom in the pursuit of sexual pleasure.''</p>
        <p>Networks accept ads of a not-so-subtle sexual nature for erectile dysfunction drugs like Viagra, often restricting them to the wee hours.</p>
        <p>Trojan has had no trouble finding other broadcasters to take its money. Jim Daniels, vice president for marketing, said that the company was spending more on this than any previous campaign, but declined to say how much. The commercial will run on ABC, NBC and nine cable networks, including MTV, Comedy Central and Adult Swim. Print ads will appear in 11 magazines and on seven Web sites. All will highlight a Web site, trojanevolve.com.</p>
        <p>The 87-year-old company placed its first ad in trade magazines for pharmacists in 1927, when druggists still kept condoms behind the counter. Though out in the aisles for decades, condoms are still purchased furtively: while the average time shopping for a home-pregnancy test is 2.5 minutes, the average condom buyer takes just 7 seconds, according to research by Trojan. ''We call it a drive-by purchase,'' Mr. Daniels said. ''People to this day are embarrassed.''</p>
        <p>In its new commercial, the word ''Trojan'' is never uttered, and the logo appears only briefly on the bathroom's vending machine and at the end. But with what according to A. C. Nielsen Research is 75 percent of the condom market (Durex is second with 15 percent, LifeStyles third with 9 percent), Mr. Daniels said the company was focusing less on growing market share than growing the market. The annual condom market is now $416 million, according to Packaged Facts, a division of MarketResearch.com.</p>
        <p>''With a 75 percent share of the market, we can prioritize growing the category and increasing overall condom usage,'' Mr. Daniels said. ''Right now in the U.S. only one in four sex acts involves using a condom. That's dramatically below usage rates in other developed countries. Our goal is to dramatically increase use.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes that goal finds Mr. Daniels seeming less like he works for Church &amp; Dwight -- the consumer products company that purchased Trojan in 2001 and also makes Arm &amp; Hammer baking soda -- and more like an agitator for public health. Last year, for example, Trojan issued its first Sexual Health Report Card, grading 100 colleges and universities on criteria including their testing for sexually transmitted diseases, sexual assault courses and, of course, condom availability.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Daniels does not disparage the company's double-entendre-heavy ''Trojan Man'' campaign from the 1990s or similar Trojan Tales Web site today, the tone of the 87-year-old company's promotions is moving away from ''Beavis and Butthead'' and toward ''Sex and the City.''</p>
        <p>''The 'Evolve' ad does a nice job of being humorous, but it's also a serious call to action,'' Mr. Daniels said. ''The pigs are a symbol of irresponsible sexual behavior, and are juxtaposed with the condom as a responsible symbol of respect for oneself and one's partner.''</p>
        <p>The industry typically tries to reach men, but this campaign's ads are running in Cosmopolitan and Glamour. Trojan sees growth potential in women customers, who make only 30 percent of condom purchases. In 2005 it introduced Elexa, a line of condoms in pastel packages that include what is known in industry parlance as a ''pleasure accessory.''</p>
        <p>Trojan and its competitors are adding the accessories across their entire product lines. The perennial challenge for condoms is the perception that they are unpleasant to use, so having an erotic add-on could increase sales as well as lower the incidence of disease and unintended pregnancies. The pleasure enhancement is a message that TV networks may be reluctant to broadcast.</p>
        <p>''We always find it funny that you can use sex to sell jewelry and cars, but you can't use sex to sell condoms,'' said Carol Carrozza, vice president of marketing for Ansell Healthcare, which makes LifeStyles condoms. ''When you're marketing condoms, something even remotely suggestive gets an overly analytical eye when it's going before networks' review boards.''</p>
        <p>ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
