<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Indonesian Terror Group Limits Attacks</title>
    <meta content="18indo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/world/asia/18indo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sulawesi (Indonesia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Poso (Indonesia)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jemaah Islamiyah (Terrorist Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mydans, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Indonesia</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Jemaah Islamiyah</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E0DD123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="956" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Indonesian Terror Group Limits Attacks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Indonesian Terror Group Limits Attacks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mydans, Seth</byline>
      <dateline>JAKARTA, Indonesia, June 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Indonesia's major terrorist group Jemaah Islamiyah appears to be pulling back from large-scale attacks, leaning more toward smaller-scale attacks and small localized wars like one now under way in Poso on island of Sulawesi; recent arrests of leader and military chief of Jemaah Islamiyah is likely to lead to further arrests and weakening of organization; but smaller groups are moving foward; expert says threat now comes mainly from 'radical fringe of the radical fringe'; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Long before the arrests of two of its top militants last week, the region's major terrorist group had been moving away from the tactic of large-scale attacks, experts said Sunday.</p>
        <p>This is a time of religious and social ferment, as Indonesia's tradition of moderation and inclusiveness is tested by a rise in conservatism and an increased focus on Islam as a religion and a moral code.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Long before the arrests of two of its top militants last week, Jemaah Islamiyah had been moving away from the tactic of large-scale attacks, experts said Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Long before the arrests of two of its top militants last week, the region's major terrorist group had been moving away from the tactic of large-scale attacks, experts said Sunday.</p>
        <p>This is a time of religious and social ferment, as Indonesia's tradition of moderation and inclusiveness is tested by a rise in conservatism and an increased focus on Islam as a religion and a moral code.</p>
        <p>Islamist violence is only one factor, and there is division and debate among militants as well as among the population at large.</p>
        <p>Even as the major terrorist group, Jemaah Islamiyah, appears to be pulling back from large-scale attacks, smaller groups are moving forward. The threat now comes mainly from what one expert called ''the radical fringe of the radical fringe.''</p>
        <p>The arrests in the past week of both the leader and the military chief of Jemaah Islamiyah were ''a body blow'' to the group, said the expert, Sidney Jones. The intelligence they provide is likely to lead to further arrests and the weakening of the organization.</p>
        <p>''It means police know about and are taking steps to dismantle the leadership of J. I.,'' said Ms. Jones, an analyst with the International Crisis Group.</p>
        <p>''I think it's going to throw the organization in a state of confusion for a while,'' she said. ''It will be a period of consolidation and lying low.''</p>
        <p>More broadly, though, whether through violence, religious teachings or political campaigns, a long-term struggle is under way as Indonesia redefines itself in a new period of democracy and openness.</p>
        <p>Since the fall of Indonesia's strongman, Suharto, in 1998, the country has experienced the rise of Islam on many fronts, from armed groups to political parties to private religious devotion.</p>
        <p>There has also been a conservative trend in Islam in Indonesia that includes a radicalization of campuses and experimentation in some local jurisdictions with mild forms of Islamic law. Much greater numbers of women are wearing Muslim head scarves than before, and more people are describing themselves as devout Muslims.</p>
        <p>Not all of this points toward the creation of a Muslim state. And very little of it supports violence.</p>
        <p>''I think that in Indonesia the story is that the violent radicals are in the process of beating themselves,'' said Richard Baker, a former American diplomat who is a special assistant to the president of the East-West Center in Hawaii.</p>
        <p>''The Bali bombings both turned off the public and turned on the government,'' Mr. Baker said in a recent interview. The bombings at two nightclubs in 2002 spurred the government to confront terrorism more directly. ''And ever since, the radicals have been on the run,'' he said. As to chasing down the leaders, he added, ''The Indonesians have done a pretty good job.''</p>
        <p>There have been no major terrorist attacks in Indonesia since 2005, and Jemaah Islamiyah appears to be leaning more toward smaller-scale attacks and small localized wars like one that is now under way in Poso on the island of Sulawesi.</p>
        <p>''There are those now within J. I. who have realized that by using violence they would not be able to achieve their objectives,'' said an Indonesian intelligence official who spoke on condition of anonymity. ''There is, I suppose you could call it, a split within the group.''</p>
        <p>It is not that they oppose mass killings on principle or that their aims have changed, Ms. Jones said.</p>
        <p>A cost-benefit analysis by the International Crisis Group issued last month indicates that large-scale attacks are more expensive and also less effective in drawing new recruits.</p>
        <p>An attempt to bomb the Australian Embassy cost about $8,000, the report said, while the assassination of the leader of the Central Sulawesi Protestant Church cost $25.</p>
        <p>Both the men arrested last week appeared briefly to make televised statements in which they admitted their roles in Jemaah Islamiyah.</p>
        <p>One of them, Zarkasih, 45, who like many in Indonesia uses only one name, was identified for the first time as the group's overall leader. He was captured shortly after Abu Dujana, 37, its military commander. Six other militants were also arrested.</p>
        <p>''If Dujana is willing to talk, he will be able to tell the police about the structure, strength, finances and the international connections, as well as the goal and objectives of J. I.,'' Ms. Jones said.</p>
        <p>The authorities said they hoped the arrests would help them capture Noordin Top, a Malaysian fugitive who has formed a more violent splinter group that continues to advocate large-scale violence.</p>
        <p>He has been blamed for the bombings in Bali in 2002, which took more than 200 lives, as well as for attacks in the next two years on the J. W. Marriott Hotel and the Australian Embassy in Jakarta and for suicide bombings in Bali in 2005.</p>
        <p>In large part the arrests are the work of an elite counterterrorism unit, Detachment 88, that was established in 2003 with assistance from the United States and Australia.</p>
        <p>Since the first Bali bombings, more than 400 members of Jemaah Islamiyah have been arrested in Indonesia and elsewhere in the region, said Zachary Abuza, an expert on terrorism who teaches at Simmons College in Boston. Nearly 200 people have been put on trial in Indonesia, he said.</p>
        <p>But the battle against violent Islamists is only part of the broader situation.</p>
        <p>''The real tension for the next indefinite time of years is not going to lie at the extremist fringe,'' said Robert W. Hefner, an expert on Indonesian Islam at Boston University, in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>''Indonesia has always had extremists and it always will have extremists,'' he said. ''They were never numerous but they have always been there, very small, just like America. But they are not going to change the system.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
