<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METROPOLITAN DIARY</title>
    <meta content="18DIARY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/nyregion/18DIARY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855409"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Metropolitan Diary"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metropolitan Diary</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E7DC123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="702" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METROPOLITAN DIARY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dear Diary</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Scene: Direct flight from Cancún, Mexico, to Newark. Seated in plane waiting for takeoff.</p>
        <p>Spring Breaker Guy in Row 17: ''Hey there, so where you from?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Yorkers travel abroad, a baseball fan makes a new friend and a police officer declines a donut.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Scene: Direct flight from Cancún, Mexico, to Newark. Seated in plane waiting for takeoff.</p>
        <p>Spring Breaker Guy in Row 17: ''Hey there, so where you from?''</p>
        <p>Good-Looking Girl in Row 18: ''Manhattan.''</p>
        <p>Spring Breaker Guy: ''Oh, so are you flying into J.F.K.?''</p>
        <p>Good-Looking Girl: ''No, I'm flying into Newark. So are you -- we're on the same plane.''</p>
        <p>Ethan Goodman</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>Recently I was in a Dunkin' Donuts on Fifth Avenue in Bay Ridge, Brooklyn. Ahead of me in line was a police officer in uniform.</p>
        <p>The officer ordered a coffee and the clerk asked solicitously, ''Would you like a doughnut?''</p>
        <p>The officer turned to me and smiled. ''You know,'' he said, ''it's just a myth.''</p>
        <p>Amy Bedford</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>The 6 a.m. regulars at the Washington Square Park dog run are, not surprisingly, a very pet-oriented group, as witnessed on a recent spring morning.</p>
        <p>One of the regulars, John, started discussing his recent business trip to Texas: ''The flight was awful! We were delayed for a few hours and then, when we finally boarded, the baby behind my seat didn't stop crying for the whole flight back to New York.''</p>
        <p>Anne, another dog-run regular, turned to him in surprise: ''What did the owner do?''</p>
        <p>Toby Young</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>On a recent hiking trip in northern Israel, I was asked how I kept my balance on the rocks and ledges we were climbing, since I did not have any walking poles.</p>
        <p>I told them that I had learned my balancing skills from riding on the subway. If I don't get a seat, I am usually standing in the middle, not wanting to touch the poles, and trying to read the newspaper without falling.</p>
        <p>I have been quite successful in keeping myself upright, and it even turned out to be a great training skill for this trip.</p>
        <p>Diane Burstein</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>The crowded American Airlines flight from Dallas landed on time at La Guardia on a recent Friday night, but there was a long wait for a gate to open up at the terminal.</p>
        <p>A 5-year-old boy traveling in coach with his family simply could not wait any longer, and he rushed to the first-class bathroom despite the efforts of the flight attendant to turn him back to his seat.</p>
        <p>While he was in the lavatory, the plane pulled up to the gate and the seat belt sign was turned off. All the alpha males in first class immediately stood up, grabbed their luggage and completely filled the aisle waiting for the aircraft door to open.</p>
        <p>Out of the lavatory pops the 5-year-old, wanting to rejoin his family. He could not see his dad and was beginning to well up with tears.</p>
        <p>Businessmen are paid to think fast, so the big guy in 1-B picks up the boy and hands him back to the executive in 2-C, who passes him on to 3-C, and so it goes, until the 5-year-old is safely returned to his family. Crisis averted.</p>
        <p>Neal Pilson</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>My office building at 60th and Madison has been undergoing an extensive renovation for the past few months, replacing all windows and the exterior facade. Construction workers on scaffolding have been going up, down, up, down all day long.</p>
        <p>On a recent Monday morning, as I was on the phone, one worker stopped his scaffolding as it descended outside my office. He motioned for me to open the window, and after a few shrugs and moments of bewilderment, I did so, and this conversation (think New York accent) ensued:</p>
        <p>Construction Worker (motioning at the framed baseball memorabilia hanging on my wall): ''I see you're a collector; I'm a collector, too. I got photos of the Babe, a ball with all the 1998 world champ Yankee signatures, DiMaggio's jersey, lots of stuff. You got a card? We should have lunch sometime.''</p>
        <p>By now my staff had gathered at my door to witness the scene. I gave him my card, shook his hand, and closed the window.</p>
        <p>I haven't heard from my new friend yet, but I thought when he calls we might even take in a ballgame or two.</p>
        <p>Alan Momeyer</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Diary</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
