<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Back to a Garden Where More Than Jams Flower</title>
    <meta content="18bonn" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/arts/music/18bonn.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855369"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bonnaroo Festival (Manchester, Tenn)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Police, The</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Tool</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Police, The</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Tool</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Police, The</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Tool</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Widespread Panic</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Sting</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sting</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sting</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE5DD123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1204" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Back to a Garden Where More Than Jams Flower</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Festival With More Than Just Jam-Bands</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <dateline>MANCHESTER, Tenn., June 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Each year the Bonnaroo Music and Arts Festival insists it's not just a hippie jam-band festival. This year two of Bonnaroo's three headliners came from way off the jam-band circuit -- Tool on Friday night and the Police on Saturday. Other performers on the three-and-a-half-day schedule spanned British rock, Canadian pop, soul, bluegrass, reggae, jazz and alternative hip-hop along with jam-band stalwarts like Sunday's finale headliner, Widespread Panic.</p>
        <p>But when the sold-out audience of 80,000 arrived, the sixth annual Bonnaroo stayed hippie. Tie-dye, long hair, peasant dresses and flowers were everywhere amid the organic food stands and recycling displays. So were smiling faces, pot smoke and the willingness to dance to anything with a beat. (''It's invent-your-own-folk-dance night,'' one of the New Orleans Klezmer Allstars said as listeners skipped and swayed to speedy Eastern European melodies mixed with a New Orleans backbeat.) Jam-band fans responded to instrumental details as well as the catchphrases of pop hits; they whooped for a hot solo. In the age of the ringtone-ready pop hook, Bonnaroo celebrates musical dexterity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This year two of Bonnaroo’s three headliners  Tool and the Police  came from way off the jam-band circuit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Each year the Bonnaroo Music and Arts Festival insists it's not just a hippie jam-band festival. This year two of Bonnaroo's three headliners came from way off the jam-band circuit -- Tool on Friday night and the Police on Saturday. Other performers on the three-and-a-half-day schedule spanned British rock, Canadian pop, soul, bluegrass, reggae, jazz and alternative hip-hop along with jam-band stalwarts like Sunday's finale headliner, Widespread Panic.</p>
        <p>But when the sold-out audience of 80,000 arrived, the sixth annual Bonnaroo stayed hippie. Tie-dye, long hair, peasant dresses and flowers were everywhere amid the organic food stands and recycling displays. So were smiling faces, pot smoke and the willingness to dance to anything with a beat. (''It's invent-your-own-folk-dance night,'' one of the New Orleans Klezmer Allstars said as listeners skipped and swayed to speedy Eastern European melodies mixed with a New Orleans backbeat.) Jam-band fans responded to instrumental details as well as the catchphrases of pop hits; they whooped for a hot solo. In the age of the ringtone-ready pop hook, Bonnaroo celebrates musical dexterity.</p>
        <p>The festival is making itself an institution. This year its promoters, A.C. Entertainment and Superfly Productions, bought the central 530 acres of the 700 acres of farmland where Bonnaroo is held, about 60 miles from Nashville. (They lease the rest for campgrounds and parking.) And the festival uses its hippie flavor as both a touchstone and something to push against.</p>
        <p>The reunited Police were a perfect fit for Bonnaroo. They were always a trio of virtuosos, packing jazzy inversions into three-minute pop songs. What disappeared when the band broke up in 1983 was a chance to hear the interaction of musicians whose blend and friction forged one of rock's most original ensemble sounds. They left behind terse, neatly arranged studio albums and a few live recordings. Now on tour again, they are jamming other options. Their Bonnaroo set interspersed familiar arrangements with new ones, often within the same song.</p>
        <p>The Police have their old strengths: Sting's springy bass lines and his reedy, fervent, undiminished voice; Stewart Copeland's drumming, with its mixture of thwacking propulsion and flurries of jazzy detail; Andy Summers's resourceful guitar parts, creating the harmonies with watercolor transparency. They radically remade a few songs, but more often they switched in and out, delivering a verse or two of the hit version amid revamps of harmony and groove and some aggressive, extended guitar solos. There were sparks, teases, intriguing excursions and a few misfires, but the Police sounded vital, still fascinated by Sting's songs and ready to tear into them anew. The band is too skillful -- and too hardheaded -- to return as simply a jukebox of old songs. It's jamming.</p>
        <p>Maynard James Keenan, the leader of Tool, mocked Bonnaroo's hippie atmosphere: ''I assume you're on the marijuana and the LSD,'' he deadpanned. ''You're all under arrest.'' But Tool played a magnificent set, with songs that built from monumentally slow, earth-shaking intros to fast, intricate progressive-rock. In a way Tool could have been the Police's evil twin, using equally intricate, quick-fingered music along with an infusion of harder rock to sound more menacing. Bonnaroo's crowd danced even as Mr. Keenan sang about a Deadhead drug casualty in ''Rosetta Stoned.''</p>
        <p>Most of the Bonnaroo audience spends three or four days in campgrounds adjoining the site for a communal (and increasingly ripe-smelling) experience beyond the music. Since they're in rural Tennessee for the duration, they don't just show up for the headliners; they enthusiastically sample all sorts of possibilities. There was music from the five main stages, a jazz stage, a comedy tent and a few smaller stages, not to mention guitars and bongos in the campgrounds.</p>
        <p>There were some jam-band circuit regulars in the lineup, like Xavier Rudd, Keller Williams, Sound Tribe Sector 9 and the String Cheese Incident. The bluesy Southern rock band Gov't Mule opened its set to guests, including John Paul Jones (Led Zeppelin's bassist, who also sat in with others during the festival) and the founders of Hot Tuna.</p>
        <p>But all the jam bands at Bonnaroo could be easily be bypassed for other bands that deserved, and got, an equally euphoric response. They included the Black Angels, playing 1960s-rooted, ritualistic drone rock; Lily Allen, delivering funny, sassy, pop-ska kiss-offs; the methodical, eclectic instrumental band Tortoise; Annuals, who play shimmering, unfurling indie-rock anthems; James (Blood) Ulmer, who brought the splintered harmolodic approach of Ornette Coleman to power-trio blues; Regina Spektor, playing childlike-sounding but tough-minded piano pop; the Hold Steady, using big '70s rock riffs behind spoken and sung tales of messed-up lives; and Dierks Bentley, a mainstream country star who's fond of trucker songs.</p>
        <p>There was a New Orleans contingent, with funk and feathers from the Wild Magnolia Mardi Gras Indians and a preview of the next album by Galactic, a New Orleans funk band that has teamed up with alternative rappers like Lateef the Truthspeaker. And there was a Philadelphia delegation too: hip-hop from the Roots, exuberant pop from Dr. Dog and jazz from the Philadelphia Experiment, including Ahmir (?uestlove) Thompson from the Roots on drums along with Christian McBride on bass, Uri Caine on piano and, at 2:30 on Sunday morning, the actress Gina Gershon (a non-Philadelphian) twanging a jew's-harp.</p>
        <p>This year's Bonnaroo had a new addition: a jazz stage set up like a club, in a dark room with tables and wait service. It was constantly packed, with a line, for music primarily from the roster of Blue Note Records, which sponsored the stage in a wise marketing move. Since Bonnaroo's audience prizes virtuosity and nuance, why not offer them in the highly evolved form of jazz? Younger musicians like the pianist Robert Glasper are already meeting contemporary music on their own terms; he played one piece based on a hip-hop groove from J Dilla, and another that mingled Radiohead's ''Everything in the Right Place'' with Herbie Hancock's ''Maiden Voyage.'' Older musicians, like the 80-year-old saxophonist Lou Donaldson and the organist Dr. Lonnie Smith, didn't need updating at all.</p>
        <p>Along with the flower-child clothing, there was another 1960s echo at Bonnaroo: antiwar statements and other political protests in songs and stage patter. Some came from politically minded performers like the Roots, the rapper and singer Michael Franti and Manu Chao, the polyglot European whose hopped-up reggae and ska tunes affirm human rights. But discontent with politicians and the war turned up all over Bonnaroo, from the Flaming Lips to the British trad-rocker Richard Thompson.</p>
        <p>Spoon, which sets literate thoughts to tersely obsessive new wave rock, introduced a new song that had the chorus ''Don't make me a target,'' while the bluegrass band Old Crow Medicine Show drew applause for a line in a gospel song, ''I Hear Them All'': ''I hear soldiers quit their dying, one and all.'' Ben Harper and the Innocent Criminals ended their set with ''Better Way,'' a song with an internationalist beat, an East-West-flavored drone and determined lyrics -- ''You have a right to your dreams and don't be denied/I believe in a better way'' -- and it sounded inspirational.</p>
        <p>Bonnaroo's weekend in the sun for hippie types who never saw the 1960s has its silly moments. But compared with hipster cool or mass-market consumerism, hippie idealismmakes a fine alternative.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
