<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Undisputed Champion At Oakmont: The Course</title>
    <meta content="18anderson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/sports/golf/18anderson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Argentina</location>
        <org class="online_producer">United States Golf Assn</org>
        <org class="online_producer">PGA Tour Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Furyk, Jim</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Nicklaus, Jack</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Palmer, Arnold</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE5DB123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Undisputed Champion At Oakmont: The Course</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">True Winner at Oakmont: The Course</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ﾃ］gel Cabrera of Argentina had the lowest score in the 107th United States Open and his name is on the trophy, but the name that should be engraved on it as the winner is: Oakmont. In capital letters.</p>
        <p>With Cabrera in the clubhouse with a one-under-par 69 that included five birdies, Tiger Woods held center stage under the pink clouds of yesterday's twilight until his 30-foot birdie putt to force an 18-hole playoff curled past the cup on the 18th green. Watching television, the 37-year-old Cabrera smiled, the champion in a major for the first time with a five-over 285 total.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>ﾃ］gel Cabrera of Argentina had the lowest score in the 107th United States Open and his name is on the trophy, but the name that should be engraved on it as the winner is: Oakmont.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ﾃ］gel Cabrera of Argentina had the lowest score in the 107th United States Open and his name is on the trophy, but the name that should be engraved on it as the winner is: Oakmont. In capital letters.</p>
        <p>With Cabrera in the clubhouse with a one-under-par 69 that included five birdies, Tiger Woods held center stage under the pink clouds of yesterday's twilight until his 30-foot birdie putt to force an 18-hole playoff curled past the cup on the 18th green. Watching television, the 37-year-old Cabrera smiled, the champion in a major for the first time with a five-over 285 total.</p>
        <p>Although a longtime winner on the European Tour and in South America, Cabrera had never finished higher in a major than fourth in the 1999 British Open, but he was a steady stroke better than Woods, the world's No. 1 golfer, and Jim Furyk, who is No. 3.</p>
        <p>''Teeing off on 18, I think that was the most difficult moment and tee shot,'' Cabrera said. ''I had to put that ball in the fairway and make 4 and sit and wait. I lost the British Open very close and I was close at Augusta. So definitely enjoying this moment.''</p>
        <p>Rebuked in his bid for a 13th major title, Woods was never able to make enough birdies to offset his bogeys. With a birdie on any of the final three holes, he would have tied Cabrera, but he never had a realistic birdie opportunity -- a putt from 45 feet away on the 16th, a chip from 20 feet in the greenside rough on the 17th and a putt from 30 feet on the final green.</p>
        <p>With a 72, Woods couldn't avert his fourth runner-up finish in a major. He also couldn't change the hard truth that, while he is 12 for 12 in a major when holding or sharing the third-round lead, he is now 0 for 25 when he has had to come from behind to win. The only two times he has won the Open, in 2000 and 2002, he held the first-round lead.</p>
        <p>''I put myself there and haven't gotten it done,'' Woods said. ''My last four majors, I've been 1, 1, 2, 2 -- not terrible, but I could have been a little bit better.''</p>
        <p>In the rolling hills above the Allegheny River outside Pittsburgh, a golfer didn't win the Open; the 7,230-yard par-70 torture chamber known as the Oakmont Country Club course did.</p>
        <p>For four warm but not hot days, the world's best golfers had to hack their ball out of the deep scraggly rough as if they were swinging a scythe in a hayfield. Just getting it back on the fairway was a triumph, much less on the green. And when they eventually got to the green, their adventure had only begun.</p>
        <p>More often than not, if a golfer's ball was in a greenside bunker or in the rough, he had to aim away from the flagstick in order to try to comply with the slopes, swales and speed of the putting surface.</p>
        <p>Don't blame the marquis de sods at the United States Golf Association who set up the Open course each year. The golfers didn't. All week, even the usual whiners at other Opens were virtually unanimous in praising Oakland as ''difficult but fair.'' Extremely difficult. But that's what happens when the world's best golfers can't just bomb it off the tee without any real rough to worry about and can't spin their approach shots close to the holes cut in the most precarious portions of the greens.</p>
        <p>At the 23 previous weekly PGA Tour events this year, the average winning 72-hole score was 13.34 strokes under par, including Zach Johnson's one-over-par triumph at the Masters. Cabrera was the only golfer to shoot under par twice -- a 69 in the first round, another yesterday to win.</p>
        <p>Oakmont has been tough in other Opens, but not this tough. Jack Nicklaus and Arnold Palmer tied at one under par in 1962 before Nicklaus won their playoff, 71 to 74. Larry Nelson was four under in 1983, Ben Hogan five under par in 1953, Johnny Miller five under par after his final-round record 63 in 1973. In 1994, Ernie Els, Loren Roberts and Colin Montgomerie were each five under before Els won the playoff.</p>
        <p>For all the people out there who play golf for fun or for $5, Woods put Oakmont in perspective halfway through this Open when he was asked Friday just how difficult Oakmont was playing.</p>
        <p>''If you're a 10-handicapper,'' Woods said, referring to someone who would average 82 on a good course, ''there is no way you're breaking 100 out there if you played all out on every shot. There is no way. You just have to be so patient, and on top of that you've got to be strong coming out of the rough and you've got to have unbelievable touch on the greens. Most 10-handicappers I know,'' he added, smiling, ''don't have that.''</p>
        <p>And at Oakmont, only a few of the world's best golfers had anywhere near that much strength and that much touch. ﾃ］gel Cabrera's name may be on the trophy, but Oakmont won this Open.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
