<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Bus Attack, Afghan Police Mourn Their Own</title>
    <meta content="18afghan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/world/asia/18afghan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855471"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kabul (Afghanistan)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Taliban (Afghan Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bearak, Barry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Afghanistan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Taliban</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E2DB123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="960" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Bus Attack, Afghan Police Mourn Their Own</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Bus Attack, Afghan Police Mourn Their Own</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARRY BEARAK; Abdul Waheed Wafa contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bearak, Barry</byline>
      <dateline>KABUL, Afghanistan, June 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Huge explosion on police bus in Kabul kills at least 24 people in one of deadliest insurgent attacks in Afghanistan since fall of Taliban in 2001; 22 victims are police academy instructors; blast also rips apart two other vehicles and wounds many passersby; Taliban spokesman says suicide bomber had infiltrated police ahd boarded bus; chaotic scene described; fellow polie officers mourn their slain comrades; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A mammoth explosion tore through a police bus in the heart of Kabul on Sunday morning, killing at least 24 people -- 22 of them police academy instructors on their way to work -- in one of the deadliest insurgent attacks in Afghanistan since the fall of the Taliban in 2001.</p>
        <p>The blast occurred at 8:15 and was powerful enough to shear off the roof and both sides of the bus and uproot many of the front seats. The Taliban claimed responsibility for the attack, with Zabihullah Mujahid, who said he was a spokesman, saying in a phone interview that a suicide bomber had infiltrated the police and guilefully boarded the vehicle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A mammoth explosion tore through a police bus in the heart of Kabul on Sunday, killing at least 24 people  22 of them police academy instructors on their way to work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A mammoth explosion tore through a police bus in the heart of Kabul on Sunday morning, killing at least 24 people -- 22 of them police academy instructors on their way to work -- in one of the deadliest insurgent attacks in Afghanistan since the fall of the Taliban in 2001.</p>
        <p>The blast occurred at 8:15 and was powerful enough to shear off the roof and both sides of the bus and uproot many of the front seats. The Taliban claimed responsibility for the attack, with Zabihullah Mujahid, who said he was a spokesman, saying in a phone interview that a suicide bomber had infiltrated the police and guilefully boarded the vehicle.</p>
        <p>Kabul's police chief, Esmatullah Daulatzai, said the precise tactics of the attack were unclear. ''Our investigation shows that a suicide attacker jumped into the vehicle and blew himself up,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Whatever the method, it was spectacularly lethal, unleashing shards of glass and metal into a crowded area beside police headquarters, the governor's office and the national archive. Two other vehicles were ripped apart by the explosion. The wounded included pedestrians waiting at an adjacent bus terminal.</p>
        <p>Raz Muhammad, a policeman standing guard at headquarters, was among the first to reach the scene. ''Those in the front seats, their bodies were very ripped apart,'' he said. ''Half of their heads were gone and there was brain matter all over. Very few of those inside survived. I could help those able to walk.''</p>
        <p>There is confusion about the death toll. Police officials originally said 36 had died, but the chief later amended that number, adding that 52 people were wounded, including 38 who had to be hospitalized. It remains possible that more than 24 people perished. Bodies were taken to more than one hospital and then quickly released to families, perhaps sacrificing an accurate mortality count.</p>
        <p>In any case, the magnitude and casualties in the attack evoked memories of a similarly huge bombing in the capital on Sept. 5, 2002, that killed at least 30 people and wounded 170 in a marketplace. Afghan and American officials blamed the Taliban and Al Qaeda for that blast.</p>
        <p>The attack on Sunday occurred on a heat-swaddled day. Havoc immediately spread through an area that customarily teems with people, in a country long contaminated with tragedy.</p>
        <p>An anguished 14-year-old named Emal recognized the bus as the one driven by his father, Muhammad Hashib. ''I must see him,'' he cried as police officials kept him away from the wreckage. Though they knew otherwise, they tried to convince the boy that his father was alive, telling him to go home to await news.</p>
        <p>Then the policemen began their own ordeal of mourning, listing the names of those friends they had lost moments before: Azul, Jaleel, Habib.</p>
        <p>The policeman they called Habib was actually Habibullah, a 26-year-old who had once taught Dari literature and Islamic studies at a high school before entering the police academy. He was such an impressive cadet that after completing the three-year program he was kept on as an instructor. Last year, he married, and on Sunday he had eaten breakfast with his wife and infant son before leaving for the Interior Ministry, where the teachers catch the bus for the academy.</p>
        <p>''I barely recognized his corpse,'' said his brother Wahidullah, another policeman. He had searched for Habibullah, who like many Afghans uses only one name, at the military hospital where many bodies were taken. ''I recognized his belt, but his eyes and forehead were gone. I had to look very, very hard.'' As he said this, another policeman embraced him, and the two men wept.</p>
        <p>The dead were washed, wrapped in shrouds and given over to their kin. Habibullah's body was taken to his home village north of Kabul, Ahmad Shab Baba Mina. There, in a ritual of grieving repeated among woebegone families on a sorrowful Sunday, his body was displayed in a coffin in the courtyard of his ancestral home.</p>
        <p>Dozens of Habibullah's students came to say goodbye -- all of them dressed in the gabardine of cadets with blue stripes above their left pockets to indicate their seniority in the academy. ''He was so nice,'' said one cadet, Abdul Wares. ''We have a saying in this country that a man is so good he would not even hurt an ant. Habibullah was such a man.''</p>
        <p>Sunday's suicide attack was the sixth in Kabul this year and the second in two days. The Taliban are employing tactics similar to those used by insurgents in Iraq. The use of improvised explosive devices is also on the increase in Afghanistan, including one employed Sunday to kill three members of the United States-led coalition forces and their local interpreter in Kandahar Province.</p>
        <p>At 2:30 p.m., Habibullah's body was carried from the house in a coffin adorned with a black and gold blanket and wildflowers. A caravan proceeded to a mosque beside a cemetery. A few prayers were said before mourners took turns looking into the open casket where the head wounds were hidden beneath balls of cotton.</p>
        <p>Then Habibullah, the police academy teacher, was laid into his grave. His students covered him for eternity with the rocky soil of the beleaguered city. Though many were in tears, they chanted words of congratulations. In their eyes, their teacher had become a martyr.</p>
        <p>7 Children Killed by U.S. Strike</p>
        <p>KABUL, Monday, June 18 (Reuters) -- Seven Afghan children have been killed in a coalition airstrike led by the United States, the coalition said Monday. They are the latest civilian deaths by foreign troops amid rising anger in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>The strike, conducted late Sunday in southeastern Paktika province close to the border with Pakistan, also killed several militants, the coalition said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
