<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Retail Giant Will Remake Private Bank</title>
    <meta content="18bank" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/business/18bank.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855374"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Names, Organizational</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bank of America</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">US Trust Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dash, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Names, Organizational</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Bank of America Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">US Trust Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E4DD123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1155" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Retail Giant Will Remake Private Bank</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Retail Giant Will Remake Private Bank</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC DASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dash, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bank of America will announce that its business supporting high net-worth customers will be called US Trust, Bank of America Private Wealth Management; takes advantage of last year's $3.3 billion purchase of US Trust; marks first time bank has adopted name of acquired business; competitors say merger and rebranding effort will weaken US Trust name because of bank's strong retail heritage; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bank of America built its brand as a financial supermarket that could be all things to all people. Now, it will see if a new name can burnish its private bank's reputation in catering to the very rich.</p>
        <p>The company is expected to announce today that its business serving high net-worth customers will be called U.S. Trust, Bank of America Private Wealth Management, taking advantage of its $3.3 billion purchase last November of U.S. Trust, one of the most prestigious names in private banking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bank of America will see if a new name, U.S. Trust, Bank of America Private Wealth Management, can burnish its private bank’s reputation in catering to the very rich.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bank of America built its brand as a financial supermarket that could be all things to all people. Now, it will see if a new name can burnish its private bank's reputation in catering to the very rich.</p>
        <p>The company is expected to announce today that its business serving high net-worth customers will be called U.S. Trust, Bank of America Private Wealth Management, taking advantage of its $3.3 billion purchase last November of U.S. Trust, one of the most prestigious names in private banking.</p>
        <p>While Bank of America has long been an acquisition machine, the rebranding represents the first time it has adopted the name of a business it bought. Perception is important in the world of private banking, widely considered one of the fastest-growing and most lucrative areas in financial services, and Bank of America's private banking operation has long been overshadowed by the bank's predominantly middle-class image.</p>
        <p>''Clients told us, 'Your brand gets lost in the market,' '' said Brian Moynihan, president of the company's Global Wealth and Investment Management division, which includes the private bank. ''We are saying to clients that you are in this large franchise, but are in this special place.''</p>
        <p>A new advertising campaign is being developed and is expected to be rolled out shortly after Labor Day. Although the marketing giant Omnicom Group won the roughly $600 million account for the entire bank in August 2005, the private banking group's campaign was quietly moved to Hill Holliday, an agency at the Interpublic Group, a few months ago.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, some competitors snipe that the changes will ultimately prove to be cosmetic or they suggest that the merger and rebranding effort will water down the U.S. Trust name. For the bank that now calls itself the ''bank of opportunity,'' they argue, promoting white-glove service for the extremely rich at the same time that the broad company is hawking credit cards and mortgages to first-time home buyers is a particularly tricky sell.</p>
        <p>Other retail banks, like SunTrust, have chosen to offer their service to private banking clients under a separate brand name. Even JPMorgan Chase uses the J. P. Morgan brand to court the rich, distinguishing it from Chase, a mass-market commercial bank. But at Bank of America, the entire private bank will be under the U.S. Trust/Bank of America brand.</p>
        <p>''Banks that have a very strong retail heritage, like B. of A., can often be stereotyped,'' said Allan Starkie, a founding partner of Knightsbridge Advisors, a boutique firm that provides consulting and recruiting services to wealth managers, ''and it is much more difficult for them to create the image of being an old-world, high net worth and ultra-high net worth advisor.'' By buying one, he added, ''the sensible thing to do would be to keep it separate and not tamper with its brand, prestige and way of doing business.''</p>
        <p>Over the last decade, Bank of America has been very successful in smoothly melding a lot of disparate operations, notably the mammoth acquisition in 1998 in which NationsBank bought Bank of America and adopted its name, and more recently, the absorption of the regional banking giant FleetBoston and of the credit card behemoth MBNA. So far, though, the merger of its services with those of U.S. Trust has been turbulent.</p>
        <p>In trying to capitalize on the boom in global wealth, the new division of Bank of America is facing formidable competition. Investment banks like those at Citigroup, JPMorgan Chase and Goldman Sachs are aggressively courting rich investors, emphasizing their global networks and broad set of capabilities, like tax and investment advice or even financing the purchase of a private aircraft.</p>
        <p>Yet the industry has at the same time exploded with niche players and boutique wealth management offices, which maintain that they can provide more personalized service and advice free from conflicts.</p>
        <p>As the deal to buy U.S. Trust from Charles Schwab nears completion early in July, Bank of America has a lot at stake in making it work.</p>
        <p>With about 5,000 advisers, nearly 134,000 clients and more than $270 billion under management, the company says its combined private banking operations will make it the largest private bank in the industry by assets. And Kenneth D. Lewis, Bank of America's chairman and chief executive, has made the expansion of its wealth management division a cornerstone of his strategy for increasing its size without striking another big deal.</p>
        <p>''We are a monster company in this business,'' Mr. Lewis said in a brief interview while he was on his way to see private banking customers in the Napa Valley. ''We expect it to grow faster than our consumer bank and commercial bank because of its demographics.''</p>
        <p>Despite a large roster of existing wealthy clients, Bank of America's private bank is widely perceived as embodying many of the qualities of the larger institution, which emphasizes size and a standardized approach to customers -- a characterization the company strongly disputes.</p>
        <p>U.S. Trust, which counts many old-money families among its clients, carries one of the elite names in private banking as well as a management team that endorses high-cost, personalized service. These different philosophies shortly led to cultural and internal turmoil.</p>
        <p>While Bank of America executives played down cultural differences and said that client and associate attrition levels were ''normal'' for a merger, some recruiters and rivals say there are a lot of U.S. Trust advisers who have left the company or are looking to leave. (It may be too early to measure the extent of any lost client accounts.)</p>
        <p>The differences may have reached a boiling point in mid-April, when Peter K. Scaturro, U.S. Trust's chief executive, who had been expected to lead the merged private wealth management group, abruptly announced his departure after clashing with Bank of America executives.</p>
        <p>In the last two months, Bank of America reorganized the division into five geographic regions run by a single management team. In the past, Bank of America had a two-tier structure where its private bank catered to customers with more than $3 million and family wealth advisers served those with $50 million or more. Now, all the clients will be part of a single organization, but with varying levels of private banking service, based on their assets and needs.</p>
        <p>''With that many customers and markets, our reach was so broad that we could run into each other too much,'' Mr. Moynihan said of the decision. ''To bifurcate the businesses, it would have been problematic.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the company installed Frances Aldrich Sevilla-Sacasa, a close lieutenant of Mr. Scaturro at both Citigroup and U.S. Trust, to replace him as the new head of the Private Wealth Management group.</p>
        <p>Some executives in the private banking industry are skeptical that she will stay, but Ms. Sevilla-Sacasa suggested otherwise.</p>
        <p>''I firmly believe that we are going to be the leader in this business,'' she said. ''I would love to make this the opportunity for the rest of my career.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
