<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Doctor, Give Me the News, And Sew Me Up Pretty</title>
    <meta content="18bell" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/arts/television/18bell.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Turner Network Television</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Williams, Treat</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E5DD123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="553" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Doctor, Give Me the News, And Sew Me Up Pretty</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Doctor, Give Me the News, and Sew Me Up Pretty</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINIA BELLAFANTE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The deglamorization that doctors have suffered with the rise of H.M.O.'s in American life has had its corrective on television, where medical dramas seem to labor ever more aggressively to establish the physician's genius. It is an immensely long gurney ride from the era of ''St. Elsewhere'' in the 1980s to the current moment of ''House,'' on which Hugh Laurie represents medicine as a field not of workaday mechanics but of brash intellectualism and analytical skill. How could a mere M.D. suffice?</p>
        <p>On ''ER,'' which has been on the air for 13 years, the traumas and conditions have over time grown more unusual. From the beginning of ''Grey's Anatomy'' it seemed that quadruple bypasses and common cancers were not going to do. Here doctors confront diseases that are obscure and vaguely medieval, the triumph over them further romanticized by the sheer bizarreness of the challenge. This year that show featured a story about a patient with fibrodysplasia ossificans progressiva, a disorder in which damaged muscles and connective tissue turn to bone, forming, essentially, a second skeleton. The universe of ''Grey's Anatomy'' is not a universe of forms and paperwork, signatures and dotted lines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This new series on TNT is an unequivocally sexy hospital drama. But there is also something distinctly retrograde about it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The deglamorization that doctors have suffered with the rise of H.M.O.'s in American life has had its corrective on television, where medical dramas seem to labor ever more aggressively to establish the physician's genius. It is an immensely long gurney ride from the era of ''St. Elsewhere'' in the 1980s to the current moment of ''House,'' on which Hugh Laurie represents medicine as a field not of workaday mechanics but of brash intellectualism and analytical skill. How could a mere M.D. suffice?</p>
        <p>On ''ER,'' which has been on the air for 13 years, the traumas and conditions have over time grown more unusual. From the beginning of ''Grey's Anatomy'' it seemed that quadruple bypasses and common cancers were not going to do. Here doctors confront diseases that are obscure and vaguely medieval, the triumph over them further romanticized by the sheer bizarreness of the challenge. This year that show featured a story about a patient with fibrodysplasia ossificans progressiva, a disorder in which damaged muscles and connective tissue turn to bone, forming, essentially, a second skeleton. The universe of ''Grey's Anatomy'' is not a universe of forms and paperwork, signatures and dotted lines.</p>
        <p>''Heartland,'' a new series beginning tonight on TNT, is an unequivocally sexy hospital drama: figuratively, because the stakes are always high, and literally, because, well, there is sex. But there is also something distinctly retrograde about it. ''Heartland'' isn't committed to laborious diagnostics. Here the surgeon's profession seems almost proletarian; it is a fix-it business. As Nathaniel Grant, an organ-transplant surgeon in Pittsburgh, Treat Williams says things to his colleagues like ''So, I see you can sew.''</p>
        <p>''Heartland'' doesn't inspire you to dig deep on WebMD and learn more about rare afflictions. The drama doesn't digress; the terminology is never inscrutable. Someone is in dire need of a new kidney/lung/liver/heart, and someone else, near death, must be found to supply one. Nathaniel makes old organs work in new bodies, and his ex-wife (played by Kari Matchett) does the scouting, convincing reluctant relatives of the terminally ill that their loved ones must be chopped up and put to use to save lives.</p>
        <p>Nathaniel is a surgeon who, 1950s style, ruined his marriage by sleeping with young nurses. He is that paradigmatic fictional doctor: the renegade who alienates. He lives more or less in his office; in the world beyond it he perpetually disappoints. Day in and day out he gives people new lives -- a second chance -- while he can't seem to grab hold of one for himself.</p>
        <p>David Hollander, who created ''Heartland,'' isn't the kind of television auteur who, when he feels the impulse toward literalism, immediately expunges it. (On ''Heartland'' a successful surgery is followed by the sound of Elton John's ''Someone Saved My Life Tonight.'') But he has pared the medical drama down to its barest notions of life and death and sliced away the acronyms, arguably just when they needed some cutting.</p>
        <p>Heartland</p>
        <p>TNT, tonight at 10, Eastern and Pacific times; 9, Central time.</p>
        <p>David Hollander, creator, writer, director and executive producer; produced by Bob Rolsky.</p>
        <p>WITH: Treat Williams (Dr. Nathaniel Grant), Kari Matchett (Kate Armstrong), Chris William Martin (Dr. Simon), Morena Baccarin (Nurse Jessica Kivala), Danielle Nicolet (I.C.U. Nurse Mary), Gage Golightly (Thea Grant) and Dabney Coleman (Dr. Bart Jacobs).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
