<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the Campaign Trail With Elizabeth Edwards</title>
    <meta content="18web-nagourney" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855472"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E3DA133FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="900" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the Campaign Trail With Elizabeth Edwards</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <dateline>TIPTON, Iowa, June 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Elizabeth Edwards was holding court in the sweltering basement at the Cedar County Courthouse in Tipton, where local Democrats fanned themselves under fluorescent light. Her husband, John Edwards, making his second run for the presidency, watched and winced as she quizzed her audience about what they knew of his biography.</p>
        <p>''How many know how many members of his family went to college before he did?'' Mrs. Edwards inquired. The correct response emerged in murmured guesses from a few listeners: none.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Elizabeth Edwards was holding court in the sweltering basement at the Cedar County Courthouse in Tipton, where local Democrats fanned themselves under fluorescent light. Her husband, John Edwards, making his second run for the presidency, watched and winced as she quizzed her audience about what they knew of his biography.</p>
        <p>''How many know how many members of his family went to college before he did?'' Mrs. Edwards inquired. The correct response emerged in murmured guesses from a few listeners: none.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Edwards nodded approvingly, and went on to Question 2. ''How many people know what his father did?'' Again, the correct response could be heard from a few people, who recalled a stock line from Mr. Edwards's 2004 campaign speech: worked in a mill.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Edwards nodded proudly, so she moved in for the final question.</p>
        <p>''How many people know the price of his most expensive haircut?''</p>
        <p>A roar of laughter filled the room. Mr. Edwards grinned, gamely if barely, at the reference to the $400 haircut that had made him a subject of some derision. ''She's been doing this joke all day,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Edwards was laughing at her husband with her audience. ''I'm having fun,'' she said. ''How about you guys?''</p>
        <p>Indeed she was. This past weekend was supposed to be Mr. Edwards's big splash across Iowa -- 14 communities in three days, a signal to Iowans and the political world that he indeed views victory in this state, where he finished a close second to Senator John Kerry in 2004, as critical to his hopes of winning the Democratic presidential nomination. But even when it was not she who was talking, his wife was often the center of attention.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Edwards has always been a dominant figure in her husband's political life, and the news of her advanced stage of cancer has made her a riveting figure in her own right. She smiled demurely at the end of campaign events over the weekend, when, at times, more Iowans were gathered around her than her husband, offering words of support and hope.</p>
        <p>But her swing through Iowa also produced moments that broke the mold of political spouses' customary manner. Typically she introduced her husband with the joke about the haircut, reflecting her own keen political instincts. How better to deal with the mockery over it than to force-feed Mr. Edwards a little humble pie and make a few jokes at his expense? And who better to do so than his wife, who presumably felt she could do it without undermining him?</p>
        <p>The introductions over, she would sit at the side of the stage and whisper advice, and corrections, to him as he spoke. He kept one eye on questioners, the other on her.</p>
        <p>When he arrived for an interview Friday evening at a hotel in Des Moines, Mrs. Edwards was with him, appearing fit, jaunty and completely relaxed. She sat at the next table, out of camera shot and away from the microphone on the reporter's recorder. Yet she was as much a presence as he was, checking him, as well as his interviewer, on matters large and small.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards was answering a question about the evolution of his views on foreign policy. ''I have more clarity'' now, he was saying, ''about the specifics of particular issues that affect the rest of the world and affect America as a result, and the connectness.''</p>
        <p>He stopped and turned to his wife, looking like a student seeking approval from a teacher. ''Is that a word? Connectness?''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Edwards nodded. ''Yes.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Edwards was asked about his increasingly aggressive stance in confronting opponents this year, he somehow sensed a rise at his side. ''No, you can't answer the question, Elizabeth,'' he said, smiling and shaking his head, never looking her way.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Edwards laughed. The reporter suggested that they both answer. ''Let me answer the question first, then I'll be glad to let Elizabeth chime in,'' Mr. Edwards said. ''She always has her own opinion.''</p>
        <p>He proceeded with a lengthy response in which he talked of his essentially positive nature but also of the importance of pointing out his differences with opponents on issues like health care and the war in Iraq.</p>
        <p>Then it was Mrs. Edwards's turn. Her response was sharper, more direct.</p>
        <p>''Early in that debate Mrs. Clinton said something about basically we're all the same about this, and that wasn't actually accurate,'' she said of the Iraq issue. ''They weren't all the same, and if everything all looks like it's packaged like butter but some of it's oleo, you know, or margarine, you've got to -- voters need to know what it is they're buying.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards these days seems more fatigued than he did four years ago; he does not smile as often as he did during the last campaign. But there was one stirring moment on Saturday afternoon.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Edwards had broken away from his motorcade -- to go shopping, he said -- and he  was conducting a town-hall-style meeting alone at the Johnson County Fairgrounds in Iowa City when he suddenly glanced across the hall to see who was walking in.</p>
        <p>''Here comes Elizabeth!'' he roared in exuberance. ''Did you get your shopping done?''</p>
        <p>His audience -- her audience -- rose in a hail of applause, flashbulb snaps and more than a few tears.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
