<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Iraqi Journalist Found Dead in Baghdad as Security Lags</title>
    <meta content="18iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/world/middleeast/18iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855404"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EFDD123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1019" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Iraqi Journalist Found Dead in Baghdad as Security Lags</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Iraqi Journalist Found Dead as Security Lags</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISSA J. RUBIN; Reporting was contributed by Karim Hilmi and Khalid al-Ansary from Baghdad, and Iraqi employees of The New York Times from Diyala, Hilla and Basra.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rubin, Alissa J</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, June 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The body of the political editor of a government-financed newspaper was found Sunday in the main Baghdad mortuary.</p>
        <p>The editor, Falieh Mijthab, 48, was kidnapped three days ago by armed men in a Shiite neighborhood of Baghdad as he drove to Al-Sabah, the daily newspaper where he worked. A longtime reporter and former correspondent for the state-run newspaper under Saddam Hussein, Mr. Mijthab wrote and edited articles on political developments in Iraq. Mr. Mijthab had been shot, officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The body of the political editor of a government-financed newspaper was found in a Baghdad mortuary, three days after he was kidnapped in a Shiite neighborhood.The editor, Falieh Mijthab,</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The body of the political editor of a government-financed newspaper was found Sunday in the main Baghdad mortuary.</p>
        <p>The editor, Falieh Mijthab, 48, was kidnapped three days ago by armed men in a Shiite neighborhood of Baghdad as he drove to Al-Sabah, the daily newspaper where he worked. A longtime reporter and former correspondent for the state-run newspaper under Saddam Hussein, Mr. Mijthab wrote and edited articles on political developments in Iraq. Mr. Mijthab had been shot, officials said.</p>
        <p>''We blame the bad security situation in Baghdad for his murder,'' said Falah al-Mishaal, the editor of the paper. ''And we blame those who use religion as a tool to justify their deeds.''</p>
        <p>He added that he believed that Mr. Mijthab's work on behalf of Hussein government might have resulted in his assassination. Shiite militias have singled out a number of people with ties to the former government.</p>
        <p>The newspaper's offices have been bombed twice, and almost everyone on the staff has received death threats, Mr. Mishaal said. He said that Mr. Mijthab had received threatening phone calls for months but had continued working for the paper.</p>
        <p>The newspaper was started under the American-led Coalition Provisional Authority in 2003 and was thought to provide the government's view of events.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mijthab's death brings to 146 the number of journalists and media workers killed in Iraq since the war started in 2003, according to the Committee to Protect Journalists, a nonprofit organization based in New York. Iraqi journalists make up by far the largest number of victims.</p>
        <p>Assassinations and kidnappings in Baghdad have continued despite the presence of thousands more American and Iraqi troops since the beginning of the Baghdad security plan in February.</p>
        <p>Lt. Gen. Raymond T. Odierno, the second-ranking American officer in Iraq, said Sunday in an interview with The Associated Press that only about 40 percent of the city was under the control of the security forces.</p>
        <p>General Odierno said, however, that now that the full complement of American soldiers involved in the security plan had arrived, troops were moving into areas that they had been unable to patrol in the past. Among those are neighborhoods of southeast Baghdad and villages just south of the city's borders believed to be havens for Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia.</p>
        <p>The effort is part of the offensive announced Saturday by Gen. David H. Petraeus, the senior American commander in Iraq, to move into Qaeda redoubts in the belts around Baghdad, which the military believes have been used as manufacturing centers for car bombs and other explosives.</p>
        <p>The United States ambassador to Iraq, Ryan C. Crocker, speaking Sunday on the NBC News program ''Meet the Press,'' said that Americans were frustrated with the pace of a constitutional overhaul but that Iraqis were frustrated, too. He predicted that a law to divide the revenues from the country's oil production would be introduced in the next several days.</p>
        <p>Mr. Crocker conceded that whatever progress was made by the Iraqi government might be too late for an American public tired of watching their sons and daughters die in a war in which conditions had steadily worsened over the past four years.</p>
        <p>''A concern I have had is that there are two clocks, and the Washington clock is running a lot faster than the Baghdad clock is,'' Mr. Crocker said.</p>
        <p>But he also highlighted a point now made frequently by the Bush administration: that the consequences of a quick withdrawal by the United States could be devastating for the region. He said he would underscore that point to Congress and the White House when he and General Petraeus made a mandated report in September.</p>
        <p>''Iraq doesn't exist in a vacuum,'' Mr. Crocker said. ''We have the issue of the neighbors, particularly Iran and Syria, playing distinctly unhelpful roles. We've got to consider what could happen, depending on the decisions that are made back home.''</p>
        <p>Another unsettled neighbor is Turkey, which accuses Iraq of harboring guerrilla fighters from the Kurdistan Workers' Party, or P.K.K., a separatist group that is believed to be responsible for multiple attacks on Turkish solders and on outposts in eastern Turkey on the Iraq border.</p>
        <p>In a meeting on Sunday between Iraq's prime minister, Nuri Kamal al-Maliki, and the Turkish ambassador to Baghdad, Derya Kanbay, the men expressed their mutual opposition to terrorist activities. Mr. Maliki assured Mr. Kanbay that Iraq was sensitive to its neighbor's concerns about the P.K.K. and that it would ''ban any activity for the party in Iraq,'' according to a statement from Mr. Maliki's office.</p>
        <p>Although the government's official policy is that the P.K.K. is forbidden from staging attacks from Iraqi territory or using Iraq as a refuge, there is sympathy among many Iraqi Kurds for the Kurdish group's cause.</p>
        <p>''The P.K.K. five or six years ago asked the Turkish government to grant them unconditional amnesty but Turkey refused, and therefore they are responsible for the group coming to Iraq,'' said Mahmoud Othman, an Iraqi member of Parliament from the Kurdish Alliance, the largest of the Kurdish blocs in the legislature.</p>
        <p>''If the P.K.K. had political freedom in Turkey and could work without encountering violence, they wouldn't come to Iraq,'' Mr. Othman said. ''In the end, there is a kind of sympathy among Kurds all over the region.'' Large numbers of Kurds live in northern Iraq, Turkey, Iran and Syria.</p>
        <p>In Iraq violence, three American soldiers died over the weekend, the military said in a statement. One died in Kirkuk Province on Saturday because of injuries from a roadside bomb. The other two were killed on Saturday in Baghdad, also from injuries caused by an explosion, the military said.</p>
        <p>Three Iraqi Army soldiers were killed Sunday and three were wounded in a suicide bombing in Bayji, north of Tikrit, and six people were killed in clashes in a predominantly Shiite area of Diyala Province. The gunmen took over the houses of those they killed and the fight continued for several hours.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
