<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wang's Sinker Sends Teams in Different Directions</title>
    <meta content="18yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855470"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2DB123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="987" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wang's Sinker Sends Teams in Different Directions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a team that is having trouble scoring, the most welcome sight is a grooved fastball or a hanging curve. The Mets are as good at pummeling those pitches as any team. But batters cannot hit those pitches if they do not exist. And last night they were few and far between.</p>
        <p>Chien-Ming Wang, sinkerballer extraordinaire, compounded the Mets' frustration by inducing ground ball after ground ball over eight and two-thirds innings in the Yankees' 8-2 victory at Yankee Stadium. When he was not throwing his sinker, he was firing 95-mile-an-hour fastballs -- on his way to a career-high 10 strikeouts -- and leaving the Mets wondering exactly where that came from.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For a team that is having trouble scoring, the most welcome sight is a grooved fastball or a hanging curve. The Mets are as good at pummeling those pitches as any team. But batters cannot hit those pitches if they do not exist. And last night they were few and far between.</p>
        <p>Chien-Ming Wang, sinkerballer extraordinaire, compounded the Mets' frustration by inducing ground ball after ground ball over eight and two-thirds innings in the Yankees' 8-2 victory at Yankee Stadium. When he was not throwing his sinker, he was firing 95-mile-an-hour fastballs -- on his way to a career-high 10 strikeouts -- and leaving the Mets wondering exactly where that came from.</p>
        <p>''He was really throwing hard,'' said Carlos Beltrán, who went 1 for 4 and drove in the Mets' final run on a single in the ninth. ''I didn't know he was capable of throwing 95, 96, 97.''</p>
        <p>Alex Rodriguez drove in three runs, including two on a towering homer in the first inning, and Jorge Posada and Johnny Damon each homered and had two runs batted in. Wang allowed two runs and six hits in winning his fourth consecutive start.</p>
        <p>He did so while pitching with a stiff neck after sleeping funny on his right side Saturday. He received ultrasound therapy and heat packs before the game but said he did not expect to miss a start.</p>
        <p>The Yankees have won 13 of 16 games this month, which is more or less the opposite of how the Mets have fared. The Mets fell to 3-12 in June, losing their fifth series in a row, although they retained their two-game lead over the Atlanta Braves in the National League East. Asked if he felt the urge to speak to his team, Manager Willie Randolph said: ''No, keep playing. Keep grinding through this. We just have to get back to winning.''</p>
        <p>At last check, the Minnesota Twins, who will play the Mets tonight in the opener of a 10-game homestand at Shea Stadium, do not have a Taiwanese pitcher. The Mets must be pleased about that. They have faced two Taiwanese pitchers in the last five games, in Wang and the Dodgers' Hong-Chih Kuo, scoring a total of three runs and losing both times.</p>
        <p>Wang's delivery may be slow and deliberate, but what comes out of his right hand is not. He consistently threw his fastball in the mid-90s, mixing in the occasional changeup and slider. And his sinker tailed in or darted away, generally bewildering the Mets.</p>
        <p>Wang's sinker had so much movement that it fooled David Wright and his catcher, Posada, on the same play. Wright flailed at a two-strike pitch in the seventh, and Posada could not block it. Wright ran to first and scored on Carlos Delgado's double.</p>
        <p>''He's sort of like a knuckleball pitcher,'' Yankees Manager Joe Torre said. ''Even though you know it's coming, there's not a whole lot you can do, as long as he keeps the sink on it.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees scored five runs in the first three innings off Orlando Hernández, who allowed six over all before being removed in the fifth inning. Whenever Hernández sees pinstripes, he is reminded of the three World Series rings he won with the Yankees. His allure still resonates here, and he received a warm ovation from partisans of both teams when he was announced before the game.</p>
        <p>Hernández means more to the Mets now, much more, because he is a pitcher who, in the absence of Pedro Martínez, is apt to take a losing streak personally and almost single-handedly win a game.</p>
        <p>''The guy likes pitching when the spotlight is on,'' Derek Jeter said of Hernández before the game. ''Hopefully, he's not as good as he usually is.''</p>
        <p>The Mets were wishing the same of Rodriguez, who has 8 home runs and 28 R.B.I. this month. No one else has more than 17 R.B.I. in June.</p>
        <p>''That's a pretty good season already,'' Damon said. ''If you had offered me that to me before the season, I definitely would have taken it.''</p>
        <p>When Rodriguez is on a streak like this, no pitcher in baseball seems able to fool him. That includes Hernández and his many breaking balls and arm angles. On his first two pitches to Rodriguez in the first inning, Hernández tried establishing the inner portion of the plate, but the balls barely missed. Rodriguez did not bite. Needing a strike to avoid falling behind, 3-0, Hernández threw a belt-high fastball that caught the inside corner. Rodriguez crushed it beyond the Mets' bullpen for a two-run homer.</p>
        <p>''It only counts for two runs,'' Rodriguez said. ''I don't get caught up in that.''</p>
        <p>With Hernández one pitch away from getting out of the second untouched, the Yankees doubled their lead with two outs. Miguel Cairo lashed a two-out double into the left-field corner, scoring Hideki Matsui. Damon followed by ripping a single through the right side.</p>
        <p>Hernández struck out Jeter to end the inning, but the Yankees again threatened in the third. Bobby Abreu led off the inning with a liner that went over Wright's head and sliced into the left-field corner. Carlos Gómez, a 21-year-old rookie, made an outstanding catch there Friday, but he is not familiar with how the ball caroms off the wall. The ball kicked past him, allowing Abreu to slide into third with a triple.</p>
        <p>Rodriguez then knocked him in with a sacrifice fly to deep center, extending the Yankees' lead to 5-0. Damon hit his homer in the fifth, and Hernández did not make it through the inning.</p>
        <p>''I'm feeling good,'' Hernández said. ''My speed is good. My control not so good. Sometimes it's good, sometimes bad. I'm not worried.''</p>
        <p>Neither is Randolph.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes when you go through rough times, you tend to run into the best pitchers on each staff,'' Randolph said, referring to Wang. ''We just ran into him at the wrong time.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
