<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Early Diagnosis of Ovarian Cancer</title>
    <meta content="l18cancer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855428"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Menopause</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E0DC123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Early Diagnosis of Ovarian Cancer</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Symptoms Found for Early Check on Ovary Cancer'' (front page, June 13):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Symptoms Found for Early Check on Ovary Cancer'' (front page, June 13):</p>
        <p>My mother died of ovarian cancer on June 4, 2006, after two harrowing years of chemotherapy, surgeries and anemia shots. By the time of her diagnosis, in a small Indiana town, the cancer had spread.</p>
        <p>My sisters and I were shocked to learn that there was no reliable available screening test for ovarian cancer. In our new experience with ovarian cancer, we learned that the health professionals referred to it as the ''silent killer'' because there were no symptoms or warnings.</p>
        <p>My family wants to thank you for breaking the silence.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Cecere  New York, June 13, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Evaluating women with abdominal complaints may lead to earlier detection of ovarian cancer, but will it be early enough to improve outcomes? The symptoms listed tell us women the grave facts: ovarian cancer exists and most likely is in its advanced stages.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the symptoms are not specific to ovarian cancer and can represent many other physical and emotional illnesses.</p>
        <p>We must find a screening tool to help detect ovarian cancer in its earliest stages -- a Pap smear of the ovary, so to speak. Until we find that test, the medical community still has a lot of work to do.</p>
        <p>Kirsten A. Hickerson  Philadelphia, June 13, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is a registered nurse.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In frustration, I read ''Symptoms Found for Early Check on Ovary Cancer.'' In March 1990, Mom thought she had a stomach bug. Wrong tests and dismissal of her symptoms finally led to a CT scan. Four precious months after she felt ''full'' she learned of her diagnosis; seven months later Mom, 55, was dead of ovarian cancer.</p>
        <p>Sixteen years later, and the best diagnostic tool experts have to offer is that doctors listen to their patients. When I start seeing articles about direct correlations between use of the pill, hormone replacement or talcum powder (Mom used them all) and their respective links to ovarian cancer, I will listen.</p>
        <p>News about the decrease in breast cancer since women in droves stopped hormone replacement shout the need for women to question the pharmaceuticals that doctors prescribe and drug companies manufacture. As one of the daughters, I ask for more hope than doctors who finally listen.</p>
        <p>Laura Hagen  Albany, June 13, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The article implies that the early symptoms in ovarian cancer are ''bloating, pelvic or abdominal pain, difficulty eating or feeling full quickly, and feeling a frequent or urgent need to urinate.''</p>
        <p>These are actually symptoms of advanced disease because the cancer is filling the abdominal cavity and accumulating fluid.</p>
        <p>You write that ''the medical profession had until now told women that there were no specific early symptoms.'' But the late Dr. Hugh R. K. Barber, a nationally recognized authority on ovarian cancer, pointed out 20 to 25 years ago that some of the earliest symptoms of the disease were persistent heartburn and indigestion. He said in a lecture, ''The road to the graveyard in ovarian cancer is paved with Gelusil tablets.''</p>
        <p>As far as what to do when there's a high index of suspicion that the patient may have ovarian cancer but tests and physical exam can't resolve the problem, I'd suggest a diagnostic laparoscopy.</p>
        <p>Paul R. Packer, M.D.  New Rochelle , N.Y., June 13, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Unusual gastrointestinal and urological symptoms as described in this article are important but occur relatively late in ovarian cancer patients and will not contribute much to the ultimate outcome. Pending future research, the only available and practical screening method today is the endovaginal ultrasound.</p>
        <p>This, in order to be effective and acceptable financially, must be incorporated into the routine periodic pelvic examination, combined with the Pap smear and breast examination, at no extra cost and regardless of symptoms. Presymptomatic changes that are not accessible on the routine traditional bimanual examination can be picked up and sorted between those that require immediate attention and those that can be safely followed to eliminate unnecessary operations.</p>
        <p>I would call it the pelvic stethoscope, as it is easily tolerated, takes no more than five minutes, and with the present availability of cheaper and portable equipment, there is no excuse why it cannot be done routinely.</p>
        <p>Michael Harel, M.D.  New York, June 13, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Now that the medical community has recognized the existence of ovarian cancer symptoms, the insurance industry must make sure that all preventive and screening measures (transvaginal sonograms) are covered. Doing so will not only save lives through early diagnosis, but will save money in the long run.</p>
        <p>Linda Rosen  Plainview, N.Y., June 14, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is president of the Long Island chapter of the National Ovarian Cancer Coalition.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
