<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Matching Masterpieces With History's Flash Points</title>
    <meta content="18stan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/arts/television/18stan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855371"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Public Broadcasting Service</org>
        <org class="online_producer">BBC Worldwide Ltd</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Schama, Simon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E4DD123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="986" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Matching Masterpieces With History's Flash Points</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Matching Masterpieces With History’s Flash Points</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was a time, not so long ago, when ''popularizer'' was a derogatory term used by academics to dismiss the popularity of a more successful colleague.</p>
        <p>When Robert Graves wrote ''I, Claudius,'' many classicists sneered. Even Kenneth Clark, the art historian who in 1969 wrote and presented ''Civilisation,'' the BBC's hugely successful survey of Western art, was mocked in some circles as a sellout.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Power of Art” teaches as much about the power of storytelling on television as it does about the history of art.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There was a time, not so long ago, when ''popularizer'' was a derogatory term used by academics to dismiss the popularity of a more successful colleague.</p>
        <p>When Robert Graves wrote ''I, Claudius,'' many classicists sneered. Even Kenneth Clark, the art historian who in 1969 wrote and presented ''Civilisation,'' the BBC's hugely successful survey of Western art, was mocked in some circles as a sellout.</p>
        <p>That fusty line between art and entertainment faded long ago. Stephen W. Hawking, the British physicist, starred in his own series on public television about the origins of the universe without any damage to his reputation. Pulitzer Prize-winning novelists line up to appear on ''Oprah.'' So it's not surprising that Simon Schama, a Columbia University professor, is turning into the Bob Barker of art criticism, a genial television host who excitedly invites viewers to come on down to high culture.</p>
        <p>In ''Simon Schama's Power of Art,'' a series that begins tonight on PBS, Mr. Schama walks through wheat fields that van Gogh painted and strolls beaches where Picasso quarreled with his first wife, Olga. Most documentary-style series nowadays include re-enactments, but this one also offers a re-enactment of the narrator as a young man. In the final segment on Mark Rothko, an actor with long hair and mod glasses recreates the moment when Mr. Schama strolled through the Tate Gallery in London and first spied that artist's murals in 1971.</p>
        <p>Sometimes the professor even strikes up a conversation with dead artists.</p>
        <p>''Yeah, right, led astray were you?'' Mr. Schama says with dripping sarcasm to Jacques-Louis David's highly flattering 1794 self-portrait, which Mr. Schama explains was David's attempt to airbrush out his culpability in the Terror of the French Revolution. ''Just doing your job? I don't think so.''</p>
        <p>''Power of Art'' teaches as much about the power of storytelling on television as it does about the history of art. Mr. Schama, who most recently undertook ''A History of Britain'' for the BBC and the History Channel, is taking a faster and more furious look at Western civilization.</p>
        <p>He does not lead viewers on a stately stroll through the centuries, as Kenneth Clark did. Mr. Schama leapfrogs across time and place, focusing on eight artists and their masterpieces, like Caravaggio's ''David With the Head of Goliath'' and Picasso's ''Guernica,'' framing each work with a dramatic turning point in history: the Counter-Reformation in Italy ( ''the greatest propaganda campaign Christendom has ever seen'') or the rise of fascism in Europe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schama justifies the title of his series by showing how these artists transformed and transcended their times; he rests his case with ''Guernica.'' That painting shatters even the thickest complacency and breaks what he calls ''the habit of taking violent evil in our stride.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schama is a passionate and persuasive docent, but unfortunately there is no ''we'' in art appreciation. Plenty of people can remain unmoved by all kinds of great works.</p>
        <p>''Power of Art'' succeeds not because of the power of the chosen masterpieces but because Mr. Schama masterfully weaves engaging mysteries around each artwork. And he walks and talks viewers through it all in a ''History Boys'' style that is so chatty and disarming that even the flintiest museumphobe wants to stick around to find out what happened next.</p>
        <p>The series begins with two episodes shown back to back, on van Gogh and Picasso. It is understandable but unfortunate that Mr. Schama opens with the two most famous artists. It's the less familiar stories that he tells best, from David's agitprop to the Rothko murals that were commissioned by the Seagram Company to hang in the Four Seasons restaurant, but ended up in London instead.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schama explains, with great gusto, that Rothko only belatedly understood that those great works would fade in the background décor, ignored by plutocrats gorging on foie gras and sole meunière. ''Anybody who would eat that kind of food, for that kind of money,'' an actor playing Rothko says on the phone before slamming down the receiver, ''will never look at a painting of mine.''</p>
        <p>The van Gogh segment opens with his suicide in 1890, soon after painting one of his greatest works, ''Wheat Field With Crows,'' which Mr. Schama describes as ''the painting that begins modern art.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Schama can also be boyishly irreverent about genius. He characterizes van Gogh, a maniacal bookworm, as ''the scary one who'll buttonhole you in the parlor and bang on and on about George Eliot and Dickens, and you'll be backing off from the awful pong.''</p>
        <p>Picasso's tale begins in his Paris studio in 1941, with the image of jackboots stomping up a staircase. Mr. Schama recounts the story, perhaps apocryphal, of a Nazi who barged in and poked around, picking up a postcard-size reproduction of ''Guernica.''</p>
        <p>The German officer said, ''Did you do this?'' Picasso replied, ''Oh, no, you did.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schama ends the segment with another anecdote, describing the moment in 2003 when Colin L. Powell, then the secretary of state, went to the United Nations to make the case for war against Saddam Hussein, and United Nations officials covered the tapestry version of ''Guernica'' with a large blue cloth, concerned that Picasso's dead children, weeping mothers and screaming horses might clash with Mr. Powell's message.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schama says this is proof that art has a power that even a superpower cannot defuse. ''You're the mightiest country in the world, you can throw your armies around, you can get rid of dictators,'' he says. ''But, hey, don't tangle with a masterpiece.''</p>
        <p>Simon Schama's Power of Art</p>
        <p>Tonight on most PBS stations (check local listings).</p>
        <p>Basil Comely, BBC, and Margaret Smilow, WNET, executive producers; Clare Beavan, BBC, series producer; Kristin Lovejoy and Junko Tsunashima, supervising producers for Thirteen Culture and Arts; Bill O'Donnell, director of program development. Simon Schama, writer and host. Produced by WNET, New York, and the BBC.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
