<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Preppie Afro-Pop And Other Odd Blends</title>
    <meta content="18vamp" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/arts/music/18vamp.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855380"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3DD123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="555" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Preppie Afro-Pop And Other Odd Blends</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Preppie Afro-Pop and Other Odd Blends</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KELEFA SANNEH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a proactive indie-rock fan in 2007 a debut album is more like an end product than a starting point. By the time that first shrink-wrapped and bar-coded CD finds its way into shops, the band will probably be old news, having suffered through many online cycles of hype and backlash. In a world that won't wait patiently for an album release date, it probably makes more sense to talk about a debut MP3, a debut YouTube appearance, a debut MySpace page.</p>
        <p>In a sense this new state of affairs is really an old one, a throwback to the early 1960s, when concerts and singles ruled, and albums were merely compilations. And it probably makes bands (not to mention record companies) nervous: It means you can pick up fans faster, and lose them faster too.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even without an album Vampire Weekend has made one of the year’s most impressive debuts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For a proactive indie-rock fan in 2007 a debut album is more like an end product than a starting point. By the time that first shrink-wrapped and bar-coded CD finds its way into shops, the band will probably be old news, having suffered through many online cycles of hype and backlash. In a world that won't wait patiently for an album release date, it probably makes more sense to talk about a debut MP3, a debut YouTube appearance, a debut MySpace page.</p>
        <p>In a sense this new state of affairs is really an old one, a throwback to the early 1960s, when concerts and singles ruled, and albums were merely compilations. And it probably makes bands (not to mention record companies) nervous: It means you can pick up fans faster, and lose them faster too.</p>
        <p>Not that anyone looked nervous at the GlassLands Gallery in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, on Saturday night. The occasion was a short but exhilarating performance by Vampire Weekend, an emerging local band that seems likely to become an indie favorite. ''This is the first show we put together ourselves,'' said Ezra Koenig, the guitarist and lead singer, and it certainly felt like a success. A throng of fans and friends (and a few music-industry types) had chosen to spend a breezy June night in a hot and humid room, dancing or nodding or singing along.</p>
        <p>Fans describing Vampire Weekend often mention ''Graceland'' -- the album, not the estate. It's an inexact reference point, but an effective one, evoking 1980s nostalgia (it's getting harder to find people who pretend to dislike that Paul Simon masterpiece) and an unfussy approach to Afro-pop.</p>
        <p>On Saturday the band members laid down a series of playful indie-rock grooves: plinky keyboards and spidery guitar lines, rattling drums and nudging bass. One of the band's best-loved songs, ''Cape Cod Kwassa Kwassa,'' seems to evoke the pleasant confusion of making out, or not making out:</p>
        <p>Can you stay up to see the dawn,</p>
        <p>in the colors of Benetton?</p>
        <p>Is your bed made? Is your sweater off?</p>
        <p>Do you want to? Like you know I do?</p>
        <p>The title makes reference to Congolese soukous music, and so does Mr. Koenig's guitar figure. But if fans can't tell exactly what has been borrowed from where, that's part of the point. And in the refrain Mr. Koenig name-checks the guy who helped make so-called world music a genre unto itself, singing, ''This feels so unnatural/Peter Gabriel too.''</p>
        <p>The band members all attended Columbia (online they claim to be specialists in ''Upper West Side Soweto,'' among other styles), and something about their preppie, polyrhythmic sound feels fresh and funny and, weirdly, inevitable. Instead of borrowing from early Talking Heads albums (the way Clap Your Hands Say Yeah and many other bands have done), they're borrowing from Afro-pop, just as Talking Heads did on later albums. In retrospect it's a brilliantly well-timed approach.</p>
        <p>The band is touring all summer (expect the stages to get bigger and the crowds to get even more enthusiastic), and listeners looking for a preview can find one online. At myspace.com/vampireweekend four songs are posted, including ''Cape Cod Kwassa Kwassa.'' And three of those songs are available from digital.othermusic.com as a self-titled digital EP. Even without an album Vampire Weekend has made one of the year's most impressive debuts.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
