<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cabrera Is the Last Man Standing When Woods's Putt Doesn't Fall</title>
    <meta content="18golf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/sports/golf/18golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Argentina</location>
        <org class="online_producer">PGA Tour Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Furyk, Jim</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Baddeley, Aaron</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Stricker, Steve</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DB123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1005" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cabrera Is the Last Man Standing When Woods's Putt Doesn't Fall</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cabrera Is Last Man Standing at U.S. Open</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa., June 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He took deep drags from a stubby cigarette and footlong divots from Oakmont Country Club until, at last, Ángel Cabrera walked off the 18th green with the hopes of a nation and the burden of a lead in a major championship.</p>
        <p>A former caddie from Cordoba, Argentina, who needed financial assistance to learn the game, Cabrera scaled a walkway above Oakmont and looked out over the expanse of the golf course. Somewhere, in the distance and out of his control, Tiger Woods and Jim Furyk were lurking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ángel Cabrera, a former caddie from Cordoba, Argentina, fended off Tiger Woods and Jim Furyk for his first major title.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He took deep drags from a stubby cigarette and footlong divots from Oakmont Country Club until, at last, Ángel Cabrera walked off the 18th green with the hopes of a nation and the burden of a lead in a major championship.</p>
        <p>A former caddie from Cordoba, Argentina, who needed financial assistance to learn the game, Cabrera scaled a walkway above Oakmont and looked out over the expanse of the golf course. Somewhere, in the distance and out of his control, Tiger Woods and Jim Furyk were lurking.</p>
        <p>Cabrera took a seat in the scorer's area of the clubhouse, watching the end of the United States Open on television like so many others, and speaking in staccato Spanish with his caddie.</p>
        <p>When Furyk missed a 45-foot birdie putt on the 18th hole and, minutes later, Woods followed with a 30-footer that was off line, Cabrera rose from his chair and into a new echelon in golf. He was the winner of the 107th United States Open.</p>
        <p>''This will be huge in Argentina,'' said Eddie Gardino, Cabrera's caddie. ''I don't know how many people in Argentina know about golf, but I think it will have a huge impact over there.''</p>
        <p>Cabrera, who trailed the overnight lead by four shots, shot a final-round 69 to defeat Woods (72) and Furyk (70) by a stroke. His five-over-par 285 on the difficult Oakmont course matched the winning score from last year's championship at Winged Foot.</p>
        <p>Cabrera, the only player to break par in two rounds, became the first player from Argentina to win the United States Open and the first to win a major since Roberto De Vicenzo won the British Open in 1967.</p>
        <p>For Woods, who was bidding for his 13th major title, Oakmont was the site of his second consecutive runner-up finish in a major, after he closed 2006 by winning the British Open and the P.G.A. Championship. For Furyk, who grew up in the Pittsburgh area, it was his second straight runner-up finish in the Open.</p>
        <p>''Ángel played a beautiful round of golf today,'' Woods said.</p>
        <p>In holding off Woods, the No. 1 player in the world, and Furyk, the No. 3 player, Cabrera, 37, also overcame the tough setup at Oakmont and his own nerves. He had never won a PGA Tour event, let alone a major, and yet he held on.</p>
        <p>''I was definitely feeling nervous, but I assumed that this is the same sensation everybody was having,'' he said through an interpreter. Later, he added: ''There are some players that have psychologists. I smoke.''</p>
        <p>Not everyone handled the emotion of a Sunday at Oakmont. Aaron Baddeley, who slept on a two-shot lead over Woods, stumbled at the start. He missed the fairway on the par-4 first hole when his tee shot sailed right, and he missed the green short and right with his approach. He hit his chip shot so far to the left that it rolled off the green and left his next chip shot about 10 feet short.</p>
        <p>He took three more putts and walked away with a triple-bogey 7, the beginnings of a lost day playing alongside Woods.</p>
        <p>At one point, Baddeley, Cabrera, Woods, Stephen Ames and Steve Stricker shared the lead on the front nine. That's when Cabrera, one of the longest hitters in the game, began to make a move. After a birdie at No. 11, he nestled an iron to the 500-yard par-4 15th to 2 feet. He raised his eyebrows when he saw where his ball landed and put his hand on his head.</p>
        <p>The birdie gave him a three-shot lead over Furyk and Woods, but they, too, started to get warm. When Furyk birdied the 15th hole for his third birdie in a row and Cabrera bogeyed No. 16 with a three-putt, Furyk was one shot back. When Cabrera missed an 8-foot putt for par on the 313-yard par-4 17th, they were tied.</p>
        <p>Furyk, who often plays conservatively, turned aggressive. He took out a driver on No. 17 and launched his tee shot into the rough.</p>
        <p>When he hit his pitch shot, he left it in the rough. His next attempt skidded 10 feet past the cup. Furyk, with many in the gallery pulling for him, lipped out the par putt, falling a shot behind Cabrera.</p>
        <p>Furyk said he was surprised his drive on No. 17 flew as far as it did, ''a little pea-shooter like myself.''</p>
        <p>After Furyk made par on No. 18, only Woods could catch Cabrera. He had turned back a double bogey on No. 3, where he hit two awful chip shots, to come within a whisker of winning his third United States Open.</p>
        <p>He made back-to-back par-saving putts on Nos. 16 and 17 and found the first cut of rough with his tee shot on the 18th. From 154 yards out, he hit a pitching wedge that was heading toward the flag, but it bounded long to the back of the green.</p>
        <p>''Second shot was not easy, because I had to come out steep to get over the grass and still send it straight up in the air,'' he said. ''And I did a good job of that, I thought, but it flew a little too far and then I had to putt.''</p>
        <p>Woods circled the green and studied the bend of the grass from both sides. He squatted next to his putter, barely even blinking his eyes.</p>
        <p>''It was a triple-breaking putt,'' Woods said.</p>
        <p>When it missed, Cabrera returned to the walkway above the 18th green. It was sunset. Cabrera removed his hat to reveal gray at his temples. He looked out at Oakmont again.</p>
        <p>''I watched all the majors on TV when I was a kid,'' he said. ''I never thought I would be here at this moment.''</p>
        <p>NOTES</p>
        <p>Ángel Cabrera collected $1.26 million. He also earned a five-year exemption on the PGA Tour, an exemption into the Open for 10 years, and a five-year exemption into the Masters, British Open, P.G.A. Championship and Players Championship.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
