<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Europeans Fear New U.S. Requirement Could Hurt Travelers</title>
    <meta content="18visa" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/washington/18visa.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855443"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/San Marino</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Visas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel Restrictions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Passports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Identification Devices</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E7DB123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Europeans Fear New U.S. Requirement Could Hurt Travelers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Europeans Fear New U.S. Requirement Could Hurt Travelers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRIAN KNOWLTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Knowlton, Brian</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Measures moving through Congress, including a requirement for travelers in some countries to register travel plans online 48 hours before departure, have raised fears in Europe of disruptions in the trans-Atlantic flow of business and leisure travel.</p>
        <p>The requirement, proposed by the Department of Homeland Security, would apply to people in 27 countries, mostly in Western Europe, who are now able to travel to the United States for up to 90 days without visas. It would also apply to new entrants to the same so-called visa waiver program, a status sought by 12 countries, many of them Eastern and Central European states new to the European Union that have placed enormous stock on getting in -- for business, tourism, family links and plain national prestige.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A measure moving through Congress would require people in 27 countries, mostly in Western Europe, to register travel plans online 48 hours before departure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Measures moving through Congress, including a requirement for travelers in some countries to register travel plans online 48 hours before departure, have raised fears in Europe of disruptions in the trans-Atlantic flow of business and leisure travel.</p>
        <p>The requirement, proposed by the Department of Homeland Security, would apply to people in 27 countries, mostly in Western Europe, who are now able to travel to the United States for up to 90 days without visas. It would also apply to new entrants to the same so-called visa waiver program, a status sought by 12 countries, many of them Eastern and Central European states new to the European Union that have placed enormous stock on getting in -- for business, tourism, family links and plain national prestige.</p>
        <p>Poles need ''proof that this is a fair relationship,'' said Janusz Reiter, the Polish ambassador to Washington. ''I'm afraid that if we fail, we may lose a generation.''</p>
        <p>Poles, who can now travel and work across the European Union, would turn against the United States, traditionally regarded as a friend, Mr. Reiter said.</p>
        <p>The existing European members of the waiver program are not thrilled by the 48-hour requirement -- a potential hardship for businesspeople, who often change travel plans at the last minute -- nor by some other tightening of standards for airports and passport handling.</p>
        <p>Nathalie Loiseau, a spokeswoman at the French Embassy in Washington, said European officials, with full French support, were working with Congress to help ''enhance trans-Atlantic relations and not to put more obstacles before people who wish to travel to the U.S.''</p>
        <p>But an American official said last week that the online registration would be a ''convenient'' process, taking five minutes or less, and causing no one to miss a flight.</p>
        <p>While the mechanics of the online registration are yet to be set, said Russ Knocke, a spokesman for the Homeland Security Department, in practice, online registration could be done fewer than 48 hours before departure. ''The concept is that whenever the ticket is purchased,'' he said, ''there's a quick 'ping' to give us advance notice on who's going to travel to the U.S.''</p>
        <p>Earlier information on travelers' identities, he said, should mean fewer flights delayed -- or even turned back -- for security reasons. The process would involve sharing no more data than from a passport, he said.</p>
        <p>American officials have long seen the waiver program as politically vulnerable. If someone entering the country from a visa-waiver country should launch a terrorist attack, Mr. Knocke said, ''the rush in Congress to shut this program down altogether would be fast and furious.'' Thus the tougher standards set by the proposed change could make it easier to bring in new countries, he said.</p>
        <p>Along with online registration, the updated program would require new and existing member countries to improve data-sharing, more rigorously report lost and stolen passports (not just blank passports), and guarantee they will repatriate citizens who are ordered out of the United States.</p>
        <p>But tied in to legislation that has passed the Senate and been introduced in the House is the question of the entry standards for countries eager to join the program.</p>
        <p>Current members are judged as among the most reliable American travel and business partners. Membership requires, among other things, a record of extremely low rejection by American consular officials of the visa applications from a country's citizens -- less than 3 percent of the total. In the past, a low total mainly reflected a small probability of a country's citizens' overstaying visas. But since the attacks of Sept. 11, 2001, terrorism concerns have played a growing role.</p>
        <p>The new European Union countries tend to have rejection rates far higher than the 3 percent threshold. Estonia had a rejection rate last year of 7.1 percent; the Czech Republic, 9.4 percent; Hungary, 12.7 percent; and Poland, 26 percent, according to State Department figures.</p>
        <p>The European Union has urged Congress to extend the waiver program to all of its citizens based on individual eligibility without regard to nationality.</p>
        <p>The countries now in the waiver program are Andorra, Australia, Austria, Belgium, Britain, Brunei, Denmark, Finland, France, Germany, Iceland, Ireland, Italy, Japan, Liechtenstein, Luxembourg, Monaco, the Netherlands, New Zealand, Norway, Portugal, San Marino, Singapore, Slovenia, Spain, Sweden and Switzerland.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
