<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Checking In With Glimmer Twins, Plato and Aristotle</title>
    <meta content="18targ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/theater/reviews/18targ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855372"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Target Margin Theater</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Isherwood, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenspan, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herskovits, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Argument, the (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Dinner Party (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Target Margin Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Herskovits, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Greenspan, David</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Argument, The (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4DD123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1229" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Checking In With Glimmer Twins, Plato and Aristotle</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Checking In With Glimmer Twins, Plato and Aristotle</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES ISHERWOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Isherwood, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Isherwood reviews Target Margin Theater production of David Greenspan play The Argument, starring Greenspan and directed by David Herskovits, and Dinner Party, created by Target Margin Theater and directed by Herskovits; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Meet Aristotle sporting Doc Martens, and hear Plato interpreted by the light of a disco ball at the new kooky klassics double feature at the Kitchen.</p>
        <p>The Target Margin Theater, which often resuscitates arcane dramas by giving them a playful poke in the eye, has been romping around the dusty, sun-drenched, wisdom-riddled byways of ancient Greece this season. The concluding presentation is a pair of one-acts inspired by two revered nontheatrical texts: a fundamental work of literary criticism and a transcript of a rowdy feast immortalized by a giant of Western philosophy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Meet Aristotle sporting Doc Martens, and hear Plato interpreted by the light of a disco ball at the Target Margin Theater’s new kooky klassics double feature.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Meet Aristotle sporting Doc Martens, and hear Plato interpreted by the light of a disco ball at the new kooky klassics double feature at the Kitchen.</p>
        <p>The Target Margin Theater, which often resuscitates arcane dramas by giving them a playful poke in the eye, has been romping around the dusty, sun-drenched, wisdom-riddled byways of ancient Greece this season. The concluding presentation is a pair of one-acts inspired by two revered nontheatrical texts: a fundamental work of literary criticism and a transcript of a rowdy feast immortalized by a giant of Western philosophy.</p>
        <p>In ''The Argument'' the impish actor and playwright David Greenspan gives an informal lecture, both learned and endearingly loopy, derived from Aristotle's ''Poetics'' and the writings of a classics scholar, Gerald F. Else. This disquisition is followed by a quirky contemporary dramatization of Plato's ''Symposium,'' created by the company and directed, as is ''The Argument,'' by Target Margin's artistic director, David Herskovits.</p>
        <p>Thinking caps, and maybe notebooks too, are really required only for the first part of the evening, in which Mr. Greenspan strides casually onstage and launches right into a dense recitation of the ''Poetics.'' Working from Mr. Else's translation, Mr. Greenspan's adaptation follows the structure and sense of the original with unexpected, and at times challenging, fidelity and meticulousness.</p>
        <p>Sudden lapses into the contemporary vernacular occasionally interrupt the academic tone. Describing the essential difference between tragedy and comedy, Mr. Greenspan's Aristotle says, ''The one imitates noble types, while the other imitates what we sometimes refer to as low-down, no-'count types.'' Got it, Ari. Mr. Greenspan does, of course, condense and elide a fair amount of material, thank goodness. (He dispenses with much of the specifics about language and diction from the later sections of the text.)</p>
        <p>He also strays into a few whimsical digressions, clearing up that pesky controversy about the unity of time with these words: ''Let us be clear lest future generations think we mean by this that tragedy (or comedy) must represent the events of a single day -- one can imagine the confusion that would lead to: no, what we say is that dramatic presentations begin in the morning and conclude before nightfall -- for as we know, stage lights will not be invented for over 2,000 years.''</p>
        <p>The casual descent from the high-flown to the, well, lowdown is emblematic of Mr. Greenspan's performance too. Although he purports to be impersonating a writer and thinker of the fourth century B.C., he is more the classics professor of a bored college student's dreams, a magnetic charmer whose passion for his subject moistens even the driest material and who is not afraid to be a cutup once in a while.</p>
        <p>The voice dances up and down, incantatory and rhythmic, now rising to a lyric croon, now tumbling to deliver a sly wisecrack. The undulating arms, carving big arcs in the air, hypnotize us into paying keen attention to the harder-to-digest chunks of text. Mr. Greenspan always seems to be in motion of some kind, seducing us through abstruse passages with a clap, a snap, a histrionic flourish of the hand. For the concept of pity he mimes falling tears. For fear clutching hands frame terror-widened eyes, like on a Joan Crawford movie poster from the 1940s.</p>
        <p>In short, while you may not be able to take in all the nuances of thought being presented -- wait, what's peripety again? -- Mr. Greenspan's delivery manages to keep you from being bored by an essentially untheatrical text. Most of all he holds the attention through his obviously heartfelt interest in his subject.</p>
        <p>The playfulness subsides, and the intensity increases, in the culminating passages of the performance, in which Mr. Greenspan departs from the ''Poetics'' proper to discuss Plato's dramatic genius, as evidenced in the ''Symposium.'' Piercing eyes agleam, Mr. Greenspan seems awestruck with wonder at the beauty of Plato's achievement in this celebrated work, in which ''everything rolls on in a golden flow of humorous invention, as each participant discourses on the nature of love.''</p>
        <p>Accordingly, you return from intermission primed for an experience that doesn't quite live up to its advance billing. For in ''Dinner Party'' Mr. Herskovits and his company take a far more irreverent approach to Plato than Mr. Greenspan does to Aristotle. They seem frantically keen to make Plato as accessible as possible to audiences with YouTube-primed attention spans and frames of reference that don't extend far beyond pop songs.</p>
        <p>This modern-dress ''Symposium'' is a freewheeling mixture of fixed text and improvisation inside a formal structure that parallels the original, right down to the complicated framing device. (I heard this story from somebody who heard thisstory.) The actors use their own names, so the Socrates figure is called Stephanie after the actress, Stephanie Weeks, who plays the role.</p>
        <p>But the strict adherence to the narrative blueprint of Plato's dialogue is not matched by an equal respect for its richness of texture and subtle seriousness of purpose. Mr. Herskovits is excellent at heightening the intended comedy, like the bout of hiccups that plagues one of the participants. The staging is brash and energetic, rambling playfully across the ramshackle assortment of funky furnishings that constitute Sarah Edkins's setting.</p>
        <p>But too many speeches are played strictly for easy laughs. I enjoyed the silly pageantry used to illustrate Aristophanes' argument that love is each soul's search for his or her other half. But it's hard to take seriously the passage in which the love of Woody Allen and Soon-Yi is put forth as a shining ideal. (''The strongest proof, his movies were getting weak, and now they are good again.'')</p>
        <p>And I could really have done without the use of the treacly Stevie Wonder-Paul McCartney duet ''Ebony and Ivory'' as a model of the harmonic perfection that love creates. Nuggets of (tongue-in-cheek?) cliché make frequent appearances: ''Love conquers all,'' ''All you need is love,'' etc.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Herskovits's intention is to illustrate how precipitously intellectual discourse has declined over the past couple of millenniums, he has succeeded spectacularly. The treatment does become more serious when Socrates/Stephanie finally holds forth, but over all ''Dinner Party'' is more parody than serious interpretation, the ''Symposium'' rewritten in comic sound bites and colorful graffiti. I was at least glad to escape without some perky philosopher offering up the insight that love means never having to say you're sorry.</p>
        <p>The Argument and Dinner Party</p>
        <p>''The Argument'' by David Greenspan, based on ''Aristotle's Poetics: The Argument, Plato and Aristotle on Poetry'' by Gerald F. Else, and ''Poetics'' by Aristotle, translated by Mr. Else; ''Dinner Party'' created by the company, based on ''The Symposium'' by Plato; directed by David Herskovits; production stage manager, Arienne Pelletier; assistant stage manager, Oliva O'Brien; dramaturg, Kathleen Kennedy Tobin; assistant director, Sherrine Azab; lighting by Lenore Doxsee; sets by Sarah Edkins; costumes by Ásta Bennie Hostetter; sound by Jane Shaw; production manager, Monica Moore; general manager, Michael Levinton; technical director, Gabriel Evansohn. Presented by the Kitchen, Debra Singer, executive director and chief curator; and the Target Margin Theater, Mr. Herskovits, artistic director. At the Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea; (212) 255-5793, Ext. 11. Through June 30. Total running time: 2 hours.</p>
        <p>WITH: David Greenspan (Aristotle/David), Han Nah Kim (Han Nah), Diana Konopka (Sound Demon), Mary Neufeld (Mary/Mary/Mary from Kansas), Steven Rattazzi (Steven), Greig Sargeant (Greig), Stephanie Weeks (Stephanie) and Ian Wen (Ian).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
