<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vowing to Love, Cherish and Root For Brooklyn Cyclones</title>
    <meta content="18cyclones" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/nyregion/18cyclones.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855432"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Minor Leagues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minor Leagues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Brooklyn Cyclones</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904EFDC123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="793" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vowing to Love, Cherish and Root For Brooklyn Cyclones</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Vowing to Love, Cherish and Root for Brooklyn Cyclones</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRYMAINE LEE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The rush begins in midwinter. The pantry needs stocking, credit cards are paid off and spring cleaning begins well before the last frost has thawed.</p>
        <p>Don and Donna Byrnes get all of life's heavy lifting out of the way, because after tomorrow, when the Brooklyn Cyclones' season begins in Coney Island, they will not have time to bother with the nuisance of writing checks or shopping for anything other than bread or milk.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Don and Donna Byrnes of Bay Ridge are obsessed with the Mets and the Brooklyn Cyclones, whose season starts tomorrow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The rush begins in midwinter. The pantry needs stocking, credit cards are paid off and spring cleaning begins well before the last frost has thawed.</p>
        <p>Don and Donna Byrnes get all of life's heavy lifting out of the way, because after tomorrow, when the Brooklyn Cyclones' season begins in Coney Island, they will not have time to bother with the nuisance of writing checks or shopping for anything other than bread or milk.</p>
        <p>Baseball, in particular the Brooklyn Cyclones minor league team and its parent club, the Mets, is their obsession; almost as important to them as their own marriage.</p>
        <p>''It's above everything else,'' Mrs. Byrnes, 46, said. ''I mean, we have to take care of work, pay the bills and make sure everything is in order before the season starts, because once the season starts, it's chaos.''</p>
        <p>New York is full of baseball fans, but in a city with two high-performing major league teams, not many of them would give up an afternoon for a Class A ballgame. Every year, the Byrneses schedule their vacations around the Cyclones season, with most days blocked out for long stretches of home games.</p>
        <p>There is also the $4,000 trip to watch the Mets at spring training in Port St. Lucie, Fla., where they hope to retire. And the few hours' drive to Binghamton for the annual welcome-back dinner for the Cyclones and the Binghamton Mets, another minor league club. Cooperstown is another favorite destination.</p>
        <p>As much a part of the stadium as die-hard fans like the Monkey Lady and Nicky Cowbells, the Byrneses will be in their seats when the Cyclones open tomorrow night against their rival, the Staten Island Yankees. Mrs. Byrnes will be the blonde holding a handmade sign in one hand and a digital camera in the other. Her husband will be studying each swing and pitch.</p>
        <p>''It's all about the promise of what they can be,'' Mr. Byrnes, 45, a security officer for New York City Transit, said. ''It's all about player development.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Byrnes, 46, a field operations supervisor for KeySpan Energy, said, ''It's like here's a kid, a pitcher or whatever who started with us in Brooklyn.''</p>
        <p>Their living room in Bay Ridge is a shrine to baseball, with autographed pictures of them standing with young Cyclones players (they spend $50 a week printing digital photographs). There are also more than 120 bobbleheads, 40 bats and 200 signed balls and the rest of the family's grand collection of baseball memorabilia. The couple also have a pair of original seats from Ebbets Field.</p>
        <p>They have helped young Cyclones players -- who earn a fraction of what the Mets make -- find places to stay in Brooklyn for the season. And they even take players out to dinner after games.</p>
        <p>''They are great for the players,'' said Steve Cohen, general manager of the Cyclones. ''You have kids coming from all over the world, be it from small towns in the Midwest or from a different country, and to bring them to Brooklyn, which is a big place, to have people take them in and treat them like they are their own kids is very important.''</p>
        <p>Mr. and Mrs. Byrnes both grew up in Park Slope, in homes that were loyal to the Mets, although they did not know each other then. ''My mother would cut out the coupons from the back of the milk cartons and send them away for free Mets tickets,'' Mrs. Byrnes said. ''That's how we got to go to see the games.''</p>
        <p>The two had seen each other on the R line over the years. One day 18 years ago, in October, marked in memory by the end of another season, they ran into each other in Bay Ridge and struck up a conversation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Byrnes said he quickly realized that he had a prize on his hands.</p>
        <p>''She wasn't making believe that she knew about baseball,'' he said. ''She would say certain things and I would be like 'Wow.' ''</p>
        <p>They married three months later.</p>
        <p>''I make fun of them about it, but I really do love how much they are into minor league baseball,'' said Mrs. Byrnes's daughter from a previous marriage, Jennifer Scipione. ''I tell them to take a cruise or go somewhere nice for vacation, but they'd rather go to spring training or to the Baseball Hall of Fame.</p>
        <p>''I actually never understood it,'' she added. ''Usually it's the fame of baseball that does it for people, but it's nice to see the two of them so into the heart of baseball. They get joy out of seeing the young guys who play with nothing but heart.''</p>
        <p>There is one drawback to living with the couple, she said. ''I'm a Yankees fan.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
