<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Late Start Has Sent Mets' Mota To Fringe</title>
    <meta content="18notebook" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/sports/baseball/18notebook.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855458"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Mota, Guillermo</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E4DB123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Late Start Has Sent Mets' Mota To Fringe</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Late Start Has Sent Mets’ Mota to Fringe</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When reliever Guillermo Mota entered in the sixth inning of the Mets' 11-8 loss to the Yankees on Saturday, the Mets were trailing by three runs. When he left before the eighth, the Mets were behind by five.</p>
        <p>Mota was suspended for the first 50 games of the season for violating baseball's policy on performance-enhancing drugs. And he, and the Mets, seem to still be paying for it. Since rejoining the team May 30, Mota has allowed eight earned runs in 10 innings for a 7.20 earned run average. Opponents are hitting .318 against him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Guillermo Mota was suspended for the first 50 games of the season for violating baseball’s policy on performance-enhancing drugs. And he, and the Mets, are still paying for it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When reliever Guillermo Mota entered in the sixth inning of the Mets' 11-8 loss to the Yankees on Saturday, the Mets were trailing by three runs. When he left before the eighth, the Mets were behind by five.</p>
        <p>Mota was suspended for the first 50 games of the season for violating baseball's policy on performance-enhancing drugs. And he, and the Mets, seem to still be paying for it. Since rejoining the team May 30, Mota has allowed eight earned runs in 10 innings for a 7.20 earned run average. Opponents are hitting .318 against him.</p>
        <p>He said before last night's game that he was continuing to work his arm into shape. ''I've only pitched in eight or nine games, and these hitters are two months ahead of me,'' said Mota, who pitched seven games for Class AAA New Orleans before being activated. ''My arm's not 100 percent yet.''</p>
        <p>The Mets have lost in each of his eight appearances. As a result, Manager Willie Randolph does not have the same confidence he had in Mota last season, and he is less apt to use him in pressure situations, the way he did last year. Mota has yet to pitch with a lead, but considering the Mets' struggles this month, that is not entirely his fault.</p>
        <p>When Mota has pitched, as he did the past two Saturdays, for instance, he has turned deficits into larger ones, making it harder for his team to rally. On June 9 in Detroit, the Mets were losing, 5-3, when he came in to start the sixth. The Mets were down, 8-3, when he left after recording one out. They lost, 8-7. ''He doesn't look much different to me,'' said Ramón Castro, who caught Mota on Saturday and in Detroit. ''He's been leaving a few pitches up in the zone, but that happens to everyone.''</p>
        <p>The Mets are already without Duaner Sánchez, who had surgery on his right shoulder, and Ambiorix Burgos, who has discomfort in his right elbow. They were looking to Mota to become another power arm in the bullpen, which is lacking them, aside from Billy Wagner. They were hoping Mota could resemble the pitcher he was last year, when he was 3-0 in 18 appearances with a 1.00 E.R.A. He proved durable, too, pitching in consecutive games three times; he has done so once this season.</p>
        <p>The Mets, satisfied with Mota's contrition after the suspension was announced Nov. 1, outbid a few other teams for his services and signed him to a backloaded two-year, $5 million deal five weeks later.</p>
        <p>Mota said he did not think that his performance this season was under greater scrutiny because of the discrepancy between his success with the Mets and his performance with Cleveland, where he was 1-3 with a 6.21 E.R.A. before being traded to the Mets in August.</p>
        <p>''People will think what they want,'' Mota said. ''If I do my job, everything will be good.''</p>
        <p>PLAYING THROUGH PAIN -- Carlos Beltrán said that his left quadriceps tightened when he had to run for balls in the gap and when he hit left-handed. But he said that he did not plan to ask for any time off or to hit right-handed exclusively.</p>
        <p>For now, he said, he must play through the pain, even if it means that his struggles at the plate will continue. He entered last night batting .143 this month. Although Beltrán was quick not to use his injury as an excuse, he said that the discomfort had disturbed his stride.</p>
        <p>''I've been trying to find a comfortable position,'' he said. ''I've been trying to avoid putting pressure on my leg, trying to protect my leg. To do that is affecting me hitting-wise.''</p>
        <p>As of last Monday, when the latest results of the balloting for the All-Star Game were announced, Beltrán had the most votes in the National League. Asked if he would consider pulling out to give himself more rest, he shook his head and said that he would not because those three days off would not make much difference.</p>
        <p>Willie Randolph said he was not concerned that Beltran needed more time off. ''He hasn't said anything to me about it,'' Randolph said. ''Everyone's a little sore. Everyone's banged up, no one's 100 percent. No one's going to say, 'Skip, I'm 100 percent.' You never hear that.''</p>
        <p>But Beltrán did say that if Moises Alou and Endy Chávez had not been injured, he probably would have asked Randolph for a week off to see if that would have helped. ''It's just one of those things,'' Beltrán said.</p>
        <p>METS SHUFFLE ORDER -- Willie Randolph batted Paul Lo Duca second last night for the first time since April 30 and moved Carlos Delgado to fifth. David Wright hit cleanup. ''I just like the way it feels, that's all,'' Randolph said.</p>
        <p>Lo Duca left in the bottom of the fourth inning with a contusion of his left triceps, sustained when he was hit by a pitch in the first.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">BASEBALL</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
