<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cadbury Expected to Sell Beverage Unit, Including 7-Up</title>
    <meta content="18cadbury" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/business/18cadbury.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855394"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Cadbury Schweppes Plc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Snapple Beverage Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Bain Capital</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Lee, Thomas H, Partners</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Texas Pacific Group</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Blackstone Group</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Lion Capital Holdings</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E1DD123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="494" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cadbury Expected to Sell Beverage Unit, Including 7-Up</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cadbury Expected to Sell Beverage Unit, Including 7-Up</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN and MICHAEL J. de la MERCED</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cadbury Schweppes is preparing to announce tomorrow that is will sell its American beverage business, which includes 7-Up, Dr Pepper and Snapple, according to people close to the company.</p>
        <p>Cadbury said in March that it would split its confectionary and soft drink businesses, but had not determined whether it would sell the beverage business or spin it off.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cadbury Schweppes is preparing to announce on Tuesday that it will sell its American beverage business, according to people close to the company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cadbury Schweppes is preparing to announce tomorrow that is will sell its American beverage business, which includes 7-Up, Dr Pepper and Snapple, according to people close to the company.</p>
        <p>Cadbury said in March that it would split its confectionary and soft drink businesses, but had not determined whether it would sell the beverage business or spin it off.</p>
        <p>On Friday, the deadline for suitors to make an offer, Cadbury received at least three bids for the beverage business, worth about £8 billion ($15.8 billion). One bidding group includes Bain Capital Partners, Thomas H. Lee Partners and the Texas Pacific Group; a second consortium includes the Blackstone Group, Kohlberg Kravis Roberts and Lion Capital. (Lion and Blackstone acquired Cadbury's European beverage unit last year.)</p>
        <p>Another bid came from a group led by Cott, a Canadian company that makes private-label drinks for retailers like Wal-Mart Stores. Should that bid be accepted, it would combine the world's third- and fourth-largest drink makers into a company that would still lag far behind the industry leaders, Coca-Cola and PepsiCo.</p>
        <p>While it was unclear yesterday which bidder was the front-runner, Cadbury has told investors that it will provide an update on the breakup process tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Since its announcement, Cadbury's stock has risen 30 percent.</p>
        <p>A report in The Sunday Times of London said the company was considering a plan to eliminate 5,000 jobs as part of a £300 million cost-cutting effort.</p>
        <p>Analysts said a sale of Cadbury's beverages unit would make sense, as the company could use the proceeds to bulk up its candy business. Among its most likely targets is Hershey, which owns a 45 percent share of the American chocolate market. The two companies already share a link: Hershey controls distribution of Cadbury's brands in the United States.</p>
        <p>But Hershey's largest shareholder, the Hershey Trust Company, has thwarted takeover bids in the past. Five years ago, as Hershey prepared to announce a $12.5 billion merger with the Wm. Wrigley Jr. Company, the trust demanded that the deal be called off amid a furor in the Pennsylvania town that bears the chocolate maker's name.</p>
        <p>The Hershey Trust also rejected a joint offer by Cadbury and Nestlé worth about $10.5 billion. Wrigley may also be a takeover candidate, albeit a less likely one, analysts have said.</p>
        <p>Conversely, Cadbury's confectionary business could become a buyout target, with analysts citing Kraft as a potential buyer. Cadbury's drinks division, which also includes the Motts, Clamato and Yoo-Hoo brands, is among the company's most profitable, bringing in about £2.6 billion in revenue, 35 percent of the company's total, last year. The division, based in Plano, Tex., has more than 18,000 employees. Its parent is based in London.</p>
        <p>Although the company made its announcement only days after Nelson Peltz, the shareholder activist and former owner of Snapple, said he had acquired a 3 percent stake, Cadbury said it had planned the divestment for some time.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
