<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For A-Rod And Critics, It's Now Wait and See</title>
    <meta content="18rhoden" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/sports/baseball/18rhoden.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855469"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E2DB123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For A-Rod And Critics, It's Now Wait and See</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For A-Rod and Critics, It’s Now Wait and See</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An hour after the Yankees defeated the Mets in the second game of a three-game series, Alex Rodriguez poked his head into Joe Torre's office. Torre had finished his postgame interviews and most members of the news media had left when Rodriguez stopped by.</p>
        <p>''Joe, I look forward to seeing you tomorrow,'' Rodriguez said, smiling at what clearly was an inside joke between the two. Torre laughed and Rodriguez went on his way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>My questions to Alex Rodriguez: What is his bottom line? What does he want out of this game? What does he want out of this city?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An hour after the Yankees defeated the Mets in the second game of a three-game series, Alex Rodriguez poked his head into Joe Torre's office. Torre had finished his postgame interviews and most members of the news media had left when Rodriguez stopped by.</p>
        <p>''Joe, I look forward to seeing you tomorrow,'' Rodriguez said, smiling at what clearly was an inside joke between the two. Torre laughed and Rodriguez went on his way.</p>
        <p>Torre, the Yankees' manager, had just been talking about Rodriguez, his star third baseman. Last season was a nightmare for Rodriguez. This season, by any measure, has been a dream -- so far.</p>
        <p>''He just seems like he's having more fun,'' Torre said. ''He's swinging the bat with so much fluidity as opposed to last year.'' Last year, Torre said, so much about A-Rod seemed forced.</p>
        <p>''It's nice to be around him when he seems to be enjoying himself,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Rodriguez began this season on fire in April. When the Yankees seemed to be sinking into oblivion, he was the franchise's beacon. He cooled off in May but seems to be back on fire in June.</p>
        <p>But A-Rod's legion of critics don't ask about June, July or August. The critics ask about September and October.</p>
        <p>My questions to Rodriguez are a bit more far reaching. What is his bottom line? What does he want out of this game? What does he want out of this city?</p>
        <p>In an interview before the season with the radio station WFAN, A-Rod suggested that his staying or leaving depended on whether Yankees fans and the front office made him feel wanted. He later said that he was committed to staying in New York.</p>
        <p>What does he want?</p>
        <p>Notoriety? He's got it. Earlier this month, Torre criticized him for an act of unsportsmanlike conduct for distracting a Toronto infielder by shouting as he ran past him on the bases. Later, there was front-page news about Rodriguez's apparent off-field escapades. Last night, when the Yankees, led by Chien-Ming Wang's pitching masterpiece, rolled over the Mets, 8-2, the undercurrent was Rodriguez, who homered, doubled and drove in three runs.</p>
        <p>The question of the hour -- every hour -- is his contractual status. Rodriguez signed a phenomenal 10-year, $252 million contract with a clause that allows him to opt out of his deal after this season. He is scheduled to earn $27 million each season in 2008, 2009 and 2010.</p>
        <p>Statistics? He's compiling them by the bushel: home runs, hits, runs batted in. He could have 500 career homers by the time the season is over.</p>
        <p>''I brought Alex here to win games,'' General Manager Brian Cashman said last night. ''Right now, we're trying to win games and he's a big part of that.''</p>
        <p>But if A-Rod has a wait-and-see attitude, so do Yankees fans. He is hot now and doing well -- like the football team that moves well between the 20-yard-lines.</p>
        <p>But can he propel this team to the World Series, and once there to a championship?</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the Mets and the Yankees completed their six-game Subway Series, the Yankees taking two of three games and sending a resounding message.</p>
        <p>Although I wonder, do Mets and Yankees fans know anything they didn't know Friday, when the Series began?</p>
        <p>Probably not.</p>
        <p>What did the three games at Shea and the three games at Yankee Stadium prove?</p>
        <p>Nothing.</p>
        <p>This is the joy of the Subway Series. The point is that there is no point.</p>
        <p>The Mets-Yankees regular-season series is water-cooler baseball, a vehicle for die-hard Yankees and Mets fans to blow off steam and engage in a passionate -- and ultimately meaningless -- war of words. The series stokes passions, but in the final analysis, it doesn't change the realities that each team faced before the latest subway ride began: The Mets, with a slender lead in the National League East, are trying to hang on. The Yankees, eight and a half games behind the Boston Red Sox, are trying to catch up.</p>
        <p>The Mets-Yankees rivalry is special, but I'm not a fan of interleague play.</p>
        <p>After Saturday's game, Torre repeated his well-known dislike for these interleague interludes and gave an interesting perspective of the emotional gap between these games with the Mets and the games with a division rival.</p>
        <p>''When we play Boston, it's a whole different set of circumstances,'' Torre said. ''There's no bragging rights involved. It's about 'We're trying to get the same plum as you.'</p>
        <p>''We're not trying to get the same plum as them,'' Torre added, referring to the Mets. ''We're just trying to have the fans be able to brag. We certainly don't have the same stake in this game as the fans do.''</p>
        <p>Water-cooler baseball.</p>
        <p>I understand the fascination with differences. As much as we'd like to remove barriers and distinctions, differences sell. But interleague play attempts to exploit differences--National League versus American League -- that, outside of the designated hitter, no longer exist in a meaningful way.</p>
        <p>This is probably a discussion for another time, but for baseball the larger issue is not simply the empty exercise of interleague play, but the challenge -- indeed, the necessity -- of removing artificial distinctions that no longer serve any purpose. I'm referring to the American and National Leagues.</p>
        <p>In 1999, baseball got rid of the National and American League president's office. The game should go one step further and reconfigure the leagues, changing them to divisions or conferences.</p>
        <p>Blasphemy, I know, and something that certainly is not going to happen any time soon. But this has to be on baseball's radar.</p>
        <p>With international competition increasing, baseball must eventually stop perpetuating empty distinctions and look at competing -- and marketing -- the game in the global marketplace.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the Yankees and the Mets closed out yet another dramatic Subway Series that left fans of each team drained and -- Yankees fans, at least -- focused on the ever unfolding A-Rod drama: Will he stay or will he go?</p>
        <p>Water-cooler baseball at its best.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
