<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Furyk's Emotional Charge Up the Leader Board Fizzles on the 17th</title>
    <meta content="18links" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/18/sports/golf/18links.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855457"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Furyk, Jim</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Baddeley, Aaron</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Stricker, Steve</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ames, Stephen</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E4DB123FF93BA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Furyk's Emotional Charge Up the Leader Board Fizzles on the 17th</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Furyk’s Emotional Charge Up the Leader Board Fizzles on the 17th</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa., June 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A second United States Open title was in Jim Furyk's grasp Sunday as he stood on the No. 17 tee, gripping his driver.</p>
        <p>Three consecutive birdies on the backside had vaulted Furyk, the 2003 champion, into a tie for the lead with Ángel Cabrera.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A second United States Open title was in Jim Furyk’s grasp Sunday as he stood on the No. 17 tee, gripping his driver. Then, suddenly, it was out of reach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A second United States Open title was in Jim Furyk's grasp Sunday as he stood on the No. 17 tee, gripping his driver.</p>
        <p>Three consecutive birdies on the backside had vaulted Furyk, the 2003 champion, into a tie for the lead with Ángel Cabrera.</p>
        <p>The 17th hole is the shortest par 4 on the Oakmont Country Club course, measuring 313 yards. That still plays plenty long for Furyk, who is No. 171 on the PGA Tour in driving distance.</p>
        <p>Furyk calibrated the wind. He pictured the flight of his ball. The one thing he did not take into account was the adrenaline that was making his fingers tingle. He struck the ball squarely, then watched in disbelief as his drive landed in a tangle of rough that Furyk had never considered himself capable of reaching.</p>
        <p>He left his second shot in the rough, pitched out long and hit a par putt that lipped out. With the bogey, Furyk dropped to six over for the championship, and that is how he finished. He parred the last hole for his second consecutive par 70, one stroke behind Cabrera, who sealed the championship with a final-round 69.</p>
        <p>It was the second straight second-place finish for Furyk at the Open, but the pain of this near miss ran as deep as his family's Pennsylvania roots. His parents grew up in Pittsburgh, and Furyk, 37, was reared outside Lancaster, across the state but close to the hearts of the locals whose support perhaps got his blood pumping too much.</p>
        <p>At 17, the fans chanted, ''Here we go, Jimmy.''</p>
        <p>And then Furyk missed the par putt, and there went the Open.</p>
        <p>''Surprised I made a bogey,'' Furyk said, his mind still replaying No. 17 after his round was over. His face was blank and he hardly blinked as he added: ''I haven't hit a ball anywhere within 20 yards of anywhere that one went. So I was shocked.</p>
        <p>''I would stick by that play through and through with the way the wind conditions were and the pin position was. In my mind, I made the right decision.''</p>
        <p>Furyk, the third-ranked player in the world, entered the final round four strokes behind the leader, Aaron Baddeley. He was one of five golfers who claimed at least a share of the lead at some point during the tense, torrid day. The others were Furyk's playing partner Steve Stricker (76), Stephen Ames (76), Tiger Woods (72) and Cabrera.</p>
        <p>''It was difficult coming in,'' said Furyk, who hit 9 of 14 fairways and took 29 putts. ''I saw the board at 15, and then we didn't see another one until 17, at the green, and it was tough, really, to be aware of what was going on ahead. But either way, it didn't matter. I was trying to hit it at the stick, just wasn't able to.''</p>
        <p>Most weeks on the Tour, it is possible to gauge how golfers are doing on the course by the cheers that erupt from every corner. Like the Masters in April, this week was different. It was so quiet, you could hear the golfers dropping strokes.</p>
        <p>Furyk tied for 13th at Augusta. His second-place finish here was his fifth top-five showing in 13 United States Opens, dating to his rookie year, 1994.</p>
        <p>''No one likes consolation prizes,'' Furyk said. ''I'm proud of the way I played and I'm proud of those finishes. But you know, a second is not that much fun, to be honest with you.''</p>
        <p>A GOOD YEAR FOR A DAD -- On the 18th hole, a baby's cries distracted Zach Johnson, who wound up bogeying the hole, a par 4, for the third time in four rounds.</p>
        <p>''That was irritating,'' he said, but there was not much more he could say.</p>
        <p>The wailing child was his 6-month-old son, Will, who was in the arms of his wife, Kim.</p>
        <p>Will is the couple's first child, and his birth remains the highlight of a year in which Johnson won the Masters and the AT&amp;T Classic and was honored last month with Zach Johnson Day in his home state, Iowa.</p>
        <p>Johnson posted rounds of 76, 74, 76 and 74 to finish in a six-way tie for 45th at 20-over-par 300.</p>
        <p>''I've had a lot of good stuff in 2007, and he certainly tops the charts on all that stuff,'' Johnson said.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
