<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Before the Cobblestones Vanish, a Push to Preserve</title>
    <meta content="03dumb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/thecity/03dumb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851900"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: DUMBO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dumbo (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dumbo Neighborhood Assn</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Landmarks Preservation Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mooney, Jake</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E2D81330F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Before the Cobblestones Vanish, a Push to Preserve</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Before the Cobblestones Vanish, a Push to Preserve</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAKE MOONEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mooney, Jake</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on years-long effort by Dumbo Neighborhood Assn to have Dumbo neighborhood in Brooklyn designated historic district; Landmarks Preservation Commission staff met recently with local property owners to discuss ramifications of designation and has developed preliminary map showing district's possible boundaries; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 1997, when preservationists and residents of the Dumbo neighborhood of Brooklyn were campaigning to have the area listed on the National Register of Historic Places, they commissioned a series of photographs to depict its industrial grandeur, from its cobblestone streets to its cavernous warehouse buildings, all perched on the waterfront between the Brooklyn and Manhattan Bridges.</p>
        <p>The appeal succeeded, and the designation came in 2000. Years later, for better or worse, the most prominent dwellings in the neighborhood are expensive apartments in new high-rises like the Beacon Tower and J Condominiums.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Dumbo Neighborhood Association has spent years seeking to have Dumbo designated a historic district.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 1997, when preservationists and residents of the Dumbo neighborhood of Brooklyn were campaigning to have the area listed on the National Register of Historic Places, they commissioned a series of photographs to depict its industrial grandeur, from its cobblestone streets to its cavernous warehouse buildings, all perched on the waterfront between the Brooklyn and Manhattan Bridges.</p>
        <p>The appeal succeeded, and the designation came in 2000. Years later, for better or worse, the most prominent dwellings in the neighborhood are expensive apartments in new high-rises like the Beacon Tower and J Condominiums.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the Dumbo Neighborhood Association, a residents' group, has spent years pursuing another goal, one that has proved much more elusive. It is seeking to have Dumbo designated a historic district, which would place restrictions on how buildings can be altered and preserve a measure of the ambience memorialized in the 1997 photographs. If the designation is made, all the buildings within the district will be protected as landmarks.</p>
        <p>A few months ago, supporters of the idea gathered those photos again, this time paired with new pictures of the same vistas, to show how quickly the neighborhood has changed and how much, in their opinion, has already been lost.</p>
        <p>On April 19, the staff of the city's Landmarks Preservation Commission met with local property owners to discuss the ramifications of a designation, and the agency has developed a preliminary map showing what the boundaries of the district might be. It would occupy a jagged plot of roughly 15 square blocks bisected by the Manhattan Bridge.</p>
        <p>Even some preservationists had underestimated how quickly Dumbo would catch on as a neighborhood.</p>
        <p>''Three years ago, there weren't really that many big buildings there,'' said Simeon Bankoff, executive director of the Historic Districts Council, a nonprofit group, ''and now it's a constant construction zone.''</p>
        <p>The next step, said Lisi de Bourbon, a commission spokeswoman, is to place the matter on the agency's calendar for consideration, a step that temporarily prevents developers from initiating new building changes and formally begins the designation process.</p>
        <p>''It will be calendared; we just don't know when,'' she said. According to Ms. de Bourbon, commission members plan to keep meeting with local property owners, including some of the hundreds of people who have recently bought local condos -- an affluent constituency that supporters of designation say has helped swing the debate in their favor. Developers and larger landowners have long objected to a designation, arguing that designation would have impeded the very residential growth that helped Dumbo thrive.</p>
        <p>Proposals for several large residential developments have galvanized support for the district, said Doreen Gallo, an artist and vice president of the neighborhood association. ''It's got all these people that live in these million-dollar apartments activated,'' she said. ''These are bad things, but it made these people show up to the owners' meeting. It made them write letters.''</p>
        <p>Opponents of the designation, though, say the designation could prevent others from investing in the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>''Dumbo west of Jay was successfully developed and invested in without being landmarked, while still preserving the overall historic nature,'' said Peter Forman, who is a co-owner of two buildings on Jay Street that would probably be in the proposed district. ''Dumbo east of Jay can achieve the same without diminishing owners' property rights.''</p>
        <p>In particular, Mr. Forman called upon the city to improve the area's roads, sewers and transportation, and to rezone the area, large parts of which are still zoned for manufacturing.</p>
        <p>''We've got a successfully built neighborhood,'' he said. ''Government can keep their controls through zoning without over-imposing through landmarking.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Gallo, who moved to Dumbo in 1980 and helped establish the neighborhood association, said she still loves Dumbo, even with all of the changes. In her opinion, a historical designation is long overdue but welcome.</p>
        <p>''I always say, you're designated when half of your neighborhood has been torn down,'' Ms. Gallo said. ''So we're at that halfway mark.''</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: DUMBO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
