<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Broadway by the Numbers: Remember Those $4 Tickets?</title>
    <meta content="03seas" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851709"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER: THE TONYS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcelroy, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E2DB1430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Broadway by the Numbers: Remember Those $4 Tickets?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN McELROY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcelroy, Steven</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article presents statistics comparing four Broadway seasons: 1946-7, 1966-67, 1986-87 and 2006-7; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE past season has done little to disprove a familiar lament: As far as Broadway is concerned, the straight play is dead. ''Journey's End'' is about to become the latest casualty. Despite six Tony Award nominations for the revival of this 1929 drama by R. C. Sherriff, the final curtain will fall after a run of just under four months, only hours before the awards are presented next Sunday. Broadway is tough on plays, and toughest of all on new ones. ''The Little Dog Laughed'' barely surpassed 100 performances, while ''Coram Boy'' closed last Sunday after only 18 previews and 30 regular performances.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE past season has done little to disprove a familiar lament: As far as Broadway is concerned, the straight play is dead. ''Journey's End'' is about to become the latest casualty. Despite six Tony Award nominations for the revival of this 1929 drama by R. C. Sherriff, the final curtain will fall after a run of just under four months, only hours before the awards are presented next Sunday. Broadway is tough on plays, and toughest of all on new ones. ''The Little Dog Laughed'' barely surpassed 100 performances, while ''Coram Boy'' closed last Sunday after only 18 previews and 30 regular performances.</p>
        <p>While the three previous seasons each offered 15 new plays, the latest fielded only 11. A glance at four seasons over 60 years -- from 1946-47 (when the Tony Awards were first presented) to 2006-7 -- suggests that the decline of the straight play is real. Everything else seems to be going up, including ticket prices and even the number of Tony categories.</p>
        <p>STEVEN McELROY</p>
        <p>1946-47  THEATERS: 34  NEW MUSICALS: 11  NEW PLAYS: 42  AVG. PAID ADMISSION: $3.90 ($36.15 today)  TONY AWARD CATEGORIES: 10  TONY CEREMONIES TICKET: $7.50 ($69.51 today)</p>
        <p>TRIVIA  The winners were announced in the Waldorf-Astoria Hotel's Grand Ballroom, but not the nominees -- those names were not released for the first time until the 1956 awards.</p>
        <p>Since the now-familiar medallion did not come along until 1949, winners the first year took home an initialed sterling silver compact case (the women) and an engraved gold money clip or cigarette lighter (the men).</p>
        <p>''All My Sons'' was a big winner, grabbing an outstanding author award for Arthur Miller and outstanding director for Elia Kazan. The Pulitzer Prize board was not as impressed though. There was no award for drama that year.</p>
        <p>1966-67  THEATERS: 34  NEW MUSICALS: 9  NEW PLAYS: 26  AVG. PAID ADMISSION: $5.91 ($36.57 today)  TONY AWARD CATEGORIES: 16  TONY CEREMONIES TICKET: $10-$35 ($61.88 -$216.59 today)</p>
        <p>TRIVIA  The awards were broadcast on national television for the first time on March 26, 1967, and an estimated 40 million people watched the hourlong telecast, which ran over by eight minutes. ''Cabaret'' was the big winner, grabbing eight awards.</p>
        <p>''Breakfast at Tiffany's'' may have made a great film, but it was a stinker of a play. The producer David Merrick shut it down on Dec. 14, 1966, after four previews and before it even opened, ''rather than subject the drama critics and the public to an excruciatingly boring evening,'' he said at the time.</p>
        <p>1986-87  THEATERS: 37  NEW MUSICALS: 10  NEW PLAYS: 15  AVG. PAID ADMISSION: $29.42 ($53.53 today)  TONY AWARD CATEGORIES: 19  TONY CEREMONIES TICKET: $50-$500 ($90.97-$909.71 today)</p>
        <p>TRIVIA  The scenic design for ''Starlight Express'' was the most expensive and complicated Broadway had ever seen, but John Napier was nominated (and won) for his costumes, not for his set. He won the scenic design award anyway, though, for ''Les Misérables.'' He was surprised by the choice. ''I'd give this to have been in the room,'' Mr. Napier said, holding up his Tony.</p>
        <p>The ceremony continued to lengthen: the 1987 telecast was granted a two-hour time slot, but ran over by about 30 minutes.</p>
        <p>2006-07  THEATERS: 39  NEW MUSICALS: 12  NEW PLAYS: 11  AVG. PAID ADMISSION: $76.32  TONY AWARD CATEGORIES: 25  TONY CEREMONIES TICKET: $200-$800</p>
        <p>TRIVIA  Though the current revival of ''Journey's End'' will close after only 5 previews and 125 performances, the original opened March 22, 1929, and ran 485 times. This year's revival is not as unfortunate as the last one, though, which opened and closed in September 1939 after just 16 performances.</p>
        <p>Angela Lansbury, nominated for best actress in a play for ''Deuce,'' has won the Tony each of the previous four times she has been nominated: for ''Mame,'' ''Dear World,'' ''Gypsy'' and ''Sweeney Todd.'' Ms. Lansbury has also been a host at the Tony Awards five times, more than anyone else.</p>
        <p>As in some other years, the Tony ceremonies will not have a host, but a lineup of presenters. Among those scheduled are: David Hyde Pierce, Audra McDonald, Eddie Izzard, Usher, Cynthia Nixon and, of course, Ms. Lansbury.</p>
        <p>(Sources by George A. Wachtel, Audience Research &amp; Analysis; The League of American Theaters and Producers; The American Theater Wing; Theatre World; Bureau of Labor Statistics; The New York Times)</p>
        <p>THEATER: THE TONYS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
