<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Dollar Sinks, European Cruises Could Be a Bargain</title>
    <meta content="03heads" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851646"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HEADS UP: CONTINENTAL CRUISES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cruises</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaufman, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Heads Up</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E0DF1730F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1240" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Dollar Sinks, European Cruises Could Be a Bargain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KAUFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaufman, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Kaufman travel article on bargain summer cruises in Europe; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DESPITE the rising euro and the near-record pound, Europe is emerging as the unexpected star of this summer's cruising season. With companies from the American cruising giants to boutique lines that specialize in river and Arctic itineraries expanding their presence throughout the Continent, European cruise capacity is expected to increase 23 percent this summer over last, according to Cruise Industry News, with an additional 10 percent more growth predicted for next year.</p>
        <p>Fueling the rise is a combination of consumer demand and cruising's unanticipated status as a vacation value option this summer. ''There are more ships out there than ever before, and companies have to put them where they will earn a strong return,'' said Henry Harteveldt, chief travel analyst at Forrester Research in San Francisco.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DESPITE the rising euro and the near-record pound, Europe is emerging as the unexpected star of this summer's cruising season. With companies from the American cruising giants to boutique lines that specialize in river and Arctic itineraries expanding their presence throughout the Continent, European cruise capacity is expected to increase 23 percent this summer over last, according to Cruise Industry News, with an additional 10 percent more growth predicted for next year.</p>
        <p>Fueling the rise is a combination of consumer demand and cruising's unanticipated status as a vacation value option this summer. ''There are more ships out there than ever before, and companies have to put them where they will earn a strong return,'' said Henry Harteveldt, chief travel analyst at Forrester Research in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>Terry L. Dale, chief executive of the Cruise Lines International Association, which represents 21 major lines, said, ''There is tremendous value in European cruising this summer because you pay for everything in dollars before boarding, which helps remove the vulnerability of fluctuating exchange rates.''</p>
        <p>Among the new entrants are Carnival and Disney, which are launching megaships in the Mediterranean this year -- the 110,000-ton, 2,984-passenger Carnival Freedom and the 83,000-ton 2,700-passenger Disney Magic, the company's first foray into the Continent. At the opposite extreme, the New York City-based operator Lindblad Expeditions is introducing the 86-passenger Sea Cloud II, which will focus on Mediterranean excursions, while Tauck World Discovery, a European river cruise specialist, is preparing for the second season of its 118-passenger Swiss Emerald and plans to add a new 361-foot sister ship next year. Royal Caribbean, Norwegian Cruise Lines and Princess Cruises are also strengthening their European presence; the luxury line Silverseas is placing its entire four-ship fleet in Europe; and Crystal Cruises is repositioning vessels from Alaska to Europe this year in response to rising demand.</p>
        <p>Once deployed, the new -- and new to Europe -- vessels will cruise throughout the region this summer from perennial favorites like Italy and Spain to Croatia and Arctic gateway towns, which, according to Mr. Dale, are going to be the season's important new destinations.</p>
        <p>Cruise industry executives and analysts said the upswing in European demand was unlikely to reach a saturation point soon, because repeat passengers and wealthier novices are likely to seek more sophisticated experiences away from traditional destinations like Alaska and the Caribbean.</p>
        <p>''We are seeing growing affluence among baby boomers who not only have more money, but more time,'' said Bob Dickinson, chief executive of Carnival Cruise Lines, whose summer 2008 launch of a second megaship in the Mediterranean will increase Carnival's European capacity 50 percent over its 2006 level. With so many lines sailing so many ships this summer, pricing on European cruises has become increasingly competitive -- particularly in this era of 200-euro hotel rooms. Much of the value comes from the nature of cruises, which, regardless of size or itinerary, generally include cabins, meals and most on-board activities for a single fee priced in dollars rather than euros or pounds.</p>
        <p>Smaller companies like Tauck and Lindblad include shore excursions and pre- and post-sailing hotel stays, generally among ''the only extras you are paying for on cruises,'' Mr. Harteveldt said.</p>
        <p>And because cruises usually price their sailings -- as well as shore excursions and even spa fees -- up to a year in advance, ''you are locking in a trip's major costs before you depart,'' said Bob Watson, manager of Watson &amp; Watson, a division of Protravel International in Scarsdale, N.Y.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Dale of the cruise ship group noted, cruise lines are bullish on the Baltics and Europe's far north this summer, along with the Dalmatian Coast. Celebrity, which will operate four vessels in Europe, is adding new ports including the Norwegian towns of Molde and Tromso in the popular fjord-filled subarctic region. Crystal, meanwhile, will pull into Eidfjord in Norway for the first time; Holland America will include Jupivogur in Iceland among its 13 new European ports; and Seabourn will call on Lysekil in Sweden and the Danish island of Bornholm.</p>
        <p>There is an equal flurry of new activity in the Adriatic, with lines like Seabourn, Holland America and Regent Seven Seas joining the rush to ports in Croatia, Slovenia and Montenegro.</p>
        <p>''Croatia is one of the most requested destinations simply because cruisers have not been there yet,'' said Bruce Good, spokesman for the Yachts of Seabourn, which will call on ports like Split, Dubrovnik, Rovinj and Zadar, as well as Kotor in Montenegro and Koper in Slovenia.</p>
        <p>Farther east, the Black Sea is proving to be popular as well, with lines like Celebrity, Crystal and Holland America pulling into Sochi in Russia for the first time. The Black Sea is also the endpoint for the newest -- and longest -- river cruise from Tauck Tours, whose European river business increased 45 percent last summer. This season, Tauck begins a 21-day, transcontinental voyage from Amsterdam to Romania's Black Sea port of Cernavoda, cruising along the Rhine, Main and Danube Rivers through Germany, Austria, Slovakia, Hungary, Croatia, Serbia and Bulgaria. Excursions include visits to Unesco World Heritage Sites like the German town of Bamberg, as well as a tour of the Serbian capital of Belgrade and an excursion to the walled fortress in Veliko Turnovo, Bulgaria's medieval capital. Prices begin at $7,530, plus airfare.</p>
        <p>Other new cruises this summer include:</p>
        <p>DISNEY -- The company's cruise operation will have its debut in Europe with eight 10- and 11-night Mediterranean cruises departing from Barcelona and stopping throughout the south of France (Villefranche, Marseille) and Italy (Palermo, Naples, Sardinia, Rome and Florence). Prices begin at $2,399 and include family-friendly extras like hunting for treasure in the Tuscan city of Lucca, making ceramics in Palermo and touring in the medieval city of Narni near Rome, the inspiration for C. S. Lewis's ''The Chronicles of Narnia'' (www.disneycruise.com, 888-325-2500).</p>
        <p>CARNIVAL -- It is launching its newest ship, the 1,487-room Freedom, in Europe with 19 sailings, including a dozen 12-day Grand Mediterranean voyages. Ports include Naples, Dubrovnik, Venice, Messina, Barcelona, Cannes and Livorno. Prices begin at $1,399 (www.carnival.com, 888-227-6482).</p>
        <p>CRYSTAL CRUISES -- The line is introducing an 11-day northern European voyage in early August on the 940-passenger Symphony. Beginning in Copenhagen, the ship docks in Oslo, Hamburg, Amsterdam, Bordeaux and Honfleur in Normandy, before its last stop in London. Prices begin at $4,755 (www.crystalcruises.com, 888-722-0021).</p>
        <p>New Dalmatian and Black Sea destinations along with additional Greek and Turkish ports make for not only a more varied European cruising season, but also a longer one as well. And that longer sailing window, now stretching as late as December on some lines, provides yet another opportunity for travelers to save. By avoiding the peak months of June through August, said Dan Hanrahan, president of Celebrity, travelers can save as much as $1,000 on a Celebrity cruise of 7 to 11 nights.</p>
        <p>The discount is typical of most lines with fall itineraries, which include sailings until early December on ships from Princess and Cunard. ''And savings can even reach up to 25 percent if you aren't locked into a specific ship on a specific itinerary,'' said Mr. Watson of Protravel.</p>
        <p>Even if you're avoiding Europe this year, a travel agent can give you a head start on booking for next summer. Nearly every major line released 2008 prices months ago -- well before the dollar's current slide. ''The time to book is absolutely right now,'' said Mary Jean Tully, chief executive of Cruise Professionals in Toronto.</p>
        <p>HEADS UP: CONTINENTAL CRUISES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
