<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Target: TRASH</title>
    <meta content="03dump" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/thecity/03dump.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851905"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sanitation Department (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mindlin, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Sanitation Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E2D81330F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Target: TRASH</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Target: Trash</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX MINDLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mindlin, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on work of New York City Sanitation Department's Illegal Dumping Task Force, whose 35 armed plainclothes officers prowl streets of city's outer boroughs in search of illegal dumpers; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was 5 in the afternoon, and the scratched-up green Dodge pickup was stopped at a light at Foster and Remsen Avenues in Canarsie, Brooklyn. A teetering bureau and a load of wooden slats were in back.</p>
        <p>''Look at that,'' said Lt. Robert DeRossi, a barrel-chested, baby-faced officer who was at the wheel of an unmarked white Jeep.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sanitation officers are on the prowl in the city’s outer precincts, pursuing illegal dumpers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was 5 in the afternoon, and the scratched-up green Dodge pickup was stopped at a light at Foster and Remsen Avenues in Canarsie, Brooklyn. A teetering bureau and a load of wooden slats were in back.</p>
        <p>''Look at that,'' said Lt. Robert DeRossi, a barrel-chested, baby-faced officer who was at the wheel of an unmarked white Jeep.</p>
        <p>His partner, Officer Joseph Fontana, thinner and bespectacled, followed his glance through the windshield. ''Let's follow,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The men tailed the truck three miles northeast into a deserted, marshy patch of East New York, watching it make repeated U-turns.</p>
        <p>''He's spooked,'' Officer Fontana said.</p>
        <p>At one point during the 30-minute tail, the pickup doubled back on them and passed the Jeep as the two officers studiously pretended to ignore it.</p>
        <p>''Is he eyeballing us?'' Lieutenant DeRossi asked.</p>
        <p>''He doesn't even know we're here,'' Officer Fontana replied.</p>
        <p>Finally, the pickup turned onto the southernmost block of Forbell Street, a lonely stretch near the Belt Parkway that is bordered by blocks of scrub, and pulled in next to a graffiti-scrawled shipping container surrounded by a spray of junk.</p>
        <p>For a few minutes, nothing seemed to be happening. From 600 yards away, the officers settled in to watch. ''Give him a chance,'' Officer Fontana said, half to himself.</p>
        <p>Then a tiny form appeared in the bed of the pickup, and an object flew off the truck into the weeds beside the road.</p>
        <p>''Bobby, they're dumping!'' Officer Fontana shouted. ''Go down there!''</p>
        <p>A man in a plaid work shirt was tossing planks and slats onto the road. As the Jeep rolled up, he began to tip over the bureau. When it hit the ground, Lieutenant DeRossi said: ''O.K. Let's get him.''</p>
        <p>Lieutenant DeRossi and Officer Fontana are members of the Sanitation Department's Illegal Dumping Task Force, a unit of 35 armed plainclothes officers, former sanitation workers all. And this is their busy season. Construction work and spring cleaning pick up in April and May, generating large amounts of debris; some 21 dumpers' vehicles were impounded in May of last year, a number exceeded only in August.</p>
        <p>''The season's heating up,'' Inspector Robert D'Angelo, the unit's commander, told a group of his officers during a briefing at their Bensonhurst headquarters in early May. ''Keep your eyes open. Let's get back to hunter mode, and be careful.''</p>
        <p>To nab their prey, task force officers fan out across the city and work around the clock, sometimes following potential dumpers for miles or lying in wait for them in vacant lots. Sleuthlike, they poke through magazines that have been discarded amid spring-cleaning debris, looking for mailing labels that will help them track down offenders.</p>
        <p>Sometimes officers sit in a welding truck, wearing hard hats and posing as welders. They have been known to lie belly down in high grass at stakeouts. When Lieutenant DeRossi was a rookie, he was fond of hiding in trees, eyeing potential offenders through the leaves.</p>
        <p>As with many other hard-to-control crimes, the punishment for illegal dumping is stiff: a fine of at least $1,500 for each person caught in the act, and a cleanup charge of $150 per cubic yard of material. In addition, officers impound the vehicle used, a practice that tends to strand dumpers in the city's most godforsaken corners.</p>
        <p>A look at the task force's yearly impoundment rates suggest that on a historical scale, the problem is waning. The city's construction boom, though it has created much stuff to dump, has also consumed many of the vacant lots that were once desirable dumping sites, and many of those remaining are being watched more closely.</p>
        <p>Last year, 201 dumpers' vehicles were impounded, the second-lowest number on record; the lowest was in 2005. By comparison, the task force impounded 464 vehicles in 1995, and close to 1,000 a year throughout the late 1980s. If current trends continue, New York may lose the unwatched no man's lands where dumping thrives. But for now, many of those parts of the city are still around.</p>
        <p>When illegal dumpers are caught, they seldom look panic-stricken, like the perps on cop shows. More often, they wear a puzzled but friendly expression, a look that says, ''What seems to be the problem, Officer?''</p>
        <p>That was the look that Paul Gordon, the pickup truck's driver, directed at Lieutenant DeRossi that afternoon. The officers had finished frisking Mr. Gordon and his passenger, Marvin Smalls, and were waiting for their backup cars.</p>
        <p>''This is our pastor's stuff,'' Mr. Gordon, wearing a turquoise fleece jacket and a Mets cap, said mildly, gesturing to a pile of freshly dumped wooden odds and ends next to the road. ''It's broken benches from our church. We were looking for the proper place, and we thought this was it.''</p>
        <p>Lieutenant DeRossi, who has a passionate distaste for litter of all kinds, surveyed the weedy roadside, the graffiti-scarred container, the mound of slats and the broken dresser. He gave Mr. Gordon a look of studied confusion.</p>
        <p>''Why would this big container ?'' the lieutenant began, before trailing off.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gordon shrugged. ''That's what I thought,'' he said, later explaining that he had mistaken the area for a legal dumping site because the shipping container was already surrounded by trash and because a Sanitation Department facility was a block away.</p>
        <p>''The city should put up simple signs that say 'No Dumping,' so honest citizens don't make this mistake,'' he told Lieutenant DeRossi. ''I'm an honest person. I would have turned right around and avoided all this hassle.''</p>
        <p>Back in the Jeep, Lieutenant DeRossi said this sort of reaction was common.</p>
        <p>''They always say, 'Oh, I didn't know; I didn't know,' '' the officer said. ''But I didn't believe that guy at all. They were going to all the spots. He knew.''</p>
        <p>Nearby, Mr. Smalls leaned against the pickup, wearing a resigned look and waiting for a ride home from a friend. He eyed the remaining slats in the truck bed. ''Since they're writing it up anyway,'' he said to no one in particular, ''can I just throw out these last pieces of wood?''</p>
        <p>In late May, Mr. Gordon was found in violation of illegal-dumping laws and fined $1,500 by a judge for the city's Environmental Control Board. Mr. Smalls, absent from his hearing, was found in default and was fined $10,000. Mr. Gordon has about a month to appeal the decision; Mr. Smalls can request a stay of default and a new hearing date.</p>
        <p>Not all dumps are equally large, and at times the task force officers almost feel sorry for their prey. Later on the night the officers encountered Mr. Gordon and Mr. Smalls, three unmarked cars, equipped with sirens, raced down a pitted alley in East Flatbush, their lights blazing in a cloud of dust, to catch a father and son who were dumping trash from a van by the side of the road.</p>
        <p>The flashing white strobe lights revealed the pitifully small haul: three plywood drawers and a neatly tied bundle of wood. The load was so modest that Sanitation Department workers would have hauled it away from the family's curb at no charge. Now, father and son would be out at least $3,000.</p>
        <p>The night was cold, and the officers sat in their warm cars, keying the summonses into handheld computers. Officer Darren Moore, a short, voluble Navy veteran wearing a floppy fishing hat that said ''Puerto Rico,'' had been called back to headquarters; he got in his car and left the scene, but became intrigued by a minivan on the way. It was heavy and riding low on its shocks, and at one point it changed course abruptly, perhaps to avoid the cluster of flashing squad cars at the father-and-son dumping site.</p>
        <p>Two blocks later, Officer Moore watched as the minivan's occupants, a mother and her grown daughter, dumped a vacuum cleaner, some broken chairs and a rug on a weedy curb, setting the stage for the third impoundment of the day. As the mother and daughter began to drive away, he pulled them over and called for backup. Several cars from the other dump site rushed over, lights flashing, and the little handheld computers came out again.</p>
        <p>''This was such a dumb idea,'' the daughter said, moaning.</p>
        <p>The Illegal Dumping Task Force knows that trash attracts trash; people dump where others already have. As Lieutenant DeRossi put it, ''They say, 'Oh, I'm going to throw it here; no one will ever know the difference.' ''</p>
        <p>But some areas are so attractive to dumpers that it hardly matters whether trash is already there. They seem to draw garbage as magnets draw iron filings, no matter how many summonses the officers give out.</p>
        <p>Many of these areas lie along the fringes of Brooklyn, where the borough dribbles off into sluggish brown waterways and fields blanketed with high scrub grass.</p>
        <p>For example, trucks have repeatedly backed through the locked gate of a yard on Dumont Avenue, nestled among the marshes along the Brooklyn-Queens border, to dump paint buckets, rags and plastic laundry bins. In East New York, a dead-end stretch of Fountain Avenue beside a brackish inlet of Jamaica Bay is lined with clumps of contractors' black trash bags sitting at three-foot intervals, like ornamental shrubs.</p>
        <p>Trash is not the only thing dumped on Fountain Avenue. A makeshift memorial here marks the spot where on Feb. 25, 2006, the police found the body of a 24-year-old graduate student, Imette St. Guillen. She had been strangled and her body left by the roadside, wrapped in a quilt. Michael Pastore, an animal control officer who worked nearby, told a reporter at the time that the street was ''one of those five or six locations that you can honestly say, 'I hope I don't stumble upon a dead body.' ''</p>
        <p>The dumpers have maintained a respectful 15-foot distance from the memorial. Beyond that distance, the trash resumes.</p>
        <p>The most popular dumping grounds have much in common. They tend to be shielded by grass, trees and uninhabited stretches of land. Many are undeveloped patches with no obvious caretaker. ''On Fountain Avenue, how are you going to solve that problem?'' Lieutenant DeRossi said. ''Nobody owns it.''</p>
        <p>But the days of ownerless space are fast ending. Everywhere you look in East New York, raw new brick-and-concrete condos are springing up. Neighborhoods that never had sewer lines are getting them, and once-open lots are being fenced in against the day when they can be sold. Even the old dump at the end of Fountain Avenue is being turned into a park.</p>
        <p>This might seem like good news for the dumping police, but it makes their jobs harder. Catching offenders is easiest when officers can simply wait for them at known dumping spots. On nearly every night in May, for instance, officers stationed in two unmarked cars watched the dusty alley where the father and son were caught dumping the drawers. ''We get guys that live on Long Island that use this spot,'' Inspector D'Angelo said.</p>
        <p>The shrinking number of such spots has forced dumpers, and hence task force officers, to adapt. The officers have learned to keep tabs on new construction sites, which are popular dumping grounds, and to rely more heavily on following suspicious vehicles, rather than simply staking out the obvious spots.</p>
        <p>The lot at the task force's headquarters holds a blue Dodge pickup that was caught going down 57th Street in Sunset Park in early May, dropping a trash bag or two in front of every house for pickup. That kind of unorthodox dumping is hard to stop.</p>
        <p>''It's a needle in a haystack with those random guys,'' Inspector D'Angelo said. ''But by being out there, we spot them. A van, a loaded station wagon -- he may be a decent guy going to a waste transfer station, but we'll follow him.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
