<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recipe Redux; 1989: Spinach Roman Style</title>
    <meta content="03food.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="61" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/magazine/03food-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851672"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Food: Recipe Redux"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Spinach</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ssam Bar (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hesser, Amanda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Middione, Carlo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chang, David (Chef)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Vegetables</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vegetables</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E2DC1430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1127" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recipe Redux; 1989: Spinach Roman Style</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">1989: Spinach Roman Style</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Amanda Hesser</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hesser, Amanda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reprint of Carlo Middione's recipe for spinach Roman style, which first appeared in New York Times Magazine in 1989, together with updated version by David Chang, chef at Ssam Bar in East Village; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sometimes I think we don't feel enough shame for the things we put on our plates in the 1980s -- the towers of tuna sprouting chives, the squiggles of mayonnaise. But in the decade's defense, it did mark the beginning of the love fest for Italian cooking that still continues. Back then, The Times published a spate of stories about Italian dishes like risotto, polenta and biscotti. In an article on antipasti in this magazine, published in 1989, there was a terrific recipe for spinach ''Roman style,'' or sautéed spinach with raisins and pine nuts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A leafy green, with roasted asparagus and fennel, from the days when antipasti and contorni were revelatory notions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sometimes I think we don't feel enough shame for the things we put on our plates in the 1980s -- the towers of tuna sprouting chives, the squiggles of mayonnaise. But in the decade's defense, it did mark the beginning of the love fest for Italian cooking that still continues. Back then, The Times published a spate of stories about Italian dishes like risotto, polenta and biscotti. In an article on antipasti in this magazine, published in 1989, there was a terrific recipe for spinach ''Roman style,'' or sautéed spinach with raisins and pine nuts.</p>
        <p>The original recipe came from ''The Food of Southern Italy,'' by Carlo Middione. In unskilled hands, the dish can be a real dud -- the spinach soggy from too much oil, the nuts bland, the raisins too hard. But Middione examined every ingredient and cooked each so as to amplify its presence: the garlic is browned, the pine nuts are toasted and the raisins are soaked in water because American raisins, he wrote, ''tend to be very sweet and do not have much depth of flavor.'' Soaking drains them of some of this excess sweetness.</p>
        <p>I wondered what a chef like David Chang, who has become the darling of the East Village for his riffs on Asian foods, would do with the recipe. He is known for serving ramen with Berkshire pork at Momofuku Noodle Bar, his first sliver of a restaurant, and deep-fried Brussels sprouts at Momofuku Ssam Bar.</p>
        <p>Turns out that the spinach was old hat. ''I've made that dish so many times,'' he said recently in his Ssam Bar kitchen. But it brought to mind some experiments he was doing with nori, the sheets of dried seaweed used to wrap sushi rolls. He was softening them in dashi and then twisting them into abstract shapes and letting them dry to make nori ''chips.'' Why not just treat nori like spinach, he thought. Attempts to wilt brittle nori in hot oil with garlic and shallots were an ugly failure. So he poured some dashi (a broth made with dried bonito flakes and kombu, or kelp) in the pan and then braised the sheets, adding them in strips one at a time. When you add them to the pan, they melt a bit like the Wicked Witch of the West. Once braised, he added toasted pine nuts and, in place of the raisins, a few bits of litchi (from a can, drained and sliced). The dish needed a final touch, which he found by grating horseradish over the top, just as you might grate Parmesan cheese over the spinach. The filaments of horseradish are a potent nod to wasabi.</p>
        <p>Chang wasn't finished, though. The nori, shallot and garlic mixture reminded him of a nori purée they had been making at the restaurant for spooning on top of chawanmushi, a delicate egg-and-dashi custard. So this time, he took that braised nori mixture and puréed it with toasted pine nuts for a nori ''pesto.'' He cracked a few eggs into a bowl, measured out a few tablespoons of nori pesto and with the help of a hot pan and butter, nori scrambled eggs were born.</p>
        <p>''This one's a little weird,'' he said. ''It doesn't taste weird. It's just hard for the brain to register what it is, since you're used to wrapping nori around egg.'' Brains will happily adapt to a dish this good.</p>
        <p>1989: Spinach Roman Style</p>
        <p>This recipe appeared in The Times Magazine in an article by Judith Barrett, who adapted it from ''The Food of Southern Italy,'' by Carlo Middione.</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons of the smallest available raisins, black or golden</p>
        <p>4 medium-size bunches of spinach (about 2 1/2 pounds), washed at least twice, but not dried, and trimmed of stems</p>
        <p>1/3 cup virgin olive oil</p>
        <p>5 medium garlic cloves, peeled and well crushed</p>
        <p>4 tablespoons pine nuts</p>
        <p>Big pinch of salt</p>
        <p>6 or 7 grindings of fresh black pepper.</p>
        <p>1. Put the raisins in a small bowl with enough warm water to cover. Soak for about 15 minutes. Set aside.</p>
        <p>2. Put the wet spinach in a frying pan large enough to hold it all and cook over a high flame until it collapses and turns dark green, stirring constantly. Transfer the spinach to a colander and set it aside. If the frying pan is wet, dry it with a paper towel.</p>
        <p>3. Pour the olive oil into the frying pan over medium-high heat. Add the garlic and brown it, being careful it doesn't burn, and then remove and discard it. Take the raisins from the water, squeeze them as dry as possible and add them to the oil with the pine nuts. Turn the heat to medium and cook until the nuts turn a golden color. Be careful, because the nuts can burn easily.</p>
        <p>4. Return the spinach to the pan, stir it with a fork and add salt and pepper to taste. Mix all the ingredients and continue cooking for about a minute. You may add additional olive oil if you think the spinach looks dry. Serves 4.</p>
        <p>2007: Nori Scrambled Eggs</p>
        <p>By David Chang, the chef and owner of Momofuku Noodle Bar and Momofuku Ssam Bar (I didn't include a recipe for the braised nori because it doesn't work unless you have top-quality nori. The scrambled eggs work with the nori found at most Asian markets.)</p>
        <p>22 grams nori (about 7 1/2 sheets)</p>
        <p>1 1/2 cups dashi or chicken broth</p>
        <p>1/3 cup toasted pine nuts</p>
        <p>3 teaspoons soy sauce</p>
        <p>Salt</p>
        <p>6 large eggs</p>
        <p>2 1/2 tablespoons butter</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon grapeseed oil</p>
        <p>Sriracha sauce (optional).</p>
        <p>1. With scissors, cut the nori sheets into strips. In a medium sauté pan, combine the nori and dashi or chicken broth and bring to a simmer. Cook until the nori wilts. Let cool. Transfer the nori, half the dashi and the pine nuts to a blender and purée, adding more dashi as needed. Add the soy sauce. Season with salt to taste.</p>
        <p>2. In a bowl, whisk the eggs and then stir in 5 tablespoons of the nori purée. Season with salt.</p>
        <p>3. In a large sauté pan, melt the butter with the oil over medium-high heat. Add the egg mixture and scramble to desired consistency. Divide among 3 plates. If you choose, pass sriracha sauce on the side. Serves 3.</p>
        <p>NOTE: Nori is the Japanese word for dried seaweed sheets. Toasted nori is used as a garnish and to wrap sushi. High-quality nori should have an ocean flavor but not be chewy. The best nori, like Miyabi, used at such restaurants as Jewel Bako, is typically not available for retail sale. But the Yamamotoyama and Urashima brands, used by the chefs at Morimoto, can be found at pacificeastwest.com.</p>
        <p>Food: Recipe Redux</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
