<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Children's Books</title>
    <meta content="Marler.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/books/review/Marler-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851630"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Children's Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Peck, Dale</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Lost Cities, The (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E7DF1730F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Children's Books</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Children’s Books</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By REGINA MARLER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE LOST CITIES</p>
        <p>A Drift House Voyage.</p>
        <p>By Dale Peck.</p>
        <p>392 pp. Bloomsbury. $16.95.</p>
        <p>(Ages 10 and up)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE LOST CITIES.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE LOST CITIES</p>
        <p>A Drift House Voyage.</p>
        <p>By Dale Peck.</p>
        <p>392 pp. Bloomsbury. $16.95.</p>
        <p>(Ages 10 and up)</p>
        <p>The premise of Dale Peck's middle-grade series, Drift House, could serve as a metaphor for novel-reading: you enter a mysterious and promising house, then find yourself adrift on timeless waters, adventure all around. In the first book, published in 2005, the three Oakenfeld children are exiled from Manhattan by worried parents after the Sept. 11 attacks and sent to their eccentric Uncle Farley's remote house on the Bay of Eternity in Canada, where delicious food and scrupulous housekeeping are provided by an apparently invisible staff. The morning following their arrival, after a storm, the children discover that the house has broken free of the shore. They are drifting on the Sea of Time, guided only by the changing images in a drawing room mural and the patchy memories of the youngest Oakenfeld, 5-year-old Murray, who has traveled to the future and back during a game of hide-and-seek.</p>
        <p>A ''transtemporal vessel,'' Drift House was built in the 17th century by a time voyager named Pierre Marin, whose portrait hangs in the stairwell and overlooks the unfolding chaos. Uncle Farley, a ''gentleman scholar'' and aesthete, bought the house without realizing its magical properties. He also can't figure out how to work the controls. Adding high-pitched critique but little help is the house mascot, President Wilson: a centuries-old parrot with human-level intelligence and speech.</p>
        <p>While the first volume centers on Susan, a 12-year-old A student who impersonates a pirate, befriends a mermaid and defeats an evil octopus queen -- all in a put-on English accent -- the second volume, ''The Lost Cities,'' is her younger brother Charles's story. At 10, Charles, the middle child, is beginning to chafe against Susan's dominance. He's just as intelligent as she is, anyway, and smarter in science. When will he get his adventure? A package is hand-delivered to the two of them, but only Charles can feel the book inside, pulsing warmly and dangerously, calling to him.</p>
        <p>The Drift House series feels familiar from the opening pages. A little too familiar, perhaps, with the first volume occupying an awkward terrain between homage and pastiche. The Sea of Time has clearly swallowed a lot of classic children's literature, especially ''The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe'' and ''A Wrinkle in Time.'' When little Murray is carried from the dumbwaiter after the hide-and-seek game, having fallen asleep, it could be Lucy emerging from the wardrobe, and when Charles steals away from Drift House with the precious book before Susan can see it, one thinks at once of Edmund, betraying his siblings for Turkish delight. ''Susan gets to do everything because she's oldest,'' Charles grumbles. ''Everyone says wait till you're as old as Susan, but she'll always be older than me. I want to be in charge for once.''</p>
        <p>However much fun he had describing Uncle Farley's collection of curios or inventing a haughty mermaid who spews gobs of raw fish, the author -- best known up to now for his ungenerous literary criticism, collected in ''Hatchet Jobs'' (2005) -- didn't quite seem to believe in his fictional world in the first book. But in the second volume, Peck has gained his sea legs. There is more action, less scene-setting. I defy any reader to untangle the dizzying timelines in ''The Lost Cities'' (tellingly, a link titled ''Facts'' on the Drift House Web site, drifthouse.com, leads to a ''coming soon'' notice), but the confusion enhances the story. Murray sipped the waters of the Sea of Time on his initial journey into the future and has become an ''Accursed Returner,'' generating various versions of himself at different ages. Almost any man whom Charles and Susan encounter in the world or out on the Sea of Time could be a version of Murray, come to warn or guide them or to use their magic to try to get back to early-21st-century New York and his lost 5-year-old self.</p>
        <p>There are two underlying messages in the Drift House series: that different eras, and the people who inhabit them, are not really so far apart, and that while magical creatures may live for centuries, humans have the benefit of stories -- the past preserved between book covers. Without a written history, millions of years might as well be 40 minutes. Of course, who's to say it isn't? The Drift House books pick up the conversation where Madeleine L'Engle left off, and will inspire any reader to reflect on time and its spiraling possibilities.</p>
        <p>Regina Marler is the author of ''Bloomsbury Pie.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Regina Marler is the author of ''Bloomsbury Pie.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
