<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Summer Doldrums? Maybe Not</title>
    <meta content="03mark" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/business/yourmoney/03mark.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851909"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E1D81330F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="563" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Summer Doldrums? Maybe Not</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Summer Doldrums? Maybe Not</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONRAD DE AENLLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">De Aenlle, Conrad</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE old admonition to ''sell in May, then go away,'' seems to have gone unheeded this time around, as stocks rose through the month and ended the week at all-time highs.</p>
        <p>Selling in the early part of June would live up to the spirit of the adage, which takes note that the market's performance is often marginal, and sometimes much worse, from May to mid-October. Whether investors should mark the calendar and lighten up on their holdings depends on which adviser is consulted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The old admonition to “sell in May, then go away,” seems to have gone unheeded this year, as stocks ended the week at all-time highs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE old admonition to ''sell in May, then go away,'' seems to have gone unheeded this time around, as stocks rose through the month and ended the week at all-time highs.</p>
        <p>Selling in the early part of June would live up to the spirit of the adage, which takes note that the market's performance is often marginal, and sometimes much worse, from May to mid-October. Whether investors should mark the calendar and lighten up on their holdings depends on which adviser is consulted.</p>
        <p>Timothy L. Swanson, chief investment officer of the private client group at National City, a Cleveland bank, is not planning to dump everything and head for the hills, but the potential seasonal headwind adds to his concerns about valuations and what he sees as investor complacency. He is encouraging caution before buying stocks and advising investors to do some selling if their portfolios contain a higher amount in equities than they usually do.</p>
        <p>''It's not a slam dunk that stocks are going down just because it's summer, but it does tend to be a below-average period,'' Mr. Swanson said. ''On the basis of fundamentals, we've become somewhat more cautious, but not overly bearish.''</p>
        <p>He has been bullish for four years, he said, but now the market has become ''roughly fairly valued,'' with more limited opportunity for further gains.</p>
        <p>''As stocks have done well, particularly over the last six months, it gets to the point where valuations are not as compelling as they once were,'' Mr. Swanson said.</p>
        <p>But Tobias Levkovich, chief United States equity strategist for Citigroup Investment Research, still finds much about the market that compels him. He mentioned a palpable anxiety among investors that a top is approaching, in contrast to the relaxed attitude that Mr. Swanson observed.</p>
        <p>If you want to justify a bearish view, Mr. Levkovich said, ''you need complacency in the stock market, and you don't have it. '' He continued, ''Valuations, earnings estimates, sentiment are not at any kind of stretched level, or even close.''</p>
        <p>As for a seasonal pattern, he acknowledged that performance tends to dip in the summer, but said the effect has been less robust in recent years.</p>
        <p>Investors who might be tempted to put off buying until the leaves begin to fall should resist the urge, Mr. Levkovich said. After a string of quarters with year-to-year earnings growth above 10 percent, average estimates for the second quarter have dipped to the low- to mid-single digits.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to get earnings releases in July,'' Mr. Levkovich said. ''I'm not saying they're going to beat the numbers, but it's not like we have this massive hurdle to get over.''</p>
        <p>He also pointed to the continued ravenous appetite for corporate acquisitions and the easy credit available to execute them. That could spell trouble in the somewhat distant future, he said, but it ought to prop up share prices into next year.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't put off purchases until the fall,'' he said. ''If you're an investor and the outlook is good over 6 to 12 months, do the next 3 months matter?''</p>
        <p>DATA WATCH -- The highlight of a sparse calendar of economic reports this week may be the snapshot on Friday of the nation's trade balance in April. A Bloomberg News poll of economists predicts a narrowing of the deficit to $63.5 billion from $63.9 billion in March.</p>
        <p>MARKET WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
