<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>That Household Name May Also Be a Value Stock</title>
    <meta content="03value" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/business/yourmoney/03value.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851910"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SUNDAY MONEY: INVESTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Citigroup Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Morgan, J P, Chase &amp; Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E1D81330F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1035" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>That Household Name May Also Be a Value Stock</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">That Household Name May Also Be a Value Stock</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By J. ALEX TARQUINIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tarquinio, J Alex</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE truth and beauty, the term ''value'' may be in the eye of the beholder. But experts say a few simple guideposts can help investors who are hunting for value stocks under most any market conditions.</p>
        <p>Compared with their peers, for example, value stocks should have a high dividend yield, low volatility and a low price-to-earnings ratio, said Sam Stovall, the chief investment strategist at Standard &amp; Poor's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Experts say a few simple guideposts can help investors who are hunting for value stocks under most any market conditions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE truth and beauty, the term ''value'' may be in the eye of the beholder. But experts say a few simple guideposts can help investors who are hunting for value stocks under most any market conditions.</p>
        <p>Compared with their peers, for example, value stocks should have a high dividend yield, low volatility and a low price-to-earnings ratio, said Sam Stovall, the chief investment strategist at Standard &amp; Poor's.</p>
        <p>Based on these criteria, Mr. Stovall and several other strategists say, there is value to be found now in a startling place: among some of the most famous blue chips in America. Mr. Stovall cites financial services giants like Citigroup, JPMorgan Chase and Bank of America.</p>
        <p>Others list household names like General Electric, Johnson &amp; Johnson and Procter &amp; Gamble. The general argument is that the recent run-up in the broader stock market has turned the shares of these mainline companies into relative bargains.</p>
        <p>For example, G.E., one of the great growth stocks of the 1990s, has a yield of 3 percent and a P/E ratio only a little higher than that of the overall S.&amp; P. 500-stock index. ''That looks like a value to me,'' said Brian Rogers, the manager of the T. Rowe Price Equity Income fund.</p>
        <p>While P/E is the most important factor in evaluating a stock for value, it isn't everything, Mr. Stovall said. Investors should put that number into context.</p>
        <p>He pointed out that many industries historically have sold at discounts to the broader stock market. Energy and mining stocks, for example, have usually had lower P/E's than the rest of the market because of the cyclical nature of their businesses.</p>
        <p>And even when an industry has a bigger-than-usual discount, Mr. Stovall said, there is sometimes a good reason for that. He pointed to the energy stocks in the S.&amp; P. 500 index, which are selling at discount of about 27 percent, compared with the average P/E for the index.</p>
        <p>Historically, the energy stocks have sold for about 16 percent less than the index. Just looking at the P/E ratios, ''you might think energy stocks are cheap now,'' Mr. Stovall said.</p>
        <p>But S.&amp; P. has a ''neutral'' rating on the energy industry because it expects earnings growth to come to a halt. The profits of the energy companies in the S.&amp; P. 500 grew 44 percent in 2005 and by 25 percent in 2006; this year, S.&amp; P. estimates that their earnings will actually fall, by 4 percent.</p>
        <p>At the moment, Mr. Stovall says, he thinks that a lot of the best value stocks are in financial services. He particularly favors insurance stocks -- whether the companies sell property and casualty insurance, or life and health insurance.</p>
        <p>Insurance stocks have been ''beaten up'' lately, he said, because of concerns about this year's hurricane season. ''That wasn't necessarily the case before Katrina,'' Mr. Stovall said.</p>
        <p>He said that this period, before the heart of the hurricane season, might be a good buying opportunity for insurance stocks. Allstate and Chubb are among S.&amp; P.'s top picks in the sector.</p>
        <p>In financial services, Mr. Stovall also recommended Citigroup, JPMorgan Chase and Bank of America. ''Those are all three large blue-chip companies that primarily pay shareholders through dividends, and some of them have yields that rival the 10-year note now,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rogers, the manager of T. Rowe Price Equity Income, also favors financial stocks now. In fact, JPMorgan Chase is the fund's second-largest holding.</p>
        <p>''Their profitability has improved a lot, and it is one of very few companies in America with a triple-A balance sheet,'' he said. The fund's top holdings also include Citigroup and the American International Group, the big insurer.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Rogers said that many traditional value stocks were now too pricey for him to hold in a value fund. He said the most extreme examples were electric utility stocks -- which were once considered the bedrock of many value funds. Such stocks now make up just 3 percent of the portfolio he manages.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, G.E. is the largest holding in the portfolio. When the domestic stock market last peaked earlier in the decade, many growth funds owned G.E. stock. Now it is increasingly viewed as a value pick. Michael Metz, the chief investment strategist of Oppenheimer &amp; Company said the main reason for this was that hedge funds and private equity funds were driving the recent run-up in domestic stocks, ''and they don't buy General Electric.''</p>
        <p>In fact, while the stock market has been climbing at home, individual American investors have been sending money overseas at a record pace.</p>
        <p>In the 12 months ended in April, Americans poured a net $128 billion into foreign stock funds but only $13.6 billion into domestic stock funds, according to AMG Data Services.</p>
        <p>Mr. Metz said he thought that this was one reason that larger stocks -- like those in the S.&amp; P. 500 -- still had relatively low P/E ratios compared with those of smaller stocks, or compared with their own historical averages.</p>
        <p>The S.&amp; P. 500 now has an average P/E of around 18, compared with a record high of 46.5 at the end of 2001. (The highest P/E came long after the stock market's peak, because earnings fell much faster than share prices.) In the last 20 years, the S.&amp; P. 500 index has had an average P/E ratio of 22.7.</p>
        <p>BUT Mr. Metz said that when American households turned back to domestic stocks, they would favor large well-known companies like Procter &amp; Gamble and Johnson &amp; Johnson.</p>
        <p>He recommended that investors who were looking for a quick, inexpensive way to hold such large stocks consider an exchange-traded fund like the iShares S.&amp; P. 100 Index fund, which owns the 100 largest stocks in the S.&amp; P. 500 index.</p>
        <p>Like many other strategists, Mr. Metz said that investing in companies like these was similar to buying foreign stocks, because so much of their profit comes from overseas. This is another way for investors to benefit from the relatively weak dollar and rapid economic growth in developing markets, he said.</p>
        <p>''If you buy General Electric or Johnson &amp; Johnson,'' he said, ''you almost don't need a foreign stock fund.''</p>
        <p>SUNDAY MONEY: INVESTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
