<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Temple Draws New Life From a Deal With a Caterer</title>
    <meta content="03templeliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03templeli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851737"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="RELIGION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bar Mitzvahs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Temple Israel (Lawrence, NY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Catering</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenbaum, Jay (Rabbi)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morrell, Scott</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Synagogues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Synagogues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E1D71430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="700" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Temple Draws New Life From a Deal With a Caterer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Temple Draws New Life From a Deal With a Caterer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <dateline>LAWRENCE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rabbi Jay Rosenbaum, spiritual leader of Temple Israel of Lawrence, Reform congregation, has taken steps to maintain congregation, which has dwindled from 1,500 families to 300; has reached agreement with Scott Morrell, owner of kosher caterer from Oyster Bay Cove for exclusive rights to weddings and bar and bat mitzvah parties at Temple Israel in exchange for covering $4.5 million cost of renovating temple's catering facilities; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN its heyday, Temple Israel of Lawrence, a Reform congregation whose home is a grand Spanish-style domed synagogue on four acres here, bustled with 1,500 families. But as more Orthodox Jews moved into the Five Towns over the last 15 to 20 years, membership dwindled to 300 families.</p>
        <p>Even so, Rabbi Jay Rosenbaum, the temple's spiritual leader, wanted to maintain the congregation, which is nearly 100 years old, as a bastion of Reform Judaism on the South Shore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawrence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN its heyday, Temple Israel of Lawrence, a Reform congregation whose home is a grand Spanish-style domed synagogue on four acres here, bustled with 1,500 families. But as more Orthodox Jews moved into the Five Towns over the last 15 to 20 years, membership dwindled to 300 families.</p>
        <p>Even so, Rabbi Jay Rosenbaum, the temple's spiritual leader, wanted to maintain the congregation, which is nearly 100 years old, as a bastion of Reform Judaism on the South Shore.</p>
        <p>''Many congregations faced with this reality take the position of holding on,'' said Rabbi Rosenbaum, 57. ''That is not good enough.''</p>
        <p>To keep expanding programs, Rabbi Rosenbaum said he has recently turned to a business relationship with the owner of a kosher caterer from Oyster Bay Cove.</p>
        <p>Scott Morrell, 42, the owner, is known for the 300 sumptuous wedding and bar or bat mitzvah parties he puts on each year at the Woodbury Jewish Center in Woodbury and at Temple Beth Torah in Melville, which cost as much as $100,000.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement with Rabbi Rosenbaum, Mr. Morrell has exclusive rights to put on such events at Temple Israel in exchange for covering the $4.5 million cost of renovating the temple's catering facilities.</p>
        <p>''We can count less and less on membership dues to sustain ourselves,'' said Rabbi Rosenbaum, who added that dues are $1,500 a family. ''We needed a partner who would not only generate the necessary funds but also represent what Temple Israel is, a history of style and elegance.''</p>
        <p>The renovation included new party areas and new kosher and glatt kosher kitchens. The temple put $1.5 million into installing new air-conditioning, changing the carpeting and sprucing up the sanctuary, which has pew seating for 1,400, ornate woodwork and stained glass, and is often the scene of weddings.</p>
        <p>More strictly Orthodox nuptials, which must be performed under the stars, can be held under a new skylight in the ballroom or outside in the garden.</p>
        <p>To accommodate parties from around the region, Mr. Morrell created a striking gallery, cocktail lounge and ballroom that mixes Old World opulence with contemporary accents: Venetian glass chandeliers, brushed stainless steel candelabras and infinity mirrors. Mr. Morrell calls it a destination facility.</p>
        <p>''People for a wedding or a bar or bat mitzvah will make the trip if something is special enough,'' he said.</p>
        <p>With a ballroom that accommodates 500 and a dance floor that can expand to 1,400 square feet, he said, he competes for bookings with places like the Pierre Hotel in Manhattan. So far he has done weddings for couples from Deal, N.J., and New City, N.Y., and said he had reservations for 90 parties through 2010. They cost from $130 to $275 a person.</p>
        <p>At the temple's annual dinner dance recently, 210 guests mingled in the cocktail lounge, which has silver leather cocktail chairs, oversize ottoman lounge seating and a 50-foot bar with an 18-foot fireplace surrounded by a glass-encased waterfall. At the smorgasbord stations, guests sampled sautéed duck and mushrooms in a puff pastry shell and braised beef and mashed potatoes served in martini glasses. At dinner in the ballroom, rack of lamb, citrus teriyaki tilapia and Cornish hen were served on $400-a-setting Bernardaud china with Christofle silverware.</p>
        <p>The congregation has also taken other initiatives, including renting its classrooms to the Jewish Community Center of the Five Towns for its nursery school and day care center. That enabled Orthodox Jews, who would not use a nursery school run by the Reform synagogue, to send children there, and now 80 percent of the 300 children who attend are Orthodox, Rabbi Rosenbaum said.</p>
        <p>Alan and Barbara Hartstein of Hewlett were married at Temple Israel 33 years ago, and Mr. Hartstein is a past president of the congregation. Ms. Hartstein said she hoped the new caterer and the J.C.C. would ''keep us vital and attract new members.''</p>
        <p>Inclusiveness is part of Rabbi Rosenbaum's strategy to keep Temple Israel humming. On May 16, for example, the Five Towns Jewish Council, an umbrella organization with an Orthodox majority, held a glatt kosher annual awards party at Temple Israel.</p>
        <p>''Anyone who has an affair here can join the spiritual with the spectacular,'' Rabbi Rosenbaum said.</p>
        <p>RELIGION E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
