<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Loosey-Goosey Voice On, Yeah, Public Radio</title>
    <meta content="03stua" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/arts/television/03stua.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851714"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Public Radio International</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Stuart</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salie, Faith</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Fair Game (Public Radio Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Public Radio International</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E2DB1430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="881" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Loosey-Goosey Voice On, Yeah, Public Radio</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Loosey-Goosey Voice on, Yeah, Public Radio</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART MILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Miller, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles Public Radio International host Faith Salie, whose new show Fair Game appears on 25 Public Radio International stations; innovative content and difficulties of scheduling show that is aimed at attracting younger listeners described; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BILL BRADLEY, the former senator, was on public radio earnestly discussing how politicians communicate with Americans when the interviewer, Faith Salie, asked, ''If Thomas Jefferson had a blog, what would he be writing about?''</p>
        <p>It wasn't H. L. Mencken, Groucho Marx or even Jon Stewart, but it also wasn't the stereotypical public radio host comment, delivered in that calm, almost solemn, authoritative voice. And that's the point: ''Fair Game'' is not seeking the same old (as in aging) listener, but a new generation of 25- to 44-year-olds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Faith Salie, the host of “Fair Game,” went from Oxford to Hollywood to public radio, where she stands out for her down-to-earth approach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BILL BRADLEY, the former senator, was on public radio earnestly discussing how politicians communicate with Americans when the interviewer, Faith Salie, asked, ''If Thomas Jefferson had a blog, what would he be writing about?''</p>
        <p>It wasn't H. L. Mencken, Groucho Marx or even Jon Stewart, but it also wasn't the stereotypical public radio host comment, delivered in that calm, almost solemn, authoritative voice. And that's the point: ''Fair Game'' is not seeking the same old (as in aging) listener, but a new generation of 25- to 44-year-olds.</p>
        <p>''There was evidence that highly educated 30-somethings were out there and not tuning in to public radio at all,'' said Melinda Ward, senior vice president of content for Public Radio International, which distributes the show. Another goal was to widen the audience at night, when public radio is weak. ''Fair Game,'' which made its debut in January, is on weeknights at 8 p.m. in New York (on WNYC-AM) and at varying times in two dozen other markets.</p>
        <p>The show's creator and executive producer, Kerrie Hillman, searched comedy clubs and scanned television and radio tapes before coming across Ms. Salie. ''Finding someone who was funny but also smart was really hard,'' she said, especially since she wanted to avoid smart-alecky cynicism.</p>
        <p>Ms. Salie, 36, has no journalism on her eclectic résumé: She graduated magna cum laude from Harvard, journeyed to Oxford as a Rhodes Scholar, then went to Hollywood to act, with credits ranging from ''Married With Children'' to ''Deep Space Nine'' (as a cyborg) and VH1's ''50 Most Awesomely Bad Songs.'' But her lack of interviewing experience didn't daunt Public Radio International, said Ms. Ward, who cited Ms. Salie's ''fearlessness about asking the unexpected question.'' Ms. Ward added, ''She gets traditionally dry people like scientists and academics laughing, which makes them seem more human.''</p>
        <p>''Fair Game'' opens with Ms. Salie and a ''Daily Show''-esque correspondent dissecting topical issues from quirky angles. There are also segments like ''Thank You, State Department,'' which revealed that a Filipino farmer trying to donate a kidney to a relative was denied entry to the United States out of concern that he might ''like America too much'' and stay.</p>
        <p>But the program's sensibility is ultimately defined more by the interviews and by Ms. Salie herself. The guests include newsmakers like Mr. Bradley, and journalists like the New Republic's Peter Beinart discussing Iraq. The most memorable interviews are offbeat or focused on the overlooked: a conversation with a documentary filmmaker about pinball machines, say, or with an expert on body organ shortages. And Ms. Salie is quick with a snappy riposte or a joke. (Commenting on the endless Congressional testimony about United States attorneys she proposed renaming the Fourth of July National Gonzales Hearing Midpoint Day.)</p>
        <p>What makes her stand out on public radio is her down-to-earth approach. She doesn't hold back on genuine (read nonjournalistic) gasps of ''Oh my God'' astonishment or delight.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to say, 'I'm a public radio personality so I must be unflappable,' '' said Ms. Salie. ''I'm just a proxy for the listener.''</p>
        <p>''Fair Game'' is making inroads in the highly traditional world of public radio, but slowly. A spokesman for WNYC, which bumped ''On Point'' for ''Fair Game,'' said the new show had improved ratings in its time slot, but wouldn't give specific numbers. At KERA in Dallas ''Fair Game'' replaced ''BBC World Service'' at 11 p.m. and has raised listenership by 58 percent. KERA initially heard grumbling from people who missed the BBC, said the station's program director, Jeff Ramirez, but now ''the main complaint is that people wish it were on earlier.''</p>
        <p>Getting on earlier -- or at all -- remains a major obstacle for ''Fair Game,'' as it does for any new public radio program (including a morning show that Public Radio International is developing aimed at the same demographic and one National Public Radio is testing too). In Baltimore, Andy Bienstock, program director at WYPR, said he had heard nothing but good things about ''Fair Game'' and ''would love to carry it, but I don't have room for it.''</p>
        <p>Public radio stations have limited scheduling flexibility, in part because many devote hours to classical music, but mainly because they're loath to drop established programs. ''Audiences contribute financially so they feel a sense of ownership,'' said Mark McDonald, program director of WAMU in Washington. ''Replacing an established show with something new and experimental is a very high risk.''</p>
        <p>The long-term solution may be high-definition radio, which allows stations to add digital channels. Atlanta's WABE is not currently carrying ''Fair Game,'' for example, but the station's new director, Kerry Swanson, said the show was at the top of his list to add to its current digital lineup.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Swanson said it would be at least two years before HD Radio had a national presence. In the meantime ''Fair Game'' continues evolving. Program directors say that its creators frequently consult them. ''In the beginning they were throwing everything they could on the air,'' Mr. Ramirez said. Now there are fewer segments and the show seems more tightly focused.</p>
        <p>Ms. Salie acknowledges that taking a comic's approach instead of a journalist's creates some tension. But, she said, ''I'm learning to let the audience hear the person and make their own decisions.''</p>
        <p>TELEVISION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
