<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books Worth a Spot On a Car Buff's Shelf</title>
    <meta content="03COBB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851814"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E3DB1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="313" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books Worth a Spot On a Car Buff's Shelf</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES G. COBB</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sunday Money  Speed! Lust! Madness! Death! A Hot Lap Around America With Nascar  By Jeff MacGregor. Photographs by Olya Evanitsky.  370 pages. HarperCollins, 2005.</p>
        <p>Early in 2002, as the wounds of 9/11 still throbbed, Jeff MacGregor packed a motor home and pointed it toward Florida. For 40 weeks and 48,000 miles he and his wife, Olya Evanitsky, crisscrossed the nation, caroming from raceway to raceway, immersing themselves in all things Nascar, the ruling body of a sport that ''distills to an essence America's obsession with speed and sex and death,'' he writes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sunday Money  Speed! Lust! Madness! Death! A Hot Lap Around America With Nascar  By Jeff MacGregor. Photographs by Olya Evanitsky.  370 pages. HarperCollins, 2005.</p>
        <p>Early in 2002, as the wounds of 9/11 still throbbed, Jeff MacGregor packed a motor home and pointed it toward Florida. For 40 weeks and 48,000 miles he and his wife, Olya Evanitsky, crisscrossed the nation, caroming from raceway to raceway, immersing themselves in all things Nascar, the ruling body of a sport that ''distills to an essence America's obsession with speed and sex and death,'' he writes.</p>
        <p>Along the way, the author roared around a track at Nascar fantasy camp, watched tough men weep for Dale Earnhardt and listened as Jeff Gordon, the California prodigy whom good ol' boys love to hate, was ''booed not just ecstatically, but spectacularly.''</p>
        <p>Wry, witty and clear-eyed, Mr. MacGregor recounts enough lore, and explodes enough myths, to keep racing followers in thrall. But his engaging book is also a primer for those who aren't among the 75 million who worship at the First Church of Nascar.</p>
        <p>While chasing the drivers who are chasing the championship, Mr. MacGregor explores the paradoxes. Though the sport is packaged in ''the appearance of solid Christian rectitude,'' the teams all cheat, young groupies called ''pit lizards'' tempt like the devil, and entire sections of fans can be as boorish as they are intoxicated.</p>
        <p>Once ''Sunday money'' was a few bucks of winnings to cover expenses; today there's a $2.4 billion television contract and untold millions in sponsorships. Nascar is big, big business. Mr. MacGregor analyzes the promoters' grandiose math and finds that the numbers don't quite compute. But Nascar's amazing ability to sell itself is part of the story, too. ''Maybe the reason that Nascar seems so spectacularly successful,'' he muses, ''is that Nascar keeps telling you it is.''</p>
        <p>JAMES G. COBB</p>
        <p>BOOKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
