<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Room With a View? No, but It's Cheaper</title>
    <meta content="03colnjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03colnj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851801"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="JERSEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coyne, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EFDC1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="862" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Room With a View? No, but It's Cheaper</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Room With a View? No, but It’s Cheaper</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Kevin Coyne</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Coyne, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>Hasbrouck Heights</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kevin Coyne Jersey column on transformation of northern New Jersey, especially Meadowlands, into place for foreign tourists to stay in summer while seeing sights of New York City; local hotels are cheaper than ones in city and hotel shuttle buses take travelers to local bus stops for trips to and from city; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON their first morning in America, at the start of a sightseeing odyssey that would traverse the breadth of a country most of them had never visited before, the 49 German tourists trickled out from the breakfast buffet at the Holiday Inn, blinking in the morning sun as the river of traffic on Route 17 rolled past.</p>
        <p>''Twenty-one days, all by bus,'' said Helga Lopolla, their tour director, standing in the parking lot and pointing the way toward the 2005 Setra TourCoach that had met them at the airport the day before and would carry them all the way to San Francisco. ''Today New York, then tomorrow we go to Washington, then Niagara Falls, Chicago, Mount Rushmore''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lots of people who want to visit New York without staying there have transformed northern New Jersey into a spare bedroom for Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON their first morning in America, at the start of a sightseeing odyssey that would traverse the breadth of a country most of them had never visited before, the 49 German tourists trickled out from the breakfast buffet at the Holiday Inn, blinking in the morning sun as the river of traffic on Route 17 rolled past.</p>
        <p>''Twenty-one days, all by bus,'' said Helga Lopolla, their tour director, standing in the parking lot and pointing the way toward the 2005 Setra TourCoach that had met them at the airport the day before and would carry them all the way to San Francisco. ''Today New York, then tomorrow we go to Washington, then Niagara Falls, Chicago, Mount Rushmore''</p>
        <p>First, though, Hasbrouck Heights. The Germans had booked two nights on a busy commercial stretch of this shady Bergen County borough not because of the view, but because of the price: less than $200 a night, perhaps half what they would pay in the place they really wanted to see, Manhattan, plus a nice big lot for their bus to park in.</p>
        <p>''This is their big day, right here,'' said Sergio Castillo, the driver, as the tourists filed onto the bus. He and Ms. Lopolla had just finished the same trip in reverse, from San Francisco to New York, with another group of Germans they had dropped off at the airport before picking up this new group. A strong euro has made American travel cheap this summer for European tourists. ''New York and the Grand Canyon, those are the highlights for them.''</p>
        <p>And here they all want to see the same thing. ''The Empire State Building,'' said Uda Janowski, 50, of Cologne, using English that everyone on the bus seemed to know, no matter how limited their facility with the language.</p>
        <p>Lots of people who want to see the Empire State Building have made the same calculation in recent years -- that you can visit New York without staying there -- and in the process have helped transform northern New Jersey, especially the Meadowlands, into a spare bedroom for Manhattan. The Meadowlands alone has 5,200 hotel rooms, the riverfront cities have another 3,000, and many of them are filled, especially during the summer travel season, with this relatively new species of guest: the commuter tourist.</p>
        <p>''It's really dictated by New York City,'' where hotel prices are at a peak, said Sally Altman, the director of sales and marketing at the Holiday Inn and a 20-year veteran of the Meadowlands hotel business. ''If New York's rates are high and their occupancy's high, then New Jersey gets more of the pie.''</p>
        <p>By 8:15, the bus was full, Mr. Castillo was nudging into the southbound flow of Route 17, and gazes were turning left through the smoked-glass windows toward the spire of the Empire State Building, which poked up in the distant haze. At the hotel the lobby still bustled: business travelers, pilots from neighboring Teterboro Airport and more German tourists.</p>
        <p>''It's a horde of Germans come to America,'' said Gabriele Christ, 47, a vacationing tour guide from Berlin who had arrived the previous day. She sat on a bench beneath the entrance portico, waiting for the shuttle van the hotel runs to the bus stop, six blocks away. ''I really enjoy coming back to New Jersey,'' she said, already sounding like a veteran commuter defending the decision to decamp across the river. ''After a while you need some quiet.''</p>
        <p>When the van came, a young married couple, also from Germany, Birgit and Lin Thiele, joined her in it. The bus ride into Manhattan, as all commuters know, varies with traffic. ''The shortest was half an hour,'' said Ms. Thiele, 31, who works in human resources. They had arrived five days earlier from their home city of Paderborn, and were leaving the next day for San Francisco.</p>
        <p>''The longest, one hour,'' said Mr. Thiele, 33, a bank clerk.</p>
        <p>The van climbed Williams Avenue, past the small brick apartment buildings, the tidy capes and Dutch colonials, the small lush lawns. ''In New York you have very big skyscrapers and traffic and trouble, and so you come here to Hasbrouck Heights,'' Mr. Thiele said. ''It's a little, lovely, I don't know, village? And you can see some of the American people, how they do their flats. That's a quite good thing to do, to experience an American way of life.''</p>
        <p>The van dropped them at the busy corner of Boulevard and Williams, where New Jersey Transit Route 163 stops on its way to Port Authority, and they were soon boarding beside some late commuters. As they had ridden in each morning, with the spiky crescendo of the skyline looming ahead, they couldn't believe that so many riders stayed buried in newspapers or books or sleep, ignoring a view they had crossed the ocean to see.</p>
        <p>''We say, 'Ohhhhh, it's the Empire State Building!' '' Ms. Thiele said. ''It's normal to them, but to us, it's amazing.''</p>
        <p>And as the bus carried them toward the city again, they kept their eyes fixed up and out, drinking in the sights that everybody else had already seen enough times to stop noticing.</p>
        <p>JERSEY E-mail: jersey@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: jersey@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
