<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>VISUALS</title>
    <meta content="Heller.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/books/review/Heller-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851616"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Summer Reading"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Heller, Steven</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EFD61630F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2183" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>VISUALS</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Visuals</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Steven Heller</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Heller, Steven</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The term ''small press'' usually refers to independent publishers with limited means and large ambitions. For the creators of an old literary genre, however, the phrase described the machinery on which very, very tiny books were produced. Bound miniature books were common in medieval and Renaissance times as illuminated manuscripts, and in the 18th and 19th centuries as everything from alphabet primers to novels; present-day artists have also used them as a medium. Although some may look like dollhouse props, these miniatures are by no means toys. Rather, they are meant to be read and collected. In MINIATURE BOOKS: 4,000 Years of Tiny Treasures (Abrams/Grolier Club, $40), Anne C. Bromer and Julian I. Edison chronicle this legacy of petite functional volumes, including some of the quirkiest -- like ''Thoughts From the Cork'' (1981), with a cover fashioned from a 1ï'-by-1-inch wine cork.</p>
        <p>Yet most are not so gimmicky. For instance, Achille J. St. Onge, a printer and designer, created stunning gold-leaf-embossed bindings -- near-perfect miniaturizations of larger leather-bound volumes -- for Dwight Eisenhower's and John F. Kennedy's Inaugural Addresses, 2 3/4 by 115/16 inches and 2 3/4 by 1¡ inches. But one of my favorites, Charles Hardy Meigs's ''Rubaiyat of Omar Khayyam'' (1900), printed in its entirety at 10 by 9 millimeters, raises the question, Why go to all this trouble?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bound miniature books were common in medieval and Renaissance times as illuminated manuscripts, and in the 18th and 19th centuries as everything from alphabet primers to novels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The term ''small press'' usually refers to independent publishers with limited means and large ambitions. For the creators of an old literary genre, however, the phrase described the machinery on which very, very tiny books were produced. Bound miniature books were common in medieval and Renaissance times as illuminated manuscripts, and in the 18th and 19th centuries as everything from alphabet primers to novels; present-day artists have also used them as a medium. Although some may look like dollhouse props, these miniatures are by no means toys. Rather, they are meant to be read and collected. In MINIATURE BOOKS: 4,000 Years of Tiny Treasures (Abrams/Grolier Club, $40), Anne C. Bromer and Julian I. Edison chronicle this legacy of petite functional volumes, including some of the quirkiest -- like ''Thoughts From the Cork'' (1981), with a cover fashioned from a 1ï'-by-1-inch wine cork.</p>
        <p>Yet most are not so gimmicky. For instance, Achille J. St. Onge, a printer and designer, created stunning gold-leaf-embossed bindings -- near-perfect miniaturizations of larger leather-bound volumes -- for Dwight Eisenhower's and John F. Kennedy's Inaugural Addresses, 2 3/4 by 115/16 inches and 2 3/4 by 1¡ inches. But one of my favorites, Charles Hardy Meigs's ''Rubaiyat of Omar Khayyam'' (1900), printed in its entirety at 10 by 9 millimeters, raises the question, Why go to all this trouble?</p>
        <p>One reason: ''It had been the custom since the 15th century to train young printing apprentices in the art of miniature-book production,'' the authors write. The point was to teach the basic skills in the smallest size possible ''in order to avoid sloppiness when working with larger books.'' Another reason: Some almanachs minuscules were made as ''ornaments of gaiety and beauty,'' a kind of jewelry presented by publishers as gifts to their clients. Then there were those created for propaganda: the Nazis sought to glorify Hitler in an annual series of miniature books called ''The FÃ1/4hrer Makes History''; during the 1960s, millions of copies of Mao's ''Little Red Book'' were published in China.</p>
        <p>Oddly, it is sometimes hard to discern whether the examples seen in this gilt-edged coffee-table book are in fact tiny. A few were photographed being held, but most are so convincingly designed and illustrated that they look like books 10 times their size.</p>
        <p>Of all the visual artifacts created for mass consumption, postcards are the most common yet varied -- they can be banal or extraordinary, sometimes both. Postcards are souvenirs designed cheaply as records of travel, yet over time they have become documents of moments and places in history. The first pictureless postcard was produced in Austria in 1869, and by the end of the century picture cards had been introduced, setting off a rash of collecting. These days there is no dearth of books devoted to the many genres and subgenres -- and just when you think you've seen them all, a new variety surfaces. In EXOTIC POSTCARDS: The Lure of Distant Lands (Thames &amp; Hudson, $35), compiled by the photographer Alan Beukers, rare sepia and hand-colored portraits from a century ago -- of people in native costume from Asia, Oceania, the Americas, Arabia and Africa -- provide a window on once-alien worlds. ''Each such picture is an excitement, an invitation to the exotic, and seems to repeat in its strangeness that this is a world that awaits further discovery,'' Paul Theroux writes in his introduction.</p>
        <p>These postcards were the National Geographic and Discovery Channel of their day -- at least the voyeuristic parts. Some innocently revealed differences in dress, while other pictures -- of a shrunken head from Ecuador, or of an imprisoned Asian man standing expressionless in a tight wooden cage -- were meant to shock. One can only wonder whether the individual subjects of these cards, who are either looking straight into the camera or rigidly posing while looking off to the side, had any idea what they were doing or why (and whether they were paid). This was at the height of European colonialism, in the years before World War I, and the images represented subjugated lands and peoples. ''The paradox in the portraits of the warriors here is that though they are fierce-looking they are obviously conquerable,'' Theroux says. Today, even in exotic lands, people wear the same logo-saturated athletic gear. And while these postcards are reminders of a time when brand names had not yet colonized the third world, the era depicted also signaled the wave of cultural exploitation by the West.</p>
        <p>In the '70s and '80s, graffiti emerged as a radical urban art form that littered subway cars, storefront gates, and other public and private surfaces with explosive hieroglyphs. In a short time, what began as small symbols made with ''subway markers'' evolved into huge, colorful, bulbous cartoon ''tags'' (signatures of the artists' nicknames, along with those of their crews of spray painters). While for many graffiti was (and still is) an urban blight, for others the tags were an admirable sign of rebellion. What's more, it took considerable guts to paint them on such grand scales while trying to avoid police detection. Some taggers became street legends; a few eventually became brand names too. One of the more pervasive tags in the East Village and Los Angeles was Claw (writ large with a three-taloned ''pussycat'' claw logo).</p>
        <p>It was the mark of one of the few women on the graffiti scene, Claw Money, a Fashion Institute of Technology dropout who, after leaving the world of illegal ''bombing'' (another graffiti term), turned to fashion styling for Korn, Ice-T and Guns N' Roses, as well as designing apparel for Nike, Adidas and Sector watches. In BOMBSHELL: The Life and Crimes of Claw Money (Miss Rosen Editions/PowerHouse Books, $35), a scrapbook of photographs and graphics, Claw's handiwork is splashed willy-nilly across glossy pages, punctuated by brief celebratory essays. Her work is what you'd expect of graffiti -- garish colors with lots of spray-painted sparkle and sheen -- but it also shows ingenuity. Nonetheless, in recent years many books showcasing graffiti artists have adhered to the same basic format: monotonous pages of messy collages and photos of the artist. Claw deserves a better presentation.</p>
        <p>Every popular art form fosters a reaction to it, and in the introduction to STICKER CITY: Paper Graffiti Art (Thames &amp; Hudson, paper, $24.95), the author, Claudia Walde, writes: ''For some 40 years city streets have been home to the modern graffiti movement, but the new century has witnessed a fresh creative explosion. Walls, phone booths, guttering, traffic signage -- the full range of surfaces ... is now adorned with hand-painted or -crafted stickers and posters.'' What she calls ''adhesive art'' -- comic illustrations, typographic logos, commercial trademark parodies and other goofy graphic icons -- has actually been around since the '80s, when skateboarders and club ravers adorned their clothes, backpacks, notebooks and school lockers with band stickers galore. In the '90s, Shepard Fairey, one of the pioneers of this guerrilla art, glued copies of his famous ''Obey the Giant'' sticker (featuring a high-contrast portrait of the wrestling star Andre the Giant) to countless public surfaces. Today he runs a thriving business selling stickers, T-shirts and posters. The idea of making multiple small and medium-size stickers, rather than one mammoth graffiti tag, appealed to the adhesive artists, many of whom were trained as graphic designers.</p>
        <p>Most of them don't sign theirwork but are still known in the sticker universe by the designs they've created and plastered on lampposts, phone booths and bathroom stalls. Their images are not necessarily meant to convey specific messages, but instead to draw attention to the artist. New Yorkers are doubtless familiar with the designers known as Thundercut, for the way they've affixed their own walking figures to pedestrian crossing signals. NoLogo of Dresden routinely sticks pixelated ogres and angels on empty walls, and Blek le Rat of Paris specializes in high-contrast, life-size stickers of soldiers and businessmen. Walde, a graffiti artist herself, notes that while adhesive art is on the rise, it's also moving off the street and into galleries. Eventually, a new art will rise in reaction against this one too.</p>
        <p>Only time will tell whether sticker art will have an esteemed place in the history of visual culture, but enough years have passed since the heyday of Communism to guarantee the status of the Soviet poster. Maria Lafont's SOVIET POSTERS: The Sergo Grigorian Collection (Prestel, paper, $25) presents the good, the bad and the ugly art used to sell Lenin, Stalin and all manner of Soviet propaganda. While the subject has been covered before, Grigorian (who lives in Moscow and London) has amassed a large number of fascinating lesser-known works, from avant-garde Constructivism to turgid Social Realism celebrating Stalin, ''the leader of the Soviet people.'' He also has a few halfhearted modern approaches that preceded glasnost (which rejected Social Realism). Organized according to specific historical periods, the collection reveals how Social Realism was used to promote a variety of virtues, including courtesy in restaurants and abstinence from liquor. Despite actual innovation immediately after the Bolshevik Revolution, the sanctioned Soviet graphics are limited and redundant -- the smiling faces of children and the heroically posed soldiers and workers reduce decades of poster art to mere kitsch.</p>
        <p>''Is painting a major art and illustration a minor one?'' Philippe Starck addresses that query in the preface to ARRESTING DESIGN: Illustration in the Marketplace (Ãditions Scala, $95), by Alain Lachartre with FranÃ</p>
        <p>oise Aveline. ''Like an abscess, this thorny question hurts when you touch it but, if left untreated, it can gnaw away at our enfeebled minds.'' This strained but pointed analogy attacks those who argue that by virtue of their client-driven motivations, illustrators are not authentic artists. The commercial illustrators exhibited in this fairly bulky, though handsome, art book -- most were hired to promote high-end clients like Chanel, Givenchy, Monoprix, Telefunken, Renault and Piper-Heidsieck -- have injected their imagination, style and panache into their commissions. And many of the expressive and impressionistic comics and illustrations by Ted Benoit, Jean-Philippe Delhomme, Isabelle Dervaux, Pierre Le-Tan, Lorenzo Mattotti, Jacques Tardi and Philippe Weisbecker, among others, could also stand on their own as integral artworks. Some of the advertising illustrations, which routinely undergo more creative interference from art directors and clients than editorial work does, look as though a committee dragged them through the gantlet. But this book demonstrates that style is not the only attribute, and that at least some advertisers, preferring the intimacy of drawing and painting, hire artists as much for their minds as for their hands.</p>
        <p>From the 1910s through the '50s, drawing and painting -- not photography -- was the dominant popular commercial art form. It was the era of Norman Rockwell, The Saturday Evening Post and Collier's, when illustrators produced a majority of advertisements and magazine art, and many were considered celebrities. One of the notables in the '20s and '30s, Tony Sarg, though all but forgotten today, was a puppeteer, a cartoonist, and the author and illustrator of more than a dozen children's books; he also developed the helium character balloons for the Macy's Thanksgiving Day Parade. One of his most ingenious books, UP &amp; DOWN NEW YORK (Universe, $19.95), has just been issued as a facsimile that is even more striking than the original 1926 edition.</p>
        <p>In this delightful homage to New York, all of Sarg's colored pen-and-ink renderings are detailed aerial views -- some from on high, others just a few stories up -- of bustling landmarks, including Grand Central Terminal, the Sixth Avenue el at 33rd Street, the 23rd Street ferry slip, Times Square and the Flatiron Building at 23rd Street. (The term ''23 skidoo'' may well have been coined because police officers would chase away men waiting for the gusts that lifted women's skirts at that intersection.) In a somewhat comic style, Sarg's packed pictures -- they have the density of ''Where's Waldo?'' -- capture the movement of the city and serve as snapshots of a bygone time that, paradoxically, is not too different from today.</p>
        <p>What Sarg accomplished through drawing, the Viennese-born Paul T. Frankl did through interior design, creating a ''skyscraper'' style of furniture that celebrated New York. His most emblematic piece, featured on the cover of Christopher Long's PAUL T. FRANKL AND MODERN AMERICAN DESIGN (Yale University, $50), is the skyscraper bookcase (circa 1927). Its lacquered wood, with silver-leaf detailing, evokes the machine age. The bookcase was his model for other limited-edition, architecturally influenced dressing tables, chairs and desks, designed and sold at Frankl Galleries in New York. He was also an advocate for modernism as both a designer and an author. Although Frankl's more visible works have been reproduced in books about the Streamline Moderne and Art Deco styles, this seems to be the first biography. It is richly illustrated with pictures of many pieces now in private collections, and with documentary photos of his lesser-known (but mass-produced) modern furniture and interiors, made after he moved to California in the mid-1930s. Long, an associate professor of architectural history and theory at the University of Texas at Austin, writes, ''After years of struggling to promote the cause of modernism, he emerged ... as its foremost spokesman.'' This book finally gives Paul Frankl his due.</p>
        <p>Summer Reading</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
