<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Time's Guardian</title>
    <meta content="03cloc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/thecity/03cloc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070617T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851895"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="URBAN TACTICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Watches and Clocks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Clock Tower Building (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schneider, Marvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giddens, Elizabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Watches and Clocks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Watches and Clocks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E3D81330F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1171" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Time's Guardian</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Time’s Guardian</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH GIDDENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Giddens, Elizabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Marvin Schneider, 67, who has been New York City's official clock master since 1992; describes tour of Clock Tower Building and what Schneider does to keep its clock running; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORKERS look to the time the way farmers look to the weather. Many have their own idiosyncratic maps of public street clocks they rely on, scurrying to work or late for appointments, but few would imagine that so many of those clocks run thanks to a man named Marvin Schneider.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schneider, who has been the city's official clock master since 1992, is a short and round 67-year-old with smiling eyes, a salt-and-pepper mustache and a grandfatherly manner. He wears a soft navy cardigan, a corduroy newsboy cap, and glasses that sometimes reflect the giant clocks he cares for, creating the startling illusion that he has clocks for eyes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As New York’s clock master, Marvin Schneider rules a quaint and majestic kingdom of gears and dials, bells and gongs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORKERS look to the time the way farmers look to the weather. Many have their own idiosyncratic maps of public street clocks they rely on, scurrying to work or late for appointments, but few would imagine that so many of those clocks run thanks to a man named Marvin Schneider.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schneider, who has been the city's official clock master since 1992, is a short and round 67-year-old with smiling eyes, a salt-and-pepper mustache and a grandfatherly manner. He wears a soft navy cardigan, a corduroy newsboy cap, and glasses that sometimes reflect the giant clocks he cares for, creating the startling illusion that he has clocks for eyes.</p>
        <p>One morning early last month, Mr. Schneider trundled up to the 1898 Clock Tower Building, an official city landmark, a few blocks north of City Hall at Broadway and Leonard Street, to wind its clock, as he has done nearly every week for 27 years.</p>
        <p>The clock tower, which was designed by McKim, Mead &amp; White to crown their neo-Renaissance wedding cake of a building, is a neat emblem of the mix of extravagance and public-mindedness that characterized the Gilded Age.</p>
        <p>Tucked into the building's 12 floors are municipal courts, parole officer headquarters and, until a few years ago, P.S. 1's Clocktower Gallery. During the gallery's 30-year sojourn in the upper stories, artists had their way with the clock: One man rigged the lifeless hands to a motor that turned them at a dizzying, mocking speed, and the artist Gordon Matta-Clark once suspended himself from the clock face wearing a black raincoat, black tights and white gloves to perform an elaborate, leisurely toilette with the aid of a garden hose.</p>
        <p>Post-9/11 security concerns forced the artists and their audience out of the building, however, and the tower is now strictly off limits to visitors. But on this rare occasion, Mr. Schneider had agreed to perform his duties in the company of 20 observers, the happy few who had landed spots in an ''Access Restricted'' tour sponsored by the Lower Manhattan Cultural Council.</p>
        <p>The rickety steps of the two-story spiral staircase that snakes up to the tower, and the drips and smells and feel of a place long unaccustomed to visitors, all imparted a sense of adventure. But the clock tower itself was nothing short of sublime, and there were gasps as the guests approached the landing.</p>
        <p>Four massive clock faces, composed of frosted glass and cast-iron Roman numerals, stare out over the four directions of Manhattan's grid. From the center of each face a delicate rod runs to the center of the room, where a confounding jumble of gears, spindles, levers and paddles perches improbably atop four cabriolet legs.</p>
        <p>With more than a dozen gears, ranging in diameter from a half inch to two feet, this is the city's largest mechanical clock, and it is attached to a hammer that hourly strikes a 5,000-pound brass bell. The clock keeps time in a manner appropriate to the pace of the era that spawned it -- that is, it's off about 10 seconds a month, a lag unthinkable for today's electronic devices that register milliseconds with the self-importance of a nuclear countdown.</p>
        <p>It takes a moment to read the giant hands' reversed version of the time, a moment during which you might notice that the four is represented as IIII instead of IV, and another moment to remember that you are still in the 21st century.</p>
        <p>Although the machine dutifully, ceaselessly counts off the moments, time itself seems to have stopped inside the tower. An impossibly elegant oil can cranes its swanlike neck over leaded glass bottles from the 1930s. A bucket holds an odd assortment of old clock hands. Down the spiral stairway, the pendulum's giant shadow sweeps a slow, stately path across a crumbling brick wall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schneider stood in the soft light suffused through the clock faces. His love for the tower was palpable and contagious, and the city behind him appealingly indistinct. Lulled by the clock's mesmerizing motion and its hypnotic ticking, you might imagine that a very different New York lay beyond the frosted faces.</p>
        <p>''If you stand here and look out on the city, you can imagine you're in an entirely different century,'' Mr. Schneider said. ''If you want to do a little time travel, this is the place to come.''</p>
        <p>AMONG the dozen public clocks that fall within his purview -- clocks in City Hall, the old courthouse in Harlem, the old Sun Building, and the borough halls of Brooklyn and Staten Island -- this is his favorite, partly because it's so exquisite and partly because it was his first. For years in the late 1970s, Mr. Schneider used to pass the clock on his way to his job in the city's Human Resources Administration, and it irked him that it wasn't running.</p>
        <p>''As a city employee, I took it personally,'' he said. ''A broken clock on a city building reflected poorly on the city itself.''</p>
        <p>So in 1979, with no experience to speak of, he persuaded a reluctant administration to let him and a colleague named Eric Reiner have a go at repairing it by assuring the administration that Mr. Reiner's father was a clockmaker. They neglected to mention that the man had been dead for 20 years.</p>
        <p>Like much else in the city in the '70s, the clock tower was in egregious disrepair, having passed through two decades of neglect.</p>
        <p>''There was a foot of garbage up here,'' Mr. Schneider recalled. ''A lot of the parts were missing; junkies had sold them. The glass faces were broken, which exposed the clock to all kinds of weather. Even the pigeons found the place repugnant.''</p>
        <p>After a year of trial-and-error tinkering, performed on a volunteer basis on lunches and weekends, the men had the clock running, and Mr. Schneider soon began eyeing other prominent timepieces. At first it was an amusing hobby, but eventually the Dinkins administration recognized his dedication and named him the city's official clock master, a post long vacant. Nearly every Wednesday morning since, Mr. Schneider has returned to the Clock Tower Building to raise the two 800-pound weights whose slow descent powers the delicate, intricate gears.</p>
        <p>''When this was built, American clocks were the best in the world,'' said Mr. Schneider. ''Even the Swiss copied our designs.''</p>
        <p>The day of the tour, he interrupted his history lesson to warn that the clock was about to strike. A second later the bell sounded its formidable reproof: 10 gongs, followed by an almost cartoonish whirring and clicking of the century-old gears.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Schneider replaced three of the 80 bulbs that illuminate the faces at night, his solitary duties seemed to bear an uncanny resemblance to those of a lighthouse keeper: his is an almost daily ritual of climbing, oiling and polishing, all with the goal of maintaining a vital public signal -- and a warning -- for unseen millions.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes,'' he said, ''I'll see people start to run when they hear the 9 o'clock bells.''</p>
        <p>URBAN TACTICS Elizabeth Giddens is a former senior editor of Harper's Magazine.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 17, 2007, Sunday  An article on June 3 about the city's clock master, Marvin Schneider, inaccurately described a 5,000-pound bell that rings hourly in the Clock Tower Building. The bell is bronze, not brass.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 17, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on June 3 about the city's clock master, Marvin Schneider, inaccurately described a 5,000-pound bell that rings hourly in the Clock Tower Building. The bell is bronze, not brass.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Elizabeth Giddens is a former senior editor of Harper's Magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
