<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Demand for School Chiefs Pushes Salaries Up</title>
    <meta content="03mainliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03mainli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851736"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="EDUCATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fringe Benefits</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">School Administration and Community Role</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fessenden, Ford</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">School Administration and Community Role</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fringe Benefits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D71430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1024" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Demand for School Chiefs Pushes Salaries Up</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Demand for School Chiefs Pushes Salaries Up</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FORD FESSENDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fessenden, Ford</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Figures released by New York State show that salaries for school superintendents rose at rate well above inflation on Long Island last year; median pay package for top job in local school districts is $248,250, increase of 5.3 percent from 2006-7; school board officials attribute increase to difficulty of finding suitable candidates; chart; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SALARIES for school superintendents rose at a rate well above inflation on Long Island last year, according to new state figures, as school board officials say it is increasingly difficult to find the leadership needed to meet the high expectations of suburban parents and homeowners.</p>
        <p>In Bay Shore, for example, Superintendent Evelyn Blose Holman negotiated a new contract in 2006 under which she received a 15 percent increase in salary and benefits in the first year, and an 8 percent increase in 2007-8. Including 15 days of vacation she can opt to take in cash, her pay and benefits will be worth slightly more than $355,000 next year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>SALARIES for school superintendents rose at a rate well above inflation on Long Island last year, according to new state figures, as school board officials say it is increasingly difficult to find the leadership needed to meet the high expectations of suburban parents and homeowners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SALARIES for school superintendents rose at a rate well above inflation on Long Island last year, according to new state figures, as school board officials say it is increasingly difficult to find the leadership needed to meet the high expectations of suburban parents and homeowners.</p>
        <p>In Bay Shore, for example, Superintendent Evelyn Blose Holman negotiated a new contract in 2006 under which she received a 15 percent increase in salary and benefits in the first year, and an 8 percent increase in 2007-8. Including 15 days of vacation she can opt to take in cash, her pay and benefits will be worth slightly more than $355,000 next year.</p>
        <p>School board members in Bay Shore, which ranks in the bottom third on Long Island in average income of residents per pupil, say they were happy to provide it.</p>
        <p>''Knowing what's out there and who you can hire, we know we have an excellent superintendent, and we have kept her for another five years,'' said Gregory Nardone, the school board president.</p>
        <p>For 2007-8, the median pay package for the top job in the Island's 124 districts is $248,250, including salary and benefits, up 5.3 percent from 2006-7, according to data the districts reported to the state. Seventeen superintendents will make more than $300,000 in total compensation next year; 11 did so in 2006-7.</p>
        <p>Carole G. Hankin, the Syosset superintendent, continues to be the highest-paid public school executive in the state, with salary and benefits worth nearly $440,000.</p>
        <p>Superintendents' pay has been rising about 5 or 6 percent a year for the last three years, mirroring other costs in school districts, which have also been advancing more sharply than the inflation rate of 3 percent.</p>
        <p>The median pay package for assistant superintendents rose 6.1 percent, to $190,750. Eighty-five assistant superintendents on Long Island make more than $200,000, up from 50 in 2006. And teacher salaries go up 4 percent to 6 percent a year, district officials say.</p>
        <p>At a time when residents are complaining about high property taxes, and the state is sending millions of new dollars to suburban school districts, Long Island districts now pay about $30 million, an increase of 16 percent since 2004-5, for the superintendents who oversee the education of 469,000 students.</p>
        <p>School board officials say they see little alternative to the continued advance of salaries but also say they have little difficulty justifying the cost to voters. ''Any place you live, people will complain,'' Mr. Nardone said.</p>
        <p>''People here are either for her or against her,'' he said, referring to Dr. Holman.</p>
        <p>The Bay Shore school board gave Dr. Holman a salary increase of 15 percent in 2006, to $240,000. This year, she is to get a raise of about 8 percent, according to the district's assistant superintendent for business, Maureen Dutcher. Dr. Holman also has the right to cash in 15 days of vacation, worth an additional $17,591.</p>
        <p>With an annuity, and insurance and pension payments, Dr. Holman's $355,315 pay package will be the fifth highest on Long Island, and in the state, next year. In 2005, her total pay of $279,777 was 11th highest among the Island's superintendents.</p>
        <p>School board members say residents may express alarm at the compensation levels, yet they also demand that their school districts maintain reputations for high quality and achievement.</p>
        <p>''The problem is you can't get superintendents -- nobody wants the job anymore, so you have to pay the freight,'' said Allenby R. Lyson, the school board president in Oceanside. ''Think about it. Half of the value of your house is based on your school district. You lose your good district reputation, you lose your house value. We're aware of that.''</p>
        <p>State law requires school districts to report the salaries of their top administrators, and any principals who make more than $110,000. Most districts comply, but some do not, and state officials say they have no authority to compel them.</p>
        <p>In some districts where there appeared to be a large increase in pay, school board members said they were actually disclosing for the first time perks or benefits that superintendents had already been getting. A law passed in the wake of the embezzlement scandal in the Roslyn district in 2004 required the state comptroller to audit all districts by 2010, and some boards are bending over backward to disclose payments to school leaders.</p>
        <p>In Jericho the board reported for the first time the value of payments made on behalf of Superintendent Henry L. Grishman to the teacher retirement system, which showed that his compensation package next year, $378,039, was 14 percent higher than it appeared to be this year.</p>
        <p>''We had not been reporting that, and we have auditors coming,'' said Barbara Krieger, the school board president. ''It is our effort to be more transparent.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Grishman is the fourth highest paid superintendent on Long Island, up from seventh last year.</p>
        <p>A few districts replaced superintendents and reported lower compensation packages. In Plainedge, where an assistant superintendent, Christine P'Simer, will replace the outgoing superintendent, John A. Richman, next year, the salary and benefits package will drop 14 percent. She will make more than $245,000 in pay and benefits in her first year.</p>
        <p>''We don't think superintendents are paid too much,'' said Patricia Zinke, the Plainedge board president. ''The pool of experienced people is not big enough, and it's a 24/7 job.''</p>
        <p>The salaries of Long Island school administrators are not out of line with other school costs. At 1.85 percent of total budgets, on average, the Island's administrative costs are below the median for the state, which was 2 percent, according to state calculations from 2004. But other costs on the Island are also high.</p>
        <p>Census figures released last week show that Long Island districts rank at the very top among more than 10,000 school districts across the nation in spending per pupil, except for a few in sparsely populated areas that must hire more teachers to reach students. Among districts with more than 250 students, 13 of the top 24 in spending per pupil were on Long Island or in Westchester, with the rest in Alaska and Wyoming, according to the census.</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
