<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Dialogue Between Plays And the World</title>
    <meta content="03bella" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/theater/theaterspecial/03bella.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851706"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER: THE TONYS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bellafante, Ginia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Tony Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/August Wilson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Wilson, August</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hare, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bogosian, Eric</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E3DB1430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1133" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Dialogue Between Plays And the World</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Dialogue Between Plays and the World</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINIA BELLAFANTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bellafante, Ginia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ginia Bellafante article on 2006-7 Broadway season says several plays dealt with issues of consequence, some using prism of 1960's to add resonance; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT seems inevitable that every awards season eventually becomes an occasion to lament the state of the medium receiving the toast. We decry the pandering. We rage against the casting of movie stars onstage; we scream at the thought of a ''Mission: Impossible VIII''; we persist in equating reality television with the end of reason. On Broadway, the critics moan, there are too few compelling straight plays and too many dopey musical revivals, a complaint leveled not out of some stuffy commitment to archaic aesthetics but because the countervailing evidence (lately at least) has remained so slim.</p>
        <p>Really, how can we understand an art form that accommodates ''The Pirate Queen''?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Among the postures we might adopt toward the current season, carping that the theater ignored issues of consequence to the grim national mood should not be one of them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT seems inevitable that every awards season eventually becomes an occasion to lament the state of the medium receiving the toast. We decry the pandering. We rage against the casting of movie stars onstage; we scream at the thought of a ''Mission: Impossible VIII''; we persist in equating reality television with the end of reason. On Broadway, the critics moan, there are too few compelling straight plays and too many dopey musical revivals, a complaint leveled not out of some stuffy commitment to archaic aesthetics but because the countervailing evidence (lately at least) has remained so slim.</p>
        <p>Really, how can we understand an art form that accommodates ''The Pirate Queen''?</p>
        <p>Yet among the many musty postures we might adopt toward the current season, carping that the theater ignored issues of consequence to the grim national mood simply should not be one of them. From the farthest reaches of downtown to the houses of Broadway there were plays rooted in the horrors of military life (''The Brig,'' ''Dying City,'' ''Journey's End,'' ''Armed and Naked in America''), the controversy of illegal detention (''Arrivals'') and the questions of America's role in global diplomacy (''The Vertical Hour''). Not all of these offerings were dramatically accomplished. Some were dull, some reductive, some too aggressive in the pronouncement of their ideologies. But they bespoke a level of worldly engagement that has long seemed absent from the theater's mission.</p>
        <p>Particularly striking, even beyond that, is the number of plays that made their claims to relevance -- grappling with issues like war, sex, race and free speech -- through the prism of the 1960s, and not always nostalgically. ( ''Frost/Nixon,'' though a clear product of Bush-era disenchantment, is the greatest triumph of Nixon revisionism the culture has thus far produced.)</p>
        <p>David Hare's ''Vertical Hour,'' a didactic exercise in topicality, did not leave you wistful for the old days. Watching it felt like bearing witness to a live CliffsNotes version of the early work of Francis Fukuyama. As its gimmick the play sets up its debate about the origins of the Iraq war along generational lines, pitting a 60-ish, Vietnam-era anti-interventionist (a doctor portrayed by Bill Nighy) against a young, neoconservative academic (Julianne Moore) wedded to the idea that it is the West's duty to promote democracy around the world.</p>
        <p>''The Vertical Hour'' is not a pro-war play, but it is not an antiwar play either. The principal object of its indictment is a moral lethargy, perceived as a tranquilizer to which the '60s left us addicted, numbing our impulses to public and private responsibility. Ms. Moore's character -- and, by virtue of that, her position -- is pure. Mr. Nighy's isn't. Having slept around for decades and ruined his family, the doctor is there to convince us what a mess the '60s mind-set was and, essentially, how little it can be trusted.</p>
        <p>''What did you believe?'' his adversary asks him.</p>
        <p>He responds: ''Oh. The more people you sleep with, the more you learn. The liberation of Eros. All right, it's no longer a fashionable point of view.''</p>
        <p>Stephen Sondheim's ''Company,'' revived on Broadway this season, indicates, remarkably enough, that such a view was possibly beginning to fall out of fashion as early as 1970, the year the show made its debut. ''Company'' isn't an overtly political musical, but it embodies a deep skepticism about the sexual libertinism of the period. In the current production the spare stage is set with clear cubes, as if to further suggest the hollow life of the central character, Bobby, a bachelor whose coupled friends, in all their malaise, are still more fulfilled than he is.</p>
        <p>''Company'' isn't about the inadequacies of marriage as much as it's about the emptiness of free sex. It celebrates the quotidian difficulties of sharing your life with another person and feels like a session with an expensive couples' therapist, speaking to urbane tastes and conservative values at the same time. Theoretically at least there's no reason the current version, which opened in Cincinnati, shouldn't play as well in Atlanta as it has in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>It is hard to know whether that claim can be made about ''Radio Golf,'' the August Wilson play that advances what is arguably an outmoded model of racial politics. ''Radio Golf,'' set in 1997, eight years before Mr. Wilson died, serves as the coda to his 10-part epic about African-American life and betrays a deep nostalgia for the ethos of the late 1960s. In the play Mr. Wilson regressively casts his lot with the identitarians of that period, who saw assimilation as the great potential undoing of black culture.</p>
        <p>The story revolves around a yuppie mayoral candidate's refusal to allow the demolition of an old house belonging to an elderly relative, one that stands in the way of a huge urban renewal project involving the construction of a Whole Foods. Prosperity is the enemy here, Tiger Woods a symbol of evil. History and soul are the virtues to be prized above all.</p>
        <p>''The masses want leaders who are educated as well as trustworthy,'' the African-American social critic Albert Murray wrote in the late 1960s, disparaging that popular point of view. They don't see middle-class blacks as ''tokens,'' he argued; ''they regard them as people who got the breaks -- or were able to make the most of the breaks.'' The rise of Barack Obama makes ''Radio Golf'' interesting if off-putting theater because Mr. Wilson's perspective, in effect, demands that we greet the arrival of people who have made the most of their breaks as a cause for concern rather than victory.</p>
        <p>And how should we greet the arrival -- or rather the return -- of Barry Champlain, the central figure in Eric Bogosian's 1987 play ''Talk Radio,'' brought to Broadway for the first time this season? Champlain is the host of a call-in show who will say anything on the air (though not perhaps as it has now been defined by Don Imus). He hates complacency and lax standards, fat people and lazy people. During his first days in radio in the early 1970s, we are told, he would give out the home phone numbers of every F.B.I. agent in Ohio. What is clear now is that Champlain exists in some sense to show us just how easily the anti-authoritarian values of the '60s morphed into an assault on the tyranny of political correctness. Champlain simply became a radical of a different kind, his transition a history lesson in the leap many liberals made to the libertarian side.</p>
        <p>It isn't surprising, of course, that the impact and themes of the '60s would have resonated with playwrights and producers in recent years. You can blame Broadway for recycling ''Legally Blonde,'' but you can't, at the moment at least, blame it for failing to try make sense of the world beyond it.</p>
        <p>THEATER: THE TONYS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
