<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Silicon Valley, the Crash Seems Like Just Yesterday</title>
    <meta content="03rivlin" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/weekinreview/03rivlin.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851946"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="IDEAS &amp; TRENDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Venture Capital</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Entrepreneurship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entrepreneurship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Venture Capital</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Silicon Valley (Calif)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Kedrosky, Paul</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Saffo, Paul</person>
        <person class="online_producer">von Liebig, William J</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E3DF1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Silicon Valley, the Crash Seems Like Just Yesterday</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Silicon Valley, the Crash Seems Like Just Yesterday</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GARY RIVLIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GRANDPA lived through the Depression, and life thereafter was indelibly shaped by haunting memories of soup kitchens and hobos. Similarly, the digerati of Silicon Valley endured the 1990s dot-com bubble, and since then have lived with the psychic shock of its ignoble end.</p>
        <p>The average valley entrepreneur tends to spot bubbles everywhere, much the way granddad feared financial ruin every time a grandchild carelessly scraped leftover food into the trash.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A once cocksure region is displaying a deep-seated insecurity  raising the question of whether there’s really a bubble about to pop or whether Silicon Valley is just suffering from post-traumatic stress.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GRANDPA lived through the Depression, and life thereafter was indelibly shaped by haunting memories of soup kitchens and hobos. Similarly, the digerati of Silicon Valley endured the 1990s dot-com bubble, and since then have lived with the psychic shock of its ignoble end.</p>
        <p>The average valley entrepreneur tends to spot bubbles everywhere, much the way granddad feared financial ruin every time a grandchild carelessly scraped leftover food into the trash.</p>
        <p>''There's such a heightened sense of bubble awareness in Silicon Valley that people confuse any expression of enthusiasm for a bubble,'' said Paul Kedrosky, the executive director of the William J. von Liebig Center for Entrepreneurism and Technology Advancement at the University of California, San Diego.</p>
        <p>''It's like people in the valley had bombs dropped on their heads six or seven years ago,'' he said, ''and now they're so hyperaware that if they even hear what they think is a lit fuse, they're scurrying for the exits, yelling, 'Bubble, bubble, bubble.' ''</p>
        <p>Yes, Silicon Valley is back, and one might think that its residents would see that as a good thing. The venture-capital money is once again flowing, and the entrepreneurial spirit is now so robust that the joke of the moment is that people can't find anyone to work at their start-ups because everyone is too busy working on their own. But a once cocksure region is also displaying a deep-seated insecurity -- raising the question of whether there's really a bubble about to pop or whether Silicon Valley is just suffering from post-traumatic stress.</p>
        <p>The latest display of self-flagellation in Silicon Valley was sparked by a jeremiad posted May 22 by Michael Arrington, who since 2005 has edited a popular blog, TechCrunch. He titled his lament, ''Silicon Valley Could Use a Downturn Right About Now,'' and over the next week readers added more than 200 postings. Most agreed with Mr. Arrington, who wrote that the ''madness'' started about a year ago.</p>
        <p>''It's just like the old days again, and Silicon Valley is no longer any fun,'' he wrote. ''It may be time for some of us to leave for a while and watch the craziness from the outside.''</p>
        <p>Many children of the boom often romanticize the early days of Silicon Valley as a period of pure, nonentrepreneurial geekdom. But it might be time for Mr. Arrington and those who agree with him to embrace the effervescent nature of Silicon Valley, a place that Paul Saffo, a technology consultant who saw the rise of the P.C., is inclined to describe as a ''cappuccino economy.''</p>
        <p>''We always have lots of little bubbles in Silicon Valley,'' Mr. Saffo said. ''It's like the froth on cappuccino. A little froth is a very good thing. A lot of froth, especially if you mix in a lot of inexperienced people, that's a bad thing.''</p>
        <p>That's exactly what happened in the second half of the 1990s, and once again that corner of the valley universe is abuzz about the preposterous prices some are paying to own a small slice of a start-up that has no clear plan for making money.</p>
        <p>A certain business sector suddenly becomes the rage -- green energy, say, or social networking -- and venture capitalists, eager to say they have a ''play'' in a particular ''space,'' stumble over one another to finance every copycat company. And even if few Internet companies are going public nowadays, the striving entrepreneur can find inspiration in companies like YouTube, the video-sharing Web site, which had yet to celebrate its first anniversary (or its first profits) when Google bought it last fall for $1.65 billion.</p>
        <p>Yet old hands say these are hardly the ''spray and play'' days of the late 1990s. Venture capitalists are investing a small fraction of the money they committed during the boom. They collectively invested $62.7 billion in technology start-ups in 2000, according to VentureOne, a financial research firm, compared with $14.3 billion last year and $3.1 billion in the first three months of 2007.</p>
        <p>''So far we haven't seen any of these loonier deals like during the bubble,'' said Scott C. Dettmer, a founding partner of Gunderson Dettmer, a Silicon Valley law firm, who serves as a kind of consigliere to entrepreneurs and venture capitalists.</p>
        <p>Another difference: Those seeking little else but gold are not descending on Silicon Valley in great numbers as they did in the late 1990s.</p>
        <p>''The same carpetbaggers who came to Silicon Valley to hit it rich last time are now looking for jobs with hedge funds,'' said Mark J. Pincus, an entrepreneur working on his fifth start-up.</p>
        <p>Talk of a new bubble has burbled off and on for the last couple of years. Lips were flapping, for instance, two years ago when Accel Partners, a Palo Alto-based venture firm, paid $12.2 million for a stake of about 15 percent in Facebook, a social-networking site.</p>
        <p>''I was one of the people saying that deal was crazy,'' said David Sze, a partner at Greylock, a venture capital firm. But the following year, Mr. Sze convinced his partners to kick in a large portion of the $25 million Facebook raised in a second round of venture financing.</p>
        <p>''Everyone who was giving me a hard time about that investment has come back to me and said, 'Wow, we were wrong,' '' Mr. Sze said.</p>
        <p>Yet whether a venture capitalist makes a particular foolish investment is mostly beside the point. The pros know that failure and the boom-bust cycle are an inherent part of tech innovation. It's half-baked companies going public that can affect 401(k)'s and the wider economy.</p>
        <p>''Bubbles become bad only when bystanders get involved,'' Mr. Saffo said. ''The problem with the bubble in the late 1990s is that everyone's grandmother got involved, and that was bad because it made the bubble too big, and it made the price of failure too high.''</p>
        <p>IDEAS &amp; TRENDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
