<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Concentrated Talent</title>
    <meta content="03RpitchersCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851750"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Porcello, Rick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harvey, Matt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finley, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEFDE1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1005" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Concentrated Talent</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finley, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Rick Porcello, 2007 Gatorade National Baseball Player of the Year from Seton Hall Preparatory School in West Orange, NJ, and Matt Harvey, senior from Fitch Senior High School in Groton, Conn, pitchers who are top two prospects for Major League Baseball's draft this season; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN most years, Rick Porcello, the 2007 Gatorade National Baseball Player of the Year, would have no equal as a high school player. He is a big, right-handed pitcher, a senior at Seton Hall Preparatory School in West Orange, N.J., who throws faster than most pros and whose route to the major leagues could be a short one.</p>
        <p>It is rare for a high school player from the Northeast to be thought of so highly. But this season, an unusual one for high school baseball talent in the region, there may be someone even better than Porcello.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN most years, Rick Porcello, the 2007 Gatorade National Baseball Player of the Year, would have no equal as a high school player. He is a big, right-handed pitcher, a senior at Seton Hall Preparatory School in West Orange, N.J., who throws faster than most pros and whose route to the major leagues could be a short one.</p>
        <p>It is rare for a high school player from the Northeast to be thought of so highly. But this season, an unusual one for high school baseball talent in the region, there may be someone even better than Porcello.</p>
        <p>Matt Harvey is a 6-foot-4-inch senior from Fitch Senior High School in Groton, Conn. He throws a 96-mile-an-hour fastball and could also be on a fast track to the major leagues.</p>
        <p>When Major League Baseball's first-year player draft begins Thursday, with the 30 major league teams choosing amateur players from North America and Puerto Rico, the first two high school players selected -- in the first of 50 rounds -- could be Harvey and Porcello. Their reward could be multimillion-dollar signing bonuses.</p>
        <p>Baseball America, a magazine that rates high school and college players, ranks Harvey as the best high school prospect in the nation, with Porcello right behind. Others view them just the opposite.</p>
        <p>''In my estimation, Rick Porcello is the top high school pitching prospect in the country, and Matt Harvey is right behind him at No. 2,'' said Jerry Ford, the president and national director of Perfect Game USA, the nation's largest independent scouting service. ''It's a weird situation, having the two top pitching prospects in the country from the Northeast.''</p>
        <p>The top high school stars typically come from warmer climates, where they can play year-round and enter the draft with polished skills that are found less often in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>No high school player from the Northeast has been chosen with the No. 1 pick since the draft began in 1965, and few are even taken in the first round. Only one player from the area -- Billy Rowell, of Pennsauken, N.J. -- was selected in the first round last year, going ninth over all to the Baltimore Orioles and signing for $2.1 million.</p>
        <p>Porcello has been forecast as high as the second pick in this draft, by the Kansas City Royals. But after Harvey, only one player from the region, Porcello's teammate Evan Danieli, is projected to be drafted in the top few rounds this week.</p>
        <p>''Every kid has dreams about playing in big leagues and being in Yankee Stadium,'' Porcello said. ''I'm no different than any other kid. I dream about all that, winning the World Series, striking out a batter in the bottom of the ninth. I just don't think about it literally right now because I know I have a lot of work to do to get there.''</p>
        <p>Entering the weekend, Porcello, who is from Chester, N.J., had won 18 games and lost one in his career at Seton Hall Prep. He was 8-0 this season and had struck out 96 batters in 56 innings. He is 6 feet 5 inches tall, and his fastball has been clocked in the high 90 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>''His ceiling is tremendously high,'' said his coach, Mike Sheppard Jr. ''Not only is he a very gifted athlete and pitcher, but he's a tremendous young man with great makeup. Without trying to put too much pressure on him, he can't miss.''</p>
        <p>Harvey, who lives in Mystic, has a 6-1 record this season and 106 strikeouts in 51 innings.</p>
        <p>''Matt has always been the type of kid who goes out and gets what he wants,'' said his father, Ed, who is also his high school coach. ''Even when he was 2, he'd ask for a toy, we'd say no, and he wouldn't give it up. He's turned that into a positive. He knows what he wants, he goes out and prepares, and he gets it done. That's the way he's always been with baseball.''</p>
        <p>After Porcello and Harvey, the area's top high school prospect is the 6-foot-8-inch Danieli, who is also a pitcher. He is 32nd on Baseball America's list of the top 100 high school prospects.</p>
        <p>There are no top 100-type prospects from Long Island or Westchester, scouts say. The best player in Westchester could be pitcher Ken Ferrer, who is from Pleasantville High School and is committed to Elon University in North Carolina. Eric Stampfl, a pitcher who is from Dix Hills and attends St. John the Baptist High School, is among Long Island's best high school prospects.</p>
        <p>For those two, making the major leagues is a long shot, as it is for most drafted players. Even for Mr. Porcello and Harvey, there are no guarantees, but they would start their professional careers with high expectations.</p>
        <p>Scott Boras, the high-profile player agent who is known for negotiating big contracts for clients, is advising Porcello and Harvey. The top high school draftee last year, Clayton Kershaw of Dallas, received a $2.3 million signing bonus after being drafted seventh over all by the Los Angeles Dodgers.</p>
        <p>Porcello and Harvey may do better. Both have also signed letters of intent to attend the University of North Carolina, but committing to a college is not unusual for top high school players. They can use their commitments as leverage if they are not happy with the offer of the major league team that drafts them.</p>
        <p>''I'm just living for the moment,'' Harvey said. ''That way it's easier to know exactly what you are doing. I'm still trying to be a high school student and help our team win. It can be a little overwhelming.''</p>
        <p>Harvey signed with North Carolina in part because Porcello decided to go there. They have played on all-star teams together and have become friends who talk regularly.</p>
        <p>Which one is better? Harvey said the subject never comes up. For now, they say, there is no rivalry, no one player trying to surpass the other. That can wait, maybe when they are opponents in the major leagues.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
