<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Dallas, New Prosecutor Means an End to the Old Ways</title>
    <meta content="03dallas" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/us/03dallas.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851985"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dna (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">District Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dallas County (Tex)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, Ralph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Watkins, Craig (Dist Atty)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Dallas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">District Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DNA (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">District Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Dallas (Tex)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EFDB1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1055" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Dallas, New Prosecutor Means an End to the Old Ways</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Dallas, New Prosecutor Means an End to the Old Ways</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RALPH BLUMENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blumenthal, Ralph</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thirteen prisoners since 2001 have been found through DNA evidence to have been wrongfully convicted in Dallas County after serving total of 185 years behind bars; more DNA exonerations could be in store under review of more than 400 other cases ordered by County Dist Atty Craig Watkins, Texas's first black district attorney; his photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Craig Watkins calls himself a different kind of prosecutor.</p>
        <p>''I lock them up if they're guilty,'' said Mr. Watkins, the new Dallas County district attorney.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Craig Watkins, the new Dallas County district attorney, calls himself a different kind of prosecutor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Craig Watkins calls himself a different kind of prosecutor.</p>
        <p>''I lock them up if they're guilty,'' said Mr. Watkins, the new Dallas County district attorney.</p>
        <p>That distinction has sometimes been lost here in the nation's highest-crime big city. Since 2001, 13 prisoners were found through DNA evidence to have been wrongfully convicted in Dallas County after serving a total of 185 years behind bars. Only Illinois and New York, besides Texas, have had more convictions overturned by genetic testing than Dallas County, a fact attributable in part to evidence retained to assure reconviction in the event of a successful appeal.</p>
        <p>Now, many more DNA exonerations could be in store under a review of more than 400 other cases ordered by Mr. Watkins, 39, who made history last November by eking out a second-try victory in a Democratic landslide to become Texas's first black district attorney.</p>
        <p>''You know who to thank for that,'' he said, alluding to President Bush. In addition to the upset by Mr. Watkins, a 6-foot-5 defense lawyer who had never prosecuted a case, Democrats won every contested countywide race, and all 42 judgeships at stake.</p>
        <p>''The sky didn't fall, did it?'' he joked to a group of Texas law professors and volunteers meeting in neighboring Fort Worth on May 25 to begin the innocence review.</p>
        <p>Some might think it had. It was not so long ago that Mr. Watkins would not have been picked for a Dallas County jury, much less be the person picking one.</p>
        <p>''Do not take Jews, Negroes, Dagos, Mexicans or members of any minority race on a jury, no matter how rich or well educated,'' a treatise from 1963 advised prosecutors here. The directive, unearthed by The Dallas Morning News in 1986, was cited by the United States Supreme Court that year in a celebrated decision barring peremptory challenges to remove black jurors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Watkins said he was not looking back. ''I don't like to disparage the dead,'' he said of the longtime district attorney and most recent Democrat to hold the job, Henry Wade, who reigned from 1951 to 1986. ''Jim Crow was the law of the day, and he enforced it.''</p>
        <p>Now, he said he was focusing on programs to educate prisoners and provide drug treatment in custody.</p>
        <p>''I encounter resistance every day,'' Mr. Watkins said. ''It's part of my job. It doesn't make any difference. Let them be on the wrong side of history.'' But, he said, his critics ''are just waiting for me to make a mistake.''</p>
        <p>The dean of Texas's district attorneys and a fellow Democrat, Ronnie Earle of Travis County, praised Mr. Watkins as an innovator. ''He brings a contemporary perspective to the ancient problem of how to make punishment a positive result for the community,'' Mr. Earle said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Watkins acknowledged the skeptics, some of whom, he said, painted him as soft on crime, citing comments like one he made to the public television station KERA in April that for those wrongfully convicted, ''we will be the first to raise the white flag and get you out.''</p>
        <p>In what Mr. Watkins denounced as a scheme to '''set up the D.A.,'' a police captain in suburban DeSoto recently taped a conversation that the captain said showed favoritism by Mr. Watkins toward an officer accused of a misdemeanor whose lawyer had worked on his transition team. Mr. Watkins denied the accusation and has barred the captain from testifying in court cases.</p>
        <p>He has bristled at criticism -- ''the rules are different for us,'' he said of blacks -- and can turn distant at times. Between questions as he was being driven back from Fort Worth, Mr. Watkins put his head on the seat back and napped.</p>
        <p>Toby Shook, former chief of the felony trial bureau and a 23-year veteran prosecutor who lost to Mr. Watkins in November, said no one could protest the freeing of the wrongfully convicted ''as long as you do it under the guidance of law and facts.''</p>
        <p>After taking office, Mr. Watkins wasted little time before making changes in what he called the conviction-at-all-costs mentality, supposedly for the victims' sake.</p>
        <p>''A person wrongfully convicted is a victim, and the person who did it is still out there,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Watkins said he had ended the practice of destroying death penalty files after a conviction, arguing that the files were vital in establishing or dismissing later claims of innocence.</p>
        <p>To install his own loyal team, he fired 10 senior prosecutors of the 234 assistant district attorneys, and 7 others resigned, including Mr. Shook.</p>
        <p>He tightened procedures in eyewitness identifications of criminal suspects, instituting a double-blind system requiring that lineups or photo displays be administered by prosecutors with no knowledge of the case so that they could not influence the outcome.</p>
        <p>And he announced a partnership with the Innocence Project of Texas, a consortium of law clinics at five universities, to examine many other claims of wrongful conviction under a 2001 Texas law granting prisoners the right to petition for DNA testing.</p>
        <p>With nearly $360,000 appropriated by the Dallas County commissioners, Mr. Watkins set up a division under a special assistant, Michael Ware, an adjunct professor at Texas Wesleyan School of Law in Fort Worth, where Mr. Watkins was in the first graduating class in 1994. Mr. Ware will head a team of 20 student volunteers to work with the Innocence Project.</p>
        <p>Of 35 cases studied since 2001, 13 ended with exonerations based on DNA tests. The latest prisoner freed, James Curtis Giles, had been convicted of raping a Dallas woman with two other men in 1983 and served 10 years before being released on parole. It turned out that the police had confused him with another man, James Earl Giles, who lived across the street from the victim and was implicated in other evidence not turned over to the defense.</p>
        <p>''We're getting ready to make history, not only in Dallas County and Texas but the rest of the country,'' said Jeff Blackburn of the West Texas Innocence Project at Texas Tech University School of Law in Lubbock. ''We have what no other county or state has -- a D.A. determined that innocent people don't get convicted.''</p>
        <p>''You don't have to be bloodthirsty to be elected,'' Mr. Blackburn said. ''People are not as crazy as prosecutors and judges think.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
