<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Fuss. No Cleanup. It's Called a Dinner Party.</title>
    <meta content="03dineweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03dinewe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851766"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Q Authentic Barbeque Restaurant and Bar (Port Chester, NY)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Backals (Scarsdale, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Blue Hill at Stone Barns (Pocantico Hills, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gabriel, Alice</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Blue Hill at Stone Barns</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E4DD1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1008" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Fuss. No Cleanup. It's Called a Dinner Party.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Fuss. No Cleanup. It’s Called a Dinner Party.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALICE GABRIEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gabriel, Alice</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alice Gabriel reviews three restaurants in Westchester that have private rooms that can be reserved for dinner parties; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOME people are meant to entertain; when it comes to party giving, they have a grace and confidence that elude many of us. In wondrous shows of multitasking, these hosts converse easily with guests while putting last-minute touches on dinner in their bright, stainless-steel kitchens. Jewel-like appetizers circulate along with flutes of Champagne. Even as it unfolds, the party is a happy memory, and glory accrues to the partygiver.</p>
        <p>Others -- and we know who we are -- cringe at the thought of entertaining. The party hour approaches, and families cower as once reasonable loved ones metamorphose into Napoleons or harridans. Something always scorches. Nothing is quite as wonderful as imagined.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you would rather mingle with than cater to your guests, holding a restaurant dinner party is an honorable way out.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOME people are meant to entertain; when it comes to party giving, they have a grace and confidence that elude many of us. In wondrous shows of multitasking, these hosts converse easily with guests while putting last-minute touches on dinner in their bright, stainless-steel kitchens. Jewel-like appetizers circulate along with flutes of Champagne. Even as it unfolds, the party is a happy memory, and glory accrues to the partygiver.</p>
        <p>Others -- and we know who we are -- cringe at the thought of entertaining. The party hour approaches, and families cower as once reasonable loved ones metamorphose into Napoleons or harridans. Something always scorches. Nothing is quite as wonderful as imagined.</p>
        <p>If you would rather mingle with than cater to your guests, holding a restaurant dinner party is an honorable way out. A restaurant will press the linens, cook and serve the meal, fill the glasses and -- here's the best part -- clean up afterward. For many challenged hosts, the expense is well worth it.</p>
        <p>Most restaurants will require a contract for a private party, usually with a prearranged menu, an agreed upon date and time, a credit card number and a signature. Many will ask for a guaranteed minimum number of guests, or charge a fixed fee for a private room. (If the minimum is 20, and you want to invite only 12, the restaurant will most likely upgrade the food and beverage selection to compensate for the extra expense.) To avoid surprises, know what is included in the price and get it in writing. Make an appointment to see the space, and sit down with a manager: Are flowers provided? Is the house wine potable? Consider using a restaurant where you are a regular; familiarity with the staff and the food will alleviate some of the jitters that come with orchestrating a party.</p>
        <p>With a fairly intimate dinner party for 10 to 12 guests in mind, I chose three Westchester restaurants that range from budget to luxury. Each has real personality, noteworthy food and outstanding service.</p>
        <p>Q Authentic Barbeque Restaurant and Bar, Port Chester</p>
        <p>The orange awning and clean-cut good looks of the main room signal fun, and Q delivers plenty. Its simple formula -- great wood-smoked barbecue -- would work especially well for a gathering of longtime friends or extended family. (Q is also an ideal place to have a Sweet 16 party.) Guests can wear jeans and T-shirts; Q ''gimme'' hats make coveted party favors. The upstairs private room at Q looks a little like a skybox at a sporting event; a chest-high glass partition allows sweeping views of the action below while your group stays well above the fray. Food is set out family style, with one or two servers dedicated to your party; dinner could include chicken wings, a big salad, two barbecued meats (ribs, chicken, brisket, pulled pork or sausage), corn bread and banana pudding. Cool down with pitchers of iced tea, beer, or the house lemonade, or treat your guests to one of the specialty bourbons stocked at the nifty split-rail-fence bar.</p>
        <p>Backals, Scarsdale</p>
        <p>A relative newcomer, Backals has the poise and versatility of a private-party mecca. The lofty main room, rimmed with pretty balconies, looks like a tiered opera house. One private balcony with a deep-set leaded-glass window allows you and your guests to have your cake and eat it, too: the door leading to the space can be shut, but you share in the bonhomie of the restaurant at large. A second, third-level balcony has cushy banquettes and lower decibels. Even greater seclusion can be found in the cheerful Members Room adorned with charming murals of cigar-smoking, cocktail-swilling monkeys. Your guests can choose from trios of appetizers, entrees and desserts from the regular menu, or you can tailor the menu. One possible lineup: a half Maine lobster with lemon mayonnaise, grilled branzino with picholine olives and crème brûlée.</p>
        <p>Blue Hill at Stone Barns, Pocantico Hills</p>
        <p>Nothing can match Blue Hill at Stone Barns for its cloistered beauty and inspired food. The airy private rooms are impeccable, with rough-grained wood floors and floor-to-ceiling glass through which diners behold pastoral swaths of tilled fields and thick woods. Here, farm-to-table cuisine is not a cliché but a high art. On surrounding acres, the raw ingredients are in the making: cows tug at grass, pigs root for acorns, hens scratch for seeds, and young leeks thrive in straight rows. The polish and sophistication of the restaurant -- no detail is left unturned -- are in wonderful contrast with the agricultural enterprise outside.</p>
        <p>One line in the kitchen is devoted to private parties. A sample menu for late spring: Maine crab salad with cucumber, rhubarb and tapioca; wild striped bass with mushrooms, spinach and Meyer lemon sauce; loin of beef with cracked rice, ramps, asparagus and poached rhubarb with rhubarb sorbet, soft goat cheese and local honey. You and your guests can eat at one long table, like farmhands, or cluster at smaller rounds. Prices are not for the faint of heart.</p>
        <p>Three That Can Make Entertaining Easier</p>
        <p>These three restaurants have private rooms and typically require reservations. Prices are per person, excluding tax and gratuity.</p>
        <p>Q Authentic Barbeque Restaurant and Bar  112 North Main Street, Port Chester, (914) 933-7427,  www.qrestaurantbar.com.</p>
        <p>The private room can be reserved for dinner Monday to Thursday and Sunday and for lunch Friday and Saturday. A typical full-course menu without drinks is about $27.</p>
        <p>Backals  2 Weaver Street, Scarsdale, (914) 722-1522,  www.backals.com.</p>
        <p>Balcony spaces can be reserved for any night of the week; the Members Room is available for fixed-price dinner parties Sunday to Thursday, with higher prices on Friday and Saturday. A three-course dinner with nonalcoholic beverage is $75; $95 with a selection of four house wines.</p>
        <p>Blue Hill at Stone Barns  630 Bedford Road, Pocantico Hills, (914) 366-9600,  www.bluehillstonebarns.com.</p>
        <p>Private rooms are available for dinner parties Wednesday to Sunday. A four-course dinner with open bar and wines is $170.</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
