<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Detroit Can Rebound</title>
    <meta content="03backpage" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EED81330F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="458" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Detroit Can Rebound</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In his commentary on the American auto industry of recent decades, Ben Stein is on target in saying that Detroit often failed to build cars that people wanted to buy (''The Dream That Once Was Detroit,'' Everybody's Business, May 27).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In his commentary on the American auto industry of recent decades, Ben Stein is on target in saying that Detroit often failed to build cars that people wanted to buy (''The Dream That Once Was Detroit,'' Everybody's Business, May 27).</p>
        <p>The column was also correct that the root of Detroit's problems goes beyond the conventional explanation that American automakers' ''legacy costs" for retiree health and pension benefits undermine the companies' ability to compete effectively. That explanation overlooks some very simple arithmetic: the cost per vehicle would decline if the companies made and sold more vehicles!</p>
        <p>When and if American manufacturers are willing to take greater risks in the design and engineering of their products, they will again provide the public with, in the column's words, ''the stuff of which dreams were made.''</p>
        <p>Robert I. Adler  Port Washington, N.Y., May 27</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Yes, we can still buy quality cars conceived with insightful market research about what the American consumer wants, designed by talented American designers and engineers, and built by productive American workers, on American soil, in efficient American plants run on sound American management techniques. Does it really matter if they have a Japanese nameplate?</p>
        <p>Zino Vogiatzis  Timonium, Md., May 28</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Ben Stein may still dream of the 1962 Corvette he once owned; my wife and I dream of the Thunderbird of the '50s. When time and reasonable success made it possible for us to buy a T-Bird, it had grown into a bulky two-door, four-seat coupe. We bought it anyway. A T-Bird was, after all, our dream car.</p>
        <p>Earlier, my dream of automotive splendor was the 1932 Cord. I never rode in it, never dared touch it, but the Cord driven by the father of a classmate was proof that even in the Great Depression things of wonder could be created by American workers and bought by a very lucky few.</p>
        <p>Wes Pedersen  Chevy Chase, Md., May 27</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As a young man I also had a dream of owning a Corvette; I couldn't wait until I could get my driver's license to gain the freedom that getting your wheels brings. And as a child I eagerly awaited the annual style changes in cars because the looks were distinct; now cars are indistinguishable from one another.</p>
        <p>Detroit should refocus on the style and design that gave its cars appeal. I thought the rerun of the Thunderbird was a good start. Imagine the rollout of an updated '57 Chevy or a '66 Olds Toronado? I never got the Corvette but did get a '68 Olds 4-4-2. I wish I had kept it.</p>
        <p>Steven A. Ludsin  East Hampton, N.Y., May 27</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
