<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Some, Calling Cautions for Debris Can Seem to Be Mere Rubbish</title>
    <meta content="03nascar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/sports/othersports/03nascar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851996"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Stewart, Tony</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gordon, Jeff</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CEEDB1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Some, Calling Cautions for Debris Can Seem to Be Mere Rubbish</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Question of Debris as Drivers Voice Doubts</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <dateline>DOVER, Del., June 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stock cars are wondrous contraptions, built to run for hundreds of miles on hot summer afternoons, often while banging into other stock cars. But they are, after all, still pieces of machinery. They can, and often do, fall apart.</p>
        <p>Many times, they break on racetracks, though not always in ways apparent to the thousands of fans in the stands and the millions more at home. Nascar has called 31 debris cautions in the 12 Nextel Cup races this season, 14 in the last 100 laps of those races.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nascar has called 31 debris cautions in 12 Nextel Cup races this season, 14 in the last 100 laps of these races.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stock cars are wondrous contraptions, built to run for hundreds of miles on hot summer afternoons, often while banging into other stock cars. But they are, after all, still pieces of machinery. They can, and often do, fall apart.</p>
        <p>Many times, they break on racetracks, though not always in ways apparent to the thousands of fans in the stands and the millions more at home. Nascar has called 31 debris cautions in the 12 Nextel Cup races this season, 14 in the last 100 laps of those races.</p>
        <p>A debris caution is akin to a holding penalty in football -- something that is not always easy to spot. Sometimes, parts fall off cars only to be blown into the infield or toward the wall. Other times, debris is not detected before another car runs over it.</p>
        <p>The second situation is a potential problem because a cut or blown tire can lead to a smoky multicar pileup. Nascar is in the business of racing, not crashing. It does not want a chunk of debris or a slick of dropped oil to spoil a good race.</p>
        <p>''I've been in this business long enough and I've been burned by not displaying a caution flag too many times,'' John Darby, Nascar's gravelly voiced series director, said Friday in his trailer at Dover International Speedway. ''If we're going to err, we're going to err on the conservative side.''</p>
        <p>But Nascar does not want to appear as if it is setting up a thrilling finish by calling a caution to close the field, as Darby and other Nascar officials have been accused of doing this year.</p>
        <p>On April 24, three days after he lost a race in Phoenix, Tony Stewart made remarks during his weekly radio show. Stewart, a two-time series champion, accused Nascar of rigging races by throwing bogus caution flags to ensure close finishes.</p>
        <p>''I think a lot of comments were made out of frustration,'' said Jeff Gordon, the Nextel Cup series leader in points entering Sunday's Autism Speaks 400 race at Dover. ''I don't think anybody's ever really agreed with those comments. I certainly don't.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''I think Nascar has a very tough job, and I do think they need to get a little bit more consistent with some of their calls, but I feel like they've made a lot of right calls. You look at sports in general, whether it's a referee or any kind of judge, you're going to get it wrong sometimes, and somebody's going to criticize you.''</p>
        <p>Since Stewart's comments, not much has changed. There have been 11 debris cautions in the past four Nextel Cup races, compared with 20 in the first eight races. Debris cautions in the final 100 laps crept up, to 1.5 a race from 1.1.</p>
        <p>What has changed, apparently, are some perceptions.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes they will call a debris caution, and there is just nothing out there,'' said Kyle Busch, who is 12th in the standings. ''They want to close the field back up and get everybody back to racing if the race is getting too boring or something like that. They want to keep excitement in it.''</p>
        <p>Busch then did a U-turn and added: ''But you know, that was the past. I have not seen that for a while. I think TV didn't help that situation earlier when they wouldn't show the debris on the racetrack; they would just cut away to pit stops or something instead of watching the cleanup truck finding it.''</p>
        <p>Darby enlists a near legion of debris finders for each race. On Sunday, Darby and about a half-dozen Nascar officials will be stationed in the timing and scoring booth above the stands near the start-finish line. Darby will have binoculars.</p>
        <p>He can refer to shots from the television cameras. A handful of Nascar officials will spread out along the one-mile racetrack, looking for potential trouble. Other officials will be in the garages to inspect cars taken in for repair, looking for pieces that could fall off.</p>
        <p>He also welcomes reports of debris from the drivers, who radio their crew chiefs, who pass along the information to Nascar officials in the pits. The group in the control tower will try to verify the debris and call a caution if one is needed.</p>
        <p>''I like Nascar's approach to it,'' the second-year driver Denny Hamlin said. ''They're trying to do the right thing by keeping safety in mind and keeping the racing good.''</p>
        <p>Naturally, some drivers, especially those who are lagging, have tried to bend the rules to their advantage. A harmless piece of black rubber roll-bar tubing, Darby said, can look like a dangerous piece of black metal pipe.</p>
        <p>The driver Robby Gordon was fined $15,000 and docked 50 points late last year for throwing a piece of roll-bar padding on the track late in a race at Atlanta Motor Speedway to cause a caution period and gain back a lost lap.</p>
        <p>The caper was a throwback to the romantic days of stock-car racing, when, as Darby said with a smile, ''they carried a whole lunchbox full of stuff in the cars with them.''</p>
        <p>But there is a flip side: The owner Jack Roush handed Darby a torn window net, a piece of pipe and a damaged driver's helmet after a Craftsman Truck Series race at Atlanta in March. The helmet belonged to Erik Darnell, one of Roush's drivers, who was hit in the head with a piece of pipe after it was run over and shot through his window.</p>
        <p>''When people ask me, 'Why do you throw debris cautions?' there's why,'' Darby said.</p>
        <p>The Nextel Cup driver Kasey Kahne lost a lead, and a race, at Dover in June 2004 when he skidded over a patch of oil and plowed into a wall before officials could call a caution.</p>
        <p>A crash like that, Darby said, explains his vigilance -- a vigilance that not every driver grasps.</p>
        <p>''It's a lot harder for me to sleep at night when something like that happens,'' he said, ''as opposed to when we call a debris caution, and the debris turns out to be nothing more than a ball of tape.''</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
