<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Name Aside, Don't Focus on the Cheese</title>
    <meta content="03dinenjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03dinenj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/RUMSON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">David Burke Fromagerie (Rumson, NJ, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cook, Karla</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E1DC1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Name Aside, Don't Focus on the Cheese</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Name Aside, Don’t Focus on the Cheese</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KARLA COOK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cook, Karla</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Karla Cook reviews David Burke Fromagerie restaurant in Rumson, NJ; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT a restaurant named Fromagerie, I expect an amazing cheese plate.</p>
        <p>There are amazing things at David Burke Fromagerie: the rolled wad of cash in the breast pocket of the man who seated us; the best steak I have eaten in recent memory; the abundant bling adorning the clientele; three-cheese popovers the size of a toddler's head.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are amazing things at David Burke Fromagerie in Rumson, but not the cheese plate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT a restaurant named Fromagerie, I expect an amazing cheese plate.</p>
        <p>There are amazing things at David Burke Fromagerie: the rolled wad of cash in the breast pocket of the man who seated us; the best steak I have eaten in recent memory; the abundant bling adorning the clientele; three-cheese popovers the size of a toddler's head.</p>
        <p>But the cheese plate was not amazing.</p>
        <p>It was safe, classic and delicious, with Humboldt Fog goat cheese, Camembert, Époisses, Manchego and Mahón, Cashel Irish blue, and Roaring Forties, a goat's-milk blue from Australia, but it was left by a waiter who barely stopped as he delivered it.</p>
        <p>Despite the absence of this and other flourishes, David Burke Fromagerie works. Diners are seated quickly at the 35-year-old restaurant, which was bought by Mr. Burke, the noted restaurateur, chef and cookbook author, in 2006. (Its founders, Markus and Hubert Peter, hired him and taught him to work at the old Fromagerie when he was ''still a kid,'' Mr. Burke says, and he confesses that his heart is in Rumson.)</p>
        <p>There is an abundance of upscale deliciousness -- fine seafood and meats and luxury condiments -- some of which are also served at his other restaurants, including davidburke &amp; donatella in New York and David Burke Las Vegas.</p>
        <p>The dining room is a scene, populated by women in form-fitting dresses with plunging necklines and men in stylish polo shirts (tucked in) and sleek Italian loafers. Chunky gold is not out of place, nor is backslapping so loud that one can imagine the hand-shaped red imprint left behind.</p>
        <p>There are several components to the menu, which is overseen by Kevin Haeger, the chef: a four-course tasting version, a list of specials, appetizers, main courses, desserts and cheeses.</p>
        <p>Both visits started with an amuse-bouche in an eggshell. The first, a foie gras flan with bacon ragout, was beautifully cooked, but the bacon overwhelmed any delicate foie gras. The second version, potato leek flan with a potato gaufrette, was better balanced.</p>
        <p>The parfait of tuna and salmon tartare was just one example of consistency in fine ingredients. Every bite was meltingly tender. It was also another example of the staff's slightly cavalier attitude: the dish came with three sauces and no explanation (curry-flavored sauce, miso vinaigrette and chili oil, which Mr. Burke makes in house).</p>
        <p>The Kumamoto oysters needed no explaining, and neither did the truffle mignonette that came alongside; both were impeccable. The yellowfin tuna sashimi with lotus chips, lobster-ginger sauce and seaweed salad was a fine and funny fusion, especially its presentation atop a bed of Himalayan rock salt. The crab cake was sweetly paired with a mango vinaigrette, but the spicy ''hot and angry lobster cocktail,'' standing upright with the help of a florist's frog, seemed out of place.</p>
        <p>There were three salads, all acceptable if uninspired: one with goat cheese and bacon; the second a heart of romaine wrapped in prosciutto di Parma; and the third containing shaved fennel and tomato.</p>
        <p>Main courses included a witty take on eggs Benedict: luxuriously creamy day-boat sea scallops topped with sunny-side-up quail eggs and accompanied by a potato cake and sweet-savory chorizo. Other standouts included the braised beef short ribs with handmade cavatelli, wild mushrooms and truffle mousse; the filet of veal with parsnip purée and beet sauce; the seared monkfish with a broth that featured roasted Peppadew peppers; and the oversize slab of dry-aged rib-eye, a stellar piece of meat, its deep brown crust mingling with pink juices encouraging bite after bite. The lamb potpie, however, failed to transcend its components. And the ''soy honey'' duck over shrimp fried rice was too close to Chinese takeout to justify its $29 price tag. Herbed and grilled asparagus, however, was luscious.</p>
        <p>Desserts included a head-turning display of cheesecake ''lollipops,'' but skip those in favor of the fresh fruit in a consommé flavored with lemon grass and ginger and topped with a chai-spiced crème fraîche. It was so smart, so delicious and so amazing that I could almost forget the fromage.</p>
        <p>David Burke Fromagerie  26 Ridge Road  Rumson  (732) 842-8088  www.fromagerierestaurant.com</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE Elegant, with white tablecloths and neutral walls with wood and white trim. No wheelchair access.  THE CROWD An expensively dressed and coiffed crowd; a few family groups with children; nonchalant servers who nevertheless get the job done.  THE BAR Separate bar menu; extensive formal wine list. Whites, which start at $45, emphasize chardonnay. Reds, $35 to $3,000, include many premium American and French selections. Eleven dinner wines by the glass, $9 to $18; five dessert wines, $10 to $28 a glass, five ports, $8 to $28 a glass, and five grappas, $14 to $28 a glass.  THE BILL Main courses $15 to $21 at lunch, $26 to $39 at dinner. (Discover Card not accepted.)  WHAT WE LIKE Yellowfin tuna sashimi, crab cake, all salads, Kumamoto oysters, tuna and salmon tartare; seared monkfish, veal mignon, grilled asparagus, rib-eye steak, short ribs and cavatelli, day-boat sea scallops Benedict, fruit with ginger-and-lemon-grass consommé.  IF YOU GO Lunch: Friday, 11:30 a.m. to 2:30 p.m. Brunch: Sunday, 11 a.m. to 3 p.m. Dinner: Tuesday to Thursday, 5 to 10 p.m.; Friday and Saturday, 5 to 11 p.m.; Sunday, 4 to 9 p.m. Reservations recommended two weeks in advance for weekends. Valet parking and ample street parking.  Reviewed June 3, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/RUMSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
