<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Streets, Two Players, One Little Town in Georgia</title>
    <meta content="03chass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/sports/baseball/03chass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851968"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago White Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Chicago White Sox</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Robinson, Jackie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EEDE1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Streets, Two Players, One Little Town in Georgia</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Two Streets, Two Players, One Little Town in Georgia</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The town of Cairo, Ga., (population 9,400) has two streets named for prominent native sons: Jackie Robinson Memorial Drive and Willie Harris Drive. Willie what?</p>
        <p>''It's the street I grew up on,'' Harris said. ''It was named after me after we won the 2005 World Series. They had a big parade.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The town of Cairo, Ga., has two streets named for prominent native sons: Jackie Robinson Memorial Drive and Willie Harris Drive. That’s a distinction that Harris, a left fielder for the Braves, proudly shares.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The town of Cairo, Ga., (population 9,400) has two streets named for prominent native sons: Jackie Robinson Memorial Drive and Willie Harris Drive. Willie what?</p>
        <p>''It's the street I grew up on,'' Harris said. ''It was named after me after we won the 2005 World Series. They had a big parade.''</p>
        <p>That World Series gained Harris another distinction. He batted 1.000 in it, stroking a pinch-hit single in the eighth inning of Game 4 and scoring the run that gave the Chicago White Sox a 1-0 victory and a four-game sweep over Houston.</p>
        <p>His first distinction he shares with Robinson. They are the only Cairo-born players who have played in the major leagues.</p>
        <p>''I'm very proud to wear that on my shoulders,'' said Harris, a surprisingly productive hitter for the Atlanta Braves, speaking of his association with Robinson. ''I try to play the game somewhat the way he did. Play hard and cause havoc on the basepaths, play the game the right way.</p>
        <p>''You think about the marquee African-American players -- Bonds, Sheffield, Griffey, Torii Hunter -- but none of those guys can say they come from where Jackie Robinson is from. That means a lot to me. Of course, I wish I could hit the ball like those guys do.''</p>
        <p>Recalled from the minors April 30, Harris has hit better than those players, batting .397 in 27 games through Friday as the Braves' primary left fielder. It's an eye-opening average for a player who hit .238 in 369 games spread over six seasons for the White Sox, Baltimore and Boston</p>
        <p>''I changed my entire approach to what it's been the past couple years,'' the 28-year-old Harris said. ''I'm having much better at-bats, seeing the ball better and longer. I don't know why. It's all confidence, trusting my hands, letting my hands work for me.''</p>
        <p>Last winter Harris, a left-handed hitter, had hitting sessions two and three times a day, breaking down his swing, he said, to figure out why he hadn't done better.</p>
        <p>Signing with the Braves as a minor league free agent, Harris continued working on his hitting in spring training with Terry Pendleton, the Braves' hitting coach, and Jack Maloof, the minor league hitting coach.</p>
        <p>''They came up with a different stance for me,'' Harris said. ''It worked in spring training, worked in Richmond, and I got to the big leagues. Why change things now?''</p>
        <p>Besides finding what he called a comfort zone in his hitting, Harris said he felt good ''playing in my home state.''</p>
        <p>''It's a lot easier to play, and I have the opportunity to see my family a lot,'' he added.</p>
        <p>He also enjoys seeing his high school football coach, Steve Bench.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't too serious about baseball in high school,'' he said. ''I was a football player. My coach instilled intensity in me. He was a really tough cookie and it paid off for me. When I go home in the off-season, I run into him and I thank him for being tough on us.''</p>
        <p>As a minor league free agent last winter, Harris could have signed with any team that was interested in him, but once the Braves indicated interest, no other team mattered.</p>
        <p>''I always wanted to play for the Braves,'' he said. ''All baseball players who grow up in Georgia want to play for the Braves and Bobby Cox.''</p>
        <p>When he was growing up in Cairo, which is closer to Tallahassee, Fla., than Atlanta, he didn't know about Jackie Robinson, Harris said.</p>
        <p>''But when I was in high school,'' he related, ''it was Black History Month, and the teacher insisted I do my research paper on Jackie Robinson, knowing how I felt about baseball. That's when I found out about him. They named my high school baseball field after him when I was a senior.''</p>
        <p>But the impact of his geographical relationship with Robinson has grown as Harris's career has progressed. ''I never thought I'd be where I am today,'' he said. ''Now it means a lot more to me.''</p>
        <p>Suzuki Revs It Up</p>
        <p>Ichiro Suzuki is the Road Runner of Major League Baseball, not for his foot speed, which is considerable, but for the speed with which his batting average goes from here -- whoosh -- to there.</p>
        <p>On May 6, Suzuki was hitting .260, an alien area for a player who batted .331 in his first six seasons in the majors. Four weeks and 25 games later, he was hitting .338 after collecting 46 hits in 112 at-bats (.411).</p>
        <p>He had two hits in 13 of those 25 games, three hits in two others and five hits in one game.</p>
        <p>Early Problems for Glavine</p>
        <p>You would think Tom Glavine is old enough (41) and has pitched in the major leagues long enough (20 years) to know that the first two innings of games count as much as other innings. But Glavine, five victories short of 300, has consistently encountered more problems in the first two innings than any other two.</p>
        <p>In his dozen starts for the Mets, Glavine has allowed eight runs in the first inning and nine in the second. The sixth inning, in which his opponents have scored eight runs, is the only one that has been as troublesome as the first two. In his other 38 innings, Glavine has permitted a total of six runs.</p>
        <p>In Glavine's last five starts, only two of which he has won, teams scored 10 runs in the first two innings -- five in each -- and 3 in the other 22 innings he has pitched.</p>
        <p>Glavine could offer no explanation for his early problems. ''I just get them out of the way early,'' Glavine said, joking.</p>
        <p>Glavine, a left-hander, attributed the runs more to luck than anything else.</p>
        <p>''Aside from a little bad luck, there's not a lot I can do,'' he said. ''The Chicago start was a bunch of bloopers that fell in. The Atlanta start was two ground-ball singles and a sacrifice fly. The Giants game was sort of the same thing. I think it's a case of me making decent pitches but not getting good results. That happens sometimes.''</p>
        <p>Biggio Nears 3,000 Hits</p>
        <p>As he draws closer to 3,000, Craig Biggio is finding hits harder to come by than at any stage of his 19-year career.</p>
        <p>Biggio, Houston's 41-year-old second baseman, a .283 career hitter entering this year, took a .236 average into the weekend. If he continues to hit that poorly, he will wind up with his lowest average since his rookie season, 1988.</p>
        <p>Biggio, however, hasn't amassed 2,977 hits struggling with his swing. He has been a .300 hitter four times and has collected more than 150 hits in a season 13 times.</p>
        <p>He is first in hits among active players, and when he becomes the 27th player to get 3,000, he will be the first to join the select club since Rafael Palmeiro made it in 2005 before exiting baseball under the cloud of a positive steroid test.</p>
        <p>Who is second among active players? Barry Bonds, with 2,876.</p>
        <p>The Struggling N.L. Central</p>
        <p>The National League Central continues to be a poor excuse for a pennant-contending division. Since the initial interleague series two weekends ago, the Central's six teams, when they haven't played one another, have won 11 games and lost 32. The .256 winning percentage would translate to a 41-121 record for a 162-game season.</p>
        <p>The records of the division's six teams in those nondivision games at the start of the weekend:</p>
        <p>Houston 0-7</p>
        <p>Chicago 2-8</p>
        <p>Milwaukee 4-7</p>
        <p>St. Louis 2-4</p>
        <p>Cincinnati 2-3</p>
        <p>Pittsburgh 1-3</p>
        <p>Readers Sound Off on Bonds</p>
        <p>Baseball fans apparently aren't any more certain than Commissioner Bud Selig about what he should do about the home run that Barry Bonds will hit to break Henry Aaron's career record.</p>
        <p>Selig has said repeatedly in recent weeks, most recently last Thursday, that he hasn't decided whether he will attend the game in which Bonds hits No. 756.</p>
        <p>''I'll make the decision at the appropriate time,'' Selig said.</p>
        <p>Readers of the On Baseball column were invited last week to express their opinions, and nearly 400 responded, with not all weighing in on whether Selig should attend. The survey demonstrated worldwide interest in the matter. Responses came from England, France, South Africa, Israel and Spain.</p>
        <p>The results:</p>
        <p>Go: 147.</p>
        <p>Go but don't participate in any celebration: 40.</p>
        <p>Don't go: 174.</p>
        <p>Told of those numbers, Selig said, ''I find them interesting but not surprising.''</p>
        <p>Many of the readers who said Selig should be at the game cited as their reason the fact that Bonds has not been convicted of anything and has not tested positive for an illegal performance-enhancing substance. In this country, they reminded, one is innocent until proven guilty.</p>
        <p>''If he doesn't have the evidence to suspend him,'' a North Carolina reader wrote, ''Selig should be there, on the field, shaking Bonds's hand.''</p>
        <p>A San Francisco reader, however, wrote, ''Selig knows Bonds cheated, and he knows the record would be fraudulent, so he should stay away, which would be his way of making a clear statement.''</p>
        <p>Selig, however, did not escape criticism.</p>
        <p>''Bud Selig has no one but himself to blame for all of this,'' a reader said. ''He rode the steroid train quite willingly during the McGwire-Sosa home run chase. Why should he get off the train now?''</p>
        <p>Another reader offered a novel, though impractical, suggestion.</p>
        <p>''After he crosses the plate for 756,'' the reader wrote, ''Bonds lifts Selig onto his shoulders and does an outfield lap so the fans can rain down their love for both men who have done so, so much for The Pastime.''</p>
        <p>Another reader called Bonds a disgrace to baseball, but one on the other side of the debate said, ''We may not like him, but he's an incredible athlete and should be honored accordingly.''</p>
        <p>A reader said that as much as he might dislike being present, Selig is the commissioner and ''will need to swallow his pride and take a dose of the medicine, 'cream or clear.' ''</p>
        <p>Another reader said Selig could go to the record-breaking game, ''but if he cheers, claps or shakes Bonds's hand, I'll be disgusted.'' The same reader made a suggestion Selig would probably like. ''My suggestion,'' he wrote, ''is that Selig skips Bonds entirely and spends the night with Hank Aaron.''</p>
        <p>But the comment Selig would agree with most was this one, ''There is no good answer, and Selig is going to catch hell no matter what he does.''</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
