<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Royal Me</title>
    <meta content="03age" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/fashion/03age.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AGE OF DISSONANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Customs, Etiquette and Manners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs, Etiquette and Manners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD71530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Royal Me</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Royal Me</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB MORRIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was after midnight, and the crowd of nightclubbers on West 27th Street was thick and antic. Outside Bungalow 8, there was a police barricade at the curb that said ''Do Not Cross.'' But why should that stop me? It was cold, and I wanted to get home quickly by skirting the sidewalk hordes and walking in the street.</p>
        <p>Without hesitation, I stepped through the barricade and off the curb to let an officer know I was a benign resident simply wanting to walk home. I thought he'd give me special permission to make my way west without inconvenience.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Not that long ago, only the aristocratic or famous felt entitled to special privileges, but nowadays we seem to be living in an age of excessive exceptionalism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was after midnight, and the crowd of nightclubbers on West 27th Street was thick and antic. Outside Bungalow 8, there was a police barricade at the curb that said ''Do Not Cross.'' But why should that stop me? It was cold, and I wanted to get home quickly by skirting the sidewalk hordes and walking in the street.</p>
        <p>Without hesitation, I stepped through the barricade and off the curb to let an officer know I was a benign resident simply wanting to walk home. I thought he'd give me special permission to make my way west without inconvenience.</p>
        <p>''Look,'' I said as I showed him my driver's license, ''I live right down that street.''</p>
        <p>He took my license. Then he wrote me a summons for disorderly conduct.</p>
        <p>I got very angry. Among other things, the court appearance date was going to cut a Mexico vacation short by a day! How dare he? On the other hand, how dare me?</p>
        <p>I mean, who tries to manipulate, then excoriate a police officer?</p>
        <p>Just about anyone these days, I'm beginning to think.</p>
        <p>We are living in an age of excessive exceptionalism, aren't we?</p>
        <p>Not that long ago, only the aristocratic or famous felt entitled to special privileges. It was only governors, actors and pop stars who had the nerve to break speed limits, societal taboos and hotel furniture on a regular basis. Rock Brynner, writing about his father, Yul, in a new biography of his family, refers to the ''extra quart of champagne in his veins,'' and suggests that when privilege is constantly reinforced, stars feel entitled to suspend common civility and the golden rule.</p>
        <p>Perhaps that explains why Sylvester Stallone smuggled testosterone into Australia recently (he said he needed it to help him make a ''Rambo'' movie) and why Paris Hilton was 15 minutes late for court last month after driving with a suspended license.</p>
        <p>Now, in the age of elite access, private prison cells and select banking, when being a millionaire is small time, and being gifted and talented is as common as having a blog, a book deal or a career from a reality-show stint, nobody wants the back of the plane, end of the line, middle of the class, or anything other than the V.I.P. lounge.</p>
        <p>And there's always a reason why they should get their way. They know the owner. They're with the press or with the band. Amy Sacco, the owner of Bungalow 8, has heard it all outside her nightclub when it is filled to legal capacity.</p>
        <p>''People tell me they're just in from London,'' she said. ''Or they're friends of celebrities. They're savvy and used to pushing their way through to get what they want.''</p>
        <p>And when they don't, they know who to call with their complaints.</p>
        <p>That's why college admissions offices have blackout periods when they won't take calls. It doesn't stop entitled parents. Even alumni who give modestly flaunt it brazenly, according to the Chronicle of Higher Education. An admissions officer at Union College in Schenectady, N.Y., recalled eating lunch on campus one day, when the wife of an influential alumnus (with a wait-listed daughter) appeared before him ''like a scud missile.''</p>
        <p>Then after college, entitled young graduates come to work and resent having a boss rather than being one. It can drive employers wild.</p>
        <p>Almost as wild as I become when I don't get my way. Don't people know who I am?</p>
        <p>The other day at Newark airport, when the Continental EliteAccess line was not available for speeding through airport security, I complained bitterly to customer service. And whenever I am stopped while driving, I end up giving the police a jagged piece of my jagged mind.</p>
        <p>Of course, this kind of behavior isn't only bad for society. It may also be bad for personal health. One 2006 British study of civil servants found that people who think they are being treated unfairly are 55 percent more likely to have a heart attack in the next decade.</p>
        <p>Maybe I should have kept that in mind when I arrived for my court appearance.</p>
        <p>Even when the courthouse staff was pleasant and accommodating, and a reasonable judge let me off, I couldn't keep myself from venting to a social worker that a foolish police officer had wasted my time by writing me a summons in the first place.</p>
        <p>''Police can always issue a ticket, so it's better not to have an attitude,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Simple but sound advice for the Mel, Nicole, Naomi and Paris in all of us.</p>
        <p>AGE OF DISSONANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
