<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Children Know Best</title>
    <meta content="03RparentingCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851751"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PARENTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winerip, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EEDE1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1185" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Children Know Best</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINERIP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Winerip, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Winerip Parenting column on his decision to take away his 90-year-old mother's car keys; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN my mother reached her mid-80s, it began to dawn on me that I'd have to start intervening in her life. This was not pleasant. Mom had always been fiercely independent, happily living on her own in suburban Boston for the 20 years after my dad died.</p>
        <p>There was no single event, just a hundred little ones that nibbled away at that solid image of Mom that was stored in my brain. I'd go back to Quincy for a visit and there would be piles of mail all over the house. Overdue bills were mixed in with supermarket stuffers that should have been tossed out weeks earlier. And I'd try to remember: Was this new?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN my mother reached her mid-80s, it began to dawn on me that I'd have to start intervening in her life. This was not pleasant. Mom had always been fiercely independent, happily living on her own in suburban Boston for the 20 years after my dad died.</p>
        <p>There was no single event, just a hundred little ones that nibbled away at that solid image of Mom that was stored in my brain. I'd go back to Quincy for a visit and there would be piles of mail all over the house. Overdue bills were mixed in with supermarket stuffers that should have been tossed out weeks earlier. And I'd try to remember: Was this new?</p>
        <p>On one visit, we cooked dinner together, and I couldn't be sure, but it appeared that more of her pots were burned on the bottom. Another time, Mom misplaced her purse, and after hours of hunting, we found it at the bottom of her closet. Her closet?</p>
        <p>The house didn't seem as clean, so as a Mother's Day gift, I hired a student from a local college for a free month of cleaning. But when the gift expired, Mom didn't keep the cleaner: She didn't clean right. Besides, Mom loved scrubbing floors.</p>
        <p>Mom wouldn't consider assisted living. We'd go on tours and she'd nod enthusiastically at all the amenities, then tell the rental agent, ''You know, I love my house.''</p>
        <p>So I found a social worker in Quincy named Kate who specialized in helping the elderly stay in their homes. Mom insisted she didn't need help, and she certainly didn't want this Kate person knowing her private business. But I persisted, and after the three of us went to lunch, Mom admitted that this Kate person seemed all right. At that point, I lied to my mother. I told her that the social worker was provided by the city free of charge, and that as a senior citizen Mom was entitled to unlimited free visits. This worked. Mom loved a bargain.</p>
        <p>Blessed Kate won Mom's heart and progressed from seeing her once a month to visiting weekly for 90 minutes. She became my eyes on Mom, my spy. Eventually, Mom trusted her so completely, she let Kate pay the bills that we couldn't do online. At the end of those visits, Mom would send Kate off with cookies or some small gift to take home to her children.</p>
        <p>One of my regular topics with Kate was Mom's driving -- nothing conclusive, just more worrisome nibbles. There was the time at the mall when a shopper found Mom slumped over the steering wheel, the car idling. Mom went to the hospital emergency room and then to her doctor. Nothing serious, they concluded; she'd just had a cold and was weak that day.</p>
        <p>I got a call from an insurance investigator. He said someone had reported Mom hitting a car in a Stop &amp; Shop parking lot. Mom adamantly denied this. She drove a 15-year-old Dodge Dart that had accumulated lots of nicks, and when I made a special visit to Boston to see the car for myself, there didn't seem to be any more scrapes than when I'd last looked.</p>
        <p>The insurance agent was very sympathetic. He said he had a grandmother Mom's age and confessed that he couldn't tell whether Mom had actually hit the other car or someone was scamming her because of her age.</p>
        <p>Then a woman told Kate that Mom had gone through a red light and done a few other things that had made her nervous when she rode with her. How much to make of this? Was Mom being overly scrutinized because of her age? If the standard for taking away a license were running red lights, much of America would be walking.</p>
        <p>I went for a drive with Mom around town, and she did fine. I contacted Mom's doctor and asked him to do an assessment, but he told me that under privacy laws, he'd need her permission. She would not give it.</p>
        <p>The social worker helped me find a reasonably priced car service that specialized in driving the elderly, but Mom would not hear of it. In her defense, Mom recited the suburban credo: ''My car is my freedom.'' She said she'd know when it was time to stop.</p>
        <p>I couldn't tell if I was noticing more problems because I was looking, or if more was going wrong. The forgetfulness seemed worse. She'd be out on an errand when she was supposed to be home for her appointment with Kate. Her hearing deteriorated further, and she refused to wear her hearing aid. She said that when she wore it, she heard the wrong things. I noticed more odd comments during our nightly phone calls. ''There's a paper here on my couch,'' she said one time, ''and I can't remember how it got there.''</p>
        <p>The law in Massachusetts, as in most states, has a procedure for filing a complaint about someone you think should no longer drive. In Massachusetts, the driver is entitled to know who filed that complaint. Mom would know it was her son Michael. I felt this was a terrible message to send at a time when I badly needed Mom's trust so we could work together to figure out how to enable her to best live out her life.</p>
        <p>Reporting Mom to the government would not build trust. I decided it was better to look her in the eye and tell the truth. I was motivated by fear as much as anything. As a newspaperman, I could see the headline: ''Confused Elderly Woman Crashes Into''</p>
        <p>''Mom,'' I said, ''I don't think you should be driving any more. I'm taking away your keys.''</p>
        <p>I was bigger, stronger, younger, and I didn't think she'd have the wherewithal to go up against me or behind my back. And I was right.</p>
        <p>But this was no victory, only lots more responsibility. It reminded me of the warning President Bush was given on Iraq: ''You break it, you own it.'' Now I owned Mom. That was 2004. She was 90.</p>
        <p>Shortly after I took the keys, she went to stay with my brother in Phoenix for the winter. In the spring, I brought her to New York and set her up -- ''strictly on a trial basis, Mom'' -- in an assisted-living residence near my home. For her remaining 18 months, Mom did not live in her Quincy home, nor did she drive again.</p>
        <p>During this time, if we were together with her bridge friends at the residence, Mom would invariably say: ''Do you know that my son Michael took my car keys away from me? Can you believe that?''</p>
        <p>Mom was not a complainer, and when she said this, she smiled. But I was being reminded: There are many degrading things about living to be 92.</p>
        <p>Her friends would shake their heads as if to say, ''What a monster son, we know the type.'' But then they would do me a kindness. What I read in their ever-so-slightly raised eyebrows was, ''You did right.''</p>
        <p>PARENTING E-mail: parenting@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: parenting@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
