<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What's On Sunday Night</title>
    <meta content="0603tvcol" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/arts/television/0603tvcol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070604T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851692"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DB1430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="498" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What's On Sunday Night</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What’s on Sunday Night</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHRYN SHATTUCK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>8 P.M. (MTV) 2007 MTV MOVIE AWARDS Sarah Silverman, left, is host of this year's ceremony, with duties ranging from frisking patrons at the door to serving popcorn -- the Golden Bucket variety. Awards, presented live at the Gibson Amphitheater in Universal City, include breakthrough performance and ''best'' in categories including villain, performance, comedic performance, kiss, fight and summer movie you haven't seen yet. Jessica Alba, Victoria Beckham, Jessica Biel, Cameron Diaz, Zac Efron, Ioan Gruffudd, Samuel L. Jackson Mandy Moore, and Bruce Willis are among the presenters. Amy Winehouse, Rihanna and Jay-Z will perform. Viewers will choose best movie spoof from among hundreds of amateur film clips at mtvmovieawards.yahoo.com.</p>
        <p>7 P.M. (CBS) MIKE WALLACE: SOME OF MY FAVORITE STORIES In this ''60 Minutes'' special Mr. Wallace interviews Mahmoud Ahmadinejad, the president of Iran, at right with Mr. Wallce; the actress Vanessa Redgrave; and Dr. Jack Kevorkian, who served eight years for second-degree murder.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (Food Network) THE NEXT FOOD NETWORK STAR Eleven foodies compete in a series of culinary challenges for a chance to play host on a Food Network program. Tonight, in this two-hour season premiere, each contestant must present an original dish to the selection committee, which includes a guest member, Bobby Flay; decorate a wedding cake to be judged by the ''Ace of Cakes'' star Duff Goldman; and join teammates to cater a wedding for 100 in just six hours under the critical eye of Robert Irvine of ''Dinner: Impossible.''</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (HBO) THE SOPRANOS In the series's penultimate episode, Tony's allies have their allegiance tested. And a case of mistaken identity has dire ramifications.</p>
        <p>10 P.M. (HBO) ENTOURAGE This episode is being billed as the Season 3 finale. But the withdrawal symptoms will be short-lived: Season 4 begins only two weeks from now, on June 17. Tonight Vince and his posse say adios to the mansion as Eric gets fixated on Sloan, Drama gets fixated on a condo, and the guys fixate on Billy Walsh to direct ''Medellin.''</p>
        <p>10 P.M. (Lifetime) ARMY WIVES Blame Iraq. This soapy new series follows a group of mismatched base dwellers brought together by the bonds of war. At their heart Roxy LeBlanc, a feisty woman from -- where else? -- the wrong side of the tracks, who, after a four-day courtship, decides to marry a soldier and move with her two children to an Army post. She soon meets Claudia Joy Holden, wife of a colonel; Pamela Moran, outcast and secret surrogate who is pregnant with twins; Roland Burton, whose lieutenant wife has just returned from abroad; and Denise Sherwood, teetering on the divide between her iron-fisted husband and her son. When Pamela goes into labor at an afternoon tea party, the women are all wedded for better or worse. The stars are, above, Sterling K. Brown; Kim Delaney, center; and Catherine Bell, as well as Sally Pressman, Brigid Brannnagh, Sterling K. Brown and Wendy Davis.</p>
        <p>KATHRYN SHATTUCK</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>8 P.M. (MTV) 2007 MTV MOVIE AWARDS Sarah Silverman, left, is host of this year’s ceremony, with duties ranging from frisking patrons at the door to serving popcorn  the Golden Bucket variety. Awards, presented live at the Gibson Amphitheater in Universal City, include breakthrough performance and “best” in categories like villain, performance, comedic performance, kiss, fight and summer movie you haven’t seen yet. Jessica Alba, Victoria Beckham, Jessica Biel, Cameron Diaz, Zac Efron, Ioan Gruffudd, Samuel L. Jackson Mandy Moore and Bruce Willis are among the presenters. Amy Winehouse, Rihanna and Jay-Z will perform. Viewers will choose best movie spoof from among hundreds of amateur film clips at mtvmovieawards.yahoo.com.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>8 P.M. (MTV) 2007 MTV MOVIE AWARDS Sarah Silverman, left, is host of this year's ceremony, with duties ranging from frisking patrons at the door to serving popcorn -- the Golden Bucket variety. Awards, presented live at the Gibson Amphitheater in Universal City, include breakthrough performance and ''best'' in categories including villain, performance, comedic performance, kiss, fight and summer movie you haven't seen yet. Jessica Alba, Victoria Beckham, Jessica Biel, Cameron Diaz, Zac Efron, Ioan Gruffudd, Samuel L. Jackson Mandy Moore, and Bruce Willis are among the presenters. Amy Winehouse, Rihanna and Jay-Z will perform. Viewers will choose best movie spoof from among hundreds of amateur film clips at mtvmovieawards.yahoo.com.</p>
        <p>7 P.M. (CBS) MIKE WALLACE: SOME OF MY FAVORITE STORIES In this ''60 Minutes'' special Mr. Wallace interviews Mahmoud Ahmadinejad, the president of Iran, at right with Mr. Wallce; the actress Vanessa Redgrave; and Dr. Jack Kevorkian, who served eight years for second-degree murder.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (Food Network) THE NEXT FOOD NETWORK STAR Eleven foodies compete in a series of culinary challenges for a chance to play host on a Food Network program. Tonight, in this two-hour season premiere, each contestant must present an original dish to the selection committee, which includes a guest member, Bobby Flay; decorate a wedding cake to be judged by the ''Ace of Cakes'' star Duff Goldman; and join teammates to cater a wedding for 100 in just six hours under the critical eye of Robert Irvine of ''Dinner: Impossible.''</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (HBO) THE SOPRANOS In the series's penultimate episode, Tony's allies have their allegiance tested. And a case of mistaken identity has dire ramifications.</p>
        <p>10 P.M. (HBO) ENTOURAGE This episode is being billed as the Season 3 finale. But the withdrawal symptoms will be short-lived: Season 4 begins only two weeks from now, on June 17. Tonight Vince and his posse say adios to the mansion as Eric gets fixated on Sloan, Drama gets fixated on a condo, and the guys fixate on Billy Walsh to direct ''Medellin.''</p>
        <p>10 P.M. (Lifetime) ARMY WIVES Blame Iraq. This soapy new series follows a group of mismatched base dwellers brought together by the bonds of war. At their heart Roxy LeBlanc, a feisty woman from -- where else? -- the wrong side of the tracks, who, after a four-day courtship, decides to marry a soldier and move with her two children to an Army post. She soon meets Claudia Joy Holden, wife of a colonel; Pamela Moran, outcast and secret surrogate who is pregnant with twins; Roland Burton, whose lieutenant wife has just returned from abroad; and Denise Sherwood, teetering on the divide between her iron-fisted husband and her son. When Pamela goes into labor at an afternoon tea party, the women are all wedded for better or worse. The stars are, above, Sterling K. Brown; Kim Delaney, center; and Catherine Bell, as well as Sally Pressman, Brigid Brannnagh, Sterling K. Brown and Wendy Davis.</p>
        <p>KATHRYN SHATTUCK</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 4, 2007, Monday  The television program listings yesterday on Page 37 of the Arts &amp; Leisure section were omitted in some copies, and the BackPage photo feature appeared in their place. The Times regrets the inconvenience to readers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 4, 2007, Monday</p>
        <p>The television program listings yesterday on Page 37 of the Arts &amp; Leisure section were omitted in some copies, and the BackPage photo feature appeared in their place. The Times regrets the inconvenience to readers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
