<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Fully Grown Adult Baby</title>
    <meta content="03funny--humor.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/magazine/03funny-humor-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851673"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE FUNNY PAGES: II: TRUE-LIFE TALES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Postal Service</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glaser, Jon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Postal Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Post Offices and Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Post Offices and Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Postal Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E2DC1430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="886" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Fully Grown Adult Baby</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Fully Grown Adult Baby</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jon Glaser</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glaser, Jon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jon Glaser article in The Funny Pages describes encounter with post office clerk in which he behaved childishly; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was tax time. I owed money this year, and I was on my way to the post office to mail my payments. You can imagine the honey of a mood I was in. Not only did I get to give the government even more money than it had already taken, I also had the pleasure of getting to stand in line at the post office and of being ''helped'' by a postal employee I will simply refer to as the Biggest Sweetheart in the World (known from here on simply as Sweetheart).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The author crumbles under the weight of the moment, despite ample opportunities for verbal domination.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was tax time. I owed money this year, and I was on my way to the post office to mail my payments. You can imagine the honey of a mood I was in. Not only did I get to give the government even more money than it had already taken, I also had the pleasure of getting to stand in line at the post office and of being ''helped'' by a postal employee I will simply refer to as the Biggest Sweetheart in the World (known from here on simply as Sweetheart).</p>
        <p>There were maybe six people ahead of me, and the line was moving rather slowly. Perhaps it was because of the Israeli guy who ran out and came back and went right to the front of the line and started telling everyone that the teller had instructed him to go right to the front of the line when he came back and blah blah blah. We get it; please just stop talking and go next. Or maybe it was the Australian woman with the gifts she had obviously just bought at the Disney Store, who for some reason was allowed to box them all up right there at the window. Allowed by Sweetheart, no less.</p>
        <p>Finally at the head of the line, I was summoned to his window. I presented my four letter-size envelopes and eight unattached certified-mail labels. All Sweetheart had to do was affix the labels and I'd be on my way. He attached one set of labels to one envelope and stopped.</p>
        <p>''Are you going to do the rest?'' I asked.</p>
        <p>''No,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Um, I'm sorry. No?</p>
        <p>I remained calm. I amicably explained that every time I had done this before, the clerk had done the labels for me. Stone-faced, Sweetheart said that if I had done this before, then I must know how to do it. He said customers are supposed to have this done before they get to the window: otherwise, he spends time showing every person how to do it, and it wastes time for the other people standing in line. He then pointed at the people in line behind me, as if I didn't know they were there.</p>
        <p>Let me just say right here that I have had numerous imaginary confrontations, and they have all gone amazingly well. Cool and collected, I have taken them all down -- post-office clerks, rental-car agents, indie-record-store clerks -- with an impressive combination of logic, confidence and clever comebacks. Often in these imaginary bouts, my side of the conversation is spoken out loud, while the other person's side takes place in my head. To avoid looking like the crazy person that I actually am, I talk into my cellphone. If you ever see me walking my dog, yelling into my headset about how the cable company should refund the entire pay-per-view fee because the soccer game cut out with five minutes left to play, you won't be able to tell if there's someone on the other line. But you will be able to tell that I'm winning the argument.</p>
        <p>But now, presented with an actual confrontation, I was crumbling under the weight of the reality of the moment. Every passing second I kept quiet was another blown opportunity to wonder aloud in an overly sarcastic and very confident voice that by refusing to help me, wasn't Sweetheart in fact slowing down the process and wasting even more of the line's time? I'd turn my head slightly, strategically directing certain words over my shoulder towards the line, so the people waiting would hear me and know that, in fact, [loud] the real reason they're being held up is because a [turn head, say even louder for emphasis] fully grown adult baby was refusing to help a customer. I pictured cheers for the Hero of the Line.</p>
        <p>Of course, the reality was that I'd just end up looking like an angry crazy person and that no one in line would really care since they just wanted the same thing I wanted, which was to get out of there as quickly as possible. If this verbal sparring with Sweetheart continued much longer, I'd be holding up the line for someone else and would end up being that person's Israeli guy. So I kept quiet, my hand trembling as I wrote my return address on each envelope. I wanted to blame the three-shot latte I finished while waiting in line, but deep down I knew that my composure was losing the battle with my anger.</p>
        <p>As I placed the final label on the last envelope, I thought of the Australian woman and how Sweetheart had, just moments before, helped wrap her packages right at the window. I wondered to myself if he would have been more helpful had I approached the window and just started talking in a horrible fake Australian accent. ''G'day, mate. Jist havin' a divil of a time tryin' to figgerout these lay-buls.''</p>
        <p>But there were no bad accents. And no smug barbs lobbed coolly over my shoulder, at least not out loud. Just an overworked, underpaid postal employee and the unappreciative, quick-tempered customer who was too impatient to figure out how to put six labels on three envelopes. The actual fully grown adult baby. The story's real sweetheart.</p>
        <p>THE FUNNY PAGES: II: TRUE-LIFE TALES Jon Glaser is a television writer in New York City. His last True-Life Tale was about playing hockey.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jon Glaser is a television writer in New York City. His last True-Life Tale was about playing hockey.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
