<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Old Devil</title>
    <meta content="Scott.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/books/review/Scott-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851627"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By A. O. Scott</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Amis, Kingsley</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Life of Kingsley Amis, The (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEED61630F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Old Devil</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Old Devil</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A. O. SCOTT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE LIFE OF KINGSLEY AMIS</p>
        <p>By Zachary Leader.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 996 pp. Pantheon Books. $39.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The authorized biography of Kingsley Amis, a man who enjoyed life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE LIFE OF KINGSLEY AMIS</p>
        <p>By Zachary Leader.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 996 pp. Pantheon Books. $39.95.</p>
        <p>In the years between the publication of his first novel, ''Lucky Jim,'' in 1954 and his death in 1995, Kingsley Amis enjoyed, to a degree matched by few of his contemporaries, the career of a Major British Author. Toward the end of it, he harvested some of the traditional honors associated with such status: a CBE, a Booker Prize, six-figure advances, knighthood. These he had earned through decades of clockwork productivity, the kind of brisk, un-neurotic industriousness more often associated with Major British Authors than with their American cousins. There was a new novel every couple of years -- more than 20 in all -- and in the intervals between them a steady outpouring of stories, reviews, poems, opinion pieces and travelogues. As a biographical note at the front of one of Amis's later books put it, ''he has written ephemerally on politics, education, language, films, television, restaurants and drink.''</p>
        <p>There is something touching about that word ''ephemerally,'' in which the candid admission that some work is not meant to last rests on the implication that the other work will of course be permanent. Zachary Leader, in the last chapter of his bulky new biography of Amis, is encouraged by his subject's prospects for literary immortality, noting that a brief posthumous ''falling off'' of public interest seems to have ended, and that ''all Amis's novels will soon be in print, either in Penguin or Vintage paperbacks.''</p>
        <p>This may well be the case in England. But though Amis, unlike many of his peers, was quite fond of the United States -- at the end of a year of teaching and adultery in Princeton in the '50s he toyed with the notion of staying here for good, but settled for a return visit a decade later and for making America the setting of ''One Fat Englishman'' (1963), one of his funniest books -- we don't seem, at the moment, to return his affection. It may be that some of his attitudes appear to be permanently out of step with the sensibilities of the domestic literary class. He wrote about women with the kind of ribald fascination that is frequently taken for misogyny, and in the course of his life his politics moved steadily rightward, from a collegiate flirtation with Communism through a passionless commitment to Labor to a hearty embrace of Margaret Thatcher. (Not quite a literal embrace, but almost: in his ''Memoirs'' Amis, an ardent connoisseur of feminine beauty, calls her ''one of the best-looking women I have ever met.'' ''This quality is so extreme,'' he continued, that ''it can trap me for a second into thinking I am looking at a science-fiction illustration of some time ago showing the beautiful girl who has become President of the Solar Federation in the year 2220.'')</p>
        <p>In any case, Amis's American comeback has yet to materialize. In the course of preparing this review, I made a fairly thorough search of bookstores in New York (and a few other places as well), and what I found was pretty much limited to ''Lucky Jim,'' a slender Penguin paperback squeezed against an imposing row of volumes by Kingsley's younger son, Martin. (The exception was a small used-book store on the Upper West Side, where I found a cache of battered Penguins and Signets that seemed to have been sitting on the shelf, moldering and untouched, for quite some time.) Martin, his father's loyal son and heir but also an enthusiastic devotee of Nabokov and Bellow (neither of whom Kingsley much admired), is more our type. Martin's politics, though they don't always track easily along the left-right continuum, are expressed in the registers of doubt, self-consciousness and regard for nuance that we expect of our liberal-minded literati. His mature novels are thick with ambition, abstraction and ambiguity. Books like ''The Information'' and ''London Fields'' are purposefully big and difficult in a way that bespeaks literary importance, a concept the elder Amis fought against with a conviction unusual in a Major British Author.</p>
        <p>Kingsley was always more inclined to traffic in sharp insights than in grand statements. Plenty of English writers and intellectuals have professed an allergy to theory, generalization and system -- a self-administered inoculation against Frenchness, among other maladies -- but few can match Amis's stubborn gusto in insisting on the adequacy of common sense and clear expression. (Early on, he was affiliated with a poetic movement -- called the Movement -- devoted to those principles and opposed what its adherents, among them Philip Larkin and Thom Gunn, saw as the heavy, foggy legacies of Romanticism and modernism). Nonetheless, Amis did leave behind a credo of sorts, in the form of the following set of rhymed and numbered propositions, the fourth and last in a series of ''Poems About Oxford,'' composed in 1950:</p>
        <p>''Here is a list of things I have understood.</p>
        <p>i. There are only two sorts of things, bad and good.</p>
        <p>ii. When he gets the good, a man ought to be glad.</p>
        <p>iii. When he gets the bad, a man ought to be sad.</p>
        <p>iv. Some of the good are joking, smoking, soaking,</p>
        <p>And (if you will permit the expression) poking.</p>
        <p>v. In a bad place these are absent, or even banned.</p>
        <p>vi. In a good place they are frequent, or ready to hand.</p>
        <p>vii. And I want as much of them as I can stand.''</p>
        <p>Next to those seven sentences, Leader's ''Life of Kingsley Amis'' stands as a thousand-page Q.E.D., a dogged chronicle of good times and bad as measured in sex, drink, tobacco and mischief (as well as in books, jobs, friendships, marriages, love affairs and changes of political opinion). To read this biography in light of the Oxford poem is to conclude that Amis pretty much got what he wanted. In his later years, as his second marriage (to the novelist Elizabeth Jane Howard) foundered, Amis's once insatiable libido flagged. Poor health compelled him to give up cigarettes. But his irrepressible, sometimes nasty sense of humor never waned. Nor did his appetite for alcohol. (''Soaking,'' we can assume, does not refer to a fondness for lingering in the bathtub.)</p>
        <p>Of course, the poem mocks its own earnestness, since frank hedonism is perhaps not the life lesson Oxford men in the aftermath of World War II were meant to absorb. But these lines are not entirely a joke. It is clear enough from Amis's own writing, as well as from Leader's account of his life, that he took pleasure seriously. It was a point of pride with him -- a matter of artistic principle, if you will permit the expression -- that his novels be entertaining and his poems amusing. He liked to have fun -- ''a man who used to LIVE for adultery,'' as Martin once described him -- and he worked hard to provide it for his readers, as anyone who has laughed out loud at ''Lucky Jim'' or ''The Old Devils'' or just about any of the stories and novels that came between them can attest. It seems fitting that ''fun'' is the last word in Leader's text, though his book also shows just how much labor, how much sober, self-denying craft, went into putting that fun into print. (Leader also, frankly and without undue moralizing, considers how often Amis's real-life kicks came at the expense of others.) To read this biography as a calendar of cocktails, club lunches and swordsmanship is to miss its point and its reason for being, which is the discipline involved in turning drunkenness, bonhomie and lechery into the sources of serious literary delight.</p>
        <p>In retrospect perhaps even more than in life, Amis is a complicated figure. The defense of fun -- as opposed to the provision or partaking of it -- can be a difficult business. It can always be objected that there are loftier, graver pursuits than boozing and carousing, and that overindulgence can be injurious to health, morals and the feelings of others. And surely, if there is more to life, there is more to literature as well. ''Is that how you'd like to be remembered,'' an interviewer once asked him, ''as Kingsley Amis the critic, the poet, the serious writer, or as Kingsley Amis the man who wrote books that made people laugh?'' Amis diplomatically chose the latter option. But comical though it is, his fiction is rarely frivolous, and one of its most serious themes is that the pursuit of pleasure -- of satisfaction -- is an ethical concern, a matter, as the Oxford poem has it, of good and bad.</p>
        <p>Consider Jim Dixon, the ''lucky'' junior lecturer at a provincial university who made Amis's fortune and who became his most recognizable alter ego. Dixon perceives his shabby, harassed circumstances as something tantamount to a conspiracy against his well-being. His acts of self-assertion, while generally rude and frequently disastrous, are nonetheless heroic. Viewed objectively, his behavior is appalling and immature. When he drunkenly sets fire to the bedclothes at a house where he is staying as a guest, he lies and tries to cover up his faux pas. Faced with inconvenient social or professional obligations, his response is to fib, to flee or to resort to elaborate and prankish schemes, like using fake names and voices on the telephone. He treats his own girlfriend callously and tries to move in on someone else's. His apotheosis is a public lecture on the subject of Merrie England that turns into a drunken rant against the very notion.</p>
        <p>And yet, from first chapter to last, we are completely on Jim Dixon's side. This is not only because, thanks to Amis's faultless mastery of free indirect style, we are in Dixon's head. It is also because the awfulness of his foes more than justifies the boorish, chaotic extremity of his tactics. In particular, he is ranged against a family of intellectuals and would-be artists -- drawn partly from the model of Amis's own in-laws, apparently -- headed by the unbearably pompous Professor Welch. The phoniness and pretension of this clan is magnified by their possession of advantages they can barely be bothered to acknowledge. Jim's career prospects depend almost entirely on the professor's good will, and so the senior man embodies both the soulless, bureaucratic aspects of academic labor and the vanity and capriciousness of wealth, cultural privilege and social entitlement.</p>
        <p>So the ''monstrous offensive by Dixon against the others'' -- and his ultimate moral victory, which entails losing the job and getting the girl, who had been claimed by Welch's horrible son Bertrand -- is unmistakably a form of class rebellion. Amis too was a rebel, though the nature of his revolt was never really political. He certainly carried with him, to Oxford and beyond, more than a hint of class resentment. ''I went up to Oxford in the spring of 1941 in impeccably proletarian style,'' he recalled in his ''Memoirs.'' But ''proletarian'' here is more tongue-in-cheek than sociologically precise, since Amis was a product of the respectable lower middle class. His father, William, worked as a clerk for Colman's, a London mustard manufacturer, and there was comfort and prosperity, if not great wealth, on both the maternal and paternal sides.</p>
        <p>It was partly the primness and modesty of that background -- the stiff-upper-lip, Little England taboos against wanting too much or pushing too hard -- against which Amis directed his rebellion. When Kingsley was young, William filled his ears with Victorian superstition about the perils of masturbation and later responded to news of one of his son's early love affairs with a scolding, censorious letter. He nearly refused to attend Amis's wedding to Hilary (Hilly) Bardwell on the grounds that the bride was pregnant (with Martin's older brother, Philip). The trait that Leader calls ''aggression'' -- ''explaining what it was like to be Kingsley Amis partly means explaining how he came to see and depict the world in this way, as suffused with violence, anger, threat'' -- can be seen as a protest against this stifling propriety, a determination to insist on the prerogatives of the self. Subsequent characters -- Roger Micheldene in ''One Fat Englishman,'' Patrick Standish in ''Take a Girl Like You,'' the title figures in the later books ''Jake's Thing'' and ''Stanley and the Women'' -- would push these prerogatives much farther than Jim Dixon, provocatively mixing fun with real unpleasantness.</p>
        <p>At the same time, a defensive loyalty to petit-bourgeois values undergirds Amis's lifelong campaign against snobbery, pretense and people who believed they were better than he was. In his fiction, the tastes and prejudices of the ''posh'' come in for frequent abuse, whether those tastes involve patrician conservatives indulging in early-music soirees (as in ''Lucky Jim'') or wealthy, left-wing bohemians dabbling in rock (as in ''Girl, 20,'' published in 1971). As an Oxford undergraduate and thereafter, Amis (along with his friends Larkin and Robert Conquest) could be scabrously irreverent about the work of some of the Major English Authors who were part of their curriculum (''Beowulf'' is a ''crass, purblind, infantile, featureless heap of gangrened elephant's sputum,'' while ''The Canterbury Tales'' is compared to ''the big pipe that takes away the waste matter from a public lavatory''). Suspicious of the exclusionary difficulty of modernism, he was among the first to take a serious critical interest in popular ''genre'' literature, producing a scholarly study of science fiction (originally delivered as Christian Gauss seminars at Princeton) and two books about James Bond, and insisting to a skeptical Christopher Hitchens that the movie ''Beverley Hills Cop'' was ''a flawless masterpiece.'' And yet, throughout his career Amis worried about declining cultural and educational standards, and recoiled against the leveling tendencies of the '60s and '70s. Like Larkin, his best friend from the 1940s on (though he callously neglected the friendship in later years), he took a mordant delight in presenting himself as a near-caricature of the harrumphing, intolerant, reactionary Englishman.</p>
        <p>eader, a professor of English literature at Roehampton University in England and a specialist in postwar British fiction, provides a detailed and convincing portrait of Amis in his times, but it can be an oddly bland and bloodless picture. To some degree, this cannot be helped. Amis once wrote an essay called ''Louis Armstrong and Tea at Grandmother's,'' defending (once again) the prerogatives of pleasure, represented by the exuberance of Satchmo's trumpet, against the claims of duty and responsibility symbolized by sitting on an uncomfortable chair eating stale cookies. A comic novelist's métier is pure Louis Armstrong, while the comprehensive literary biography is, more often than not, the epitome of tea at Grandmother's. To put it another way, Amis was always the life of the party; Leader is the designated driver.</p>
        <p>He is also the editor of Amis's letters, and the present book relies heavily on them, and also on Kingsley's ''Memoirs'' and Martin's ''Experience.'' All three are, perhaps inevitably, more satisfying literary performances than the ''Life,'' which is most alive in quotation. Leader is a reluctant gossip, a dutiful researcher and a keen literary critic, and he often seems more comfortable talking about the novels than about their author. Much as he tries to stop himself -- much as he clearly knows better -- he cannot help treating the fiction as evidence, a trap into which far too many biographies fall. The lapse is not theoretical -- Amis's life is self-evidently the basis of his work -- but rather aesthetic. The whole point of Amis's art is to refine, exaggerate and improve upon life, to make it funnier, more shapely, more awful, and nothing is gained by reversing the process.</p>
        <p>Indeed, ''The Life of Kingsley Amis,'' like most biographies of living or recently dead writers, inverts the probable terms of its subject's posthumous survival even as it provides an easy reference for curious readers in the future. Written in the twilight of Amis's celebrity, the book is tasteful catnip for high-minded voyeurs -- the present writer included -- who take pleasure in contemplating the sexual and medical histories of people they have never met, and in overhearing table talk at dinner parties to which they would never have been invited. This has its charms, but the serious fun lies elsewhere, in the novels that should be, for American readers, much nearer to hand than they are.</p>
        <p>Amis took pleasure seriously. It was a point of pride -- a matter of artistic principle -- that his novels be entertaining and his poems amusing.</p>
        <p>A. O. Scott is a film critic for The Times. He is writing a book about the American novel since World War II.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">A. O. Scott is a film critic for The Times. He is writing a book about the American novel since World War II.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
