<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Doors Open: Chapter 4: The Faker</title>
    <meta content="03funny--serial.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/magazine/03funny-serial-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851674"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE FUNNY PAGES: III: SUNDAY SERIAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rankin, Ian</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Doors Open (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E2DC1430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Doors Open: Chapter 4: The Faker</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">‘Doors Open’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ian Rankin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rankin, Ian</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chapter 4 of Ian Rankin's book Doors Open; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last week: The professor, Mike and Allan had a drink, and the professor explained a plan for a heist: stealing paintings from a warehouse owned by the National Gallery on Doors Open Day, the day the storage space is opened up to the public.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This week, Chapter 4: Hugh Westwater  Westie to those who knew him  always thought of the government as “They.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last week: The professor, Mike and Allan had a drink, and the professor explained a plan for a heist: stealing paintings from a warehouse owned by the National Gallery on Doors Open Day, the day the storage space is opened up to the public.</p>
        <p>Hugh Westwater -- Westie to those who knew him -- was sitting comfortably amid the chaos of his top-floor tenement apartment. The bay-windowed living room had become his studio; paint-smeared bedsheets were draped over the old sofa and chair that Westie had claimed from a Dumpster. Canvases rested against the available wall space, and newspaper clippings and photos were taped to whatever surfaces remained. Pizza cartons and beer cans littered the floor, some of the cans torn in half to serve as ashtrays. It was a wonder, Westie sometimes thought, that they still let you smoke in the comfort of your own home. These days in Scotland you couldn't smoke in pubs, clubs or restaurants, or at your workplace or even in a bus shelter. When the Stones played a stadium gig and Keith lit up onstage, they considered prosecuting him.</p>
        <p>Westie always thought of the government as ''They.''</p>
        <p>One of his first portfolio pieces was a manifesto, printed in black against a blood-red backing: They Are Out to Get You/They Know What You Do/They See You as Trouble. At the foot of the sheet, the printing had switched to white-on-red for his coda: But I Am Better Than Them at Art.</p>
        <p>His tutor only just agreed, giving him a ''narrow pass.'' The tutor liked Warhol, so Westie's next piece was a stylized Irn-Bru bottle against a custard-yellow background. The mark was more favorable, sealing (though he couldn't have known it then, of course) Westie's fate.</p>
        <p>He was in his final year now and had almost completed the portfolio for his degree show. It struck him only recently that there was something odd about the whole notion of a degree show: if you studied politics or philosophy, you didn't attach your essays to the walls for strangers to read. If you were going to be a veterinarian, you didn't have the general public watching as you put some poor animal to the knife. But every art and design college in the land expected its students to show off their shortcomings to the world. Westie's space had already been allocated -- deep in the bowels of the college building on Lauriston Place, next to a sculptor who worked with straw and a video artist whose main claim to fame was a 30-minute stop-motion animation of a slowly lactating breast.</p>
        <p>''I know my place,'' was all Westie said.</p>
        <p>Influenced (retrospectively) by Banksy, and spurred on by his experience with the Warholesque Irn-Bru bottle, Westie's specialty was pastiche. He would copy a Constable landscape but add just the tiniest idiosyncrasy: a crushed beer can (almost his signature, fellow students said) or a scrap of windblown rubbish. A Stubbs painting of a proud stallion might feature a small aircraft in the distant sky. In Westie's version of Raeburn's ''Reverend Walker Skating,'' the only perceptible difference was that the man of the cloth now found himself sporting a black eye. One of his tutors had gone on at length about ''anachronism in art,'' seeming to think it a good thing, but others had accused him of simple copying -- ''which is by no means the same as art, merely good draftsmanship.''</p>
        <p>All Westie knew was that he had a marketable-sounding nickname and only a few more weeks to go before the end of term. Which meant he should either be applying for postgraduate places or else looking for a job. His girlfriend wanted him to become a graphic artist, meaning comic books. She worked front-of-house at a cinema and reckoned the way for Westie to become a top Hollywood director was for him to start drawing cartoons. The problem being (as he'd pointed out more than once) that he had no interest in directing films -- she was the one who wanted it.</p>
        <p>''But you're the one with the talent,'' she'd responded, stamping a foot.</p>
        <p>Another day, he told her about a screen academy that was setting up in the city. Her excitement had lasted until a trawl of the net explained the financial outlay.</p>
        <p>''So I only need to work another 10 years and I can afford it,'' she'd said.</p>
        <p>''If I bump up my prices at the degree show. . . . '' Westie began to speculate, but his voice died away. They both knew he was going to sell very little. No matter how good his ''draftsmanship.'' In terms of actual artistry he was still that same ''narrow pass,'' at least in the eyes of the people whose marks counted most.</p>
        <p>When the doorbell sounded, he got to his feet slowly, realizing he'd been staring into space the past half-hour or more. He was meant to be working . . . putting finishing touches . . . surfing the junk shops for cheap gilt frames into which to place his Stubbs, his Constable, his Raeburn. . . .</p>
        <p>Instead of which, he found himself opening the door to one of those people whose marks counted most: Prof. Robert Gissing, asking to come in.</p>
        <p>The professor wasn't alone. He'd brought two friends, introduced them as exactly that: ''two friends.'' No names, and Westie didn't know the faces. Dealers perhaps, here to make a pre-emptive bid on his degree show? He didn't think so. Gissing took charge and gestured for them to sit. One of the visitors made to remove the covering-sheet from the sofa.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't if I were you,'' Westie warned. ''Got it from a Dumpster . . . a few interesting stains.''</p>
        <p>''And a strong whiff of turps,'' the visitor decided.</p>
        <p>''To cover the more interesting smells,'' Westie apologized. There were smiles all round at this, but then a silence descended. Westie wasn't sure why. ''I'd offer tea or something,'' he apologized, ''but there's no milk. . . .''</p>
        <p>Gissing waved this aside, then rubbed his hands together, making eye contact with the more handsome visitor. It was this visitor who eventually spoke.</p>
        <p>''What we'd like to do,'' he said, ''is help you buy yourself a new sofa. And maybe a few other bits and pieces besides.''</p>
        <p>''You're in the market for a painting?'' Westie shifted a little. ''I didn't think the professor was my biggest fan.''</p>
        <p>''I'm a fan,'' Gissing said with a thin smile. ''Enough of a fan that I could see to it you pass the course with distinction.''</p>
        <p>''There'd be a cash incentive, too, of course,'' the talkative visitor said.</p>
        <p>''Well, I'd be happy to show you some of my work.''</p>
        <p>''We already have Professor Gissing's word that your work is up to scratch, Westie.'' The visitor paused. ''Is it O.K. to call you that?''</p>
        <p>''Sure.''</p>
        <p>''But we're not buying 'off the peg,' so to speak.''</p>
        <p>''A commission?'' Westie was almost bouncing on the spot.</p>
        <p>''A secret commission,'' Gissing corrected him. ''No questions asked.''</p>
        <p>But now the handsome visitor was looking at the professor. ''Thing is, Robert,'' he interrupted, ''I can see Westie's not stupid. And the project's hardly going to stay secret, is it? We need Westie to be part of it, and that means trusting him.'' Turning his attention back to the young artist: ''The professor tells me you've got an anarchic streak; you like to poke fun at the art establishment. Is that right?''</p>
        <p>Westie didn't know which answer would be best received, so just shrugged instead.</p>
        <p>''You want me to copy a painting?'' he asked into the silence.</p>
        <p>''Half a dozen, actually,'' the other visitor pipedup. ''All of them from the National Collection.''</p>
        <p>''And it's to be done in secret. . . . '' Westie broke off, eyes widening. ''Has somebody stolen them, is that it? And the gallery doesn't want anyone to know?''</p>
        <p>''I told you he was smart,'' the handsome visitor stated, rising to his feet. ''Come on, Westie, let's show you what we're talking about.''</p>
        <p>The four of them sat at individual desks in Robert Gissing's office. Allan and Mike had introduced themselves to Westie by their first names. Mike wasn't sure why Allan said so little back in Westie's flat -- cold feet perhaps, or maybe it was because Mike had already said that he'd be happy to bankroll the operation. Stood to reason they'd need funds, and he was the one with cash to spare. For a start, he was sure Westie would need paying -- paying for his silence, as well as his expertise.</p>
        <p>''And I hope I'll still be getting a masterpiece on the cheap.''</p>
        <p>''Not that we're doing it for the money,'' Gissing had growled.</p>
        <p>Now, as they sat in semidarkness, Gissing was showing them slides from the collection of the National Gallery, everything from the old masters to Cubism and beyond. On the way over, they explained a little more of the plan to Westie, who slapped his knees, laughing with glee.</p>
        <p>''If I can help, count me in,'' he said between gulps of air.</p>
        <p>Now, as they looked at the slides, he seemed at his ease: one leg crossed over the other, seated so low in his chair he was almost horizontal.</p>
        <p>''I could do that,'' was his refrain.</p>
        <p>Gissing, Allan and Mike had already pored over a number of the exhibits, the ones held in the overflow warehouse. Each had chosen two favorites, but they had to be sure the young artist could cope with the different styles.</p>
        <p>''Shouldn't be too hard,'' Westie said when pressed.</p>
        <p>''You need special paints and brushes? The right age of canvas?''</p>
        <p>Westie shrugged. ''Look, if an expert comes along, they'll spot it eventually. Even an exact copy isn't an exact copy.''</p>
        <p>''Yet some forgers get away with it for years,'' Mike offered.</p>
        <p>Westie nodded. ''But once you bring in the forensic equipment, the carbon-dating, all that stuff . . . well. . . . '' Another shrug.</p>
        <p>''Thing is,'' Allan said quietly, ''the works aren't going to go missing.''</p>
        <p>''Because you're switching them for my copies.'' Westie gave a chuckle. ''You're not really serious, are you? I mean, no disrespect, but you're three establishment guys of a certain age. You're not master-criminal material, and you can't pull off something like this without a bit more firepower.''</p>
        <p>''Meaning?'' Mike asked.</p>
        <p>''Meaning I want in -- not just doing you a few copies. I'm on the team. You want to steal six paintings, might as well make it seven.'' He folded his arms.</p>
        <p>''You understand we're not selling them on? They're never going to hit the open market?''</p>
        <p>''Understood.''</p>
        <p>''And if it ever got out that we'd. . . . ''</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to grass you up,'' Westie said with another laugh. ''I totally agree with the whole crazy setup. It's just that I want to be more than a 'brush for hire.' ''</p>
        <p>''And in return for your services, we hand you a painting?'' Mike asked.</p>
        <p>''I'll earn my painting, Mr. M. I'll also earn the cash you're going to pay me.''</p>
        <p>''How much cash?'' Gissing asked.</p>
        <p>Westie sat forward in his chair. ''Enough to see my girlfriend through film school,'' he said.</p>
        <p>When Westie had gone, there was silence in Gissing's office for a couple of minutes, until Allan cleared his throat.</p>
        <p>''All getting a bit serious, isn't it?''</p>
        <p>''Something we'd do well to remember,'' Gissing muttered. He had switched off the projector and was opening the blinds. ''Worst-case scenario: we all go to jail, our lives ruined.''</p>
        <p>''For the sake of art,'' Allan said with a snort.</p>
        <p>''You bailing out on us, Allan?'' Mike asked quietly.</p>
        <p>''No.''</p>
        <p>''We need to be sure in our own minds why we're prepared to go through with it,'' Gissing added.</p>
        <p>''That's easy,'' Allan countered. ''I want something at home the bank could never have.''</p>
        <p>Gissing gave a soft smile. ''When I retire to Spain, my two go with me. I could be happy all day just looking at them. . . . ''</p>
        <p>Mike studied his two friends but said nothing himself. Didn't think they'd want to hear him say he was bored to high heaven and looking to be challenged for the first time in a long time. And then, of course, there was the Monboddo. . . .</p>
        <p>''Young Westie had a point,'' he said at last. ''Even if there are four of us, it's not going to be easy.'' He looked at Gissing. ''Had a chance to draw up that plan yet?''</p>
        <p>Gissing nodded and reached into his desk drawer. The three men stood over the sheet of paper, holding its corners flat against the table. As a professor and an art historian, Gissing had visited the warehouse dozens of times. Problem was, this made him a known face; dangerous for him to be part of the actual heist. He had, however, drawn a beautifully rendered plan of the site, including guard room, security cameras and alarm buttons.</p>
        <p>''You did this from memory?'' Mike asked, duly impressed.</p>
        <p>''They may have made some changes since my last visit.''</p>
        <p>''But you'll do another recce before we hit the place?'' Allan asked.</p>
        <p>Gissing nodded. ''After which I'll be useful only as the getaway driver.''</p>
        <p>Nods from both the younger men; they'd already been through this.</p>
        <p>''You've been to the Doors Open Day before?'' Mike prompted. Gissing started running his finger along a dotted line on the plan.</p>
        <p>''The route they take,'' he explained. ''Same this year as previous ones, hopefully. Limited to a dozen visitors every hour. Three staff inside, one manning the gatehouse.''</p>
        <p>Mike shared a glance with Allan, the same thought running through their minds: We need more bodies.</p>
        <p>Problem was -- whose?</p>
        <p>Alice Rule was late getting home from the cinema. She was trying to set up a Sunday-evening film club and had been finalizing the direct-mail letter. It would have been nice to walk into the flat and smell supper on the stove, but she knew better than to expect anything like that. No aroma of fresh paint either, and no sign that Westie had collected any frames from the junk shops he'd told her he would be visiting. But as she walked into the living room (even after all these months, she refused to bow to pressure and call it ''the studio''), there was a popping sound, then a spume of foam from the neck of a Champagne bottle.</p>
        <p>''And what exactly are we celebrating?'' Alice asked, aware that it would have been her salary paying for the bubbly Westie was busy pouring into two wineglasses; they didn't look as if he'd bothered to rinse them from the previous night.</p>
        <p>''Some businessmen came to see me,'' he was explaining. ''They want a few of my originals for their offices.''</p>
        <p>''Their offices?''</p>
        <p>''That's right.''</p>
        <p>''What company? Where's the office?''</p>
        <p>Westie proffered a huge wink, which told her he'd already had a few drinks. ''All very hush-hush,'' he confided in a stage whisper.</p>
        <p>''Hush-hush?'' she echoed, accepting her glass. Had a little smile to herself. Westie was terrible at keeping secrets, always blurted out the identity of her birthday and Christmas gifts weeks in advance. She didn't see why this should be any different.</p>
        <p>Especially when she was so intrigued. . . .</p>
        <p>Next week: A debt collector named Hate pays a call.</p>
        <p>THE FUNNY PAGES: III: SUNDAY SERIAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
