<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Spa Town Reclaims Its Glory</title>
    <meta content="03surfacing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/travel/03surfacing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851655"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SURFACING: HEILIGENDAMM, GERMANY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Spas</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Heilgendamm (Germany)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradley, Kimberly</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Surfacing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Germany</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CEFDF1730F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="529" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Spa Town Reclaims Its Glory</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Spa Town Reclaims Its Glory</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIMBERLY BRADLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradley, Kimberly</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kimberly Bradley travel article on resurgence of spa town of Heilgendamm, Germany; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EIGHT miles of barbed-wire security fencing is up. Beach promenades have been scrubbed clean. And when the world leaders from eight industrial countries arrive this week for the G-8 summit, the spa town of Heiligendamm, on Germany's Baltic coast, will have come full circle.</p>
        <p>Founded as Germany's first seaside resort in 1793 by Duke Friedrich Franz I of Mecklenburg-Schwerin, Heiligendamm was once the favored retreat for Europe's noble and elite classes, who were drawn to its blond dunes, wide blue skies and snow-white manors. But that changed after World War II, when the elegant bleached facades faded to gray. Grand lodgings once used by vacationing German kaisers and Russian czars became a sanatorium for Socialist workers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the world leaders from eight industrial countries arrive this week for the G-8 summit, the spa town of Heiligendamm, on Germany’s Baltic coast, will have come full circle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EIGHT miles of barbed-wire security fencing is up. Beach promenades have been scrubbed clean. And when the world leaders from eight industrial countries arrive this week for the G-8 summit, the spa town of Heiligendamm, on Germany's Baltic coast, will have come full circle.</p>
        <p>Founded as Germany's first seaside resort in 1793 by Duke Friedrich Franz I of Mecklenburg-Schwerin, Heiligendamm was once the favored retreat for Europe's noble and elite classes, who were drawn to its blond dunes, wide blue skies and snow-white manors. But that changed after World War II, when the elegant bleached facades faded to gray. Grand lodgings once used by vacationing German kaisers and Russian czars became a sanatorium for Socialist workers.</p>
        <p>The recent turnaround was led by the Kempinski Grand Hotel Heiligendamm (49-38203-7400; www.kempinski-heiligendamm.de), which converted six buildings including the Kurhaus, the duke's original house, into a glittering seaside campus. Opened in 2003, the resort has a 32,000-square-foot spa, a chandeliered ballroom, high-end restaurants and 225 rooms starting at 195 to 295 euros ($267 to $404 at $1.37 to the euro) a night, depending on the season.</p>
        <p>The wedding cake-like resort has become a haunt of celebrities like the fashion designer Wolfgang Joop, the supermodel Nadja Auermann and members of the German national soccer team, as well as less celebrated people. ''We get a lot of young families, or people who come for a weekend from Hamburg or Berlin,'' said Hannelore Neubert, a waitress at the hotel's Baltic Bar.</p>
        <p>Then there was President George W. Bush, who stayed at the Kempinski last July during a 36-hour diplomatic visit to meet with Chancellor Angela Merkel.</p>
        <p>''My kids still talk about 'Georgie,' who went biking without his bodyguards last year,'' said Birgit Koch, who operates a small guesthouse nearby, Gästehaus Koch (Gartenstrasse 1a; 49-38203-63882; www.urlaub-in-heiligendamm.de).</p>
        <p>Heiligendamm isn't just high thread counts and white-gloved concierges. A quiet, natural beauty envelops the town. Sandy beaches extend for miles. Hiking trails crisscross the beech woodlands. And there are lush rolling fields, which visitors can view from the Molli, a vintage train that chugs through fairy-tale forests.</p>
        <p>Farther inland is a freshwater lake, the Conventer Niederung, which draws spagoers and rehab patients to its peat mud, long reputed to have curative properties. Twenty-minute heated mud baths at the Moorbad Bad Doberan (Schwaaner Chaussee 2, Bad Doberan; 49-38203-930; www .moorbad-doberan.de), an old bathhouse that relocated to a modern clinic in 1996, start at 36 euros; weeklong retreats are 735 euros.</p>
        <p>''The landscape is lovely, the air is good, and this area just brims with history,'' said Rainer Grimm, its director.</p>
        <p>There are other signs that Heiligendamm is regaining its glory. A historic horse racing track, Ostsee-Rennbahn (www.ostseerennbahn.de), was once consigned to landfill status. Now there are V.I.P.'s in fancy hats and long gloves sipping Champagne in the summer. And a string of derelict seaside villas near the Kempinski is slated to become regal summer homes and luxury shops.</p>
        <p>''I knew this place when it was falling apart,'' said Frauke Müller, the public relations manager at the Kempinski, which will play host to the G-8 heads of state and their entourages during the summit. ''The whole region's in transformation.''</p>
        <p>SURFACING: HEILIGENDAMM, GERMANY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
