<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Mothers, a Camera And a Look at School Lunch</title>
    <meta content="03topicweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Health; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03topicwe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851777"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CHILD NUTRITION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lunch and Breakfast Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Better School Food (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rubin, Susan P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kalafa, Amy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Charkes, Juli Steadman</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Two Angry Moms (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lunch and Breakfast Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lunch and Breakfast Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE2DD1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="618" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Mothers, a Camera And a Look at School Lunch</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Two Mothers, a Camera and a Look at School Lunch</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULI S. CHARKES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Charkes, Juli Steadman</byline>
      <dateline>BEDFORD</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Susan Rubin of Bedford, NY, and Amy Kalafa, filmmaker from Weston, Conn, who have produced Two Angry Moms, 90-minute documentary aimed at convincing parents, schools and legislators to improve school lunches; Rubin, who formed advocacy group Better School Food, says children are at mercy of schools that are harming their health, impairing their ability to learn and jeopardizing their economic future; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN her quest to improve the quality of food in America's public schools, Susan P. Rubin has tried several tactics. She has emptied a bag of vending machine items onto a principal's desk; she has delivered impassioned testimony to members of the Institute of Medicine of the National Academies in Washington while holding up potato chips and lollipops; and she has sneaked cafeteria food out of her children's school after being barred from showing up without an appointment.</p>
        <p>But her latest strategy may be her most effective: ''Two Angry Moms,'' a 90-minute documentary featuring Ms. Rubin and directed by the other angry mom, Amy Kalafa, a filmmaker from Weston, Conn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bedford.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN her quest to improve the quality of food in America's public schools, Susan P. Rubin has tried several tactics. She has emptied a bag of vending machine items onto a principal's desk; she has delivered impassioned testimony to members of the Institute of Medicine of the National Academies in Washington while holding up potato chips and lollipops; and she has sneaked cafeteria food out of her children's school after being barred from showing up without an appointment.</p>
        <p>But her latest strategy may be her most effective: ''Two Angry Moms,'' a 90-minute documentary featuring Ms. Rubin and directed by the other angry mom, Amy Kalafa, a filmmaker from Weston, Conn.</p>
        <p>The film presents the good (a schoolyard in Katonah where students grow their own vegetables), the bad (chips and soda for lunch), and the ugly (what it is really like inside a school cafeteria kitchen).</p>
        <p>''This film is for all the women in every town of Westchester and beyond who are banging their heads against the wall,'' Ms. Rubin, 47, a former dentist, said last month from her office in Bedford, where she runs a nutrition counseling practice and lives nearby with her husband and three daughters, ages 16, 14 and 9.</p>
        <p>''I used to go into schools and nurseries and do tooth talks,'' she said. ''And I would be just shocked at what kids were eating.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Rubin formed an advocacy group, Better School Food, whose membership has grown to 750 in two years. In her office last month, days before a screening in Fairfield, Conn. -- another is scheduled this fall at the Jacob Burns Film Center in Pleasantville -- Ms. Rubin addressed what she hopes parents will take away from the movie: that students are at the mercy of schools that are harming their health, impairing their ability to learn and jeopardizing their economic future.</p>
        <p>''This is a national security issue,'' she said. ''Without adequate nutrition, we will not have future leaders.''</p>
        <p>Ready at her fingertips are the alarming statistics: Since 1980 obesity rates have doubled among children and tripled among adolescents, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. The film notes the growing number of children with asthma and allergies, which some experts believe is linked to diet.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rubin said she was encouraged in April when Gov. Eliot Spitzer proposed the Healthy Food Act, which would essentially eliminate most junk food from schools and replace it with fruits and vegetables.</p>
        <p>Not all schools share Ms. Rubin's alarm. ''This district works hard to include everyone's voice at the table,'' said Martin M. Fitzgerald, the principal of the Robert E. Bell Middle School in Chappaqua. ''But there are sometimes parents who can be frustrated by the pace of change.</p>
        <p>''There are many challenges to take into account when planning school lunch, including the eating habits of children. We promote health, but it's not as obvious as people think.''</p>
        <p>The Katonah-Lewisboro School District is featured in ''Two Angry Moms'' as an undisputed success. With Ms. Rubin's encouragement, the district changed its lunch policy, even hiring an outside chef to train food service staff.</p>
        <p>''We went from refrying processed chicken nuggets to grilling fresh chicken breasts and making homemade apple crisp,'' said Donna D. Walsh, a member of the Katonah-Lewisboro Board of Education.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rubin and Ms. Kalafa plan to spend the summer trying to raise money for the film's national distribution in the fall and responding to media requests. ''There is no question there is a tipping point about to happen,'' Ms. Rubin said. ''It's all coming to a crucial crossroads where parents, schools and legislators have to connect the dots between the health of their children and what they are eating.''</p>
        <p>CHILD NUTRITION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
