<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Company for an Only Child, and for Parents, Peace of Mind</title>
    <meta content="03only" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/03only.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851988"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EFDB1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1447" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Company for an Only Child, and for Parents, Peace of Mind</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Company for an Only Child, and for Parents, Peace of Mind</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY</byline>
      <dateline>PARSIPPANY, N.J.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It would have been an innocent picture: Katie Hall, age 9, enjoying an outing with her mother and a dozen children like her, playing on the plastic slides of a Fuddruckers restaurant at dinnertime.</p>
        <p>But Katie, who only sometimes wishes she had a sibling, and would prefer a brother because ''girls are more sensitive, and if you hurt a boy's feelings he wouldn't get as upset,'' politely requested not to be photographed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Support groups are popping up for the parents of single children.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It would have been an innocent picture: Katie Hall, age 9, enjoying an outing with her mother and a dozen children like her, playing on the plastic slides of a Fuddruckers restaurant at dinnertime.</p>
        <p>But Katie, who only sometimes wishes she had a sibling, and would prefer a brother because ''girls are more sensitive, and if you hurt a boy's feelings he wouldn't get as upset,'' politely requested not to be photographed.</p>
        <p>''Because everyone will know I'm an only child,'' she said. ''They'd think I'm spoiled.''</p>
        <p>The percentage of women having only one child has nearly doubled over a generation, according to census figures, a trend experts attribute to a larger number of women working full time; delayed child-bearing and infertility; divorce; concerns about the environmental effects of large families and perhaps the desire of hyper-parents to focus intently on a singleton rather than feeling harried with several.</p>
        <p>But in some upper-middle-class circles, three has become the new two, four the new three -- or so it seems to trend watchers and some parents of only children. Which leaves one as a pretty lonely number for some here at Fuddruckers, who complain that they face ever more pressure -- from relatives, nosybodies, and their own children -- to produce siblings.</p>
        <p>And for every societal pressure, it seems, there is an equal and opposite support group: in this case, the Mothers of Only Children of Northern New Jersey, whose monthly meetings alternate between child-centered play dates and parents' nights out. It is one of several that have sprung up -- in Northern California, an offshoot of Las Madres Neighborhood Playgroups has attracted 20 members since it was formed in April -- along with Web sites and online discussion groups devoted to all things only.</p>
        <p>A magazine called Only Child, which features articles on caring for aging parents solo along with profiles of famous siblingless people like Robin Williams and Rudolph W. Giuliani, has had a spurt in circulation this year. Its 2004 book, ''The Seven Common Sins of Parenting an Only Child'' (which include overindulging, overprotecting, and overpraising) is nearing a second printing and is being translated into a sixth language, Korean.</p>
        <p>While having one child -- i.e., living in a household with just one easily overridden opinion on what video to watch, with the ability to get out the door in under 10 minutes, and without pinching fights in the back seat during long car trips -- might not seem like a grievous condition, there is a surprising amount to commiserate about.</p>
        <p>The parents in the group trade tips on vacation destinations that attract children, how to be a toddler's main playmate, and what to say to strangers at the supermarket who ask questionable questions like, ''Why bother having kids if you're only going to have one?''</p>
        <p>One favorite comeback: ''They're children, not potato chips.''</p>
        <p>They share their worries -- Lori Munk, of Livingston, said of 5-year-old Samantha, ''She wants to play with other kids more than anything else in the world'' -- and shore one another up by emphasizing the upsides.</p>
        <p>''She's comfortable with adults because she's used to adult conversation every night,'' Liza Bianchi-Keil said of her 4-year-old daughter, Hope, at a recent support group meeting at a coffee shop in West Caldwell. ''She talks about her day, but she's also talking about our day.''</p>
        <p>Many of the only children at the indoor play space at Fuddruckers seemed largely oblivious to the notion that they might somehow be lacking something (''I have a dog,'' Samantha Munk explained cheerfully). It's the parents who need reassurance.</p>
        <p>No matter that numerous studies by psychologists and sociologists have shown that only children turn out just fine. Really.</p>
        <p>Various studies have found that only children are no more prone to divorce or depression than other people. And as adults, only sons are more likely to describe themselves as ''very happy'' than men with brothers or sisters. Only children also have a slight advantage in terms of vocabulary and math readiness over their siblinged counterparts, though ''by the time they're 25 or so, it's pretty much dissipated,'' according to Toni L. Falbo, a psychology professor at the University of Texas at Austin who has studied only children for decades.</p>
        <p>''The need for a parents' support group has always struck me as a bit amusing,'' said Professor Falbo, who is an only child and who became interested in studying the subject after teachers and relatives repeatedly told her she did not seem like one. (''I began to wonder what they were talking about,'' she recalled.)</p>
        <p>''Support groups are for alcoholics, or obese people, and it suggests that being an only child is a disease,'' she added. ''Yet that's a way it has been looked at historically.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, G. Stanley Hall, considered a founder of child psychology, declared in 1898 that ''being an only child is a disease in itself.''</p>
        <p>Such biases still show up in subtle ways.</p>
        <p>''People say when are you going to have children, or how many children do you have, not do you have a child,'' Professor Falbo said. ''It's always in the plural, and it builds into a way of thinking that children come in multiples, not just one.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps this reflects the unspoken truth that if each couple had only one child, the human race would eventually die off (unless, of course, there are multiple couplings per person). Maybe people love their siblings so much they cannot bear to think of anyone living life without one. Or could it be a little transference: Parents assume their only children need support when in fact they are the ones feeling isolated.</p>
        <p>At a parents' night out in April, for instance, Mary Ann Paone, a teacher from Chatham, remarked how hard it can be ''to run around dressed up as princesses on weekends.''</p>
        <p>The increase in worry about only children comes amid an actual increase in only children.</p>
        <p>Census figures from 2004, the latest year statistics are available, show that 17.4 percent of women ages 40 to 44 had one child. In 1976, the percentage of women in that age bracket with one child was 9.6 percent. The percentage of women in the same age group without any children also nearly doubled in that period, to 19.3 from 10.2.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, large families declined: The percentage of women with three children fell to 18.1 from 22.7 in 1976, and the number of women with four children fell to 7.4 percent from 15.8 percent.</p>
        <p>Over all, the census shows, women approaching the end of their childbearing years in 2004 had an average of 1.9 children, compared with 3.1 for their 1976 counterparts.</p>
        <p>But regardless of what the statistics say, Katie Hall's mother, Jean Cowan, a teacher who lives in Montclair and started the New Jersey group about four years ago, said she felt that one-child families were not so common in her circle.</p>
        <p>''In my experience it's more like 10 percent'' of families having one child, she said.</p>
        <p>So the parents, mostly mothers, gather, and discuss what to say when asked at the grocery store, as little Hope Keil was, ''So, when's mommy going to have a little sister for you?''</p>
        <p>It's a question Hope has also asked. Joanne Kowalski, one of the group's organizers, tried to reassure Hope's mother, saying that her own daughter, Ruth, often used to ask that when she was 4, but seldom does now that she is 6.</p>
        <p>''So I have to deal with this another two years,'' Ms. Bianchi-Keil moaned.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kowalski, who lives here in Parsippany and is a stay-at-home mother, advised: ''I would say, 'I don't think we're going to have any more babies, Ruth,' and I would try to divert her to another topic.''</p>
        <p>Deena Dworkin, a human resources consultant who lives in West Orange, said of her 5-year-old son, ''I think I'm more concerned about him being alone than he is.'' Still, she added, ''I feel like I can focus on one child, and one set of issues, and I don't have to deal with siblings.''</p>
        <p>Carol Lippincott, a stay-at-home mother who lives in Montclair with her husband and 5-year-old son, said she definitely appreciated her family size.</p>
        <p>''I see families divide and conquer when they have a lot of children of different ages, with one adult going with one child, and the other going with the other,'' she said. ''The whole family is split up over the weekend.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Paone, the mother who admitted tiring of playing dress-up with 3-year-old Alyssa, smiled as she watched her daughter play with the other outgoing onlies at the restaurant.</p>
        <p>''Other people are telling her what to do, which is good,'' she said. ''She's usually telling other people what to do.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
