<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yet Again, Camping's Loss Is Land Preservation's Gain</title>
    <meta content="03topicliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03topicli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851738"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OPEN SPACE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Camps and Camping</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">East Hampton (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boys and Girls Harbor (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Camps and Camping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E1D71430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="645" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yet Again, Camping's Loss Is Land Preservation's Gain</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Yet Again, Camping’s Loss Is Land Preservation’s Gain</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Officials from Boys and Girls Harbor confirm negotiations are under way to sell 28-acre Boys Harbor Camp, summer retreat in East Hampton, NY, for low-income children and adults that was closed last June, to Suffolk County and Town of East Hampton; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANOTHER summer camp may soon become publicly owned open space in eastern Suffolk County, where the sale of camps that have become increasingly expensive to operate has helped local governments meet land-preservation goals.</p>
        <p>Latest on the list is the 28-acre Harbor Camp and Environmental Center, also known as Boys Harbor, situated since 1954 on Springy Banks Road near Three Mile Harbor in East Hampton.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANOTHER summer camp may soon become publicly owned open space in eastern Suffolk County, where the sale of camps that have become increasingly expensive to operate has helped local governments meet land-preservation goals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANOTHER summer camp may soon become publicly owned open space in eastern Suffolk County, where the sale of camps that have become increasingly expensive to operate has helped local governments meet land-preservation goals.</p>
        <p>Latest on the list is the 28-acre Harbor Camp and Environmental Center, also known as Boys Harbor, situated since 1954 on Springy Banks Road near Three Mile Harbor in East Hampton.</p>
        <p>The camp, a part of Boys and Girls Harbor, a nonprofit group in Manhattan founded in 1937 by the philanthropist Anthony Drexel Duke when he was a college student, had been a summer retreat for low-income children and young adults from the city until it closed last June. Mr. Duke has a summer home nearby.</p>
        <p>Officials from Boys and Girls Harbor confirmed last week that negotiations were under way to sell the camp to Suffolk County and the Town of East Hampton. A spokesman for the group declined to say why it decided to sell or whether the camp would reopen elsewhere. He said Mr. Duke was not available.</p>
        <p>Christopher Chapin, a broker at Prudential Douglas Elliman in East Hampton, said the camp property, an expanse of woods and fields, had been listed with his agency for $12 million last year and attracted interest. It abuts 57 acres that Mr. Duke sold to the town and the county for $12 million in 2001.</p>
        <p>Jay Schneiderman, a Republican Suffolk County legislator from Montauk, said he expected that Boys and Girls Harbor would accept the offer from the county and the town. Neither the town nor the county would say what it had offered for the property.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schneiderman said that while he welcomed preservation, he lamented ''the lost opportunity for underprivileged kids to experience the great beauty of the East End.''</p>
        <p>In a sale in 2006, the Girl Scouts of Nassau County agreed to sell Camp Tekakwitha, a 65-acre property along Peconic Bay, to the Town of Southampton for $16.5 million.</p>
        <p>Donna L. Ceravolo, the group's executive director, said some of the proceeds had been used to upgrade Camp Blue Bay, a 170-acre camp in the Springs hamlet of East Hampton that the Nassau Girl Scouts continue to own and operate. She said there were no plans to sell that property, one of the largest remaining pieces of open space in East Hampton.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ceravolo said upkeep and insurance for two camps had been a burden, particularly because the Girl Scouts' interest in camping had been ''on the decline for quite a while.''</p>
        <p>In an earlier sale that saved woodlands within the 53,000-acre core of the Long Island pine barrens from becoming a golf course, the Nassau County Council of Boy Scouts agreed in 1996 to sell 147 acres at Camp Wauwepex near the Calverton National Cemetery in Riverhead to the state for $1.8 million. The council retained ownership of more than 400 acres, where the camp still operates.</p>
        <p>Edward A. McLaughlin, the scout executive of what is now called the Theodore Roosevelt Council, said $1.5 million in sale proceeds went into an endowment fund for programs and camp upkeep and improvements.</p>
        <p>A long-gone summer escape for city boys, Camp Carey in Jamesport, is indirectly linked to the creation of Long Island's newest state park, the Jamesport State Park and Preserve.</p>
        <p>Founded by William L. Carey in 1901, the camp was operated as a Boys' Club of New York on bluffs overlooking Long Island Sound. The Long Island Lighting Company bought the property in 1973, but its plan to build two nuclear power plants there was rejected by the state.</p>
        <p>Keyspan, Lilco's successor, sold 525 acres that included the former camp to New York in 2002 for $16 million, little more than half its appraised value. A total of 225 acres where camp buildings stood are now the state park; the sale also permanently preserved 300 acres of farmland.</p>
        <p>OPEN SPACE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
