<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>COMICS</title>
    <meta content="Hodgman.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/books/review/Hodgman-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851610"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Summer Reading"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Comic Books and Strips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cartoons and Cartoonists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comic Books and Strips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cartoons and Cartoonists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Deitch, Kim</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bertozzi, Nick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EFD61630F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>COMICS</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Comics</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John Hodgman</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Few ''underground'' cartoonists deserve that subterranean title so fully as Kim Deitch. He was there at the beginning of the movement, drawing for The East Village Other in 1967, and his work retains much of that psychedelic, R. Crumb-like earthiness.</p>
        <p>But also: He's constantly digging, churning the inky soil of American pop culture and marveling over the fossils he turns up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Few “underground” cartoonists deserve that subterranean title so fully as Kim Deitch, whose work is available in two new collections.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Few ''underground'' cartoonists deserve that subterranean title so fully as Kim Deitch. He was there at the beginning of the movement, drawing for The East Village Other in 1967, and his work retains much of that psychedelic, R. Crumb-like earthiness.</p>
        <p>But also: He's constantly digging, churning the inky soil of American pop culture and marveling over the fossils he turns up.</p>
        <p>In ''The Boulevard of Broken Dreams'' (2002), he constructed a fake but convincing history of early American funny-animal cartoons via the many iterations of Waldo the Cat, the white-gloved, foulmouthed feline muse who has graced (or invaded) his work for 40 years.</p>
        <p>Now in two new books, Shadowland (Fantagraphics, paper, $18.95) and Alias the Cat! (Pantheon, $23), Deitch draws a dark, twisting line from the carnival sideshow to New Jersey and its brief tenure as the movie serial capital of the United States, from lost comic strips to urban myths to fairy tales to the provenance of flea market antiques and eBay finds and all the other strange and sometimes forgotten ways we told stories to one another in the last century.</p>
        <p>Collecting 10 tales that previously appeared in publications like Weirdo and Raw, ''Shadowland'' charts the scoundrel's progress of one Al Ledicker from his childhood in his father's patent-medicine show through his own checkered career as whorehouse henchman, carnival kingpin, killer and all-around clown-faced lout. (According to Deitch's introduction, Ledicker's clown makeup, creepily present from boyhood to deathbed, was inspired by John Wayne Gacy's).</p>
        <p>Waldo makes only a cameo here, as a figurine among an array of Ledicker's grotesque sideshow mementos. But the story is a typically Deitchian shaggy-cat tale.</p>
        <p>It begins plainly, touchingly, with Toby the Flying Pig, whose daring leaps from a 50-foot tower were once a highlight of the old Ledicker road show. Each full-page panel is beautiful, almost overwhelming.</p>
        <p>Most cartoonists today don't draw as cartoonishly as Deitch does. All his eyes have those Mickey Mouse-ish white pie slices in them, and his baroquely detailed borders, full of smiling moons and scowling devils, are astonishing in their composition. Meanwhile, Deitch's heavy black-and-white line work illuminates at once the bright attraction of the turn-of-the-century carnival and the unwholesome darkness lurking just beyond the stage. Once Toby is threatened with slaughter, he escapes his pen to take one last suicidal leap. He ends up as a stuffed umbrella stand -- one of the many showbiz victims to have perished under Deitch's hand.</p>
        <p>After this when-pigs-fly introduction, anything goes. Deitch's stories get progressively grander and weirder, flying forward in time to Ledicker's widow's roadside museum of the odd, and back again to his father's adventures with a group of tiny mystics who are as obsessed with old silent films as Deitch is, and then up to the stars, where the whole drama is observed by aliens the size of kewpie dolls.</p>
        <p>It's crazy, invigorating stuff, but it's also a mystery: how can an artist so clearly in control of his work go so fully off the rails? It's a pattern that is repeated in darker, more startling and disorienting hues in ''Alias the Cat!''</p>
        <p>''Alias,'' which collects more recent work, starts out calm. The book is presented as autobiography, with Deitch speaking directly to the reader. He's a mature old duffer, his vestigial counterculture ponytail offset by the cheesy watch-hanging-from-the-belt-loop badge of middle age. He lives with his loving wife, Pam. Instead of kids they have cats and obsessions, and they go on flea-market quests for what Deitch calls ''the stuff of dreams.'' He loves old silent movie stills; she scours eBay for black cat dolls, especially the countless Felix knockoffs that have paraded through film and funny-animal comics.</p>
        <p>It's bad luck for them, because here comes Waldo. Initially drawn in 1967 as Deitch's own subversive take on the Felix/funny-animal tradition -- big smile, white gloves, exposed genitals -- Waldo, we realize, especially in this volume, has grown into perhaps Deitch's most unhealthy obsession.</p>
        <p>Once Deitch and Pam stumble across an ancient Waldo doll at a flea market, the story quickly goes down the rabbit hole. Deitch relates a psychotic old shipwreck tale supposedly told to him by the doll's owner. This indirectly leads him to track down a lost comic strip and movie serial from 1915 featuring a feline-garbed avenger called Alias the Cat, and finally sets him off on a quest for Midgetville, the little-person-proportioned Shangri-La of New Jersey urban legend. Each hidden world leads to the next in a kind of dream logic or, better, flea-market logic: the follow-your-nose path of an eBay addict seeking ever more esoteric finds.</p>
        <p>And behind them all lurks Waldo. Because Deitch never lets up on the queasy conceit of the book: that Waldo is real -- not a character, but an actual bit of cultural ephemera that Deitch accidentally copied. (In fact, he offers $1,000 to anyone who can produce an original Waldo doll.)</p>
        <p>Or else Waldo is an actual potty-mouthed cat demon whom only Deitch and other sages can see. Or else Deitch is just plain crazy.</p>
        <p>Deitch deals with all three possibilities so forthrightly and guilelessly that there are times when it's unclear whether you are reading a fanciful blend of fact and fiction or a massive, Henry Darger-esque bit of brilliant cuckoo.</p>
        <p>''This story ... doesn't come to a neat and tidy conclusion,'' Deitch writes at one point. ''But then I guess that is a key difference between truth and fiction.'' That's a pretty bold bit of unreliable narration, given that the untidy conclusion of ''Alias the Cat!'' finds Deitch finally confronting Waldo in a Midgetville bedroom.</p>
        <p>Waldo, for his part, votes for cuckoo. ''I'd just like to know why any of this,'' Waldo says, berating his creator and holding up part of the book we've just read, ''which is totally irrelevant to anything going on in the world today, should make any difference whatsoever to you! ... You're in the 21st ... century! ... Wake up and smell the coffee!''</p>
        <p>Personally, I hope Deitch doesn't. Like all collectors of ephemera, he charts those strange, enchanting curlicues in our culture that would vanish completely if we failed to look for them. And he makes you dream there is some strangeness left. Presumably that's his real address at the bottom of the $1,000 offer for proof of his illusion. I hope someday to have a reason to collect.</p>
        <p>E. C. Segar's ''Popeye: 'I Yam What I Yam!' '' (Fantagraphics, $29.95) is the first in what will presumably be an infinite number of volumes collecting Popeye's comic strip appearances, because of course Popeye goes on and on -- in movies, cartoons, video games and the funny pages -- to this very day.</p>
        <p>But with each sock of Bluto's jaw, the blandly heroic Popeye of today beats down a little further the dim memory of the Popeye born in ''Thimble Theatre'' in 1929.</p>
        <p>At that time, Segar had already been chronicling the Oyl family for 10 years, when the lovable schemer Castor Oyl decided he needed to hire a seaworthy hand for an ocean adventure.</p>
        <p>And then, suddenly, there he is. For a comic strip character, Popeye is, in his earliest incarnation, surprisingly recognizable to us: those misshapen forearms and calves, that ''shipwreck'' of a face (as Olive Oyl calls it), his squinty brow and enormous chin are already present and instantly iconic in the first panel. To paraphrase Popeye's own mangled, existential cry: He is what he is -- but is that all he is?</p>
        <p>For this Popeye is at once more ornery and more pathetic than the binary spinach-on/</p>
        <p>spinach-off version who would replace him</p>
        <p>on the cartoon screen. In 1929, Popeye</p>
        <p>needed no dietary aids to knock a villain off the deck, and he could absorb a rain of bullets to save his friends. Yet he's also strangely</p>
        <p>vulnerable to Castor's continued ''insulks,'' both fist-happy and oddly insecure.</p>
        <p>''Why did you strike my butler?'' one gentleman asks him. At this moment, Popeye expresses his greatest peak of emotion: turning and staring angrily the other way.</p>
        <p>''I don't need no reason,'' he replies. ''I socks 'em where I sees 'em, an' I leaves 'em where I socks 'em -- an' tha's that.'' O.K., then.</p>
        <p>He's not exactly a funny animal, but a kind of noble beast that Castor is constantly trying to civilize. From the beginning, Popeye's and Castor's seesawing contempt and affection for each other made them a great comic duo: the schemer and the muscle. But they are doomed. Each time Castor calls Popeye from the docks to send him to a tutor or invites him to join his detective agency, Popeye inevitably fouls up his friend's charity by socking someone in the face.</p>
        <p>What Castor doesn't seem to notice is that Popeye eventually stops going back to the docks. Suddenly he's living with the Oyls, moving in on Olive's affection and taking over the whole strip. Within a year, the sheer force of his ''personaliky'' would cast the decade's worth of ''Thimble Theatre'' strips that preceded him so thoroughly into the realm of trivia that they aren't even collected here. In some ways this is precisely the bit of lost history Deitch hopes to preserve: scanned from original newspaper clippings that otherwise had been yellowing somewhere or another, this book documents not only the birth of a great American comic character, but also, in a smaller measure, the death of a great straight man.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in the early 20th century, Pablo Picasso was developing Cubism by reading ''The Katzenjammer Kids.''</p>
        <p>''You miss the simple of it,'' Picasso explains to his dismissive friend Georges Braque in Nick Bertozzi's art-history mystery The Salon (St. Martin's Griffin, paper, $19.95). Defending his beloved comic strip (Gertrude Stein, it is said, supplied</p>
        <p>him with copies), Picasso-via-Bertozzi pronounces: ''Easy to see ... read fast ... no try to be thing of beauty. Is thing of beauty.''</p>
        <p>Like Deitch's work, ''The Salon'' blurs the frame between fiction and history, art and reality. Drawn in oblong comic-strip panels and colored in beautiful blue- and rose-period hues, it follows Picasso, Braque, the Steins (Gertrude and her brother Leo) and an assortment of other moderns as they try to solve a series of murders plaguing Paris in 1907. The solution lies in a set of newly discovered Gauguins and a bottle of rare absinthe that allows the artists to literally enter the paintings to search for clues -- or, in the case of Apollinaire, to frolic with Gauguin's Tahitian muses. That Apollinaire!</p>
        <p>This is an amusing and well-played game, and often eerie, though there is something a little self-serving about Bertozzi's use of Picasso to defend comics: his transformation of paintings into immersive cartoons, and of their artists into gumshoes -- it's the pulpification of high art.</p>
        <p>But this is more than made up for by Bertozzi's deft characterization. I've never understood Cubism as well as when Bertozzi's Braque and Picasso are first discussing it on a train, with Braque theorizing about simultaneous points of view and Picasso protesting that he was merely drawing the reflection in the train window.</p>
        <p>Throughout the book, Picasso is a fireplug, always ready to smack Matisse in the face, always championing the brusque, intuitive punch of art over Braque's philosophical deliberations. There's something so winning about their friendship in ''The Salon,'' something so Castor-and-Popeye-ish, that you hardly need a luminous, absinthe-colored murder scene to enjoy it.</p>
        <p>The same goes for Marvin and Herbert of ''Dungeon,'' the comic written by Lewis Trondheim and Joann Sfar and illustrated chiefly by them with the occasional help of others from their ''nouvelle génération'' of talented French cartoonists.</p>
        <p>The publisher NBM has been releasing Joe Johnson's English translations in twice yearly albums, the most recent of which is Dungeon Parade, Vol. 1: A Dungeon Too Many (NBM, paper, $9.95).</p>
        <p>I could begin by telling you that the ''Dungeon'' series is an ambitious, surprising epic, its two dozen or so existing episodes scattered over three generations of characters, with the promise of possibly hundreds more episodes to come. But eventually I'm going to just have to come out and say it: ''Dungeon'' is about a duck and a dragon going on adventures in a Dungeons &amp; Dragons-style fantasy realm called Terra Amata. The humor can be biting and sly: the Dungeon, a gigantic castle-and-catacombs complex designed to part foolish adventurers from their gold, is run by its keeper -- some kind of chubby tern, I think -- with all the quotidian officelike dreariness of, well, ''The Office.'' But there are flatulence jokes and other low bits of slapstick as well. This is pure funny-animal stuff. (Though because it is French, it would be more accurate to say funny, sexy animal stuff.) And precisely because it is so light and warmhearted, the moments of melancholy and actual profundity reach into your chest, pull out your heart and keep it hostage.</p>
        <p>That's what literally happens to Herbert, the craven, titular bird of the book DUNGEON, VOL. 1: Duck Heart (NBM, paper, $14.95), probably the best entry point into this world. Herbert is a minor Dungeon functionary charged with finding a suitable barbarian to go on a secret mission for the dungeon keeper. When he accidentally causes the chosen candidate to die, he ends up taking his place. Leaving his heart behind to ensure his return (it's taken from him and kept alive by the keeper's magician, some kind of vulture, I think), Herbert sets out on a dangerous quest with a sword he cannot draw and a companion, the dragon Marvin, who only pities him.</p>
        <p>That doesn't last, of course, because during their wacky adventures the two naturally become best friends. This would be banal if it weren't accomplished with such warmth, and if the books didn't bristle with great ideas and ingenious narrative devices: a giantess whose tears take days to fall, or a fablelike test by which Herbert must learn to fight his way through 10,000 goblin doors, the numbers of goblin guards doubling at each step until the battle of the final door, which lasts for days on end.</p>
        <p>At one point, Marvin commandeers a giant flying chicken to escape an army bent on killing him. He soon asks the chicken's pilot why their flight has become erratic. Only in the next panel do you see that the chicken has been beheaded by a cannon. Naturally it continues to fly -- a chicken with its head cut off -- for several more pages, though very poorly. It's a great big dumb visual gag, but it's pulled off with such casual smarts that it's exciting and sublime.</p>
        <p>Very occasionally the translation feels a little off, and the pacing so brisk and breezy that you wonder if you missed a page of exposition. In fact, you may be missing entire books. Throwaway details like the dungeon keeper's pining for Alexandra will be lost on you if you have not read the cycle of ''Early Years'' stories recounting the keeper's own childhood. Similarly, if you read the ''Twilight'' stories telling of the Dungeon's downfall, you won't know why one fond character has gone so horribly wrong (that story has yet to be written in French or English), but you will feel unaccountably sad. Unaccountably, because these are silly animals. Sad, because they, like you, are only human.</p>
        <p>One final note. It annoys me to have to rely on that old cliché of comics criticism, but in this case I have no choice: comic books aren't just for kids anymore. I do not say this so much to warn you of mature themes in these books (they exist), but to alert you that the funny animals of ''Dungeon'' are frequently having sex with one another.</p>
        <p>One villainous cat, with his wisecracks and lack of, er, modesty, seems almost a direct homage to Waldo. But more, these characters are unashamed. It's rare to read a contemporary comic that is unconcerned with redefining the form and instead concentrates so nakedly on having a good time. The ''Dungeon'' series doesn't try to be beautiful, to paraphrase that funny animal Picasso: it simply is.</p>
        <p>Summer Reading John Hodgman is the author of ''The Areas of My Expertise.'' He writes regularly about comics and graphic novels for the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">John Hodgman is the author of ''The Areas of My Expertise.'' He writes regularly about comics and graphic novels for the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
