<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vive le Tour? Bien Sur!</title>
    <meta content="603MAIN.txt" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Play" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/sports/playmagazine/0603play-main.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851583"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE MAIN EVENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tour de France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tour De France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Discovery Channel</org>
        <org class="online_producer">T-Mobile</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Armstrong, Lance</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Vinokourov, Alexander</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ullrich, Jan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Landis, Floyd</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDA1F31F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1831" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vive le Tour? Bien Sur!</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Vive le Tour? Bien Sur!</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Edward Pickering</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since Lance Armstrong pedaled triumphantly into the sunset in 2005, his sport seems to have embarked on a sincere and surprisingly efficient effort to destroy itself, most notably by a theatrical series of drug scandals. Though we're shocked -- shocked! -- that anybody in this toughest of endurance races would illicitly boost his octane, it's hard not to be impressed by the magnitude of the bamboozlement. Exhibit A: Operation Puerto, a Spanish investigation that began in May 2006 and that uncovered, among other violations, a freezer brimming with 223 bags of blood from over 100 top riders, plus coded notes tracking their ''treatments.'' Say what you will about the seriousness of Balco: until the day when a sizable chunk of Major League Baseball stars are storing doped blood at the clinic for stretch-run transfusions, American sports still have some catching up to do. All of which leaves us in a dilemma: do we pass grim judgment (a pox on les cheaters!), or sit back on July 7 with a cold sauvignon blanc and toast the world's most grueling, beautiful, unbelievable race? We've made our choice. Ã votre santé!</p>
        <p>1. THE CONTENDERS</p>
        <p>NAME: ALEXANDER VINOKOUROV  NATIONALITY: KAZAKH  AGE: 33  TEAM: ASTANA  BEST FINISH: THIRD IN 2003  PROFILE: He's tougher than a piece of iron, looks meaner than a caged badger and seems not to understand the concept of pain. Vinokourov used to be a support rider, aggressively defending his team leaders, but flowered into a Tour contender when he finished third to Armstrong in 2003. He might have won in 2005 but for a devastating day in the Alps, during which his German T-Mobile teammates Jan Ullrich and Andreas KlÃ</p>
        <p>den refused to let him pull ahead, sparking speculation that only a rider from Deutschland could lead the team. Dissension could be an issue again this year: Astana's loyalties may be split (see below).</p>
        <p>NAME: ANDREAS KLÃ</p>
        <p>DEN  NATIONALITY: GERMAN  AGE: 31  TEAM: ASTANA  BEST FINISH: SECOND IN 2004  PROFILE: KlÃ</p>
        <p>den is reputed to like surfing more than he does cycling, but his results say otherwise (he finished in third place last year). Ever laid-back, he prefers not to attack, but can outlast almost any rider in the Tour, possibly even his teammate Vinokourov.</p>
        <p>NAME: ALEJANDRO VALVERDE  NATIONALITY: SPANISH  AGE: 27  TEAM: CAISSE D'EPARGNE  BEST FINISH: NEVER FINISHED  PROFILE: Valverde is a sprinter who climbs (or a climber who sprints), which in cycling makes him the ultimate multitasker. Nicknamed ''the Unbeatable'' for good reason, Valverde is virtually impossible to outrun in a sprint up any hill. Since this year's Tour includes several mountaintop finishes, he'll give his rivals sleepless nights. His weakness? Crashing. He has yet to make the finish in Paris, though early struggles aren't necessarily a bad sign. It took a certain Texan five Tours -- three of which he didn't finish -- to finally win.</p>
        <p>NAME: OSCAR PEREIRO  NATIONALITY: SPANISH  AGE: 29  TEAM: CAISSE D'EPARGNE  BEST FINISH: SECOND IN 2006  PROFILE: Known as a strong climber, Pereiro has twice finished in the top 10. Last year in the Pyrenees, he swapped the yellow jersey four times with Floyd Landis until losing it for good during Landis's now infamous comeback in the Alps. If Landis is stripped of his victory because of his alleged doping (as of press time, his case was still in arbitration), Pereiro will be named the 2006 champion.</p>
        <p>2.THE LONG SHOTS</p>
        <p>NAME: CARLOS SASTRE</p>
        <p>NATIONALITY: SPANISH</p>
        <p>AGE: 32 TEAM: CSC  BEST FINISH: FOURTH IN 2006  PROFILE: Possibly the shyest man in professional cycling -- he's soft-spoken and sometimes looks ready to burst into tears -- Sastre is devastatingly fast uphill, and the mountain stages are what usually decide the race. Unfortunately, he loses ground during the long, flat time trials.</p>
        <p>NAME: DENIS MENCHOV  NATIONALITY: RUSSIAN  AGE: 29 TEAM: RABOBANK  BEST FINISH: SIXTH IN 2006  PROFILE: Winner of the 2003 maillot blanc (given to the top Tour finisher under age 25), the seemingly tireless Menchov works harder than anyone to keep up with the very best riders.</p>
        <p>NAME: CHRISTOPHE MOREAU  NATIONALITY: FRANCE  AGE: 36 TEAM: AG2R  BEST FINISH: FOURTH IN 2000  PROFILE: The nearest the French have to a contender, he shows up every year with legs as strong as his tactics are unorthodox.</p>
        <p>3. THE CASTAWAYS</p>
        <p>FLOYD LANDIS Last year's winner has filed one appeal after another to overturn his positive drug test. The lawsuit is making the Alec Baldwin-Kim Basinger rift look downright cordial.</p>
        <p>JAN ULLRICH Last year's favorite was linked to the Operation Puerto scandal and banned from the Tour. He retired in April, just before DNA tests proved definitively that his blood was found in bags confiscated in the raid.</p>
        <p>IVAN BASSO Banned in 2006 because of his alleged connection to Operation Puerto, Basso, from Spain, was hired last fall by Team Discovery Channel, the outfit co-owned by Lance Armstrong. In April, Basso quit and later admitted to ''attempted doping'' -- which is to say he didn't inhale.</p>
        <p>TYLER HAMILTON An American rider, he was banned for two years after being suspected of blood doping and now rides for a team owned by a Russian beer magnate. Hamilton is off to a rocky start: he was suspended from the team last month because of, yes, alleged involvement in Operation Puerto.</p>
        <p>4.THE SECOND COMING OF LANCE  DOES ANY AMERICAN HAVE EGO AND TALENT ENOUGH TO STEAL THE SHOW? WELL . . .</p>
        <p>LEVI LEIPHEIMER  AGE: 33  TEAM: DISCOVERY CHANNEL  DOES HE SOUND LIKE LANCE? 5/10.  Despite looking like him (the resemblance is uncanny until Leipheimer takes off his helmet to reveal his shiny-bald head), Leipheimer is a quiet underachiever, while Armstrong was an outspoken overachiever.</p>
        <p>DOES HE RIDE LIKE LANCE? 4/10. Like Armstrong, Leipheimer is a strong climber and time-trialist. But he lacks panache and a killer instinct.</p>
        <p>IS HE THE NEW LANCE? 5/10</p>
        <p>TOM DANIELSON  AGE: 29  TEAM: DISCOVERY CHANNEL  DOES HE SOUND LIKE LANCE? 2/10.  Affable in the extreme. The kind of cyclist you could take home to Mom and Dad.</p>
        <p>DOES HE RIDE LIKE LANCE? 4/10. One of the best climbers in the sport, though cynics say that he, like Leipheimer, could use a spine transplant.</p>
        <p>IS HE THE NEW LANCE? 3/10</p>
        <p>DAVE ZABRISKIE  AGE: 28  TEAM: CSC  DOES HE SOUND LIKE LANCE? 1/10. See Danielson.  DOES HE RIDE LIKE LANCE? 3/10. Depends on the terrain. He can dominate a time trial but struggles in the mountains.</p>
        <p>IS HE THE NEW LANCE? 2/10</p>
        <p>5. THE WILDLIFE</p>
        <p>The Tour would be nothing without the tens of thousands of fanatics who turn up to watch the race. But the seemingly homogeneous crowd lining the road is actually composed of very distinct groups, divided roughly along national lines.</p>
        <p>THE FRENCH  They've been watching the Tour roll by for over a century and will have bagged the prime viewing spots before the dew dries. They are also the best prepared, with tables, chairs, beach umbrellas, radios, food, wine and cultural superiority.  Cheering for: Any rider, so long as he's French.  Danger rating: 1/5</p>
        <p>THE BRITISH  Sunburned, unfashionable, ill-prepared and few in number, these fans of the Tour have precious little to cheer for: no British rider has ever won, and none is likely to do so this year. If they look lost and bewildered, be nice to them.  Cheering for: The Americans, if for no other reason than a shared language. This year's race starts in London, which doesn't make it any more likely that a Briton will dominate.  Danger rating: 0/5</p>
        <p>THE DUTCH  Found only in the Alps, and easy to spot. They wear orange, drink more than is healthy at high altitude (not uncommon at the Tour, no matter the nationality) and crank the Eurodisco at maximum volume for days leading up to the arrival of the peloton.  Cheering for: The predominantly Dutch Rabobank team and life in general.  Danger rating: 3/5</p>
        <p>THE BASQUES  Like the Dutch, they wear orange, but their preferred habitat is the Pyrenees. Roll up your windows when you drive past. Do not engage them.  Cheering for: Their local team, Euskaltel, which hires only Basque riders.  Danger rating: 5/5</p>
        <p>THE AMERICANS  They wear Team Discovery Channel jerseys. The least popular are those asking, ''Which one's Lance?''  Cheering for: The red, white and blue, baby!  Danger rating: 2/5</p>
        <p>6. THE ADHD TOUR  Three weeks is a long time to follow a race. To appease the impatient, here are the two stages you have to see.</p>
        <p>STAGE 8: SUNDAY, JULY 15, LE GRAND-BORNAND TO TIGNES The race hits the Alps with three major climbs that take the riders straight uphill for more than 40 miles, with only short pauses for breath on the frenetic downhills. It's here in the mountains where the contenders will emerge.</p>
        <p>STAGE 15: MONDAY, JULY 23, FOIX TO LOUDENVIELLE The second day in the Pyrenees is a five-mountain roller coaster ride that finishes with an eight-mile headlong descent. The riders will be shattered from the previous day's difficult stage, so watch for crashes. Any rider with serious designs on the yellow jersey will use this stage as a springboard to escape from his rivals. By day's end, the Tour's winner may not be known, but the list of possibilities will be down to the final names.</p>
        <p>7. LES SCANDALES!  Cheating at the Tour de France is a time-honored tradition.</p>
        <p>1904  Riders were beaten up by rival fans. The 1903 winner, Maurice Garin, was driven off the course. At least one rider was caught receiving a tow (he held on, with his teeth, to a cork wired to a car). Henri Cornet accused his rivals of stuffing his chicken with sleeping pills. He survived to win the race, but only after the four riders ahead of him were disqualified.</p>
        <p>1906  History has otherwise forgotten Maurice CarrÃ</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Drug cheats. Crazy fans. Men in tights pedaling furiously. It’s time for the Tour de France.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Since Lance Armstrong pedaled triumphantly into the sunset in 2005, his sport seems to have embarked on a sincere and surprisingly efficient effort to destroy itself, most notably by a theatrical series of drug scandals. Though we're shocked -- shocked! -- that anybody in this toughest of endurance races would illicitly boost his octane, it's hard not to be impressed by the magnitude of the bamboozlement. Exhibit A: Operation Puerto, a Spanish investigation that began in May 2006 and that uncovered, among other violations, a freezer brimming with 223 bags of blood from over 100 top riders, plus coded notes tracking their ''treatments.'' Say what you will about the seriousness of Balco: until the day when a sizable chunk of Major League Baseball stars are storing doped blood at the clinic for stretch-run transfusions, American sports still have some catching up to do. All of which leaves us in a dilemma: do we pass grim judgment (a pox on les cheaters!), or sit back on July 7 with a cold sauvignon blanc and toast the world's most grueling, beautiful, unbelievable race? We've made our choice. Ã votre santé!</p>
        <p>1. THE CONTENDERS</p>
        <p>NAME: ALEXANDER VINOKOUROV  NATIONALITY: KAZAKH  AGE: 33  TEAM: ASTANA  BEST FINISH: THIRD IN 2003  PROFILE: He's tougher than a piece of iron, looks meaner than a caged badger and seems not to understand the concept of pain. Vinokourov used to be a support rider, aggressively defending his team leaders, but flowered into a Tour contender when he finished third to Armstrong in 2003. He might have won in 2005 but for a devastating day in the Alps, during which his German T-Mobile teammates Jan Ullrich and Andreas KlÃ</p>
        <p>den refused to let him pull ahead, sparking speculation that only a rider from Deutschland could lead the team. Dissension could be an issue again this year: Astana's loyalties may be split (see below).</p>
        <p>NAME: ANDREAS KLÃ</p>
        <p>DEN  NATIONALITY: GERMAN  AGE: 31  TEAM: ASTANA  BEST FINISH: SECOND IN 2004  PROFILE: KlÃ</p>
        <p>den is reputed to like surfing more than he does cycling, but his results say otherwise (he finished in third place last year). Ever laid-back, he prefers not to attack, but can outlast almost any rider in the Tour, possibly even his teammate Vinokourov.</p>
        <p>NAME: ALEJANDRO VALVERDE  NATIONALITY: SPANISH  AGE: 27  TEAM: CAISSE D'EPARGNE  BEST FINISH: NEVER FINISHED  PROFILE: Valverde is a sprinter who climbs (or a climber who sprints), which in cycling makes him the ultimate multitasker. Nicknamed ''the Unbeatable'' for good reason, Valverde is virtually impossible to outrun in a sprint up any hill. Since this year's Tour includes several mountaintop finishes, he'll give his rivals sleepless nights. His weakness? Crashing. He has yet to make the finish in Paris, though early struggles aren't necessarily a bad sign. It took a certain Texan five Tours -- three of which he didn't finish -- to finally win.</p>
        <p>NAME: OSCAR PEREIRO  NATIONALITY: SPANISH  AGE: 29  TEAM: CAISSE D'EPARGNE  BEST FINISH: SECOND IN 2006  PROFILE: Known as a strong climber, Pereiro has twice finished in the top 10. Last year in the Pyrenees, he swapped the yellow jersey four times with Floyd Landis until losing it for good during Landis's now infamous comeback in the Alps. If Landis is stripped of his victory because of his alleged doping (as of press time, his case was still in arbitration), Pereiro will be named the 2006 champion.</p>
        <p>2.THE LONG SHOTS</p>
        <p>NAME: CARLOS SASTRE</p>
        <p>NATIONALITY: SPANISH</p>
        <p>AGE: 32 TEAM: CSC  BEST FINISH: FOURTH IN 2006  PROFILE: Possibly the shyest man in professional cycling -- he's soft-spoken and sometimes looks ready to burst into tears -- Sastre is devastatingly fast uphill, and the mountain stages are what usually decide the race. Unfortunately, he loses ground during the long, flat time trials.</p>
        <p>NAME: DENIS MENCHOV  NATIONALITY: RUSSIAN  AGE: 29 TEAM: RABOBANK  BEST FINISH: SIXTH IN 2006  PROFILE: Winner of the 2003 maillot blanc (given to the top Tour finisher under age 25), the seemingly tireless Menchov works harder than anyone to keep up with the very best riders.</p>
        <p>NAME: CHRISTOPHE MOREAU  NATIONALITY: FRANCE  AGE: 36 TEAM: AG2R  BEST FINISH: FOURTH IN 2000  PROFILE: The nearest the French have to a contender, he shows up every year with legs as strong as his tactics are unorthodox.</p>
        <p>3. THE CASTAWAYS</p>
        <p>FLOYD LANDIS Last year's winner has filed one appeal after another to overturn his positive drug test. The lawsuit is making the Alec Baldwin-Kim Basinger rift look downright cordial.</p>
        <p>JAN ULLRICH Last year's favorite was linked to the Operation Puerto scandal and banned from the Tour. He retired in April, just before DNA tests proved definitively that his blood was found in bags confiscated in the raid.</p>
        <p>IVAN BASSO Banned in 2006 because of his alleged connection to Operation Puerto, Basso, from Spain, was hired last fall by Team Discovery Channel, the outfit co-owned by Lance Armstrong. In April, Basso quit and later admitted to ''attempted doping'' -- which is to say he didn't inhale.</p>
        <p>TYLER HAMILTON An American rider, he was banned for two years after being suspected of blood doping and now rides for a team owned by a Russian beer magnate. Hamilton is off to a rocky start: he was suspended from the team last month because of, yes, alleged involvement in Operation Puerto.</p>
        <p>4.THE SECOND COMING OF LANCE  DOES ANY AMERICAN HAVE EGO AND TALENT ENOUGH TO STEAL THE SHOW? WELL . . .</p>
        <p>LEVI LEIPHEIMER  AGE: 33  TEAM: DISCOVERY CHANNEL  DOES HE SOUND LIKE LANCE? 5/10.  Despite looking like him (the resemblance is uncanny until Leipheimer takes off his helmet to reveal his shiny-bald head), Leipheimer is a quiet underachiever, while Armstrong was an outspoken overachiever.</p>
        <p>DOES HE RIDE LIKE LANCE? 4/10. Like Armstrong, Leipheimer is a strong climber and time-trialist. But he lacks panache and a killer instinct.</p>
        <p>IS HE THE NEW LANCE? 5/10</p>
        <p>TOM DANIELSON  AGE: 29  TEAM: DISCOVERY CHANNEL  DOES HE SOUND LIKE LANCE? 2/10.  Affable in the extreme. The kind of cyclist you could take home to Mom and Dad.</p>
        <p>DOES HE RIDE LIKE LANCE? 4/10. One of the best climbers in the sport, though cynics say that he, like Leipheimer, could use a spine transplant.</p>
        <p>IS HE THE NEW LANCE? 3/10</p>
        <p>DAVE ZABRISKIE  AGE: 28  TEAM: CSC  DOES HE SOUND LIKE LANCE? 1/10. See Danielson.  DOES HE RIDE LIKE LANCE? 3/10. Depends on the terrain. He can dominate a time trial but struggles in the mountains.</p>
        <p>IS HE THE NEW LANCE? 2/10</p>
        <p>5. THE WILDLIFE</p>
        <p>The Tour would be nothing without the tens of thousands of fanatics who turn up to watch the race. But the seemingly homogeneous crowd lining the road is actually composed of very distinct groups, divided roughly along national lines.</p>
        <p>THE FRENCH  They've been watching the Tour roll by for over a century and will have bagged the prime viewing spots before the dew dries. They are also the best prepared, with tables, chairs, beach umbrellas, radios, food, wine and cultural superiority.  Cheering for: Any rider, so long as he's French.  Danger rating: 1/5</p>
        <p>THE BRITISH  Sunburned, unfashionable, ill-prepared and few in number, these fans of the Tour have precious little to cheer for: no British rider has ever won, and none is likely to do so this year. If they look lost and bewildered, be nice to them.  Cheering for: The Americans, if for no other reason than a shared language. This year's race starts in London, which doesn't make it any more likely that a Briton will dominate.  Danger rating: 0/5</p>
        <p>THE DUTCH  Found only in the Alps, and easy to spot. They wear orange, drink more than is healthy at high altitude (not uncommon at the Tour, no matter the nationality) and crank the Eurodisco at maximum volume for days leading up to the arrival of the peloton.  Cheering for: The predominantly Dutch Rabobank team and life in general.  Danger rating: 3/5</p>
        <p>THE BASQUES  Like the Dutch, they wear orange, but their preferred habitat is the Pyrenees. Roll up your windows when you drive past. Do not engage them.  Cheering for: Their local team, Euskaltel, which hires only Basque riders.  Danger rating: 5/5</p>
        <p>THE AMERICANS  They wear Team Discovery Channel jerseys. The least popular are those asking, ''Which one's Lance?''  Cheering for: The red, white and blue, baby!  Danger rating: 2/5</p>
        <p>6. THE ADHD TOUR  Three weeks is a long time to follow a race. To appease the impatient, here are the two stages you have to see.</p>
        <p>STAGE 8: SUNDAY, JULY 15, LE GRAND-BORNAND TO TIGNES The race hits the Alps with three major climbs that take the riders straight uphill for more than 40 miles, with only short pauses for breath on the frenetic downhills. It's here in the mountains where the contenders will emerge.</p>
        <p>STAGE 15: MONDAY, JULY 23, FOIX TO LOUDENVIELLE The second day in the Pyrenees is a five-mountain roller coaster ride that finishes with an eight-mile headlong descent. The riders will be shattered from the previous day's difficult stage, so watch for crashes. Any rider with serious designs on the yellow jersey will use this stage as a springboard to escape from his rivals. By day's end, the Tour's winner may not be known, but the list of possibilities will be down to the final names.</p>
        <p>7. LES SCANDALES!  Cheating at the Tour de France is a time-honored tradition.</p>
        <p>1904  Riders were beaten up by rival fans. The 1903 winner, Maurice Garin, was driven off the course. At least one rider was caught receiving a tow (he held on, with his teeth, to a cork wired to a car). Henri Cornet accused his rivals of stuffing his chicken with sleeping pills. He survived to win the race, but only after the four riders ahead of him were disqualified.</p>
        <p>1906  History has otherwise forgotten Maurice CarrÃ  THE MAIN EVENT Edward Pickering is a writer for England's Cycle Sport magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Edward Pickering is a writer for England's Cycle Sport magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
