<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN THE REGION/Long Island; Seeing More in a Marina</title>
    <meta content="03lizo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/realestate/03lizo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851810"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="In the Region | Long Island"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DB1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN THE REGION/Long Island; Seeing More in a Marina</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Seeing More in a Marina</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VALERIE COTSALAS</byline>
      <dateline>BAY SHORE</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AN aging 21-acre marina at a prime waterfront location in this hamlet is getting attention from public officials and residents who see greater potential.</p>
        <p>Construction is now under way to rip out a bulkhead with gaping holes on the southeastern end of the Bay Shore Marina and replace it with a steel support wall, a dual boardwalk, benches and tables. This is just one component of a plan to revitalize the marina and draw more people from the local area.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 21-acre marina at a prime waterfront location in Bay Shore is getting attention from public officials and residents who see greater potential.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AN aging 21-acre marina at a prime waterfront location in this hamlet is getting attention from public officials and residents who see greater potential.</p>
        <p>Construction is now under way to rip out a bulkhead with gaping holes on the southeastern end of the Bay Shore Marina and replace it with a steel support wall, a dual boardwalk, benches and tables. This is just one component of a plan to revitalize the marina and draw more people from the local area.</p>
        <p>Despite its waterfront location, the community of Bay Shore descended into crime-ridden blight and neglect in the 1970s and 1980s. Nearly half of the storefronts on Main Street were vacant. But in the last decade, developers have built hundreds of new housing units and new businesses, cafes and restaurants have opened downtown.</p>
        <p>The town of Islip, encompassing the hamlet of Bay Shore and the village of Brightwaters, which share a school district, held a meeting in April for residents to help plan the future of this marina, which juts out into the Great South Bay, the water that separates the southern shore of Long Island from Fire Island.</p>
        <p>''We don't have a soccer field or a baseball field'' like other parts of the town, said Steven Flotteron, an Islip town councilman who has lived in Brightwaters for 12 years. ''This is our park. That's it.''</p>
        <p>The event was a ''visioning'' run by Vision Long Island, a nonprofit planning organization that advocates ''smart growth'' development, including features that encourage walking instead of driving.</p>
        <p>While the location of the 500-slip marina in this community on the south shore of Suffolk County is prime -- next to three restaurants, close to the ferryboats that run to Fire Island, and minutes from the train station and Main Street shops -- it has remained largely unused most of the time, even during the summer months.</p>
        <p>The biggest feature is three huge parking lots, with many spaces striped so that cars are parallel to the water view, instead of facing it. To use the small town beach and playground on the southwestern end of the town-owned marina, which is at the end of South Clinton Avenue, residents have to park in the lots and cross a road that serves the marina.</p>
        <p>Although the view of the bay and the passing ferries and smaller boats makes the area an inviting place to relax and read the paper, the beach itself is somewhat sad, with the 200-foot-wide swimming area closed in by an industrial-style concrete jetty and a floating line to stop swimmers from venturing very far. Just beyond the playground is a boarded-up concession stand, made unprofitable by the marina's decline and the slowing flow of visitors.</p>
        <p>Over all, there is a lack of cohesion, so that a driver discovers the public beach, the playground or the boat slips on the north side only when those places whiz by the car window.</p>
        <p>Some residents also complain that fishermen clog the one existing walkway along the ocean with their nets, tackle boxes and poles.</p>
        <p>One part of the plan developed at the meeting is to include two boardwalks -- one for the fishermen close to the water, and another slightly set back where visitors can stroll without tripping over fishing gear, Mr. Flotteron said.</p>
        <p>The plan will be presented to the town planning board in phases, he added. Planned changes include adding a drop-off area and parking adjacent to the beach, enlarging the playground and building public restrooms, and adding a sprinkler park for young children.</p>
        <p>For teenagers, basketball courts now next to the playground would be moved to a part of the mostly unused parking lot on the southeast end of the marina, and combined with a public roller rink to be run by the town. One of the most important features of the plan is to have a continuous walkway connecting parts of the marina and the restaurants.</p>
        <p>The half-mile-long marina offers spectacular views, Mr. Flotteron said, but right now, ''it's not connected; taking a car is the safest way to get from one area to another.''</p>
        <p>Boaters who lease the slips from the town are also concerned with keeping their boats safe and improving infrastructure on the docks.</p>
        <p>Nora Detweiler, the deputy commissioner for parks and recreation in Islip, said the electrical and water systems would be upgraded on the marina's 12 docks.</p>
        <p>Lockable gates will also be added, according to Eric Alexander, executive director of Vision Long Island. ''The key is to keep the boaters happy while making the broader community more likely to use the marina,'' Mr. Alexander said. ''We need to get more activity down here.''</p>
        <p>At the meeting, it was also suggested that sewer lines be extended to the marina and an affordable food concession be added. Currently, the town leases space at the far eastern end of the marina to a restaurant called Nicky's Clam Bar, whose prices were described as too high.</p>
        <p>The marina revitalization began with the bulkhead replacement in March, after New York State legislators approved a $1.5 million grant for the project. Mr. Flotteron estimated that future costs for the overhaul, including the dock improvements, would be about $5 million.</p>
        <p>The plan also looks forward to possible further development, he said. For example, developing a three-quarter-acre lot next to the marina, acquired by the county in 1997, might help defray costs for the project.</p>
        <p>The town, which controls zoning for the area, could invite developers to submit plans for the parcel, possibly including condos, he said. A developer who wanted to build condos on the lot could be required to pay for infrastructure improvements in return for approvals to build more units than would normally be permitted. Improvements might include extending the sewer lines, which Mr. Flotteron estimated at about $500,000.</p>
        <p>A new concession stand, moved from its current location where it would block the view of the imaginary condos on the vacant lot, could also be a developer's contribution.</p>
        <p>''Where else on Long Island,'' Mr. Flotteron asked, ''could you have a one-bedroom condominium facing the water that is walking distance to a downtown Main Street, to a marina and to the Fire Island Ferry?''</p>
        <p>In the Region | Long Island</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
