<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Finding a Proper Home For 8.5 Tons of Iron</title>
    <meta content="03cannonsnjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03cannonsnj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851797"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MILITARY HISTORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cannons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fort Monmouth (NJ)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clarke, Jeffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mallozzi, Vincent M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E0DC1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="612" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Finding a Proper Home For 8.5 Tons of Iron</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Finding a Proper Home for 8.5 Tons of Iron</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VINCENT M. MALLOZZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mallozzi, Vincent M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on possible fate of pair of eight-foot cannons at Fort Monmouth, NJ, dating to Civil War; fort is scheduled to close in 2011 as part of military spending cuts and ultimate decision on cannons rests with Dr Jeffrey Clarke, Army's chief of military history; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY stand at attention, some 40 yards apart, inside the walls of Fort Monmouth, awaiting further orders.</p>
        <p>Silenced for more than a century, a pair of eight-foot cannons dating to the Civil War will have a new home by the time the fort closes in 2011 as part of an effort to cut military spending.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY stand at attention, some 40 yards apart, inside the walls of Fort Monmouth, awaiting further orders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEY stand at attention, some 40 yards apart, inside the walls of Fort Monmouth, awaiting further orders.</p>
        <p>Silenced for more than a century, a pair of eight-foot cannons dating to the Civil War will have a new home by the time the fort closes in 2011 as part of an effort to cut military spending.</p>
        <p>But where the cannons -- or iron Rodman guns, as they are officially known -- will be transferred remains a mystery. The issue has also become a bit of a political cannon ball in New Jersey as fort officials deal with Congressional inquiries concerning the twin gun tubes, as the cannons were once called.</p>
        <p>''I know that there has been interest regarding these guns via Congressional sources, including Senator Lautenberg's office,'' said Tim Rider, a spokesman for the fort, referring to Senator Frank R. Lautenberg. ''But it's not our mission here at Fort Monmouth to make decisions about the placement of historical properties, and that includes deciding the future of these guns.''</p>
        <p>The ultimate decision on the cannons rests with Dr. Jeffrey J. Clarke, the Army's chief of military history, who is based at Fort McNair in Washington. He is responsible for all of the Army's historical property, including 565,000 artifacts scattered around the country dating to the American Revolution.</p>
        <p>J. Terry Dougherty, the acting director of Army museums, who works under Dr. Clarke, said that at some point this year, ''we will go to Fort Monmouth to survey that installation for potential historical property.''</p>
        <p>''We will look at that collection in terms of items that may be set aside for other organizations,'' Mr. Dougherty said. ''But in making final decisions like these, we do try and take the requests of local communities into consideration.''</p>
        <p>The cannons, each weighing about 8,500 pounds and having a barrel eight inches in diameter, arrived at Fort Monmouth in 1950 from Fort Hancock on Sandy Hook, which had closed as a military installation and is now a part of the Gateway National Recreation Area.</p>
        <p>The cannons, which have more sentimental than monetary value -- they are said to be worth in the neighborhood of $50,000 apiece -- could return to Fort Hancock, which dates to the 1890s and has a Civil War-era Rodman gun of its own. The cannons could also end up at another Army installation or in a national park, and not necessarily in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>That is of major concern to some state politicians and veterans groups, even though New Jersey would still have 55 other cannons.</p>
        <p>''I have always had an interest in preserving the history of New Jersey,'' said Representative Rush D. Holt, a Democrat whose district includes Fort Monmouth and a large part of Monmouth County. ''These cannons are now a part of our history and should remain here. I will continue to work with the Army so that New Jerseyans can have access to the monuments that commemorate the sacrifices of our ancestors.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dougherty, who noted that there are 59 Army museums across the nation, did not rule out the possibility of the cannons being shipped to the Aberdeen Proving Ground in Maryland, where the United States Army Communications-Electronics Museum, now a part of Fort Monmouth, is to be relocated.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, the two cannons remain under the stewardship of Mindy Rosewitz, the museum's curator.</p>
        <p>''We will be looking at these two cannons as part of a process to see where these guns best fit within the United States Army,'' Mr. Dougherty said. ''We will also look, as a part of the process, at where these two guns would best be suited if the Army made the decision not to retain them.''</p>
        <p>MILITARY HISTORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
