<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yanks Brightened a Life By Showing They Cared</title>
    <meta content="03smith" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851984"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E2DB1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="513" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yanks Brightened a Life By Showing They Cared</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ray Smith, a spirited Yankees fan, once decided the team's lineup with Manager Joe Torre, called catcher Joe Girardi one of his best friends and playfully told the announcer Michael Kay that he would one day have Kay's job on the YES Network. Smith's life revolved around his faith, his family and baseball.</p>
        <p>That short, determined life ended last Tuesday night when Smith, who was born with a congenital heart defect, died from heart disease at Yale-New Haven Hospital in Connecticut. Smith turned 23 one day earlier. Funeral services are today at Grace Community Church in Lake Katrine, N.Y.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ray Smith, a spirited Yankees fan, once decided the team's lineup with Manager Joe Torre, called catcher Joe Girardi one of his best friends and playfully told the announcer Michael Kay that he would one day have Kay's job on the YES Network. Smith's life revolved around his faith, his family and baseball.</p>
        <p>That short, determined life ended last Tuesday night when Smith, who was born with a congenital heart defect, died from heart disease at Yale-New Haven Hospital in Connecticut. Smith turned 23 one day earlier. Funeral services are today at Grace Community Church in Lake Katrine, N.Y.</p>
        <p>''He had a bad heart, but he had a great heart,'' said Ray Smith Sr., his father. ''Ray touched a lot of people.''</p>
        <p>One of those people was Torre. Smith wrote Torre an emotional two-page letter in 1997 in which he praised Torre's caring style as a manager and also inquired about Torre's brother Frank, who had undergone a heart transplant in 1996. Smith had one request for Torre. He asked if Torre's family would pray for him.</p>
        <p>Torre received Smith's letter at a charity event, and he said that ''it gave me goose bumps to have someone feel that way about me.'' Torre invited Smith to compile the Yankees' lineup, with some guidance, at a game.</p>
        <p>So on May 31, 1998, Torre leaned on the blue dugout bench to look eye to eye with Smith. They mutually decided to bat Chuck Knoblauch first, followed by Derek Jeter, Paul O'Neill, Tino Martinez and so on. The Boston Red Sox scored 11 runs in the third inning and went on to beat the Smith-Torre lineup, 13-7, but Smith was still thrilled that he had been Torre's sidekick.</p>
        <p>''Ray's spirit, despite knowing what was ahead of him, was uplifting,'' Torre said. ''He didn't spend any time feeling sorry for himself. It was touching to see that courage in someone so young.''</p>
        <p>Girardi, who was listed as the ninth batter on a lineup card that was signed by Torre and Smith, spent time with Smith that day and said he made a friend for life.</p>
        <p>''I just took a special liking to him,'' Girardi said. ''We were pals ever since.''</p>
        <p>Girardi said Smith was ''an amazing kid with an amazing attitude toward life.'' Smith had Girardi's cellphone number, but he used it sparingly and would not share it with anyone. Not even Heather, his younger sister.</p>
        <p>''Every time I spoke to him,'' Girardi said, ''I felt better afterwards.''</p>
        <p>There were Yankees balloons attached to Smith's bed and a blue Connecticut School of Broadcasting T-shirt hanging on the wall in his room in Yale's intensive care unit. Smith was about to graduate from the school and pursue a career in broadcasting, hoping to some day announce games for the Yankees.</p>
        <p>''I called him my ray of sunshine,'' said Dorothy, his mother. ''We'll miss him so much. But I'm not a mother who worries about what has happened to her son. With Ray's faith and the way he lived, I know exactly where he is now.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
