<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Convincing Victory Gives Kiwis A 2-0 Lead</title>
    <meta content="03cup" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/sports/othersports/03cup.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851995"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="YACHT RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/New Zealand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/New Zealand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">America's Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sailboats and Sailing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sailboats and Sailing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">America's Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Zealand</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02EEDB1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Convincing Victory Gives Kiwis A 2-0 Lead</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">America’s Cup: Team New Zealand Widens Its Lead</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <dateline>VALENCIA, Spain, June 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After outclassing the lone entry from the United States in the semifinals of the Louis Vuitton Cup, Luna Rossa Challenge is searching for answers and for the lead, any lead, after falling behind by 2-0 to Emirates Team New Zealand in the finals.</p>
        <p>Suspense quickly gave way to domination Saturday, when the New Zealanders captured a seemingly routine 40-second victory. The ease of their win was quite a surprise, considering how closely matched Luna Rossa and the Kiwis appeared only 24 hours earlier in the same body of water with the same kind of breeze.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Suspense quickly gave way to domination, as Team New Zealand took a 2-0 lead over the Italians in the final of the Louis Vuitton Cup.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After outclassing the lone entry from the United States in the semifinals of the Louis Vuitton Cup, Luna Rossa Challenge is searching for answers and for the lead, any lead, after falling behind by 2-0 to Emirates Team New Zealand in the finals.</p>
        <p>Suspense quickly gave way to domination Saturday, when the New Zealanders captured a seemingly routine 40-second victory. The ease of their win was quite a surprise, considering how closely matched Luna Rossa and the Kiwis appeared only 24 hours earlier in the same body of water with the same kind of breeze.</p>
        <p>But the details can make all the difference in this best-of-nine America's Cup challenger series, and the Kiwis have the early advantage. The third race is Sunday.</p>
        <p>''Awesome day; one of the best days we've had on board,'' said Ray Davies, Team New Zealand's strategist.</p>
        <p>The Kiwis also have the full attention of Alinghi, the Swiss-based team that will defend its title here later this month against the winner of this cross-hemisphere duel. As if to remind the challengers of what is ahead, Alinghi has been training in range of the races.</p>
        <p>Few spectators had the time or desire to pay much attention to Alinghi's sleek yachts Friday, when the New Zealanders and the Italians traded tacks and tactics in a thriller that the Kiwis eventually won by eight seconds. But there was ample time to let the gaze and mind drift elsewhere Saturday, when the New Zealand helmsman Dean Barker and his 16-man crew took control early in the first leg.</p>
        <p>When it was over, Luna Rossa's team members huddled on board for a meeting of the minds as they were towed back to Port America's Cup. They passed hundreds of their still-cheering supporters, who perhaps should have paid closer attention to the race.</p>
        <p>After rounding every mark ahead of BMW Oracle in the semifinals, the Italians have rounded every mark behind the Kiwis in the first two races of the finals.</p>
        <p>''There's definitely nothing wrong with the boat or speed of it,'' said Joe Newton, Luna Rossa's trimmer. ''We felt that if we get our nose in front, it will be no problem at all, but today Team New Zealand got in front and did a great job of staying there, so full credit to them.''</p>
        <p>Terry Hutchinson, Team New Zealand's tactician, received plenty of credit from his teammates for building on the lead. When Luna Rossa looked for a shift in wind and fortune later in the race, Hutchinson let the Italians go, at least for a little while, because he was convinced that no gains were to be had.</p>
        <p>But it was the prestart, once again, that proved critical. Luna Rossa's helmsman, James Spithill, succeeded in putting his yacht on the right side of the course at the start, but his late maneuvering for position cost Luna Rossa precious speed as it hit the starting line. The Kiwis were at full sail, with a fresh mainsail to boot. Soon they had opened enough of a gap that they were able to tack over and make life difficult for the Italians.</p>
        <p>Despite a tacking duel begun by Luna Rossa at the first mark, the Kiwis' lead was 25 seconds. Still, the Luna Rossa crew members defended their helmsman.</p>
        <p>''Our weather call was a must-have right,'' Newton said. ''We've had clear-weather calls, and he's been getting the side we wanted, so as far as we're concerned, I think James is doing a great job.''</p>
        <p>The hottest weather unit in the Vuitton Cup appears to belong to Team New Zealand. And its leader is Roger Badham, who has been around the Cup and a barometer long enough to have earned the nickname Clouds.</p>
        <p>Few clouds were overhead Saturday, on a delightful day for sailing, with a relatively steady, midrange breeze of 12 to 14 knots and the occasional whitecap. Wind conditions are expected to be lighter Sunday.</p>
        <p>Whatever the conditions, the Italians need to win soon and win often if they are to stop the New Zealanders from earning a rematch with Alinghi, which humiliated them at the last America's Cup in 2003 in Auckland, New Zealand.</p>
        <p>''Our team's feeling good, but we know Luna Rossa are really talented sailors, and James has the ability to turn things around in a moment,'' Davies said. ''They're not going to cave like we saw Oracle cave.''</p>
        <p>YACHT RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
