<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LIVING IN/Glen Cove, L.I.; Downtown, Meet Waterfront</title>
    <meta content="03livi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/realestate/03livi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851830"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Living In | Glen Cove, L.I."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E6DA1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1625" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LIVING IN/Glen Cove, L.I.; Downtown, Meet Waterfront</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Downtown, Meet Waterfront</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JODI CUNNINGHAM, a 48-year-old single mother from Jericho, spent two years shopping for a house she could afford, scouring the market in Plainview, Syosset and Jericho for a half-million-dollar home that didn't need extensive repairs.</p>
        <p>''I was really disappointed in what I was seeing,'' Ms. Cunningham said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For those without the deepest pockets, Glen Cove offers access to Long Island Sound with an appealing variety of housing options.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JODI CUNNINGHAM, a 48-year-old single mother from Jericho, spent two years shopping for a house she could afford, scouring the market in Plainview, Syosset and Jericho for a half-million-dollar home that didn't need extensive repairs.</p>
        <p>''I was really disappointed in what I was seeing,'' Ms. Cunningham said.</p>
        <p>In March, she found what she had been looking for: a new 2,200-square-foot colonial for $550,000. It is on a tidy street in Glen Cove, a city of more than 26,000 on the North Shore of Nassau County. And to Ms. Cunningham, ''it is a dream come true.''</p>
        <p>For those without the deepest pockets, Glen Cove is like that -- on the water, no less, and with an appealing variety of places to live.</p>
        <p>More ethnically and economically diverse than many communities on the North Shore, this seven-square-mile city dead-ending at Long Island Sound has not only marinas and beaches but also a bountiful mix of estates, single residences, two-family homes, town houses, condominiums, co-ops and rental apartments.</p>
        <p>It is also a city with a downtown in transition -- a place seeking to shed elements of its long early history as an industrial center. Officials and developers are currently debating what to do with a 56-acre former industrial site essentially blocking the city's downtown area from the waterfront.</p>
        <p>Talk to Donald Monti, a partner in the Glen Isle Development Company, and he depicts the former brownfields Superfund site -- reclaimed from World War II era metals processing pollution -- as ''a jewel waiting to happen.''</p>
        <p>His developer's-eye-view includes 860 residential units in tiered midrise buildings set against a wooded hillside, along with a luxury hotel, spa, offices and retail shops, marinas, museums and perhaps even a culinary and wine school.</p>
        <p>The land, however, belongs to the city's Industrial Development and Community Development Agencies, whose chairman is the mayor, Ralph V. Suozzi. As enthusiastic as Mr. Monti is, Mr. Suozzi obviously doesn't feel the same way. He recently described the Glen Isle project -- which has been on the drawing board since 2003 -- as currently in a ''wait mode.''</p>
        <p>Mayor Suozzi, a cousin of the Nassau County executive, Thomas R. Suozzi, said he was concerned not just about issues like height, density and traffic, but also about whether the developers, who have invested $6 million of their own, have been straightforward.</p>
        <p>''What they have been showing to the planning board and the public is different than what they were contracted for,'' he said. ''I am for developing the waterfront, but that doesn't mean do what you want.''</p>
        <p>Initially, the mayor added, plans had called for ''a Mystic Seaport style waterfront experience,'' with only commercial and retail uses. But shortly before he took office last year, a zoning change allowed a larger residential component. The mayor contended that the model the developers used to facilitate the zoning change was different from the current renderings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Monti acknowledged that the revised plan included less retail space but described it as ''designed to complement the existing downtown areas.'' The smart-growth building plan also leaves 25 percent of the site as open space, he said.</p>
        <p>He predicted that the city, which is in financial straits, stood to gain $20 million a year in tax revenue from the project.</p>
        <p>County Executive Suozzi -- who as mayor of Glen Cove during the late 1990s was the initiator of the waterfront cleanup efforts -- emphasized the need to avoid a stalemate on the plan, recommending that his cousin the mayor and the Glen Isle developers open a dialogue.</p>
        <p>''The waterfront must be developed,'' the county executive said. ''Residential will make economic sense and will make it a more vibrant, sustainable community for the long term. The only problem is the current proposal is simply too big.''</p>
        <p>As for the mayor, he says he is working on a new master plan, to be completed by September. Since March 2006, a moratorium on new subdivisions has been in place.</p>
        <p>For now, aside from a waterfront esplanade built by the city in 2003, the only tangible progress is the nearly completed Charles Street bridge, part of a new roadway near the intersection of Glen Cove Avenue and Pratt Boulevard that makes the waterfront area directly accessible from downtown.</p>
        <p>But Mayor Suozzi remains unconvinced that the new roadway will do much to avoid any traffic crunch.</p>
        <p>What You'll Find</p>
        <p>An estates area runs north of Forest Avenue, following Dosoris Lane to the Sound, with Gold Coast mansions -- some now converted to hotels, schools and parks -- along Crescent Beach Road. About 130 homes occupy East Island, formerly called Morgan Island after its owner, the financier J. P. Morgan.</p>
        <p>In the more densely populated southern parts of town like the Orchard and the Landing, the city has ramped up its code enforcement in response to illegal subdivision of homes by immigrants.</p>
        <p>''We are being more aggressive about it,'' Mr. Suozzi said. The city has a center for Hispanic laborers looking for work.</p>
        <p>Downtown shopping areas along School and Glen Streets bustle with activity, with a multiplex, restaurants, salons, banks, professional offices and a Staples.</p>
        <p>Francine Ferrante, executive director of the Glen Cove Downtown Business Improvement District, said the vacancy rate was about 10 percent.</p>
        <p>''We have been getting new businesses opening up fairly consistently,'' Ms. Ferrante said, noting that national retailers were shy of Glen Cove because of its location at the tip of a peninsula.</p>
        <p>What You'll Pay</p>
        <p>Compared with surrounding communities, Glen Cove is a relative bargain.</p>
        <p>''Prices are 10 to 15 percent lower for comparable homes than a Locust Valley or Lattingtown,'' said Suzanne Wehren, an agent with Daniel Gale Associates in Locust Valley.</p>
        <p>Prices range from $365,000 for a three-bedroom, two-bath town house, to $19.5 million for the 20,000-square-foot former F. W. Woolworth mansion; most top-tier homes are in the $2 million to $4 million range.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cunningham, the single mom who recently found her dream house, ascribed some of her luck to a market glut. According to Mishelle Berger, the sales manager at Sherlock Holmes Realty in Glen Cove, there are 199 homes on the market. The median price, $650,000, hasn't changed, but last year at the same time, there were 110 homes for sale.</p>
        <p>Rentals, a rare commodity in Long Island suburbs, are available in Glen Cove. The Avalon Glen Cove North, an upscale complex, opened downtown in mid-April. The 111 apartments range from studios to two-bedrooms, according to Terese Santoro, a manager. Rents range from $1,650 to $3,000 a month. Amenities include a heated swimming pool, fitness center and 24-hour concierge. The building, up the block from the three-year-old Avalon Glen Cove South, is more than 50 percent leased.</p>
        <p>What to Do</p>
        <p>There are three resident-only beaches -- Crescent, Pryibil and Morgan Memorial Park -- as well as marinas and nine parks. The municipal Glen Cove Golf Course has 18 holes, and views of Dosoris Pond and Long Island Sound. Residents pay $75 a year for a permit, and green fees in the $20-to-$30 range, depending on the time of the week. Nonresidents can join for $875 a year. The club also has a restaurant, driving range, pistol range, tennis courts and a playground.</p>
        <p>The 62-acre Garvies Point Museum and Preserve, a county-owned Native American archaeology and regional geology museum, has five miles of nature trails.</p>
        <p>The Commute</p>
        <p>Tucked at the northern tip of central Nassau County, Glen Cove is 27 miles from Manhattan. The Long Island Expressway is a 10-minute ride away, down Route 107 and Glen Cove Road.</p>
        <p>The Long Island Rail Road makes three stops inside city limits on the Oyster Bay line: Sea Cliff, Glen Street and Glen Cove. The 6:16 p.m. express from Pennsylvania Station takes 59 minutes to the Glen Cove station at Pearsall Avenue and Duck Pond Road. Monthly tickets are $203, slightly less online.</p>
        <p>The Schools</p>
        <p>Forty percent of the 2,900 students in the Glen Cove School District are Hispanic, 14 percent are African-American and 4 percent are Asian. Mean SAT scores for the class of 2006 were 458 for critical reading, 475 for math and 445 for writing, versus state scores of 510, 493 and 483. The district is embarking on an international baccalaureate program for students seeking college-level work.</p>
        <p>State English Language Arts scores for Grades 3 through 8 have been improving. Eighth graders, for instance, scored 23 points better than last year: 72 percent passed in 2007, versus 49 percent in 2006.</p>
        <p>Among the private schools in the district are the Solomon Schechter Day School of Nassau County and High School of Long Island, a Conservative Jewish middle and high school; All Saints Regional Catholic School for nursery through Grade 8; and Friends Academy for preschool through Grade 12.</p>
        <p>The History</p>
        <p>In the 1890s, Charles Pratt Sr., a co-founder of Standard Oil, bought 1,100 acres on Glen Cove's northwestern waterfront and gave land to each of his six sons, according to Paul J. Mateyunas, the author of ''North Shore Long Island: Country Houses 1890-1950'' (Acanthus Press 2007). Each built his own mansion. Among them is the Glen Cove Mansion, a hotel and conference center that was originally home to John Teele Pratt Sr. Also, what was Harold I. Pratt's Welwyn, built in 1913, is home to the Holocaust Memorial and Tolerance Center and Children's Memorial Garden.</p>
        <p>A Snapshot</p>
        <p>Glen Cove's diversity makes it a standout among North Shore communities.</p>
        <p>Going Forward</p>
        <p>The city is considering a new ferry terminal along Garvies Point Road, which would offer a water route to Manhattan. But without more commuters, or tourists who might be drawn to the Glen Cove waterfront by a project like Glen Isle, water service to the city may not have much of a shot.</p>
        <p>Living In | Glen Cove, L.I.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
