<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Day in the Life of an Interconnected World</title>
    <meta content="03shelf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/business/yourmoney/03shelf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851925"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OFF THE SHELF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Off the Shelf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Altman, Daniel</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EED81330F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1008" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Day in the Life of an Interconnected World</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Day in the Life of an Interconnected World</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN KOTKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kotkin, Stephen</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DANIEL ALTMAN, a well-traveled columnist for this section, earned a Ph.D. in economics from Harvard. In ''Connected: 24 Hours in the Global Economy'' (Farrar, Straus, Giroux, $24), he promises to use his formidable knowledge and access to take readers beyond stock market indexes and into the inner workings of the global economy.</p>
        <p>The international economic system, Mr. Altman declares, is ''an enormous machine crammed with six billion interlocking cogs and wheels.'' That is, people. ''Not everyone's wheel is the same size,'' he adds, ''but everyone's wheel matters.'' Hmm. This is not a book about hierarchies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In “Connected: 24 Hours in the Global Economy,” Daniel Altman promises to take readers into the inner workings of the global economy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DANIEL ALTMAN, a well-traveled columnist for this section, earned a Ph.D. in economics from Harvard. In ''Connected: 24 Hours in the Global Economy'' (Farrar, Straus, Giroux, $24), he promises to use his formidable knowledge and access to take readers beyond stock market indexes and into the inner workings of the global economy.</p>
        <p>The international economic system, Mr. Altman declares, is ''an enormous machine crammed with six billion interlocking cogs and wheels.'' That is, people. ''Not everyone's wheel is the same size,'' he adds, ''but everyone's wheel matters.'' Hmm. This is not a book about hierarchies.</p>
        <p>''Connected'' avoids the often wearying debate over globalization. The author writes that he does not identify either with the ''jingoistic pronouncements of a laissez-faire true believer'' or with ''the screams of a black-clad protester outside a major trade summit.'' Such evocation of extremes leaves him plenty of room.</p>
        <p>Mr. Altman grandly asserts that ''everything's connected, and every action by an individual instantly affects everyone else.'' Hyperbole aside, bringing alive the many links over vast distances turns out to be a killer task.</p>
        <p>To depict the world as he sees it, Mr. Altman uses a clever move: presenting a montage of 14 snapshots taken on June 15, 2005, from Damascus to Dili. He eschews straightforward narrative, favoring zoom-in, zoom-out impressions and lengthy quotations from a kaleidoscope of people. He also interjects tutorials on topics like the oil market or the global currency trade. ''Connections'' comes across as disjointed -- almost deliberately so.</p>
        <p>Chapters leap about. For example, the opening section on Ericsson of Sweden discusses a deal it proposes with Napster for downloading music on mobile phones. The chapter also takes in various corporate mergers and a downloaded ramble from a carbon emissions trader on a trip to Slovakia -- replete with ruminations on the author Dan Brown and the BlackBerry -- before snapping back to Ericsson-Napster. The takeaway point? ''It never stops.''</p>
        <p>In another chapter, riffs on postwar Japanese bureaucrats and Eliot Spitzer of New York, among other topics, suggest a need for international regulatory harmonization. But how? Elsewhere, a chapter on hedge funds indicates that global risk might be astronomical, so we need greater cooperation among banks in monitoring exposure. But what if they don't?</p>
        <p>Another chapter spotlights Mark Sobel of the United States Treasury Department, ''a believer in convergence of global financial regulation.'' Mr. Altman reveals that for Mr. Sobel, ''convergence'' entails other countries' adopting United States regulations. Americans, Mr. Altman says, almost never consider foreign practice to see whether it could be useful. (For good measure, he remarks that United States growth may not be so impressive, and that Americans are not happy.)</p>
        <p>Seeking complexity, Mr. Altman poses excellent questions. But his jumping hypertext of a book (offline, as it were) does not seem to want to answer them systematically.</p>
        <p>Keep scrolling. A chapter that deftly illustrates the differences in the economies of a booming Turkey, which has a stock exchange, and an impoverished Syria, which does not, paradoxically ends up mentioning that China has achieved phenomenal growth with a very immature stock market.</p>
        <p>More pointed is a finely wrought portrait of Intel's business in Vietnam, where Mr. Altman shows how this American company -- to mass Vietnamese benefit -- took full advantage of the Communist government's monopoly. ''Intel has succeeded in Vietnam,'' he elucidates, ''because its goal and the government's are roughly the same: more Vietnamese using computers.'' And if petty officials in Vietnam demand bribes from Intel, the company can rat them out to the central powers in Hanoi.</p>
        <p>In the same chapter, Mr. Altman observes that Beijing has invited foreigners to buy some Chinese companies to force domestic businesses to become more competitive, in effect using the barbarians as an arm of the Chinese state. The Communist leadership has also directed some state companies to sell shares on foreign exchanges before listing them at home, so they can hone international accounting practices.</p>
        <p>The bottom line: What partly distinguishes China and its emulators is that their rulers maintain political control while outsourcing crucial market reforms to foreigners who have the incentives and skill. (Then, in many cases, the Asian companies throw over the foreign partners like ballast.)</p>
        <p>This insight into authoritarian governments' use of Western-based multinationals links to a discussion of Western citizens' ability to influence the behavior of these companies abroad. It is hard to impose rules on them in their home countries, Mr. Altman observes, because evidence of wrongdoing must be collected far away. And companies can relocate offshore if pressured.</p>
        <p>Nongovernmental organizations and the media can still force change, he writes. He points to Gap Inc., which after being accused of using sweatshops now proudly promotes itself as the corporation with a conscience. The globe is a fishbowl.</p>
        <p>The globe can also be a bottleneck, when it comes to labor. Mr. Altman notes that amid xenophobia over immigrants, New Zealand and Canada, Poland and Ukraine, are scrambling to lure back expatriates. He refrains from inquiring whether workers might finally be reacquiring some leverage.</p>
        <p>IN an epilogue, he writes that ''there's still no substitute for real human contact.'' This seems strange in a book evidently filled with e-mail solicited from people asked to report on their June 15 activities as well as transcripts of cellphone conversations that day.</p>
        <p>Mr. Altman also states that ''the day when you could sit at home and think only of your own little circle, your own work and your own neighborhood has clearly passed.'' This for a readership in a country that is fighting two wars, in Afghanistan and Iraq, but where the vast majority of citizens can tune out those complications.</p>
        <p>Perhaps his most revealing moment, as a journalist covering the global beat, lies in his assertion that just keeping abreast is tantamount to some kind of mastery of global forces. If you pay attention, he advises, ''you'll start to feel your cog or wheel getting a bit more purchase on the big machine.''</p>
        <p>''In short,'' he adds, ''you'll be making connectedness work for you.'' If only globalization were actually that easy.</p>
        <p>OFF THE SHELF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
