<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Term Limits Force an Early Start to '09 Campaign</title>
    <meta content="03term" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/03term.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851991"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DEFDB1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1326" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Term Limits Force an Early Start to '09 Campaign</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Term Limits Force an Early Start to ’09 Campaign</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Melinda R. Katz, a city councilwoman from Queens, has held so many fund-raisers in her campaign for city comptroller in recent months that she cannot remember the precise number -- ''somewhere between seven and 10.''</p>
        <p>''It all melds together,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City’s term limits law seems to have created a near-permanent state of campaigning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Melinda R. Katz, a city councilwoman from Queens, has held so many fund-raisers in her campaign for city comptroller in recent months that she cannot remember the precise number -- ''somewhere between seven and 10.''</p>
        <p>''It all melds together,'' she said.</p>
        <p>That is just the beginning. Ms. Katz, a Democrat from Forest Hills, plans to hold a dozen more money-raising events before the end of June. She has hired a fund-raising consultant and set up a campaign Web site. And she books at least four meetings a day to discuss the politics and issues that will shape the Democratic primary.</p>
        <p>That race, by the way, is more than two years away. The general election is nearly 30 months from now.</p>
        <p>Ms. Katz's whirlwind of preparations is in many ways the fruit of the New York City term-limits law, which restricts elected officials to two consecutive four-year terms. The law, approved in a referendum in 1993 and reaffirmed by voters three years later, led to a wholesale change in the city's elected leadership in 2001. Ms. Katz was part of that sweep, but she and everyone else elected that year will have to give up their offices in 2009.</p>
        <p>As a result, New Yorkers will be asked to go to the polls in two years to elect replacements for the mayor, the public advocate, the comptroller, four of the five borough presidents and 36 of the 51 City Council members.</p>
        <p>When the term-limits bill passed, no one was certain of the long-term political consequences. It now seems clear that the law has created a near-permanent state of campaigning, with many officials eyeing their next office soon after they are sworn in to the job they have just won.</p>
        <p>''Term limits have really restructured the rhythm of politics in New York City,'' said Joseph P. Viteritti, a professor of public policy at Hunter College. ''Because people are limited to eight years in which they can be the incumbents, people have to become more ambitious, less likely to wait. It speeds things up politically.''</p>
        <p>Several officials who are being forced out by term limits have started raising money for the mayoral race. They include the comptroller, William C. Thompson Jr.; the public advocate, Betsy Gotbaum; and City Councilman Tony Avella of Queens. Congressman Anthony D. Weiner of Queens also has registered with the New York City Campaign Finance Board as a mayoral candidate, though term limits do not apply to him.</p>
        <p>Two Council members in addition to Ms. Katz are running for comptroller: David I. Weprin, Ms. Katz's fellow Democrat from Queens, and Simcha Felder, a Brooklyn Democrat. Also in the race is Assemblyman James F. Brennan, a Democrat from Brooklyn who, as a state official, is not affected by term limits.</p>
        <p>Eric N. Gioia, a councilman from Queens, is planning, meanwhile, to run for public advocate. Other council members whose terms expire in 2009 have said they plan to run for citywide office, although they have not decided -- or have not said -- which one.</p>
        <p>In all, almost 30 candidates have registered for the 2009 elections with the Campaign Finance Board, which administers a program that provides public matching funds to office seekers. As of the most recent filing, in January, those candidates had raised a total of $6.8 million and had spent $1.7 million.</p>
        <p>By comparison, the board says, just 11 candidates had filed at the same point in 1999, and had raised $2 million and spent $478,000.</p>
        <p>''With two years before the 2009 elections, you have more candidates being more active, raising more money and doing more campaigning than in any other election cycle,'' said Eric Friedman, a spokesman for the Campaign Finance Board. ''The activity is occurring a lot sooner in the cycle than in the past.''</p>
        <p>While many officials have declared their intentions, some have simply said that they are raising money for higher office and are keeping their options open.</p>
        <p>One of them is City Councilman John C. Liu, a Queens Democrat, who as of January had raised more than $1 million for an unspecified race.</p>
        <p>''Right now, I'm raising money, and I know that I would like to serve in a citywide capacity if the people will have me,'' said Mr. Liu, who said he was considering running for comptroller and public advocate.</p>
        <p>The Brooklyn borough president, Marty Markowitz, said he, too, was raising money and was leaning toward running for mayor.</p>
        <p>''I'm weighing it,'' he said, adding that he would prefer to remain borough president if he were not bound by term limits. ''By raising money now, it affords me the opportunity to be a contender.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Markowitz had raised $332,000 as of January and had spent nearly $200,000 toward a 2009 campaign.</p>
        <p>The very nature of these would-be campaigns has become an issue in the city's political order. Some candidates are chiding potential rivals for being indecisive.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people are undeclared,'' Mr. Weprin said of his potential rivals in the comptroller's race. ''They simply want to run for something, anything. In my case, I've made up my mind.</p>
        <p>''The way I see it,'' he added, ''the more formidable I become early on, the less likely someone else might run for that office.''</p>
        <p>The competition could include state legislators, who are exempt from term limits. Some of them are looking at municipal seats that will become open in 2009 because the salaries can be higher and the jobs do not involve travel to Albany.</p>
        <p>''If you're in the State Legislature, you'll pay attention to your colleagues in the City Council,'' said Evan Stavisky, a political consultant. ''And you'll see that they have higher pay, a shorter commute, greater job satisfaction and a clearer path for career advancement.''</p>
        <p>And some city officials who do not have to give up their offices because of term limits are looking at jumping into the 2009 election anyway. With so many citywide jobs open in the next election, candidates are less likely to face an incumbent than if they wait until 2013.</p>
        <p>One such potential candidate is the Manhattan borough president, Scott Stringer, who was elected in 2005. Mr. Stringer has said that is too early to make any decisions, but he has registered as a candidate for an unspecified position in 2009 and has not yet listed himself as a candidate for re-election. (He is widely thought to be considering the race for comptroller.) As of January, Mr. Stringer had raised about $250,000 and had spent $35,000.</p>
        <p>The 2009 election has thrown some council colleagues into competition with one another -- Ms. Katz and Mr. Weprin, for instance, in the comptroller's race. Some political consultants have suggested that such rivalries could lead to heightened infighting -- and less effective legislating -- on the Council for the next 30 months.</p>
        <p>Several Council members denied that such tensions will arise.</p>
        <p>''I think we're doing our jobs, and everyone is being extremely professional and collegial,'' said Ms. Katz. ''And I assume that will continue to be the case as we get closer to 2009.''</p>
        <p>None of the candidates has begun campaigning at subway stations or in shopping areas. But they have been busy raising money.</p>
        <p>Mr. Liu has held several fund-raisers in the past few weeks, including one on the top level of a two-story bar in the Flatiron area of Manhattan at which he mingled with about 100 contributors and discussed issues facing the city.</p>
        <p>One of Ms. Katz's fund-raisers in May was at the New York Athletic Club, on a terrace with stunning views of Central Park. While contributors nibbled on appetizers, she talked about her race for comptroller.</p>
        <p>Other events are not as fancy. Mr. Liu, for example, greeted about 20 contributors at the home of a friend in Bayside, Queens, last month.</p>
        <p>''When you run for a citywide office,'' he said, ''the great thing is that you can have a fund-raiser anywhere, from a basement apartment to a law firm to a restaurant.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
