<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recipe for a Museum: 200 Fire Trucks and a Dream</title>
    <meta content="03towns" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/03towns.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851987"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OUR TOWNS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Applebome, Peter</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EFDB1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recipe for a Museum: 200 Fire Trucks and a Dream</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Recipe for a Museum: 200 Fire Trucks and a Dream</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER APPLEBOME</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Applebome, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>WALLKILL, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>First, in late 2002, came a red 1959 Seagrave from Elmwood Place, Ohio, a 12-cylinder quint -- meaning it had a pump, an aerial ladder, a ground ladder, a booster tank and a hose. He bought it on eBay for $7,300. He'd collected antique all-wheel-drive dump trucks from the same company before. Why not try one of their fire engines?</p>
        <p>Next came a cream-colored 1959 Pirsch ladder truck from Bergen County that was sitting by the road in Elizabeth, N.J., with a for-sale sign because the owner had lost its storage space. He thought, why not?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The idea to start a museum came to Andrew Leider around the time he bought his 15th fire truck.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>First, in late 2002, came a red 1959 Seagrave from Elmwood Place, Ohio, a 12-cylinder quint -- meaning it had a pump, an aerial ladder, a ground ladder, a booster tank and a hose. He bought it on eBay for $7,300. He'd collected antique all-wheel-drive dump trucks from the same company before. Why not try one of their fire engines?</p>
        <p>Next came a cream-colored 1959 Pirsch ladder truck from Bergen County that was sitting by the road in Elizabeth, N.J., with a for-sale sign because the owner had lost its storage space. He thought, why not?</p>
        <p>Then he bought another on eBay, a 1972 Seagrave pumper that had been used in Clarence, N.Y., and drove up to Buffalo to drive it home.</p>
        <p>And then, around his 15th acquisition, he began thinking there had to be a way to let people see them. Which is why Andrew B. Leider, 55, was wending his way through a three-acre abandoned industrial building, surrounded by 150 vintage fire trucks from the 1920s to the 1980s -- about 120 owned by him and 30 by five others. Altogether he owns about 200 (at a cost of around $800,000) with more on the way, which he hopes to turn into the nation's largest public collection of motorized fire trucks.</p>
        <p>Maybe you can attract enough people to a fire engine museum just outside Circleville in Orange County, and maybe you can't. But somewhere in the intersection of men and their toys and the mental landscape of the 9/11 world, you can find Mr. Leider, a real estate lawyer and developer and the owner of Staten Island Towing Service, who, with a core of co-conspirators, has made every 6-year-old boy's dream come true.</p>
        <p>''What can I say? People get excited by fire trucks,'' he said, making his way through a maze of trucks in about 10 shades of red with a few outliers in lime green or white, made by small American companies like American LaFrance, Ward LaFrance, Ahrens-Fox, Seagrave, Maxim, Pirsch, FWD, and Walter, most now gone or merged into larger firms. ''Whenever I've taken one on the road, I get mobbed. I drove one up from Virginia, and people are cutting you off, waving, swerving in and out to take pictures. It was total insanity.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Leider had always been partial to industrial equipment, not fire trucks. But he did have a habit of collecting things -- beginning with old dump trucks (he now has 12). Mr. Leider, a retired colonel in the National Guard, was intimately involved with the 9/11 recovery through the Guard and his towing company, which carted away many of the charred and wrecked New York Police Department and Fire Department vehicles.</p>
        <p>So for him, the fire trucks were about two things. One was a tribute to firefighters and the work that they did. But at least as important was paying homage to a vanished industrial America where small companies cranked out models of elegance and utility, with their graceful lines, elongated shapes, odd angles, personal markings.</p>
        <p>''I really love industrial equipment manufactured in the 20th century: fire trucks, bulldozers, heavy-duty trucks, automobiles -- it's really an American art form. So you look at these trucks: What you see here, you'll never see again.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Leider first kept his collection in Staten Island, thought of displaying it at Pine Island in Orange County, then heard about the current site, which once housed a concrete plant and then a steel-manufacturing operation.</p>
        <p>Most days it is staffed by people like Bob Reynolds and Steve Radzinsky, retirees and longtime volunteer firemen in nearby Middletown (46 years for Mr. Radzinsky, 48 for Mr. Reynolds), who work on engines, find space for new arrivals, putter and tinker in the kind of clubhouse you sometimes find in your 60s and 70s instead of when you're a kid.</p>
        <p>There are other fire museums, like the Firemen's Association of the State of New York Museum in Hudson or the New York City Fire Museum in SoHo. Mr. Leider's idea is for something more tactile, where you could climb on the machines, where they'd demonstrate the ladders and pump systems, where the appeal was the machines as much as the people who used them.</p>
        <p>There's a difference between accumulating machines and fashioning a museum. But this is gearhead country, home of the Orange County Choppers, full of current and retired New York City firefighters. You never know. In any case, he's expecting five more trucks over the next two weeks and plans a public display on June 10.</p>
        <p>Mr. Radzinsky, whose own father in 1959 wrote a history of firefighting in Middletown called ''Brave Men and Bright Machines,'' walks around comparing the eccentricities of these trucks with the boxy, utilitarian models of today. He stopped by a classic 1925 Ahrens-Fox city service ladder truck, with its right-side drive, black leather seats, bell instead of a siren, pike poles, wooden ground ladders.</p>
        <p>''I'd love to see this coming down the street,'' he said.</p>
        <p>OUR TOWNS E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
