<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A League of His Own</title>
    <meta content="Jennings.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/books/review/Jennings-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851620"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Brooklyn Dodgers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Robinson, Jackie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Eig, Jonathan</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Opening Day: The Story of Jackie Robinson's First Season (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805EED61630F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1364" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A League of His Own</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A League of His Own</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY JENNINGS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OPENING DAY</p>
        <p>The Story of Jackie Robinson's First Season.</p>
        <p>By Jonathan Eig.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 323 pp. Simon &amp; Schuster. $26.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It’s been six decades since Jackie Robinson broke baseball’s color barrier.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OPENING DAY</p>
        <p>The Story of Jackie Robinson's First Season.</p>
        <p>By Jonathan Eig.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 323 pp. Simon &amp; Schuster. $26.</p>
        <p>Sports anniversaries pile up with insidious regularity. Whereas a D-Day comes around only once a war, the Super Bowl adds another Roman numeral every January (or February), and college basketball gives us the Final Four like clockwork every March (or April). This all but guarantees that in 5- or 10-year increments, we will look back in sepia tones with weepy eyes at various athletic accomplishments, replaying their ''firsts'' and measuring their importance. Only a few justify such commemoration. Some live on from sheer spontaneous drama, as with Bobby Thomson's 1951 home run. Some gather weight over time, as with the victory of Texas Western's black starting five against an all-white Kentucky team in the 1966 N.C.A.A. basketball finals. And a handful are heavy with significance both at the moment and long beyond, as with Jackie Robinson's entry into major-league baseball as its first modern-day African-American player, 60 years ago this season -- an operatic tale cannily orchestrated by Branch Rickey, the president of the Brooklyn Dodgers, and brilliantly performed by Robinson.</p>
        <p>No American sports story has been so often told, and no athlete so rightly deemed a hero. From the long shelf of books, a number by Robinson himself and his family, we know indisputably that he bore epithets and real threats with stoicism and dignity while executing on the field with consummate skill and characteristic abandon. Rickey, a wily lawyer, gave Robinson the best chance he could to succeed by assigning him to the Dodgers' minor-league team in the outpost of Montreal for a year as a test run and by stage-managing the release of information -- like what position he would play -- to reduce the pressure on him (and on the player whose job he might take). On Robinson's end, had he produced even a little less spectacularly than he did, batting .297 and scoring 125 runs in leading the Dodgers to the World Series, or exploded in anger even once, the so-called great experiment would have stalled. Yes, integration of baseball was inevitable, but one could not imagine a smoother, more elegant bridge to it than the Brooklyn one constructed by Rickey and Robinson.</p>
        <p>In 1997, for the 50th anniversary of Robinson's dash through the color barrier, Arnold Rampersad (whose biography of Ralph Ellison was recently published) came out with the definitive account of Robinson's life, leaving others to atomize the player's career further. Chris Lamb's ''Blackout: The Untold Story of Jackie Robinson's First Spring Training,'' for example, was published a few years ago. And now we have ''Opening Day: The Story of Jackie Robinson's First Season,'' by Jonathan Eig, who crosses boroughs on a subway series of his own after his well-received biography of the Yankees' Lou Gehrig (''Luckiest Man'') from two years ago.</p>
        <p>History has a way of playing cruel jokes, and this anniversary comes at a time when persuading black athletes to choose baseball (over basketball and football) has proved almost as much of a challenge as allowing them in was more than half a century ago. As of 2005, the number of African-American players in the major leagues had dipped to 8.5 percent, the lowest in 26 years, according to a study by the Institute for Diversity and Ethics in Sport. In 1985, Vince Coleman of the St. Louis Cardinals answered a Robinson-related query with: ''I don't know nothin' about him. Why are you asking me about Jackie Robinson?'' Now, according to C. C. Sabathia, the only African-American player on the Cleveland Indians' roster at the end of last year, the question has regressed to kids in his California hometown asking him, ''What's baseball?'' In ''Opening Day,'' I learned that the 1947 Dodgers, therefore, after they acquired Dan Bankhead in August to join Robinson, had twice the number of African-American players as the Indians of 2006.</p>
        <p>That current dearth would seem reason enough to celebrate the publication of another work about Robinson, especially one that compresses the most dramatic year of his career into a tidy package that doesn't pretend to be comprehensive and so promises to be more accessible than a monument like Rampersad's book or Jules Tygiel's ''Baseball's Great Experiment.'' Eig's brisk chronicle is full of local color and period details that recreate a bygone age of athletes who scraped by like other working stiffs, holding down off-season jobs and traversing the city on the subway rather than in tinted-window Escalades. Train travel was still de rigueur for away games; the Brooklyn manager, Burt Shotton, wore street clothes with a bow tie (thus restricting him to the bench, since only those in uniform were allowed on the field); TV viewers saw the World Series on ''gray screens no bigger than a lunchbox''; and many players were from the segregated South, including two Dodgers nicknamed Dixie. Robinson and his wife, Rachel, with a new son, Jack Jr., rented a room from a single woman in a Bedford-Stuyvesant brownstone, where they shared her bathroom. Hardly the TriBeCa penthouse that the former Mets catcher Mike Piazza recently showed off in Elle Decor magazine.</p>
        <p>Against this backdrop, Eig recounts the flash points that have grown into myths and largely reduces them from grand opera to folk song, a story of endurance and forbearance rather than sturm und drang. Dixie Walker, a popular Alabamian who supposedly led an internal team revolt, is portrayed as mostly concerned about how playing with Robinson might affect his hardware business back home. A famous gesture of support from Pee Wee Reese, the Kentucky-born shortstop who reputedly threw his arm around Robinson on the field to quiet a hostile crowd, is presented as largely apocryphal, and an alleged strike by the Cardinals as very likely a media exaggeration. Eig's deflation of the extremes of both opposition and support seems more complexly true and does justice to the man rather than the legend.</p>
        <p>Restraint and circumspection -- by Rickey, by the black fans who thronged both Ebbets Field and other parks, by most of the press, and, of course, by Robinson -- marked the integration of baseball more than any confrontation did. Rickey consulted with the sociologist Dan Dodson before hatching his plan, and the blueprint could have been lifted directly from Gunnar Myrdal's suggestions for integrating the workplace from his 1944 classic, ''An American Dilemma'': ''If Negro workers are introduced a few at a time, if they are carefully picked, if the leaders of the white workers are taken into confidence and if the reasons for the action are explained, then the trouble can be minimized, and the new policy may eventually become successful.'' This approach panned out, but took its toll on Robinson, a lonely figure celebrated by fans but not embraced by his teammates, even sympathetic ones. And during that year, Robinson never had to travel farther south than Cincinnati or St. Louis to test restraint as a tactic. Certainly, over the next two decades, in Little Rock, Birmingham and other places where the battlegrounds weren't baseball diamonds, stronger action would be required.</p>
        <p>Eig's analysis and prose are hit-and-miss. His structural gambit of interviewing contemporary figures and relating their memories of Robinson works with the Bronx-raised former Secretary of State Colin Powell -- ''We said, 'Oh, Lord, don't let him strike out.' The greatest fear was that he wouldn't do well, and that would be a mark against all of us'' -- but more often interrupts the flow of events with cloying sentimentality, as when he says of an aspiring teenage journalist, ''Only then did he begin to realize that life in America was different for black people.'' At several points where the writing induces a grimace (''As summer rounded second and headed for third...''), I began to suspect that the book, despite an impressive number of interviews and deep research, had been rushed for the anniversary release.</p>
        <p>Still, with the Bums pushing the Yankees to seven games in the World Series and Robinson being named rookie of the year, it's a difficult story to tell badly, and it will be worth telling again in another 10 years -- if that generation is not still asking, ''What's baseball?''</p>
        <p>Jay Jennings is a frequent contributor to the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jay Jennings is a frequent contributor to the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
