<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Demolition Man</title>
    <meta content="Maloney.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/books/review/Maloney-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851629"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Palahniuk, Chuck</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Rant (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E7DF1730F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1065" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Demolition Man</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Demolition Man</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FIELD MALONEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Erik T. Johnson</p>
        <p>RANT</p>
        <p>An Oral Biography</p>
        <p>of Buster Casey.</p>
        <p>By Chuck Palahniuk.</p>
        <p>320 pp. Doubleday. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chuck Palahniuk is back, with the legend of a rabid folk hero who dies in a fiery car crash.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Erik T. Johnson</p>
        <p>RANT</p>
        <p>An Oral Biography</p>
        <p>of Buster Casey.</p>
        <p>By Chuck Palahniuk.</p>
        <p>320 pp. Doubleday. $24.95.</p>
        <p>Not long into ''Rant'' -- 21 pages to be exact, after the car wrecks featuring impaled lungs and ''severe internal exsanguination,'' after the torn-apart carcasses of mule deer and rabbits, after the black widow bites on human nether parts and the blood-drinking family dogs -- the author describes the prairie storms that hit the little burg of Middleton, blowing over trash cans, strewing used condoms and panty liners and sanitary napkins (but nothing else, apparently) along the barbed wire fences on the edge of town. He zooms in -- he can't resist -- for a closer look: ''Old blood and chunks so black it could be road tar. Blood brown as coffee. Watery pink blood. Sperm died down to almost-clear water.''</p>
        <p>A new Chuck Palahniuk novel has arrived! But don't think Palahniuk, the author of ''Fight Club,'' is a garden-variety shock jock. This is the gross-out gone existential. This is about keeping it real. About staring down what one character in ''Rant'' calls ''the fake ... nature of everything,'' and exposing our collective split jugular. ''That night, even as a little boy, Rant Casey'' -- the country-boy hero of the new novel -- ''just wanted one thing to be real. Even if that real thing was stinking blood and guts.''</p>
        <p>''Rant'' unfolds as an oral history of Buster (Rant) Casey by the people who knew him before (and perhaps after -- the novel plays with fluid sci-fi notions of time) Casey drove off a bridge in a Cadillac with a flaming Christmas tree strapped to its roof. The novel is about the building of an urban legend: Casey is a dystopian folk hero who may or may not have been a serial killer. Of course, the rant is also Palahniuk's preferred method of fictional oratory: jazzy, digressive riffs mixing science, pop cultural detritus and slacker lore, cumulatively sketching out a bent, fallen world. At its best, Palahniuk's prose has the rat-a-tat immediacy of a bravura spoken word performance. When he misses, which he does often in ''Rant,'' it's just overcooked and indulgent.</p>
        <p>As a lad, Rant Casey likes to go ''animal-fishing'' -- heading out into the desert to stick his bare hand down animal holes. ''Didn't matter what critter -- scorpion, snake or prairie dog -- Rant would be reaching blind into the dark underground, hoping for the worst.'' No high like getting bit, Rant tells his pal Bodie Carlyle, whose hand has just been punctured clean through by jackrabbit chompers: ''This here, far as I'm concerned, this is how church should feel.''</p>
        <p>Unsurprisingly, Rant contracts a wicked case of rabies, which he wantonly spreads through Middleton, an act that's either viral terrorism or liberation theology. (Rant preaches resistance to McSociety, which sometimes requires a little foaming at the mouth.) One character calls Rant Casey a modern-day Huck Finn, but what really comes to mind (and it's not the first time with Palahniuk) is Holden Caulfield gone goth: perpetual adolescence waging war on the phonies and squares. This point of view -- which Palahniuk has a knack for expressing in bumper-stickerlike rallying cries -- is catnip to preadults (these days, just about everyone under 45), which helps explain why his books are best sellers.</p>
        <p>Soon Rant splits Middleton for the big city. Palahniuk can be impressively lyrical: here he describes Rant's parting, waiting with his father outside town for a bus to take him away. Notice the alliterative bursts and rhythmic cadences of the sentences, which mimic the sounds of cars racing by, and amplify the desolate pathos of the scene.</p>
        <p>''A star blinks on the edge of the world, getting bright, blinding bright, growing so fast it goes past before you can hear the sound, the wind and dust of it -- only a car, already come and gone. The headlights fading over the far side of the world.''</p>
        <p>The city, when Rant gets to it, is a nameless, postapocalyptic sprawl. It's run by fascist traffic planners who have segregated the citizenry into Daytimers (who move freely during daylight) and Nighttimers (an underclass of the destitute and otherwise misfit). Shoot-on-sight guards enforce curfew. Rant joins the Nighttimers (in the Palahniuk cosmos, salvation -- or at least consolation -- is always found among the leagues of the disaffected). He quickly falls in with the ''Party Crashers,'' a sort of citywide impromptu demolition derby league organized around theme nights. For ''Honeymoon Night,'' say, they all deck themselves out in tuxedos and wedding gowns and bridesmaid dresses, festoon their cars with shaving cream signs and cans strung to bumpers, and prowl around town at high speeds, looking for other costumed cars to rear-end. (For ''Soccer Moms,'' pennants and booster uniforms; and so on.)</p>
        <p>Rant's girlfriend, Echo Lawrence, describes her first Party Crash, pursuing a mock deer hunter in camos, with a Styrofoam buck on top of his sedan. ''Chasing him, I forget I have a bum arm and leg. I forget that half my face can't smile. Chasing him, I'm not an orphan or a girl. I'm not a Nighttimer with a crummy apartment. The deer ... dodges through traffic, and that's all I see.'' It's fitting that Echo, Rant's true love and the novel's heroine, is beautiful but disfigured. For Palahniuk the morbid aesthetic has devolved past cool-cat pose into reflexive tic.</p>
        <p>The problem with collecting and sentimentalizing freaks, though, is that they get reduced into cute caricatures. And the specter of cuteness has always dogged Palahniuk; even at his most grisly, it's like watching Gene Simmons spit blood and breathe fire onstage. (Tellingly, Palahniuk has been known to respond to fan mail with care packages of toy animals and severed plastic limbs.)</p>
        <p>Even his admirers may be disappointed by ''Rant.'' As a project, it has a dialed-in, flabby air. The sci-fi conceits are derivative and give the plot a hoary implausibility (and I'm not even addressing his ''Michael Crichton for the Utne Reader set'' conspiracy theories about Henry Kissinger, AIDS and Africa). Palahniuk has always been more sensation artist and cultural vacuum than storyteller. His characters aren't developed so much as given colorfully grotesque and morbid mannerisms and back stories. Sometimes he gets away with this by force of an assured voice and a febrile imagination: ''Fight Club'' had a cold stylish gleam; at some level its fantasies seduced. Take that away and all that's left is shock as shtick.</p>
        <p>Field Maloney is writing a book about wine in America.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Field Maloney is writing a book about wine in America.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
