<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Relative Distance</title>
    <meta content="03lives.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="70" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/magazine/03lives-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851669"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Lives"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reddi, Rishi</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">India</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E2DC1430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Relative Distance</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Relative Distance</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Rishi Reddi</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reddi, Rishi</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rishi Reddi article on her grandmother's latest visit to US from India and the closeness of their relationship despite distance that separates them (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Recently, my Indian grandmother visited the United States for a prolonged stay. She has made this journey several times, but she is 79 now, and my mother said that this would be her last trip. Since her last visit I had become a mother, and my grandmother made a point of delaying her return to India so that she could attend Maya's first birthday celebration at my home in Boston.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Family members may be closer than they appear from half a world away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Recently, my Indian grandmother visited the United States for a prolonged stay. She has made this journey several times, but she is 79 now, and my mother said that this would be her last trip. Since her last visit I had become a mother, and my grandmother made a point of delaying her return to India so that she could attend Maya's first birthday celebration at my home in Boston.</p>
        <p>When I was my daughter's age, I lived with my grandparents for several months in Hyderabad, India, while my parents, who were in England, found their footing in a foreign land. My parents and I moved to the United States when I was 4. Growing up, I envied the casual, impromptu way that my American friends came to know their grandparents. I could never be ''dropped off'' at their home when my parents needed an emergency baby sitter, and my grandmother and I never spent Sunday afternoons baking cookies. Even during summer vacations in India, there were barriers that prevented us from speaking freely: my Telugu was less than perfect; my grandmother's English was never smooth. We communicated through other people -- my mother, my aunt, my cousins -- in a maze of translations. Every aspect of our relationship was elaborately arranged and took time; we sent letters scrawled on blue aerogrammes; my family phoned at preset times, on connections that sounded like rustling newspapers, our voices echoing across oceans and atmosphere.</p>
        <p>During my grandmother's time in this country, which took her to Kansas and Michigan as well as Boston and lasted more than a year, I took the opportunity to get to know her. I forced myself to struggle with Telugu. I asked her about her life. I told her about mine. Having her here allowed me to make the effort, and I felt that I was making up for lost time. As Maya's birthday neared, so did my grandmother's final departure from the United States, and I feared our time of connection would end.</p>
        <p>At Maya's party, after the cake, my husband and I succumbed to pressure to open the presents while our guests watched. My aunt pushed my grandmother's wheelchair to the table with Maya's gifts. I am still surprised when I see her being wheeled around in this way. I remember when she traveled long hours by bus in India, riding from the city to the country to supervise the farming on family lands. She commanded a squadron of house servants, using a tone of voice that she would never use with me. Now she is a quiet woman. She inspected each of Maya's presents as it was unwrapped. She held up the clothes and looked at the stitching. She played with the toys with the same seriousness that Maya now does. ''This is very good,'' she said to me in Telugu, oblivious to whether the presenter of the gift could hear or understand. She nodded with approval at a gift certificate. At one point, realizing that both sets of grandparents had given Maya the same book, her unlined face broke into a smile. I was satisfied just to see her partake in Maya's birthday in this simple way.</p>
        <p>As the party died down and guests drifted off, I sat back and saw us -- my grandmother, my mother, myself, my daughter, a line of eldest females. Regardless of geography, we all bear the weight of being the firstborn, the primary repository of our parents' failed dreams and hidden aspirations, the child that altered their status in the world. And I thought about the ways in which, despite the distance between us, my grandmother and I do know each other. The scent of her saris reminds me of a time almost before memory. She was the first in my family to say that my non-Indian husband was handsome. I remember an afternoon I took her to see the swans at the Public Garden and to walk a beach on Massachusetts Bay. It was an ordinary tourist type of day, but to my grandmother, who had never seen a real swan and who had touched the ocean only once before, it was something special.</p>
        <p>Two days after the party, my husband and daughter and I went to Logan Airport to say goodbye. My grandmother sat in the wheelchair, the folds of her sari tucked under a heavy cardigan, her hair pulled neatly away from her face. ''Next time I talk with you,'' she said, ''you must tell me that there will soon be a little brother for Maya.'' She spoke about the distance between our countries as if it were the old days, as if it would be weeks, even months before I spoke to her again. ''I hope so,'' I said, just to play along. The truth is, I can call her in Hyderabad at any time now, and the line would be as clear as if I were talking with my neighbors next door. And yet, if I want my daughter to know her great-grandmother, it will take thousands of dollars, multiple plane rides and a day without sleep to arrive at her doorstep.</p>
        <p>Little Maya, of course, understood none of this. As we said our final goodbyes and my aunt began to push my grandmother's wheelchair into the security line, Maya's face was radiant with the happiness of practicing her wave.</p>
        <p>Lives Rishi Reddi is the author of a collection of short fiction, ''Karma and Other Stories.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Rishi Reddi is the author of a collection of short fiction, ''Karma and Other Stories.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
