<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Innocents Lost</title>
    <meta content="Blythe.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/books/review/Blythe-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851599"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Englander, Nathan</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Ministry of Special Cases, The (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1D61630F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1243" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Innocents Lost</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Innocents Lost</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILL BLYTHE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE MINISTRY OF SPECIAL CASES</p>
        <p>By Nathan Englander.</p>
        <p>339 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Nathan Englander’s first novel, a Jewish family in Argentina is torn asunder during the country’s “Dirty War.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE MINISTRY OF SPECIAL CASES</p>
        <p>By Nathan Englander.</p>
        <p>339 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
        <p>Who is this Nathan Englander, at 37 so young in novelist years, but already possessed of an old master's voice? Well, it's not his voice exactly; one senses that Bernard Malamud and Isaac Bashevis Singer are living under the name Nathan Englander in a witness protection program for Jewish fabulists. But the man's apparent lack of vanity is impressive.</p>
        <p>At an age in the life cycle of the male fiction writer normally characterized by the peacock strut of recently acquired style, voice being easier to conjure than character, Englander demonstrates with his first novel, ''The Ministry of Special Cases,'' that he's willing to channel the dead, to disappear into a tradition suffused with older rhythms, as if translated from the Yiddish. He's willing to forge a style not all his own -- or not his own at all.</p>
        <p>There's an impersonality to Englander's voice that reads as an act of homage to the Jewish past. He may have abandoned the Orthodox Judaism under which he was raised, but in his writing, he appears to rebel against his rebellion. In a splendid story called ''The Gilgul of Park Avenue'' from his remarkable 1999 collection, ''For the Relief of Unbearable Urges,'' the thoroughly secular Charles Luger awakes in a cab to the fact that he has a Jewish soul. ''Jewish, here in the back,'' he informs the driver. Englander's characters find themselves helplessly connected to a Jewish tradition that gives them an identity, whether they seek it or not.</p>
        <p>This is also true in ''The Ministry of Special Cases.'' Here, Englander might as well have airlifted Gimpel the Fool out of the shtetl and landed him in the broad avenues of Buenos Aires, where this novel is set. It is 1976, the outset of Argentina's ''Dirty War,'' in which nearly 30,000 students, union members and political opponents were ''disappeared'' by the military government. Not only have civil rights been suspended in this novel, the rules of realistic fiction have too. Englander's Argentina is a mythological realm, ruled more by the gods of literature than by the generals of the junta. Englander names his protagonist Kaddish, after the Jewish prayer of mourning. This is not like calling a character Joe or Don or Bobby Lee. A fellow named Kaddish has clearly got some heavy thematic lifting to do.</p>
        <p>Kaddish is an outsider's outsider -- not just a Jew but a Jew in Argentina, and not just a Jew in Argentina, but a Jew in Argentina condescended to by his fellow Jews. He's a schlemiel with a big nose, a hijo de puta, ''son of a whore,'' a husband who disappoints his long-suffering wife, a father who enrages his son (and accidentally maims him), a pariah hectored by rabbis, a literal chiseler whose vocation is to efface from tombstones the names of Jews buried in a cemetery of gangsters and prostitutes, thus sanitizing the reputations of the descendants who pay for this service. The more Kaddish fails, the more we love him. In the tradition of Jewish bumblers in literature, he seems protected by God. Or at least by the author.</p>
        <p>Kaddish is married to the stalwart Lillian, who works at an insurance company. They have a college-age son, Pato. He resentfully accompanies his father on his nighttime missions of effacement and then, back home, vanishes into his room to listen to rock 'n' roll. He's proud of his identity. When Kaddish and Lillian get nose jobs, in a comic subplot worthy of Gogol, Pato refuses to have his monumental honker bobbed.</p>
        <p>And then one night he is dragged from the family's apartment by men who carry three books with them as incriminating evidence; Kaddish has incinerated much of Pato's library to protect him but has failed to burn all the objectionable titles. Husband and wife scour Buenos Aires in search of their son. Lillian trudges to the Ministry of Special Cases, a nightmare bureaucracy out of Kafka, another of Englander's tutelary spirits. Guarded by clerks who abdicate responsibility with responses like ''not my decision,'' the ministry finally disgorges a prisoner into Lillian's custody -- but not Pato. She turns to a member of the Jewish establishment for help, a self-satisfied official named Feigenblum, who boasts that he's managed to get the government to ''admit that these are the people we accuse them of incarcerating.'' ''They admit that you accuse them?'' Lillian responds. ''That's your best?''</p>
        <p>It goes worse with Kaddish. He is led to a fisherman on a pier overlooking the Rio de la Plata. Bearded, tattooed, an ominous, ruined jester, the fisherman tells Kaddish: ''A guilty man can't get himself killed in this town. Only the innocent need watch out. ... I'm living proof.'' He confesses how he used to push drugged captives out of airplanes high above the sea. He is haunted by a girl who startled out of her stupor long enough to try to pull her killer into the sky with her. ''The government sees me as a treasure,'' he says. ''I'm the man who tells their secret and out of whose mouth it sounds like a lie.''</p>
        <p>After this encounter, Kaddish starts living up to his name and praying for the dead. He believes his son is among them, though Lillian refuses to give up Pato for lost. She sits in the apartment, looking out the window, waiting for her son to come around the corner. Just as Kaddish chips away at gravestones, Englander hammers his themes so deeply that the foundation of the novel begins to crack. He has superimposed a fable of Jewish continuity onto a political novel about the Dirty War. The two forms jostle uneasily against each other like prisoners squeezed inside too narrow a cell. Kaddish, Lillian and Pato are lovable and kindhearted -- perhaps too much so, as odd as that may sound. ''The Ministry of Special Cases'' lives up to its title: its characters are so sweet, so literary in antecedent, that they seem exceptions to the grim rules of historical catastrophe. This is true even though Pato disappears. The family bickers and fusses, but their affection endures through every disaster. One reads this novel in awe of Englander's talent, and yet with a nagging sense of the distance between his characters and the actual Argentines persecuted during the war. His themes devour the real; history seems invented to provide all those elegant variations on disappearance, on loss of identity.</p>
        <p>In a jail cell, for instance, an imprisoned girl discovers tiny notes Pato has left behind in a mattress. She reads them, swallows them for safekeeping and then is thrown into the sea, where writing and girl dissolve in the motion of the waves -- indecipherable, vanished. It's an unbearably lyrical passage. And that feels false.</p>
        <p>Doesn't the larger-than-life quality of the fable employed here make the disappeared disappear again, not into the sea but into a fairy tale of redemption and continuity? Englander softens the jagged edges of history too much; the Dirty War becomes a stage set for explorations of identity. Beautifully written, ''The Ministry of Special Cases'' nonetheless presents a conundrum. Englander does in fiction what his absent God cannot: create a world. And then he peoples that world with characters that he treats better than history ever would. Such decency is not a large failing in a young novelist. If only the junta had been half so kind.</p>
        <p>Will Blythe is the author of ''To Hate Like This Is to Be Happy Forever.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Will Blythe is the author of ''To Hate Like This Is to Be Happy Forever.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
