<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Travel Tips From a Dog's Best Friend</title>
    <meta content="03pracdog" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/travel/03pracdog.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851643"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRACTICAL TRAVELER: TRANSPORTING PETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Millan, Cesar</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Higgins, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Practical Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E0DF1730F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1127" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Travel Tips From a Dog's Best Friend</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Travel Tips From a Dog’s Best Friend</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELLE HIGGINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Higgins, Michelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michelle Higgins Practical Traveler column interviews Cesar Millan, dog behaviorist and author, who offers advice on traveling with dogs; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRAVELING with pets is an increasingly common affair, as many pet owners have decided that Fido deserves a summer vacation as much as they do, and shouldn't be left behind in a kennel while they are off lounging on a beach or taking in the mountain air.</p>
        <p>The travel industry has been quick to cash in on this trend: many hotels now offer packages with pet beds and special room-service menus for four-legged companions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cesar Millan, better known as National Geographic Channel’s Dog Whisperer, answers questions about traveling with pets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TRAVELING with pets is an increasingly common affair, as many pet owners have decided that Fido deserves a summer vacation as much as they do, and shouldn't be left behind in a kennel while they are off lounging on a beach or taking in the mountain air.</p>
        <p>The travel industry has been quick to cash in on this trend: many hotels now offer packages with pet beds and special room-service menus for four-legged companions.</p>
        <p>But many pet owners still have concerns about hitting the road -- or, to be more specific, the sky. More than two million pets and other live animals are transported by air every year in the United States, according to the Department of Transportation. Though rare, incidents involving the loss, injury or death of animals do happen. During June, July and August of last year, 12 animals, mostly dogs, died, 3 were injured and 4 were lost during air travel.</p>
        <p>For tips on traveling with your dog or leaving one behind when taking a vacation, I talked with Cesar Millan, a dog behaviorist and best-selling author, better known as National Geographic Channel's Dog Whisperer. Mr. Millan, a native of Mexico, also owns the Dog Psychology Center in Los Angeles, which specializes in rehabilitating dogs with extreme behavior problems. When we spoke by phone, he was in Miami with two dogs -- Daddy and Coco -- who were going to travel to Minneapolis to film an episode of the show.</p>
        <p>Q. How do you travel with your dogs?</p>
        <p>A. Right now, I'm fortunate to travel with two of them -- a pitbull and a Chihuahua. They're not flying with me, but we have an R.V., which is much easer for them because they're able to meet the land. I ask the driver: every four hours, make sure they experience where they are.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you have any advice for people who can't take their pets cross-country by car?</p>
        <p>A. My large personal dogs have never traveled on a plane. My small dogs have, and it's easier because, you know, they're next to us, right there under the seat, as they request on the airline. So it feels like they're just doing a different activity. Of course, they're going to feel the altitude, and so I'm going to be right there to calm them down, just to make them feel relaxed. But until I get my own private plane, my large dogs will not fly.</p>
        <p>Q. So you always have them take the R.V. and not a plane?</p>
        <p>A. Yes, because it's not very controlled in the areas where they put the large dogs. I hope the airlines will get smart about it and learn that it's business, because we do want to bring our dogs with us. But they have to be able to make sure the temperature is ideal, and ideally a human can be there just to provide some kind of comfort to dogs. I think it can be done -- it's just a matter of whether the airlines are willing to do it.</p>
        <p>Q. More hotels are trying to appeal to pet owners with special doggy beds and room service. Does it matter what kind of hotel you stay at?</p>
        <p>A. They don't understand if it costs $1 or $300. They can't make the difference between Bloomingdale's and Kmart. What they're going to know is what state of mind they were in when you offered that.</p>
        <p>Q. Any tips for traveling by car?</p>
        <p>A. Dogs are daytime animals, and my pack is so accustomed to do activities in the daytime that at least every four hours the driver stops and walks them, which is good for the driver and is good for my dogs. It's important for a dog to know the land because in a way they're migrating to another place. It's important for them to see and to smell the environment. Wherever they are, it's going to be a different temperature, a different scent and a different feeling. You want to be sure they know how to associate themselves with it in a more natural way.</p>
        <p>Q. Is sedation an option?</p>
        <p>A. Yeah, but again you have to condition the mind to see what the side effects are and what doses work and what medication works. It shouldn't make them lethargic. It's just for them to feel thoroughly relaxed. It's like a glass of wine. It doesn't have to make you feel angry or frustrated. It's just to relax you.</p>
        <p>Q. How should you choose a kennel?</p>
        <p>A. You want to find a place where they immediately know how to adopt a dog and to make a dog really not focused on the fact that you left but really focused on what is there for him. It's very important that professionals learn it's a big deal for a dog to detach himself from his pack, and so the new pack has to be just as good or better than the pack he just left.</p>
        <p>Q. What about dogs that get nervous when traveling? Is there anything you can do to keep them calm?</p>
        <p>A. If a dog is nervous at home, it's more likely for him to get worse in different environments. You definitely have to work, before you go on the vacation, to start learning about how you can make your dog not nervous at home. Everything starts from home. A lot of people also get frustrated when they're traveling, and the dog is trembling or whining or drooling. But that's not going to help the dog either. Your energy influences a lot, and once you recognize and become aware of the energy you share when your dog is under stress, then you realize, oh, O.K., I have to work on myself.</p>
        <p>Q. Are some dogs more suited to travel than others?</p>
        <p>A. Balanced dogs. It's not the breed or the size. You can't generalize that the size or the breed will make it a better travel dog. A balanced dog is always going to be a perfect dog to be around; an unstable dog, regardless of the size, is not going to be comfortable to travel with. So it's a state of mind, not a breed or a size.</p>
        <p>Q. Is there anything else travelers should keep in mind?</p>
        <p>A. Once you arrive at your destination, make sure you go for a long walk before you go inside the hotel or the condominium or wherever you're going because that will give a dog a better understanding of where they are and what the surroundings are, and that the same rules and boundaries or limitations that you might have had in L.A. exist in Florida. That will make him feel so comfortable, so at home, and enjoy his new adventure.</p>
        <p>PRACTICAL TRAVELER: TRANSPORTING PETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
