<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Pursuit of Beauty</title>
    <meta content="03books" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/fashion/03books.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851888"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF STYLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E4D81330F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="881" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Pursuit of Beauty</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Pursuit of Beauty</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIESL SCHILLINGER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yoga Facelift  By Marie-Véronique Nadeau.  160 pp. Conari Press.  $19.95.</p>
        <p>The 5-Minute Face  By Carmindy.  208 pp. HarperCollins.  $19.95.</p>
        <p>MARIE-VÉRONIQUE NADEAU, limber and vital at 58, could be one of those women on the disconcerting new shampoo ads who whip their shiny lush tresses aside to reveal a face that's more Fairy Godmother than Rapunzel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE YOGA FACELIFT.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yoga Facelift  By Marie-Véronique Nadeau.  160 pp. Conari Press.  $19.95.</p>
        <p>The 5-Minute Face  By Carmindy.  208 pp. HarperCollins.  $19.95.</p>
        <p>MARIE-VÉRONIQUE NADEAU, limber and vital at 58, could be one of those women on the disconcerting new shampoo ads who whip their shiny lush tresses aside to reveal a face that's more Fairy Godmother than Rapunzel.</p>
        <p>''I've never felt more vivacious or self-assured in my life,'' she declares. The secret to her inner and outer radiance? Specialized yoga for 10 to 15 minutes a day. Could it really be this easy? As Ms. Nadeau demonstrates in her new book, ''The Yoga Facelift,'' easy may not be the operative word.</p>
        <p>She recommends that practitioners start by standing with their backs to a mirror, feet apart, and bend at the waist to view their upside-down reddened faces.</p>
        <p>Multiple chins and sagging cheeks are a typical finding. ''Take a few seconds to recover from the shock, then take note of the areas where you will want to work,'' she counsels.</p>
        <p>One pose that helps firm the neck-and-facial terrain is the Lion, described by her daughter as ''the cat coughing up a hairball exercise.'' She instructs that the following must be done all at once: ''Exhale forcefully, make an O with your mouth, then smile without changing the O shape (this forces the cheeks towards the ears), open your eyes wide, and look up.''</p>
        <p>Then stick your tongue out and down, like Gene Simmons from Kiss, and growl ''RRRRRR'' as fiercely as you can. (This may not stop aging, but at least you can go down roaring.)</p>
        <p>Her book uses photographs to illustrate specific exercises to combat crows'-feet, turkey wattles, marionette lines and the other playfully named but soul-shrinking acquisitions of age.</p>
        <p>Rejecting ''treadmill bondage,'' she favors gentler workouts (''You can be a couch potato and still remain a hot tomato'') and asks her readers to avoid harsh exfoliation procedures like glycolic peels, Retin-A and microdermabrasion, which she believes ''ultimately accelerate aging.''</p>
        <p>Nor does she approve of more drastic measures assisted by Botox injections and scalpels. ''Wiping all the character from a person's face is the most profound form of identity theft I can imagine,'' she writes.</p>
        <p>The author advocates a holistic life, incorporating calisthenics, a healthy diet and edible beauty products. She gives recipes for nourishing masks made of honey, oatmeal and avocado, and an exfoliating mask of sour cream.</p>
        <p>(Note: I tried the sour cream mask and it works surprisingly well, leaving skin tingling and refreshed, but producing a craving for borscht.)</p>
        <p>FOR women who find the Downward Dog too much of a challenge and a 10-minute daily workout too great a commitment, Carmindy, the makeup miracle worker from TLC's ''What Not to Wear,'' has created a sweat-free face fix. In ''The 5-Minute Face,'' she shares the shortcuts from her 15 years as a cosmetic artist, as well as her generous view of beauty: ''I don't believe that women are flawed or that there is any set standard of beauty they MUST meet.'' Still, she recognizes that some features are better than others, and encourages women to optimize their best points.</p>
        <p>Carmindy breaks down her palette by skin tones. For porcelain-skinned redheads she recommends ''soft peaches, coppers, bronzy tones.'' Blondes, she writes, should use an opal-iridescent shimmer highlight to give skin a ''sexy, ethereal look.'' She advises Asian women to use rose or plum blush and lipstick, and mentions a useful half-inch-wide lash curler.</p>
        <p>Emerald green, brown or deep wine eye shadows work well for women with mocha skin, she says, while dark-skinned women can line the inner rims of their eyelids with sapphire blue pencil to make the eyes ''pop.'' Women with olive skin are urged to enhance their natural lip color with sheer shimmery nude gloss. Each beauty prescription is accompanied by a full-color photograph of a ravishing woman who could look better in five minutes than most women could in five hours.</p>
        <p>''The 5-Minute Face'' also breaks down looks for special occasions and for different age groups. Carmindy advises teenagers to just say yes to colored mascara, but avoid ''rampant overplucking of eyebrows.'' Women in their 30s are warned, ''There is nothing worse than seeing a woman in her thirties wearing glitter.'' And those in their 50s are urged to have their teeth whitened and to ''say no to tattooed on makeup.'' A shopping guide offers women tools to recreate each look, with high-end and economy options for products with drool-worthy names like diamond cream shimmer, truffle eye color, outside cafe blush and strawberry cream lip sauce.</p>
        <p>Carmindy came by her fascination with makeup as a teenager, watching her artist mother paint watercolors. Her mother's technique inspired her own: using sheer washes of color, and showing the face's main attractions. ''I want makeup to be a fast and foolproof way for all women to maximize their beauty potential,'' she writes, but most women know this is not as simple as it sounds. Foolproof can depend on the fool wielding the purple mascara wand and baby-blue cream eye shadow.</p>
        <p>In a perfect world, Ms. Nadeau and Carmindy would make house calls, showing women how to work their magic. As it is, you'll have to take up their spell books and try your luck.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF STYLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
