<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Around-the-World Ticket for Your Portfolio</title>
    <meta content="03fund" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/business/yourmoney/03fund.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851908"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FUNDAMENTALLY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Fundamentally</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E1D81330F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1144" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Around-the-World Ticket for Your Portfolio</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Around-the-World Ticket for Your Portfolio</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL J. LIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lim, Paul J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOREIGN stocks can add some ballast to your portfolio, despite the effects of globalization.</p>
        <p>To be sure, domestic and overseas equities are more in sync with each other than they have ever been. This has led some investors to question whether owning foreign shares does anything to reduce volatility in a stock portfolio.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>To benefit from buying foreign stocks, investors must be willing to buy and hold shares from all parts of the world  not just regions where stocks are running hot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOREIGN stocks can add some ballast to your portfolio, despite the effects of globalization.</p>
        <p>To be sure, domestic and overseas equities are more in sync with each other than they have ever been. This has led some investors to question whether owning foreign shares does anything to reduce volatility in a stock portfolio.</p>
        <p>The answer is clear, says Liz Ann Sonders, chief investment strategist at Charles Schwab. ''Even though correlations between domestic and foreign stocks have increased over the last 10 years,'' she said, ''there is still some diversification benefit.'' But to enjoy that benefit, investors must be willing to buy and hold shares from all parts of the world -- not just those regions where stocks are now running hot. And it remains to be seen whether many people are willing to do that.</p>
        <p>Currently, there is a correlation of about 85 percent between movements in the Standard &amp; Poor's 500 index of domestic stocks and the Morgan Stanley Capital International EAFE (for Europe, Australia and the Far East) index of foreign shares. To put that in perspective, a 100 percent correlation would imply that the two asset classes move in perfect lock step.</p>
        <p>But it is important to note that not all individual foreign markets are so closely aligned with Wall Street. Consider Japan. Currently, there is a correlation of only 29 percent between movements in Japanese stocks and United States stocks, according to S.&amp; P. And over the last 20 years, that figure has never risen higher than 59 percent. Several other Asian stock markets are also relatively uncorrelated with the S.&amp; P. 500, including India, at 43 percent; Hong Kong, 55 percent; and South Korea, 67 percent.</p>
        <p>That means Asian stocks could help diversify your portfolio more than European or even Latin American equities. Markets in Germany, France, Spain and Britain, for example, all now have a correlation of more than 80 percent correlation with the S.&amp; P. 500. There is a 74 percent correlation between Mexican stocks and domestic shares.</p>
        <p>Yet recently, the bulk of new investments into foreign stock funds has been going into international portfolios that invest either exclusively or primarily in Europe. There has been far less enthusiasm for Asian funds, especially those that invest primarily in Japan.</p>
        <p>That is not terribly surprising. ''Those investments that have done well recently are attracting new money, while those investments which are performing below average aren't,'' says Greg Schultz, a principal at Asset Allocation Advisors, a financial planning firm in Walnut Creek, Calif. European stocks have been among the best-performing assets lately.</p>
        <p>Over the last three years, European equities have returned nearly 22 percent, annualized. In 2006 alone, the average European stock fund delivered total returns of nearly 34 percent, according to Morningstar, the fund tracker.</p>
        <p>This would explain why United States investors plowed nearly $11 billion of net new money last year into European stock funds and an additional $102 billion into funds that invest a vast majority of their assets in that region, according to the Financial Research Corporation, which tracks fund flows.</p>
        <p>By comparison, Japanese stock funds -- which lost nearly 2 percent, on average, in 2006 -- received only about $2.6 billion in net new investments last year.</p>
        <p>Is there anything wrong with betting exclusively on Europe? Well, if you are a market timer who thinks that European equities are poised to outperform other markets significantly this year, the answer is no.</p>
        <p>Moreover, one could argue that while domestic and European stocks tend to move in tandem, the two asset classes have delivered different degrees of returns recently -- with European stocks trouncing domestic shares over the last three years.</p>
        <p>But this begs a question. ''How does that help if the U.S. market starts to turn down?'' asks Alec Young, international equity strategist at S.&amp; P. Equity Research. ''At the end of the day, you want something that will zig when the S.&amp; P. 500 zags.''</p>
        <p>This means that if you are investing in foreign stocks, aiming for some long-term overseas diversification, you must be willing to spread your bets into less-correlated regions of the world -- even if those regions aren't performing so well at the moment.</p>
        <p>At the very least, you have to be willing to invest in Asia in addition to Western Europe and Latin America, Mr. Young says. Given that many emerging markets have posted above-average gains since the start of the decade, it may be smart to look for value in Asian stocks in the developed markets. That would point to Japan, a huge market that has greatly underperformed over the last decade.</p>
        <p>For instance, say you now invest 50 percent of your equity portfolio in domestic stocks, with the other half in European shares. Over the last decade, the worst three-month stretch for such a portfolio would have been a loss of 18.6 percent from July to September 2002, according to Morningstar.</p>
        <p>If had you put 20 percent of your foreign stake in Japanese stocks with the remaining 30 percent in Europe, your worst three-month loss would have been slightly less: 17.3 percent. And your portfolio would have been 7 percent less volatile over the last five years.</p>
        <p>Why can Japanese equities, in small doses, help diversify your holdings?</p>
        <p>For starters, they add another region of the world to your mix, which on its own provides some extra diversification benefit. And in general, Mr. Young says, ''you have a greater number of differences in terms of the things that impact stock prices.''</p>
        <p>For example, in recent months, stocks in the United States and Europe have been rising in part because of a flurry of merger-and-acquisition activity in those two regions.</p>
        <p>In the first quarter this year, Europe and North America accounted for 82 percent of the $1.1 trillion in global deal activity, according to Thomson Financial. By comparison, Japan accounted for just 4 percent, which may help explain why correlations with the Japanese market have been lower recently, Mr. Young said.</p>
        <p>IF you invest in a broad-based foreign stock fund, you will have some exposure to Japan and other parts of Asia. For instance, the average foreign large growth stock fund holds 16.7 percent of its assets in Japan, according to Morningstar. Still, that is less than the nearly 23 percent weighting of Japanese equities in the MSCI EAFE index.</p>
        <p>For diversification, S.&amp; P. recommends that investors add a 3 percent allocation to Japanese stocks, over and above their exposure to the broad foreign markets. Again, this is not because Japanese stocks are expected to take off, as European or Latin American shares have done in recent years.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Young argues that if global volatility rises in the coming months -- which a number of market strategists expect -- a small additional ''satellite'' allocation to Japanese stocks may give your portfolio a softer cushion if United States and European equities tumble.</p>
        <p>FUNDAMENTALLY Paul J. Lim is a financial writer at U.S. News &amp; World Report. E-mail: fund@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Paul J. Lim is a financial writer at U.S. News &amp; World Report. E-mail: fund@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
