<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where the World Meets Sweden, And Vice Versa</title>
    <meta content="03next" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/travel/03next.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851645"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEXT STOP: GOTEBORG"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Goteborg (Sweden)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sweden</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ferren, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Next Stop</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Sweden/Goteborg</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Goteborg (Sweden)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E0DF1730F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where the World Meets Sweden, And Vice Versa</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Where the World Meets Sweden, and Vice Versa</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW FERREN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ferren, Andrew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Andrew Ferren travel article on visit to Goteborg, Sweden; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE its big sister Stockholm, Goteborg, Sweden's second city, is as much about boats and water as it is about bricks and mortar. Built on the broad estuary of the Gota River, greater Goteborg stretches for miles before fanning out into the North Sea across an archipelago of some 1,000 islands.</p>
        <p>While most of them are no more than bare rocks that turn into popular perches for sunbathing Swedes in the heat of summer, others have small villages and are served by ferries. In a city that has more tour boats than buses, getting out on the water is a must.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like its big sister Stockholm, Goteborg, Sweden’s second city, is as much about boats and water as it is about bricks and mortar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE its big sister Stockholm, Goteborg, Sweden's second city, is as much about boats and water as it is about bricks and mortar. Built on the broad estuary of the Gota River, greater Goteborg stretches for miles before fanning out into the North Sea across an archipelago of some 1,000 islands.</p>
        <p>While most of them are no more than bare rocks that turn into popular perches for sunbathing Swedes in the heat of summer, others have small villages and are served by ferries. In a city that has more tour boats than buses, getting out on the water is a must.</p>
        <p>Another must is tasting the city's modern Swedish gastronomy (four restaurants rate stars in the Michelin Guide). The city has been home to seven of the last 12 national Chef of the Year titles as decided in a national competition. Stockholm's chefs, as anyone in Goteborg can -- and will -- tell you, have won just two.</p>
        <p>But any competitiveness ends there; within the city's foodie community there is a relaxed sense of pride and camaraderie. When asked to recommend another restaurant, Linda Rasberg, the headwaiter at the Michelin-starred Fond, quickly drafted an annotated list of eight suggestions.</p>
        <p>The same Scandinavian plain dealing occurs in the performing arts, with equal prominence given the city's dance troupes or philharmonic as to the popular heavy metal festivals like Pier Pressure on July 1.</p>
        <p>Founded by King Gustaf II Adolf in 1621, Goteborg has a considerable history in international relations, starting with the city's raison d'être, which was to get the Danes off Sweden's west coast. The king invited Dutch engineers to build a fortified city on the marshy banks of the river, and gave them incentives to remain when the work was completed.</p>
        <p>In the 18th century, German traders received a similarly warm reception, as did the East India Company, which was established there in 1731, bringing huge revenues and exotic Asian wares into the country. A century later, the influx was British -- Scots mostly -- with expertise in shipbuilding and brewing, and new fortunes quite literally washed ashore.</p>
        <p>But immigration flowed both ways. If you're Swedish-American, there is a good chance your ancestors spent their last European night in Goteborg, which was the principal massing and departure point for the half-million Swedes who headed to America in the late 19th and early 20th centuries.</p>
        <p>A young city by European standards, Goteborg still retains a trace of the frontier town, a little like a Swedish San Francisco that promises vast riches for those bold enough to give the city a try. It has a similar boom-bust résumé and, not surprisingly, there is a slightly aspirational aspect to the city's architecture, from the studied formality of the compact and orderly Baroque city carved out of a swamp by the Dutch, to the more audaciously grandiose new city that spread out to the south when the walls came down in the 19th century.</p>
        <p>For a glimpse of the latter, look no farther than the broodingly massive Goteborg Museum of Art, crowning a hill above the old city. Built in 1923 in belated celebration of the city's tricentennial, it has the kind of taut rationalist classicism that Albert Speer stayed up nights striving for in Berlin a generation later. Its grand plaza has theaters for concerts and the ballet on either side, and a colossal, yet somehow spritely, bronze Poseidon gazes down to the harbor from the city's cultural acropolis.</p>
        <p>Hugging the foundations of the museum walls and enclosed in a sheer glass and steel arc is Fond, the luxuriously minimalist canteen run by Stefan Karlsson (the 1995 Chef of the Year). A recent meal there began with a selection of crusty, seed-flecked dark breads that arrived with a decadent butter sampler -- butter with flakes of sea salt, butter whipped with yogurt and olive oil, and cream cheese topped with toasted olive oil.</p>
        <p>The struggle to save room for dinner was rewarded by panko-crusted langoustines served with an orange-perfumed cream sauce and diced roasted turnips. Then came tiny tender pink lamb filets with more root vegetables and a compote that involved roasted garlic and milk and was exponentially more delicious than it sounded.</p>
        <p>My dinner, with two glasses of cabernet franc, came to 660 kronor (about $95, at 7 kronor to the dollar) -- expensive, yes, but it was a truly memorable meal of pure, clean flavors that were yet satisfyingly homey.</p>
        <p>To offset that expenditure, I joined the locals for lunch the next day at the central city market, the Stora Saluhallen, bellying up to the bar at Kagelbaren for baseball-size Swedish meatballs in a rich brown gravy served with the standard boiled potatoes, lingonberry preserves, green salad and a glass of water for a mere 45 kronor (a light beer will set you back a further 29 kronor).</p>
        <p>The market sits just inside the old city, which is now bordered by the verdant Kungsparken that replaced the old city walls along the Dutch-built moat. The main boulevard crossing this park is the grand Kungsportsavenyn, better known as the Avenyn, which is the axis on which most of Goteborg's prominent shops and restaurants, not to mention theaters and nightclubs, can be found.</p>
        <p>LONG winters seem to have made the Swedes excellent nest featherers, and the city has a number of noteworthy housewares emporiums.</p>
        <p>Josephssons sells everything from Orrefors (its colorful and lower-priced Home line fills many a shop window) to charming brikka mugg sets (small plates with indentations for a mug that are perfect for transporting soup and a sandwich to a favorite armchair on a cold winter day). NK, the gold standard of Swedish department stores, is similarly stocked with clever kitchen gadgets, as well as stylish Swedish designers, with folks like Filippa K, J. Lindeberg or the stationers Ordning &amp; Reda having swank in-store boutiques.</p>
        <p>Luxury retail is nothing new here: for 80 years until 1810, the East India Company had 36 clipper ships making the trip to East Asia and returning with porcelains, silks and spices. The company's former headquarters on the central canal is now the City Museum, displaying local history from the Vikings to a provocative look at Sweden's neutrality during World War II.</p>
        <p>The influence of Asia is surprisingly prominent at the Rohsska Museum of Decorative Arts, where an exceptional display of Chinese and Japanese furniture, textiles and ceramics underscore the aesthetic links between these cultures and Scandinavian design. At lunchtime, the museum's bright, sunny cafe serves a popular vegetarian buffet (79 kronor) as well as the biggest, greenest pear macaroons imaginable.</p>
        <p>Those looking for the vintage version of Swedish design should head to Haga, the city's oldest suburb, where the rows of beautifully restored 17th-century wooden houses now shelter cozy cafes and antiques stores. These include Sma Kara Ting, whose shelves heave under stacks of colorful and graphic 1950s and '60s Swedish ceramics -- tea pots, chafing dishes, casseroles -- which are hugely popular among Japanese collectors.</p>
        <p>Even Liseberg, a picturesque pink and green 1923 amusement park (not to worry, the rides have been updated) just a five-minute walk from the art museum, has an impressive shopping component -- everything from specimen rose bushes to clever rakes that pick up leaves up all by themselves. The annual Christmas fair brings in some 500,000 visitors, a number that exceeds the population of the metropolitan area. Yet more evidence that Goteborg is once again the place where Sweden meets the world.</p>
        <p>A NATION'S SECOND CITY THAT SEES ITSELF AS NO. 1 IN FOOD</p>
        <p>SAS (www.flysas.com) has service from Newark with a stopover in either Stockholm or Copenhagen. Recently, fares for travel in late June started at $683.</p>
        <p>Ryanair (www.ryanair.com) has discount fares from many European cities to Goteborg City airport with round-trip fares from London Stansted as low as at £35.45 ($70 at $2.01 to the pound) in late June.</p>
        <p>A Goteborg Pass (www.goteborg.com) offers free use of city trams, buses and archipelago boats, and free entry to virtually all museums and attractions. Best of all is avoiding the long lines to enter Liseberg amusement park. The passes come in 24- and 48-hour versions for 225 and 310 kronor, about $32 and $44 at 7 kronor to the dollar.</p>
        <p>WHERE TO STAY</p>
        <p>Elite Park Avenue Hotel (Kungsportsavenyn 36-38; 46-31-727-1000; www.elite.se) is situated handily for museums and night life. The 291 rooms have a slick urbane touch. Doubles from 1,300 kronor.</p>
        <p>Hotel Flora (Gronsakstorget 2; 46-31-138-616; www.hotelflora.se) has 68 rooms near the heart of the old city with a casual décor and free wireless Internet. Doubles are 1,195 kronor but drop to 850 on the weekends.</p>
        <p>WHERE TO EAT</p>
        <p>At Fond (Gotaplatsen; 46-31-812-580; www.fondrestaurang.com), the elegantly minimalist décor lets bold flavors stand out. Dinner for two with wine, 1,500 kronor.</p>
        <p>Basement (Gotabergsgatan 28; 46-31-282-729; www.restbasement.com) is the second restaurant of Ulf Wagner to receive a Michelin star. It offers tasting menus of four to eight small courses with wine starting at 1,135 kronor a person.</p>
        <p>Kagelbaren (Stora Saluhallen; 46-31-130-700) is a fast-paced lunch counter serving authentic home-style Swedish fare augmented by a few exotic plates like the very popular chili con carne salad. Lunch for two with beer, 150 kronor.</p>
        <p>Locatelli (Kungsportsavenyn 36-38; 46-31-727-1089) is a chic, lively Italian restaurant in the Elite Park Avenue Hotel with a lounge where stylish Swedes meet over vodka drinks made with homemade juices. Cocktails from 82 kronor.</p>
        <p>NEXT STOP: GOTEBORG</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
