<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Charming Filly</title>
    <meta content="Banks.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="42" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/books/review/Banks-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851596"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Ruffian: A Racetrack Romance (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E1D61630F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Charming Filly</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Charming Filly</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC BANKS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RUFFIAN</p>
        <p>A Racetrack Romance.</p>
        <p>By William Nack.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 111 pp. ESPN Books. $14.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ruffian won all 10 of her starts (handily) before her disastrous stumble.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RUFFIAN</p>
        <p>A Racetrack Romance.</p>
        <p>By William Nack.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 111 pp. ESPN Books. $14.95.</p>
        <p>BEFORE Barbaro, there was Ruffian. More than three decades have elapsed since that great horse broke down on the Belmont Park backstretch in perhaps the most hyped race ever, yet she continues to rouse the popular imagination. This week, nearly 32 years after the fact, a television movie about that licorice-black filly is scheduled for broadcast by ABC. The consultant on the project was William Nack, author of the renowned ''Secretariat: The Making of a Champion.'' Experiencing on the set a déjà vu trip back to the mid-1970s (felons have received lesser sentences), Nack was stirred again by the memory of Ruffian. As he writes in this short, fascinating, melancholy hybrid of turf history and personal memoir, ''I have thought of Ruffian so often over the years that today she flits around like a ghost in all the mustier rooms of my reveries, a boarder who has had a run of the place.''</p>
        <p>Maybe it's no surprise that Ruffian's story keeps being retold. She had the lickety-split to reach fifth gear two steps out of the gate and hit cruise control soon after. But she did so with an impossible-to-define elegance that turned hardened handicappers into lovesick, weak-kneed school kids. The result of any race involving Ruffian -- from the dazzling 15-length victory in her debut on May 22, 1974, through her waltz in the Coaching Club American Oaks 13 months later -- had become a fait accompli. She'd set or tied the track record in all eight stakes races she entered. She'd won her 10 starts over all by an average of eight lengths (more than 60 feet); for that matter, she'd never even trailed at any pole in any race. ''I had never seen a 2-year-old do what she was doing,'' Nack writes in ''Ruffian,'' and ''with an insouciance that bordered on the downright cavalier, moving as she pleased with a restrained grace and power and at velocities rarely seen in animals so young. She was, in my experience, sui generis.''</p>
        <p>After Ruffian had won so many races in so complete a fashion, ''she had become a kind of national pet.'' As journalists began to call for her trainer, Frank Whiteley, to test her mettle against colts, the New York Racing Association arranged the Great Match Race, a two-horse battle pitting Ruffian against Foolish Pleasure, winner of the 1975 Kentucky Derby. A mere 42 seconds into the race, the unbeaten filly took a bad step and shattered the minuscule sesamoid bones in her ankle. Veterinarians labored through the evening to save her but, as was eventually the case with Barbaro, it was to no avail. She was buried in the Belmont infield, a singular honor at that time in the track's history.</p>
        <p>Before tragedy came farce. Horse racing in New York (as elsewhere) was beginning its long, slow decline in the mid-'70s, losing attendance after the introduction of Off-Track Betting in 1971 and the establishment of the state lottery in 1966, and the match race was seen as a potential bonanza. On the heels of the Billie Jean King-Bobby Riggs ''Battle of the Sexes'' spectacle, the N.Y.R.A. shilled the race as a boy-against-girl showdown (in Nack's words, ''refrying some very old and tasteless beans''). However it was billed, it backfired, and Ruffian's breakdown in front of 18 million television viewers that Sunday afternoon poisoned the sport in many of their eyes. If feminism survived the Great Match Race, many observers mark July 6, 1975, as a date from which racing never recovered.</p>
        <p>Count Nack among them. For him the romance with racing had been burning for two decades, from his teenage years near Chicago, where the match-race defeat of his beloved Swaps at the hoofs of Nashua made him lose his lunch in a neighbor's yard. At the University of Illinois, he pored over dusty 19th-century accounts of the breed, and during the Tet offensive, stationed just outside Saigon, he listened over and over to the tapes his mother sent him of the calls of important races. (''I had left my recorder and tapes under my bed at the Prince Hotel on Tran Hung Dao, and it pleasured me now to imagine some VC colonel lying on his back on my mattress ... listening in curious wonder to the call of Damascus winning the Travers by 22.'')</p>
        <p>In looking back at that halcyon year with Ruffian and its horrific denouement, Nack is ever a sensitive observer, and by 1975 he knew something had changed in the sport. (Match races will have that effect: they are the sport at its most atavistic, with the all-out head-to-head competition akin to that of an 18th-century blood sport.) The breeding industry had emphasized speed over stamina -- ''These were the termites in the walls of the breed. Ruffian was not without her own nest of them'' -- with a resulting rise of fatal breakdowns. Watching the ministrations to a dying gelding, he writes, he began to see not ''the old romantic notion, shaped by those summers'' in Chicago ''and all that reading I had done in college,'' but ''a picture framed by cannon bones and inked in darker and more somber hues.'' When he witnessed the stricken Ruffian, in shock and pain before being euthanized, that ink had fully dried. Some might scoff at describing the demise of a horse (and all she symbolized) as a tragedy, but Nack's requiem -- for the animal, for his feelings -- summons nothing less.</p>
        <p>Eric Banks is the editor in chief of Bookforum. He has written on horse racing for Slate and Newsweek.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Eric Banks is the editor in chief of Bookforum. He has written on horse racing for Slate and Newsweek.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
