<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shattered</title>
    <meta content="Towers.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/books/review/Towers-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851639"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Schulman, Helen</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Day at the Beach, A (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E6DF1730F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shattered</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shattered</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH TOWERS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A DAY AT THE BEACH</p>
        <p>By Helen Schulman.</p>
        <p>214 pp. Houghton Mifflin Company. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In this novel, a marriage’s fault lines are revealed after the events of 9/11.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A DAY AT THE BEACH</p>
        <p>By Helen Schulman.</p>
        <p>214 pp. Houghton Mifflin Company. $24.</p>
        <p>On the one hand, it's bad timing: who would want their 9/11 novel to be published so soon after Don DeLillo's 9/11 novel? DeLillo, it's fair to say, began circling this material long ago. (The cover of ''Underworld,'' to name one uncanny example, had a planelike bird flying toward the twin towers.) On the other hand, if your novel happens to be as finely wrought, deeply felt and mercifully funny as Helen Schulman's ''Day at the Beach,'' then this timing turns out to be an affirming coincidence, allowing us to see how another talented writer can alchemize that same terrible day.</p>
        <p>For Schulman, whose novel unfolds over the course of 24 hours, the events of 9/11 function primarily as a shattering catalyst in the marriage of Gerhard and Suzannah Falktopf, a glamorous TriBeCa couple. Now in his mid-50s, Gerhard is a famous German choreographer; 36-year-old Suzannah, who was raised in the Bronx, is his former prima ballerina. (She has mostly given up dancing since the birth of their son, Nikolai, four years earlier.) Until 8:46 a.m. on Sept. 11, 2001, their lives are full of cultural and material -- if not emotional -- riches: Film Forum, dim sum, hip playgrounds, live jazz, linen handkerchiefs and, Gerhard's favorite for breakfast, duck eggs from the Union Square farmers' market. As we soon see, theirs is a union in which multiple layers of anger, disappointment and grief have been carefully spackled over.</p>
        <p>The planes change all that. The family witnesses the disaster from their loft and, as if the towers were a giant, flaming Rorschach test, their reactions are telling. Gerhard, staring at the tiny figures ''clinging to open windows above the gaping hole,'' can't help himself: ''Go down the stairs, Gerhard wanted to bellow. People were sheep. They needed someone to tell them what to do every minute of every day of their lives. Gerhard knew how to make decisions. He was a choreographer. If he were in that building he'd make those lost souls move.''</p>
        <p>For Suzannah, the sight of the burning towers is inextricably linked to her anxieties about her son: ''Forever after Suzannah would ask herself, Why did I take Nikolai with me to look? She'd be plagued by this question, once she crossed the bridge from that life to this life.'' And Nikolai, whose parents -- especially Suzannah -- are in excruciating denial about the cause of his spinning, humming and lack of eye contact, takes the mortal wounding of the towers to be his fault. ''Sowry,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Schulman, who has already written three accomplished novels and a collection of stories, isn't making any radical moves, at least in terms of her book's conceit. The somnambulant marriage split open by a pivotal event is a sturdy old trope, and in a classy aside she even tips her hat to Paula Fox's novel ''Desperate Characters'' when Gerhard finds a dog-eared copy in the back of a drawer. But what may be radical -- or at least a gamble -- is that Schulman desacralizes 9/11, turning it into a literary device and using it to infiltrate the inner lives of Gerhard and Suzannah.</p>
        <p>This move pays off thanks to the depth and limberness of her characterizations. Gerhard is a charismatic, irrepressible bastard. Part Balanchine, part big baby, he has had a hard time adjusting to Suzannah as a mother -- as someone else's mother. Schulman perfectly captures the sadism inherent in his desire to see his wife dance again:</p>
        <p>''Gerhard believed all dancers did their best work when they were just past the height of their powers, physically, technically, and yet had the wisdom of their experience, a deeper and more profound understanding of being in the world and were therefore reckless in their resolve not to waste any of it -- when they were under the spell of the ticking clock. When they were desperate. He wanted Suzannah on the stage. He wanted her back the way she was.''</p>
        <p>Yet Gerhard is also capable of unselfish acts. He rescues a terrified mother and her child; he quickly gets his family to the safety of a borrowed house in East Hampton; and as the day goes on he finds himself increasingly released from his rampaging ego, able to lose himself in life's prosaic delights: a sugary coconut cupcake; a beautiful mother and her blue-eyed baby; an encounter with a dear old friend. For both Gerhard and the reader, this is a moving relief.</p>
        <p>No such solace exists for Suzannah, who serves as the novel's emotional ground zero. Like Clarissa Dalloway, she is haunted by a falling man -- only here Suzannah actually sees the man jump. This figure soon begins to function as a terrifying reality principle: he ''swan-dived out of the blazing building and into her head,'' and there he remains. Suzannah can't deny him; nor, finally, can she deny the state of her marriage or the state of her beloved child. And it is here that Schulman mines the depths of maternal love and grief. ''You never kiss Nikolai,'' Suzannah, half-mad with exhaustion and defeat, shouts at Gerhard. ''So what if he's completely demented. ... He's demented and I still kiss him. I kiss him, I kiss him, I kiss him.''</p>
        <p>Nearly 3,000 people died on Sept. 11. Schulman's triumph here is that she breaks our hearts with three who lived.</p>
        <p>Sarah Towers teaches creative writing at the Bard Prison Initiative.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Sarah Towers teaches creative writing at the Bard Prison Initiative.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
