<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>You Won It! Now What Do You Do With It?</title>
    <meta content="03mill" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/theater/theaterspecial/03mill.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851708"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER: THE TONYS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Stuart</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Tony Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DB1430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="926" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>You Won It! Now What Do You Do With It?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">You Won It! Now What Do You Do With It?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART MILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Miller, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on where various Tony winners keep their awards; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JEFF WHITTY keeps his Tony Award in a display case, among his collection of vintage trophies for cheerleading, raccoon hunting, ballroom dancing and elderly bodybuilding. Philip Bosco isn't quite sure where his is at the moment. ''I guess it's up in my library somewhere,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Tony Award -- the Broadway theater's most celebrated honor, named for Antoinette Perry -- was first presented in 1947. That year there was just a scroll, along with a cigarette lighter or bill clip for men and a compact for women. But in 1949 a medallion was designed, emblazoned with the masks of comedy and tragedy. And beginning in the late 1960s the medallions came mounted on an arc-shaped arm sunk into a black pedestal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>What’s a person to do with their Tony? Several recipients reveal where they keep their award.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JEFF WHITTY keeps his Tony Award in a display case, among his collection of vintage trophies for cheerleading, raccoon hunting, ballroom dancing and elderly bodybuilding. Philip Bosco isn't quite sure where his is at the moment. ''I guess it's up in my library somewhere,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Tony Award -- the Broadway theater's most celebrated honor, named for Antoinette Perry -- was first presented in 1947. That year there was just a scroll, along with a cigarette lighter or bill clip for men and a compact for women. But in 1949 a medallion was designed, emblazoned with the masks of comedy and tragedy. And beginning in the late 1960s the medallions came mounted on an arc-shaped arm sunk into a black pedestal.</p>
        <p>But what's a person to do with it?</p>
        <p>''You're so stunned by the physical existence of this award,'' said Mr. Whitty, who won in 2004 for the book of ''Avenue Q.'' ''It's such a weird object to find a place for.''</p>
        <p>If Mr. Bosco, who won in 1989 as lead actor in ''Lend Me a Tenor,'' occupies one extreme, decrying the ''mania'' over such awards, perhaps Harvey Fierstein occupies the other.</p>
        <p>Although at the moment, Mr. Fierstein said, his Tonys for ''Torch Song Trilogy,'' ''La Cage aux Folles'' and ''Hairspray'' are in storage, this is only temporary. Once his home renovations are completed, he said, they will have a new setting, ''an absolutely terrific, spotlighted shelf on which they will be allowed to live out their days in bucolic comfort.''</p>
        <p>Somewhere in the middle, perhaps, is the costume designer William Ivey Long, whose collection includes Tonys for ''Nine'' (1982), ''Crazy for You'' (1992), ''The Producers'' (2001) and ''Hairspray.'' Mr. Long said he feels the awards should be ''a little private, just for me,'' so he keeps them on a marble mantelpiece in his private library.</p>
        <p>Bill Haber, a producer who has been involved in winners, from ''Proof'' to ''Spamalot'' to ''The History Boys,'' agreed. ''I don't think a gentleman should display his accomplishments.'' Mr. Haber exported his to his second home, in Tours, France. ''No one there speaks English or knows what a Tony is, so I'm not embarrassed by it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Christopher Plummer, who won for ''Cyrano'' in 1974 and ''Barrymore'' in 1997, feels keeping them in the living room would embarrass guests, so he stashes his ''in a back room, away from the rest of the house, to be as discreet as possible.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Plummer's current co-star in ''Inherit the Wind,'' Brian Dennehy, won in 1999 for ''Death of a Salesman'' and 2003 for ''Long Day's Journey Into Night.'' He also keeps his Tonys out of the spotlight, in his private office at home.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Dennehy, looking at the awards reminds him that an odd sense of loss accompanied the triumph of winning them. After all that anticipation, ''you're just holding a statuette,'' he said. ''You realize the next day the world is going to be the same place, and you still have to get up the next day and go find work.''</p>
        <p>Denis O'Hare, who won for best featured actor in ''Take Me Out'' (2003), tries to walk a middle path. ''I don't hide it, but I don't advertise,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Before it was temporarily packed away during renovations of his apartment, Mr. O'Hare's Tony was stuck on a little table behind a door, right next to a bobblehead figurine of the Yankee slugger Jason Giambi upon which a friend had glued a picture of Mr. O'Hare's face.</p>
        <p>Jeff Marx, who co-wrote the score for ''Avenue Q,'' gave his Tony to his parents in Florida, so they could show it off to ''the friends who said they were crazy to let me keep mooching money off them as I continued searching for my purpose well into my 30s.''</p>
        <p>While many winners share such pride, they also know not to take the award itself too seriously. When the lighting designer Brian MacDevitt won his first Tony in 2002 for ''Into the Woods,'' he placed it atop the toilet tank in his studio. ''I wasn't being disrespectful, I was trying for comic effect, to do a homage to false humility,'' he said.</p>
        <p>After winning a second one, for ''The Pillowman'' (2005), he brought the first out of the bathroom and onto his studio desk, where it is lost in the clutter, while the new one is unobtrusively in his study at home. ''If you asked my wife, she probably couldn't tell you where it is,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ruben Santiago-Hudson's Tony is near his collection of black memorabilia and photos of his children. ''People like to touch it and play with it,'' he said. ''I even let the babies play with it.'' And those babies who visit the home of Mr. Santiago-Hudson, who won for featured actor in a play, ''Seven Guitars'' in 1996, are not alone in enjoying the tactile pleasures of a Tony.</p>
        <p>Mary Zimmerman, the winning director of a play in 2002 for ''Metamorphoses,'' keeps hers in her living room near Northwestern University, where she teaches. ''Sometimes my students like to gather around and hold it,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Liev Schreiber, who won in 2005 for featured actor in a play, ''Glengarry Glen Ross,'' knows just how those students feel.</p>
        <p>''It is so much fun to spin,'' he said. ''It has really great action on it.'' Usually he keeps his in the office where he writes, but since he's currently acting (in ''Talk Radio''), he has brought it downstairs, ''just so I can spin it once in a while.''</p>
        <p>THEATER: THE TONYS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
