<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Howl</title>
    <meta content="Chapman.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="44" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/books/review/Chapman-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851603"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Doty, Mark</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Dog Years: A Memoir (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E0D61630F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="863" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Howl</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Howl</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIELLE CHAPMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DOG YEARS</p>
        <p>A Memoir.</p>
        <p>By Mark Doty.</p>
        <p>216 pp. HarperCollins Publishers. $23.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a memoir, the poet Mark Doty meditates on grief and the death of his dogs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DOG YEARS</p>
        <p>A Memoir.</p>
        <p>By Mark Doty.</p>
        <p>216 pp. HarperCollins Publishers. $23.95.</p>
        <p>Mention the term ''doggie lit'' to most winners of England's T. S. Eliot Prize for poetry and they'll probably think you're referring to a graduate course on classical representations of Cerberus -- or maybe to something Hollywood starlets give their Chihuahuas to browse while getting doggie pedicures. But Mark Doty, the only American to have won the prize (for his 1993 collection ''My Alexandria''), is that rare thing: a serious poet with what seems to be a keen eye for trends. At a time when John Grogan's ''Marley &amp; Me'' has revealed a public appetite for the gushing reveries of a dog owner, and Joan Didion's ''Year of Magical Thinking'' proved that readers can handle articulate narratives of grief, Doty has delivered a memoir that is both at once.</p>
        <p>Doty has long been an elegist. He is perhaps best known as the author of the stirring memoir ''Heaven's Coast'' (1996), which told of life lived in the grip of the AIDS epidemic and the eventual death of his partner, Wally, from the disease; and another memoir, ''Firebird'' (1999), about growing up gay and artistic in an itinerant, troubled Southern family. He has documented the personal and cultural toll of AIDS in several books of poems as well, particularly ''My Alexandria'' and ''Atlantis,'' large parts of which are elegies to Wally. Doty's dogs, Beau and Arden, have made many appearances in his work, so it's not surprising that their deaths would inspire another memoir. ''I am not, resolutely, used to it,'' Doty writes. ''Too easy an acceptance seems, frankly, sentimental, an erasure of the particular irreplaceable stuff of individuality with a vague, generalized truth.'' And so begins his resurrection of that particular stuff: not only of Beau's ''beautiful rump'' or the corn-muffin smell of Arden's ears, but of his own will to live without them. ''My two speechless friends,'' he writes. ''They were the secret heroes of my own vitality.''</p>
        <p>Doty's elegiac tendency is aided by his dazzling, tactile grasp of the world. He's often wonderful when illuminating some visual detail -- like an old house in Provincetown that has been souped up with ''chocolatey-plum varnish'' so ''the whole thing gleams like a vaguely dangerous piece of pastry.'' His descriptions of Beau and Arden frolicking around the Cape, Greenwich Village or the various locations of Doty's teaching appointments can be both arresting and touching. About Beau he writes: ''When he swims in the Great Salt Lake, water so thick with salinity it's weirdly buoying, he rides up high on the small waves, his mouth closed, his dignified head sailing above the surface.'' Sometimes, though, this rapture turns into a swoon. Being given a tomato-juice bath after being sprayed by a skunk, ''Arden is positively symphonic with scent, like that fantasy creation of the decadent symbolist des Esseintes, in Huysman's 19th-century novel, the perfume organ.''</p>
        <p>This book aspires to the seriousness of books like Elizabeth Marshall Thomas's splendid ''Hidden Life of Dogs,'' which sought to uncover canine thought processes and emotions. ''Dog Years'' is packed with reverent meditations on a dog's capacity for nobility, sensitivity and grief; academic postulations on how dogs wake us from the ''enabling exile of symbol-making'' back to our primitive selves; and discussions of dog food, dog acupuncture and dog kennels, all of which receive the kind of anxious care parenting magazines reserve for the cognitive evaluation of infants. But Doty's scholarly meanderings do little to disguise the fact that he is going over old ground here, sometimes to a startling degree. There is a passage where Doty first brings Beau home to Wally that is a nearly verbatim re-enactment of the end of ''Atlantis.''</p>
        <p>Two-thirds of the way through ''Dog Years,'' Doty experiences what he calls ''the worst moment of my life'' when, suddenly overwhelmed by the many griefs he's survived, he has a suicidal urge to jump off the Staten Island Ferry and take Beau (who is sick with a serious neurological disorder) along with him. Soon Beau and Arden will both pass away. The remaining pages offer up meditations on death and despair via the Kabbala, Emily Dickinson, Judy Garland, the ''suffering Christ'' and a dream Doty had at 16 or 17 in which he was overtaken by a skeletal ferryman in a rowboat. ''When I looked into the dark sockets of those eyes, I was suddenly utterly and completely terrified,'' Doty writes, without the slightest smirk at his 16-year-old gravitas. ''There was nothing there, behind that blank, but the great open emptiness of the world.''</p>
        <p>It's no surprise, really, that a poet's memoir about his dogs would turn into a book about mortality. Nor is it surprising that events that seem quite ordinary from the outside would be felt with this degree of intensity by a poet. But with its breathless aestheticizing of dog life, its melodrama and its rehashing of old material, ''Dog Years'' often comes dangerously close to parodying Doty's best work. While one never doubts the authenticity of Doty's love for his dogs, one does doubt the wisdom of attempting to turn all of this into the stuff of high tragedy.</p>
        <p>Danielle Chapman is an editor at Poetry magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Danielle Chapman is an editor at Poetry magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
