<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MY RIGHT ARM</title>
    <meta content="603WOOD.txt" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Play" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="52" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/sports/playmagazine/0603play-wood.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851591"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Chicago Cubs</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Chicago Cubs</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wood, Kerry</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bissinger, Buzz</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Soriano, Alfonso</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Piniella, Lou</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bissinger, Buzz</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wood, Kerry</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clemens, Roger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ryan, Nolan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7D91F31F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="6846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MY RIGHT ARM</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">My Right Arm</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Buzz Bissinger</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bissinger, Buzz</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are few things in sports more full of promise than a major-league clubhouse before a game, and on this second Monday in April -- the home opener for the Chicago Cubs in the frumpish glory that is forever Wrigley Field -- the Cubs' clubhouse is brimming with a hopefulness that seems positively staggering.</p>
        <p>The Cubs have failure and calamity sewn into the organization as tightly as the red stitching on a baseball. But for the home opener a certain level of irrational exuberance is tolerated, even encouraged. Loyalists are lining up outside the portals of Wrigley at 9:30 in the morning even though game time is 3 hours and 50 minutes away and they can't get in yet. The main concourse has been scrubbed clean of its persistent beery stench -- the one that so nicely captured the essence of going 99 years without winning a World Series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Masochism may be a regular condition of Cubs fandom, but even so, no player in the recent history of the team has broken more hearts than Kerry Wood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are few things in sports more full of promise than a major-league clubhouse before a game, and on this second Monday in April -- the home opener for the Chicago Cubs in the frumpish glory that is forever Wrigley Field -- the Cubs' clubhouse is brimming with a hopefulness that seems positively staggering.</p>
        <p>The Cubs have failure and calamity sewn into the organization as tightly as the red stitching on a baseball. But for the home opener a certain level of irrational exuberance is tolerated, even encouraged. Loyalists are lining up outside the portals of Wrigley at 9:30 in the morning even though game time is 3 hours and 50 minutes away and they can't get in yet. The main concourse has been scrubbed clean of its persistent beery stench -- the one that so nicely captured the essence of going 99 years without winning a World Series.</p>
        <p>Inside the clubhouse, the Cubs have worked like mad to make the clichés of springtime rebirth into something real. The team has added new lockers, new carpeting, new players like Alfonso Soriano and Cliff Floyd and Jason Marquis and Ted Lilly and Mark DeRosa -- the products of a last-hurrah $300 million spending spree before the Tribune Company announced it would sell the club. There is also a new manager, Lou Piniella, a wise bird who has won a World Series and still smells conspiracy every time he comes near an umpire. The Cubs' blue-and-white uniform shirts, which have been set out by the staff with the circumspection of English butlers, flow from one locker to another. It is a striking tableau, and you have to look hard to find the single downbeat note -- the locker all the way at the end on the right-hand side that is largely taken up by three cardboard boxes.</p>
        <p>That locker belongs to Kerry Wood, the Cubs' 29-year-old right-handed pitcher. Masochism may be a regular condition of Cubs fandom, but even so, no player in the recent history of the team has broken more hearts than Wood. At age 20, he was a hulking, grim-faced fireballer who seemed poised to follow in the footsteps of his fellow Texans Nolan Ryan and Roger Clemens. Nine years later, Wood's career line reads like a gruesome forensics report -- torn labrum, torn rotator cuff, torn ulnar collateral ligament, every kind of arm ''soreness'' imaginable -- and nobody in the Cubs organization has any idea when, or if, he will return. ''It is tragic, in a way, to see a young man come from a small town in Texas,'' Piniella says, ''and work his way to the big leagues relatively quickly, and show that type of desire and competitiveness and skill to reach the top of your profession in a very short period,'' and then to have it end abruptly. Piniella watched the latest setback this spring when Wood, attempting yet another comeback, had to shut it down because the tendons in his shoulder suddenly felt like they were on fire.</p>
        <p>In major-league front offices, Wood has become less a real ballplayer than a cautionary tale. Sure, there is the memory of that overcast day in Chicago in 1998 when he struck out 20 batters at the age of 20, a game that some stat-heads argue is the greatest performance ever turned in by a pitcher. There is the memory of the 2003 season in which Wood seemed to have put the first wave of injuries behind him and helped lead the Cubs to within five outs of the World Series. But over the past three seasons, as he has collected $32.5 million from the Cubs while mostly sitting on the disabled list, Wood's story has come to symbolize all the nightmarish possibilities for young pitchers -- how heralded prospects fall prey to the whims of their managers, how the efforts to protect their fragile arms from injury may actually put them in danger. Wood, once the ultimate can't-miss kid, now watches the new kids with their live fastballs and their wicked sliders and thinks to himself, It's just a matter of time. If you ask him what he uses his Cubs locker for now, he will tell you, ''It's turned into storage.''</p>
        <p>As the Cubs play the Milwaukee Brewers at the end of April, Kerry Wood is in Phoenix, finishing up his rehabilitation work at Fischer Sports Physical Therapy, in a nondescript building near the airport. Wood, who has a torn rotator cuff, has been exiled to the disabled list for the 11th time in his 10-year career. His previous trips to the D.L. have been buoyed by the hope that he might re-emerge as a starter, but this time his sights have been adjusted downward: he is hoping for the bullpen at best, and it will be an accomplishment if he makes it back to a major-league ballpark at all. Wood is here to try to relearn the craft of pitching.</p>
        <p>Pennants of various professional sports franchises hang from the ceiling of the gym. The walls are adorned with more framed photos than the office of the most insecure politician, pictures of the dozens of athletes with whom Brett Fischer, a trainer, physical therapist and conditioning specialist, has worked over the years. The place has the enforced cheer of a counseling center, maybe because so many pro athletes have come here to regain some measure of a former glory that they once took for granted.</p>
        <p>Wood settles into a black leather chair in a conference room and opens a bottle of water. He is 6-foot-5, and thanks to Fischer's grueling regimen of exercise, the walruslike body he once lugged around looks positively gaunt at 210 pounds. (Wood says he has lost 35 pounds.) He has a beard that is closely trimmed. His teeth are pearly white, which surprises me, maybe because he is from Texas and I have met few athletes from Texas over the age of 12 who do not dip tobacco and carry around a little Styrofoam spit cup like an appendage. Wood is seeing me because Jim Hendry, the Cubs' general manager, interceded on my behalf; he is looking at the floor, an athlete's telltale signal that he is only talking to you because somebody said he should.</p>
        <p>As it turns out, Wood is accessible and expansive; the onslaught of injuries has taught him to regard his condition with a certain deadpan honesty. ''I've been through this before,'' Wood says. ''I've been getting ready to break camp and break for the season, not a worry in the world about whether my shoulder was going to last or not, and then all of a sudden the next day I can't put my seatbelt on.'' If there was any happy news about his latest injury, it was that Wood does not require surgery (he has had three procedures since entering the majors) -- only the grind of more rehab in Phoenix to reduce severe tendinitis, which afflicts him because those muscles he has developed are simply unused to the act of throwing. But the bland happy-talk you get from so many athletes is gone, too, and it is Wood who raises the inevitable question: ''What keeps this from happening again?''</p>
        <p>Anyone who followed baseball in the 1990s remembers Wood's swagger. No pitcher in major-league history reached 1,000 strikeouts more quickly, either in games or innings pitched. He would go way inside to let the batter know who was in control, a tactic that had the benefit of expanding the outside of the plate into a thick wedge of porterhouse. He had a fastball once clocked at 102 miles per hour and a devastatingly hard curve/slurve that tumbled a foot in its journey to home plate; Astros first baseman Jeff Bagwell once said of the pitch, ''I got no chance.'' When in a foul mood, Wood occasionally let a ball drift near a batter's head at 96 or 97 m.p.h., a gesture that, in the euphemistic words of Cubs catcher Michael Barrett, made you feel ''uncomfortable.'' That was the healthy, cocksure Kerry Wood. Now he is a man in gym shorts fiddling with a bottle of water 1,800 miles from Wrigley Field.</p>
        <p>He considered quitting after the disappointment of spring training. But he says he decided otherwise in large part because of his 17-month-old son Justin, and the slight chance that his career will last long enough for Justin to get a taste of the big-league atmosphere. ''I want him to be around it,'' Wood says. ''I want him to be able to come into the clubhouse. I want to take him into the stadium and hit fly balls to him. I want him to be able to do that. I'm not going to be able to do that if I don't at least give it a shot.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, Wood is grappling with the question facing every athlete: If he quits now, will he always wonder whether he gave it his best shot? ''I don't want to look back on my career and say, 'You know what, I gave up when I was 29 or 30 years old.' . . . I'm not going to have hindsight when I'm done with this game. I've seen too many ex-players [who] can't do it when they're done, can't be away from the game.''</p>
        <p>Piniella says he has not given up on Wood, but considering Wood's fragile health, it is hard to know how much the Cubs really even want him. When he was healthy, Wood was universally heralded by Cubs beat writers as a great source for quotes, and by the other players as a fiercely loyal teammate. (Perhaps most endearing is that Wood remains the prime suspect in the unsolved mystery of Who Destroyed Sammy Sosa's Boom Box With a Bat, after Sosa walked out of the last game of the 2004 season.) But having him puttering around the clubhouse useless and discouraged was a drag on the Cubs' already-delicate team chemistry. ''Nothing is like a clubhouse when you're active,'' Wood says, adding that ''there's no worse place to be'' when you are not.</p>
        <p>Fischer has Wood exercising three to four hours every day. Today's workout consists largely of what Fischer describes as ''functional training,'' exercises that recreate what Wood does on the pitcher's mound with his hips and legs and shoulders, but with more flexibility and athleticism. He puts Wood through a series of balance exercises, to reduce his tendency to ''fly open'' -- that is, to rotate his front shoulder outward too early -- during his delivery. He puts him through a series of leg lunges to help develop lower-body strength (a key element of what made workhorses like Ryan and Clemens so durable). There are also exercises to strengthen the hamstrings, which will help reduce the stress on Wood's shoulder when his arm decelerates after he throws. Wood does upper-body weightlifting three days a week, but the goal is to build endurance and strength without turning into a professional bodybuilder. Too many pitchers are overmuscled in the chest, Fischer believes. He has seen Greg Maddux and Randy Johnson without their shirts on, and he tells me that while their physiques are not exactly inspirational, their durability is.</p>
        <p>Fischer says Wood has a tremendous work ethic and believes the final chapter of his career has yet to be written. Wood's shoulder is pain-free now, and Fischer hopes that he might be back in a Cubs uniform by July.</p>
        <p>''I feel like I've got many years left,'' Wood says, and I think he believes it. But a few moments later, his head is down again and his fingers are playing with the bottle of water. He is aware that any pitcher's arm -- and especially his arm -- basically hangs by a thread.</p>
        <p>''Maybe I'm lying to myself,'' he says.</p>
        <p>PITCHING A BASEBALL is, to put it mildly, a torturous and self-destructive act. Pitching is the fastest known motion in human biomechanics, the shoulder rotating at the rate of 7,200 degrees per second at its maximum, or the equivalent of 20 full revolutions per second. At the time of the ball's release, the forces acting on the shoulder are basically equivalent to the pitcher's body weight; they are akin to someone of similar size trying to yank his arm out of his shoulder socket. Right before release, the pitcher's elbow straightens at a rate of 2,000 degrees per second, or the equivalent of 5.5 full revolutions per second. As Glenn Fleisig, the research director of the American Sports Medicine Institute, told me, the elbow was never designed for that type of stress. In Wood's case, the risk of injury was only exacerbated by the way in which he learned to throw. He tended to throw across his body, which meant that he was relying almost exclusively on his arm instead of using his legs as a source of energy.</p>
        <p>Wood's injuries may be more extreme than those of the average pitcher, but he is a symptom of a larger problem. For all the attention paid to the care and feeding of young pitchers these days, there are no indications that the number of injuries has been significantly reduced. As reported by the American Journal of Sports Medicine, 49 percent of the 349 players who spent time on the disabled list in 1998 were pitchers. According to Rick Wilton's Baseball Injury Report (probably the most comprehensive compendium of major-league baseball injuries publicly available), there were about the same number of players on the D.L. in 2006 -- 347 -- but the number of those who were pitchers had risen to 69 percent. To get an even better idea of how much time pitchers lose to injury, consider that 244 of the pitchers who played in the majors in 2006 have been on the disabled list at least once in the past five years. Their injury time adds up to 27,351 days, the equivalent of 149 lost seasons.</p>
        <p>Although the act of pitching a baseball repeatedly is exceedingly stressful, doctors now generally accept that it is not the act itself that causes injury nearly so much as pitching while fatigued. A study by the American Sports Medicine Institute shows that pitchers between the ages of 16 and 20 who often throw with arm fatigue are 36 times more likely to be seriously injured than those who do not. In 20 years of research for the institute, Fleisig calls the fatigue factor ''the single strongest statistical finding'' he has ever encountered. Fatigue can cause a pitcher to overthrow and to alter his mechanics to compensate for the loss in power. This is why recovering from injuries is so precarious, because a pitcher often tries to find an arm slot in his delivery that doesn't hurt, which in turn leads to using joints and muscles in new and unfamiliar ways. And it's why pitching while hurt, which Wood has been doing throughout his career, may be the most devastating thing you can do.</p>
        <p>The tried-and-true method of preventing young pitchers from throwing when they are fatigued has been to keep them on strict pitch counts in the minor leagues -- 100 pitches per game has become something of an industry standard. But there is an intriguing school of thought emerging that holds that one of the problems with today's young pitchers is that they do not throw enough in the minors before getting called up. As the thinking goes, pitch counts prevent young pitchers from learning to pitch while tired, to pace themselves during a game, to get out of jams without simply handing the ball to the bullpen. ''We condition [young pitchers] to develop pitches,'' says Nolan Ryan, a Hall of Famer who owns two of the Houston Astros' minor-league clubs. ''We condition them to pitch a certain number of innings. I don't know if we do a real good job of conditioning them to compete. Let them have a long inning and get out of it.'' Ryan says that when he pitched, he never wanted to put the game in anyone else's hands. ''When you talk about that, they look at you like you're from another planet.''</p>
        <p>Ferguson Jenkins, a Cubs Hall of Fame pitcher who spent only one month on the disabled list in his 19-year career, adds that young pitchers are too coddled. ''They don't let them pitch enough in the minors [so that] they know how to counteract all the different pressures they have in the major leagues.''</p>
        <p>Ryan and Jenkins's theory is supported by the experiences of still-active pitchers who started professionally in their late teens. The San Diego Padres' Greg Maddux threw for 491 1/3 innings before his first full season in the majors at 21. He has thrown for 200 innings or more in 18 seasons and possesses perhaps the single most impressive statistic in baseball history: he has been on the disabled list only once in his 22-year career. The New York Mets' Tom Glavine, also drafted out of high school, threw for 536 2 / 3 innings before his first full big-league season at 22, and is now in his 21st season. He has thrown 200 innings or more in 13 of them.</p>
        <p>Maddux and Glavine are command-and-location pitchers, but such heralded fireballers as Randy Johnson and Curt Schilling also spent appreciable time in the minors learning their craft. Johnson pitched 418 1/3 innings before his first lengthy season in the majors when he was 25. Schilling pitched 701 2 / 3 innings before his first sustained call-up at 23. Together they have lasted 38 seasons. Daisuke Matsuzaka, the Boston Red Sox import from Japan, threw 588 innings before he was 21, following the Japanese custom of pitching lots of early-career innings.</p>
        <p>These apprenticeships reinforced a crucial aspect of a pitcher's mechanics, which is delivering the ball the same way every time. Significant minor-league experience also teaches young pitchers that what they are trying to perfect is a complex tango of command and location and changing speeds, not some personal duel with the radar gun. ''One of the things you learn over time is the art and value of pitching over throwing,'' says St. Louis Cardinals Manager Tony La Russa. It means throwing a fastball on a 2-and-1 count with a little less velocity to disrupt a hitter's timing, since he is expecting high heat. It means throwing well-located pitches early in the game, which can earn some quick outs and save the arm from wear and tear. ''These are lessons [you learn] with experience and the only place where you can learn that is the minor leagues,'' La Russa says. Instead, he believes, too many young pitchers, particularly those who have attracted media attention, come up to the majors too soon and feel an obligation to go full bore all the time. They are constantly reaching back for extra velocity, and if they are doing it as fatigue begins to set in, the possibility of their arms breaking down only multiplies.</p>
        <p>The rule of thumb is that a pitcher should get some 400 innings of work in the minors before being called up. But with today's baseball economics, La Russa knows that has become an untenable luxury. Even the New York Yankees, who regularly chase pricey free agents, rushed 20-year-old prospect Philip Hughes to the majors this season -- after vowing not to -- when their rotation was decimated by injuries. In his second start, Hughes was carrying a no-hitter into the seventh inning when his hamstring went out. He was immediately put on the disabled list. Mike Pelfrey of the Mets came out of spring training as the team's fifth starter at the age of 23, with all of 96 1/3 innings of minor-league work under his belt. His low number of innings in the minors was offset to some degree by the innings he pitched in college at Wichita State, but regardless, he did not appear ready for the major leagues; after going 0-5 through mid-May, the Mets sent him back to the minors. The wunderkind Felix Hernandez of the Seattle Mariners, who wound up in the majors in 2005 when he was just 19, pitched a stunning one-hitter against the Red Sox this April, but shortly after was placed on the disabled list with a strained ligament in his elbow -- an injury that is particularly troubling because it can be a precursor to a torn ligament. Francisco Liriano, in his first full season with the Minnesota Twins in 2006, went 12 and 3 and seemed destined for greatness, but he will miss the entire 2007 season after undergoing ligament replacement surgery -- the so-called Tommy John procedure -- on his elbow last November. ''The economic push is to bring kids up, and it's unfortunate,'' La Russa says.</p>
        <p>Perhaps no case illustrates this better than that of Mark Prior, a dazzling young pitcher from the University of Southern California whom the Cubs chose with the No. 2 pick in the 2001 draft. The Cubs' hope was that Prior would eventually give them another top-of-the-rotation ace alongside Wood. Prior threw for 138 innings at U.S.C. in 2001 but only 51 minor-league innings before being called up in 2002 at the age of 21. He finished 18-6 in 2003, but has since suffered from a series of mysterious ailments, many in his shoulder. He has been on the disabled list nine times; in April, Prior had surgery on his shoulder and is out for the rest of the season.</p>
        <p>Wood, who threw 281 1/3 innings in the minors, was kept on a strict pitch count every game, and he believes it was more hindrance than help. In the minors, 100 pitches can get you into the eighth inning or even the ninth because of the lesser talent of the competition. In the majors, the hitters are far better at working the counts and fouling off pitches with two strikes against them, and Wood discovered that 100 pitches might not even get you into the middle of the fifth. He believes that young pitchers tend to break down at the end of the season ''because they can't handle the load'' and have never been sufficiently pushed in the minors to learn to handle it.</p>
        <p>Wood also discovered something else upon his transition to the majors: no matter what a pitcher has been told about proper mechanics, no matter how many times he has been told not to reach beyond his ability, he is going to resort to whatever it takes when he's in a jam. ''You're in the big leagues,'' he told me. ''You're on the mound, which by the way is a very lonely place with the bases loaded; you'll come up with anything. You will come out of your norm to try to do anything to get out of that.''</p>
        <p>As a lower-middle-class kid growing up in Irving, Tex., just outside of Dallas, with a father who worked for a check-printing company and a mother who was an insurance underwriter, Wood did what a lot of Texas kids do. He found an outlet in sports. He tried football for a while, but as a 5-foot-3-inch junior-high quarterback he couldn't see over the offensive line. So he stuck with baseball. He started at shortstop as a freshman at MacArthur High School, having grown to 5-foot-9. In between his freshman and sophomore years he shot up another six inches, and he began to consider his future as a pitcher. Unlike Mark Prior, who was groomed to be a pitcher in his youth and was tutored by the professional pitching coach Tom House, Wood was initially taught only by his father. He later began to imitate his idol Nolan Ryan, but there was not much technique to it -- just ''step back, lift your leg up and throw to the plate,'' he says. Still, if Wood lacked proper mechanics, he made up for it with sheer talent. For his senior year, when it became clear that he would be drafted by a major-league team, he transferred to Grand Prairie High School, for the sole reason that its coach was Mike McGilvray, who ran his program with the discipline of a major-league organization.</p>
        <p>McGilvray is hardly a household name in baseball, but among Cubs fans he is spoken of in the same wrathful tones as those used for Billy Sianis's goat or Steve Bartman. From the Cubs' perspective, Wood was set on the path to being a permanent fixture on the disabled list when McGilvray misused him in a high-school doubleheader.</p>
        <p>Wood was a sensation in his senior year at Grand Prairie, going 14-0 with an e.r.a. of 0.84. On June 1, 1995, the Cubs made Wood the fourth pick overall in baseball's amateur draft. But for the moment, Wood was still a high-school pitcher under the tutelage of McGilvray. Two days after the draft, with Grand Prairie needing to sweep a doubleheader to get into the state tournament, McGilvray had Wood throw 146 pitches in the first game, then come back to start the second and throw 29 more pitches, for a mind-blowing total of 175 in a single day. Wood was the winning pitcher in both games, and actually won the second one with his bat when he hit a grand slam.</p>
        <p>Ed Lynch, the general manager of the Cubs at the time, reportedly threw the phone across the room when he heard about the doubleheader. McGilvray told me he was fully aware of Wood's major-league potential and went out of his way to pamper him during the regular season. (The number of pitches Wood threw in a game usually ranged from 90 to 110.) ''Yes, I know it's a high pitch count,'' says McGilvray of the infamous doubleheader, but he says he talked to Wood and his father before making the decision and that it was the only time he extended him like that. Besides, McGilvray explains, ''He did it effortlessly.'' And despite the Cubs' objections, McGilvray correctly points out that it was not until four years later, when he was in the Cubs organization, that Wood began having significant arm problems. He says he thought the Cubs were being hypocritical and misleading by trying to blame him for Wood's problems.</p>
        <p>Wood's first manager in the majors, in 1998, was Jim Riggleman. He, too, had things on his mind other than Wood's health -- he had a record of 217-251 with the Cubs and had yet to make the playoffs. But Riggleman, who is now the field coordinator for player development for the Cardinals, is the only manager willing to admit that he might have had something do with Wood's injuries.</p>
        <p>Though Wood had rocketed through the Cubs' organization, Riggleman says, he wanted to keep him in Class AAA for more seasoning. But 1998 was shaping up as a magical year for the downtrodden Cubs -- after two straight losing seasons, they had a playoff-worthy lineup led by Sammy Sosa, who would hit 66 home runs that season in a duel with Mark McGwire that would focus almost-daily attention on the team. Influential Cubs players were clamoring for Wood. So when a spot opened up in the rotation in April because of injury, the Cubs brought him up. Wood believed he was ready to handle the workload, but he now says he was carrying too much weight and had paid too little attention to his mechanics to prevent injury. But he was 20; and when you're 20, with a tremendous fastball and an even better curve, you don't think twice about heading off to the majors. As Wood told teammate Mark Grace one day, ''I'm gonna win 15 games and strike out the world.''</p>
        <p>He pitched passably in his first four starts. Then came the fifth, a day game against the Astros for which Wrigley Field was less than half full. Few argue with the assertion that it was the most dominating game ever pitched at Wrigley. Some say that it may have been the most dominating pitching performance in the history of baseball. The only Astros hit was an infield grounder by Ricky Gutierrez that bounced off the glove of Cubs third baseman Kevin Orie. Wood's fastball reached 100 m.p.h., but it was not the fastball that had the Astros shaking their heads: it was the curve, which broke sharply downward thanks to the tremendous torque Wood's arm supplied. The Cubs won, 2-0, and Wood's line read like this:</p>
        <p>IP H R ER BB SO HR BF Pit-Str</p>
        <p>9 1 0 0 0 20 0 29 122-84</p>
        <p>Wood, still virtually unknown to the casual fan, had just equaled Roger Clemens's single-game record for strikeouts. All of a sudden, he found himself mentioned alongside the heady company of hard-throwers like Clemens, Sandy Koufax, Juan Marichal and Bob Gibson. ''The expectations were ridiculous for someone at 20,'' Wood says. ''I had pitched five games. I had, like, 17 innings. It's tough when you punch out 20 guys in your fifth start and then everybody expects you to do that from here on out.''</p>
        <p>Riggleman says he actually contemplated lifting Wood from the game as his pitch count climbed beyond 100 pitches, but adds, ''If I had taken Kerry out of the game, they would have had to have security take me out of the ballgame.''</p>
        <p>Wood went 13-6 and struck out 233 batters that season and earned National League Rookie of the Year honors. But in August his elbow began to ache. The club shut him down for the rest of the regular season, then brought him back in the first round of the playoffs with the Cubs down two games to none to the Atlanta Braves. Wood threw five solid innings, but he now wonders why Riggleman even bothered bringing him back. ''What's the point? . . . We're down 2-0,'' he told me. The Cubs were swept anyway.</p>
        <p>In his very first start in spring training the next season, Wood tore the ulnar collateral ligament in his elbow on a warm-up pitch before the second inning. It would require reconstructive surgery and make him the first pitcher since World War II to win 12 or more games as a rookie and then miss the entire next season. ''I think the wear and tear he put on his arm the previous year had something to do with what happened to his elbow,'' Riggleman says. But for a manager whose job was on the line (he was fired the following season, after the Cubs finished 67-95), using a high-strikeout pitcher who could work deep into the game was an essential form of self-preservation.</p>
        <p>''I have some reservations,'' Riggleman says now. ''I wish I would have done some things differently. I'm sure I was caught up in trying to get to the playoffs.'' In hindsight, he says, he would have taken Wood out of some games earlier than he did because of his pitch count, which topped 120 pitches or more eight times in 1998, including a high of 133 in a game at the end of August. Riggleman says he sighed with relief whenever Wood left a game, and eventually he told Wood to stop throwing the hard curve/slurve -- a combination of curveball and slider -- he had used against the Astros because of the damage it might do to his arm. (Wood ultimately abandoned the pitch.)</p>
        <p>Riggleman also notes that the Cubs' medical reports showed that Wood's ligament was thin to begin with, making it likely to blow at some point anyway. Then there was the issue of his mechanics. Throwing across your body as a pitcher is good in terms of creating deception, because the ball is harder for the batters to pick up, but it puts terrible stress on the elbow and shoulder. Wood himself does not remember any Cubs coaches telling him to alter his mechanics, and even if they did, he says he probably would have ignored them. ''Who's gonna say anything to you?'' he says. ''Who is gonna say, 'Oh, you're throwing twelve inches across your body.' No one's gonna tell you that, because you're having success and you're not gonna listen anyway. . . . You don't think about that stuff. You're young.''</p>
        <p>Kerry wood began the 2000 season on the disabled list, still recovering from surgery, and didn't pitch his first major-league game until the beginning of May. In the summer, he went back on the D.L. for 22 days because of a strain in his left oblique muscle. He pitched only 137 innings all season. But the next three years were largely pain-free. His run of good health culminated in a wonderful 2003 season, the best of Wood's career, in which he won 14 games and led the majors with 266 strikeouts. In September, as the Cubs advanced toward a Central Division title under their new manager, Dusty Baker, Wood was 3-1 with an e.r.a. of 1.00. (He also won two games in the playoffs.) His pitch counts were high, an average of 111 per start, second in the majors only to the Cubs' new phenom, the equally overworked Mark Prior.</p>
        <p>Like Riggleman before him, Baker has come under withering criticism for using both Wood and Prior so much that he risked destroying their careers. He protests when I bring it up with him. ''What is overuse?'' he says. ''There didn't used to be such a word but now it's widely used. . . . You got to blame somebody, and I got blamed for everything.''</p>
        <p>Baker says that when he came to the Cubs in 2003, he saw photographs of Wood's mechanics and expressed concern about further injury to members of the organization. But nothing happened, hesays.</p>
        <p>Baker had been given a $15 million contract, with expectations that he would lead the Cubs to the playoffs. Wood and Prior were his two best weapons, and sometimes, Baker tells me, ''You got to overextend if you're going to try to win it.'' There was another factor: it often wasn't until the fifth inning, when Wood was nearing 100 pitches, that he seemed to find his rhythm. Baker's bullpen was not very good, so he kept Wood in the game no matter what the pitch count. ''You manage the team that you have,'' Baker says. ''You stay with your starters longer.'' (Baker was fired after the 2006 season.)</p>
        <p>As usual, Wood blames himself and exonerates Baker. He says he was out of shape and that it took a toll toward the end of the season. ''You just get tired,'' he says. ''You start jumping. You start lunging. You're taking every bit of energy from your toes to your head to get the ball to the plate. And you get out of whack. You start winging it -- or I did, anyway. You can't deliver the ball to the plate the same way if you aren't in shape.''</p>
        <p>Kerry Wood was 26 years old after the 2003 season, and he had the look of a starter coming into his prime. That meant money, loads of it -- and the Cubs, who had constructed a World Series-ready rotation of Wood, Prior, Carlos Zambrano and Greg Maddux, ponied up a three-year, $32.5 million contract. And yet the specter of the previous injuries haunted Wood. Way back in 1998, writing in ''Sports Illustrated,'' Keith Olbermann had cautioned that ''so many strikeouts at such a tender age have usually doomed a pitcher,'' and said of Wood: ''Sell his baseball cards. Now.''</p>
        <p>Steve Stone, a former Cy Young Award winner who was then the Cubs' color analyst on WGN-TV, felt that Wood's faulty mechanics would lead to further disaster. Stone says he had a private conversation with team president Andy MacPhail in 2000 in which he predicted the following: ''He's going to have at least one or possibly two more surgeries. They will be in the shoulder. The elbow will probably hold up. He's going to break your heart on almost a yearly basis. He will never win as many games as you think he should, and he will consistently break down to the point where you will give him an extraordinary amount of money for very few active days.'' (MacPhail does not recall the conversation with Stone.)</p>
        <p>Stone was off by a few seasons, but his prediction proved accurate. The 2004 season marked the beginning of Wood's tenure as a permanent fixture on the disabled list. He would work only 140 1/3 innings in 2004, spending two months on the D.L. with a strained triceps. In 2005, he sat out roughly three months because of shoulder problems and underwent arthroscopic surgery in which his labrum -- a thin piece of tissue that goes around the rim of the socket, which had partially detached -- was reattached. Labrum surgery is considered highly risky for a pitcher who wants to come back, but Wood, after having spent much of the month of August working out of the bullpen for the first time in his life, elected to have it. He still wanted to be a starter but could not throw more than 55 pitches without his shoulder giving out on him. In hindsight, it seems clear that Wood was trying to be the kind of pitcher he could no longer be.</p>
        <p>When he returned in 2006, his shoulder still did not feel right. At first, he just thought it was scar tissue from the surgery, and he tried to find a pitching angle for his arm that didn't hurt. But he felt pain on every pitch he threw and pain in between every pitch he threw. His velocity fell into the high 80s. He might actually feel decent until the third or fourth inning, but then would fight to get to the sixth or seventh. When he went to the bench between innings in one game, he could not pick up a water bottle. After another, he couldn't lift his arm to apply hair gel. ''I wasn't going out to pitch to win,'' he says. ''I was just trying to save the bullpen for the other guys.'' He started four games in 2006 before landing on the disabled list on June 7th, with what was ultimately discovered to be a torn rotator cuff that had apparently not been diagnosed at the time of the labrum surgery. And that was the last time he pitched during the regular season.</p>
        <p>Is there someone to blame for what happened to Kerry Wood? As in ''Murder on the Orient Express,'' everybody took a turn with the dagger. A high-school kid never should have thrown 175 pitches in a single day. Jim Riggleman never should have let him exceed 120 pitches eight times as a rookie, or brought him back for that one game in the 2003 playoffs. Dusty Baker, who allowed Wood to exceed 100 pitches 24 times in 2003, should have taken greater note of his injury history. Wood should have kept himself in better shape and paid more attention to his mechanics. But whether we like it or not, professional athletes are meant to be sacrificed, not preserved. And the most fatal dagger-thrust of all has been fate's. Wood threw the way he did because that was the way he had learned how to pitch. And he continued to throw that way because for a brief moment it made him the most exciting pitcher in baseball.</p>
        <p>In return for the Cubs' investment in him (his $32.5 million contract for the last three seasons works out to $691,489 per game), Wood has given the team his loyalty. Instead of testing the free-agent market, where he likely could have gotten a one-year contract of $5 million, he re-signed with the Cubs for $1.75 million. His career, if it ends here, will add up to a mishmash of memories. He carries with him the 20-strikeout game against the Astros -- not just the accomplishment but also the sheer fun of it, like a game of ''burnout'' with his brother in his backyard in Irving, when the goal was to snap the ball off as hard as you could. He carries with him the July day in 2003 when the Cubs were playing the Marlins in Florida, and it was sweltering on the field, and before the game he wasn't sure he would survive five innings; but he became so locked-in that he couldn't even hear the crowd noise, and everything seemed easy and perfect, and before he knew it he was into the ninth on the way to a two-hit win in which he threw 130 pitches. But most of all, perhaps, he carries the advice he received from his first pitching coach in professional baseball, Oscar Acosta, who died this April at the age of 49 in a traffic accident in the Dominican Republic.</p>
        <p>''The game doesn't build character; it reveals it,'' Acosta told him, and as Kerry Wood moves from being the 20-year-old pitcher with the live fastball to the 29-year-old with an arm that may have finally surrendered -- or maybe, maybe, still has some few ounces of beauty left in it -- he thinks, more than ever before, about what Oscar Acosta said.</p>
        <p>Buzz Bissinger is the author of the sports books ''Friday Night Lights'' and ''Three Nights in August,'' and a contributing editor at Vanity Fair. He lives in Philadelphia.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Buzz Bissinger is the author of the sports books ''Friday Night Lights'' and ''Three Nights in August,'' and a contributing editor at Vanity Fair. He lives in Philadelphia.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
