<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crash-Test Kudos for 2 Convertibles</title>
    <meta content="03CRASH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/automobiles/03CRASH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851821"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Motoring</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Insurance Institute for Highway Safety</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Bayerische Motorenwerke AG</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Audi Division of Volkswagen AG</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E1DB1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="418" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crash-Test Kudos for 2 Convertibles</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Crash-Test Kudos for 2 Convertibles</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHERYL JENSEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the first crash tests of convertibles by the Insurance Institute for Highway Safety, the Saab 9-3 and Volvo C70 earned the top rating, good, for protection in front, side and rear collisions.</p>
        <p>Each was named a Top Safety Pick, a designation that requires ratings of good in all three crash tests as well as an electronic stability control system and roll bars. Stability control helps to prevent skids; roll bars are designed to maintain room above the occupants' heads in a rollover.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the first crash tests of convertibles by the Insurance Institute for Highway Safety, the Saab 9-3 and Volvo C70 earned the top rating.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the first crash tests of convertibles by the Insurance Institute for Highway Safety, the Saab 9-3 and Volvo C70 earned the top rating, good, for protection in front, side and rear collisions.</p>
        <p>Each was named a Top Safety Pick, a designation that requires ratings of good in all three crash tests as well as an electronic stability control system and roll bars. Stability control helps to prevent skids; roll bars are designed to maintain room above the occupants' heads in a rollover.</p>
        <p>Seven other 2007 models -- the Audi A4 Cabriolet, BMW 3 Series, Ford Mustang, Mitsubishi Eclipse, Pontiac G6, Toyota Camry Solara and Volkswagen Eos -- were tested along with a 2008 Chrysler Sebring.</p>
        <p>The tests were done with the convertible tops open. The institute said that many of the cars fared well despite the lack of a roof, which can be important in maintaining the vehicle's structural rigidity. The Saab 9-3 convertible, for example, earned the same good ratings as the 9-3 sedan.</p>
        <p>The institute, which is financed by the insurance industry, issues ratings of good, acceptable, marginal and poor. Five models earned the highest rating of good for front and side crash protection. Three (BMW, Audi and Pontiac) received marginal ratings for side-impact protection in a test that represents what happens when a vehicle is struck by a pickup or sport utility. And half of the 10 convertibles tested received poor ratings for rear crash protection.</p>
        <p>The BMW received a rating of good for front crash protection, marginal for the side and poor for the rear. It has standard side air bags designed to protect the heads and torso of the front-seat occupants. Still, instruments attached to the driver dummy indicated that rib fractures and internal organ injuries could occur in a real-world crash in which a 3 Series was hit by a pickup truck or S.U.V. at 31 m.p.h.</p>
        <p>''It's something about the design of their air bag; it doesn't do a good job of protecting the chest and abdomen of the driver,'' said Adrian Lund, president of the institute.</p>
        <p>The Pontiac G6, which was tested with the optional front-seat-mounted torso air bags, fared the worst with ratings of acceptable for front, and marginal for side and rear protection. In addition, because the driver's seat in the G6 came loose and moved forward 4 inches on the left side, the dummy's head slid around the air bag and hit the instrument panel.</p>
        <p>Details of individual vehicles tests are available at iihs.org.</p>
        <p>CHERYL JENSEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
