<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>STREETSCAPES/East 73rd Street; On a Block of Stables, An Unexpected Restoration</title>
    <meta content="03scap" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/realestate/03scap.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851809"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Streetscapes | East 73rd Street"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Streetscapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Upper East Side (NYC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E7DB1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>STREETSCAPES/East 73rd Street; On a Block of Stables, An Unexpected Restoration</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On a Block of Stables, an Unexpected Restoration</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER GRAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Marquand stable, on East 73rd Street, was long thought to be irrevocably entombed in stucco, applied after the rich brick surface had been brutally roughened. But now a new owners are going to extraordinary lengths to restore the facade, which will revivify an unusual work by Richard Morris Hunt.</p>
        <p>The reason that parts of streets like East 69th, 73rd, 77th and 83rd were so thoroughly dominated by stable construction is not fully understood, but it started on the block of 73rd from Lexington to Third Avenues in the early 1880s.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Long thought to be irrevocably entombed in stucco, new owners are going to extraordinary lengths to restore the Marquand stable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Marquand stable, on East 73rd Street, was long thought to be irrevocably entombed in stucco, applied after the rich brick surface had been brutally roughened. But now a new owners are going to extraordinary lengths to restore the facade, which will revivify an unusual work by Richard Morris Hunt.</p>
        <p>The reason that parts of streets like East 69th, 73rd, 77th and 83rd were so thoroughly dominated by stable construction is not fully understood, but it started on the block of 73rd from Lexington to Third Avenues in the early 1880s.</p>
        <p>In 1883, Henry Gurdon Marquand, a banker, railroad executive and art collector, began his private stable at 166 East 73rd and finished it the following year. More such construction followed in the 1890s and the early 1900s -- like the wonderfully outlandish Flemish-style stable at 168 East 73rd designed in 1899 by Charles Romeyn. This block of 73rd Street became one of the most populated stable streets in New York.</p>
        <p>Marquand and Hunt were good friends and had been among the founders of the Metropolitan Museum of Art in 1870. Hunt was the first American architect to study at the École des Beaux-Arts; he designed the Marquand stable just as he was finishing the magnificent Marquand mansion (demolished in the 1910s) at the northwest corner of 68th and Madison. He also designed the family's house in Newport, R.I., and the family tomb there.</p>
        <p>The stable was elegantly severe, too simple even to be called Romanesque. It had just a few windows and arched openings, dark and brooding behind a screen of brick the color of rare roast beef.</p>
        <p>According to the original plans for the $25,000 stable, the front part of the main level had a washing area and spaces for three carriages; the middle area had three double and six single horse stalls; and the rear yard had a small court and a 5-by-10-foot manure pit. At the back of the second floor was a hayloft, with staff apartments in the front and on the third floor.</p>
        <p>The manure pit was right next to the chancel of St. James' Episcopal Church, on the north side of 72nd Street. Coincidentally (or not), the year the stable was built, the church moved to its present building at Madison Avenue and 71st Street.</p>
        <p>In 1890 Marquand became the president of the Metropolitan Museum, soon arranging for Hunt to design its Fifth Avenue frontage. The present central section is his, but he died in 1895, and others completed the museum along complementary lines.</p>
        <p>The earliest census returns for the Marquand stable are from 1900 and list the Irish-born coachman Owen Donahoe, 70; his wife, Anna; and their three children. Their 28-year-old son, Thomas, was also a coachman. There were also two boarders: Richard Jones, 29, a coachman; and Alexander Ross, 21, a groom.</p>
        <p>Marquand died in 1902, and his estate sold the stable to the publisher Joseph Pulitzer, then just completing his own mansion at 11 East 73rd Street. When Pulitzer died in 1912, his $17 million estate included the stable, valued at $68,000, with two brown mares appraised at $125 and $100, a bay at $65 and a chestnut horse at $75. He owned no automobiles, but had three carriages: a landau worth $50, a victoria worth $40, and a hansom worth $10.</p>
        <p>In 1924 the MacDowell Club -- an institution supporting the MacDowell Colony, the artists' retreat in Peterborough, N.H. -- bought the old Marquand stable. By then, horses on the block had almost all been displaced by automobiles, their quarters converted to garages.</p>
        <p>At a club event five years later, the banker and opera supporter Otto Kahn told an audience that although he personally disliked talking pictures, he thought they would elevate movies to a higher plane, in part because they would permit serious stage actors to cross over to films. At the same event Martha Graham presented a series of Russian dances, the musicians and singers in Russian costume.</p>
        <p>It was apparently the MacDowell Club that put on the gloppy coat of stucco sometime before a fire swept the building in 1935 and destroyed prints by Whistler, Hassam and others. The brick was hammered to provide a rough surface and then coated with a light-color stucco, although the picturesque iron numerals, reading 1 8 8 3, survived.</p>
        <p>In 1979, the Landmarks Preservation Commission proposed 12 of the 13 stable and garage buildings on the block for designation, excluding the Marquand building. A year later Halina Rosenthal, head of the block association and later founder of the Friends of the Upper East Side Historic Districts, lobbied the commission to include the Marquand stable in the designation, which it did in 1981.</p>
        <p>The brutal treatment of the original brick and the tightly bonded stucco have made restoration seem a lost cause. But now Robert and Ellen Kapito have bought the building for conversion to a two-family residence and have embarked on a most unusual effort. After chipping off the stucco and exposing the raw, damaged brick, they are planning to have it sanded down to reveal the original deep molten red.</p>
        <p>A few patches of the exposed brick are visible through the construction barrier, including a spot at the far west end of the building that has been both stripped and sanded. The Kapitos did not respond to phone and mail messages requesting more information on their restoration, but it is rare to see a building so fully resurrected from so deep a grave.</p>
        <p>Streetscapes | East 73rd Street E-mail: streetscapes@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: streetscapes@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
