<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Décor Says Caribbean, But the Menu Says French</title>
    <meta content="03dinectCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03dinect.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851754"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/RIDGEFIELD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">La Saliere Brasserie (Ridgefield, Conn, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooks, Patricia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EEDE1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Décor Says Caribbean, But the Menu Says French</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Décor Says Caribbean, but the Menu Says French</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooks, Patricia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patricia Brooks reviews La Saliere Brasserie in Ridgefield, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN décor, La Salière, whose name in French means salt shaker, speaks more of the South Seas or the Caribbean than of a French brasserie, what with the netting, starfish and tank stocked with iridescent tropical fish.</p>
        <p>That is, until the huge menu arrives. It is decisively French, the creation of Mario Molliere, the owner and chef, with house mussels (Prince Edward Island) as the main attraction. They are offered in several different ways, either as starters or entrees -- in fennel and Pernod sauce; à la marinière (shallots, garlic, wine sauce); Basquaise (tomato and red pepper sauce); and, my preference, Grenobloises (in a lovely tarragon-accented caper sauce). They are also cooked with shallots, spices and some of La Salière's specialty beers (Uerige, Aventinus, Kölsch or Hefeweizen). As starters, they range from $8 to $11, as entrees from $18 to $24. Even the starters are bountiful enough to double as a light meal, especially with the piping hot crusty rolls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>La Salière in Ridgefield is decisively French, with house mussels as the main attraction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN décor, La Salière, whose name in French means salt shaker, speaks more of the South Seas or the Caribbean than of a French brasserie, what with the netting, starfish and tank stocked with iridescent tropical fish.</p>
        <p>That is, until the huge menu arrives. It is decisively French, the creation of Mario Molliere, the owner and chef, with house mussels (Prince Edward Island) as the main attraction. They are offered in several different ways, either as starters or entrees -- in fennel and Pernod sauce; à la marinière (shallots, garlic, wine sauce); Basquaise (tomato and red pepper sauce); and, my preference, Grenobloises (in a lovely tarragon-accented caper sauce). They are also cooked with shallots, spices and some of La Salière's specialty beers (Uerige, Aventinus, Kölsch or Hefeweizen). As starters, they range from $8 to $11, as entrees from $18 to $24. Even the starters are bountiful enough to double as a light meal, especially with the piping hot crusty rolls.</p>
        <p>A few of the many indicators of a French presence in this establishment are the Mediterranean fish soup, a combination of bay scallops, mussels, squid, fish and shrimp in a rich, tomato-tinged broth; vol au vent d'escargots au basilic (snails in puff pastry with an assertive basil-garlic sauce); and coquilles Saint-Jacques à l'estragon frais (seared sea scallops in a Champagne-tarragon-wild mushroom sauce).</p>
        <p>Tarragon, a popular herb in chef Molliere's kitchen, was also used in the tartar sauce that accompanied the crisp-edged jumbo lump crab cake and in one of three dips that came with the plateau de fruits de mer royal, a splendiferous platter of chilled seafood that included jumbo shrimp, sea scallops, mussels, squid, raw oysters and clams and a whole cooked lobster. (The platter was supposed to contain a half lobster and a half crab, but because there was no crab the night we visited, the chef generously substituted an additional half lobster.)</p>
        <p>Less spectacular entrees were seared venison steak (tender and well cooked) in a fresh cranberry sherry glaze, and organic milk-fed veal steak in a slightly oversalted wild mushroom brandy sauce. Like most entrees, these came with potato gratin, haricots verts and cauliflower.</p>
        <p>I should have stayed with seafood, La Salière's forte, but couldn't resist tagine d'agneau à la menthe et couscous -- braised lamb cooked in a mint harissa sauce. Though I am partial to harissa, a spicy North African condiment, I couldn't give it a full taste test. Even extricating several lamb cubes and carrot chunks from one of the greasiest pools of hot, dark liquid I have ever seen and cooling them in the side bowl of couscous didn't help much. The oily residue was overwhelming.</p>
        <p>Several desserts are served. The best was a fondant au chocolat, loose-textured chocolate cake in a seductive dark chocolate sauce. A serving of berry sorbet was so soupy our waiter kindly volunteered to remove it from the bill.</p>
        <p>Fanciers of mussels will enjoy this low-key French place (more a cafe than a brasserie) for a quick fix. In fact, the seafood is enough reason for a visit anytime -- that and the superior beer list.</p>
        <p>La Salière Brasserie  3 Big Shop Lane  Ridgefield  (203) 438-1976</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE A small dining room, next to a narrow, separate bar, resembles a South Seas cafe more than a brasserie, with fish netting, tropical fish tanks and starfish; shaded patio in front for outdoor dining. Ground level; wheelchair accessibility.  THE CROWD Casual attire; mostly shoppers at lunch, couples and foursomes in the evening. On many weekdays and nights, the place has only one server, making service painfully slow.  THE BAR Good, well-priced wine selection, beginning at $25 a bottle, $7 to $10 by the glass. Beer and ale list is even more impressive, if overpriced ($5.50 to $12.50), with many Belgian microbrews, rare Uerige Altbier and vintage brews like Aventinus Eisbeck.  THE BILL Lunch: $11.50 to $22.50. Dinner: appetizers, $7.50 to $13; entrees, $13.50 to $32; desserts, $7.50 to $14. All major credit cards accepted.  WHAT WE LIKE House mussels, endive salad, Mediterranean fish soup, vol au vent d'escargots au basilic, house crab cake; coquilles Saint-Jacques, seared venison steak, plateau de fruits de mer royal, sole meunière au riesling; fondant au chocolat.  IF YOU GO Lunch: Monday to Saturday, 11:30 a.m. to 4 p.m. Dinner: Monday to Thursday, 4 to 10 p.m. Friday and Saturday 4 to 11 p.m. Sunday, 4 to 9:30 p.m. Brunch: 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. Sunday. Free parking lot in front of the restaurant.  Reviewed June 3, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/RIDGEFIELD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
