<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Voice From the Slums That Refused to Be Silenced</title>
    <meta content="03colctCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03colct.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851759"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Austin, Cindy Brown</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloom, Lary</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">By the Rivers of Babylon (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E7DD1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="859" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Voice From the Slums That Refused to Be Silenced</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Voice From the Slums That Refused to Be Silenced</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lary Bloom</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bloom, Lary</byline>
      <dateline>WEST HARTFORD</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lary Bloom column on Cindy Brown Austin, 42, who once lived in public housing project in Hartford, Conn, and whose second novel, By the Rivers of Babylon, has just been published; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE guest of honor on the college campus -- the author for whom the punch and pastries were prepared and the ordinary commerce of literature would be conducted -- could have been excused if she wondered whether this book signing was fictional.</p>
        <p>Certainly, Cindy Brown Austin wished that parts of her life had been so. At 19, living a few miles from Saint Joseph College in a Hartford slum, holding her third baby girl at her breast and swatting away roaches in the dresser drawer that served as a crib, she wondered aloud, ''Oh, Lord, is there no place on earth for me?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Without credential except a high school diploma and courage, Cindy Brown Austin became a byline known to many readers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE guest of honor on the college campus -- the author for whom the punch and pastries were prepared and the ordinary commerce of literature would be conducted -- could have been excused if she wondered whether this book signing was fictional.</p>
        <p>Certainly, Cindy Brown Austin wished that parts of her life had been so. At 19, living a few miles from Saint Joseph College in a Hartford slum, holding her third baby girl at her breast and swatting away roaches in the dresser drawer that served as a crib, she wondered aloud, ''Oh, Lord, is there no place on earth for me?''</p>
        <p>Ms. Austin herself had been a child of Charter Oak Terrace, the public housing project where renegades became villains and mothers worried that their sons wouldn't live through the night. Her mother insisted on strict rules of conduct that Ms. Austin sometimes ignored.</p>
        <p>Self-esteem was an issue. A ''bastard child'' was how she referred to herself -- a daughter of strictly divided cultures. Her mother, African-American, and her father, from Jamaica, led separate lives. That Ms. Austin emerged with any hope was because of her mother's persistent love and the enduring devotion of the man she married at 17, David Austin, the father of the children -- four girls in all.</p>
        <p>In 1991, without credential except a high school diploma and courage, she sent an essay to Northeast, The Hartford Courant's Sunday magazine, which I edited at the time. It sat on the slush pile until a staff member said, ''Boss, you should read this.''</p>
        <p>''Streets of Poison'' was about growing up in terror of the surroundings, and it had enormous emotional power. Even so, there was work to be done, as there always is in such cases, so we asked Ms. Austin to meet with us. As she interpreted it at the time, we were calling her in to reject her. Still, she bought a briefcase for 50 cents at a tag sale; she couldn't walk into a newspaper office without looking like a writer.</p>
        <p>Over the next few years, the byline of Cindy Brown Austin became familiar in Connecticut and to subscribers of Reader's Digest, as she wrote what no one else was writing: an intimate portrait of a city population so often portrayed in sensational headlines that reinforced stereotype.</p>
        <p>But though she revealed the humanity in the poorest of neighborhoods, she did not escape unscathed. As with other minority writers, she suffered criticism that she was betraying her community by airing dirty laundry. Yet she persisted, even as she prepared to become an Apostolic minister, tended to her daughters' needs and, all along, held on to the dream of going to college. As a child she had visited Trinity College, thinking of it as Oz. Her own daughters, she hoped, would earn degrees. Maybe even she would -- though it seemed, because of economic circumstance, beyond the possibilities.</p>
        <p>Out of the city by then (the Austin family bought a house in Windsor), Ms. Austin plugged away on fiction meant to illuminate the society she had left behind. When her novel was done, it got an uncommon reception for a first work by a relative unknown: a fat contract from Simon &amp; Schuster. The publisher asked her to come to New York -- people there had the idea that Cindy Brown Austin might be the next Toni Morrison. She had never been to the city, and she worried that at lunch she would be so nervous she'd use the butter knife to cut her steak, and the deal would be off.</p>
        <p>Nothing like that happened, but ordinary publishing disappointment did. Her editor was fired, and the manuscript became an orphan. As years passed, people wondered if Ms. Austin had really sold anything. It was a decade later, this spring, when her second novel, ''By the Rivers of Babylon,'' was published by Strebor Books International, a Simon &amp; Schuster imprint. This is a potboiler rich in characters (including a reporter whose issues reflect some of Ms. Austin's) and with urban detail that is learned first-hand.</p>
        <p>That was the reason for the reception at Saint Joseph College -- her first reading and signing. But there were more reasons to celebrate. Two of Ms. Austin's daughters had graduated from Saint Joseph, Tahari in 2004 and Torria last year. (Tiffani is a student at the University of Hartford, and Tianna, the married daughter, is a certified child care worker.) And Ms. Austin, at 42, has completed all the course work for a bachelor's degree in English.</p>
        <p>So, on a late afternoon in May, wearing a white suit and facing an audience that included her mother, daughters, husband, sisters and old friends (including another survivor of Charter Oak Terrace), she told of her journey. She said: ''You know that I love God the way some people love money. He was on a stroll one day to the junkyard, and he saw me all broken in pieces, and saw fit to pick me up.''</p>
        <p>Yes, if we like, we can praise the Lord. But praise, too, a woman who saw her destiny, and, facing extraordinary pressures and an indifferent marketplace, could not be silenced.</p>
        <p>E-mail: conn@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: conn@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
