<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Wall Talks, but What Does It Say?</title>
    <meta content="03post" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/realestate/03post.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="POSTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Graffiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Graffiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">SoHo (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DA1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="532" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Wall Talks, but What Does It Say?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Wall Talks, but What Does It Say?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. HUGHES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MICHAEL NAMER had for years heard rumors that something beautiful was hidden behind the walls at 151 Wooster Street, a building he owns in SoHo, near Houston Street.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Namer, a principal of Alfa Development, did not undergo his eureka moment until last month, when demolition started inside the eight-story limestone building to make way for a dozen luxury condos.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, Michael Namer heard rumors of something beautiful behind the walls at 151 Wooster Street. Then a partial demolition revealed a luminous mural.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MICHAEL NAMER had for years heard rumors that something beautiful was hidden behind the walls at 151 Wooster Street, a building he owns in SoHo, near Houston Street.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Namer, a principal of Alfa Development, did not undergo his eureka moment until last month, when demolition started inside the eight-story limestone building to make way for a dozen luxury condos.</p>
        <p>Behind a bathroom's Sheetrock wall was a luminous mural of a jet, a lamp, a cake and hearts, and words in tall scrawls of graffiti.</p>
        <p>Clues to the work's date are numerous -- and despite the archaeological quality of Mr. Namer's experience, we are not talking prehistory. There are terms like ''Fab 5,'' as in Freddy, an early rapper, and more than one ''1980.'' The palette favors hot pink.</p>
        <p>Also, records show that Edit deAk, an influential art-magazine editor, lived in the eighth-floor space in the early 1980's, when the neighborhood was teeming with painters and galleries, Mr. Namer said.</p>
        <p>Gallery owners and museum directors say Ms. DeAk regularly socialized with artists whose medium was spray paint -- people like Jean-Michel Basquiat, traces of whose handle, ''Samo,'' appear on the wall, Mr. Namer said, pointing to two letters.</p>
        <p>An event organized in the building last month by the Guggenheim Museum seemed to authenticate the discovery. Diego Cortes, a Basquiat contemporary who is himself an artist, spoke persuasively on the subject, Mr. Namer said, adding that there are eventual plans to move the piece off the site.</p>
        <p>But in the meantime, the find has served as an inspiration for the new condo, whose living rooms, at 1,000 square feet, intentionally recall the lofts of SoHo's heyday, said the architect Lee Skolnick.</p>
        <p>''A piece of SoHo's artistic history is built right into our structure,'' said Mr. Skolnick, a 1970's SoHo resident who has worked for Eric Fischl, the painter, and Robert Hughes, the critic. ''It's everything we're trying to do, wrapped in a bow.''</p>
        <p>Most units, which will retain the barrel-vaulted ceilings typical of SoHo lofts, will measure 3,000 square feet. For another differentiating touch, Mr. Skolnick will forgo granite counters for limestone, which will also be used for fireplaces, he said.</p>
        <p>Unit prices in the $45 million project, which will conclude in a year, range from $3.5 million to $9.75 million; none have closed since sales began in May, Mr. Namer said.</p>
        <p>''We've stayed true to the ideal of a loft,'' he said, ''but brought it into the 21st century.''</p>
        <p>The mural seems an authentic period piece, owing to cartoonishly violent images like a falling bomb, said Marc Mayer, the director of Musée d'Art Contemporain de Montréal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mayer, who curated a Basquiat show two years ago for the Brooklyn Museum, cited further possible evidence of the artist's possible connection to the mural: ''Futura 2000,'' another name on the wall, was a friend of Basquiat's.</p>
        <p>But if turns out to have different creators, the mural still has value as a time capsule of a fertile period, in which a gathering in a downtown home could have prompted spontaneous hieroglyphics.</p>
        <p>''Graffiti artists put their mark on every surface they could,'' Mr. Mayer said, ''and they always had art supplies with them.''</p>
        <p>POSTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
