<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At a 50-Year-Old Art Center, All Things Clay</title>
    <meta content="03artsweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03artswe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851765"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ARTS AND ENTERTAINMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ceramics and Pottery</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Port Chester (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Clay Art Center (Port Chester, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hodara, Susan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ceramics and Pottery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Clay</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sculpture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ceramics and Pottery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Clay</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sculpture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E4DD1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1060" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At a 50-Year-Old Art Center, All Things Clay</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At a 50-Year-Old Art Center, All Things Clay</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN HODARA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hodara, Susan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Clay Art Center in Port Chester, NY, which is celebrating its 50th anniversary; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MIDWAY through its yearlong 50th-anniversary celebration, the Clay Art Center, housed in a two-story building at the back of a municipal parking lot in Port Chester, is setting up its next exhibition, ''At the Table: Morning, Noon and Night.'' The exhibit will feature tableware made by 50 past and present Clay Art Center members -- from full place settings to pitchers, trays, serving bowls, platters, candlesticks and even wall sculptures -- all laid out on cloth-draped tables. At the opening reception, on Friday, some of those pieces will be filled with food prepared from Potluck, the new cookbook of 250 recipes gathered from and compiled by Clay Art Center members.</p>
        <p>Reena Kashyap, a ceramic artist who has been the center's director since 1997, said the show is a great example of what the center does really well. ''We work side by side,'' she said. ''We collaborate. We share a true sense of camaraderie.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Members of the Clay Art Center in Port Chester make everything from functional pottery to whimsical sculptures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MIDWAY through its yearlong 50th-anniversary celebration, the Clay Art Center, housed in a two-story building at the back of a municipal parking lot in Port Chester, is setting up its next exhibition, ''At the Table: Morning, Noon and Night.'' The exhibit will feature tableware made by 50 past and present Clay Art Center members -- from full place settings to pitchers, trays, serving bowls, platters, candlesticks and even wall sculptures -- all laid out on cloth-draped tables. At the opening reception, on Friday, some of those pieces will be filled with food prepared from Potluck, the new cookbook of 250 recipes gathered from and compiled by Clay Art Center members.</p>
        <p>Reena Kashyap, a ceramic artist who has been the center's director since 1997, said the show is a great example of what the center does really well. ''We work side by side,'' she said. ''We collaborate. We share a true sense of camaraderie.''</p>
        <p>That spirit has sustained the Clay Art Center since it was founded in 1957 by Katherine Choy, a Hong Kong native whose dream, Ms. Kashyap said, ''was to create an environment where ceramic artists could explore their vision.'' The center provided communal kilns and materials and soon became known as a ''clay haven.'' When Ms. Choy died unexpectedly the following year, Henry Okamoto, her friend and fellow potter, took on the maintenance of the center until his death in 1988.</p>
        <p>''Henry was beloved,'' said Ms. Kashyap, 53, a resident of Rye. ''He did his best. He was more concerned about the soul of the place than collecting rent from the artists. People who were there in those days remember it as an incredible environment, even though there was often no heat during the winter.''</p>
        <p>Today, there is heat and much more. The 6,650-square-foot space, formerly a trumpet mouthpiece factory and dance studio, includes the Choy Gallery on the main floor and the smaller Henry's Project upstairs, which was formalized as an exhibition space in commemoration of the center's 50 years. Its 45 members now work in 14 individual studio spaces and one communal studio, and share a glaze area, three gas kilns, four electric kilns, a Raku kiln, and equipment like slab rollers, pug mills, extruders and electric wheels. For the past five years, the center has rented a nearby 1,340-square-foot annex as an additional classroom.</p>
        <p>In recognition of its anniversary, rather than its usual schedule of solo shows by noted artists, each of this year's exhibitions highlights a different aspect of work produced at the center. In February, ''Cups Coming Together'' presented 160 cups created by past and current members. (Past members include prominent clay artists like Kelli Damron, Rene Murray, Stephen Rodriguez and Barbara Walch.) In October, four current members will exhibit installations of ''bottlescapes'' in a show called ''All Bottled Up.'' For a group whose members are variously referred to as potters, ceramicists or sculptors, the term ''clay artist,'' said Leigh Taylor Mickelson, the center's new program director, ''encompasses all that clay has to offer -- pottery, decorative vessels, wall works, abstract sculpture and everything in between.''</p>
        <p>Members run the gamut. Some, like Audrey Greenwald, 75, who has worked at the center since its founding, make functional pottery. Others, like Ms. Mickelson and Albert Pfarr, 46, the center's director of operations, are rooted in the abstract. Mr. Pfarr, who lives in Yonkers, creates enormous, unglazed terra-cotta structures that resemble trees; Ms. Mickelson's pieces are whimsical sculptures whose forms are derived from nature.</p>
        <p>The Clay Art Center's extensive educational offerings were begun by Ms. Kashyap, and remain her primary focus. ''When I came, we were known in the ceramics world, but we weren't known in the local community,'' she said. ''I knew we needed more public engagement and exposure.'' She considers all forms of educational outreach -- the center's array of classes and workshops, its residencies, the after-school programs it runs in local middle and high schools, or its 11 exhibits each year -- essential to the center's objective.</p>
        <p>What started as a single class in 1997 has grown to 14 weekly adult classes as well as monthly workshops and master classes led by nationally renowned artists and a summer teacher training course. There are also classes for children and teenagers, and beginning in August, six two-week camp sessions for ages 6 and up. According to Ms. Mickelson, the center enrolled 241 students -- the most ever -- this spring.</p>
        <p>Many members live in Westchester, but some travel from New York City, Connecticut and New Jersey. In addition to their creative work, they share studio chores like mixing glazes and emptying kilns. In keeping with Ms. Kashyap's intention, even outside of classes, they are learning. ''We grow alongside one another,'' said Sarah Koster, who joined the center in 2002. ''We're not even conscious that we're observing each other and taking things in.''</p>
        <p>Natalie Kase, a member since the 1980s, agreed. ''We are a community,'' she said. ''We can't help but learn from one another.''</p>
        <p>Thanks to its educational programs, the Clay Art Center now has a positive income stream. Nevertheless, it has just been granted nonprofit status. This will enable it, Ms. Mickelson explained, ''to get grant money, solicit funds, and do more outreach work with the underserved.''</p>
        <p>Membership, which is predominantly women, is not juried now, but that may change, Ms. Kashyap said. ''We are in the enviable position of having a waiting list of people who want to become members. We are on the road to being more selective.''</p>
        <p>When it comes to the center's two yearlong artist-in-residence positions, however, the center is very selective. Residents are given private studio space, full access to the facilities, and solo shows at the end of their stay. ''Membership here is on the older side,'' said Ms. Mickelson, who lives in Ossining. ''Besides bringing new talent into the building, it's nice to mix up the age range.''</p>
        <p>A current resident, Kyla Toomey, whose pastel-glazed nesting bowls will appear in ''At the Table,'' is 24. She has taught some of the center's classes -- an experience, she said with an appreciative smile, that is ''like having 50 moms.''</p>
        <p>''At the Table: Morning, Noon and Night,'' opens Friday and runs through June 23 in the Choy Gallery at the Clay Art Center, 40 Beech Street, Port Chester; (914) 937-2047; www.clayartcenter.org. There is a free reception Friday from 6 to 9 p.m.</p>
        <p>ARTS AND ENTERTAINMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
