<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Iraq's Curse: A Thirst for Final, Crushing Victory</title>
    <meta content="03wong" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/weekinreview/03wong.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851966"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sunni Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sunni Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Baath Party</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Mahdi Army</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hussein, Saddam</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sadr, Moktada Al-</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E7DE1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1332" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Iraq's Curse: A Thirst for Final, Crushing Victory</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Iraq’s Curse: A Thirst for Final, Crushing Victory</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WONG</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PERHAPS no fact is more revealing about Iraq's history than this: The Iraqis have a word that means to utterly defeat and humiliate someone by dragging his corpse through the streets.</p>
        <p>The word is ''sahel,'' and it helps explain much of what I have seen in three and a half years of covering the war.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>No faction has been able to secure absolute power, and that has only sharpened the hunger for it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PERHAPS no fact is more revealing about Iraq's history than this: The Iraqis have a word that means to utterly defeat and humiliate someone by dragging his corpse through the streets.</p>
        <p>The word is ''sahel,'' and it helps explain much of what I have seen in three and a half years of covering the war.</p>
        <p>It is a word unique to Iraq, my friend Razzaq explained over tea one afternoon on my final tour. Throughout Iraq's history, he said, power has changed hands only through extreme violence, when a leader was vanquished absolutely, and his destruction was put on display for all to see.</p>
        <p>Most famously it happened to a former prime minister, Nuri al-Said, who tried to flee after a military coup in 1958 by scurrying through eastern Baghdad dressed as a woman. He was shot dead. His body was disinterred and hacked apart, the bits dragged through the streets. In later years, Saddam Hussein and the Baath Party crushed their enemies with the same brand of brutality.</p>
        <p>''Other Arabs say, 'You are the country of sahel,' '' Razzaq said. ''It has always been that way in Iraq.''</p>
        <p>But in this war, the moment of sahel has been elusive. No faction -- not the Shiite Arabs or Sunni Arabs or Kurds -- has been able to secure absolute power, and that has only sharpened the hunger for it.</p>
        <p>Listen to Iraqis engaged in the fight, and you realize they are far from exhausted by the war. Many say this is only the beginning.</p>
        <p>President Bush, on the other hand, has escalated the American military involvement here on the assumption that the Iraqi factions have tired of armed conflict and are ready to reach a grand accord. Certainly there are Iraqis who have grown weary. But they are not the ones at the country's helm; many are among some two million who have fled, helping leave the way open for extremists to take control of their homeland.</p>
        <p>''We've changed nothing,'' said Fakhri al-Qaisi, a Sunni Arab dentist turned hard-line politician who has three bullets lodged in his torso from a recent assassination attempt. ''It's dark. There will be more blood.''</p>
        <p>I first met Mr. Qaisi in 2003 at a Salafi mosque in western Baghdad, when the Sunni Arab insurgency was gaining momentum. He articulated the Sunnis' simmering anger at being ousted from power. That fury has blossomed and is likely only to grow, as religious Shiite leaders and their militias become more entrenched in the government and as Kurds in the north push to expand their region and secede in all but name.</p>
        <p>Caught in the middle of the civil war are the Americans. To Iraq's factions, they are the weakest of all the armed groups in one crucial respect: their will is ebbing and their time here is limited. That leaves Iraqis more motivated than ever to cling to their weapons, preparing for what many see as an inevitable plunge into the abyss.</p>
        <p>''Everyone -- the Sunni, the Shia -- is playing the waiting game,'' an Iraqi leader told me over dinner at his home in the Green Zone. ''They're waiting out the Americans. Everyone is using time against you.''</p>
        <p>Much seemed different in April 2003, when the Americans pulled down the statue of Saddam Hussein in Firdos Square and allowed Iraqis to drag it through the streets. It looked like an act of sahel at the time, but the Americans failed to establish total control, as Iraqi history says a conqueror must.</p>
        <p>Four years on, Sunni and Shiite attacks against the Americans are expanding. There is little love among Iraqi civilians for the troops, though many fear the anarchy that could follow an American withdrawal.</p>
        <p>''I'm still sticking by my principle, which is against the occupation,'' Mr. Qaisi said in an interview here while visiting from his new home in Tikrit. ''I'm Iraqi, and I think the Iraqi people should have this principle. We have the right to defend our country as George Washington did.''</p>
        <p>As long as I have known him, Mr. Qaisi has rejected the idea that the Sunni Arabs are the minority in this country. To him and many other Sunni Arabs, the borders of Iraq do not delineate the boundaries of the war. The conflict is set, instead, against the backdrop of the entire Islamic world, in which demography and history have always favored the Sunnis. That sense of entitlement is fed by the notion that Iraq's Shiite Arabs are just proxies for Iran's Persian rulers.</p>
        <p>For the Shiites, who make up 60 percent of Iraqis, the unalloyed hostility of the Sunni Arabs only reinforces a centuries-old sense of victimhood. So the Shiite militias grow, stoking vengeance. Through force of arms, and backed by the Americans and Iran, the religious Shiites intend to dominate the country entirely, taking what they believe was stripped from them when their revered leader Hussein was murdered in the desert of seventh-century Mesopotamia.</p>
        <p>It was at the site of that ancient bloodletting, Karbala, that I twice witnessed the intense Shiite ache for righteousness and triumph. In early 2004, thousands of young fighters in the Mahdi Army, the militia of the nationalist Shiite cleric Moktada al-Sadr, fought and died in a fevered uprising against the Americans. Last March, the same zealotry showed in a different way, as millions of Shiite pilgrims marched to Karbala's shrines to commemorate the death of Hussein. They went despite relentless attacks by Sunni Arab suicide bombers. To them, it was all part of the unending war.</p>
        <p>''No country in the world is fighting such terrorism,'' said Adel Abdul Mehdi, an Iraqi vice president and leader in the Supreme Islamic Iraqi Council, a powerful Shiite party, on the day he made his pilgrimage. ''Every time we give more martyrs, we are more determined. This is a big battle, there is no such battle in the world.''</p>
        <p>The Shiites have waited centuries for their moment on the throne, and the war is something they are willing to tolerate as the price for taking power, said the Iraqi leader who had invited me to dinner in the Green Zone. ''The Shia say this is not exceptional for them, this is normal,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The belief of the Shiites that they must consolidate power through force of arms is tethered to ever-present suspicions of an impending betrayal by the Americans. Though the Americans have helped institute the representative system of government that the Shiites now dominate, they have failed to eliminate memories of how the first President Bush allowed Saddam Hussein to slaughter rebelling Shiites in 1991. Shiite leaders are all too aware, as well, of America's hostility toward Iran, the seat of Shiite power, and of its close alliances with Sunni Arab nations, especially Saudi Arabia.</p>
        <p>''One day we'll find that we've returned back to 1917,'' said Sheik Muhammad Bakr Khamis al-Suhail, a respected Shiite neighborhood leader in Baghdad, referring to the installation here of a Sunni Arab monarchy by the British after World War I. ''The pressure of the Arab countries on the American administration might push the Americans to choose the Sunni Arabs.''</p>
        <p>Sitting in the cool recesses of his home, the white-robed sheik said he was a moderate, a supporter of democracy. It is for people like him that the Americans have fought this war. But the solution he proposes is not one the Americans would easily embrace.</p>
        <p>''In the history of Iraq, more than 7,000 years, there have always been strong leaders,'' he said. ''We need strong rulers or dictators like Franco, Hitler, even Mubarak. We need a strong dictator, and a fair one at the same time, to kill all extremists, Sunni and Shiite.''</p>
        <p>I was surprised to hear those words. But perhaps I was being naïve. Looking back on all I have seen of this war, it now seems that the Iraqis have been driving all along for the decisive victory, the act of sahel, the day the bodies will be dragged through the streets.</p>
        <p>THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
