<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Flounder Restrictions Squeeze Sport Fishermen</title>
    <meta content="03mainnjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03mainnj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851798"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FISHING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fluke (Fish)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Flounder (Fish)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E0DC1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="910" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Flounder Restrictions Squeeze Sport Fishermen</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Flounder Restrictions Squeeze Sport Fishermen</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strauss, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on impact that new, severe fluke fishing restriction is having on sport fishermen and sport-fishing industry in New Jersey; restrictions are in place so that population can reach 204-million-pound goal set by Congress for 2010; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Strathmere Fishing and Environmental Club had its annual opening day flounder tournament last Saturday, a beautiful late-spring day.</p>
        <p>''A seven-pounder won the tournament; it ran 25 inches, a real nice fish,'' said Frank Jankowski, who has seen 25 opening days from his business, Frank's Boat Rentals, in the village just north of bustling Sea Isle City.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Strathmere Fishing and Environmental Club had its annual opening day flounder tournament last Saturday, a beautiful late-spring day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Strathmere Fishing and Environmental Club had its annual opening day flounder tournament last Saturday, a beautiful late-spring day.</p>
        <p>''A seven-pounder won the tournament; it ran 25 inches, a real nice fish,'' said Frank Jankowski, who has seen 25 opening days from his business, Frank's Boat Rentals, in the village just north of bustling Sea Isle City.</p>
        <p>The problem is that Mr. Jankowski has never seen an opening flounder day so late in the year. That could create difficulties for him and others in the sport-fishing industry.</p>
        <p>''Usually, I'm opening by the first weekend in May, but these new restrictions, whew!'' he said. ''It won't kill me, but to lose three weeks of business, well, that isn't a good thing.''</p>
        <p>The Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission and the Mid-Atlantic Fishery Management Council have mandated strict restrictions on the fishing of fluke -- the summer flounder most often caught along the Atlantic Seaboard. Restrictions on other fish may also come in the next few years.</p>
        <p>The fluke restrictions were put in place so that the population can get to the 204 million pounds Congress set as a goal for 2010. Last year, the estimated population was slightly more than half that.</p>
        <p>So this year, the agencies put each state on fluke-fishing restrictions of various stringencies on the size of the fish and the length of the season.</p>
        <p>New Jersey has among the most severe restrictions. The 2006 season was rather short, from early May to mid-October, and this year is even shorter, from May 26 to Sept. 10.</p>
        <p>In addition, sport fishermen can keep only eight flounder again this year; all must be at least 17 inches long, up from 16 1/2 inches last year.</p>
        <p>''By shortening the season, that is literally time you never get back,'' said Jim Reinknecht, who with a partner, Richard Moore, runs two party boats -- the Teal, out of Atlantic Highlands, and the AC Lady, out of Atlantic City.</p>
        <p>So instead of fishing for flounder early in the season, his boats went farther afield -- about five or six miles out in the ocean instead of in the back bay or near shore -- to find bluefish and striped bass.</p>
        <p>''The trips are longer, the fishing is harder, and the fish aren't as plentiful,'' Mr. Reinknecht said. ''It puts a stress on all the boats and the bluefish, too. It puts a crimp on everyone.''</p>
        <p>Salt-water fishing is big business, accounting for $1.13 billion annually in the state, said John DePersenaire, fisheries policy and biological researcher for the Recreational Fishing Alliance, a lobbying group based in New Gretna.</p>
        <p>The fluke population started slowing in the 1990s, but for no apparent reason, said Thomas W. McCloy, administrator for the Bureau of Marine Fisheries in the Division of Fish and Wildlife in the State Department of Environmental Protection.</p>
        <p>At more than 100 million pounds along the coast, the fluke population is not endangered but is not expanding as officials want, he said. ''We don't know what is keeping the population low, whether it is predators or competition for food or slight overfishing, but we want to have a large, stabilized population and, unfortunately, the sport fishermen are taking a hit right now,'' he said.</p>
        <p>There are restrictions on commercial fishing of fluke as well, but they seem to have created less of a stir economically, said Tina Berger, a spokeswoman for the Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission, which is made up of officials from states from Maine to Florida. Commercial fishermen are allotted 60 percent of the catch, with sport fishermen taking 40 percent.</p>
        <p>She said restrictions might come in the next several years for weakfish, blackfish and lobsters, but they should affect sport fishing less because they would not be as stringent. Plans are, for instance, to limit weakfish catches in 2008 to fish larger than 13 inches and to bar recreational divers from keeping lobsters larger than 5 1/4 inches.</p>
        <p>Things have not been bad for everyone in the industry, though. John Larson, who has run recreational and commercial fishing businesses at Barnegat Light since 1961, said that he had long gone on bluefish trips and that business was up so far this season for a different reason.</p>
        <p>''Over the last several years, people have been able to afford their own boats, with Fiberglas and mass production,'' Mr. Larson said. ''With better electronics and global positioning systems, too, they can do almost as well getting to the fishing spots as we experts can.</p>
        <p>''But now you see that $3 gas -- or even more when you have to buy it at a marina -- limits these guys,'' he said. ''They are not likely to go out as far. It's an expensive proposition. So more people are doing party boats, at least for now.''</p>
        <p>Still, the fluke restriction is important because fluke is the primary sport fish along the coast. It is easily caught with big hooks, with the boat cruising along slowly and lines dragging the bay or ocean floor where the fish like to stay. There are an estimated 125 party boat operators along the coast in New Jersey and in the New York City region.</p>
        <p>''There are flounder all over the place here,'' said Mr. Reinknecht, speaking from Atlantic City. ''We could have been going out every day and making people happy.</p>
        <p>''Take those weeks on either end out for us, though,'' he said, ''and I'll bet you see some boats go belly up in the not-too-distant future.''</p>
        <p>FISHING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
