<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reviving a Birthplace of Civil Rights</title>
    <meta content="03nati" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/business/yourmoney/03natreal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851834"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NATIONAL PERSPECTIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia/Atlanta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlanta (Ga)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E5DA1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1209" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reviving a Birthplace of Civil Rights</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Reviving a Birthplace of Civil Rights</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELSA BRENNER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>J. W. ROBINSON, 80, remembers when the Sweet Auburn neighborhood in Atlanta was a mecca for aspiring African-American professionals like himself. Just out of college in the early 1950s, Mr. Robinson, a fledgling architect, used to frequent the stylish establishments along the 1.5-mile-long stretch of Auburn Avenue -- among them the Royal Peacock, a nightclub that featured Ray Charles and well-known jazz performers of the day.</p>
        <p>''Back when I was in my early 20s, Auburn Avenue was a street that had everything a person could need -- fine restaurants, the best stores and great entertainment,'' said Mr. Robinson, who is now one of the architects charting a $48.5 million revitalization of the neighborhood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Local leaders want to revive Atlanta’s Sweet Auburn neighborhood, once a mecca for aspiring African-American professionals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>J. W. ROBINSON, 80, remembers when the Sweet Auburn neighborhood in Atlanta was a mecca for aspiring African-American professionals like himself. Just out of college in the early 1950s, Mr. Robinson, a fledgling architect, used to frequent the stylish establishments along the 1.5-mile-long stretch of Auburn Avenue -- among them the Royal Peacock, a nightclub that featured Ray Charles and well-known jazz performers of the day.</p>
        <p>''Back when I was in my early 20s, Auburn Avenue was a street that had everything a person could need -- fine restaurants, the best stores and great entertainment,'' said Mr. Robinson, who is now one of the architects charting a $48.5 million revitalization of the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Situated several blocks from Atlanta's downtown, the area known as Sweet Auburn has been called the cradle of the civil rights movement and has since received national and local historic landmark designations. Auburn Avenue was the birthplace of Martin Luther King Jr., and he is buried there.</p>
        <p>But as the rest of the city opened up its neighborhoods to blacks as well as whites, successful residents tended to move away, and the area deteriorated economically. It also suffered when a highway connector at Interstates 75 and 85 split the neighborhood in two. These days it is pockmarked with empty stores and vacant lots and plagued by crime.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the historic designations ''put a damper on new construction, because of the limits they place on certain changes,'' said A. J. Robinson, the president of Central Atlanta Progress, a downtown business improvement group. (He is not related to J. W. Robinson, the architect.) Until the recent creation of a special tax district, ''there were no incentives for developers,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Now city officials, a private developer and leaders of the Big Bethel African Methodist Episcopal Church in Atlanta are trying to reverse that downward trend by building housing and commercial space on one block of Auburn Avenue, hoping that will inspire change in the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>In a joint venture of the church, located on Auburn Avenue since 1847, and the Integral Group, a local development company, the partners are building Renaissance Walk at Sweet Auburn. On three acres, it will include 30,000 square feet of retail space and condominiums and lofts selling for $250,000 to $600,000, all scheduled to open this fall.</p>
        <p>Since its inception, the church -- where President William Howard Taft spoke in 1911 and Nelson Mandela appeared in 1990 -- has played a significant role in the social, political and economic life of its congregation, said the Rev. Gregory V. Eason Sr., the current pastor. Even after congregants move to other parts of Atlanta, many return on Sundays to the church, which also runs a high-rise housing project in the neighborhood and housing for recovering addicts.</p>
        <p>The church began buying parcels as they came up for sale in the years after desegregation. Its goal with Renaissance Walk, Pastor Eason said, is to bring the middle class back to live in Sweet Auburn.</p>
        <p>About $9 million in private equity for the project has come from the Integral Group, with the remainder being financed through the Bank of America, said Egbert L. J. Perry, an Atlanta resident and the chief executive of the Integral Group. The company was a developer of nearby Centennial Place, which was nationally recognized as a model for urban mixed-income, mixed-use neighborhood revitalization.</p>
        <p>So far, two-thirds of the one- and two bedroom condos at Renaissance Walk have been sold, Mr. Perry said, noting that the buyers are primarily young African-American professionals and empty nesters, some of whom work in downtown Atlanta, which is within walking distance from the new residences.</p>
        <p>Rodney Lee, an African-American businessman, bought a one-bedroom condo at Renaissance Walk and is moving from College Park, a suburb of Atlanta, to Sweet Auburn with his wife, Tyesha, and two sons. ''We want to be part of everything that's going on there in terms of reclaiming the spirit of this place,'' said Mr. Lee, who is reopening a floral shop that had gone out business in the blighted neighborhood.</p>
        <p>David M. Hamilton, an architect for the project, said his company, Praxis3, designed Renaissance Walk around the shells of several one- and two-story buildings, including the now-defunct Mutual Federal Savings Bank of Atlanta, one of the first black-owned banks in the nation. The older structures, dating from the first half of the 20th century, will house most of the retail space and some of the lofts. Although they were gutted and renovated, their exteriors remain essentially unchanged, Mr. Hamilton said.</p>
        <p>A new seven-story brick and precast stone structure, which includes most of the condos and is designed to harmonize with the existing architecture, ''blends in but doesn't mimic what is there,'' said Stuart Romm, another principal of Praxis3, which is based in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>J. W. Robinson, who renovated Dr. King's birth home and is the lead architect for his family-owned architectural firm, J. W. Robinson &amp; Associates in Atlanta, has overseen construction of a six-level parking garage and replacement of the old sewer system, which was built in the late 1800s out of hand-chiseled stone.</p>
        <p>''It's been a most complex site to build on,'' Mr. Robinson said, ''mostly because of the very high water table in the area and the poor soil. And while we put in the new sewer system, we had to keep the old one functioning.''</p>
        <p>The city, Fulton County and the Atlanta Public Schools district created a special tax district and issued about $50 million in bonds for a variety of projects -- including the new sewage system in Sweet Auburn -- in several economically depressed areas of the city. Traditionally, the amount of such a bond is based on how much a project will generate in taxes over a longer-term period, in this case 25 years, said A. J. Robinson of the Central Atlanta Progress. The project is the ''largest and most significant investment in terms of private capital in the Auburn Avenue district in three decades,'' according to Mr. Robinson.</p>
        <p>Kwanza Hall, a city councilman whose district includes Auburn Avenue and whose late father, Leon Hall, worked with Dr. King, said that since construction began on Renaissance Walk, Georgia State University began building a 2,000-bed dormitory in the Sweet Auburn district. The dormitory project, Mr. Hall said, will most likely lead to a big increase in the number of people using the businesses along Auburn Avenue.</p>
        <p>Some community activists, however, are concerned that the area will become gentrified and out of the reach of many working-class African-Americans, even though 20 percent of the units have been designated as affordable and are selling for less than $200,000.</p>
        <p>At the Historic District Development Corporation, Joan P. Garner, the president and chief executive, explained that preservation and affordability are two main goals of her nonprofit group. ''We're glad to see development happening in the area,'' she said, ''but we were concerned to see some old buildings torn down in the process.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Perry of Integral Group defended the 20 percent set-aside of below-market-rate units, saying: ''If that percent of all new residential construction was affordable, so many cities wouldn't be seeing such a severe crisis of work-force housing. Renaissance Walk should serve as a good model for others to follow.''</p>
        <p>NATIONAL PERSPECTIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
