<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Whistle-Blower</title>
    <meta content="03wwln--Q4.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/magazine/03wwln-Q4-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851680"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 6-03-07: QUESTIONS FOR MIKE JONES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Life Church (Colorado Springs, Colo)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Michael (Male Escort)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haggard, Ted (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Solomon, Deborah</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">I Had to Say Something (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Haggard, Ted</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E1DC1430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="696" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Whistle-Blower</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Whistle-Blower</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SOLOMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Solomon, Deborah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Deborah Solomon interview with Mike Jones, male escort who outed Ted Haggard and forced his resignation as head of New Life Church in Colorado Springs; he comments on his decision to write memoir about their affair called I Had to Say Something; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q: As the male escort who outed Ted Haggard, the celebrity preacher and former head of the New Life Church in Colorado Springs, it was probably inevitable that you would write a memoir about your affair with him. Are you concerned that your new book, ''I Had to Say Something,'' exploits his sorrows for financial gain? No. I received a very small advance for the book. And when I decided to come out with the story last year, I lost everything. I lost all my massage clients; I lost all my personal-training clients. I got fired from my modeling job at the art school.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The escort who brought down the Rev. Ted Haggard talks about why he wrote a book about it, why the gay community is still divided on his having done it and the joys of Sea World.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q: As the male escort who outed Ted Haggard, the celebrity preacher and former head of the New Life Church in Colorado Springs, it was probably inevitable that you would write a memoir about your affair with him. Are you concerned that your new book, ''I Had to Say Something,'' exploits his sorrows for financial gain? No. I received a very small advance for the book. And when I decided to come out with the story last year, I lost everything. I lost all my massage clients; I lost all my personal-training clients. I got fired from my modeling job at the art school.</p>
        <p>You modeled for a life drawing class? At the Art Institute of Colorado. I love that people draw me. I have a nice bod. I work so hard at it, why not show it off? Every morning I'm in the gym at 5 lifting weights.</p>
        <p>Haggard, in the meantime, has apologized to the church and reportedly moved with his wife and the youngest of his five children to Phoenix, where he plans to pursue a psychology degree online. I think he is taking psychology to self-examine himself. I don't think he wants to treat other people.</p>
        <p>What led you to out him after what you say was your three-year relationship with him? I've been with some pretty famous people, and I would never out them. This was a unique situation. Here is Ted preaching about being shameful -- You won't see the kingdom of God if you're gay, and blah, blah, blah -- and then he sneaks around with me.</p>
        <p>I agree he's a world-class hypocrite, but how many of us could stand having our private lives exposed on the evening news? That's why it is not fair for the Christian right to put such a harsh judgment on a certain segment of society. Look in your own closet, people.</p>
        <p>Are you politically active? I'm really not this left-wing liberal like some people have tried to paint me. I think I'm very moderate.</p>
        <p>Even so, your disclosure came just days before the midterm election and gave the Democrats a boost by tarnishing the Christian right. Are you a Democrat? I'm a registered Democrat, but I've voted Republican. I voted for Bush in the last election.</p>
        <p>I see you won a lifetime achievement award from the Harvey Milk Club in San Francisco in May. Yes, but no other group, except for the Gay and Lesbian Task Force in New York City, has contacted me to say, even, Are you O.K.? It has been a very lonely time for me. I can only guess that they think I'm a bad example of the gay community.</p>
        <p>Millions of people appreciate that you spoke up, but still, as a prostitute, you're hardly a shining exemplar of gay accomplishment. I prefer the term ''male escort.'' If I was strictly a prostitute, people would probably think I was working the street. And I'm not. These men were coming to me with really big emotional issues, and I was comforting them.</p>
        <p>What are you planning to do job-wise, now that all your clients have fled? If I could do my life over again, I would probably go into marine biology. I'm a big dolphin person.</p>
        <p>Why not go to college and get a degree? I'm too old for that. I just turned 50. If I could get a job at Sea World, I'd probably be happy.</p>
        <p>I doubt Sea World would hire you, considering your lusty image. Yes, it's weird. I have become kind of a hot potato. You know what would be fun? Even it was a very small part, I would like to be in a play. That would really take my mind off this.</p>
        <p>Best of luck getting a role, but are you worried you'll be arrested for prostitution in the meantime? The Denver Police did knock at my door, yes. I referred them to my attorney, and I have heard nothing since. I would think they would need more proof, actual substance, to pursue.</p>
        <p>But isn't your book a confession? I don't know. I don't know if the police will read it.</p>
        <p>DEBORAH SOLOMON</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 6-03-07: QUESTIONS FOR MIKE JONES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
