<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gay Inmates to Be Granted Conjugal Visits in California</title>
    <meta content="03visit" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/us/03visit.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851974"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, Jesse</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Civil Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <org class="online_producer">American Civil Liberties Union</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E6DD1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="642" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gay Inmates to Be Granted Conjugal Visits in California</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gay Inmates to Be Granted Conjugal Visits in California</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JESSE McKINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, Jesse</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, June 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gay and lesbian prisoners in California will be allowed overnight visits with their partners under new prison policy, believed to be first time state has allowed same-sex conjugal stays (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gay and lesbian prisoners in California will be allowed overnight visits with their partners under a new prison policy, believed to be the first time a state has allowed same-sex conjugal stays.</p>
        <p>The policy comes more than two years after a 2003 California law provided equal rights for registered domestic partners in California, including those of the same sex and non-married heterosexuals. Gay and civil rights groups had threatened to sue to permit the conjugal visits in prisons, which they say have been slow to enact changes promised by the law.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new policy in California, believed to be the first of its kind, comes after gay and civil rights groups had threatened to sue to permit the visits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gay and lesbian prisoners in California will be allowed overnight visits with their partners under a new prison policy, believed to be the first time a state has allowed same-sex conjugal stays.</p>
        <p>The policy comes more than two years after a 2003 California law provided equal rights for registered domestic partners in California, including those of the same sex and non-married heterosexuals. Gay and civil rights groups had threatened to sue to permit the conjugal visits in prisons, which they say have been slow to enact changes promised by the law.</p>
        <p>''It's a little troubling that a state agency had to be threatened with legal action to obey state law,'' said Geoff Kors, the executive director of Equality California, a gay rights organization. ''There was no justifiable excuse for not complying.''</p>
        <p>Terry Thornton, a spokeswoman for the state Department of Corrections and Rehabilitation, said the slow pace of change was due, in part, to considerations of whether allowing the visits would expose gay inmates to danger inside the prison, where they are sometimes singled out for attack. ''We had to thoroughly evaluate all the security concerns,'' Ms. Thornton said.</p>
        <p>The policy change was spurred by a letter warning of legal action from the American Civil Liberties Union on behalf of Vernon Foeller, 40, a gay man who had been serving a 20-month sentence for attempted burglary at the state prison in Vacaville, Calif. Alex Cleghorn, an AC.L.U. lawyer, said that Mr. Foeller was eligible for a conjugal visit except that the prison system ''didn't recognize his partner as a family member.''</p>
        <p>''They have pages and pages of regulations that must be met to permit these visits,'' Mr. Cleghorn said, ''and Vernon met all of these requirements.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Foeller was released in April.</p>
        <p>Overnight visits, which can be up to 72 hours long, have been allowed in California since the 1970s, Ms. Thornton said, and are conducted in units inside prison grounds, often trailers. While suggestive of sexual activity, the visits sometimes include several family members, including children.</p>
        <p>''It's not exclusive to conjugal activities,'' Ms. Thornton said.</p>
        <p>Gay and lesbian inmates were not allowed visits from their partners because only spouses were recognized as ''immediate family.''</p>
        <p>Several categories of inmate are not allowed the visits, including those on death row, sex offenders, those serving sentences of life without parole, and those who have been violent with minors or family members. Prisoners also must have been on good behavior, with no violations.</p>
        <p>The new policy will allow only those currently registered as domestic partners to ask for the visits, and affirms that no prisoners will be allowed overnight visits with other prisoners, regardless of status.</p>
        <p>Only a handful of states -- including New York -- allow conjugal visits, which some prison officials say can help reduce the stress of prison life and maintain prisoners' connections to their families. Critics, however, have cited a variety of reasons to oppose the visits, including the potential for spreading sexually transmitted diseases and the additional cost of maintaining separate conjugal prison quarters.</p>
        <p>Shannon Minter, the legal director for the National Center for Lesbian Rights in San Francisco, called the policy change a ''great leap forward'' but said gay and lesbian inmates were often still the target of discrimination and violence.</p>
        <p>''There are certain social arenas that have been insulated from social changes going on in broader society, and jails and prisons is one of those areas,'' Mr. Minter said.</p>
        <p>California has a ban on same-sex marriage, although that law has been the subject of legal battles. The California Supreme Court is currently reviewing the law's constitutionality as part of a suit brought by the City of San Francisco and a group of gay and lesbian couples.</p>
        <p>The policy change must be approved by the state's Office of Administrative Law before taking effect, most likely later this year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
