<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wolf Pack Hockey Team to Stay in Hartford</title>
    <meta content="03weekctCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03weekct.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851787"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hartford Civic Center (Conn)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tornadoes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hartford (Conn)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Somers (Conn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Northland AEG</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hartford Wolf Pack</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holtz, Jeff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/Hartford</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tornadoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E6DC1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wolf Pack Hockey Team to Stay in Hartford</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Week in Connecticut</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF HOLTZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holtz, Jeff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Week column; minor league Hartford Wolf Pack hockey team reaches agreement with Northland AEG, new operators of Hartford Civic Center, to stay in city through 2013; rare type of small tornado called landspout causes significant damage to horse barn in Somers, Conn (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hartford may have lost the Whalers to North Carolina. But for now, it is keeping the Wolf Pack.</p>
        <p>The Hartford Wolf Pack hockey team, the New York Rangers' top minor league affiliate and a member of the American Hockey League, announced an agreement last Tuesday with the new operators of the Hartford Civic Center, Northland A.E.G., to keep the team in the city through 2013.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hartford may have lost the Whalers to North Carolina. But for now, it is keeping the Wolf Pack.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hartford may have lost the Whalers to North Carolina. But for now, it is keeping the Wolf Pack.</p>
        <p>The Hartford Wolf Pack hockey team, the New York Rangers' top minor league affiliate and a member of the American Hockey League, announced an agreement last Tuesday with the new operators of the Hartford Civic Center, Northland A.E.G., to keep the team in the city through 2013.</p>
        <p>The team's fate had been uncertain because its owner, Madison Square Garden, is to stop operating the Hartford Civic Center on June 30.</p>
        <p>Under the new agreement, M.S.G. will continue to own the team and make the decisions on players and coaches. Northland A.E.G., however, will be responsible for the day-to-day business operations, including marketing and ticket sales.</p>
        <p>''The Rangers organization is, in our eyes, a first-class organization,'' said Bob Newman, the chief operating officer for A.E.G. Facilities, a division of Northland A.E.G. ''We're entering a collaboration with one of the premier A.H.L. franchises in existence.''</p>
        <p>Hartford's mayor, Eddie A. Perez, said the team was important for the city's economy.</p>
        <p>''We have a large hockey fan base from when the Whalers were here, and the Wolf Pack has kept that going,'' he said. ''This keeps people coming to the civic center and to the central business district, and it keeps the discussion about bringing the N.H.L. back to Hartford going.''</p>
        <p>Last season, the Wolf Pack ranked 18th out of 27 teams in the league in attendance, drawing 182,516 fans for 40 games -- an average of 4,563 a game.</p>
        <p>Mr. Newman said the company hoped to improve the attendance. ''Our goal is to create a new atmosphere at the Wolf Pack games and all events at the Hartford Civic Center,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Wolf Pack began playing in Hartford in the 1997-98 season -- the Whalers had left the season before to become the Carolina Hurricanes -- and has made the playoffs each year. It won the A.H.L.'s championship, the Calder Cup, in 2000.</p>
        <p>Landspout, a Small Tornado, Damages Horse Barn</p>
        <p>A rare type of small tornado called a landspout caused significant damage to a horse barn in Somers last Monday.</p>
        <p>The landspout formed around 1 p.m., according to the National Weather Service in Boston. It tore two holes, one approximately 50 feet by 50 feet and the other around 20 feet by 40 feet, in the metal roof of the Shallowbrook Equestrian and Polo Center. There were no injuries to people or horses.</p>
        <p>The weather service said the funnel consisted of winds from 65 to 75 miles per hour. It said it was approximately 60 feet wide, traveled about 650 feet and lasted less than a minute.</p>
        <p>The tornado registered an F-0 on the Enhanced Fujita scale, which is a six-category scale that determines the damage a tornado can cause in relation to its wind strength.</p>
        <p>Deby Gottfried, 22, a riding instructor who saw the landspout, said it formed without warning. ''I actually thought it was an explosion at first,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Hal A. Vita III, 19, whose family owns the center, said it could cost as much as $250,000 to repair the barn.</p>
        <p>Unlike more common larger tornadoes, a landspout is not associated with precipitation. It is instead caused by an air disturbance related to the formation of cumulus clouds. The weather service said there was a line of cumulus clouds in the Somers area at the time last Monday.</p>
        <p>''These are more common in desert areas,'' said Bill Jacquemin, the director and chief meteorologist at the Connecticut Weather Center in Danbury, referring to landspouts. ''We usually don't have this kind of thermal activity when it's not associated with rain. This was unusual.''</p>
        <p>The weather service said a similar tornado, which registered as an F-1, occurred in Ellington on Aug. 16, 2000. In that case, the funnel lifted up a number of horse trailers and dragged them in a circle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jacquemin said the tornado in Somers was one of two in the state last month, with the other in the Bethel area. He said the state normally averaged one a year.</p>
        <p>THE WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
