<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jennifer Openshaw and Randy Schwimmer</title>
    <meta content="03VOWS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/fashion/weddings/03VOWS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851856"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS: VOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Openshaw, Jennifer (Jennifer Schwimmer)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwimmer, Durant</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/Vows</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEEDF1230F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jennifer Openshaw and Randy Schwimmer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jennifer Openshaw and Randy Schwimmer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JENNIFER OPENSHAW had been walking for hours before she settled into a cafe on a side street in Florence. Her hair was pulled back in a ponytail, she wore no makeup and she had on sweat pants, a T-shirt and sneakers. Though weary from the walking, she contentedly began eating a mocha gelato.</p>
        <p>''I was just relishing the moment of being there,'' said Ms. Openshaw, 42, of the solo trip to Italy she took in October 2005, a few months after an 11-year engagement ended.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The couple met over a sandwich and gelato while they were both on trips to Florence, Italy. They were married May 12 in Greenwich, Conn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JENNIFER OPENSHAW had been walking for hours before she settled into a cafe on a side street in Florence. Her hair was pulled back in a ponytail, she wore no makeup and she had on sweat pants, a T-shirt and sneakers. Though weary from the walking, she contentedly began eating a mocha gelato.</p>
        <p>''I was just relishing the moment of being there,'' said Ms. Openshaw, 42, of the solo trip to Italy she took in October 2005, a few months after an 11-year engagement ended.</p>
        <p>Her reverie was interrupted when another tourist sat down. ''Boy, am I hungry,'' declared Durant Schwimmer, who noticed Ms. Openshaw reading a guidebook as he dived into a ham sandwich.</p>
        <p>Silently hoping he wasn't talking to her, Ms. Openshaw tried not to acknowledge his overture. ''The last thing I wanted to do in Italy was start talking to another American,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Openshaw is an entrepreneur described by friends as a savvy, driven, tenacious ''ball of fire.'' She is the host of ''Winning Advice,'' on ABC Radio, and the author of ''The Millionaire Zone: Seven Winning Steps to a Seven-Figure Fortune'' (Hyperion).</p>
        <p>She was still semi-ignoring Mr. Schwimmer when he told her he was vacationing alone for the first time since his 20-year marriage had ended in divorce. But when the lopsided conversation turned to business, Ms. Openshaw perked up.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwimmer, 50, an investment banker known as Randy, is the senior managing director for Churchill Financial in New York. He is as unflappable as he is creative. He plays guitar, sings and writes poetry. Ms. Openshaw mentioned financial products for consumers she was developing and Mr. Schwimmer offered catchy names for them.</p>
        <p>The gelato and ham sandwich were long gone, and to thank him for his ideas, Ms. Openshaw, who was now not so put off, invited him for drinks later.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwimmer, who hadn't had a date in more than two decades, was unprepared. ''I did not go to Italy looking for romance,'' he said. But he quickly went shopping for a cashmere sweater and cologne.</p>
        <p>That evening they met in a piazza near a replica of Michelangelo's ''David.'' As Ms. Openshaw, now wearing a slinky brown dress, strolled toward Mr. Schwimmer, he was stunned.</p>
        <p>''I'm like, 'Oh, my God, this is a very attractive woman,' '' he said. He asked another tourist to snap their photograph.</p>
        <p>They lingered over dinner. ''We just had a very platonic date, but it was a lovely romantic evening,'' Mr. Schwimmer recalled. He thought she was vivacious and worldly, yet innocent, but quickly brushed away the possibility of seeing her again. He was leaving for Tuscany the next morning; she was heading to Rome and Paris. And the biggest wrinkle? Ms. Openshaw lived in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>The next morning, Ms. Openshaw decided she was curious to know more about Mr. Schwimmer, who exuded wholesomeness and had a gentlemanly manner (even if he did quirkily order German wine in Italy). ''There was a quiet beauty to Randy that was tugging at me,'' she said. ''I like to have everything buttoned up, and I wasn't about to leave something unfinished.''</p>
        <p>They returned home, to their respective coasts, on the same day. Mr. Schwimmer, who said Ms. Openshaw filled his thoughts as he traveled around the romantic Tuscan countryside, planned to wait a few days before contacting her. But she e-mailed him her first day back, and that evening they spoke on the phone for three hours.</p>
        <p>''I felt like, 'Wow, there is a connection here,' '' Mr. Schwimmer said. ''I wasn't dreaming it.''</p>
        <p>The following weekend Mr. Schwimmer flew to Los Angeles to see her. When he returned home, he realized he ''wasn't going to dabble in relationships,'' he said. ''When you are divorced and middle-aged, the normal thing is to date 50 women half your age. I'm not that kind of guy.''</p>
        <p>After a six-month bicoastal courtship, Ms. Openshaw moved east. And, the following October they returned to Italy to vacation. Mr. Schwimmer planned to propose in the cafe in Florence, but when they got there, ''dishes were clanking'' and the floor was filthy, he said. A week later in Positano he dropped to his knees and asked her to marry him.</p>
        <p>On May 12, in front of 150 guests at Christ Church in Greenwich, Conn., they were married by the Rev. Mark L. Fitzhugh, an Episcopal priest. The bridegroom read a poem he wrote after the first time Ms. Openshaw visited him:</p>
        <p>All roads cross some bridge, to show</p>
        <p>From where we've come, where we'll go.</p>
        <p>At a dinner reception at Tappan Hill Mansion in Tarrytown, N.Y., the bride, in evening gloves and a crystal-encrusted mermaid-style gown, recalled how on that first evening in Florence, Mr. Schwimmer had yanked her away from an oncoming car.</p>
        <p>In retrospect she realized that act was ''a sign.'' ''This is about being open to the possibilities,'' Ms. Openshaw said later. ''Even the person sitting next to you in a patisserie can be the person who changes the course of your life forever.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS: VOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
