<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Fly on the Gallery Wall</title>
    <meta content="03ganek" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/fashion/03ganek.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851943"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Ganek, Danielle</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE7DF1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1517" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Fly on the Gallery Wall</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Fly on the Gallery Wall</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RUTH LA FERLA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT a glance, Mia, the self-effacing heroine of ''Lulu Meets God and Doubts Him,'' Danielle Ganek's catty vivisection of the New York art world, has little in common with her peers. They are ''gallerinas,'' formidably icy girl Fridays, imperious behind their steel-and-stone desks at Manhattan galleries.</p>
        <p>In her debut novel Ms. Ganek flicks at these glorified receptionists, ''pretentious creatures in intellectual fashion and high heels, dripping with attitude and sarcasm.'' Black-clad ravens to Mia's genteel wren, they trade in impeccable pedigrees, glossy sex appeal and, mostly, information.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Danielle Ganek’s novel, “Lulu Meets God and Doubts Him,” has the art world asking who is who.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT a glance, Mia, the self-effacing heroine of ''Lulu Meets God and Doubts Him,'' Danielle Ganek's catty vivisection of the New York art world, has little in common with her peers. They are ''gallerinas,'' formidably icy girl Fridays, imperious behind their steel-and-stone desks at Manhattan galleries.</p>
        <p>In her debut novel Ms. Ganek flicks at these glorified receptionists, ''pretentious creatures in intellectual fashion and high heels, dripping with attitude and sarcasm.'' Black-clad ravens to Mia's genteel wren, they trade in impeccable pedigrees, glossy sex appeal and, mostly, information.</p>
        <p>As for Mia, a failed artist, ''I never get the poop,'' she says forlornly more than halfway through the book. And then, one day, she does. By the tale's denouement, she has gleaned enough inside intelligence to impress everyone in her rarefied orbit -- the reclusive artists, the pompous dealers, the art-lusting collectors, ''horny as teenagers.'' And she has enough poop to write a scathing tell-all about the after-hours scheming inside the proverbial Chelsea white box.</p>
        <p>Like Ms. Ganek, her real-world alter ego, Mia also gets to live out the cherished fantasy of certain striving New Yorkers: A self-described exile with uncommon reserves of cunning and patience, Mia becomes the ultimate insider, penetrating the private recesses of her arcane world.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ganek, 43, who wore a tailored white shirt, a beige skirt and tan sling-backs for an interview last week, shares more with Mia than her demure wardrobe. Bubbling beneath that studiedly low-key surface is a well of ambition. ''I definitely have painted, badly. I can relate to that aspect of Mia's story,'' she said last week, over chilled mineral water on a rooftop terrace at the Barbara Gladstone Gallery in Chelsea. Without irony, she added, ''I have wrestled with the creative process. Mia, on some level, her story is autobiographical.''</p>
        <p>But while Mia acquires much of her stinging material sitting behind her concrete slab of a desk, Ms. Ganek gathers hers at the constellation of Chelsea galleries where she is a frequent visitor, and at the art fairs and galas she attends with her husband, David K. Ganek, a hedge fund manager and a Guggenheim trustee. Last year the Ganeks served as chairmen of the Guggenheim's International Dinner, raising an impressive $4 million for the museum.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ganek writes at a computer in her duplex, with its four bedrooms and a library, at 740 Park Avenue, one of the city's most prestigious co-ops. Purchased last year for around $19 million, it houses a collection that includes works by noted art world humorists like Richard Prince, Maurizio Cattelan and Jeff Koons.</p>
        <p>Prominent collectors (''Yes, you can read 'prominent' as 'wealthy,' '' Mia informs her readers), the Ganeks are well acquainted with the machinations of an overheated market, in which, as Mia's boss observes, ''art is the new cocaine,'' and the measure of an artwork is its price.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ganek, the daughter of Frank DiGiacomo, a former financial vice president of W. R. Grace, grew up in Switzerland and Brazil but considers herself a committed New Yorker. Since settling in Manhattan two years ago with her husband, who founded his fund, Level Global, in 2003, she has maintained a quiet presence.</p>
        <p>But that is likely to change with the publication tomorrow of ''Lulu,'' which its publisher, Viking, is marketing as the ''Devil Wears Prada'' of the Chelsea set. Poised to become a hot beach read, the book also promises to ease Ms. Ganek's transition from working mom and former magazine editor to certified member of A-list society in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Her ascent seems assured. Earlier this spring she was one of the most talked about women at a gathering at Sloan Barnett's Georgian town house on the Upper East Side of Manhattan. Last Wednesday night she was the guest of Lisa Dennison, the Guggenheim director, who gave her a book party at the museum. Her photo frequently appears in The New York Social Diary, a Web site. She has been photographed at dinners in honor of designers to the Uptown crowd, and has overseen charity benefits at her home in Southampton, N.Y.</p>
        <p>IN her book, the title character, an artists' muse, is urged to use her hip girl-about-town status to introduce her own fashion label. Clearly Ms. Ganek knows a thing or two about self-branding. ''She is a textbook lesson on how to do it,'' said David Patrick Columbia, the publisher of Social Diary.'' ''She takes all of her advantages -- her talent, her husband's financial aura, her involvement in one of the city's major charities'' -- City Harvest -- ''and uses them optimally.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Columbia maintained that Ms. Ganek has shrewdly applied business techniques to raise her profile socially. Yet Ms. Ganek insisted, ''I don't have any social agenda. If you're talking about people who go to a lot of benefits, that's not what I do. It's very disconcerting to go out and do these interviews,'' she added. ''I'm basically quite shy.''</p>
        <p>Still, as Janet Maslin observed in a book review in The New York Times on Monday, Ms. Ganek's rising stature and ''proximity to her subject gives her an insider's wisdom without seriously compromising her ability to dish.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ganek seems to have had little trouble reconciling her new insider status with an exile's point of view. ''As an American living abroad, I have always been an outsider,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mia, too, seems at first to hover in the margins. Like any self-respecting chick-lit heroine, she skewers her boss, Simon Pryce, a peacock in Turnbull &amp; Asser with an immovable coiffure. At the same time she nurses a crush on a young art adviser, a charmer with lank hair and a camel coat slung over his broad shoulders. '' 'Lulu Meets God and Doubts Him' is a genre book,'' Ms. Maslin acknowledged in her review, but as a genre book, ''it's better than most.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ganek's tale centers on the fate of the painting that gives the book its strangely weighty title, a 9-by-12-foot portrait of a 9-year-old girl wielding a dripping brush. The work is by Jeffrey Finelli, a one-armed ''emerging'' artist in his 50s, who has briefly returned to New York from his adoptive home in Italy for the premiere showing of his paintings.</p>
        <p>On the night of his opening, Finelli steps onto the rain-slicked street in front of the Pryce Gallery and is struck by a cab. With his demise comes the inevitable spike in the value of his work, ''Lulu'' in particular, and the equally inevitable skirmish as a hive of scheming dealers, collectors and celebrities zoom in for the kill.</p>
        <p>They include speculators and art trophy hunters like Martin Better, a real estate developer known to drop ''five, ten, even twenty or thirty million on a piece with the nonchalant air of a housewife grabbing a box of Honey Nut Cheerios at the Stop &amp; Shop.'' There is the greedy collector Connie Kantor, married to a toilet-paper-dispenser magnate, ''a moving sight gag'' in five-inch heels and hooded mink sweatshirt, carrying the requisite Birkin bag, ''so big it looks fake, but Connie doesn't have the confidence to carry a fake.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ganek does not spare the big-ticket artists, flimflammers like Dane O'Neill, known equally for his sprawling installations and for getting naked at parties. She takes aim, too, at operators like the contessa, Finelli's mistress, regal in black, trailing hashish plumes from her ivory cigarette holder.</p>
        <p>Her characters have given rise to a flurry of speculation about who might be their real-life models.</p>
        <p>''Certain people are composites,'' said Amy Cappellazzo, the international co-head of postwar and contemporary art at Christie's.</p>
        <p>INDEED, a dealer like Simon bears a superficial resemblance to Philippe Ségalot, a New York dealer with a famously leonine mane. Stock figures, Ms. Ganek's characters nonetheless ring true. They are bound to, Ms. Cappellazzo said: "Sitting in back rooms with someone trying to sell her something, you can't deny that she has firsthand experience in this area."</p>
        <p>Ms. Ganek acknowledged that it is intriguing to play that kind of guessing game: ''The art world has such colorful characters, almost costumed in the way they dress.'' But while her book reads like a roman à clef, ''mine are really made-up characters,'' she insisted. ''I don't mean to sound defensive. It's a fact.''</p>
        <p>She is more comfortable discussing her family. She has no regrets about moving to New York from Greenwich, Conn., with her husband and three children, now 12, 10, and 5. ''We have always been passionate New Yorkers,'' she said. When one of their sons was about to enter the fifth grade, ''we looked at that as a time to come home.''</p>
        <p>She is passionate, too, about the artists she is drawn to, those who comment acerbically ''on the human condition and who use humor effectively,'' she said. Among her treasures is a Cattelan work called ''Cheap to Feed,'' a tiny stuffed lap dog that sits in the entry of her home.</p>
        <p>''When people come into our house, they say hello, they interact with it,'' Ms. Ganek confided mischievously. ''It makes for interesting conversation when I have to explain, 'No, our dog isn't dead.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
