<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Eternal Sunshine</title>
    <meta content="McKay.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="50" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/books/review/McKay-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851631"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Actors and Actresses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Actors and Actresses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Day, Doris</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Santopietro, Tom</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Considering Doris Day (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E7DF1730F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1726" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Eternal Sunshine</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Eternal Sunshine</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NELLIE McKAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CONSIDERING DORIS DAY</p>
        <p>By Tom Santopietro.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 388 pp. Thomas Dunne Books/</p>
        <p>St. Martin's Press. $25.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A biography looks at the multifaceted career of Doris Day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CONSIDERING DORIS DAY</p>
        <p>By Tom Santopietro.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 388 pp. Thomas Dunne Books/</p>
        <p>St. Martin's Press. $25.95.</p>
        <p>What accounts for the stupefying popular success of Doris Day? Like Elvis, she was generally underserved by her motion pictures, though her charisma and forthright personality always carried her through. She is the No. 1 female box-office star of all time, setting the record over three seismic decades -- the 1940s, '50s and '60s. Did she embody McCarthyism or transcend it? As John Updike once said, ''I'm always looking for insights into the real Doris Day because I'm stuck with this infatuation and need to explain it to myself.''</p>
        <p>Singing with the swing-era big bands, Day became a beacon of light through the grim times of World War II. Her radiant pleasantness during cold war paranoia was derided as the cultural revolution of the '60s gained momentum but welcomed by those grateful for her aura of bright optimism and cheery respectability. In her book, ''Doris Day: Her Own Story,'' written with A. E. Hotchner, she expresses happiness at giving up touring for movies because ''my nature is to fold early; I should have been a bird or a flower.'' That natural, simple impulse is evident on her records: her music is uncluttered, sensual and free, driven by an irrepressible will to live.</p>
        <p>Her movies feature a gay man playing a straight man making jokes about homosexuals, Ronald Reagan as a civil rights crusader and working women who are referred to unceasingly as ''girls.'' Her characters are rarely seen working -- if one of them holds a ''respectable'' job, it usually serves as a backdrop to two hours of romantic volleyball (men, unlike women, have entire film genres devoted to work, with romance taking a secondary role).</p>
        <p>Yet Molly Haskell has said, ''Doris Day really in a sense led the way.'' In the dossier ''Move Over Misconceptions: Doris Day Reappraised,'' by Jane Clarke, Diana Simmonds and Mandy Merck, Merck discusses the ''actor as signifier'' -- how consistent dialogue takes on different meanings depending not only on how it is said but also on who is saying it. Day has been a balm to the older generation but played a career woman in a majority of her films, the earliest of which preceded feminism's second wave by about 20 years. Though the mostly male-written screenplays subvert the capable, successful characters Day portrays, her energetic performances are at odds with the traditional gender roles insisted on in the scripts. Similarly, in his book ''Katharine Hepburn: Star as Feminist,'' Andrew Britton wrote of Hepburn, ''Her presence forces her films to go in directions they cannot possibly follow, adopt strategies they cannot fully sustain, raise issues they cannot adequately resolve.''</p>
        <p>Day's later career choices reflected a skepticism of new mores. As Clarke remarks: ''The widespread use of and public respectability for 'the Pill' by the late '60s put a new pressure on women. Far from 'sexual freedom' the Pill was a gun placed at any woman's head: as if the threat of pregnancy was the only reason a woman might have wished to say no to sex.'' Day evinced ''distaste for the new 'permissiveness,' which she perceptively saw to be oppressive rather than liberating.''</p>
        <p>Her pictures feature meat diets, carriage rides, careers in the cattle industry; they depict chicken-truck accidents as hilarious. In ''Do Not Disturb,'' she saves a fox but sports a fur. Day is an inexhaustible animal advocate today, but these plotlines dismay because, as Tom Santopietro notes in ''Considering Doris Day,'' ''she functioned as a role model through whom thousands of women worldwide lived vicariously.'' Day herself has mentioned projects she refused or changes she insisted on: she declined the role of Mrs. Robinson in ''The Graduate'' (finding it exploitative) and had vulgarities removed from ''Lover Come Back.'' She demanded proper care and feeding of the animals involved in the Alfred Hitchcock film ''The Man Who Knew Too Much,'' which was shot partly in Morocco.</p>
        <p>What Day refuses to tolerate is relevant because while her performances were a product of their era, sales of her albums seem to double or triple with each passing year, and DVDs of her movies are increasingly popular. She may not have pursued a political image, but her effect is more intimate, and more powerful, than that of many politicians. A testament to this power is that the organizations founded in her name have attracted more than 180,000 members, continuing to draw attention to the issue of animal rights, which has been called the most progressive cause of our time.</p>
        <p>In 1977, she founded the Doris Day Pet Foundation (now the Doris Day Animal Foundation), and 10 years later the Doris Day Animal League, which focuses on lobbying Washington for pro-animal legislation, like bills ending the slaughter of horses for human consumption and creating a federal entity to review and approve alternatives to animal testing. The Animal League has also initiated a program called the Vicious Circle, which explores the connection between violence against animals and violence against people. (Santopietro repeatedly refers to Day as an ''animal lover,'' a common misnomer. One doesn't have to love animals to respect them. ''Animal lover'' can't help carrying a note of condescension, often used by those wishing to dismiss the larger issues at stake; it is similar to calling a white person who fights for civil rights a ''Negro lover.'' Day cares for her companion animals, but what she has achieved through her organizations and lifestyle goes beyond affection: she's pursuing a change in the mind-set that allows human beings to treat other species as objects.) In 2006, the Animal League joined forces with the Humane Society of the United States, the largest animal protection organization in America.</p>
        <p>Day's personal life is best covered in her autobiography; perhaps realizing this, Santopietro concentrates on her multifaceted career. He is sympathetic to women and knowledgeable about his subject, and his respect for her is refreshing -- he obviously enjoys her work and refrains from sensationalism. Less astute are his positive comments about the ''period dress'' in ''Love Me or Leave Me'' (historical accuracy not being a Hollywood strength); overuse of phrases like ''right on the money'' and ''first-rate''; and comparisons with Judy Garland and Barbra Streisand. (He is also the author of ''The Importance of Being Barbra.'') Still, ''Considering Doris Day'' includes a comprehensive filmography, a selected discography and many photographs, and covers ground less traveled by traditional biographies. It's an easy read, at times illuminating -- as when Santopietro discusses the ''three-stage cycle'' of ''mass popularity, widespread derision and, years later, a nostalgic embrace of fondly recalled cultural touchstones that evolves into a cultural reassessment.''</p>
        <p>Day is an emblem of sunshine, communion with nature and animals, and common civility. She also symbolizes (more than contemporaries like Debbie Reynolds and Shirley MacLaine) Middle America in the nuclear era, putting a happy face on a not-so-innocent time (on a personal level, this seems an understandable compensation for the domestic violence and betrayal that were part of her private life).</p>
        <p>A surge of nostalgia followed World War II, when a new generation was rebelling against antique customs, good and bad. Rapidly improving technology created a futuristic vision of modern life, and the possibility of annihilation contributed to a yearning for a seemingly simpler time. Day's 1970s television specials feature some charming canine guests but also bear shades of ''Laugh-In'' humor, the slight whiff of Lawrence Welk not entirely cut by Perry Como's quiet diffidence.</p>
        <p>What she possessed, beyond her beauty, physical grace and natural acting ability, was a resplendent voice that conveyed enormous warmth and feeling. Beginning with a sound that resembled the young Ella Fitzgerald's, it deepened, gaining in huskiness and personality to create a timbre distinctly her own. Though Day's songs, heard on more than 600 recordings, range from time capsule to timeless, her humanity always shines through. Her canon combines modern freshness with reassurance. Though pressured to sing novelty tunes, she also covered standards and songs that were atypical for her, like Duke Ellington's ''Mood Indigo'' and Willie Nelson's ''Night Life.'' While the LP ''What Every Girl Should Know'' espouses advice like ''a fellow needs a girl ... to sit by his side and listen to him talk and agree with the things he'll say,'' at least the arrangements -- and the main attraction -- sound lovely.</p>
        <p>If popular wisdom is correct about learning more from bad movies than good, then Doris Day movies are a great place to start. Santopietro knocks ''Send Me No Flowers,'' the last film made with the Day/Rock Hudson/Tony Randall triumvirate, but it wins the most unintentional laughs and offers the campiest subtext -- so by rights it should be a genre classic.</p>
        <p>Although she grew up abhorring prejudice, her output and image (Day has always loathed the very notion of ''image'') were directed at white, segregated (by law or culture) America. Every reference in her movies to ''Injuns,'' ''redskins'' and ''varmints'' makes you wince. In the later comedies there are sequences so offensive -- to women, blacks, the obese, gays, the aged -- they make one gasp. A conceit considered acceptable fun back then, that African art is ugly, is intolerable now.</p>
        <p>Day's ''sophisticated sex comedies'' of the post-McCarthy era continue to be associated with whitewashed cinema. ''Pillow Talk'' is beloved by many but scorned by those who see it as the apolitical low point of an industry that had been smothered by fear (although art is never truly apolitical -- if nothing else, it supports the status quo). It was even directed by the blacklist victim Michael Gordon, his first Hollywood film in eight years.</p>
        <p>Santopietro quotes the critic Will Friedwald: ''Surely no other great American artist ... was so willing to forgo cleverness for the sake of truth.'' Day was the picture of innocence and sweetness as the world entered a new era of inhumanity. She played a character -- herself -- who was honest and straightforward, as doublespeak and duplicity reached new heights of insanity.</p>
        <p>Sexy but not overtly so, successful but not decadent, Day is easy to relate to, kindhearted but no patsy. In a time when cynicism rules, her eager humanity is ever more precious. If her movies seem dated, the lady does not. ''Hooray for Hollywood,'' Doris Day sings, ''where you're terrific if you're even good.'' Lucky for us, this was never a problem. She's terrific through and through.</p>
        <p>Nellie McKay has recorded two albums, ''Get Away From Me'' and ''Pretty Little Head.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Nellie McKay has recorded two albums, ''Get Away From Me'' and ''Pretty Little Head.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
