<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Utility Judgment</title>
    <meta content="03wwln--ethicist.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/magazine/03wwln-ethicist-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851678"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 6-03-07: THE ETHICIST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Transportation Security Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/The Ethicist</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DC1430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Utility Judgment</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Utility Judgment</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Randy Cohen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Randy Cohen Ethicist column comments on whether you may appeal to a utility executive who serves with you on board of nonprofit agency to have one of his company's rotting poles near your house replaced if your use of normal channels has not been fruitful; also comments on whether Transportation Security Administration is right to allow first-class airline passengers to skip to front of security line (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A utility pole behind our garage was rotting and likely to fall, so we notified the utility company. Weeks passed without action. Then my wife, the executive director of a small nonprofit agency, contacted a member of her board, who heads the utility. The pole was replaced within 48 hours. Now my wife feels she did wrong. Did she?</p>
        <p>Michael Grimaldi, Kansas City, Mo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dilemmas involving pole-vaulting and line-jumping.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A utility pole behind our garage was rotting and likely to fall, so we notified the utility company. Weeks passed without action. Then my wife, the executive director of a small nonprofit agency, contacted a member of her board, who heads the utility. The pole was replaced within 48 hours. Now my wife feels she did wrong. Did she?</p>
        <p>Michael Grimaldi, Kansas City, Mo.</p>
        <p>She did. While your wife did not seek to enrich herself and may have even done the community some good by getting the utility to respond to a potential danger, she erred by exploiting her position with the nonprofit for personal advantage. This is cronyism: Those with connections get their poles fixed promptly; those without get to enjoy the spectacle of a tumbling pole, a power outage or, as I, a person with no electrical knowledge, understand it, a lightning bolt that splits the world in twain.</p>
        <p>More discreditable is the conduct of the head of the utility. It is a fine thing for an executive to respond to customer concerns but not so fine to secure better service for his pals than other customers. This fellow abused his position by overriding the ordinary procedures and priorities for repairs, jumping a friend to the head of the line. Work crews should be dispatched according to the gravity of a problem, not the intimacy of a social connection.</p>
        <p>Of course, you can't be certain that this is what happened. The swift repair could have been a belated response to your first call. Or the boss could have discerned its urgency. And that new lotion I (pretend to have) bought could give me a rich luxuriant head of hair.</p>
        <p>I flew out of Denver International Airport shortly after a bad storm and spent three hours in the security line. First-class passengers had no wait because the Transportation Security Administration allowed them to skip to the front of the line. Security costs are shared by the airlines and taxpayers. Should preference be given to first-class passengers?</p>
        <p>Allison Moule, Broomfield, Colo.</p>
        <p>While airlines share the cost of passenger screening, they also share the cost, through their taxes, of state troopers. But when a first-class flier gets a speeding ticket, he is treated like everyone else. Passengers submit to screening as a legal obligation; all should be treated the same. To establish a short line for those who pay more and an endless line for those who pay less violates the spirit of equal treatment under the law -- unlike when an airline provides comfy first-class seats and miserable coach seats, which is not a legal situation (but, rather, a perverse psychological experiment).</p>
        <p>Societies, particularly democratic societies, are built on shared experience, especially in times of crisis, and airport screening is certainly a response to crisis. Even before the draft disappeared, we had long since abandoned the Civil War practice of letting the rich opt out of military service by hiring substitutes. Similarly, the moneyed -- among whom are influential people who helped shape this very policy -- should not be exempt from those exasperatingly long lines.</p>
        <p>If we must have a caste system in America, let's make our brahmins not those with fat wallets but those who give joy to millions. At the Randyland International Airport, Aretha Franklin would sashay through security. The billionaire Wal-Mart Waltons -- Rob, Jim and Alice? We thank you for your patience.</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 6-03-07: THE ETHICIST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
