<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Money or Your Life</title>
    <meta content="Genzlinger2.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/books/review/Genzlinger2-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851607"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Barris, Chuck</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Big Question, The (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E0D61630F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="636" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Money or Your Life</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Money or Your Life</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL GENZLINGER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE BIG QUESTION</p>
        <p>By Chuck Barris.</p>
        <p>277 pp. Simon &amp; Schuster. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The man who gave us shows like “The Newlywed Game” is now channeling his age rage into comic novels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE BIG QUESTION</p>
        <p>By Chuck Barris.</p>
        <p>277 pp. Simon &amp; Schuster. $24.</p>
        <p>Chuck Barris, it appears, is not aging gracefully. This is great news, and not just because there's a kind of pleasure in thinking that the guy who inflicted ''The Newlywed Game'' on the world is spending his late 70s cranky and unfulfilled. No, the real payoff for us is that Barris has been able to channel his age rage, along with his eclectic résumé, into a shamelessly entertaining, if somewhat late-to-the-party, comic novel, ''The Big Question.''</p>
        <p>In case you've forgotten, Barris is the producer who created or helped create not only ''The Newlywed Game'' but also ''The Gong Show,'' ''The Dating Game'' and assorted others, after having had a bit of success as a songwriter. (Freddy Cannon's ''Palisades Park'' may still be stuck in your head if you're old enough.) Oh, and he was also an undercover agent for the C.I.A., or so he said in ''Confessions of a Dangerous Mind,'' a book that may or may not have been an autobiography.</p>
        <p>A pretty clear line connects ''The Gong Show'' and the rest to today's reality-TV explosion, and in ''The Big Question,'' Barris follows that line into the not-too-distant future. It's 2011, assisted suicide is legal and a television producer in need of a hit takes the whole game-show/reality-show thing to its most extreme extreme: he creates a game show in which the finalist will be asked a single $100 million question, with the punishment for a wrong answer being live televised death.</p>
        <p>The life-on-the-line premise isn't particularly new, of course; just ask the lady or the tiger. Barris has been joking about this particular ultimate game show for years, but he waited too long to crank out this book for the idea to be dazzling: against the recent film ''American Cannibal,'' supposedly a documentary of a botched reality show, ''The Big Question'' seems almost quaint. (And are you kidding me with the $100 million grand prize? That's not even a decent Mega Millions jackpot.)</p>
        <p>But it's not the game that makes ''The Big Question'' such a hoot; it's the buildup to it. Four-fifths of the book has gone by before the show goes on the air, and in these pages Barris adds another notch to that goofy résumé of his. Turns out he's an excellent juggler, deftly creating an assortment of eccentrics and misfits who find themselves on paths that converge in the ''Big Question'' greenroom. There's the hillbilly who moves to New York and ends up with a very big gambling debt. There's the petty criminal who becomes a top-dog prison inmate and then an imam. There's a prostitute, a priest, a little old lady. Barris keeps these various balls in the air effortlessly, and everyone gets a rich, colorful back story.</p>
        <p>In among them, Barris awards himself a hilarious extended cameo. Without giving too much away, it is here that we begin to suspect the author/game-show guru/songwriter/</p>
        <p>assassin/juggler is not enjoying the golden years -- that he has turned into a geriatric Archie Bunker. This, for instance, is just a snippet from a lengthy, outrageous rant in which he imagines himself collapsing in the street unnoticed, even though a personal nurse is right there:</p>
        <p>''Why? Because my nurse Begonia or Fantasia or something will be messing around with some hip-hopping dude named Snoop Kitty Ditty or Twelve Dollar 'N Six Cent who just walked up to her and made nice-nice. She'll be playing teasie-weasie with him, not the slightest bit concerned that I'm jerking around in the street like someone being electrocuted. Nor will she care that taxis are swerving this way and that trying not to run over me.''</p>
        <p>If Barris, like his bigoted alter ego, is in fact a bitter old man, he's a darn funny one.</p>
        <p>Neil Genzlinger is a staff editor at The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Neil Genzlinger is a staff editor at The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
