<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Free Your Mind, and Your Spine Will Follow</title>
    <meta content="03joy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/arts/dance/03joy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851695"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cedar Lake Contemporary Ballet</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodwin, Joy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Naharin, Ohad</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Batsheva Dance Company</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Naharin, Ohad</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E4DB1430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1281" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Free Your Mind, and Your Spine Will Follow</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Free Your Mind, and Your Spine Will Follow</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOY GOODWIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodwin, Joy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles Israeli choreographer Ohad Naharin, who is in New York to coach dancers in his work Decadence, which is to be performed by Cedar Lake Contemporary Ballet; Naharin has dancers concentrate on mental imagery rather than looking in mirrors; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ELEVEN hyper-alert dancers stood stock still in a line, fighting the irresistible rhythms of the pulsing Arabic music. Suddenly one erupted in movement, ducking and twisting with astonishing liquid quickness. Then she froze. Down the line a second dancer burst into motion: another spineless creature from the same strange planet. Abruptly the whole line turned sideways and pounded the air with sinuous arms and hard fists, then froze.</p>
        <p>There could be only one explanation: Ohad Naharin was back in town. There he stood, watching the rehearsal in cargo pants and a plaid hoodie, his eyeglasses swinging from a lanyard around his neck. Unshaved and wild-haired, his serious gaze fixed on the scene before him, he looked like a cross between a holy man and an aging skateboarder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At Batsheva Dance Company, dancers operate not from the mirror but from the gut.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ELEVEN hyper-alert dancers stood stock still in a line, fighting the irresistible rhythms of the pulsing Arabic music. Suddenly one erupted in movement, ducking and twisting with astonishing liquid quickness. Then she froze. Down the line a second dancer burst into motion: another spineless creature from the same strange planet. Abruptly the whole line turned sideways and pounded the air with sinuous arms and hard fists, then froze.</p>
        <p>There could be only one explanation: Ohad Naharin was back in town. There he stood, watching the rehearsal in cargo pants and a plaid hoodie, his eyeglasses swinging from a lanyard around his neck. Unshaved and wild-haired, his serious gaze fixed on the scene before him, he looked like a cross between a holy man and an aging skateboarder.</p>
        <p>Motioning to an assistant to stop the music, Mr. Naharin, 54, loped over to the dancers, his perennially untied shoelaces slapping the floor. ''It feels a little soft,'' he said in a low voice. The dancers nodded, rapt. ''We need to find the explosiveness.'' To demonstrate he flung his body into two rapid-fire leaps: the first floppy, like a crash-test dummy, the second bracingly sharp.</p>
        <p>Mr. Naharin (pronounced nah-hah-REEN), the choreographer and artistic director of Batsheva Dance Company of Tel Aviv, was in New York to coach the dancers of the Cedar Lake Contemporary Ballet in his ''Decadance,'' an evening length work. (It opens on Thursday at Cedar Lake's home theater, 547 West 26th Street in Chelsea.) Mr. Naharin is new to Cedar Lake, the repertory company founded and financed by the Wal-Mart heiress Nancy Walton Laurie in 2002, but he is no stranger to New York.</p>
        <p>Born and raised in Israel, Mr. Naharin first came to Manhattan in 1975, after Martha Graham plucked him -- a 23-year-old fresh out of the military -- from the junior ranks of Batsheva to study with her. He received much of his training in New York, at the Graham school, the School of American Ballet and Juilliard, and danced with Graham's company for a season. Here, in 1978, he married the Alvin Ailey dancer Mari Kajiwara, a native New Yorker, who died of cancer in 2001 at 50. And it was here that he choreographed and presented his first dances, from 1980 to 1990, when he left to lead Batsheva.</p>
        <p>Charla Genn, a New York ballet teacher who has known Mr. Naharin since the 1970s, still recalls his ''unique way of moving'' in his dancing days. ''It was almost as though he had no spine,'' she said. ''He was like an amoeba. To me what's been amazing over the years is how he's been able to get other dancers to move like him.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Naharin's signature style -- distinguished by stunningly flexible limbs and spines, deeply grounded movement, explosive bursts and a vitality that grabs a viewer by the collar -- has taken shape during his 17 years at Batsheva. Under his watch the reputation of the company, founded in 1964 by Graham and the Baroness Bethsabée (Batsheva) de Rothschild, has steadily grown. Over the last decade Mr. Naharin has garnered dozens of prestigious commissions and coveted festival invitations and back-to-back Bessie Awards (in 2002 and 2003).</p>
        <p>Nigel Redden, who has presented Mr. Naharin's work at both the Spoleto Festival U.S.A. in Charleston, S.C., and the Lincoln Center Festival in the last 12 months, places him in ''a rarefied group'' of the world's foremost modern-dance choreographers.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Naharin has staged ''Decadance'' for companies other than his own, he says he has never received an offer like the one Cedar Lake made last year: three months of rehearsal, license to retrain the company's dancers and 24 performances of his signature work.</p>
        <p>''Usually when I work with another company, the time is shorter, and there's a bigger adjustment of my work to the dancers' habits,'' he said recently, during a rehearsal break. ''But here there is a unique opportunity to have my movement language become theirs. It's about changing habits and learning new ones. And we have the time, the talent, the desire to do it.''</p>
        <p>The generosity of the offer was typical of Cedar Lake, whose resources include a stable of highly trained dancers with 52-week contracts and two spacious, light-filled studios on the western edge of Chelsea, which once belonged to the photographer Annie Leibovitz. Yet its pristine rehearsal studio has been without mirrors since the day in late March that Mr. Naharin's assistants arrived and covered them up.</p>
        <p>''We had no mirror,'' said Heather Hamilton, a company member. ''No mirror! In ballet, you spend hours correcting yourself in the mirror. Now you can't judge yourself.''</p>
        <p>After a lifetime of mornings at the barre Cedar Lake's ballet-trained dancers found themselves warming up in ''Gaga'' class, Mr. Naharin's set of guided exercises designed to move dancers away from critiquing themselves and into the world of sensations and freedom. Dancers operate not from the mirror but from the gut.</p>
        <p>Imagery -- say, the suggestion of rubbing oil into the skin -- stimulates the imagination. Dancers are encouraged to explore their weaknesses and break old movement habits. Other exercises focus on the placement of the body in space and developing sensitivity to the energy of the dancers nearby. The goal, Mr. Naharin said, is to connect dancers to ''pleasure and effort, madness and demons, to all the things that really create an interesting performer.'' The kind of performer, he might add, that makes a potent vessel for his very specific body language.</p>
        <p>During a rehearsal last month he noted the changes in Cedar Lake's dancers, who had been immersed in Gaga for seven weeks. ''They become more efficient and more free,'' he said. ''I see a more intimate relationship with their bodies. I feel more the animal that they are.''</p>
        <p>The changes were technical too. Lifelong ballet dancers dug their knees and feet into the earth, rose up in the air and came down flat-footed. In his quiet way Mr. Naharin gave corrections: never angry, never critical, yet in utter command of the room. ''Make sure you connect to the sensation and not to showing a picture,'' he told the group. ''Relax your jaw. A little bit of space between your lips. Feel that?''</p>
        <p>They did. ''The whole attitude changes,'' he said. ''It's more alive.''</p>
        <p>Though he asks dancers to tap into strong emotions, his voice is calm and circumspect, his demeanor closed. He is, his associates say, a very private person. He seldom discusses the death of his wife, who worked alongside him in rehearsals for more than 20 years, though its effects on him have been profound. In 2002 he stepped down as Batsheva's artistic director for a time, serving solely as its choreographer for two years, during which he made the sober, intimate ''Mamootot,'' seen in 2005 at the Brooklyn Academy of Music.</p>
        <p>''I'm sure it must have been very distressing to go on without her,'' Ms. Genn said. ''The truth of the matter is that he's a great choreographer, and he has been able to continue.''</p>
        <p>''Decadance,'' which combines Mr. Naharin's past and present, is a remix of strongly flavored excerpts from his work. The piece has had many incarnations; this time the fragments cover two decades of his output, painstakingly reworked by Mr. Naharin.</p>
        <p>The rehearsal suggested the scope of Mr. Naharin's imagination, from a go-go party danced to the theme from ''Hawaii Five-O'' to a romantic, hushed duet set to Vivaldi.</p>
        <p>Benoit-Swan Pouffer, Cedar Lake's artistic director, looked on, mesmerized, as his dancers moved with newly liquid spinesand sharp intentions.</p>
        <p>''It's something about the connection, the way they look at each other,'' he said. ''It just grabs you, and the emotion comes out of you.''</p>
        <p>DANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
