<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BEST SELLERS: June 03, 2006</title>
    <meta content="Besthard.fiction" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="54" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851594"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E1D61630F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1279" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BEST SELLERS: June 03, 2006</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended May 19, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>Editor's Choice  Other ecent books of particular interest</p>
        <p>THE OCCUPATION OF IRAQ: Winning the War, Losing the Peace, by Ali A. Allawi. (Yale University, $28.) Iraq's former defense minister tries to pinpoint the role of the country's new political class in shaping the catastrophe there.</p>
        <p>THE LIZARD CAGE, by Karen Connelly. (Nan A. Talese/Doubleday, $26.) Connelly's novel bares a Burmese political prisoner's innermost self.</p>
        <p>THE SEA LADY: A Late Romance, by Margaret Drabble. (Harcourt, $24.) After 30 years of shunning each other, an estranged couple meet again.</p>
        <p>VARIETIES OF DISTURBANCE: Stories, by Lydia Davis. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, paper, $13.) Dispensing with straight narrative, Davis microscopically examines language and thought.</p>
        <p>THE CANON: A Whirligig Tour of the Beautiful Basics of Science, by Natalie Angier. (Houghton Mifflin, $27.) A journalist surveys the fundamentals she believes educated people should master.</p>
        <p>CITY OF ORANGES: An Intimate History of Arabs and Jews in Jaffa, by Adam LeBor. (Norton, paper, $14.95.) Jaffa from the perspective of a half-dozen clans intertwined in peace and conflict.</p>
        <p>FLIGHT, by Sherman Alexie. (Black Cat/Grove/Atlantic, paper, $13.) A troubled teenager time-travels to hot spots in American Indian history.</p>
        <p>THE DEVIL IN THE KITCHEN: Sex, Pain, Madness, and the Making of a Great Chef, by Marco Pierre White with James Steen. (Bloomsbury, $24.95.) A British bad boy's moving memoir.</p>
        <p>THE LAST TYCOONS: The Secret History of Lazard FrÃ</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended May 19, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>Editor's Choice  Other ecent books of particular interest</p>
        <p>THE OCCUPATION OF IRAQ: Winning the War, Losing the Peace, by Ali A. Allawi. (Yale University, $28.) Iraq's former defense minister tries to pinpoint the role of the country's new political class in shaping the catastrophe there.</p>
        <p>THE LIZARD CAGE, by Karen Connelly. (Nan A. Talese/Doubleday, $26.) Connelly's novel bares a Burmese political prisoner's innermost self.</p>
        <p>THE SEA LADY: A Late Romance, by Margaret Drabble. (Harcourt, $24.) After 30 years of shunning each other, an estranged couple meet again.</p>
        <p>VARIETIES OF DISTURBANCE: Stories, by Lydia Davis. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, paper, $13.) Dispensing with straight narrative, Davis microscopically examines language and thought.</p>
        <p>THE CANON: A Whirligig Tour of the Beautiful Basics of Science, by Natalie Angier. (Houghton Mifflin, $27.) A journalist surveys the fundamentals she believes educated people should master.</p>
        <p>CITY OF ORANGES: An Intimate History of Arabs and Jews in Jaffa, by Adam LeBor. (Norton, paper, $14.95.) Jaffa from the perspective of a half-dozen clans intertwined in peace and conflict.</p>
        <p>FLIGHT, by Sherman Alexie. (Black Cat/Grove/Atlantic, paper, $13.) A troubled teenager time-travels to hot spots in American Indian history.</p>
        <p>THE DEVIL IN THE KITCHEN: Sex, Pain, Madness, and the Making of a Great Chef, by Marco Pierre White with James Steen. (Bloomsbury, $24.95.) A British bad boy's moving memoir.</p>
        <p>THE LAST TYCOONS: The Secret History of Lazard FrÃ</p>
        <p>05,05,06,64</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  Last  On</p>
        <p>Week  Week  List  FICTION</p>
        <p>1  2  1  THE 6TH TARGET, by James Patterson and Maxine Paetro. (Little, Brown, $27.99.) In San Francisco, children and their nannies are disappearing, and Detective Lindsay Boxer and the Women's Murder Club investigate.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>1  BAD LUCK AND TROUBLE, by Lee Child. (Delacorte, $26.) Jack Reacher must discover who is hunting down members of a team of former military investigators.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>1  INVISIBLE PREY, by John Sandford. (Putnam, $26.95.) The Minneapolis detective Lucas Davenport finds connections between the murder of several elderly residents and a political scandal.</p>
        <p>4  3  3  THE YIDDISH POLICEMEN'S UNION, by Michael Chabon. (HarperCollins, $26.95.) A detective investigates a neighbor's murder in a Jewish settlement in Alaska.</p>
        <p>5  2  4  SIMPLE GENIUS, by David Baldacci. (Warner, $26.99.) Two former Secret Service agents investigate a scientist's murder while one battles her own demons.</p>
        <p>6  4  5  THE CHILDREN OF HÃRIN, by J. R. R. Tolkien. Edited by Christopher Tolkien. Illustrated by Alan Lee. (Houghton Mifflin, $26.) In Middle-earth, an evil lord wants to destroy his rival's children.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>1  Pearl Harbor, by Newt Gingrich and William R. Forstchen. (Thomas Dunne, $25.95.) The buildup to the historic attack, with an alternative ending.</p>
        <p>8  7  3  RANT, by Chuck Palahniuk. (Doubleday, $24.95.) The ''oral biography'' of a serial killer.</p>
        <p>9  6  5  THE WOODS, by Harlan Coben. (Dutton, $26.95.) A prosecutor must confront family secrets when new evidence surfaces about a murder and disappearance at a summer camp 20 years earlier.</p>
        <p>10  8  11  NINETEEN MINUTES, by Jodi Picoult. (Atria, $26.95.) The aftermath of a high school shooting reveals the fault lines in a small New Hampshire town.</p>
        <p>11  5  7  I HEARD THAT SONG BEFORE, by Mary Higgins Clark. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $25.95.) A woman marries a childhood acquaintance suspected of several murders.</p>
        <p>12  12  4  BODY SURFING, by Anita Shreve. (Little, Brown, $25.99.) A woman takes a job as a tutor and becomes involved in a wealthy family's tensions and rivalries.</p>
        <p>13*  9  5  THE GOOD HUSBAND OF ZEBRA DRIVE, by Alexander McCall Smith. (Pantheon, $21.95.) The eighth novel in the No. 1 Ladies' Detective Agency series.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>1  THE QUEST, by Wilbur Smith. (Thomas Dunne, $27.95.) In ancient Egypt, a magus searches for the cause of a series of plagues.</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>1  FALLING MAN, by Don DeLillo. (Scribner, $26.) The effect of 9/11 on a middle-class Manhattan family.</p>
        <p>16*  13  3  ALL TOGETHER DEAD, by Charlaine Harris. (Ace, $24.95.) Sookie Stackhouse, a New Orleans cocktail waitress, is swept up in the intrigue of a vampire summit.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  Last  On</p>
        <p>Week  Week  List  NONFICTION</p>
        <p>1  4  3  GOD IS NOT GREAT, by Christopher Hitchens. (Twelve, $24.99.) Religion as a malignant force in the world.</p>
        <p>2  1  6  EINSTEIN, by Walter Isaacson. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $32.) A biography based on newly released personal letters.</p>
        <p>3  5  3  ANIMAL, VEGETABLE, MIRACLE, by Barbara Kingsolver with Steven L. Hopp and Camille Kingsolver. (HarperCollins, $26.95.) The novelist and her family spend a year eating homegrown or local food; an argument for diversified farms and sustainable agriculture.</p>
        <p>4*</p>
        <p>1  PLATO and A PLATYPUS WALK INTO A BAR, by Thomas Cathcart and Daniel Klein. (Abrams Image, $18.95.) A humorous tour of philosophical traditions.</p>
        <p>5  6  14  A LONG WAY GONE, by Ishmael Beah. (Sarah Crichton/Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $22.) A former child soldier from Sierra Leone describes his drug-crazed killing spree and his return to humanity.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>1  JESUS OF NAZARETH, by Benedict XVI. (Doubleday, $24.95.) The pope discusses Jesus' identity as revealed in the Gospels.</p>
        <p>7*  9  2  PRESIDENTIAL COURAGE, by Michael Beschloss. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $28.) Profiles of nine presidents who had the courage to make unpopular decisions.</p>
        <p>8  2  3  AT THE CENTER OF THE STORM, by George Tenet. (HarperCollins, $30.) The former director of the Central Intelligence Agency looks back on his career.</p>
        <p>9  7  5  WHERE HAVE ALL THE LEADERS GONE?, by Lee Iacocca. (Scribner, $25.) The former C.E.O. of Chrysler protests the lack of political and business leadership on issues like health care and energy policy.</p>
        <p>10  12  2  TALES FROM Q SCHOOL, by John Feinstein. (Little, Brown, $26.99.) Inside the 2005 PGA Tour Qualifying Tournament, which determines whether a golfer will have a slot on the PGA Tour, from the author of ''A Good Walk Spoiled.''</p>
        <p>11  3  7  PAULA DEEN: IT AIN'T ALL ABOUT THE COOKIN', by Paula Deen with Sherry Suib Cohen. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $25.) A memoir with recipes from the Southern cooking impresario (Food Network shows, restaurants, cookbooks, magazine).</p>
        <p>12  14  10  HOW DOCTORS THINK, by Jerome Groopman. (Houghton Mifflin, $26.) A doctor and New Yorker staff writer describes how doctors arrive at diagnoses.</p>
        <p>13  11  4  THE BLACK SWAN, by Nassim Nicholas Taleb. (Random House, $26.95.) The role of the unexpected.</p>
        <p>14  8  42  I FEEL BAD ABOUT MY NECK, by Nora Ephron. (Knopf, $19.95.) A witty look at aging from a novelist and screenwriter (''When Harry Met Sally'').</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>1  RICKLES' BOOK, by Don Rickles with David Ritz. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $24.) A memoir by the insult comedian.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
