<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Let Them In, or Send Them Back?</title>
    <meta content="l03immig" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851954"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E0DF1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="863" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Let Them In, or Send Them Back?</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Make a Bad Bill Better'' (editorial, May 29):</p>
        <p>There is another argument for a more constructive approach to those currently in the United States illegally.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Make a Bad Bill Better'' (editorial, May 29):</p>
        <p>There is another argument for a more constructive approach to those currently in the United States illegally.</p>
        <p>As a fairly new American, I hugely admire the determination, optimism and drive that are part of the American character. I have come to realize that at least one reason for these characteristics is that the immigrants who came, whether legally or illegally, suffered extreme hardships to get here and often lived in appalling conditions while they worked hard to give their children opportunities in this new world.</p>
        <p>Aren't some of our current illegal immigrants of the same cloth? They are optimistic and determined, hard workers who will suffer any hardship and uncertainty to achieve some opportunities for themselves and their children.</p>
        <p>Maybe these are exactly the sort of people that the United States needs.</p>
        <p>Linda Senat  New York, May 30, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Where is the fairness to those immigrants who play by the rules to come here, often waiting as long as 10 years for a visa to become available?</p>
        <p>Can anyone seriously believe that the proposed bill will alleviate the problem, rather than aggravate it?</p>
        <p>In 1986, this country passed immigration reform legislation because deporting two million illegal immigrants was deemed ''impractical.'' Now we're facing 12 million illegal immigrants who probably came here encouraged by our abject failure to enforce our laws.</p>
        <p>What will it be in 2027? Fifty million? Then what?</p>
        <p>The message must be clearly and unequivocally conveyed: The United States will not reward those who have broken the law. Period.</p>
        <p>Vaughn A. Carney  Stowe, Vt., May 29, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Bush Calls Attacks on Immigration Bill 'Empty Political Rhetoric' '' (news article, May 30):</p>
        <p>''If you want to scare the American people, what you say is the bill's an amnesty bill,'' President Bush said on Tuesday. ''That's empty political rhetoric trying to frighten our citizens.''</p>
        <p>Despite the irony of Mr. Bush's remarks -- for who knows better than he how to frighten our citizens with empty political rhetoric -- he happens to be right on this one.</p>
        <p>The immigration bill has serious flaws, especially those aspects of it that prevent family unification and its unrealistic requirements with respect to temporary workers, but at least it puts to rest the foolish talk of sending about 12 million people back to where they came from.</p>
        <p>The bill deserves the support of the American people.</p>
        <p>John A. Viteritti  Southold, N.Y., May 30, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''America the Generous: A Lost Story of Citizenship,'' by Lawrence Downes (Editorial Observer, May 27): When my four grandparents immigrated to this country, every immigrant who was in good health was granted admission at Ellis Island.</p>
        <p>Today their grandchildren are making important contributions to our country. Among us are one cardiologist, one Ph.D. researcher, two teachers and two business people.</p>
        <p>The energy, motivation, talent and intelligence that immigrants bring to our shores did not end with my grandparents and their progeny. Two years ago my mother's life was saved by a brilliant, committed geriatrician -- who was also a new American citizen of Indian birth.</p>
        <p>When we say no to those who are willing to give up their homes, extended families and languages to join us in this great adventure called America, we cut ourselves off from an incredibly vital source of renewal. It is that renewal which is at the core of our greatness as a nation.</p>
        <p>Denise Gelberg  Ithaca, N.Y., May 27, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Lawrence Downes doesn't address one important difference between the America of, say, 1900 and the America of 2007: the population of the United States in 1900 was around 76 million, while it is now more than 300 million.</p>
        <p>America is no longer a sparsely populated country in need of more workers to exploit our abundant natural resources. We have all the population our resources can comfortably support, and then some.</p>
        <p>Immigration cannot solve our economic problems indefinitely. Someday Americans will have to learn to harvest our own food, paint our own houses, care for our own children and do our own landscaping, because it will be impossible to import others to do those things for us.</p>
        <p>Why not now, while there is still room to breathe?</p>
        <p>Richard Hussong  Groton, Mass., May 27, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Wide Disparities Found in Judging of Asylum Cases'' (front page, May 31):</p>
        <p>The immigration judge is not necessarily the main factor in the outcome of an asylum case. The process can also depend on other elements, such as the competence of the lawyer for the asylum-seeker.</p>
        <p>During the course of appeals I handled in the period studied by the research you describe, the transcripts were replete with serious lapses by the lawyers involved, so that clear winners became inevitable losers.</p>
        <p>There were even instances where clients were actually hurt by their own lawyer.</p>
        <p>Clearly, true justice -- in the immigration court, as well as elsewhere -- results only when all parties, not just the judges, perform at their most competent level.</p>
        <p>Nicholas A. F. Arena  New York, May 31, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
