<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Word for Word | They'll Say Anything; Soviet-Style 'Torture' Becomes 'Interrogation' in the War on Terror</title>
    <meta content="03shane" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/weekinreview/03shane.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070610T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851967"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Word for Word | Theyll Say Anything"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Stress (Human)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stress (Human)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stress (Human)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E7DE1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Word for Word | They'll Say Anything; Soviet-Style 'Torture' Becomes 'Interrogation' in the War on Terror</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Soviet-Style ‘Torture’ Becomes ‘Interrogation’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SCOTT SHANE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOW did the United States, in the aftermath of the 9/11 attacks, come to adopt interrogation techniques copied from the Soviet Union and other cold war adversaries?</p>
        <p>Investigators for the Senate Armed Services Committee are examining how the methods, long used to train Americans for what they may face as prisoners of war, became the basis for American interrogations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 1956 article, “Communist Interrogation,” shows that methods embraced after 2001 were once considered torture that would produce false information.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOW did the United States, in the aftermath of the 9/11 attacks, come to adopt interrogation techniques copied from the Soviet Union and other cold war adversaries?</p>
        <p>Investigators for the Senate Armed Services Committee are examining how the methods, long used to train Americans for what they may face as prisoners of war, became the basis for American interrogations.</p>
        <p>In 2002, the C.I.A. and the Pentagon became concerned that standard questioning was inadequate for suspected terrorists and turned to a military training program called Survival, Evasion, Reconnaissance and Escape, or SERE. For decades, SERE trainers had exposed aviators and others at high risk for capture to Soviet-style tactics, including disrupted sleep, exposure to extreme heat and cold, and hours in uncomfortable stress positions. Sometimes the ordeal included waterboarding, in which a prisoner's face is covered with cloth and water is poured from above to create a feeling of suffocation.</p>
        <p>Some of those techniques have been used on prisoners at Guantánamo Bay and in Afghanistan and Iraq, and at the C.I.A.'s secret overseas jails for high-level operatives of Al Qaeda.</p>
        <p>Many SERE veterans were appalled at the ''reverse engineering'' of their methods, said Charles A. Morgan III, a Yale psychiatrist who has worked closely with SERE trainers for a decade.</p>
        <p>''How did something used as an example of what an unethical government would do become something we do?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>His question is only underscored by a 1956 article, ''Communist Interrogation,'' in The Annals of Neurology and Psychology, recently turned up by the Intelligence Science Board, which advises the spy agencies. Written by doctors working as Defense Department consultants, Lawrence E. Hinkle Jr. and Harold G. Wolff, the article shows that methods embraced after 2001 were once considered torture that would produce false information.</p>
        <p>SCOTT SHANE</p>
        <p>The article describes basic Soviet N.K.V.D. (later K.G.B.) methods: isolation in a small cell; constant light; sleep deprivation; cold or heat; reduced food rations. Soviets denied such treatment was torture, just as American officials have in recent years:</p>
        <p>The effects of isolation, anxiety, fatigue, lack of sleep, uncomfortable temperatures, and chronic hunger produce disturbances of mood, attitudes and behavior in nearly all prisoners. The living organism cannot entirely withstand such assaults. The Communists do not look upon these assaults as ''torture.'' But all of them produce great discomfort, and lead to serious disturbances of many bodily processes; there is no reason to differentiate them from any other form of torture.Interrogators looked for ways to increase the pressure, including ''stress positions'':</p>
        <p>Another [technique] widely used is that of requiring the prisoner to stand throughout the interrogation session or to maintain some other physical position which becomes painful. This, like other features of the KGB procedure, is a form of physical torture, in spite of the fact that the prisoners and KGB officers alike do not ordinarily perceive it as such. Any fixed position which is maintained over a long period of time ultimately produces excruciating pain. Overt brutality was discouraged, as it was at American facilities:</p>
        <p>The KGB hardly ever uses manacles or chains, and rarely resorts to physical beatings. The actual physical beating is, of course, repugnant to overt Communist principles and is contrary to K.G.B. regulations. Closed trials and military tribunals were standard, as at Guantánamo:</p>
        <p>Prisoners are tried before ''military tribunals,'' which are not public courts. Those present are only the interrogator, the state prosecutor, the prisoner, the judges, a few stenographers, and perhaps a few officers of the court. The Bush administration concluded that the Geneva Conventions did not apply to Qaeda detainees. Similarly, the Soviets argued that international rules did not apply to foreign detainees:</p>
        <p>In typical Communist legalistic fashion, the N.K.V.D. rationalized its use of torture and pressure in the interrogation of prisoners of war. When it desired to use such methods against a prisoner or to obtain from him a propaganda statement or ''confession,'' it simply declared the prisoner a ''war-crimes uspect'' and informed him that, therefore, he was not subject to international rules governing the treatment of prisoners of war. Communist-style interrogation routinely produced false confessions:</p>
        <p>The cumulative effects of the entire experience may be almost intolerable. [The prisoner] becomes mentally dull and loses his capacity for discrimination. He becomes malleable and suggestible, and in some instances he may confabulate. By suggesting that the prisoner accept half-truths and plausible distortions of the truth, [the interrogator] makes it possible for the prisoner to rationalize and thus accept the interrogator's viewpoint as the only way out of an intolerable situation.</p>
        <p>Word for Word | Theyll Say Anything</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 10, 2007, Sunday  The Word for Word article last Sunday excerpting a 1956 medical journal article on Communist interrogation methods misstated the name of the journal. It is The Archives of Neurology and Psychiatry, not The Annals of Neurology and Psychology. In addition, the meaning of the acronym SERE, an American military training program, was misstated. SERE stands for Survival, Evasion, Resistance, and Escape -- not Survival, Evasion, Reconnaissance and Escape.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 10, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>The Word for Word article last Sunday excerpting a 1956 medical journal article on Communist interrogation methods misstated the name of the journal. It is The Archives of Neurology and Psychiatry, not The Annals of Neurology and Psychology. In addition, the meaning of the acronym SERE, an American military training program, was misstated. SERE stands for Survival, Evasion, Resistance, and Escape -- not Survival, Evasion, Reconnaissance and Escape.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
