<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Tonys' All-Star Lineup</title>
    <meta content="03bran" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/theater/theaterspecial/03bran.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851715"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER: THE TONYS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schreiber, Liev</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gaines, Boyd</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Langella, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Plummer, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Byrne, Brian F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Tony Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Schreiber, Liev</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Langella, Frank</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Plummer, Christopher</person>
        <person class="online_producer">O'Byrne, Brian F</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gaines, Boyd</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E2DB1430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1286" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Tonys' All-Star Lineup</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Leading Men Lead the Field: Five Riveting Performances Make for a Stiff Competition</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley article on five Tony Award nominees for best actor - Liev Schreiber, Boyd Gaines, Frank Langella, Christopher Plummer and Brian F O'Byrne; discusses why their performances are so good; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A WALL of smoke separates Barry Champlain from anyone who might get close to him. The wall is erected eight times a week by Liev Schreiber, whose brilliant, chain-smoking performance as Barry, the antagonistic shock jock in the Broadway revival of Eric Bogosian's ''Talk Radio,'' is the best argument going for the continued existence of cigarettes.</p>
        <p>For if Barry's touch-me-not nicotine haze keeps would-be friends and lovers at a distance, it allows theatergoers to zoom right in on him. What Barry uses to hide behind becomes, for Mr. Schreiber, a means of illuminating the character he's playing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>By my capricious reckoning you would have to reach back to 1974 to find a comparably competitive and crowded lineup for the Tony Award for best actor in a play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A WALL of smoke separates Barry Champlain from anyone who might get close to him. The wall is erected eight times a week by Liev Schreiber, whose brilliant, chain-smoking performance as Barry, the antagonistic shock jock in the Broadway revival of Eric Bogosian's ''Talk Radio,'' is the best argument going for the continued existence of cigarettes.</p>
        <p>For if Barry's touch-me-not nicotine haze keeps would-be friends and lovers at a distance, it allows theatergoers to zoom right in on him. What Barry uses to hide behind becomes, for Mr. Schreiber, a means of illuminating the character he's playing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schreiber, who is up for a Tony for best actor this year, has some stiff competition in the art of using smoke screens. Frank Langella, the man most likely to beat him, provides a stunning, intricately layered portrait of one of the all-time masters of obfuscation, Richard M. Nixon, in Peter Morgan's ''Frost/Nixon.'' And Christopher Plummer, a veteran of nearly six decades on the stage, dissects a great bamboozler in virtuoso style, playing (but of course) a grandstanding lawyer in the revival of Jerome Lawrence and Robert E. Lee's ''Inherit the Wind.''</p>
        <p>Using the actor's tricks of dissimulation to uncover a character's tricks of dissimulation, conscious or unwitting, is a magic act that only the most skilled prestidigitators can pull off. But it has happened again and again during this Broadway season, the richest in recent memory for multidimensional performances by leading men. While the Tony nominating committee had to scramble to fill some categories (including best revival of a musical and, surprisingly, best actress in a play), that of best actor is notable for its omissions.</p>
        <p>By my capricious reckoning you would have to reach back to 1974 -- when Zero Mostel, Jason Robards, George C. Scott and Nicol Williamson went up against Michael Moriarty (who won, for ''Find Your Way Home'') -- to find a comparably competitive and crowded lineup.</p>
        <p>In addition to Mr. Schreiber, Mr. Langella and Mr. Plummer, the roster of nominees this year includes the eminently worthy Brian F. O'Byrne (for Tom Stoppard's three-part ''Coast of Utopia'') and Boyd Gaines (in the revival of R. C. Sherriff's ''Journey's End''). But Hugh Dancy (Mr. Gaines's co-star in ''Journey's End''), Michael Sheen (who plays the television interviewer David Frost to Mr. Langella's Nixon) and Bill Nighy, of David Hare's ''Vertical Hour,'' definitely deserve to be contenders.</p>
        <p>What these men share is an ability to project not only a bravura surface but also a sense of what lies beneath that contradicts and eats away at the formal show of personality. Whether brash and noisy (like Mr. Schreiber's radio host) or strong and silent (like Mr. Gaines's British World War I lieutenant), these are all palimpsest portraits, which allow us to glimpse the tracery of nerves beneath the solid flesh.</p>
        <p>Mr. Langella and Mr. Schreiber offer the flashiest and most immediately gripping versions of this paradox. As Nixon, Mr. Langella faces the greater challenge, playing a man who has inspired more caricatures and impersonations than perhaps any American president. He has to embrace living memories of Nixon and his interpreters while staking a claim for his own original version.</p>
        <p>Cleverly Mr. Langella avoids Rich Little-style facsimile, going instead for heightened traits that suggest equivalents to Nixon's most conspicuous qualities (smoggy voice, stooped shoulders) without replicating them. This actor's real genius is in how he uses exaggeration to anatomize a man for whom outer image and inner self were finally indistinguishable.</p>
        <p>The levels of consciousness (and self-consciousness) that Mr. Langella packs into his performance are astonishing. He gives us a Nixon whose insecurity is matched only by his intelligence. And in the show's mesmerizing centerpiece, a drunken late-night telephone call made by Nixon to Frost, Mr. Langella shows us a man of ravening anger and self-pity who also uses those emotions as instruments of manipulation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schreiber's Barry is also a smart fellow, too smart to be doing what he's doing without some serious self-anesthetizing. A confrontational late-night radio host with a God complex, Barry has created an artificial construct called Barry Champlain. He achieves this with the aid of microphones, assorted stimulants and depressants and those clouds of smoke with which he creates his own isolation chamber. He's a self-poisoning Wizard of Oz.</p>
        <p>It's the sheer physicality of Mr. Schreiber's Barry that hijacks the audience. The Olympian Barry is repeatedly pulled to earth by such mortal irritants as nasal congestion and acid reflux. His amplified voice may sound like it comes from Mount Sinai, but his skin assumes the blotchy pallor of an all-too-frail human. Body and soul (or superego) are clearly out of sync.</p>
        <p>Mr. Plummer doesn't have the same depths to probe in ''Inherit the Wind,'' the glib 1955 drama inspired by the Scopes ''monkey'' trial. His character, Henry Drummond, modeled on the legend-wreathed lawyer Clarence Darrow, is shaped by the conventional dramatic formula of a superficially cynical man with a hero's conscience (''an atheist who believes in God,'' as another character disdainfully puts it).</p>
        <p>But the wily Mr. Plummer milks every ounce of psychological tension from this dichotomy. He uses Drummond's gaudy suspenders the way Mr. Schreiber uses cigarettes: They're the most conspicuous weapon in his diversionary arsenal. When he snaps and stretches those bright braces, he is the essence of the lawyer as strutting actor.</p>
        <p>But as with Mr. Schreiber, Mr. Plummer makes us aware of the gravitational pull of the physical being behind the professional performer, and he uses it to signal a spiritual unease within Drummond. This lawyer feels the heat of the courtroom and the aches of old age, which start to seem like correlatives for a moral disgust with a part he has played for too long.</p>
        <p>Lieutenant Osborne, Mr. Gaines's character in the superlative production of ''Journey's End'' (a show Broadway theatergoers have foolishly resisted embracing), is a painfully familiar type. He's the middle-class Briton with the stiff upper lip; a good, solid chap who responds to crisis by drawing thoughtfully on his trusty pipe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gaines, though, obviates parody by carefully underlining Osborne's stoicism with a steady pulse of fear, as he and his fellow soldiers await orders for battle in a trench. His eyes betray an anxiety that we can see, even though his comrades cannot. It's a performance of eloquent minimalism and the perfect center for a play that finds its most potent shades of emotion in silence.</p>
        <p>As intense as all of the above-described performances are, surely none among those nominated for Tonys is as physically taxing as was Mr. O'Byrne's. Playing the Russian writer Alexander Herzen in ''The Coast of Utopia,'' Mr. Stoppard's sweeping portrait of 19th-century Russian intellectuals with revolutionary dreams, Mr. O'Byrne had to take his character from youth to the cusp of old age through three separate plays that together consume close to nine hours of stage time.</p>
        <p>Audience members who did not see all three installments of ''Utopia'' will be unable to appreciate fully the marvel of Mr. O'Byrne. He conveyed the physical processes of aging so subtly that you acknowledged them without even realizing it.</p>
        <p>Even more important, though, in a play about the gap between idealistic theory and the waywardness of human nature, were the spiritual weariness and exasperation that overtook Mr. O'Byrne's Herzen. By the trilogy's end he had the slightly stunned look of a man whose hopeful thoughts have run up again and again against the brick wall that is real life.</p>
        <p>In this sense Mr. O'Byrne demonstrated the same principle of great acting as his fellow nominees. Getting the bright externals of a character is easy for a good craftsman. It's the shadowy contradictions between outer and inner that distinguish craft from art.</p>
        <p>THEATER: THE TONYS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
