<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Post-Lawsuit Yonkers, the City's Landlord Is Center Stage</title>
    <meta content="03peopleweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03peoplewe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851776"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC HOUSING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yonkers (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Assn for the Advancement of Colored People</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shuldiner, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gruen, Abby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Landlords</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landlords</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Yonkers (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E2DD1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="796" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Post-Lawsuit Yonkers, the City's Landlord Is Center Stage</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Post-Lawsuit Yonkers, the City’s Landlord Is Center Stage</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GRUEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gruen, Abby</byline>
      <dateline>YONKERS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of and interview with Joseph Shuldiner, 62, executive director of Yonkers (NY) Municipal Housing Authority; city's 27-year lawsuit with National Assn for the Advancement of Colored People over segregationist policies was finally resolved in May and city has begun $180 million urban-renewal project; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT 62, Joseph Shuldiner is an unlikely landlord. A tenant advocate in his 20s and 30s, he had rented his whole life until moving into his own home for the first time this year after taking over as executive director of the Yonkers Municipal Housing Authority.</p>
        <p>Now, he is one of the city's most influential landlords, responsible for more than 4,000 public housing and rent-subsidized units.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yonkers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT 62, Joseph Shuldiner is an unlikely landlord. A tenant advocate in his 20s and 30s, he had rented his whole life until moving into his own home for the first time this year after taking over as executive director of the Yonkers Municipal Housing Authority.</p>
        <p>Now, he is one of the city's most influential landlords, responsible for more than 4,000 public housing and rent-subsidized units.</p>
        <p>Since settling in full time on April 9 -- he started part time in January while finishing a consulting contract in Chicago -- he has been visiting the 19 projects he oversees, meeting with tenants to introduce himself and the new managers he has appointed at each project.</p>
        <p>''Call me Joe,'' Mr. Shuldiner said last month at the William A. Walsh Homes, a senior citizens' complex, where an audience of more than 75 residents filled the top-floor community room. A tinsel-covered nylon Christmas tree and a well-used bingo board faced a wall of windows with panoramic views of Yonkers.</p>
        <p>To the west, the new train station and luxury condominiums that have opened along the Hudson River are the first signs of a renaissance in Yonkers. But that growth is also having an enormous impact on the public housing sector.</p>
        <p>The city's 27-year lawsuit with the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, over segregationist policies that concentrated most of its public housing units in western Yonkers, was finally resolved last month, and the city has begun a $180 million urban-renewal project that includes replacing Mulford Gardens, the city's largest and oldest public housing project, with mixed-income housing.</p>
        <p>''Right now, public housing is in transition,'' said Peter A. Smith, 65, Mr. Shuldiner's predecessor, who retired in January after 33 years. ''Westchester is in a crisis. The agency is facing a challenge to generate more housing and maintain the housing stock that does exist in a sustainable way in the future.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith said he was thrilled that Mr. Shuldiner had taken the job. Mr. Shuldiner, who is married with two grown children, has run housing agencies in New York City, Chicago and Los Angeles, and spent about three years in Washington as the assistant secretary of Public and Indian Housing.</p>
        <p>''Joe has the wealth of knowledge to know what opportunities can fit into the different development schemes,'' Mr. Smith said.</p>
        <p>The 10-year redevelopment plan by the developers, Struever Fidelco Cappelli, a partnership of three major East Coast companies, includes billions of dollars in private investment in real estate, with 6 percent of the residential units designated as affordable housing. The plan's first phase is called River Park Center, which includes two of Yonkers's largest housing projects, the William A. Schlobohm Houses and Ross F. Calcagno Houses.</p>
        <p>''The question is, Where do we fit in?'' Mr. Shuldiner said in an interview last month in his office at Charles L. Curran Court, a complex for the elderly. ''Most of our remaining family units are in the area that is part of the redevelopment of the downtown. The flip side of concentrating all of the public housing in one neighborhood is that this is now the hot neighborhood.''</p>
        <p>With a mandate to look for new public housing opportunities, Mr. Shuldiner also has to reorganize the housing authority's operations to be consistent with new federal housing regulations for decentralized asset management.</p>
        <p>There are now seven full-time, on-site superintendents and managers who, instead of simply passing rents up to the central office, will use the money to maintain and improve their buildings with input from residents.</p>
        <p>At the William A. Walsh Homes, Mr. Shuldiner told residents about one way they could spend their money differently.</p>
        <p>''Right now, you have 4 guards, 24 hours a day, 7 days a week,'' Mr. Shuldiner said. ''That costs you $500,000 a year. We need to decide where we want to channel that money.''</p>
        <p>Security eats up 70 percent of the authority's annual capital budget. ''That's money we could be spending on new boilers and roofs,'' said Mr. Shuldiner, who has begun talking to tenant groups about alternate security systems, like keeping buildings locked and using intercoms to limit access and guards to monitor security cameras.</p>
        <p>He has also met twice with Edmund Hartnett, the Yonkers police commissioner, to discuss strategies for keeping projects' borders secure.</p>
        <p>''We're talking about alternative ways of policing,'' said Commissioner Hartnett, who came to Yonkers from the New York Police Department six months ago. ''I think it will be a good partnership.''</p>
        <p>Queen E. Ramsay, 71, head of the tenant organization at the William A. Walsh Homes, liked what she heard at the meeting with Mr. Shuldiner.</p>
        <p>''I think Joe is going to be fantastic,'' Ms. Ramsay said. ''He is a strong person. I have a good feeling that he will straighten things out.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC HOUSING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
