<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vintage Trend</title>
    <meta content="03wwln--consumed.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/magazine/03wwln-consumed-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851666"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 6-03-07: CONSUMED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WineStyles (Wine Merchants)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vino 100 (Wine Merchants)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Walker, Rob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Franchises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Franchises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3DC1430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vintage Trend</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Vintage Trend</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Rob Walker</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Walker, Rob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rob Walker column on WineStyles and Vino 100, two chains of wine stores that present wine to consumers in way that is unpretentious and demystified and that seek to make their stores gathering places, much like Starbucks coffeehouses; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Retail Wine Chains</p>
        <p>Consumer sophistication is on the rise. Just look at what we drink. Not coffee from a can or mass-market beer, but complex lattes and fine pinot noir. When there is a great enough thirst for sophistication (or anything else), something becomes inevitable: a chain of relevant franchises. Or in the case of wine, a couple of them: one recent list of fast-growing franchises included both Vino 100 (with about 60 locations open) and WineStyles (about 110 locations).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Turning a purchase requiring specialized knowledgeinto something for Everyman  everywhere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Retail Wine Chains</p>
        <p>Consumer sophistication is on the rise. Just look at what we drink. Not coffee from a can or mass-market beer, but complex lattes and fine pinot noir. When there is a great enough thirst for sophistication (or anything else), something becomes inevitable: a chain of relevant franchises. Or in the case of wine, a couple of them: one recent list of fast-growing franchises included both Vino 100 (with about 60 locations open) and WineStyles (about 110 locations).</p>
        <p>In both instances, the guiding mission is to present wine to consumers in a manner that's unpretentious and demystified -- not so, you know, sophisticated. Each chain emphasizes a desnobbed lexicon for wine discussion, a heavily edited selection of relatively low-priced bottles and an emphasis on the shop as a location for events and socializing.</p>
        <p>WineStyles, which began franchising in 2004, sorts its offerings on shelves not by country of origin or grape varietal but by way of a ''style system'' that boils down to eight ''flavor profile'' words, like ''crisp'' ''silky'' and ''bold.'' This is an easier system for a consumer to relate to, according to Robert Spuck, the C.E.O. of WineStyles. Similarly, a typical WineStyles store carries about 160 wines, because, he argues, that's as much as the shopper wants to deal with. Many of the selections at any given WineStyles store are actually proprietary: the chain works with wineries to produce batches that are under labels, like Killer Bee, that the chain owns. This means you ''don't have to pay for all that branding and everything'' that's built into the price of some other wines, Spuck says. New house labels are introduced all the time to meet the wine consumer's thirst for variety. But the strategy also happens to play to many a wine buyer's tendency to buy some labels over and over -- long after the actual vintage he first enjoyed has been quaffed (as oenephiles like to say) out of existence.</p>
        <p>At Vino 100, the organizing principle is suggested by the name: a hundred wines priced at $25 or less. Employees are trained to use the company's ''vino speak,'' which avoids words like ''tannin'' or ''sulfates'' in favor of continuums like dry versus fruity and light versus heavy, and food pairings. ''It's talking English,'' says Gary Blumenthal, the founder. Blumenthal is also the president of Tinder Box, a chain of 150 or so cigar stores, and he aims to replicate the system he says has worked well for that chain, keeping track of customers' purchases, likes and dislikes to guide new suggestions. ''People ask me all the time, 'What's a good cigar?' '' he says. ''I tell them it's the one you like.'' It's the same with wine, he says: ''Somebody is involved with cigars or wine because they want to be. They want it to be fun. They don't want it to be stressful, they don't want to feel stupid and they don't want to feel cheap.''</p>
        <p>It's safe to say that these chains aim to be something like the Starbucks of wine. Starbucks, after all, is an icon of the new and more sophisticated America. You can argue that Starbucks has achieved its place by fancying up a commodity (coffee) or by making the once-unusual latte into something as easily obtainable as a Whopper. But both Spuck and Blumenthal stress a different Starbucks-like quality: the retail establishment as gathering place. Vino 100 franchises hold scores of events with names like Wining Women. WineStyles shops all have clubs, some with hundreds of members. Both have put a great deal of effort into inviting store design. In a way, the actual wine sounds less important than the context in which it's purchased. ''That's what people in our demographic enjoy doing,'' Spuck says. ''Meeting other people who are congruent with their personality and with income and probably education background. We give them a meeting place, and wine happens to be the focal point.''</p>
        <p>Or rather, lots of meeting places. These chains have not invented the idea of the comfortable, neighborhood wine shop, which has been around for a long time. One pertinent example is Best Cellars, which opened in Manhattan in 1996 with a welcoming design, a 100-bottle selection and an eight-category flavor-profile system -- ''fresh,'' ''juicy,'' ''big,'' etc. (It now has eight locations.) Then again, Starbucks did not invent the cafe. The key to chains in the new sophisticated America is the same as ever: not creating a special place but replicating it, as far and wide as possible.</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 6-03-07: CONSUMED</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
