<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Three Spaces for the Price of One</title>
    <meta content="03hunt" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/realestate/03hunt.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851828"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE HUNT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/The Hunt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E7DA1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1098" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Three Spaces for the Price of One</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Three Spaces for the Price of One</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE COHEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WAS it a live-work space she needed, a smaller work studio or a cheaper apartment? Beck Hickey wasn't quite sure, but she knew she needed to downsize.</p>
        <p>Excited at the growth of her business -- handbags made from skateboards -- Ms. Hickey found herself split between three locations, spending way too much on rent. ''High hopes,'' Ms. Hickey said. ''I took on more than I should have, too soon.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beck Hickey wasn’t quite sure whether she needed a live-work space, a smaller work studio or a cheaper apartment. But she knew she needed to downsize.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WAS it a live-work space she needed, a smaller work studio or a cheaper apartment? Beck Hickey wasn't quite sure, but she knew she needed to downsize.</p>
        <p>Excited at the growth of her business -- handbags made from skateboards -- Ms. Hickey found herself split between three locations, spending way too much on rent. ''High hopes,'' Ms. Hickey said. ''I took on more than I should have, too soon.''</p>
        <p>She had her $2,300 apartment in the East Village, her $1,500 work studio in the garment district and her parents' garage in Holbrook, on Long Island, which she used as a woodworking shop. That cost her nothing -- but it was 80 minutes away by train, and $26 round-trip.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hickey, who rarely uses her given name, Rebecca, studied design at Syracuse University. After the terrorist attacks of Sept. 11, 2001, she was laid off from her job at an advertising agency whose main client was United Airlines. She then earned her keep by freelancing, baby-sitting, waiting on tables and making gifts -- including handbags from upholstery fabric.</p>
        <p>One day, browsing through the bags in the Prada store on Broadway in SoHo, with its curving ''big wave'' design that reminded her of a skate ramp, she had a brainstorm: Why not make handbags out of used skateboards? So she did.</p>
        <p>People admired them, word got out, and she began to sell her sk8bags online at beckycity.com, as well as at boutiques. After Teen magazine wrote that the pop star Ashlee Simpson loved her sk8bag, orders streamed in from teenage girls.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hickey, now 36, loved her one-bedroom apartment on Avenue C in the East Village, where she had lived for about three years. ''I was convinced I was never moving out of that apartment, ever,'' she said. But the dining area, which she used as her office, was filling up with paperwork and, sometimes, bolts of satin and stacks of skateboards.</p>
        <p>Her work studio in the garment district, and the $3,000 rent, was shared with a wedding dress designer, but it didn't allow for any dirty work -- cutting and sanding -- so she kept those operations in her parents' garage. It was far from ideal -- cold in winter and hot in summer. ''And my mom was complaining she couldn't put the car in the garage anymore,'' Ms. Hickey said.</p>
        <p>A year ago, her parents announced that they would be retiring to Florida. Her garage workshop, where she had a workbench and a table saw, would vanish. She had to make a move.</p>
        <p>She figured she would pare her expenses and eliminate her constant running around by consolidating. But there weren't many live-work spaces suitable for her equipment. ''It wasn't as though I could sneak a home office in,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The first plausible place was on South Fifth Street in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. It was nicely divided, with a storefront workspace in front and living quarters in back. Though it was on a ''weird dead end'' with little foot traffic, the place was ''insanely cheap,'' at $1,500 a month for 1,200 square feet.</p>
        <p>But it was run-down and had little natural light. ''I was afraid of spending days on end there,'' Ms. Hickey said. ''Sometimes when I am working, I don't go outside. I could be in this cave and it was sort of depressing.''</p>
        <p>She took her father, Steve Hickey, to whom she spoke daily about her hunt, to see the place. ''It really worried me,'' he said. He envisioned her ''coming home at 10 or 11 at night, and there was nobody around,'' except maybe for transients beneath the Williamsburg Bridge, he said.</p>
        <p>She soon found a 1,700-square-foot place in Washington Heights, with 12-foot ceilings and a wall of north-facing windows, renting for $2,800. The raw space was being fully renovated.</p>
        <p>''I said instantly I was taking the place,'' Ms. Hickey said. But the agent was discouraging, telling her the landlord wouldn't want a self-employed tenant. She begged and pleaded, offering her parents as guarantors, but the agent was adamant.</p>
        <p>So she figured she would hunt for a cheaper work studio and a cheaper apartment. But nothing was quite right. She found a work space in Williamsburg, but she would be paying $800 a month to share it with two other people.</p>
        <p>''I got sucked into apartment hunting thinking there's something better out there,'' she said. ''I would get swayed by seeing a cheaper apartment that sounded great, and I would look at it and see it was not that great.''</p>
        <p>A nice-looking rental building was going up on East Second Street, but when Ms. Hickey visited, she found that studio apartments started at around $2,000. ''I realized that to stay in the East Village and find a place as nice as mine was impossible,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, she kept encountering the listing for the Washington Heights place. ''I was bitter, I was sad, I was definitely still looking, but the fact I kept seeing this place was derailing my hunt,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She assumed that nobody else was interested, so she was now a more appealing tenant. But her messages to the agent went unanswered.</p>
        <p>Fed up, she went to the building to ask the construction workers who their employer was. She tracked down the owner's phone number. But it took weeks of calling before he answered the phone.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'I am an artist looking for a live-work space,' and he said, 'This is perfect for you.' He was not the least put off by the fact I was self employed,'' Ms. Hickey said. Only later did she find out the agent had never passed her application along.</p>
        <p>The renovations took longer than expected, and the certificate of occupancy was delayed. ''Becky was complaining so much and I didn't want to hear her complaining,'' said her father, who works in the construction field. He helped her navigate through the Department of Buildings, and she prodded the landlord.</p>
        <p>Finally, in late fall, the building received its certificate of occupancy. Ms. Hickey, with all her skateboards and equipment, moved into her new apartment, which occupies the entire top floor.</p>
        <p>Her friends say she has the nicest apartment they have seen in New York. It has one gigantic room, though the landlord added a wall to partition off the work space. There's even a washer and dryer.</p>
        <p>''It has improved my life and has made my bag business much less stressful,'' Ms. Hickey said. She can work around the clock if she likes. After dinner, ''I can make a few bags, drink a glass of wine, make more bags,'' she said.</p>
        <p>THE HUNT E-mail: thehunt@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: thehunt@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
