<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peerless Stallion</title>
    <meta content="Barich.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/books/review/Barich-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851597"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Scanlan, Lawrence</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Horse God Built, The: The Untold Story of Secretariat, the Worlds Greatest Racehorse (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E1D61630F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="881" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peerless Stallion</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Peerless Stallion</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL BARICH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE HORSE GOD BUILT</p>
        <p>The Untold Story of Secretariat,</p>
        <p>the World's Greatest Racehorse.</p>
        <p>By Lawrence Scanlan.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 335 pp. Thomas Dunne Books/</p>
        <p>St. Martin's Press. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Secretariat was clumsy as a colt, but his groom knew how to talk to him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE HORSE GOD BUILT</p>
        <p>The Untold Story of Secretariat,</p>
        <p>the World's Greatest Racehorse.</p>
        <p>By Lawrence Scanlan.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 335 pp. Thomas Dunne Books/</p>
        <p>St. Martin's Press. $24.95.</p>
        <p>It takes a brave writer to tackle a subject as well documented as Secretariat, among the most popular racehorses ever. Already celebrated in two substantive biographies, Big Red, as he was called, was such a media darling that he has been commemorated on a United States postage stamp. As Lawrence Scanlan notes, Secretariat came of age during the corrupt Watergate era, and since he didn't cheat, lie or order any illegal wiretaps, he embodied the wholesome values Americans treasure. When his picture appeared on the cover of Time in 1973, many readers found it ''refreshing'' to see the front end of a horse in the space usually reserved for politicians.</p>
        <p>Scanlan's goal is ''to paint a fresh portrait in words,'' and he approaches the task from the perspective of an avid horseman rather than a track insider. His quest sends him on a road trip through Kentucky, South Carolina and Florida as he digs for any scrap of information that might provide a new twist on the old story. A zealous researcher, he seems to have read everything about racing and even attends such mundane events as the unveiling of a bronze statue of Secretariat in hopes that it will yield some clues.</p>
        <p>From the start, Secretariat had the look of a matinee idol. Born at the Meadow Stud in Virginia, he was a handsome chestnut -- ''bright as an orange, shiny as brass'' -- and the manager of the farm described him as a ''big, strong-made foal with plenty of bone.'' Despite such assets, the colt was so clumsy when he first took to the track that he earned the nickname Ol' Hopalong, and it would be months before he was comfortable with his magnificent physique. (His heart was twice the normal size, and his gait the most efficient ever measured, according to an M.I.T. equine specialist.) Under the tutelage of Lucien Laurin, his French Canadian trainer, he went on to astound the public, never more so than when he won the 1973 Belmont Stakes by 31 lengths.</p>
        <p>It's unfortunate for Scanlan that Laurin is dead, as are other members of Secretariat's entourage. More than 30 years have passed since the horse's last race, and memories grow dim. Racetrack folks are notoriously tough nuts for an outsider to crack, too, pledged as they are to a peculiar code of omertà. When a jockey or an exercise rider does open up to Scanlan, the results are hardly revelatory. Secretariat was a wonderful horse, they all agree, and everybody loved him. It doesn't help matters when Scanlan consults the Internet and reproduces similarly bland sentiments from the fans.</p>
        <p>Scanlan fares better with Edward (Shorty) Sweat, Secretariat's devoted groom, a flashy dresser who liked vodka, danced the boogaloo and fathered four children by three different women. Powerfully built, with massive forearms, Sweat joined the exodus of Southern black men who hired on as grooms because the job paid a halfway-decent wage and beat picking cotton. The son of a poor sharecropper, he was working steadily with horses at 14 and eventually landed at Laurin's Holly Hill Farm, the ticket that led him to the big time in New York.</p>
        <p>Like Laurin, Sweat has been dead for years, so Scanlan must rely on the testimony of friends and relations. He locates Marvin Moorer, Sweat's son, and the groom's old cronies Gus Gray and Charlie Davis, among others. Again the comments he records are remarkably uniform. By all accounts, Sweat was kind and generous, with a habit of deference to whites and a gift for drawing out the best in a horse. He adored Secretariat and even slept on a cot outside his stall before important races. Their rapport was extraordinary. Moorer says Sweat talked constantly to his charge in a Creole patois known as Geechee, a centuries-old slave language, and Secretariat listened.</p>
        <p>In the end, though, there's a fair degree of unsolved mystery about Sweat, who lost his house in Queens in a dispute over back taxes and died a pauper. Drink played a part, apparently, and he may not have been properly compensated for his efforts on behalf of Secretariat and Riva Ridge, another Derby winner, but grooms are a strange tribe and often contribute to their own misery. Scanlan rightly praises them as unsung heroes who deserve better pay and living conditions, yet they also resemble Melville's Bartleby, in that they ''prefer not to.'' Shorty Sweat had the skills to be a trainer, for instance, but Moorer suggests he didn't want the responsibility.</p>
        <p>A case can be made that Sweat's sad decline was a form of mourning for the horse he loved, and the celebrity that went with it, but it's equally probable that Sweat knew how to do only one thing -- be a groom -- and it ultimately wore him down. Scanlan is a compassionate reporter, but he doesn't bring Sweat to life or explore his dark side, so the rough-and-tumble aspects of racing stay under wraps. Still, the author is an amiable companion on the road, and his portrait, though neither gritty nor entirely fresh, will satisfy those who can't get enough of Secretariat.</p>
        <p>Bill Barich's racing books ''A Fine Place to Daydream'' and ''Laughing in the Hills'' have recently been published in new paperback editions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Bill Barich's racing books ''A Fine Place to Daydream'' and ''Laughing in the Hills'' have recently been published in new paperback editions.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
