<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Palestinian Militant Is Killed as the Air Fire Over Gaza Declines</title>
    <meta content="03mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/world/middleeast/03mideast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851993"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza Strip</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Islamic Jihad</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershner, Isabel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abu Mustafa, Fadi</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Gaza Strip</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Islamic Jihad</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Al Aksa Martyrs Brigades</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905EEDB1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="688" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Palestinian Militant Is Killed as the Air Fire Over Gaza Declines</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Palestinian Militant Is Killed as the Air Fire Over Gaza Declines</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ISABEL KERSHNER; Taghreed El-Khodary contributed reporting from Gaza.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershner, Isabel</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, June 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fadi Abu Mustafa, field commander from Palestinian militant faction Islamic Jihad, is killed in Israeli air attack on his vehicle in Gaza Strip (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A field commander from the Palestinian militant faction Islamic Jihad was killed in an Israeli air attack on his vehicle in Khan Yunis, in the southern Gaza Strip, on Friday night, army officials and Islamic Jihad said.</p>
        <p>On Saturday morning, Islamic Jihad and the Fatah-affiliated Al Aksa Martyrs Brigades claimed responsibility for firing a rocket from Gaza at the Israeli border town of Sderot, causing damage to houses but no injuries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A field commander from the Palestinian militant faction Islamic Jihad was killed in an Israeli air attack on his vehicle, army officials and Islamic Jihad said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A field commander from the Palestinian militant faction Islamic Jihad was killed in an Israeli air attack on his vehicle in Khan Yunis, in the southern Gaza Strip, on Friday night, army officials and Islamic Jihad said.</p>
        <p>On Saturday morning, Islamic Jihad and the Fatah-affiliated Al Aksa Martyrs Brigades claimed responsibility for firing a rocket from Gaza at the Israeli border town of Sderot, causing damage to houses but no injuries.</p>
        <p>In general, though, hostilities between Gaza and Israel seemed to have wound down in the past few days after two weeks of intensive Israeli airstrikes and Palestinian rocket fire, as Hamas, which played a leading role in the recent violence, appeared to be lowering its profile.</p>
        <p>Since Tuesday, the Israeli Air Force has carried out one or two raids a day, compared with as many as 11 a day during the week before, according to an army spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>The number of rockets launched from Gaza toward Israel also dropped in the past few days by about half, according to army figures. Eight rockets were launched on Friday and six on Thursday, compared with a rough average of 14 per day in the previous two weeks.</p>
        <p>Also on Saturday, medical workers in Gaza reported that two Palestinians had been shot dead by Israeli soldiers close to the border fence. An Israeli Army spokeswoman said that two Palestinians had approached the border fence south of the Karni crossing and had not stopped even after warning shots had been fired. Soldiers then shot at the two, aiming at the lower body, the spokeswoman said. One was hit, but both were seen fleeing, she said.</p>
        <p>The escalation of violence started in mid-May after Hamas, the faction that dominates the Palestinian government, announced that it was resuming rocket fire against Israel, breaking a six-month Gaza cease-fire to which it had largely adhered. Its decision to do so came after a week of factional violence in Gaza between gunmen of Hamas and its rival and coalition partner, Fatah, in which about 50 people were killed.</p>
        <p>In response, the Israeli Army stepped up air attacks in Gaza, aiming mostly at Hamas military compounds and outposts, as well as weapons-storage facilities and rocket-launching cells. More than 50 Palestinians have been killed in the Israeli strikes, at least 31 of them militants, according to Palestinian medical officials. Two Israeli civilians were killed by the rocket fire.</p>
        <p>Israel Radio reported that Hamas had not been firing rockets at Israel for a few days, and though Hamas has not announced any cessation, a Hamas spokesman, Fawzi Barhoum, suggested Saturday that the movement had already accomplished its objectives.</p>
        <p>''The firing of rockets is part of the strategy of resistance, and whatever we did has achieved many goals,'' said Mr. Barhoum, who would not explicitly confirm a halt in Hamas rocket fire. ''We have achieved a balance of fear, we have made public Israel's violations against Palestinian citizens, and we have united the Palestinian factions into one front.''</p>
        <p>The deputy political chief of Hamas, Moussa Abu Marzouk, told the Egyptian daily Al Ahram on Saturday that Hamas might agree to renew the calm with Israel for one year. But he said that there would have to be a commitment from both sides, and that the cease-fire would have to apply simultaneously to the West Bank as well as Gaza.</p>
        <p>Israel has rejected the idea of expanding the cease-fire to the West Bank until it is properly carried out in Gaza. Smaller Palestinian factions such as Islamic Jihad continued sporadic rocket fire from Gaza during the six-month cease-fire, often explaining their actions as a response to Israeli military raids in the West Bank. Neither Hamas nor Fatah, which dominates the official Palestinian Authority security forces, acted against them.</p>
        <p>Israeli security officials described the aerial attack on the Islamic Jihad militant, Fadi Abu Mustafa, 22, as a joint operation between the army and the Shin Bet internal security agency. The officials, who under army rules could not be identified, said Mr. Abu Mustafa had been ''involved in terrorist activity against Israel since 2003.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
