<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Directions: Hug, Smile, Schmooze, Repeat</title>
    <meta content="03robe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/theater/theaterspecial/03robe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER: THE TONYS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robertson, Campbell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gallagher, John</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Spring Awakening (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/New York Theater Workshop</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Tony Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drama Desk Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Actors and Actresses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Actors and Actresses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">American Theater Wing</org>
        <org class="online_producer">League of American Theaters and Producers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Drama Critics Circle</org>
        <org class="online_producer">drama league</org>
        <org class="online_producer">new dramatists</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Drama Desk</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gallagher, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Groff, Jonathan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DB1430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1944" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Directions: Hug, Smile, Schmooze, Repeat</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Directions: Hug, Smile, Schmooze, Repeat</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAMPBELL ROBERTSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robertson, Campbell</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article focuses on actor John Gallagher, star of show Spring Awakening, as example of publicity frenzy before Tony Awards; actors attend numerous parties, benefits, award shows and press events to promote themselves and their shows; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''GENTLEMEN,'' the photographer said, ''hug each other.''</p>
        <p>John Gallagher Jr. and Jonathan Groff, the two Tony-nominated actors from ''Spring Awakening,'' put their arms around each other and smiled.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Gallagher Jr., who is nominated for best featured actor for his role in “Spring Awakening,” has never been Out There before. But he is learning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''GENTLEMEN,'' the photographer said, ''hug each other.''</p>
        <p>John Gallagher Jr. and Jonathan Groff, the two Tony-nominated actors from ''Spring Awakening,'' put their arms around each other and smiled.</p>
        <p>Snap.</p>
        <p>Now, they were told, hug the people from the American Theater Wing.</p>
        <p>Snap.</p>
        <p>Now hug Angela Lansbury.</p>
        <p>Snap.</p>
        <p>Now hug Jay Johnson.</p>
        <p>Snap.</p>
        <p>The hugging continued all over the Tony nominees' press reception on May 16: hugs with actors they knew, hugs with actors they'd never met, even hugs with people who were about to interview them. The hugging would continue -- and had already been going on -- at a steady stream of cocktail parties, luncheons, benefits, awards shows and press events.</p>
        <p>It is a part of being, to use the jargon, Out There.</p>
        <p>Out There is an almost mythically important place to be during Tony season, which begins in early May and ends next Sunday with the awards ceremony. It's a place that exists at big events and local hangouts, everywhere a nominee might run into a few producers, journalists, artists or other industry types who are among the 750 or so Tony voters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gallagher, 22, who plays Moritz -- the one with the hair -- and is nominated for best featured actor in a musical, has never been Out There before. But he is learning.</p>
        <p>''Overwhelmed?'' he said to a reporter, who was following him from event to event, watching as he answered the same questions from countless interviewers and responded to countless good wishes. ''A little.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gallagher hasn't gone to everything, though there's plenty of Out There to go around. There is the annual League of American Theaters and Producers road conference for example. And the Dramatists Guild benefit. And, let's see, the Easter Bonnet Competition, the Actors Fund Gala, the New York Drama Critics Circle Awards, the Lucille Lortel Awards, the Drama League luncheon, the New Dramatists luncheon, the Manhattan Theater Club benefit, the Drama Desk Awards, the Obies, the Outer Critics Circle Awards and the Theater World Awards.</p>
        <p>To name just a few.</p>
        <p>It's not only a big campaign season: The charities take in real money, and the news articles boost ticket sales during the most written-about part of the season. Overt campaigning is bad form (and besides, at these events one is mostly seeing the same people one saw two days ago). No, what you need to do is simply show up, smile, shake hands and be charming.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gallagher is not the most experienced of the young actors in ''Spring Awakening'' -- Lea Michele, the show's 20-year-old lead actress, made her Broadway debut at the age of 8 -- but he's not green. He was on Broadway last year in ''Rabbit Hole.'' He wasn't nominated, though, and barely participated in the Tony season. So this is all new.</p>
        <p>One of the first events was a cocktail party for the Drama Desk nominees, held this year on May 1. (The ceremony itself was on May 20.)</p>
        <p>The Drama Desk Awards, often referred to as the Golden Globes in relation to the Tony's Academy Awards, are given by a group of theater writers to shows and performers on and off Broadway. Members of the Drama Desk are from all over the place, from daily and community newspapers to one-person operations, so at this party, a crowded, hot, hug-filled affair at the Arte Cafe on West 73rd Street, it was hard for a nominee to know whom he should be talking to. Even experienced actors were ushered around by press agents and producers to meet and smile at the right people.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gallagher, along with his two nominated co-stars, Ms. Michele and Mr. Groff, posed for a barrage of photographs. Then Ira Pittelman, one of the lead producers of ''Spring Awakening,'' brought two men over to meet them. And they were?</p>
        <p>''I don't know,'' Mr. Pittelman said quietly after finessing the introduction.</p>
        <p>The crowd swirled, the photographers did their jobs, and in between warm smiles and handshakes, actors, even veterans, described the scene under their breath in unprintable terms. Thing is, they had to be there, not only for themselves -- not even mainly for themselves -- but for their shows.</p>
        <p>''The star of a Broadway show is the ambassador,'' said Harvey Fierstein, who won a Tony Award in 2003 for ''Hairspray,'' which also won the Tony for best musical. ''Nobody wants to see the producer, and nobody really wants to see the director, so you have the responsibility.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gallagher, however, was in a corner fixating. ''I can't believe I called Wayman Wong the wrong name,'' he kept saying, almost to himself. ''I called him John. I thought he was one of our producers.'' (Mr. Wong works for The Daily News and Playbill.com, and is a Drama Desk voter. It should also be said that ''Spring Awakening'' has more than 30 producers.)</p>
        <p>Half an hour later Mr. Gallagher had not gotten over it. ''You'll learn this about me,'' he said. ''I'm a fretter.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gallagher is pretty low key, actually, so in that sense the season is not bringing on any nervous breakdowns. But in terms of the details -- like what, exactly, the Drama Desk is -- he's mostly in the dark.</p>
        <p>''The funny thing about this is, as much as I appreciate and love musical theater, I so don't know what's going on,'' he said over lunch one day (a day on which his main chore was borrowing an old suit from Stephen Spinella, an actor in ''Spring Awakening,'' to wear at the next occasion).</p>
        <p>So he waits for the show's press agents to tell him where to go and when to go there. This would be an easy undertaking if it wasn't on top of his eight shows a week and the already crowded lineup of television appearances, interviews and promotional shoots.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gallagher -- or, really, the producers and press agents who call the shots -- is not the canniest operator, not like the real pros who have their portraits unveiled at Sardi's at the right time or their photographs taken at the late-season Broadway openings, or who hire personal publicists to steer them through the season in the hope that a few well-placed entrances will make a difference.</p>
        <p>''It's a small enough pool that basically you never know,'' said Richard Kornberg, a Broadway press agent. ''If it's a contest that is rather close, and if it's an actor or actress who has a larger-than-life personality, their appearance at these things could add a couple of votes.''</p>
        <p>Emanuel Azenberg, a manager, this year, of ''Spring Awakening'' and a longtime producer, said that's a myth. The main thing is just to show up at the big events -- or, more specifically, not to not show up.</p>
        <p>''If you don't show up at these things, you'll be seen as arrogant,'' he said. What you do at the events or how many interviews you give doesn't really matter.</p>
        <p>A week and a half later the Drama League luncheon took place. Mr. Gallagher did not know what a Drama League was at this time last year. (He's still not entirely sure.) Now he was facing scores of league members in a cavernous ballroom at the Marriott Marquis, eating lunch on a dais with Frank Langella, F. Murray Abraham and a few dozen other major and minor Broadway players.</p>
        <p>''It was so surreal,'' Mr. Gallagher said. ''It's like, 'So then I was playing poker with Albert Einstein and a Labrador.' ''</p>
        <p>Other than talking, once again, to the press, the only thing an actor is called upon to do at the luncheon is give a two-minute speech that is funny/heartfelt/modest. With scores of actors giving these little speeches, it can't matter all that much what you say, right? Right?</p>
        <p>''It is very, very nerve racking,'' Mr. Gallagher said. ''Someone before you is saying something you were planning to say or mostly something better than what you were going to say, and you're scarfing down your food to be finished before you have to speak.''</p>
        <p>Remember: a fretter.</p>
        <p>This can all be a bit much for the actors, but the sacrifice only entails time and nerves. The producers, on the other hand, have to part with serious money. There are new ads to buy to tout all the nominations, expensive tables at benefits and pricey seats at awards ceremonies. Then there's the musical number during the Tony telecast, a three-minute segment that can sell a lot of tickets but also costs a lot of money to stage: up to a quarter of a million dollars for a big musical.</p>
        <p>Altogether, one producer said, the Tony season can cost a production half a million dollars.</p>
        <p>On May 15, the day the nominations came out, Mr. Gallagher spent the afternoon with friends in Queens, where he lives. He went out to dinner with his parents and then stopped by a late-night party in Manhattan to see his agent.</p>
        <p>It's a day he would experience over and over again as he would be asked about it by reporters approximately four million times during the next few weeks -- beginning the next morning at the Tony nominees' press reception.</p>
        <p>This reception is a rather efficient way to do the necessary: about 60 press outlets take over The View, the donut-shaped restaurant at the top of the Marriott Marquis, and do interviews. Every few feet there sits another reporter, calling out for the marquee names.</p>
        <p>''Is Angela gone?''</p>
        <p>''Is Vanessa here?''</p>
        <p>''Audra, one minute! Just one minute!''</p>
        <p>Mr. Groff and Mr. Gallagher, more or less under the radar, were escorted by the show's press agent from table to table.</p>
        <p>''First it was Broadway.com,'' Mr. Gallagher said. ''Then, well, I don't know who those people were.''</p>
        <p>It lasted about two hours, though the questions were pretty much the same each time. The two actors were shaking the hands of some ''Spring Awakening'' producers whom they hadn't met when the press agent approached again: ''You got one more in you?'' And it was off to the microphones.</p>
        <p>The Drama Desk Awards ceremony was the last of the big events for Mr. Gallagher before the Tonys themselves. But ''Spring Awakening'' had a performance that night, and the cast didn't arrive until halfway through the ceremony. He did stick around for the various after and after-after parties, which lasted past 4 a.m. But even early in the evening many of the actors who are in the race were beginning to looked a little tired.</p>
        <p>''Now it's on to the Tonys,'' David Pittu, also nominated for best featured actor in a musical, for his role in ''LoveMusik,'' was overheard saying on the way out of the ceremony.</p>
        <p>There would be the Tony nominees no-press-allowed luncheon the following Thursday and the Stars in the Alley concert in Shubert Alley on Wednesday. Mr. Gallagher had a few more press obligations, but nothing out of the ordinary: It was pretty much a wide open road between the Drama Desk and the big night.</p>
        <p>''It's funny,'' Mr. Gallagher said over lunch a couple of days after the Drama Desk ceremony. (He didn't win.) ''You never talk about it, but then you're at the bar and somebody says, 'Dude, what if you win a Tony?'</p>
        <p>''Do I prepare something? Do I prepare words? I'd like to say I'm not, but the fact is I am. It's scary.''</p>
        <p>A press agent was trying to line up a suit he could wear to the ceremony, Mr. Gallagher said. He was also filling out the forms to buy two more tickets for his family. But otherwise it's a waiting game.</p>
        <p>''At the end of the day,'' he said. ''All you can really do is just do your show.''</p>
        <p>THEATER: THE TONYS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
