<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Do You Believe in Magic?</title>
    <meta content="Teresi.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/books/review/Teresi-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851623"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mushrooms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mushrooms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Shroom: A Cultural History of the Magic Mushroom (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EED61630F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1205" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Do You Believe in Magic?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Do You Believe in Magic?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DICK TERESI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SHROOM</p>
        <p>A Cultural History of the Magic Mushroom.</p>
        <p>By Andy Letcher.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 360 pp.</p>
        <p>Ecco/HarperCollins Publishers. $25.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An examination of the mythology surrounding hallucinogenic mushrooms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SHROOM</p>
        <p>A Cultural History of the Magic Mushroom.</p>
        <p>By Andy Letcher.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 360 pp.</p>
        <p>Ecco/HarperCollins Publishers. $25.95.</p>
        <p>My friends here in western Massachusetts usually don't let me down. Kris, the truck-stop waitress, referred me to Michelle, a bartender at the gentlemen's club down the road, who directed me to Kim, the red-haired dancer with an ankh-tattoo armband, who referred me to an ex-boyfriend's wife's girlfriend, another redhead, who met me outside an American Legion hall in Chicopee (Nipmuck for ''land of violent pee'') and informed me that magic mushrooms were ''out of season,'' but she could get me LSD instead. ''Acid -- same deal as mushrooms,'' she said. Besides, she wondered why a guy in his 60s wanted to experiment with shrooms. The answer was obvious. I had a review to write.</p>
        <p>Even if read while sober, Andy Letcher's ''Shrooms: A Cultural History of the Magic Mushroom,'' is a near-transcendent experience. Well written and thoughtfully researched, the book works on the limbic system too: after reading it, one is tempted to hit the streets in search of a religious-experience-in-a-fungus. Letcher has contributed a delightful, journalistic addition to the genre known as trip lit.</p>
        <p>While magic mushrooms are hallucinogens -- Chicopee wisdom aside -- their effects are different from those of LSD. Letcher describes acid as having a ''rainbow trajectory'' lasting from 10 to 12 hours. A shroom trip lasts from 4 to 5, and its primary active ingredient, psilocybin, is about 100 times less potent than LSD.</p>
        <p>In a shroom trip, Letcher explains, ''colors seem brighter, more saturated.'' At high doses, one's connection to reality may be severed; ''everything is suddenly tattooed with light, while unbidden faces may peer out from the woodwork.'' It is more giggly than LSD; mundane aspects of life can become comical. One myconaut reported that the freckles on her arm ''got up and danced away.'' Some trips are hellish, complete with dragons and snakes. The mushroom itself sometimes talks to you. One seller advised his customers ''not to operate any equipment more technically demanding than a spoon.''</p>
        <p>Letcher, a Briton, holds doctorates in both ecology and religious studies, and in the 1990s, when he was an eco-protester, lived in a treehouse. (Or maybe he just hallucinated that his house was levitating.) In 1993, he attended a lecture by Terence McKenna, the ''geeky American'' who became the Johnny Appleseed of psilocybin. Letcher wrote in his diary: ''Far out. McKenna just blew my mind.'' Fortunately, for this, his first book, Letcher's mind has remained unblown. In ''Shroom'' he rewrites the history of magic mushrooms, systematically destroying the myths festered by pioneers like McKenna, R. Gordon Wasson, Robert Graves, Aldous Huxley and others, while recognizing their heroic efforts in promoting mycomania.</p>
        <p>There are an estimated 209 species of trippy mushrooms, which mainly fall into two broad groups. The psilocybes, containing psilocybin and psilocin, are the friendlier magic mushrooms. One of the most common is the Liberty Cap. Any 20 Liberty Caps ''picked in different parts of the world,'' Letcher writes, ''will have, on average, the same concentration of active ingredients, and therefore the same pharmacological effect.'' Another psilocybe, cubensis, is less potent than the Liberty Cap, but easier to grow and more popular. It was favored by McKenna.</p>
        <p>The second type is the amanita. The best known is the fly-agaric, Amanita muscaria, the red-and-white-spotted mushroom familiar from storybooks, the favored resting stool of gnomes. The amanitas are more myth-ridden than the psilocybes, and their psychic results more unpredictable. Letcher says the fly-agaric contains a ''fuzzy cocktail of different chemical alkaloids''; it can produce increased stamina and euphoria but also nausea, dizziness and twitchiness. ''Compared to, say, the Liberty Cap,'' Letcher writes, ''the fly-agaric is like a chemical cocktail shaker into which a blindfolded bartender has poured whatever ingredients come to hand -- vodka, juice or carpet cleaner.''</p>
        <p>Letcher seems most intent on upending the standard history of shrooms. For the past half-century we have been told that prehistoric cultures used magic mushrooms, that the true origins of religion lay in an early mushroom cult, that Jesus ate not bread and wine but fly-agaric at the Last Supper, that the magical Soma cited in the Rig Veda was actually made from shrooms, that the mystical raptures reported at the ancient Greek celebrations at Eleusis were really shroom-fests. Same deal with the Druids at Stonehenge. I won't elaborate here on the theory that witches used their broom handles to apply mushroom goop topically. Some very smart people -- Wasson, Graves, McKenna -- have promulgated shroom myths, and Letcher meticulously runs every one of them to earth. ''There is not a single instance of a magic mushroom being preserved in the archaeological record anywhere,'' he writes. ''We really do not know, one way or the other, whether the ancients worshipped the holy spores of God,'' Letcher continues. ''If they did, they left not a single piece of evidence of having done so.''</p>
        <p>The myco-mythologists use the same goofy logic as today's neo-Darwinists: if something could have happened, it did happen. McKenna, for instance, who believed shrooms are the ''portal to a shamanic realm,'' said that when our hominid ancestors left the African forests for the plains, they ate psilocybe mushrooms growing in cattle dung. This sharpened their visual acuity and conferred an evolutionary advantage. At medium doses, shrooms worked as an aphrodisiac, and improved their reproductive success, and at high doses these protohumans began to speak. One assumes their first words were ''Oh wow.''</p>
        <p>More interesting is Gordon Wasson, a vice president of J. P. Morgan &amp; Company, whose hobby and obsession was mushrooms. In 1955 he traveled to Oaxaca, Mexico, where he met MarÃa Sabina, a Mazatec Indian, who introduced him to magic mushrooms and mysticism. On his first shroom trip, he felt ''as if his soul had been scooped out of his body.''</p>
        <p>Wasson kick-started the psychedelic movement, according to Letcher, when he wrote an article in 1957 for Life magazine entitled ''Seeking the Magic Mushroom.'' Westerners began tripping to Oaxaca and scarfing up shrooms. Letcher claims the Life article inspired Timothy Leary to experiment with psychedelics. Even the Time/Life founder Henry Luce turned on with Wasson. As Letcher puts it, Wasson ''may have failed in his attempt to prove the existence of an ancient mushrooming cult, but in doing so he gave the world a modern one.''</p>
        <p>Does Letcher use shrooms himself? He makes no comment, but he clearly resents the fact that magic mushrooms, with a few exemptions, are now illegal throughout the Western world. I would guess he shrooms a bit. I hope, though, he doesn't turn on in his treehouse. We need him in one piece to continue writing lovely books for us.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile I keep searching for the ''numinous feelings'' and ''bizarrerie de l'ambiance'' promised by shrooms. I ran into reddish Kim at the truck stop, and registered my complaint about the limitations of her Chicopee friend. I told her about the poor Siberians in the 18th century who could not afford shrooms and would loiter outside houses where mushrooms were being ingested. When partygoers came outside to relieve themselves, the poor would collect the urine in wooden bowls and drink it down. ''Look,'' Kim said, ''I know a guy. ... ''</p>
        <p>Dick Teresi is writing a book about death.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Dick Teresi is writing a book about death.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
