<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Using Wood to Define an Open Space</title>
    <meta content="03sketch" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/realestate/03sketch.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851825"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SKETCH PAD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lofts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lofts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403EEDB1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1161" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Using Wood to Define an Open Space</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Using Wood to Define an Open Space</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRACIE ROZHON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DAVID HOWELL, a Manhattan architect, stood looking at the old brick loft building at 295 Third Avenue, between 22nd and 23rd Streets, his gaze traveling up from the street-level bar to the tall windows above.</p>
        <p>Although a photograph of the third-floor space appeared with its description online -- a condominium loft with four windows facing west, listed for $775,000 -- it was hard to judge whether it would seem cramped or spacious inside. And what, if anything, could be done to redesign a roughly 35-foot-by-20-foot rectangle with 11-foot ceilings? In a way, this loft presented a bigger challenge than a space full of dormers and towers and a complex web of tiny rooms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Manhattan architect redesigns a condominium loft, addressing a question potential buyers have been asking themselves: What to do with the empty space?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DAVID HOWELL, a Manhattan architect, stood looking at the old brick loft building at 295 Third Avenue, between 22nd and 23rd Streets, his gaze traveling up from the street-level bar to the tall windows above.</p>
        <p>Although a photograph of the third-floor space appeared with its description online -- a condominium loft with four windows facing west, listed for $775,000 -- it was hard to judge whether it would seem cramped or spacious inside. And what, if anything, could be done to redesign a roughly 35-foot-by-20-foot rectangle with 11-foot ceilings? In a way, this loft presented a bigger challenge than a space full of dormers and towers and a complex web of tiny rooms.</p>
        <p>The building dates from about 1900, and after the climb up two very steep sets of stairs (no one with vertigo need apply), it seemed clear that this particular loft needed something: any original details had been cleared out, and there was a huge plastered structure in the middle, blocking the views from the entrance. The structure held a loft bed, with sprinkler pipes about a foot from the sleeper's nose. (Did someone actually design this awkward situation, or were the pipe and sprinkler added afterward?)</p>
        <p>Yet the loft's virtues were also immediately apparent. Besides the convenient location in the Gramercy Park area, it was wide, and not too deep. The sunlight from the four front windows reached back to the entrance door -- very unusual. And the 1970s-style renovation aside, the proportions were terrific. Wouldn't it be nice to toss out everything and just use the big space for entertaining? But where would you put the bedroom? And the bathroom? And the kitchen?</p>
        <p>Young loft buyers, often accompanied by their parents, were asking the same questions, said Rex Gonsalves, a Halstead Property agent who is listing the apartment. ''People are intrigued,'' he said. ''They sit here for two hours. They can't exactly fathom what to do with the empty space.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Howell vowed to find a solution, but he warned that it wouldn't be cheap.</p>
        <p>''As real estate values go up and up, people become more willing to invest more in renovations -- they'll get it back when they go to sell,'' Mr. Howell said. ''They want contemporary lines, plain furnishings and a modern sensibility.''</p>
        <p>He paused. ''The last thing we want to do,'' he said, ''is create a suburban, corridor-ridden space.''</p>
        <p>Not a chance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Howell was born in New Zealand and first traveled to the United States in 1992 on a Queen Elizabeth II Arts Council Grant. He fell in love with Manhattan and now has a staff of 14 in his office, in an old building next to Barnes &amp; Noble on Union Square.</p>
        <p>One week later, Mr. Howell produced his finished renderings, and they combined elements of old and new, even though the ''old'' -- the addition of dozens of ceiling beams placed close together -- was jazzy and contemporary. In the ceiling, strip lighting is concealed behind the beams, placed randomly and creating patterns.</p>
        <p>What had been a bland, predictable arrangement was turned on its head. The existing kitchen, visible the second that one walked in the door, has been swiveled around to face into the main living space. A huge table, which appears to flip down from the kitchen wall, is suspended from the ceiling by a series of bronze rods.</p>
        <p>The bathroom, formerly hidden in a back corner, has been placed just to the left of the entrance hall and has been encased in a milky glass box. ''You'll be able to see people moving around in there,'' Mr. Howell said, ''but not much more than that.''</p>
        <p>That gave the ''hidden'' spot -- as much as anything in a loft is hidden -- to the bedroom, which now becomes the most private part of the space.</p>
        <p>Mr. Howell has completely camouflaged the old wooden floor, covering it with epoxied concrete. It runs down the right side of the space and into the bedroom and bath. This wide space, clear most of the time, could double as a long dining room, full of round tables, for a dinner party.</p>
        <p>The rest of the living space, up to the width of three of the four windows, is to be covered in a continuous roll of reclaimed oak planks, stained dark. The wood starts at the top of the windows, flowing downward in separate horizontal pieces, a take on old-fashioned Venetian blinds. A bench sits across the front wall, covering the bottoms of the three windows. Then the wood becomes the living room floor, continuing under both the bench and the suspended table and eventually sweeping up to form the back of a sloping kitchen wall.</p>
        <p>Finally, the wood wraps over the bathroom, suspended by the same type of bronze rods, to create a ceiling or even a floor for a second-level guest bed.</p>
        <p>The design, if carried out, would render the loft sleek and stylish.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people who came to see it have been scared of renovations,'' said Mr. Gonsalves, the agent. ''Mom and Dad are going to pay, but how much would it cost?'' Now they know. If they like Mr. Howell's ultra-modern scheme: about $250,000, plus his fee.</p>
        <p>For those who still have money left, there are even more possibilities. Mr. Gonsalves said a small room at the back of the loft -- reached by a door in the hallway -- might be available for sale. Put a bathroom there, perhaps?</p>
        <p>And not only that. An entire apartment adjoining this one, facing the back, is also for sale. It is listed at $625,000 and could give the buyer a floor-through.</p>
        <p>The great expanse of dark wood that Mr. Howell envisions -- creating ''shutters'' filtering light from the windows, rolling down across the living room and up to make the rear kitchen wall -- makes sense.</p>
        <p>''To insert a continuous object is smoother and sleeker than to break the space up into pieces,'' he said. ''The furnishings add storage and seating and a place to show off the art.''</p>
        <p>He could have left the existing wood floor, though. It had a charm of its own.</p>
        <p>''Yes, I know,'' he said. ''But it's so much more fun to design absolutely everything.''</p>
        <p>THE SPECS  Sketch Pad focuses on an apartment, house, loft or shack now for sale that has unrealized potential. Each month, a different architect or designer is asked to create a vision of what the place might look like.</p>
        <p>There are no guarantees that the plans would be approved by co-op boards, municipal building departments or planning boards. But they can help real estate shoppers learn to see past ugly paint, too-small kitchens and a warren of rooms.</p>
        <p>ARCHITECTS  David Howell  (212) 477-7700</p>
        <p>PROPERTY  A 770-square-foot walk-up loft at 295  Third Avenue (23rd Street)  Price: $775,000</p>
        <p>RENOVATION COST  $250,000  includes new floors, ceiling, kitchen and bathroom enclosed in translucent glass</p>
        <p>REAL ESTATE AGENTS  Rex Gonsalves (212) 381-4245  Ivana Tagliamonte (212) 381-6575  Halstead Property</p>
        <p>SKETCH PAD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
