<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bugs and Trees, Up Close and Luminous</title>
    <meta content="03artsnjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03artsnj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851793"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Noyes Museum of Art (Oceanville, NJ)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genocchio, Benjamin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starn, Doug</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starn, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Noyes Museum of Art</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Starn, Mike</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E2DC1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="732" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bugs and Trees, Up Close and Luminous</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bugs and Trees, Up Close and Luminous</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN GENOCCHIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genocchio, Benjamin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Benjamin Genocchio reviews recent photographs by Doug and Mike Starn on view at Noyes Museum of Art in Oceanville, NJ; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The summer program of the Noyes Museum of Art in Oceanville has gotten into full swing early this year with ''Recent Works by Doug and Mike Starn,'' an inviting exhibition of more than three dozen photographs by the twin brothers, who work together as a collaborative team. Born in Absecon in 1961, they attended college in Boston, then moved to New York, where they were feted and fawned over in the 1980s. They have kept a low profile since then, and their work has benefited as a result.</p>
        <p>The Starn twins are masters of appealingly lyrical photographs of nature, their images rich in feeling and metaphor. The two series of photographs represented here are very much in this mold, filling galleries on the lower and upper areas of the split-level building. Their resonance is magnified as you gaze out the windows onto sweeping views of a pond and the adjoining wildlife refuge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An exhibit at the Noyes Museum of Art in Oceanville features works by Doug and Mike Starn, who are masters of appealingly lyrical photographs of nature.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The summer program of the Noyes Museum of Art in Oceanville has gotten into full swing early this year with ''Recent Works by Doug and Mike Starn,'' an inviting exhibition of more than three dozen photographs by the twin brothers, who work together as a collaborative team. Born in Absecon in 1961, they attended college in Boston, then moved to New York, where they were feted and fawned over in the 1980s. They have kept a low profile since then, and their work has benefited as a result.</p>
        <p>The Starn twins are masters of appealingly lyrical photographs of nature, their images rich in feeling and metaphor. The two series of photographs represented here are very much in this mold, filling galleries on the lower and upper areas of the split-level building. Their resonance is magnified as you gaze out the windows onto sweeping views of a pond and the adjoining wildlife refuge.</p>
        <p>The upper-level gallery has several photographs and photographic collages from the artists' ongoing ''Attracted to Light'' series, most of which are close-ups of moths, flies and insects buzzing around a lamp in upstate New York. They were photographed at night using a camera with a three-foot-long telephoto lens.</p>
        <p>In some cases, the bugs are little more than blurs. But in other cases the pictures capture a mind-blowing level of detail, the cumulative impact of which is substantial -- a sense of terror, mostly, especially where the artists have dramatically enlarged a negative to the point where the bugs in the printed imagery become the size of small cars. Suddenly the bugs start to look like menacing dinosaurs. Yikes.</p>
        <p>What is also interesting about this series is the unusual way the photographs are printed. The artists experimented for 18 months with liquid silver emulsion and various kinds of paper and printing processes to refine their technique. Such opulent fixation on process and materials has resulted in delicately smoky black-and-white images printed on sheets of wafer-thin, mottled handmade Thai mulberry paper. In their delicacy and dusty coloring, they vaguely resemble butterfly wings.</p>
        <p>What you feel most in the presence of these ethereal images is a sense of wonder at the marvels and diversity of the bug kingdom and a swooning pleasure in the mysterious, foglike density of the prints. They are immensely seductive, even if the imagery falls somewhere between art and a kind of old-fashioned amateur-naturalist taxonomical project. You might say it is both art and science.</p>
        <p>At the gallery entrance stands a table with a stack of test prints, for those who want to handle the delicate paper or run their fingers across the ghostly imagery of the moths. Children will be thrilled, as will those smitten with a how-did-they-do-that kind of curiosity.</p>
        <p>There is a bit more heft to the pictures in the second gallery. Sumptuous and vibrant, they are from the artists' ''Structure of Thought'' series showing silhouettes of trees, whose signal quality -- call it a heightened romanticism -- epitomizes a great deal of nature photography these days. While the subject is defiantly traditional, the technique is once again boldly experimental.</p>
        <p>To make these images, the artists began by coating a regular print of a silhouette of trees with wax. A second print on tissue paper was laid on top of the first, then coated with more layers of wax. Finally, a second photograph of another tree was printed on a thin layer of paper that was saturated with varnish and then laid over the existing image. Typically, this final layer gives the photographs an intense luminosity.</p>
        <p>Although they can sometimes look a bit like high-end postcards, these collage-photos are infallibly elegant and lovely; indeed, the best of them are magical, the twisting, threadlike structure of the branches turning almost angelic in silhouette. Then there is the dimmed, yellowish light opposing the starkly isolated inky shadow of the twining trees. It is almost as if the sky were preparing to be swept by some sort of apocalyptic rain, or as if a portal in time were about to open.</p>
        <p>There are perhaps too many silhouette photographs packed into the second gallery, which detracts from the impact of the stronger pictures. Sometimes less is more, especially when artwork is so thoroughly absorbing.</p>
        <p>''Recent Works by Doug and Mike Starn,'' the Noyes Museum of Art, Lily Lake Road, Oceanville, through Aug. 5. Information: (609) 652-8848 or noyesmuseum.org.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
