<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shepherding the Suburban Returnees</title>
    <meta content="03RgenLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03Rgen.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851729"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GENERATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hirshey, Gerri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E3D71430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1281" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shepherding the Suburban Returnees</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shepherding the Suburban Returnees</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERRI HIRSHEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hirshey, Gerri</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gerri Hirshey Generations essay praises her friend, Ellen, who grew up in suburbs of Connecticut, had career in Manhattan and returned to raise her family and show her many friends how to embrace suburbs; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN my parents moved us from a cramped apartment in an aging industrial city out to a raw new development in the suburbs, it seemed like Disney's Frontierland -- without Uncle Walt's thoughtful amenities. Dad took the Chevy to work, so the rest of us walked everywhere at first. The nearest loaf of bread was about a mile away. My mother adored her new pink ranch with the blue-tiled bathroom, but she missed the corner store and her sisters a short walk away. In a weak moment, as we struggled toward town against a mean November wind with my little brother, she yelled into the gale, ''How do people live here?''</p>
        <p>A generation later, as my husband and I moved back out from Manhattan, two wee ones in tow, I understood her discomfiture. I knew the lay of the land; I'd grown up in the adjacent town. But, staring at a local newspaper listing announcing napkin-folding classes, not possessed of sufficient bonhomie for Newcomers Club sock hops, I howled, too: Where can you get a bottle of decent Vietnamese fish sauce? Why are they still selling -- and wearing -- the lime green golf slacks embossed with spouting whales that I hooted at in high school?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even those who have lived in the suburbs as children can use a wise guide when they return as parents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN my parents moved us from a cramped apartment in an aging industrial city out to a raw new development in the suburbs, it seemed like Disney's Frontierland -- without Uncle Walt's thoughtful amenities. Dad took the Chevy to work, so the rest of us walked everywhere at first. The nearest loaf of bread was about a mile away. My mother adored her new pink ranch with the blue-tiled bathroom, but she missed the corner store and her sisters a short walk away. In a weak moment, as we struggled toward town against a mean November wind with my little brother, she yelled into the gale, ''How do people live here?''</p>
        <p>A generation later, as my husband and I moved back out from Manhattan, two wee ones in tow, I understood her discomfiture. I knew the lay of the land; I'd grown up in the adjacent town. But, staring at a local newspaper listing announcing napkin-folding classes, not possessed of sufficient bonhomie for Newcomers Club sock hops, I howled, too: Where can you get a bottle of decent Vietnamese fish sauce? Why are they still selling -- and wearing -- the lime green golf slacks embossed with spouting whales that I hooted at in high school?</p>
        <p>Bratty? Yep. Self-indulgent? You bet. If my parents were willing postwar pioneers out here, my generation are balky prodigals -- and most of us are spoiled at that. Many of us have come back kicking and screaming -- for the sake of the children, the schools, the square footage.</p>
        <p>So it was a small miracle when I encountered Ellen. Like me, she had grown up in southern Connecticut, fled to an engaging Manhattan career and then returned, mit kinder.</p>
        <p>We met 11 years ago in our children's preschool and bonded over a weekly lunch-and-library story hour. The children involved are now in high school. And I am far more at ease amid these wooded hills and vinyl-sided strip malls for having known this small, curly-haired dynamo. Ellen's special grace: Instead of raging at the dying of the 24-hour deli lights, she embraced the quiet -- and hit the road. She went looking for stimulation -- cultural and culinary -- wherever life found her. Here in the precision-sodded fields of complacency, she remains relentlessly curious, a tireless ex-urban flâneur in a Toyota minivan.</p>
        <p>Alone, or with a sidekick like me, Ellen explores. She will pilot you to a tiny restaurant wrapped around a gourmet chocolate factory where you can watch the semisweet artistry as you lunch. She knows where there's a Tuscan cooking teacher willing to roll gnocchi with third graders. Ellen and her family visit galleries, orchards and monasteries, maritime centers and fondue joints. She mines those giveaway fliers at the library for the locally weird and wonderful. As a result, her two kids are self-starters as well. On any given Saturday, that frosty juvenile exhalation ''I'm bored'' never chills their family hearth.</p>
        <p>There is a practical side to Ellen's inquisitive mien. Developed long before an Ohio woman hit Internet pay dirt by turning her local consumer expertise into ''Angie's List,'' Ellen's roster of the best (and worst to avoid) service providers has been my mainstay. Need a gentle but high-tech dentist? A tree guy? A new well pump? A gynecologist? She vets them all with a Nader-like zeal. As her consumer acolyte, I am thrilled when I can reciprocate with referrals of my own -- a simpatico computer techie, a great Asian market tucked away in a moribund mall.</p>
        <p>Of course, I prefer the fun stuff. I have learned not to hesitate when Ellen -- up at the crack of dawn, like me -- e-mails at 6 a.m.: Found a great place for breakfast. Venezuelan beach food. Meet me at 9?</p>
        <p>Fully caffeinated, hands wrapped around a hot, savory arepa filled with fennel and melting queso blanco, I marvel anew. How'd you find this place?</p>
        <p>Often, her answer begins, ''Well, I was curious. '' The proprietor of the Venezuelan eatery catered a theater-and-lunch event that Ellen had volunteered to usher for -- just to see what it was like. His empanaditas were killer; they got to talking.</p>
        <p>With two kids in elementary school, Ellen was one of the first docents at a new children's museum. At the middle school, she helped match over 100 kids in a mentorship program with local professionals, from auto mechanics to neurosurgeons, ''because it's fun to see what kinds of jobs people do out here.''</p>
        <p>Besides raising her family, volunteerism is her steadfast but low-key avocation. It's not the sort of service that turns others into shrill, bossy ''room parents'' with draconian cupcake prohibitions and a different colored marker for each assigned task. Nor is it pious; Ellen's sense of humor is too wicked, her tolerance for fools too scant. For her, volunteerism is a natural urge, and somewhat of a family tradition.</p>
        <p>This I came to understand as I listened to a host of inconsolable speakers at the funeral service for Ellen's father, a much-loved and longstanding volunteer at a local hospital. His specialty: taking pediatric pre-op patients on hospital tours so engaging and humane that the kids forgot to be afraid.</p>
        <p>I knew, when I left off a pot of chili for Ellen's grieving family, that my own father had begun his slow dying in our same little ranch house. Like Ellen's dad, he was supported by neighbors of 40 years who had, as young men, helped one another coax lawns from hardpan plots that the cheesy developers had denuded of topsoil. They ponied up taxes for new schools to contain their wave of offspring.</p>
        <p>Now, as these patriarchs of suburbia pass on, they are properly mourned by communities. They have burial plots. In our little town full of newcomers and corporate ''relos,'' the Colonial-era cemeteries are full; there are debates as to whether to sanction a new one. Few of us expect to die here. The split levels and raised ranches our parents paid off -- over 30 years, at a traditional fixed rate -- are teardowns to my incoming ilk. Real estate agents here tell me they sell no ''forever'' houses.</p>
        <p>By virtue of this motile adulthood, we returning sons and daughters -- willfully deracinated, overscheduled, over-thinking and perhaps overreaching -- are a much looser daisy chain. Relo has already cost me the comforts of close friends out here. Ellen says she's not going anywhere, and I cling to that promise. It is only when I am with her in a greater pond -- a school event, a restaurant -- that I realize how wide a net she's cast. She has lots of fans besides me -- and she knows what their favorite things are, too.</p>
        <p>A few years back, while most of her friends on the precipice of 40 were wallowing in self-pity and enriched moisturizer, Ellen decided to celebrate that milestone by tossing a potluck at her home ''so all my friends can meet each other.'' In the women trooped on that December night: college friends, fellow school volunteers, high school pals, tennis partners, old neighbors -- many of us suburban returnees.</p>
        <p>We uncovered our salads and gratins and shared recognitions and overlaps like some gabby, animated Venn diagram. (''Oh, you're the one with the twins in sixth grade.'') We pounced on a buffet that Ellen would collect the recipes from -- and pass along. Most of us obeyed the ''absolutely no presents'' edict, but of course the birthday queen sent us all away with little mementos.</p>
        <p>Ellen looked happy in the candlelight, but she would not countenance any fussy toasts. We should have overruled her. On behalf of that grateful sisterhood, I salute her now: All blessings to our steadfast Suburban Optimist, who showed us the way to go home.</p>
        <p>GENERATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
