<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cameras Were Ready; The Revolution Wasn't</title>
    <meta content="03ridi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/movies/03ridi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851697"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Vaslui (Romania)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Romania</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riding, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Porumboiu, Corneliu</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ceausescu, Nicolae (1918-89)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">12:08 East of Bucharest (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Romania</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E4DB1430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1185" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cameras Were Ready; The Revolution Wasn't</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cameras Were Ready; The Revolution Wasn’t</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riding, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Romanian director Corneliu Porumboiu grew up in town of Vaslui, where he watched overthrow of Communist dictator Nicolae Ceausescu on television; his new film 12:08 East of Bucharest is comedy in which residents of Vaslui recount dubious claims of revolutionary heroism; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AMONG the anti-Communist revolutions that swept Eastern Europe in late 1989, that of Romania stood out, not for its velvety idealism, but for its violence -- the country's Stalinist tyrant Nicolae Ceausescu was summarily executed -- and for its confusion. Even now there is no consensus over what actually happened. Instead -- built around television images, blurred memories and fantasy -- there are myriad conflicting accounts of how Romania recovered its freedom. Yes, there must have been heroes, but where are they?</p>
        <p>In his first feature film, ''12:08 East of Bucharest,'' which opens Wednesday at Film Forum in New York, Corneliu Porumboiu goes in search of them, not on the streets of Timisoara, where the national mutiny erupted, or in Bucharest, where the revolution culminated, but in his hometown, Vaslui in eastern Romania, where heroism was apparently in short supply.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his first feature film, “12:08 East of Bucharest,” Corneliu Porumboiu goes in search of answers to how Romania recovered its freedom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AMONG the anti-Communist revolutions that swept Eastern Europe in late 1989, that of Romania stood out, not for its velvety idealism, but for its violence -- the country's Stalinist tyrant Nicolae Ceausescu was summarily executed -- and for its confusion. Even now there is no consensus over what actually happened. Instead -- built around television images, blurred memories and fantasy -- there are myriad conflicting accounts of how Romania recovered its freedom. Yes, there must have been heroes, but where are they?</p>
        <p>In his first feature film, ''12:08 East of Bucharest,'' which opens Wednesday at Film Forum in New York, Corneliu Porumboiu goes in search of them, not on the streets of Timisoara, where the national mutiny erupted, or in Bucharest, where the revolution culminated, but in his hometown, Vaslui in eastern Romania, where heroism was apparently in short supply.</p>
        <p>Still, he gives Vaslui a chance -- of sorts. In a comedy that fits into that absurdist corner of the psyche known as Balkan humor, Mr. Porumboiu revisits the exact moment that Ceausescu fled Bucharest -- 12:08 p.m. on Dec. 22, 1989 -- and invites Vaslui to take its place in history.</p>
        <p>The film fares better than Vaslui. ''12:08'' won the Camera d'Or for best first feature at last year's Cannes Film Festival and in a sense paved the way for the Romanian new wave's great triumph to date: last Sunday Mr. Porumboiu's countryman Cristian Mungiu won the Palme d'Or, the top prize at Cannes, for ''4 Months, 3 Weeks and 2 Days.''</p>
        <p>When it came to turning the clock back to 1989, however, Mr. Porumboiu was not much helped by his own memories. Now 32, he was only 14 at the time of the revolution. ''I was playing Ping-Pong with a friend at 12:08,'' he said in a telephone interview from Bucharest.</p>
        <p>But he remembers his parents and their friends glued to the television as the flight of Ceausescu and his much-reviled wife, Elena, was followed by their arrest, their trial by a military tribunal and, on Christmas Day 1989, their hurried execution (also shown on television).</p>
        <p>''It was like watching a thriller,'' Mr. Porumboiu said.</p>
        <p>And so it was that television, long devoted to numbing Romania with official propaganda, came to be identified with revolution. And many years later, long after Mr. Porumboiu had exchanged plans for a career in management for the dream of making movies, it was again television that connected him to the events of 1989.</p>
        <p>Watching a program in 1999 in which six people were asked to recount ''their'' revolution, he imagined his own fictional version of such a program. And when he finally came round to making it, after finishing film school in Bucharest, he set it in wintry Vaslui on the eve of the 16th anniversary of the revolution.</p>
        <p>Before the movie's debate goes live at the local television station, Mr. Porumboiu, who also wrote the screenplay, introduces the unlikely participants, starting with the moderator, Virgil Jderescu (Teodor Corban), the television station's owner, who is looking anxiously for witnesses able to address the key question: ''Was there a revolution or not in our town?''</p>
        <p>Fortunately (or perhaps not) he finds Tiberiu Manescu (Ion Sapdaru), a drunken schoolteacher, who claims to have joined three other ''heroes'' in shouting, ''Down with Ceausescu!'' in the main square in front of Town Hall before 12:08 p.m. on Dec. 22, 1989. Also on the program, almost by accident, is Emanoil Piscoci (Mircea Andreescu), a distracted geezer best known in town as a Santa Claus of last resort.</p>
        <p>The problem is that neither Jderescu nor Piscoci believes Manescu's version. And when Jderescu invites telephone calls, there is no shortage of people ready to testify that no one entered the square on Dec. 22 until after 12:08 p.m., when of course it was suddenly safe to cheer the fall of the dictatorship.</p>
        <p>So was there a revolution at all? Well, Mr. and Mrs. Ceausescu were certainly dispatched to another place, but what followed was a very slow transition rather than sudden change. Many former Communists, reinventing themselves as democrats, were soon again running Romania. There were also no trials of members of Ceausescu's infamous Securitate secret police.</p>
        <p>''When Ceausescu was dead, he was guilty of everything,'' Mr. Porumboiu said. ''If he is dead, we are safe now. A commission was formed to blame the Communists, but it caused a big scandal here. A lot of people said it was not true. We have difficulty in dealing with the past, that's for sure.''</p>
        <p>In one sense the country's entry into the European Union this year has made it easier to forget what happened before 1989. Yet if Romanians prefer to look forward, now thinking of themselves first and foremost as Europeans, Mr. Porumboiu has at least reminded them that the past is unresolved or rather, as he puts it, it has been turned into fiction.</p>
        <p>''I was interested in dealing with these small histories,'' he went on, ''how people perceive history because each one tried to prove himself and prove his acts through this moment. And they make their own version of history.''</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Porumboiu has added his own droll version through what he calls ''reconstructing reality.'' And for authenticity he shot the movie's debate scenes with a fixed camera -- he said he imagined the cameraman as the raconteur -- in a studio of one of Vaslui's three television stations.</p>
        <p>But if television is this director's accomplice in ''12:08,'' the popularity of television in Romania today is also an obstacle to young moviemakers who have discovered relatively little domestic demand for art-house films.</p>
        <p>For instance, to finance his $300,000 film, which he also produced, Mr. Porumboiu had to improvise, persuading a milk factory, a hotel, a vegetable oil producer and a bakery to invest in the adventure. And in the end it drew an audience of only 13,000 when it played in Romania.</p>
        <p>''The people who liked the movie said they liked it,'' Mr. Porumboiu noted stoically, ''and the people who didn't like the movie didn't say anything.''</p>
        <p>Yet for all that, ''12:08'' has confirmed the emergence of a new Romanian cinema. From before the revolution, only the work of the long-exiled director, Lucian Pintilie, stands out. But in the last couple of years, along with Mr. Porumboiu, several other Romanian directors have won praise abroad, notably Cristi Puiu for ''The Death of Mr. Lazarescu,'' Catalin Mitulescu for ''How I Spent the End of the World'' and most recently Mr. Mungiu with ''4 Months, 3 Weeks and 2 Days.'' Their number also includes Cristian Nemescu, who died in a car accident last year at 27, and whose ''California Dreamin' '' just won the top prize in Cannes' Certain Regard section. ''12:08,'' then, is hardly an isolated phenomenon.</p>
        <p>''Porumboiu belongs to a tradition which cultivates like few others a macabre smile, a destructive lucidity, a tragic absurdity and a refined misanthropy,'' Le Monde's film critic, Jacques Mandelbaum, wrote. He added: ''Dwelling on human pettiness, this admirably modest film brings together Gogol and Beckett.''</p>
        <p>And of course, not for the first time, it celebrates Balkan humor as a weapon of survival.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
