<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Town Hall, an Arboreal Tug of War</title>
    <meta content="03mainctCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03mainct.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851778"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC SPACE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demolition</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Stamford (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barnes, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nakian, Reuben (1897-1986)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Malone, Matthew J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Machinery and Equipment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0DD1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="901" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Town Hall, an Arboreal Tug of War</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Town Hall, an Arboreal Tug of War</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW J. MALONE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Malone, Matthew J</byline>
      <dateline>STAMFORD</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on dispute over plan by Ben Barnes, director of operations of Government Center in Stamford, Conn, to remove stand of honey locust trees outside building to make room for bronze sculpture by Reuben Nakian; majority of critics cite environmental impact of removing trees rather than objection to another display of art by Nakian; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE yellow fliers appeared on a stand of honey locusts outside town hall in April, 16 days before Arbor Day. Unless a written appeal was filed, the fliers said, the trees could be cut down in 30 days.</p>
        <p>When the local newspaper reported on the fliers, the letter writers went to work, and what began as an attempt to display a work by Reuben Nakian, one of the 20th century's most distinguished sculptors -- and a man who called Stamford home for more than four decades -- turned into a small-scale environmental showdown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stamford.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE yellow fliers appeared on a stand of honey locusts outside town hall in April, 16 days before Arbor Day. Unless a written appeal was filed, the fliers said, the trees could be cut down in 30 days.</p>
        <p>When the local newspaper reported on the fliers, the letter writers went to work, and what began as an attempt to display a work by Reuben Nakian, one of the 20th century's most distinguished sculptors -- and a man who called Stamford home for more than four decades -- turned into a small-scale environmental showdown.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, the city was lent ''Sea Odyssey,'' a 10-foot-tall, 8-foot-wide bronze sculpture by Mr. Nakian, who lived and worked in the city from 1945 until his death in 1986 at the age of 89. The Long Island couple who owned the work were moving and no longer had room to display it.</p>
        <p>So with the help of Mr. Nakian's son, Paul, a lawyer, they arranged for a long-term loan to the city. Ben Barnes, the city's director of operations, moved quickly to find a suitable home. A sculpture garden planned along the Mill River, which is scheduled to undergo a multimillion-dollar restoration, was years away from being ready. But Mr. Barnes said he thought the Stamford Government Center, which sits on a busy thoroughfare downtown, might be appropriate -- minus the cluster of trees in the front courtyard.</p>
        <p>''The idea that the trees were overgrown beyond the size that's appropriate for that location is not a new idea,'' Mr. Barnes said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barnes said he had always planned to present design options to the public and that he posted the fliers to get the process rolling, with the hope that the sculpture would be in place by summer. But after the local paper, The Advocate, ran a story about the tree-cutting plan, the response made him realize he had struck a nerve.</p>
        <p>Over the last several weeks, the paper has published a steady stream of letters criticizing the plan, with a majority protesting the environmental impact rather than objecting to another display of Mr. Nakian's art (four of his sculptures already grace public streets in Stamford).</p>
        <p>''Trees are beautiful, and cutting one down for cosmetic reasons is a disrespectful and an ungodly thing to do,'' wrote one resident, Angie Ramirez.</p>
        <p>Robert F. Neu, a former city tree warden, said permanently losing trees to make way for a temporary display was a bad idea. ''I don't see any malicious intent by the city fathers to pull down trees,'' he said. ''I think sometimes these things get away from them and something is done and you can't get it back.''</p>
        <p>The outcry prompted a committee of the city's board of representatives to propose legislation granting the board control over the fate of any healthy trees in front of the government building. Under the proposal, if the city's tree warden rejects appeals from residents not to remove the trees, the representatives would have the right to overrule the decision. The board may take up the ordinance this week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barnes says he was surprised by the strength of the opposition to the tree removal, and plans a comprehensive public hearing sometime this summer.</p>
        <p>Of the fliers, he said: ''With 20/20 hindsight, should I not have posted them right before Arbor Day? Probably not.''</p>
        <p>The Mill River restoration project puts even more trees in Stamford at risk. On Arbor Day, April 27, the city celebrated the 50th anniversary of the planting of nearly 100 cherry trees along the riverbank. A Japanese immigrant donated the trees as a thank-you to the city that became his home.</p>
        <p>Most of the trees might not survive to the 52nd anniversary. The restoration calls for the reconstruction of the river banks, which are now concrete walls, and requires that most of the trees be cut down. A local tree foundation got the city to agree to replant six of the trees and hopes to persuade them to save several more.</p>
        <p>Reuben Nakian left behind a prodigious collection of nude sketches, bronze portrait busts and large sculptures, many of which he produced in his Stamford studio. He created ''Sea Odyssey'' in 1984. The sculpture depicts a woman appearing as though she's running, her arms raised, with three dolphins dancing around her. It remains to be seen whether ''Sea Odyssey'' will find a home at the town hall. But the outcry should come as no surprise, said Mary Ludwig, who becomes president of the Connecticut Urban Forest Council, a state-sponsored land management group, this month. Ms. Ludwig said trees tended to take a back seat to development, a reality that neglects both their environmental value in absorbing carbon emissions and their aesthetic appeal.</p>
        <p>''I don't go around hugging trees, but at the same time, I can't imagine what the world would be like if everything was clear cut,'' Ms. Ludwig said.</p>
        <p>Paul Nakian, the artist's son, said that he's a tree lover, too -- he belongs to the local arboretum -- and that he hoped the city could work out a plan for installing ''Sea Odyssey'' downtown that incorporates trees, whether the honey locusts or new plantings. If the trees are too overgrown, he said, the sculpture and new landscaping would be a great way to spruce up the courtyard.</p>
        <p>''It's like a poodle,'' he said. ''If you don't groom it, it's going to be a shaggy dog.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC SPACE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
