<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boy to Man, a Life in Planes</title>
    <meta content="03boss" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/business/yourmoney/03boss.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851914"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="JOBS: THE BOSS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/The Boss</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Careers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Human Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">AirTran Holdings</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E0D81330F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="815" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boy to Man, a Life in Planes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Boy to Man, a Life in Planes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LEONARD; As told to Patricia R. Olsen.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olsen, Patricia R; Leonard, Joe</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GROWING up, I lived behind an airport in Augusta, Ga. All I had to do was climb over a fence. I'd sit in the planes and pretend I was flying, until someone chased me out.</p>
        <p>When I was 11, I started washing and gassing the airplanes. I got 75 cents an hour but I never saw any of it. I was paid in flying time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“When I was 11, I started washing and gassing the airplanes,” said Joe Leonard, chairman and chief executive of AirTran. “I was paid in flying time.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GROWING up, I lived behind an airport in Augusta, Ga. All I had to do was climb over a fence. I'd sit in the planes and pretend I was flying, until someone chased me out.</p>
        <p>When I was 11, I started washing and gassing the airplanes. I got 75 cents an hour but I never saw any of it. I was paid in flying time.</p>
        <p>I got a degree in aerospace engineering at Auburn University and in the late 1960s became a flight test engineer for Boeing. I was responsible for the 737 target thrust reverser test program. (Thrust reversers slow the plane after touchdown.)</p>
        <p>We were doing high-speed runs where we accelerated to landing speed and stopped the plane with the reversers. Then we took measurements for the rigorous test requirements of Boeing and the F.A.A.</p>
        <p>We kept calling the tower and complaining that there were rocks on the runway. The maintenance staff would come out and clean them away, and the same thing would happen again. It turned out we were blowing tar residue from along the concrete and blasting tar balls onto the runway. When the controllers told us, we were red-faced.</p>
        <p>After I left Boeing I accepted a position at United as a power plant engineer. Then I got an offer from Northwest Airlines. I called the headhunter who got me the United job and told him I had changed my mind, that I was taking the job with Northwest. He said I had to be out of my mind.</p>
        <p>If I had gone to United I would have been just be another cog in the wheel, but at Northwest I could make a difference and learn more. The guy who got my job at United was laid off six months later.</p>
        <p>At United I would have been responsible for one engine part. Northwest was an extremely lean organization. I was responsible for one engine model and half of another, and I monitored engine conditioning for the entire fleet. The airline also believed in promoting young people. When I was 29, I ran the second-largest organization in the company, line maintenance.</p>
        <p>The C.E.O., Donald Nyrop, was a stickler for detail. He'd quiz you over and over about your operation. It wasn't always fun, but you learned a lot. His motto was ''Keep it simple and say no a lot.'' I've followed that same motto.</p>
        <p>I've been involved in several mergers, starting when I was with Eastern Air Lines. You have to be respectful of the other guy, whether you're being purchased or you're purchasing somebody else. Everybody brings something to the party. When we sold Eastern to Texas Air in 1986, we did it voluntarily because we thought it was best for the company.</p>
        <p>Our negotiations to take over Midwest Airlines have been somewhat different from usual because we have a different idea about their vulnerabilities than they do. Our bid last October was nonsolicited.</p>
        <p>When I joined both Eastern and, in 1999, AirTran, I had a couple of sleepless nights because of the shape the companies were in. I've been in tough situations and improved companies my whole career, but Eastern was a tougher cultural situation than I first thought. The environment was hostile. There were silly rules favoring labor that made the airline unproductive, and we didn't make much progress in getting them changed.</p>
        <p>The cost of fuel has been a main driver in our industry's losses. Five years ago fuel was 15 percent to 18 percent of our costs. Today it's 35 percent. That's difficult to deal with in a short period of time.</p>
        <p>We use future-forward contracts to hedge fuel costs. We've already bought more than a third of our fuel for 2007 and some for 2008. I also think we have a technological advantage. Our average plane is three years old and thus burns less fuel than an older plane.</p>
        <p>We have a fuel conservation program, too. Our pilots taxi in and out on one engine, we run auxiliary power only when necessary, and we lay power cords where the plane stops, instead of dragging them across the ramp, allowing a quicker shift to ground power. We also have air-conditioning at our gates so we can keep the planes cool in summer instead of using the airplane systems.</p>
        <p>At one point, every night before I went to bed I would watch Lou Dobbs to learn the price of fuel. Every morning I'd get up and watch the Weather Channel to find out what the weather was. Those two things have the biggest impact on the airline industry, and I have control over neither.</p>
        <p>JOE LEONARD  Chairman and chief executive, AirTran Airways</p>
        <p>BIRTH DATE  July 10, 1943</p>
        <p>HOMETOWN  Augusta, Ga.</p>
        <p>RECENT VACATION  Family home on a lake in Minnesota</p>
        <p>FAVORITE MOVIE  ''The Aviator''</p>
        <p>JOBS: THE BOSS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
