<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Imported Doesn't Always Mean Important</title>
    <meta content="03ishe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/theater/theaterspecial/03ishe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851716"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER: THE TONYS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Isherwood, Charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Tony Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">London (England)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">National Theater</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Lincoln Center Theater</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Goodman Theater</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E2DB1430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1604" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Imported Doesn't Always Mean Important</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Imported Doesn’t Always Mean Important</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES ISHERWOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Isherwood, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Isherwood article on large number of Broadway plays imported from Britain; successes and failures of current season imports discussed; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE mania for all things British continued unabated this season on Broadway, and there's no reason to believe it will subside anytime soon. The slow slide of the dollar versus the pound notwithstanding, American producers embark on shopping trips to snap up rights to hot London productions with the casual air most of us associate with popping into Duane Reade to pick up a new toothbrush.</p>
        <p>The Anglophilia of the higher-brow New York theater world is hardly new of course. David Merrick and Alexander Cohen, two legendary names in theater producing circles, were known for their assiduity in squiring the hot London shows into the city. Since their deaths the roles have been eagerly assumed by any number of others. It sometimes seems as if half the shows on Broadway are either written by, directed by, or starring British artists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Much of the London-originated product seen in New York this season left me disappointed in one way or another.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE mania for all things British continued unabated this season on Broadway, and there's no reason to believe it will subside anytime soon. The slow slide of the dollar versus the pound notwithstanding, American producers embark on shopping trips to snap up rights to hot London productions with the casual air most of us associate with popping into Duane Reade to pick up a new toothbrush.</p>
        <p>The Anglophilia of the higher-brow New York theater world is hardly new of course. David Merrick and Alexander Cohen, two legendary names in theater producing circles, were known for their assiduity in squiring the hot London shows into the city. Since their deaths the roles have been eagerly assumed by any number of others. It sometimes seems as if half the shows on Broadway are either written by, directed by, or starring British artists.</p>
        <p>But the continuing tide of London-originated plays and productions on Broadway in recent years claimed a few prominent victims this season. As Broadway's big night approaches, perhaps it's proper to spare a sympathetic word for one of the season's more resounding flops, ''Coram Boy,'' the lavish London import about foundlings adrift in 18th-century Britain. Its failure may also be a cautionary tale worth heeding.</p>
        <p>The production has earned a highly respectable six Tony nominations, double the total of the attention-getting ''Frost/Nixon'' -- another London import -- and putting it in the top third of all nominated shows in terms of sheer numbers. But it closed less than a month after opening, losing its reported $6 million capitalization and putting the show among the most expensive failures in the history of plays on Broadway.</p>
        <p>It also received some of the direst reviews of the season, unusual, to say the least, for a production arriving with the stamp of approval reading ''First seen at London's National Theater.'' (Whence came of course last season's Tony darling, ''The History Boys.'')</p>
        <p>Critics seemed to be in an unusually bilious mood when poor ''Coram Boy'' came caroling at the tail end of the season, after its fellow British imports -- ''The Coast of Utopia,'' ''Frost/Nixon'' and ''Journey's End'' -- had received reviews ranging from respectable to ecstatic. Jacques le Sourd, who writes for the Gannett newspaper chain and is, granted, not known for his temperate views, screeched that ''Coram Boy'' ''leaves you feeling like a goose that has been force-fed to make foie gras'' in the first line of his pan. ''In other words, it's torture,'' he helpfully clarified.</p>
        <p>In The New York Post the more sedate Clive Barnes sniffed, ''Absurdity chases absurdity in a not particularly well-acted melodrama.'' (And Mr. Barnes happens to be British.)</p>
        <p>''Coram Boy'' did not excite me, I'll admit, but it didn't excite me to effusions of dispraise either. And yet it did seem unnecessary: an innocuous, old-fashioned melodrama neither interesting enough nor entertaining enough to warrant the lavish expenditure of bringing it to Broadway, with its large cast and Handel-singing chorus.</p>
        <p>But much of the London-originated product seen in New York this season left me disappointed in one way or another. The cumulative effect has left me wondering whether this was simply an off season, or whether all the money being lavished on plays and productions from across the ocean is bringing much in the way of lasting rewards to the Broadway environment.</p>
        <p>''Frost/Nixon'' was an enjoyable but lightweight docudrama notable primarily for a majestically good performance by Frank Langella. In terms of insight into the workings of a mind much analyzed in the last quarter-century, it was less revealing than ''Nixon's Nixon,'' Russell Lees's play revived by the MCC Theater last fall, or ''Secret Honor,'' the play by Donald Freed and Arnold M. Stone that was filmed in 1984 by Robert Altman. In terms of insight into the workings of David Frost's mind -- well, who in the audience really cares about the workings of Mr. Frost's mind?</p>
        <p>The World War I drama ''Journey's End'' was a beautifully restored relic that seemed oddly out of step with the current climate, given its predictable depiction of the horrors of war. (And like ''Coram Boy'' it failed to find an audience this season, despite a far more enthusiastic critical response.) The British playwright David Hare made two appearances on Broadway, but neither one was among his better efforts. His play ''The Vertical Hour,'' a dramatically limp tussle between an American woman (Julianne Moore) and a British man (Bill Nighy) over the ethics of the Iraq war, received tepid reviews and closed early. As a director Mr. Hare must take his share of the responsibility for the theatrical nonevent that was ''The Year of Magical Thinking,'' the uninvolving stage adaptation of Joan Didion's memoir. And the most egregiously unnecessary Brit import was surely the coarse comedy ''Losing Louie'' by Simon Mendes da Costa presented by the Manhattan Theater Club at its Broadway home, the Biltmore.</p>
        <p>You may have noticed I've left out the mother of all this season's British imports, Tom Stoppard's trilogy, ''The Coast of Utopia,'' produced by Lincoln Center Theater and unquestionably the must-have ticket for serious theatergoers. Although Mr. Stoppard's play itself seemed to me a dramatically flaccid slab of aesthetic and political history, the production, directed by Jack O'Brien, revealed how the intimate alliance between the New York and London theater can, at its best, benefit both. Mr. O'Brien's production was, in my view and that of many others who saw them both, far superior to the original at (where else?) the National Theater. It had a warmer pulse than the London version, as Mr. O'Brien's flair for colorful stagecraft helped smooth over the longueurs.</p>
        <p>It also had a vibrant cast of mostly American actors, which brings up another obvious benefit to the New York theater of the rich traffic in British plays on Broadway. In addition to ''The Coast of Utopia,'' with its ample cast of 38 adult actors, ''Coram Boy'' was recast with American actors for its Broadway stand -- some 40, including the chorus. As was, for the most part, ''Journey's End.'' That's a lot of gainful employment for a lot of talented actors in New York.</p>
        <p>But I wonder if the city's playwrights and directors are as enthusiastic about Broadway's continuing infatuation with the British. Three of the four nominees in the play directing category are British: Michael Grandage for ''Frost/Nixon,'' David Grindley for ''Journey's End'' and Melly Still for ''Coram Boy.'' The fourth is Mr. O'Brien, for the British ''Coast of U.'' That production was without doubt the best of the season's imports -- and a pretty safe bet to take the best-play prize at the Tony ceremonies next Sunday. But it did monopolize the resources of one of the city's (indeed the country's) leading nonprofit theaters for a whole season, while two adventurous new plays from young American playwrights, ''The Clean House'' by Sarah Ruhl and ''Dying City'' by Christopher Shinn, played at the company's smaller stage downstairs. (Neither would have filled the Vivian Beaumont, but the company regularly produces at other Broadway houses too.)</p>
        <p>You have to wonder what the many millions of dollars spent on all these productions might have brought in the way of benefits to American writers and artists if such sums were not so regularly channeled east. The lack of important young American playwrights on Broadway is often bemoaned, but an aspiring playwright could well be discouraged that the country's premiere showcase for theater seems to be colonized by the British in such large numbers, season after season.</p>
        <p>If the work being presented was of an unquestionably high caliber, it would be hard to argue that Americans are being relegated to second-class status on Broadway. But it seems lately that the city's most active producers are bringing over some of these productions simply because they are the hot shows in London and Broadway has a few empty theaters that need filling. (Bob Boyett and Bill Haber, lead producers on both ''Coram Boy'' and ''Journey's End,'' have a contract with the National Theater giving them first dibs on transferring its productions to Broadway, although ''Journey's End'' did not originate there.) The questions of intrinsic quality or appeal to American audiences don't always seem to enter into the conversation.</p>
        <p>One of the best things I saw in the last year was Robert Falls's revelatory ''King Lear'' at the Goodman Theater in Chicago, starring Stacy Keach, in the fall. Given that the Public Theater was already scheduled to produce its own ''King Lear,'' with Kevin Kline this spring, chances are that a Broadway transfer of Mr. Falls's production would be a long shot. But I wonder if any of the New York producers racking up all those frequent-flyer miles on scouting trips to London even bothered to check it out. (Unsurprising postscript: Ian McKellen arrives in yet another ''Lear,'' from the Royal Shakespeare Company, at the Brooklyn Academy of Music in September.)</p>
        <p>Broadway is above all a business. Producers can't be expected to support worthy American plays merely for charitable purposes. (And I suppose that those who regularly lose money bringing the work of August Wilson to Broadway would point out that they already do.) But the indiscriminate appetite for bringing all things British to Broadway could eventually sour producers on the British theater as a whole at the same time that it closes off potential opportunities for the development of American artists. A few seasons of flops like ''Coram Boy'' and ''Journey's End'' could be dangerous, leaving disgruntled investors ready to throw out the baby with the bath water, and disgruntled critics ready to pounce the next time a fluty British accent comes wafting across the footlights.</p>
        <p>THEATER: THE TONYS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
