<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Rocking Strings To Detailed Drawings</title>
    <meta content="03arbusliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03arbusli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851725"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">East Hampton Historical Society</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arbus, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cotroneo, Nicole</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE6D71430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="655" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Rocking Strings To Detailed Drawings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From Rocking Strings to Detailed Drawings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICOLE COTRONEO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cotroneo, Nicole</byline>
      <dateline>EAST HAMPTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of and interview with David Arbus, native of Surrey, Eng, who played violin as guest artist on 1971 album by The Who and whose artwork is on view at East Hampton Historical Society's Clinton Academy; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you are a fan of the British rock band the Who, you're probably familiar with David Arbus whether you know it or not. He delivered the searing violin coda to the song ''Baba O'Riley'' -- popularly known as ''Teenage Wasteland'' -- as a guest artist on the group's 1971 album ''Who's Next.'' Since then, Mr. Arbus, a native of Surrey, England, has continually reinvented himself: as a teacher, a model and a furniture maker. For the last decade, he has traded his violin bow for a drawing pen.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arbus, 65, is showing his artwork through June 24 at the East Hampton Historical Society's Clinton Academy. The exhibition, ''Drawn to East Hampton,'' features renderings of local historic buildings and a few portraits in a variety of media.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you are a fan of the British rock band the Who, you’re probably familiar with David Arbus whether you know it or not.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you are a fan of the British rock band the Who, you're probably familiar with David Arbus whether you know it or not. He delivered the searing violin coda to the song ''Baba O'Riley'' -- popularly known as ''Teenage Wasteland'' -- as a guest artist on the group's 1971 album ''Who's Next.'' Since then, Mr. Arbus, a native of Surrey, England, has continually reinvented himself: as a teacher, a model and a furniture maker. For the last decade, he has traded his violin bow for a drawing pen.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arbus, 65, is showing his artwork through June 24 at the East Hampton Historical Society's Clinton Academy. The exhibition, ''Drawn to East Hampton,'' features renderings of local historic buildings and a few portraits in a variety of media.</p>
        <p>In the late 1960s and the '70s, Mr. Arbus and some college friends performed as East of Eden, a progressive rock band that landed a recording contract, produced three albums and toured England and continental Europe, he said.</p>
        <p>After the group disbanded to pursue other projects, Mr. Arbus taught English in Saudi Arabia, where he started sketching buildings and developed a business designing Christmas cards for expatriates and Western companies based in the Middle East.</p>
        <p>After two years Mr. Arbus returned to England and switched careers again, he said, spending the next 15 years designing and building rattan furniture. He also returned briefly to professional music with a stint in a British bluegrass band led by the banjo player Keith Pearson.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arbus said that after deciding that he ''wasn't really a craftsman,'' he stopped making furniture and returned to drawing, while also working as a freelance model in London. He plays violin now only for pleasure, he said.</p>
        <p>Though he has lived around the world -- in Thailand and Spain, among other places -- this is his first time living in the United States, or even visiting. He and his wife, Louise Ventura, and his stepdaughter, Olivia Ventura, 10, arrived in the United States eight months ago, knowing only that they wanted to live in the New York area. They drove up the Hudson River Valley and into Connecticut and almost chose to settle in Greenwich, he said. Then they took a ferry to Long Island and traveled to the East End.</p>
        <p>The area suits him, ''because there's lots of very interesting buildings,'' Mr. Arbus said over coffee recently at the Maidstone Arms, an inn and restaurant dating from the 1700s that has served as the subject of four of the artist's drawings.</p>
        <p>Richard Barons, the executive director of the historical society, invited Mr. Arbus to show his work at the Clinton Academy. The two met while Mr. Arbus was drawing inside the Osborn-Jackson House, an 18th-century building that contains the offices of the society. ''He liked what I was doing and asked if I would like to have an exhibition sponsored by them,'' Mr. Arbus recalled. For the next six months he set to work producing the 65 pieces currently on display.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arbus favors architectural subjects because he likes structure. ''It's a personality thing,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He sketches with soluble ink and uses water to blur the lines, he said. Sometimes he adds pastel or watercolor, a process that he called therapeutic.</p>
        <p>''To use color is to do feeling and emotion,'' he said. ''For me, that's difficult to express, so it's probably good for me to do it. And in the spring and the fall, how can you not work in color?''</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Arbus's favorite portraits shows 88-year-old Marie de Boer, an East Hampton resident and Dutch immigrant, seated in the parlor of her home wearing slippers. Ms. de Boer said she loved the portrait, which is in the show, because ''it's about where I live.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Arbus's wife said his portraits were deliberately anecdotal. ''They show the details of a room,'' she said. ''You're learning about the person through bits and pieces.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
