<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PAPERBACK BEST SELLERS: June 03, 2007</title>
    <meta content="Bestpaper.hardadvice" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="56" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851598"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1D61630F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1116" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PAPERBACK BEST SELLERS: June 03, 2007</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended May 19, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended May 19, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>05,06,64</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  On</p>
        <p>Week  List  FICTION</p>
        <p>1  3  THE HUSBAND, by Dean Koontz. (Bantam, $7.99.) A man whose wife has been kidnapped has 60 hours to come up with a huge ransom.</p>
        <p>2  5  WATER FOR ELEPHANTS, by Sara Gruen. (Algonquin, $13.95.) A young man -- and an elephant -- save a Depression-era circus.</p>
        <p>3  8  THE ROAD, by Cormac McCarthy. (Vintage, $14.95.) A father and son travel in post-apocalypse America.</p>
        <p>4  48  THE MEMORY KEEPER'S DAUGHTER, by Kim Edwards. (Penguin, $14.) A doctor's decision to secretly send his newborn daughter, who has Down syndrome, to an institution haunts everyone involved.</p>
        <p>5  5  THE 5TH HORSEMAN, by James Patterson and Maxine Paetro. (Warner, $14.99.) Detective Lindsay Boxer and the Women's Murder Club investigate unexplained deaths at a San Francisco hospital.</p>
        <p>6  6  Suite FRANÃAISE, by IrÃ</p>
        <p>ne Némirovsky. (Vintage, $14.95.) Two novellas, which came to light more than 50 years after the author's death at Auschwitz, about life in France under the Nazis.</p>
        <p>7  4  SUSANNAH'S GARDEN, by Debbie Macomber. (Mira, $7.99.) A woman returns to her hometown and re-examines the troubling events of her past.</p>
        <p>8  115  THE KITE RUNNER, by Khaled Hosseini. (Riverhead, $15.95 and $14.) An Afghan-American returns to Kabul to learn how a childhood friend has fared under the Taliban.</p>
        <p>9*  3  COVER OF NIGHT, by Linda Howard. (Ballantine, $7.99.) A young widow fights back when intruders storm her bed-and-breakfast in rural Idaho.</p>
        <p>10  4  DEAD WATCH, by John Sandford. (Berkley, $9.99.) A political operative investigates the murder of a former senator.</p>
        <p>11  9  TWO LITTLE GIRLS IN BLUE, by Mary Higgins Clark. (Pocket, $14.99.) A small girl communicates telepathically with her kidnapped twin.</p>
        <p>12  4  THE BOOK OF FATE, by Brad Meltzer. (Warner, $7.99.) The apparent murder of a presidential aide reveals Masonic secrets in Washington and a 200-year-old code invented by Thomas Jefferson.</p>
        <p>13  13  THE ALCHEMIST, by Paulo Coelho. (HarperSanFrancisco, $13.95 and $13.) A tale about the lessons a Spanish shepherd boy learns during his travels to Egypt in search of treasure.</p>
        <p>14  4  BORN IN DEATH, by J. D. Robb. (Berkley, $7.99.) Lt. Eve Dallas investigates the disappearance of a pregnant woman; by Nora Roberts, writing pseudonymously.</p>
        <p>15  9  SNOW FLOWER AND THE SECRET FAN, by Lisa See. (Random House, $13.95.) The lives of two women in 19th-century China.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  On</p>
        <p>Week  List  NONFICTION</p>
        <p>1  1  THE FINAL MOVE BEYOND IRAQ, by Mike Evans. (Frontline, $14.99.) The author, a political conservative, says America should act decisively in confronting radical Islam and restricting Iran's nuclear plans. ()</p>
        <p>2  17  EAT, PRAY, LOVE, by Elizabeth Gilbert. (Penguin Books, $15.) A writer's yearlong journey in search of self takes her to Italy, India and Indonesia.</p>
        <p>3  71  THE GLASS CASTLE, by Jeannette Walls. (Scribner, $14.) The author recalls a bizarre childhood during which she and her siblings were constantly moved from one bleak place to another.</p>
        <p>4  7  BLINK, by Malcolm Gladwell. (Back Bay, $15.99.) The author of ''The Tipping Point'' explores the importance of instinct to the workings of the mind.</p>
        <p>5  30  90 MINUTES IN HEAVEN, by Don Piper with Cecil Murphey. (Revell, $12.99.) A minister on the otherworldly experience he had after an accident.</p>
        <p>6  144  THE TIPPING POINT, by Malcolm Gladwell. (Back Bay/Little, Brown, $14.95.) A journalist's study of social epidemics, otherwise known as fads.</p>
        <p>9  7  STUMBLING ON HAPPINESS, by Daniel Gilbert. (Vintage, $14.95.) A Harvard professor explores why people can't predict what will make them happy.</p>
        <p>65  8  NIGHT, by Elie Wiesel. (Hill &amp; Wang, $9.) The horrors of Auschwitz and Buchenwald.</p>
        <p>9  17  THE MEASURE OF A MAN, by Sidney Poitier. (HarperSanFrancisco, $14.95.) The movie actor's spiritual autobiography.</p>
        <p>10  16  THREE CUPS OF TEA, by Greg Mortenson and David Oliver Relin. (Penguin Books, $15.) A former climber builds schools in Pakistan and Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>4*  11  MAYFLOWER, by Nathaniel Philbrick. (Penguin Books, $16.) How America began, from the author of ''In the Heart of the Sea.''</p>
        <p>12  14  THE YEAR OF MAGICAL THINKING, by Joan Didion. (Vintage, $13.95.) The author's attempts to come to terms with the death of her husband and the grave illness of their only daughter.</p>
        <p>13  3  POSSIBLE SIDE EFFECTS, by Augusten Burroughs. (Picador, $14.) Autobiographical essays from the author of ''Running With Scissors.''</p>
        <p>14  75  DREAMS FROM MY FATHER, by Barack Obama. (Three Rivers, $13.95.) The Democratic senator from Illinois reflects on life as the son of a black African father and a white American mother.</p>
        <p>15  3  ARMED MADHOUSE, by Greg Palast. (Plume, $15.) A collection of articles about the ''war on terror,'' the 2008 election and other topics by an investigative reporter.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  On</p>
        <p>Week  List  Advice, How-to and Miscellaneous: Hardcover</p>
        <p>1  19  THE SECRET, by Rhonda Byrne. (Atria/Beyond Words, $23.95.) The law of attraction as a key to getting what you want.</p>
        <p>2  3  THE DANGEROUS BOOK FOR BOYS, by Conn Iggulden and Hal Iggulden. (Collins/HarperCollins, $24.95.) Skipping stones, tying knots and other essential activities -- video games not included.</p>
        <p>3  2  REPOSITION YOURSELF, by T. D. Jakes. (Atria, $24.) How to grow spiritually and materially by putting faith into action.</p>
        <p>4  1  THE EXCEPTIONAL PRESENTER, by Timothy J. Koegel. (Greenleaf, $21.95.) Techniques for improving your communication skills. ()</p>
        <p>5  25  YOU: ON A DIET, by Michael F. Roizen and Mehmet C. Oz et al. (Free Press, $25.) Weight-loss tips, from the authors of ''You: The Owner's Manual.''</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  On</p>
        <p>Week  List  Advice, How-to and Miscellaneous: Paperback</p>
        <p>1  67  1,000 PLACES TO SEE BEFORE YOU DIE, by Patricia Schultz. (Workman, $18.95.) A guide to travel.</p>
        <p>2  314  WHAT TO EXPECT WHEN YOU'RE EXPECTING, by Heidi Murkoff, Arlene Eisenberg and Sandee Hathaway. (Workman, $13.95.) Advice for parents-to-be. ()</p>
        <p>2  3  THE VOLUMETRICS EATING PLAN, by Barbara Rolls. (Harper, $15.95.) Recipes and techniques for feeling full on fewer calories.</p>
        <p>4  323  RICH DAD, POOR DAD, by Robert T. Kiyosaki with Sharon L. Lechter. (Warner, $16.95.) Teaching one's children how to get rich and stay rich. ()</p>
        <p>5  1  THE VOLUMETRICS WEIGHT-CONTROL PLAN, by Barbara Rolls and Robert A. Barnett. (Harper and HarperTorch, $13 and $6.99.) An approach to eating based on the concept of ''energy density.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
