<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Breakdown</title>
    <meta content="Churchwell.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="52" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/books/review/Churchwell-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851605"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Kavenna, Joanna</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Inglorious (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E0D61630F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="931" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Breakdown</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Breakdown</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH CHURCHWELL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INGLORIOUS</p>
        <p>By Joanna Kavenna.</p>
        <p>286 pp. Metropolitan Books/</p>
        <p>Henry Holt &amp; Company. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A journalist quits her job and watches her life start to unravel after her mother’s death.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INGLORIOUS</p>
        <p>By Joanna Kavenna.</p>
        <p>286 pp. Metropolitan Books/</p>
        <p>Henry Holt &amp; Company. $25.</p>
        <p>Rosa LANE, a successful journalist living a cautious, insulated life in London, finds herself suddenly aware that she has been stuck in a holding pattern: ''Sitting at her desk that day, sweating into her shirt, she thought, If they told me I would never do anything more than this, would I want to live or die on the spot? Then she thought, What is the reason for it all, what is it for?''</p>
        <p>This question may strike some readers as rather belated and jejune, not really enough to send an intelligent 35-year-old into a tailspin, but Rosa quits her job on the spot, determined to discover the meaning of life. It quickly emerges that her sense of dislocation has been precipitated by her mother's death a few months earlier, and that Rosa has not, to say the least, dealt with her emotions in the aftermath. Instead, she catalogs her symptoms: ''Malaise. Intellectual disintegration. Epistemological meltdown. A strange rash on my arms that won't be treated. Hypochondria of the undistilled sort. An aversion to conversation. Acedia plain and simple.''</p>
        <p>The smart-alecky irony of calling acedia ''plain and simple'' is typical of Rosa's sardonic humor, and of how defensive her cleverness can be. Her logorrhea may deflect grief and loss, but it also rebuffs everyone around her.</p>
        <p>Liam, the man Rosa has lived with for 10 years, soon breaks up with her, explaining that he has been waiting for the right time to leave but will not remain endlessly while she manufactures crises, which seems fair enough. Liam turns out to have another reason for ending the relationship -- it won't surprise a mildly attentive reader -- and so Rosa finds herself jobless and homeless, imposing herself on friends and wandering around a city in which she feels increasingly alienated.</p>
        <p>Unable to persuade herself to find work, panicking about her mounting debt, resentful of Liam's new relationship, Rosa spends most of her days navel-gazing and growing increasingly paranoid. She becomes obsessed with graffiti, seeing the word ''temp'' everywhere and desperate to discover its meaning. When Rosa isn't puzzling over its obvious connotations (''time's winged whatsit, flapping at her back'') she makes preposterous lists:</p>
        <p>''Get a job. Wash your clothes. Clean the kitchen. Phone Liam and ask about the furniture. Buy some tuna and spaghetti. Go to the bank and beg for an extension -- more money, more time to pay back the rest of your debt. Read the comedies of Shakespeare, the works of Proust, the plays of Racine and Corneille and 'The Man Without Qualities.' Read 'The Golden Bough,' the Nag Hammadi Gospels, the Upanishads, the Koran, the Bible, the Tao, the complete works of E. A. Wallis Budge. Read Plato, Aristotle, Confucius, Bacon, Locke, Rousseau, Wollstonecraft, Kant, Hegel, Schopenhauer, Kierkegaard, Nietzsche and the rest. Hoover the living room. Clean the toilet. Distinguish the various philosophies of the way. Clean the bath.''</p>
        <p>At first amusing, this list is repeated again and again, with minor variations, becoming as exasperating as Rosa herself. When her father informs her, ''You have to grip life, or it all collapses into chaos,'' this seems like good advice, although it could be put more brutally: she just needs to get a grip.</p>
        <p>Clearly, Rosa is depressed; unfortunately, Rosa's problem becomes the book's problem. Trapped inside Rosa's spiraling fatalism, the reader can no more escape her helplessness and self-pity than Rosa can: everything grinds to a halt, stalled by misery. Depression's resistance to movement, its tendency toward paralysis, is clear in those endless lists, which are symptomatic of Rosa's, and her story's, immobility.</p>
        <p>The opposite of depression, as any psychologist will tell you, isn't happiness -- it's animation, energy, vivacity. Freud differentiated between mourning, a dynamic psychic process, and melancholia, which is obsessive, chronic, stagnant. He also linked melancholia to narcissism: depression creates a kind of pre-Copernican self-centeredness; it rearranges the world around the central axis of the self, transforming people into black holes. When mutual friends tell Rosa that Liam found her ''depressive, overbearing, self-obsessed,'' you can see what he meant. Without a doubt, Kavenna successfully renders depression. What's less certain is whether successfully rendering depression renders a novel successful. Change and conflict provide a story's oxygen; without them, it chokes.</p>
        <p>And this is a pity because Kavenna writes with elegance and flair, endowing Rosa with a graceful articulacy. (''We are all, thought Rosa, speeding through space, a velocity too wild to contemplate. ... Everything spinning in emptiness. And Rosa as her own fleeting vantage point.'') Kavenna also has a mordant way with social satire. When Rosa encounters a wealthy wife who exhibits the telltale signs of cosmetic surgery, she imagines the husband ''coming home from his office, finding his wife had been under the knife again. 'Darling, new face?' he would ask, as he picked up the newspaper and rustled it open.''</p>
        <p>But Rosa's flippancy is generally rebarbative; for the most part, she simply hides behind her pointless philosophizing and never admits that she's just scared stiff and running like hell from her glimpse of the abyss. And because Kavenna never forces her to confront her grief, because she too successfully buries her pain, Rosa appears to be wallowing rather than mourning.</p>
        <p>Insight, even of the slanting, oblique kind, is in short supply: Rosa's limitations hold Kavenna back. The denial is too absolute, her numbness too deadening -- everything is in abeyance, and limbo is no place to set a novel. In the immortal words of Elvis, a little less conversation, a little more action, please.</p>
        <p>Sarah Churchwell is author of ''The Many Lives of Marilyn Monroe.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Sarah Churchwell is author of ''The Many Lives of Marilyn Monroe.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
