<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who Benefits From This Buyback?</title>
    <meta content="03gret" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/business/yourmoney/03gret.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851928"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FAIR GAME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Subprime Lending</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">NVR Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7D71330F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="947" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who Benefits From This Buyback?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Who Benefits From This Buyback?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRETCHEN MORGENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morgenson, Gretchen</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LOOK at the shares of NVR Inc., the parent of Ryan Homes, Fox Ridge Homes and NVHomes, and you might just think that the real estate bubble never popped. The nation's 10th-largest seller of residential housing, NVR has generated stock gains of 21 percent so far this year. Its seven largest peers -- including D. R. Horton, Toll Brothers, the Lennar Corporation and KB Home -- have posted losses ranging from 5.3 percent to 18.5 percent this year.</p>
        <p>NVR's shares, which closed on Friday at $780, sell at four times the company's book value. Its peers trade at an average of 1.2 times book value.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Look at the shares of the nation’s 10th-largest seller of residential housing and you might think that the real estate bubble never popped.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LOOK at the shares of NVR Inc., the parent of Ryan Homes, Fox Ridge Homes and NVHomes, and you might just think that the real estate bubble never popped. The nation's 10th-largest seller of residential housing, NVR has generated stock gains of 21 percent so far this year. Its seven largest peers -- including D. R. Horton, Toll Brothers, the Lennar Corporation and KB Home -- have posted losses ranging from 5.3 percent to 18.5 percent this year.</p>
        <p>NVR's shares, which closed on Friday at $780, sell at four times the company's book value. Its peers trade at an average of 1.2 times book value.</p>
        <p>So is NVR, with $6 billion in home-building revenues last year, impervious to the subprime mortgage woes hammering the real estate business? Not exactly. ''Current market conditions continue to exert a depressed effect on selling prices,'' the company said in its first-quarter filing on May 4. Customer traffic has fallen off considerably, too.</p>
        <p>Sure enough, revenues were down 9 percent in the period, compared with the first quarter of 2006, and net income declined 36 percent. Gross profit margins slipped to 21 percent from 27 percent.</p>
        <p>Investors may be counting on better performance from NVR because it operates more conservatively than many other home builders. NVR does not buy and develop land on speculation; it builds only what its customers have signed contracts to buy.</p>
        <p>Neither is the company exposed to the currently comatose real estate markets in Florida, Las Vegas and California. It operates mostly on the East Coast -- Maryland, Virginia, New Jersey, New York and the Carolinas -- and some parts further west, including Michigan, Ohio, Pennsylvania and Kentucky.</p>
        <p>But the mid-Atlantic region contributes the most to NVR earnings, and that worries Daniel Oppenheim, an analyst at Bank of America. He downgraded the stock to ''sell'' on Tuesday after seeing disappointing trends in Washington and Baltimore -- markets that brought in 72 percent of NVR's profits in the first quarter of 2007.</p>
        <p>Mr. Oppenheim also said he expects that customer cancellations will leave NVR with unwanted inventory in a softening market and that the company's profit margins could fall to 17 percent this year. His pessimism is not unique. The three other Wall Street analysts following the company are neutral or negative on its stock.</p>
        <p>NVR itself, however, is decidedly bullish about its own stock. Or so one might conclude from the company's aggressive buyback program. In the first quarter, NVR bought back $86 million worth of its shares, and on April 4 it announced plans to purchase an additional $300 million. The company did not say when it would buy, only that it would do so periodically in the open market or in private transactions.</p>
        <p>Buybacks are one way companies return money to their shareholders, and NVR has conducted them since 1994. Dividends are another, perhaps more effective approach, one that NVR has shunned.</p>
        <p>One problem with buybacks is that they may come at too high a cost. If a company pays a premium, as NVR has recently, shareholders may well wonder whether the transactions are an intelligent use of their cash.</p>
        <p>But when big repurchase plans occur even as company insiders are dumping their own stakes, buybacks become downright perplexing.</p>
        <p>Such is the case at NVR. Dwight C. Schar, NVR's chairman and former longtime chief executive, sold 259,193 shares from April 25 to May 3. That was 80 percent of his accessible stake and generated $211.4 million.</p>
        <p>The sales came during an impressive move in NVR stock that occurred about a week after the company announced its first-quarter earnings in a news release. On April 26, for example, Mr. Schar sold 100,000 shares. Instead of depressing the stock, which typically trades rather thinly, the shares jumped almost $45 that day, closing at $842, the high for the last 12 months. A total of 350,000 shares changed hands as Mr. Schar was selling that day, almost four times the daily average during the past six months.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schar sold his stock for an average price of $815 a share. After he concluded his sales, NVR's stock fell back below $800.</p>
        <p>An NVR spokeswoman said that no one at the company was available to discuss the buyback program or Mr. Schar's recent sales.</p>
        <p>So I asked Bob Gabele, an expert on insider transactions at 3DAdvisors, an independent equity research firm, to provide a historical perspective on the recent sales by insiders at NVR. Mr. Gabele examined Mr. Schar's stock sales back to 1994 and said the recent sales were the largest reduction Mr. Schar has made in his holdings. Mr. Gabele noted that Mr. Schar holds 242,653 shares in his deferred-compensation plan but cannot sell those until he retires.</p>
        <p>Other NVR executives have also made significant sales recently, Mr. Gabele said. William J. Inman, president of one of the company's units, NVR Mortgage Finance, has jettisoned 45 percent of his available shares. Robert W. Henley, the company's controller, has dumped 65 percent. Combined with Mr. Schar's sales, the value of stock sold by insiders so far this year exceeds the total sales of all insiders in each of the last 13 years, except 2003.</p>
        <p>''In cases such as these, we must look at the actions of a company's insiders to help us gain information that is not forthcoming in more tangible disclosures,'' Mr. Gabele said. ''For those who suspect a lurking positive surprise behind NVR's better-than-average share performance, I would remind them to pay attention to what the boss is doing.''</p>
        <p>Which brings us back to those NVR stock purchases. The company's board has approved them, of course. But when insiders are cashing out, should shareholders' money be used to buy?</p>
        <p>FAIR GAME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
