<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Award for Most Hopeful Goes to an Atlanta Theater</title>
    <meta content="03good" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/theater/theaterspecial/03good.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851699"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE TONYS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Alliance Theater (Atlanta)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodman, Brenda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/New York Theater Workshop</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Tony Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia/Atlanta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlanta (Ga)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Alliance Theater</org>
        <org class="online_producer">American Theater Wing</org>
        <org class="online_producer">League of American Theaters and Producers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Booth, Susan V</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E3DB1430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Award for Most Hopeful Goes to an Atlanta Theater</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Award for Most Hopeful Goes to an Atlanta Theater</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRENDA GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodman, Brenda</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Alliance Theater of Atlanta, which won 2007 Tony Award for outstanding regional theater; efforts to attract new, younger and more diverse audience described; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JUST days after learning that the Alliance Theater had won the 2007 Tony Award for outstanding regional theater, Susan V. Booth, its artistic director, was already trying to win another.</p>
        <p>''Tony Kushner is a son of the South,'' Ms. Booth said, sitting in her office surrounded by congratulatory bouquets and staring dreamily into the middle distance. ''I would love to have him originate work with us.'' (Mr. Kushner, the Pulitzer Prize- and Tony Award-winning playwright best known for ''Angels in America,'' was born in Manhattan but grew up in Lake Charles, La.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Atlanta’s Alliance Theater, which won the 2007 Tony Award for outstanding regional theater, wants a little more love from the locals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JUST days after learning that the Alliance Theater had won the 2007 Tony Award for outstanding regional theater, Susan V. Booth, its artistic director, was already trying to win another.</p>
        <p>''Tony Kushner is a son of the South,'' Ms. Booth said, sitting in her office surrounded by congratulatory bouquets and staring dreamily into the middle distance. ''I would love to have him originate work with us.'' (Mr. Kushner, the Pulitzer Prize- and Tony Award-winning playwright best known for ''Angels in America,'' was born in Manhattan but grew up in Lake Charles, La.)</p>
        <p>Such is the chest puffing and name dropping that is going on in the administrative offices of the Alliance these days, as the staff members try to think of ways to capitalize on the award. What they most want, apart from a new play by Mr. Kushner, is a little more love from the locals.</p>
        <p>In recent years, even as the Alliance developed a national reputation as an incubator for new Broadway-bound musicals like ''The Color Purple,'' the company has struggled to retire a $1.5 million debt and revitalize a subscriber base that has been graying and shrinking.</p>
        <p>Supporters of the Alliance believe the theater is in a good position to take advantage of the honor.</p>
        <p>Kenny Leon, who was the Alliance's artistic director for 11 years, is one of them. ''The country has said: 'You're important. You're important to the field,' '' explained Mr. Leon, the director of the Broadway production of August Wilson's ''Radio Golf.'' ''And now it's up to them to educate the community about what that means, to show what we've got right here in Atlanta.''</p>
        <p>The theater company, which shares the Woodruff Arts Center campus with the High Museum of Art and the Atlanta Symphony Orchestra, has had trouble appearing hip and gritty in a city teeming with young people on the hunt for what Ms. Booth calls ''punky itchy scratchy'' theater, the kind that often turns up in Atlanta's many smaller houses like Dad's Garage and PushPush.</p>
        <p>Ms. Booth's efforts to reach a more diverse audience were driven as much by economic necessity as a desire to help the Alliance better mirror its home city. Over the last decade the average age of an Alliance season ticket holder has hovered around 56. And though Atlanta's population is 54 percent black, the Alliance had a reputation of playing primarily to white patrons. That narrow focus proved disastrous in 2001 after the Sept. 11 attacks, when the theater saw its annual subscriber base shrink to just 9,000 from 14,000, where it stayed for the next five years. In search of more bodies and buzz, Ms. Booth, 43, conducted ''field research,'' haunting the productions of many of the smaller local companies to see what was bringing people through their doors.</p>
        <p>The result was City Series, a collaboration with local companies that allowed them to produce more experimental plays in the Hertz, the Alliance's smaller stage (its exposed ductwork adding a note of hipness). Though the project folded in 2004 after only two years, Ms. Booth said she was happy with the results of the experiment.</p>
        <p>And the audience has responded. Administrators project that the Alliance, with a $10.5 million annual budget, will have about 13,000 subscribers next season.</p>
        <p>Those familiar with the theater's history, however, see its main problem as image, and they hope the Tony recognition will help.</p>
        <p>''It's not about, 'Gee, this season is great,' '' said Howard Sherman, executive director of the American Theater Wing, the nonprofit service organization that, with the League of American Theaters and Producers, presents the Tonys. ''They've been participating in a lot of work that's been nationally recognized,'' he said, alluding to Alfred Uhry's ''Last Night of Ballyhoo,'' Elton John and Tim Rice's ''Aida'' and ''The Color Purple,'' which all originated at the Alliance.</p>
        <p>But, Mr. Sherman added, the theater has ''balanced that with a strong commitment to new writers and education.''</p>
        <p>In 2005 the Alliance won a significant grant from an anonymous donor to create the Kendeda Graduate Playwriting Competition, which is unusual in that it produces the winner's play, rather than simply giving it a staged reading or workshop. The Alliance has also made an effort to present works about the South. In 2005 it opened the season with the comedy ''Moonlight and Magnolias'' by Ron Hutchinson, about the making of the movie ''Gone With the Wind.'' That same year it produced ''The Heart Is a Lonely Hunter'' by Rebecca Gilman, an Alabama native who adapted it from the Carson McCullers novel.</p>
        <p>What the Tony may do for the Alliance's ticket lines and bottom line remains to be seen. Robert Brustein, the former artistic director of the American Repertory Theater in Cambridge, Mass., said that winning the regional theater award in 1986 had made little tangible difference to that theater. But it changed a lot for the Utah Shakespearean Festival in Cedar City, which saw a bump in press coverage, ticket sales and financial contributions in the six months following its Tony win in 2000.</p>
        <p>Ms. Booth said she had no intention of letting the award simply sit metaphorically on a shelf. In September the Alliance will open ''The Women of Brewster Place,'' a new musical by Tim Acito based on the novel by Gloria Naylor about seven black women living in a housing project in the 1970s.</p>
        <p>And after that, perhaps a little something by Mr. Kushner?</p>
        <p>THE TONYS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
