<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When in the Netherlands</title>
    <meta content="03Possessed" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/fashion/03Possessed.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851837"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="POSSESSED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Council of Fashion Designers of America</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06EFD71530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="578" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When in the Netherlands</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When in the Netherlands...</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID COLMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''ARE WE ROME?'' is a much-talked-about new book, but if Justin Giunta were to write his own treatise about the glory of the United States, he might use a different title.</p>
        <p>''Are We Amsterdam?'' isn't as catchy, true, but for Mr. Giunta, the current zeal for luxury goods summons not the Roman Empire but the Dutch Golden Age of the 17th century, when well-to-do merchants helped create the first truly capitalist country, with a hugely prosperous trade empire.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Justin Giunta’s line, Subversive Jewelry, has earned him a nomination for emerging accessories designer of the year from the Council of Fashion Designers of America.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''ARE WE ROME?'' is a much-talked-about new book, but if Justin Giunta were to write his own treatise about the glory of the United States, he might use a different title.</p>
        <p>''Are We Amsterdam?'' isn't as catchy, true, but for Mr. Giunta, the current zeal for luxury goods summons not the Roman Empire but the Dutch Golden Age of the 17th century, when well-to-do merchants helped create the first truly capitalist country, with a hugely prosperous trade empire.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giunta, 28, is not an upstart economic theorist with a book to peddle, but he is a clever observer of 17th- and 21st-century fashions nonetheless.</p>
        <p>His line, Subversive Jewelry, often combines styles of different eras, and it has earned him a nomination for emerging accessories designer of the year from the Council of Fashion Designers of America, whose awards ceremony is tomorrow night.</p>
        <p>Citing a penchant for things he called ''beautiful, but a little aggressive, with a narrative to tell,'' Mr. Giunta said he has long been fascinated by Dutch Baroque art, which he studied in painting school. He has a special fondness for the still life, particularly those painted by Ambrosius Bosschaert, Pieter Claesz, Jan Davidsz. de Heem and Willem Claesz. Heda.</p>
        <p>''These painters were like the Prada or Gucci of their day -- in the hierarchy of painting, they were the brand names,'' Mr. Giunta said.</p>
        <p>With religious subjects falling into disfavor, these artists devoted themselves to exquisitely rendered compositions of what might today be called status objects -- exotic seashells, fancy flowers, costly foodstuffs, silver and glass knickknacks and baroque bouquets.</p>
        <p>But of all the extravagances that reflected the country's new wealth and glory, Mr. Giunta became most fixated on the bouquets' vases: typically baroque handblown Venetian goblets of sap-green glass. As an art student at Carnegie Mellon University, he lusted after them. He even got in trouble in 2001, when as an intern at the artist Robert Wilson's art and theater center in Water Mill, N.Y., he saw that Mr. Wilson had a collection and decided to drink from one. Mr. Wilson did not appear amused.</p>
        <p>A year later, a Dutch friend found and gave Mr. Giunta a goblet of his own. Touched, he vowed not to keep and admire it on a shelf, but to use and love it.</p>
        <p>You can guess how that ended.</p>
        <p>Even after it shattered, the knowledge that the glasses could still be found fired his obsession anew. When his Subversive Jewelry line took off, he said his first indulgence was to march into ABC Home on Broadway and buy a dozen reproductions -- handblown in the Czech Republic, they cost about $70 each. He uses them every day; his collection grew to almost 30.</p>
        <p>''They're surprisingly resilient,'' he said. ''They've been dropped, bounced, kicked.''</p>
        <p>Still, six or so of them have eventually felt destiny's final blow -- a few of them in the dishwasher.</p>
        <p>''My heart breaks every time,'' he said. ''But using them so outweighs the risk or the loss. Even when they break, they've been paid for in use value alone.''</p>
        <p>Their fragility nicely illustrates another Dutch painting tradition: the vanitas, a lovely still life to which the painter added a skull as a reminder that, well, you can't take it with you. Or that it's better to ruin an item of great beauty than to keep it behind glass forever. It's a lesson that all empires -- Roman, Dutch, Prada, Gucci -- have to contend with, sooner or later.</p>
        <p>POSSESSED</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
