<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shut Me In for the Ballgame</title>
    <meta content="603TRIBE.txt" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Play" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="90" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851590"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MY TRIBE"/>
      <identified-content/>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E7D91F31F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="879" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shut Me In for the Ballgame</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Neal Pollack</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you think you have a dorky hobby, imagine spending several hours a week waiting for a Web site to play simulated baseball games. Then imagine that the teams were constructed using the statistics of nearly every player who has ever played pro baseball, going back to 1885, the vast majority of whom you've never heard of. The games are simulated three times a day, so that a season takes about two months. You're now imagining one of my hobbies. Suddenly your own doesn't seem so dorky anymore, does it?</p>
        <p>One afternoon a couple of years ago, I followed a link on Major League Baseball's home page and found myself at whatifsports.com, which informed me that within minutes I could be playing SimLeague Baseball, managing a team that included Ichiro Suzuki and Steve Balboni. Commingling those particular greatnesses had never been a dream of mine. I already played regular fantasy baseball, which involves tracking the day-to-day statistics of currently active baseball players. That was time-consuming enough, to the point where it occasionally created tension in my marriage, but this was a more insidious beast, and I sensed its destructive potential. Nonetheless, I was curious. I plunged in. Soon, I was gazing upon baseball-nerd heaven.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you think you have a dorky hobby, imagine spending several hours a week waiting for a Web site to play simulated baseball games. Then imagine that the teams were constructed using the statistics of nearly every player who has ever played pro baseball, going back to 1885, the vast majority of whom you've never heard of. The games are simulated three times a day, so that a season takes about two months. You're now imagining one of my hobbies. Suddenly your own doesn't seem so dorky anymore, does it?</p>
        <p>One afternoon a couple of years ago, I followed a link on Major League Baseball's home page and found myself at whatifsports.com, which informed me that within minutes I could be playing SimLeague Baseball, managing a team that included Ichiro Suzuki and Steve Balboni. Commingling those particular greatnesses had never been a dream of mine. I already played regular fantasy baseball, which involves tracking the day-to-day statistics of currently active baseball players. That was time-consuming enough, to the point where it occasionally created tension in my marriage, but this was a more insidious beast, and I sensed its destructive potential. Nonetheless, I was curious. I plunged in. Soon, I was gazing upon baseball-nerd heaven.</p>
        <p>I signed up for a trial team and began drafting. Crazy times ensued as the $80 million salary-cap restriction forced me to make some choices. Batting Ted Williams behind Joe DiMaggio wasn't going to happen; nor would Sandy Koufax be pitching in the same rotation as Bob Gibson. Instead, I found myself with an offense led by Otis Nixon, Don Mattingly and Willie MontaÃ$(1$)ez, a player I vaguely remembered from the 1970s.</p>
        <p>My team won 67 of 162 games. Of course I had to try again.</p>
        <p>I hit the message boards, and asked some other ''managers'' questions like ''How do I find guys who won't walk the bases loaded and then give up grand slams?'' Some questions were ignored, possibly because the managers were 12 years old and therefore operated at a low level of social ease. Others were met with a ''figure it out for yourself, rookie'' attitude. But I did get some useful tips from a guy who called himself ''Wonder Boys,'' and I was able to piece together a viable pitching staff. I then concocted a lineup of hitters that included Ty Cobb and Ralph Kiner, plus Cecil Cooper, who, like most members of the World Series-losing 1982 Milwaukee Brewers, had abundant facial hair. My team won 93 games and the division. It was bounced in three games in the first round of the playoffs. I had to try again, again.</p>
        <p>Thirty teams and 10 playoffs later, I'm still playing. Compared with other SimLeague players, some of whom have 30 teams going at one time, I'm a model of restraint. As my obsession advanced into routine and my wife began making references to ''that stupid baseball game that's destroying our marriage,'' I moved on to the ''theme'' leagues, to spice things up a bit. Some of the theme leagues offer higher (or lower) salary caps. Some of them feature only players who were on major-league rosters from 1960 onward. The iterations go beyond arcane: I've seen leagues with rosters solely consisting of players whose last names begin with L, ones in which all the players have been renamed after cartoon characters and a ''Lyman Bostock Tribute League.'' By comparison, real-life baseball can seem pedestrian, even arbitrary. Once you can dump your third baseman for Wade Boggs in his prime, there's no going back.</p>
        <p>As I traveled deep into the SimLeague, I learned too much. The games play out according to a statistical formula known in SimLeague parlance as ''log5.'' It's almost impossible to win until you crack the formula, and after that it's almost impossible to lose, except to others who have solved the mystery. I wanted to crack the code myself, but there was no one with whom to share my obsession. My wife openly despised the game, and I couldn't get any friends interested. In fact, I worried that I'd actually lose friends if I told them I was playing. As always, I was alone when I realized that the key was to use pitchers from 1894, who had been undervalued en masse by the mysterious ghosts in the machine.</p>
        <p>I wanted to shout joyously as my team won a championship in an easy five games, but I couldn't, because I learned of my victory while on my laptop at one of my son's play dates.</p>
        <p>Recently, the site's staff reconfigured the system, changing player salaries and making other adjustments. They do this, I learned, once too many players crack the code. The message boards erupted in panic, some of it from veteran players who didn't want to lose their sinecure. I didn't protest, but I felt the change in my bones. I knew that my next championship might be years away.</p>
        <p>My current team, Slappy's Fireballs, has won six straight games, and I've added a second one, made up only of Chicago Cubs, that has potential. That's the eternal promise of the SimLeague: you may grow old and tired and (more than likely) stupid from staring at the computer all day, but simulated baseball never dies.</p>
        <p>MY TRIBE Neal Pollack is the author of ''Alternadad'' and ''Never Mind the Pollacks.'' He lives with his family in Los Angeles.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Neal Pollack is the author of ''Alternadad'' and ''Never Mind the Pollacks.'' He lives with his family in Los Angeles.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
