<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>P.S. I Loved You</title>
    <meta content="03mann" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/opinion/03mann.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070613T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Beatles</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Lennon, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">John, Elton</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EFDF1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>P.S. I Loved You</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">P.S. I Loved You</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Aimee Mann</byline>
      <dateline>Los Angeles</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MY big brother was always the one to bring new music into the house. Until I heard the Beatles playing on his stereo in the basement, my favorite music had been Glen Campbell singing ''Galveston'' or my father playing ''Won't You Come Home, Bill Bailey'' on the piano.</p>
        <p>I was young enough to giggle when my brother changed the words of ''P.S. I Love You'' tosomething more puerile, and four years later, young enough to think that ''Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band'' was really a band, and not the name of a Beatles record. In those intervening years, a transformation had taken place, and both the sound and the look of the Beatles had completely changed. Also, I was a little slow on the uptake, and didn't notice the name ''Beatles'' spelled out in flowers on the cover.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Sgt. Pepper’s” meant everything once. Does it still?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MY big brother was always the one to bring new music into the house. Until I heard the Beatles playing on his stereo in the basement, my favorite music had been Glen Campbell singing ''Galveston'' or my father playing ''Won't You Come Home, Bill Bailey'' on the piano.</p>
        <p>I was young enough to giggle when my brother changed the words of ''P.S. I Love You'' tosomething more puerile, and four years later, young enough to think that ''Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band'' was really a band, and not the name of a Beatles record. In those intervening years, a transformation had taken place, and both the sound and the look of the Beatles had completely changed. Also, I was a little slow on the uptake, and didn't notice the name ''Beatles'' spelled out in flowers on the cover.</p>
        <p>Is it a testament to the quality, or purity, or beauty, or timelessness of that record (released 40 years ago this weekend) that it appealed so thoroughly to an 8-year-old, one who had virtually no contact with pop culture? I could not have been more out of tune with the zeitgeist -- it would be two more years before I discovered radio, and even then I would have only the vaguest notion of what was out there. I bought my first LP solely on the basis of the cover (one of the reasons today I try to take extra care with the packaging of my CDs). It was pure dumb luck that it turned out to be Elton John's ''Madman Across the Water,'' still one of my favorite albums of all time.</p>
        <p>But the favorite is, and was, and must remain ''Sgt. Pepper's.'' I had a love affair like no other with that record. My brother had bought it, of course, and when I heard it, I braved his wrath and smuggled it out to my friend's house so I could play it over and over. You'd have had to know my brother back then to fully understand how daring that was.</p>
        <p>In a way, that record seemed made for children: the fun false mustaches that came with the package, the bright shiny outfits, the cheery melodies, the jaunty horns. The band itself seemed almost irrelevant -- scruffy mustachioed men in costumes, lost in a sea of collaged faces. I ignored them.</p>
        <p>My ignorance extended to the opening song, which I took at face value as a real live introduction of the singer Billy Shears, who, whoever he was, became my favorite, with his dopey baritone, in humble gratitude for his pals -- bless them, it all was so innocent, those marmalade skies and winking meter maids (whatever they were.) The darkest moments were with the runaway girl -- although a throwaway line in ''Getting Better'' (''I was cruel to my woman, I beat her'') gave me pause. He beat her? What the heck? But hey -- things were getting better all the time, so  I shrugged and let it go.</p>
        <p>And then things took a weird turn: a nightmare cacophony of strings, someone blowing his mind out in a car -- what was that? Did he get shot in the head? What were the holes in Albert Hall? Things had gotten creepy and dark, and it lost me. I started skipping that last song.</p>
        <p>I can't listen to ''Sgt. Pepper's'' anymore. As a musician, I'm burnt out on it -- its influence has been so vast and profound. As a lyricist, I find that my ear has become more attuned to the likes of Fiona Apple and Elliot Smith, and though the words of ''Sgt. Pepper's'' are full of vivid images -- Rita's bag slung over her shoulder, Mr. Kite sailing through a hogshead of fire, the runaway girl with her handkerchief -- there's an emotional depth that's missing. I'm ashamed to say it, but sometimes John Lennon's melodies feel a bit underwritten, while Paul McCartney's relentless cheerfulness is depressing. The very jauntiness I used to love as a girl feels as if it's covering up a sadder subtext. And what's bleaker than a brave face?</p>
        <p>The whole experience is uncomfortable, like realizing you can beat your own father at chess or arm-wrestling. I don't want to go back and find that the carcass has been picked clean. Because I know without a doubt that ''Sgt. Pepper's'' changed the course of my life. If the magic is gone, it's only because first loves can't be repeated. When I was 8, I'd never heard anything like it, and I can honestly say that if I live to be 100, I'll never hear anything like it again.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Aimee Mann is a singer and songwriter.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 13, 2007, Wednesday  An Op-Ed article on June 3, about the anniversary of ''Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band,'' misquoted the lyrics of a song on the album. The line from the song, ''Getting Better,'' is ''I used to be cruel to my woman,'' not ''I was cruel.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 13, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An Op-Ed article on June 3, about the anniversary of ''Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band,'' misquoted the lyrics of a song on the album. The line from the song, ''Getting Better,'' is ''I used to be cruel to my woman,'' not ''I was cruel.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Aimee Mann is a singer and songwriter.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
