<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Republicrats of Long Island</title>
    <meta content="LI--Endorse" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/opinion/nyregionopinions/LI-Endorse.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851741"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Long Island"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">County Executives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Steve (County Exec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Levy, Steve</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E1D71430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="482" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Republicrats of Long Island</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Republicrats of Long Island</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial holds failure of Suffolk County Republican Party to offer its own candidate to compete against incumbent Democratic County Executive Steve Levy is embarrassment for GOP; holds healthy political system requires opposition and dissent</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The failure of the Suffolk County Republican Party to put up its own candidate for county executive this year is an embarrassment for the G.O.P. and a triumph for the incumbent, Steve Levy, a Democrat who won the Republicans' cross-endorsement on May 24.</p>
        <p>It is the first time one of the major parties has ever done that for a county executive race on Long Island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Democracy requires at least two functioning parties  not one that works and another that’s flat on its back.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The failure of the Suffolk County Republican Party to put up its own candidate for county executive this year is an embarrassment for the G.O.P. and a triumph for the incumbent, Steve Levy, a Democrat who won the Republicans' cross-endorsement on May 24.</p>
        <p>It is the first time one of the major parties has ever done that for a county executive race on Long Island.</p>
        <p>One assumes that the Republicans' decision, mortifying as it was, would have been a lot harder if Mr. Levy had been a more distinctly different political animal from them. But Mr. Levy's brand of dogged populism, with its tough lines on taxes, spending and Latino immigrants, is intensely popular with white middle-class voters of both parties.</p>
        <p>It has given him an aura of invincibility -- in Suffolk County, anyway -- and when county Republican leaders could not come up with someone, anyone, to be trampled by Mr. Levy in November, they bowed in humility before the county executive, who graciously accepted their tribute.</p>
        <p>It was a proud moment for Mr. Levy, but it's too bad for voters, who deserved a choice this fall. Many Democrats and Republicans are impressed, and rightly so, with Mr. Levy's energy and public-spiritedness, but there are others who are put off by his stringent, Lou-Dobbsian views on immigration, his array of enforcement initiatives and restrictionist oratory that have worked to marginalize his critics, done little to discourage hate-mongers and stymied progress toward practical solutions to Suffolk's old, unresolved problems of day laborers and its simmering class and ethnic tensions.</p>
        <p>Through smart governance and relentless attention to hot-button issues, Mr. Levy has made himself one of the most powerful leaders around, and all that power needs a counterweight -- particularly on the immigration issue, which has seen so much hostility vented locally upon the utterly powerless and poor. To stand up for them requires, in many cases, standing up to Mr. Levy, something few if any elected officials now seem willing or able to do.</p>
        <p>Democrats may cheer at the spreading blueness of this formerly rock-ribbed-Republican island, with charismatic, pragmatic Democratic leaders running both counties and several of its sprawling towns. But a healthy political system requires opposition and dissent.</p>
        <p>For now, the Democrats are the forces of change and renewal. But while it's possible for members of any party to don the garb of reformers, said garb has to be changed regularly or it begins to smell. The crumbling of Long Island's all-powerful and frequently corrupt Republican Party machinery is a good thing, but the vacuum that has replaced it is not.</p>
        <p>Our wish is not for resurgent machines but for a healthy body politic, a living organism with sturdy parts made strong by the exercising of conflicting opinions and the toil of consensus-building. That's democracy, and it requires at least two functioning parties -- not one that works and another that's flat on its back.</p>
        <p>Long Island</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
