<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fighting Worsens as Lebanese Army Surrounds Militants</title>
    <meta content="03lebanon" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/world/middleeast/03lebanon.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851992"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lebanon</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fatah Al Islam (Militant Group)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fatah</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bakri, Nada</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fattah, Hassan M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Lebanon</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Fatah al-Islam</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDB1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="557" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fighting Worsens as Lebanese Army Surrounds Militants</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fighting Worsens as Lebanese Army Surrounds Militants</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NADA BAKRI and HASSAN M. FATTAH; Nada Bakri reported from Tripoli, and Hassan M. Fattah from Dubai, United Arab Emirates.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fattah, Hassan M; Bakri, Nada</byline>
      <dateline>TRIPOLI, Lebanon, June 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Heavy shelling and gunfire continues for second day at Nahr al Bared refugee camp, as Lebanese Army intensifies its offensive against Fatah al Islam militia; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Heavy shelling and gunfire continued for the second day at the Nahr al Bared refugee camp, as the Lebanese Army intensified its offensive against the Fatah al Islam militia.</p>
        <p>Three soldiers were killed and 15 were wounded in the fighting by Saturday afternoon, the army reported, raising the number of the army's deaths from the two-day offensive to six.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Heavy shelling continued for the second day at a refugee camp as the Lebanese Army intensified its offensive against the Fatah al Islam militia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Heavy shelling and gunfire continued for the second day at the Nahr al Bared refugee camp, as the Lebanese Army intensified its offensive against the Fatah al Islam militia.</p>
        <p>Three soldiers were killed and 15 were wounded in the fighting by Saturday afternoon, the army reported, raising the number of the army's deaths from the two-day offensive to six.</p>
        <p>Dozens of militants from Fatah al Islam, a group inspired by Al Qaeda, have also been killed or wounded, the army said. But that figure could not be independently verified, and it was not immediately clear how many victims were fighters and how many were civilians trapped in the camp.</p>
        <p>Reports have estimated that about 8,000 of what was once 40,000 Palestinian refugees may still be in the camp.</p>
        <p>By midday, the army had wrested control of all the positions held by the militants outside the camp and had destroyed many sniping positions in the camp, stopping short of actually crossing into the official boundaries of the camp, the military said.</p>
        <p>''The army is now fighting on the exterior lines and the militants are fighting on the interior lines,'' said Elias Hanna, a former general in the army. ''They are trying to squeeze them inside their circle.''</p>
        <p>An army helicopter attacked suspected militant hideouts with missile and machine-gun fire on the western edge of the camp, apparently in an attempt to block escape by sea, The Associated Press reported.</p>
        <p>After a brief afternoon lull, during which Palestinian and religious leaders tried to negotiate a cease-fire, the fighting resumed in the evening.</p>
        <p>''This is the beginning of the end,'' said Mazen Faqih, a member of Lebanon's civil defense corps who has helped evacuate bodies and the injured from the camp in the last two weeks. ''The militants are blocked from the sea and from the eastern, northern and southern borders. There's nowhere for them to go.''</p>
        <p>The offensive began Friday as the army tightened its cordon around the camp, moving several hundred yards closer to the camp, seizing new ground in a daylong fight that left 18 dead and dozens wounded.</p>
        <p>The fighting broke a tense 10-day cease-fire, and it raised fears that the army was planning to move straight into the camp.</p>
        <p>The militants again said they would fight to the last man, if necessary.</p>
        <p>''Morale is high,'' said Abu Hureira, deputy leader of Fatah al Islam, speaking to The Associated Press by telephone. ''Let them come. We are ready.''</p>
        <p>Though he conceded that his fighters had abandoned some positions in the northern end of camp, he described the pullback as ''tactical.''</p>
        <p>Residents living on the outskirts of the camp, meanwhile, said that they were locking up their homes and barricading their blocks to try to keep the Fatah al Islam fighters from taking cover in their neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>A statement issued by the army on Saturday said that militants were trying to hide in mosques and at aid organizations, storing weapons there and using the remaining civilian population as ''human shields'' to stir up Muslim anger.</p>
        <p>The army has insisted that it is aiming only at militants. It has been impossible to independently verify the military's movements, however, because journalists are being prevented from seeing the fighting.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
