<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Wee Small Hours</title>
    <meta content="Kirn.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/books/review/Kirn-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851612"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Murakami, Haruki</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">After Dark (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07EFD61630F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1118" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Wee Small Hours</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In the Wee Small Hours</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER KIRN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER DARK</p>
        <p>By Haruki Murakami.</p>
        <p>Translated by Jay Rubin.</p>
        <p>191 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $22.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Haruki Murakami’s novel features two sisters, one in an enchanted sleep, the other up all night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER DARK</p>
        <p>By Haruki Murakami.</p>
        <p>Translated by Jay Rubin.</p>
        <p>191 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $22.95.</p>
        <p>Should the aliens ever descend in their sleek ships and train their great scanners on our population centers, capturing our deeds and dreams for transmission back to cosmic headquarters, let's hope they show us the patient tenderness of Haruki Murakami, the Japanese novelist, who himself is not wholly of this world. In a dozen books on our existence here -- not in Japan or any special nation but as children of gravity, as earthlings -- Murakami has done as good a job as any contemporary writer of pleading humanity's poignant case before the court of whoever may be out there. Have mercy, oh interstellar lords. We're lonesome and small and we know not what we do, only that we're obliged by God or nature to bathe, dress, eat and keep on doing it.</p>
        <p>''After Dark,'' Murakami's latest novel, is a streamlined, hushed ensemble piece built on the notion that very late at night, after the lamps of logic have been snuffed and rationality has shut its eyes, life on earth becomes boundariless and blurred. Individuals who were separate during the day begin to lose uniqueness, to leak distinctiveness, melting into a soft psychic collective. As the hands of the clock slice deeper into the shadows, physics weakens, yielding to metaphysics, and the rigid you and I of things breaks down. During the wee hours, we're all in this together, our spirits spooned like lovers' bodies.</p>
        <p>The book's all-night story is set in Tokyo, in a seedy downtown entertainment district, but, as is usual with Murakami, whose highly exportable brand of realism wavers between sur- and hyper-, the maps that matter are mental, not geographic. His characters don't stroll on from stage left, they materialize in place, coalescing from clouds of fine particulates. ''On her table is a coffee cup. And an ashtray. Next to the ashtray, a navy blue baseball cap with a Boston Red Sox 'B.' It might be a little too large for her head. A brown leather shoulder bag rests on the seat next to her. It bulges as if its contents had been thrown in on the spur of the moment. She reaches out at regular intervals and brings the coffee cup to her mouth, but she doesn't appear to be enjoying the flavor. She drinks because she has a coffee cup in front of her: that is her role as a customer.''</p>
        <p>The scene here is a Denny's restaurant, an outpost of the synthetic global culture that Murakami serenely accepts, wisely aware that most every country nowadays is a hallucinated hodgepodge of other countries, of America especially. The 19-year-old female coffee drinker, Mari, whose attachment to the Red Sox goes unexplained and probably doesn't bear explaining -- no more than do the lyrics of the pop songs that sprinkle down out of the ceiling of the diner -- is killing time with an unnamed book. It's a bit of a mystery why she's up so late but it may have to do with her lovely sister, Eri, who's at home in the suburbs, mired in a slumber that has been going on, unbroken, for months. Mari is awake because Eri is asleep -- some sort of twinned homeostasis is at work, perhaps. Murakami doesn't push the issue. He chooses his metaphors for their musical value, not their intellectual architecture, and lets them play on by breath and intuition.</p>
        <p>To Mari's modest table come a series of visitors, beginning with a chatty jazz trombonist, who involve her, by stages, through casual conversations that tend toward the anecdotal and philosophical, in a minor crime drama just down the road, where a businessman-john has battered an immigrant prostitute and left her bleeding and fetal in a hotel room. Mari speaks Chinese, the prostitute's native language, and is asked by the manager of a ''love hotel'' to translate for her. That's Mari's role in the novel -- go-between, not heroine. She's the loom on which Murakami weaves his cloth, a useful framework of passivity. What she wants for herself, it appears, is very little -- possibly just to be left alone to read -- but the night has its own intentions for her, as it does for those around her. The conflict of wills that is typically the basis for suspenseful storytelling never quite emerges in ''After Dark.'' Instead what we get is a dissipation of wills into a charged communal flow.</p>
        <p>The book's short chapters swap back and forth between Mari's ramblings with her new acquaintances and a prolonged, poetic set-piece featuring her sleeping-beauty sister, who lies in bed in a bare room next to a wormhole of a TV screen on which her image occasionally appears and into which her soul is being absorbed. It's a trifle too fancy and mind-bending, this business of passing the dreamer through a plugged-in looking glass, and although these trippy, heightened interludes are meant to complement the flatness of the novel's stretches of table-talk, their effect is disruptive and distracting. Imagine high-concept segments of ''The Twilight Zone'' cut into an ad-libbed indie movie.</p>
        <p>It's when his technique is inconspicuous and not when he's waving his wand above the hat that Murakami's spell is most persuasive. Moving outward from obscure Mari through her shifting circle of friends, Murakami takes in widening perimeters of a nocturnal urban habitat. We get a strong sense, though we're not quite certain how, of the city's fugitive social ecology, of the bargains and compacts among its tribes and classes. Women are prey for the most part and band together, particularly the poor and the unmarried. Men venture forth more boldly, lone marauders, though sometimes they leverage their power by forming gangs. Behind and underneath it all are the monstrous, semiautonomous grids and systems -- police forces, garbage trucks, fiber optic networks -- that labor to keep order until morning. The night is a chaos of sprees and errands, of trysts and stickups, escapes and rescue missions, but dawn is a return to productivity.</p>
        <p>Murakami, through his portal on the mother ship, hovers, observes and ultimately approves. He sees how bravely earthlings muddle on, bits of eternity lashed, prodded by baffling appetites and instincts into vinyl-upholstered booths at Denny's and Lysol-soaked rent-by-the-hour motel cubicles. No wonder it's his practice as a writer to log every song that comes in over the radio; catchy tunes offer legitimate solace to such beings. In the darkness a beacon is anything that shines, however weakly, however briefly. Standing sentry above the common gloom, Murakami detects phosphorescence everywhere, but chiefly in the auras around people, which glow brightest at night and when combined but fade at dawn, when we go our separate ways.</p>
        <p>Walter Kirn is a regular contributor to the Book Review. His new novel is ''The Unbinding.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Walter Kirn is a regular contributor to the Book Review. His new novel is ''The Unbinding.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
