<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Heartburn and Magic</title>
    <meta content="Kuczynski.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/books/review/Kuczynski-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851617"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Dormen, Lesley</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Shomer, Enid</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EFD61630F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Heartburn and Magic</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Heartburn and Magic</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX KUCZYNSKI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE BEST PLACE TO BE</p>
        <p>By Lesley Dormen.</p>
        <p>176 pp. Simon &amp; Schuster. $22.</p>
        <p>TOURIST SEASON</p>
        <p>Stories.</p>
        <p>By Enid Shomer.</p>
        <p>254 pp. Random House. Paper, $13.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A novel in stories and a story collection trace the troubles of middle-aged women.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE BEST PLACE TO BE</p>
        <p>By Lesley Dormen.</p>
        <p>176 pp. Simon &amp; Schuster. $22.</p>
        <p>TOURIST SEASON</p>
        <p>Stories.</p>
        <p>By Enid Shomer.</p>
        <p>254 pp. Random House. Paper, $13.95.</p>
        <p>I approached ''The Best Place to Be'' with suspicion. When a book is called ''a novel in stories,'' as this one is on its cover, I wonder: Is it a ploy to avoid the heavy lifting of novel writing? Is the writer incapable of connecting the dots -- or fresh from an M.F.A. program, armed with a collection of stories that happen to feature the same character?</p>
        <p>Lots of authors have written collections of related short pieces that splinter one plot into different arcs, each illuminating a detail from a unique time and place. Some offer, as John Updike did in the Maples stories, a provocatively refracted view of a marriage going slowly, deliberately haywire. But others, like Melissa Bank's ''Girls' Guide to Hunting and Fishing,'' can feel incomplete, merely sound bites for the A.D.D. generation.</p>
        <p>In ''The Best Place to Be,'' Lesley Dormen has produced a friendly, intelligent collection of stories, all told from the point of view of Grace Hanford, a woman reviewers in most parts of the country would describe as neurotic. I would simply call her a New Yorker. In the opening story, Grace is married, childless, newly orphaned, Ambien-dependent, frequently head-shrunk and in the middle of a major kitchen renovation: ''Now I was 50, not a mother, not a daughter, and the kitchen was in the living room and I didn't know how I was supposed to behave.''</p>
        <p>Dormen's stories are often delightfully, crushingly funny, even if I found myself occasionally wondering if I was rereading sections of Nora Ephron's ''Heartburn.'' (In Dormen's book, as in Ephron's, there's much discussion of cooking, home renovation and affairs with diplomats. But in ''The Best Place to Be,'' the women are having affairs with Egyptian diplomats or the Palestinian representative to Mozambique, while in ''Heartburn,'' Thelma Rice fools around with the under secretary of the Nationalist Chinese Embassy, not to mention the narrator's husband.)</p>
        <p>As Grace advances deep into middle age, she is witnessing the demise of the previous generation: ''All the parents were dying, the decent ones and the nightmares, the incest parents and the saints, the parents who doted and the ones who drank. ... Who would be left to remember World War II and the cha-cha and the thank-you note? Yes, the end of Communism was huge. But the end of parents!''</p>
        <p>Other stories have Grace in her 30s, spending three sessions with her therapist discussing whether to accept a raccoon coat from her mother, with whom she has a glamour conflict: her mother is glamorous; she is dowdy. Going even farther back, we see Grace as a college student in the 1960s, in love with Robert F. Kennedy. In one story, she goes on a boring blind date and realizes halfway through that she has already been on a boring blind date with this same boring guy -- but now he cooks. Stories feature Grace having an affair with a married man, or trying to block the memory of her stepfather molesting her, or on a trip to Rome with her brother, debating whether they should scatter their mother's ashes in the Fendi shop.</p>
        <p>Enid Shomer's ''Tourist Season'' is a more ambitious literary attempt -- short stories linked only by the fact that each is about a woman at a different station in life. While both books inhabit universes where husbands care about cooking and older mothers are more chic than their middle-aged daughters, Shomer dabbles in comedy, tragedy, even magic realism, with the style of a poet. (Not surprising, since she's the author of four poetry collections.)</p>
        <p>In the opening story, a Florida speech therapist is dislodged from her suburban life by two Tibetan monks, convinced she's the reincarnation of a lama. Another woman's transformation comes via magic: 64-year-old Helen becomes younger by the day, her muscles growing firmer, her hair turning sleekly brown, until she realizes she's turning into a wolf. In Mexican folklore, her housekeeper informs her, when women get older and no one wants them anymore, they're changed into wolves or pigs and wander in packs, setting fires or baying at the moon.</p>
        <p>In another story, a divorcing couple take a last vacation. He doesn't swim. She goes deep-sea diving, but may have misjudged the effects of the ocean, making her fatally susceptible to the rapture of the deep: ''She descended ever so slowly, the pearl in the Prell shampoo bottle. ... The blue deepened to bootblack except for the area lit by her flashlight, which began to dim.''</p>
        <p>We know the real reason for her plunge: she wants to die. Shomer's characters are strong women, and by that I don't mean that they're strong enough to admit they feel comfortable with their chubby-thighed, Dove-clean bodies or strong enough to be a C.E.O. Rather, they're strong enough to know when they've had enough. They also helped me understood why Dormen wrote her book the way she did: her narrator's life is incomplete -- is in shards -- even if she's desperately, bravely, hoping to convince herself that she is, as the title suggests, in the best place to be.</p>
        <p>Alex Kuczynski is the author of ''Beauty Junkies.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Alex Kuczynski is the author of ''Beauty Junkies.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
