<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Family Tradition</title>
    <meta content="Hitchens.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851609"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0D61630F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1387" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Family Tradition</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER HITCHENS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FATHERS AND SONS</p>
        <p>The Autobiography of a Family.</p>
        <p>By Alexander Waugh.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 472 pp. Nan A. Talese/Doubleday.</p>
        <p>$27.50.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FATHERS AND SONS</p>
        <p>The Autobiography of a Family.</p>
        <p>By Alexander Waugh.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 472 pp. Nan A. Talese/Doubleday.</p>
        <p>$27.50.</p>
        <p>If students of George Bernard Shaw can be called Shavians, a friend of Evelyn Waugh's named John Sutro argued, then those interested in all things Waugh might be called Wavians. I now realize that, without knowing it, I have been a Wavian for many years. And I opened this book eagerly, anticipating a trove of revelation about the author's father, Auberon, and grandfather Evelyn. Instead, I was engrossed for almost half the book by an extraordinary depiction of the true paterfamilias, Arthur Waugh, whose position in London publishing helped launch his two sons -- the elder brother, Alec, and the younger, Evelyn -- on their careers as authors. Here is a sample of the old boy's prose. He is writing to his favorite, Alec, who has been having a spot of sexual trouble at school:</p>
        <p>''The nails that pierce the Son's hands pierce the Father's also: the thorn-crowned head of the Dying Savior is seen to be lying upon the Father's bosom. And it is always so with you and me. Every wound that touches you pierces my own soul also: every thorn in your crown of life tears my tired head as well. Be sure of that, as you are also sure (for you must be that) that when your hour of redemption comes, the first to share it will be the father who has never doubted or given way. ... With deep love and unfaltering trust, still and always, your ever devoted and hopeful Daddy.''</p>
        <p>One notes here not just the absence of stiff upper lip but something verging on the creepy: it is almost as if the man believes himself to be his boy's mother. Arthur Waugh's own childhood had been desperately short on affection (family lore referred bluntly to his father as ''the Brute'') and his overcompensation took the most extravagant forms. He would write ever more fervent letters to Alec, every single day, while reserving for Evelyn something more like disapproval. It scarcely requires a clinical psychologist to understand why Alec fled the smothering influence and became a raffish exile, while Evelyn made great literary use of the sense of being a less than wanted child.</p>
        <p>There was a time when more readers had heard of Alec Waugh than of Evelyn. His first novel, ''The Loom of Youth,'' published during the First World War, was a succÃ</p>
        <p>s de scandale on account of its portrayal of homosexuality in an identifiable English public school. His best-known later work is probably ''Island in the Sun,'' which was successfully filmed. But he himself always knew that Evelyn was the superior one. Alexander Waugh has some gentle fun with his great-uncle, representing him as an incurable philanderer and dilettante, while supplying plenty of clues about the elements that went into his grandfather's masterpiece, ''Brideshead Revisited.'' Among other parallels, there is the younger son's sense of having just missed the First World War (in which Alec fought bravely and was taken prisoner). There is the father who doesn't even pretend to like the son. And there is the weak and absent mother, who at the crucial moment goes off to join the war effort.</p>
        <p>A curious side-effect of Arthur's intense and sickly Anglican religiosity was to make Alec into an unbeliever and Evelyn into a Roman Catholic. A letter from the father about Evelyn accidentally captures the essence of what was to become the Wavian style. ''He has also been serving at the altar and going to picnics -- a weird mixture of faith and frivolity.'' Intermittent warfare between the two was to persist for decades. Evelyn put his father, in disguised but recognizable and insulting form, into ''A Handful of Dust.'' Arthur retaliated by writing to Alec's first child that ''the three great things in my life have been my mother, my wife and my son -- your father.'' The omission was deadly and deliberate. Evelyn in turn expressed a rather breezy attitude to family values by writing to his father to introduce his new (second) bride, Laura: ''She is very young, very thin, rather poor, dead silent, long-nosed, laudably devoid of literary, artistic or social ambition, lazy, affectionate, timid, ignorant. I will bring her to see you at the first opportunity.''</p>
        <p>Alexander Waugh's running joke about this long-suffering and eccentric woman is that she actually preferred cows to people. The thing is, it wasn't a joke. She really did prefer cows to people. A letter to her sister, written at the time of her son Auberon's very upsetting eye operation at the age of 7, is 80 percent taken up with news of her cows' health, allowing just room at the end to report how ''hellish'' it is to have to take ''Bron'' to doctors' appointments during his convalescence. An impressive amount of this book is in direct quotations, many from hitherto unpublished family papers and correspondence, and this ability to let his ancestors speak directly in their own voice justifies Waugh's otherwise odd choice of subtitle.</p>
        <p>Young Alexander has a high standard for what constitutes fatherhood, and his great-uncle Alec doesn't meet it. He ''was an unusual man,'' Alexander writes. ''He insisted on a stark choice between work and family, but never suggested that the same choice might apply between work and his mistresses, work and cricket, work and golf, work and his various gentlemen's clubs. All other things could be fitted in; it was only his family who couldn't.''</p>
        <p>About Alec's children he adds: ''He was friendly and polite with them, he did not argue with their mother and seldom disciplined them. Once he picked Peter up and hurled him out of a window, but that was an aberration and he felt guilty about it for the rest of his life.'' The deadpan tone here shows Alexander to be a true and worthy descendant of the line. The genius of Evelyn Waugh, apart from the combination of ''faith and frivolity,'' was his ability to be hilariously heartless. (One thinks of the risible injustices he inflicts on his characters, from Paul Pennyfeather in ''Decline and Fall'' onward.) Alexander Waugh has a good eye for the real-life version of this trope. In one single paragraph he has his grandfather referring to his dyslexic fifth child, Harriet, as ''my dud daughter,'' and poisoning another child's pet rabbits with vodka during the Christmas festivities. When his son Auberon was horribly injured while serving as a soldier in Cyprus, Evelyn chose the moment of his hospitalization to cut off the young man's allowance. His belief in original sin mutated into a campaign to make sure that life was understood, and indeed experienced, as unfair.</p>
        <p>Perhaps this is good for the soul and the character after all. It doesn't seem to have done Alexander Waugh any conspicuous harm. His father, Auberon, enjoined upon him a certain anarchic stoicism, obviously derived from his own father, about the vicious floggings that both endured at their monastic schools: ''The monks enjoyed whipping boys as a release from the constraints of their celibacy, and my father, throughout his life, always claimed that to be beaten was a small sacrifice for a boy and a great treat for a monk.''</p>
        <p>Alexander doesn't mention the novels published by his mother, Teresa Waugh (this is, after all, a book about the Y chromosome) and writes that: ''I suppose, when I think of it, that all of us Waughs only became writers to impress our fathers.'' This is (excusable) poppycock. There are almost no examples of literary talent extending through so many generations, as even the Longfords and the Amises would have to concede. Nor is it common for writers like V. S. Naipaul and A. N. Wilson to say, as both did of Auberon Waugh, that the son's stature exceeded his father's. Nobody would claim this for ''Bron's'' very slight novels, but it might well be said of his vast output of social criticism and satirical commentary. Alexander, attempting none of the above, has written well about music, published a sparkling atheist polemic -- ''God'' -- that his father offered to pay him not to write, and has now become a biographer of distinction. The apple can, in fact, fall a long way from the tree. Such is the variety of Waviana.</p>
        <p>Christopher Hitchens, a columnist for Vanity Fair, wrote the introduction to the Penguin Classics edition of Evelyn Waugh's ''Scoop.'' His latest book is ''God Is Not Great: How Religion Poisons Everything.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Christopher Hitchens, a columnist for Vanity Fair, wrote the introduction to the Penguin Classics edition of Evelyn Waugh's ''Scoop.'' His latest book is ''God Is Not Great: How Religion Poisons Everything.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
