<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Swimmers</title>
    <meta content="Cavett.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/books/review/Cavett-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851602"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Swimming Pools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Contested Waters (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E0D61630F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1252" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Swimmers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Swimmers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DICK CAVETT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CONTESTED WATERS</p>
        <p>A Social History of Swimming Pools</p>
        <p>in America.</p>
        <p>By Jeff Wiltse.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 276 pp.</p>
        <p>University of North Carolina Press. $29.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The American swimming pool has a complicated social history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CONTESTED WATERS</p>
        <p>A Social History of Swimming Pools</p>
        <p>in America.</p>
        <p>By Jeff Wiltse.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 276 pp.</p>
        <p>University of North Carolina Press. $29.95.</p>
        <p>Haven't we all awakened from time to time hoping that perhaps this will be the day a book comes along about swimming pools?</p>
        <p>What a silly idea, I thought, but I dutifully read this book anyway. I am one who came to scoff but remained to pray. It quickly becomes clear that Jeff Wiltse's ''Contested Waters'' isn't a dreary historical catalog of shapes and styles of swimming pools vast and small. It's the colorful story of America's municipal swimming pools in the 19th and 20th centuries. Against that backdrop it becomes a story of America.</p>
        <p>It's all here: a sense of this country's benevolence, its community relations, civic wars, social strata, sexuality and sexism as well as our capacity for having a good time. Chronicled along with these are our ill-feeling, prejudice, ignorance and racial strife. Public pools became flashpoints, Wiltse observes, because they were where ''Americans came into intimate and prolonged contact with one another. People who might otherwise come in no closer contact than passing on the street, now waited in line together, undressed next to one another and shared the same water.''</p>
        <p>America's public pools ranged from simple bathhouses to -- in Chicago, St. Louis and other big cities -- grand and majestic structures with beaches of hauled-in sand, chairs for reclining, and refreshment and recreation areas. These virtual resorts must have seemed, to less fortunate patrons, Taj Mahal-like in their opulence. And at their best, the pools enabled members of all classes, including those for whom vacations were undreamed of, to escape for a time the stupefying heat and frolic in the waters.</p>
        <p>Inevitably, who got to swim when, and with whom, became major concerns. Among the first public pools in America to offer mixed-gender swimming -- though blacks were excluded -- was the Fairgrounds Pool in St. Louis, which opened in 1913. Because the pool had a sandy beach, Wiltse writes, ''city officials applied the social standard of the seashore to it.'' Men and women swam together. This ''sexually charged public space,'' as Wiltse describes it, set off moral panic. Would seeing more of the other sex's body than was customary cause people to lose control? Later, I recall, someone even came up with a crackpot theory that men and women's swimming in the same water could result in pregnancy. The theory held that spermatozoa -- presumably with navigation skills rivaling those of Captain Bligh -- might just find their way home, as it were.</p>
        <p>Before there were public pools, both young and older boys swam ''mother nekkid'' in rivers and streams beside towns and cities. The strait-laced, who seemed somehow unable to look elsewhere, were distressed. A man still living recalls the hazards, including the occasional drowning, of swimming as a kid in the Hudson River, accompanied by garbage, condoms, feces, giant rats and, now and then, human remains.</p>
        <p>Both boys and men climbed up and peeked over the fences that walled in the pools frequented by the fair sex, enjoying the novelty of females in the act of swimming. Women's swimsuits revealed little more than the lower arm and lower leg, but sometimes clung, causing consternation among the guardians of propriety.</p>
        <p>Pools with their showers did tend to serve the civic goal of helping to get the great unwashed washed. Laborers and immigrants often had no baths in their homes. The pools, it was hoped, would serve to reduce the spread of transmittable diseases.</p>
        <p>Some pools served all classes, so poor kids met rich kids they would never have known. So did adults, and in the minimal, non-designer pool clothing of the time. Because expensive watches and jewelry were left in locker rooms, signs of rank were absent and status was hard to discern. People actually made friends outside their class.</p>
        <p>All in all, the pools that blossomed all over America were a blessing to the thousands of city dwellers imprisoned in wretched living conditions. In some cases, the races swam harmoniously. (Because many black men were heavy laborers, they often exhibited muscled torsos. This, along with the widely accepted myth of the sex-crazed black male, enhanced fears that white ladies seeing them might be, well, impressed. White men began to work out.)</p>
        <p>In others places, and not only in the South, blacks trying to swim were shoved out of line, punched, kicked and pelted with rocks. When lucky enough to somehow make it past the showers and into the water, they were surrounded, slugged, shoved under and all but drowned by whites.</p>
        <p>Wiltse writes well about the slow and painful desegregation of America's public pools -- the result of constant pressure, in the form of protests and lawsuits, by groups like the N.A.A.C.P. -- in the 1940s and '50s. It was an ugly period. The pool guards and police, if any, either did nothing or joined in with the attackers. (Gore Vidal on an old show of mine: ''We must always remember that the police are recruited from the criminal classes.'') The victims, not the assailants, were often arrested for creating disorder.</p>
        <p>I can't imagine the combination of bravery, pride and fear required in those who persisted, returned and suffered further brutality. All for presuming that they, too, were entitled to enjoy blessed relief from the heat, and to have some fun. The pools were, after all, ''public.'' Sometimes, in the face of their sheer persistence, the white enemy tired of warfare and the blacks got in unharmed. As those pools became unsegregated, white attendance plummeted, and the pools would sometimes close.</p>
        <p>Anyone who has endured the equatorial, sweltering night-and-day heat of St. Louis or Kansas City in summer can only wonder how those cities' residents did it. Some lived with many family members in one-room dwellings with no windows, no moving air and no running water. Many houses stood in sewage. What a few cool and happy hours at a pool meant to those people would make heaven an anticlimax.</p>
        <p>Many pools were built for blacks only and built where they lived. Likewise for lower-class whites. This was partly out of civic benevolence but mainly to keep them in their own neighborhoods. The pools for whites would have bordering sand ''beaches'' for lolling. Those for blacks were merely fenced. Separate was not equal.</p>
        <p>A pool at the north end of Central Park, proposed about 1910, ran into heavy resistance. Wealthy aldermen felt that the park was for gentlemen and ladies who rode horseback and in carriages. The New York Times weighed in, fearing that the pool would be a ''disease breeder''; its news pages reported the mayor's fear that ''if it is used by all classes it will become foul.'' Wiltse tells us: ''Middle-class Americans at the time perceived immigrants, laborers and blacks as equally dirty and prone to carry communicable diseases. As a result, they avoided swimming in the same pool with the working classes no matter their race or ethnicity.''</p>
        <p>I fear I lack the art of book reviewing. I don't know how to convey the sweep of the social history of this book, or its emotional color. At the end, Wiltse laments the passing of the great romantic pools and recalls his own experience of one in Seattle. They're his most cherished childhood memories. Finishing ''Contested Waters,'' I felt I'd had a good course in America. All its traits, fine and lamentable are found here -- the most vivid being, alas, ourstinking racism.</p>
        <p>Dick Cavett, the former television talk-show host, is a columnist for TimesSelect.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Dick Cavett, the former television talk-show host, is a columnist for TimesSelect.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
