<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If Artists Ventured to the East End, He Snapped Them</title>
    <meta content="03artsliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03artsli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851726"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pollock-Krasner House and Study Center (East Hampton, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genocchio, Benjamin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">budnick, dan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Pollock-Krasner House and Study Center</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E5D71430F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If Artists Ventured to the East End, He Snapped Them</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">If Artists Ventured to the East End, He Snapped Them</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN GENOCCHIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genocchio, Benjamin</byline>
      <dateline>EAST HAMPTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Benjamin Genocchio reviews exhibit of photographs by Dan Budnick of famous artists who have lived in, worked in or visited Long Island's East End, on view at Pollock-Krasner House and Study Center in East Hampton; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dan Budnick's photographs of famous artists who have lived in, worked in or visited the East End are spread around the walls of the main room of the Pollock-Krasner House and Study Center here like so many cocktail party guests. The setting is nicely appropriate, for the former home of Jackson Pollock and his wife, the painter Lee Krasner, was once a summer gathering place for artists, critics, socialites and art world hangers-on.</p>
        <p>The selection focuses on abstract painters associated with the New York School, whose members congregated in the area after Pollock and Krasner moved out from New York permanently in 1945. Among those who had homes here were Willem and Elaine de Kooning, Mark Rothko, Helen Frankenthaler and Robert Motherwell. But there are also pictures of artists associated with later movements like Pop art, including Roy Lichtenstein, Claes Oldenburg and Philip Guston.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dan Budnick’s photographs of famous artists who have lived in, worked in or visited the East End are on view at the Pollock-Krasner House and Study Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dan Budnick's photographs of famous artists who have lived in, worked in or visited the East End are spread around the walls of the main room of the Pollock-Krasner House and Study Center here like so many cocktail party guests. The setting is nicely appropriate, for the former home of Jackson Pollock and his wife, the painter Lee Krasner, was once a summer gathering place for artists, critics, socialites and art world hangers-on.</p>
        <p>The selection focuses on abstract painters associated with the New York School, whose members congregated in the area after Pollock and Krasner moved out from New York permanently in 1945. Among those who had homes here were Willem and Elaine de Kooning, Mark Rothko, Helen Frankenthaler and Robert Motherwell. But there are also pictures of artists associated with later movements like Pop art, including Roy Lichtenstein, Claes Oldenburg and Philip Guston.</p>
        <p>The pictures document the artists in their studios or commemorate tender private moments, which elevates the photographs above the level of mere society portraiture. Then, too, Mr. Budnick, born in 1933, is a talented professional photographer whose career has spanned half a century. His photo essays have appeared in magazines and newspapers including The New York Times Magazine, The Times of London, Look, Newsweek, Vogue and Fortune.</p>
        <p>Standouts include the 1964 portrait of the early modern pioneer Stuart Davis, taken in the artist's New York studio the year he died. Davis fills the right side of the frame, scowling at the camera with his hands on his hips. It is almost as if he is saying to Mr. Budnick, ''Get out of here, kid, I've got work to do.'' During his twilight years Mr. Davis painted expressive, joyful abstracts, as witnessed by a group of late paintings of blocky shapes in fluorescent-bright colors lying around the studio behind him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis is something of an interloper in this exhibition, for he hated the beach and rarely came out to the East End. His portrait was included here by the exhibition's curator, Helen A. Harrison, because he is buried, at the request of his wife, in Green River Cemetery in Springs. You can't help but think he would not have been happy about this choice of final resting place.</p>
        <p>Among the area's living resident artists depicted here is John Chamberlain, who has a studio on Shelter Island. His portrait, from 1966, shows him smoking a cigarette next to one of his roughly elegant minimalist sculptures of smashed-up car parts. There is a similar toughness to his appearance, with slicked-back hair, dark glasses and a large handlebar mustache.</p>
        <p>Other pictures also brilliantly match artworks with the personality and appearance of their creators. A prime example is the 1965 portrait of Alexander Calder in his studio in Connecticut -- he was a visitor to the East End -- which shows the artist surrounded by a mess of paintings, models and mobiles, along with bits and pieces of artworks-in-progress hanging from diagonal rows of string attached to the ceiling. Mr. Budnick has wickedly positioned the old Surrealist sculptor in such a way that some of the lines of string appear to be emanating from his head. It's priceless.</p>
        <p>Other portraits are meant to dazzle. A portrait of Lichtenstein depicts him behind a screen of Benday dots, for instance, and another shows him in the studio surrounded by a mountain of comic books from which he is shamelessly lifting images for paintings. His sons, David and Mitchell, are on the floor in front of him, reading comics. This picture takes as its loose subject the apparent disconnect between the public image of the artist and his private studio behavior.</p>
        <p>The rest of the photographs are just as interesting, containing not a shred of sameness or uniformity, a common limitation of so much celebrity-oriented portraiture. Each is its own unique image, redolent with the personality of its subject. The resulting portraits often blur the line between documentary and fiction.</p>
        <p>''Picturing Artists (1950s-1960s): Photographs by Dan Budnick,'' Pollock-Krasner House and Study Center, 830 Fireplace Road, East Hampton, through July 29. Information: (631) 324-4929 or naples.cc.sunysb.edu/CAS/pkhouse.nsf.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
