<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Demand for School Chiefs Pushes Salaries Up</title>
    <meta content="03mainweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03mainwe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851775"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="EDUCATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">School Administration and Community Role</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fessenden, Ford</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">School Administration and Community Role</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E2DD1530F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Demand for School Chiefs Pushes Salaries Up</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Demand for School Chiefs Pushes Salaries Up</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FORD FESSENDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fessenden, Ford</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Figures released by New York State show that salaries for school superintendents rose at rate well above inflation in Westchester County last year; median pay package for top job in local school districts is $288,400, increase of 7.1 percent from 2006-7; school board officials attribute increase to difficulty of finding suitable candidates; chart; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SALARIES for school superintendents rose at a rate well above inflation in Westchester last year, according to new state figures. School board officials attribute the increase to the difficulty of finding candidates capable of meeting the high expectations of suburban parents and homeowners.</p>
        <p>In Mount Vernon, for example, the school board is searching for a replacement for its superintendent, Brenda L. Smith, who is retiring at the end of the school year to work for an international church ministry. The board has budgeted just under $317,000 in salary and benefits to hire a new superintendent, an increase of nearly $100,000, or 45 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>SALARIES for school superintendents rose at a rate well above inflation in Westchester last year, according to new state figures. School board officials attribute the increase to the difficulty of finding candidates capable of meeting the high expectations of suburban parents and homeowners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SALARIES for school superintendents rose at a rate well above inflation in Westchester last year, according to new state figures. School board officials attribute the increase to the difficulty of finding candidates capable of meeting the high expectations of suburban parents and homeowners.</p>
        <p>In Mount Vernon, for example, the school board is searching for a replacement for its superintendent, Brenda L. Smith, who is retiring at the end of the school year to work for an international church ministry. The board has budgeted just under $317,000 in salary and benefits to hire a new superintendent, an increase of nearly $100,000, or 45 percent.</p>
        <p>''In order to entice anyone to come into Westchester, we had to be competitive with the rest of the salaries in Westchester,'' said Lynn McBride, the school board president in Mount Vernon, one of the county's least wealthy districts. ''Our superintendent has been one of the lowest paid.''</p>
        <p>She said the actual pay and benefits for the new superintendent could end up being lower, depending on the candidate and negotiations.</p>
        <p>For 2007-8, the median pay package for the top job in the county's 39 districts is $288,400, including salary and benefits -- an increase of 7.1 percent from 2006-7, according to data the districts reported to the state. Thirteen superintendents will make more than $300,000 in total compensation next school year; seven did so in 2006-7.</p>
        <p>Robert J. Roelle, the Ossining superintendent, is the highest paid public school executive in Westchester, with salary and benefits worth more than $345,000 in 2007-8.</p>
        <p>Superintendents' pay has been rising about 6 percent to 7 percent a year for the last three years, mirroring other costs in school districts, which have also been rising more sharply than the inflation rate of 3 percent.</p>
        <p>The median pay package for assistant superintendents rose 5.1 percent, to $208,250. And teachers' salaries rise about 5 percent to 6 percent a year, district officials say.</p>
        <p>Westchester's administrators are the best paid in the state, by a wide margin. The median salary for superintendents is 16 percent higher than on Long Island, and 66 percent higher than the state median of $173,400.</p>
        <p>At a time when residents are complaining about high property taxes, and the state is sending millions of new dollars to suburban school districts, Westchester districts now pay about $10.8 million, an increase of 18 percent since 2004-5, for the superintendents who oversee the education of 122,000 students.</p>
        <p>School board officials say they see little alternative to the continued increase in salaries, but also say they have little difficulty justifying the cost to voters.</p>
        <p>The superintendent in Briarcliff Manor, Frances G. Wills, will get a 9.5 percent raise in pay and benefits next year, to nearly $314,000.</p>
        <p>Susan Bodansky, the school board president, said: ''We want to pay her what we feel she deserves and what's comparable with others in the county, and the amount commensurate with the work she gives us. To get a new superintendent would be an extremely expensive proposition in money and time, and I don't know if we would get someone as good as she is.''</p>
        <p>A survey by the New York State Council of School Superintendents in 2006 found more and more districts offering higher pay and incentives to keep superintendents. The average age of superintendents is increasing, because educators are taking the job later in their careers, and the average term of a superintendent is shrinking, said Robert N. Lowry Jr., the council's deputy director.</p>
        <p>''We found an increase in the number of superintendents with incentives in their contracts to encourage them to stay in their current district -- from 13.3 percent in 2003, to 26.7 percent in 2006,'' Mr. Lowry said in an e-mail message.</p>
        <p>Residents may express alarm at the compensation levels, school board members say, yet they also demand that their school districts maintain reputations for high quality and achievement.</p>
        <p>''Community expectations are extremely high,'' said Lois Winkler, vice president of the Westchester-Putnam School Boards Association and a school board member in Pleasantville. ''The community wants a lot for their children, and they're very vocal about it.''</p>
        <p>Voters, who can reject school budgets in public elections, have been willing to put up with large increases in property taxes in recent years. ''I guess most people believe in the public school system,'' said Ms. McBride of Mount Vernon, where voters approved a 6.5 percent increase in the tax levy on May 15 for a budget that contained the big increase in superintendent salary and benefits. ''They're grateful we are trying to keep the taxes as low as we can.''</p>
        <p>State law requires school districts to report the salaries of their top administrators and any principals who make more than $110,000. Most districts comply, but some do not, and state officials say they have no authority to compel them.</p>
        <p>The salaries of Westchester school administrators are not out of line with other school costs. At 1.84 percent of total budgets, on average, the county's administrative costs are below the median for the state, which was 2 percent, according to figures reported to the state in 2005.</p>
        <p>Census figures released last week show that Westchester and Long Island rank at the top among more than 10,000 school districts across the country in spending per pupil, except for a few in sparsely populated areas that must hire more teachers to reach far-flung students. Among districts with more than 250 students, 13 of the top 24 were on Long Island or in Westchester, with the rest in Alaska and Wyoming.</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
