<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Turkey, It's First Down and Miles to Go</title>
    <meta content="03cheer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/sports/football/03cheer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851983"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CHEERING SECTION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey/Istanbul</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey/Ankara</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Turkey</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Ankara (Turkey)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Istanbul (Turkey)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E3DB1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1078" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Turkey, It's First Down and Miles to Go</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Turkey, It’s First Down and Miles to Go</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK ST. AMANT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Until recently, I never would have guessed that a football mecca could take shape anywhere near the actual Mecca. But then I received an e-mail message from a Hilmi Celtikciolu.</p>
        <p>Celtikciolu, from Ankara, Turkey, was writing to me about my fantasy football book. He had been a huge N.F.L. fan since 1995, when he started watching a tape-delayed N.F.L. game of the week on Fox Turkey. While I was surprised to learn that I had a reader outside my ZIP code, let alone near the Black Sea, I was more amazed by something he added almost as an afterthought:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Turkey is not on the shortlist for places likely to adopt American football. And yet what would eventually become the Turkish American Football League began in Istanbul in 1987.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Until recently, I never would have guessed that a football mecca could take shape anywhere near the actual Mecca. But then I received an e-mail message from a Hilmi Celtikciolu.</p>
        <p>Celtikciolu, from Ankara, Turkey, was writing to me about my fantasy football book. He had been a huge N.F.L. fan since 1995, when he started watching a tape-delayed N.F.L. game of the week on Fox Turkey. While I was surprised to learn that I had a reader outside my ZIP code, let alone near the Black Sea, I was more amazed by something he added almost as an afterthought:</p>
        <p>''I played football here for years, and now I'm coaching defense,'' he said. ''So 'the disease' is spreading to Muslim countries. How about that?''</p>
        <p>Turkey is the only secular democracy in the Muslim world and is progressive by Middle Eastern standards, but it is not exactly on the shortlist for places likely to adopt American football. Soccer is a national obsession, as is the ancient sport of wrestling. Also, according to Pew Global Attitudes Project, only 12 percent of Turks view us favorably.</p>
        <p>So how in the name of George Halas is this American sport gaining popularity in a part of the world where the United States is not popular?</p>
        <p>''Ah, the journalist in you wants to know why we've started playing the 'infidel sport,' '' he wrote jokingly in a later e-mail message. ''You should come see for yourself.''</p>
        <p>So I did.</p>
        <p>I landed in Ankara at 3:45 a.m. on Monday, May 7, and Celtikciolu kindly insisted on picking me up.</p>
        <p>What would eventually become the Turkish American Football League appeared to start at Bogazici University in Istanbul in 1987, when some local American Navy men played a pickup game with curious students: no pads, no helmets, explaining the rules as they went. The students were intrigued enough to form a club team, the Bogazici Sultans.</p>
        <p>Word soon spread to other Istanbul and Ankara universities, and they formed clubs -- like the team Celtikciolu coaches, the Gazi University Warriors -- and recruited the way any campus club finds members: orientation-day booths, dorm fliers, word of mouth.</p>
        <p>But this being the dark ages before eBay, actual football equipment was nearly impossible to find. Although they did receive occasional equipment donations from American coaches and other, as Celtikciolu called them, Christian missionaries, who conducted an annual football clinic and hoped to ''convert a few Muslims,'' players simply toughed it out without protection.</p>
        <p>But by 2005, teams had scraped up the money -- from private sponsors, personal savings or spare change from their colleges -- to buy helmets and pads. That same year, the government-affiliated sports federation that runs other ''infidel'' leagues (baseball and softball) expanded to include football as an official sport. When I arrived, the T.A.F.L. was two years old and 18 teams strong.</p>
        <p>The how of Turkish football was clear, but I was more interested in the why. After all, these guys had no football frame of reference growing up. No Pop Warner to teach the basics. No high school programs. And certainly no Turkish professionals whom they could dream of being when they grew up. (Gatorade never quite got around to that ''Be Like Mehmet'' ad campaign.)</p>
        <p>I got stock answers at first: the camaraderie; going on road trips to games; the hitting; knowing that 40 guys have your back at all times.</p>
        <p>But there had to be more to it than testosterone-fueled friendship. They were at an age (18 to 22) when most people are on their own for the first time. So might the attraction have also been about rebellion, defying conventional authority -- be it religious or parental -- and rejecting what society deems acceptable?</p>
        <p>''Yes, some of us are forbidden to play,'' said a 21-year-old tailback nicknamed Straw for his lanky build. He slouched comfortably, forearm resting on the shoulder of a defensive end sitting next to him, and seemed to be speaking for everyone.</p>
        <p>He scratched his Mohawk haircut as Celtikciolu translated: ''Guys sneak to practice and hide their equipment so their parents won't find out. Our friends don't like that we don't play soccer. They act like soccer was invented in Turkey or something, or that it's the 'proper' Muslim sport. They don't even know what football is -- some think it's your fake wrestling, how is it called, the W.W.E.? But them not liking it makes me want to play more.''</p>
        <p>Driving back to my hotel, Celtikciolu offered his own theory. ''I think Turks just want to belong,'' he said. ''We're not really accepted by Europe, because they think some Muslim customs are archaic. And we're not accepted by the Middle East because they feel that we're not Muslim enough. We don't belong anywhere, really.''</p>
        <p>After five days of absorbing Turkish football information like so much secondhand hookah smoke, it was finally time to see some action. Luckily for my visit, the second-place Warriors had reached their first T.A.F.L. ''Super Bowl'' against the first-place Hacettepe University Red Deers.</p>
        <p>There were maybe a thousand fans on Hacettepe's campus, a huge crowd considering regular-season games attracted maybe 50. The atmosphere was charged. The game, however, was not.</p>
        <p>It was a plodding affair with sloppy arm-tackling and missed blocks that would have led to concussions in the States. A below-average Texas high school team would have annihilated each squad. Add to that the neophyte referees who huddled more often than the players as they debated penalty flags -- not surprising considering they learned most of the rules by playing the EA Sports Madden games.</p>
        <p>There were six total pass attempts as the teams ran conservative offenses like the double wing, with tight formations, no wideouts and countless misdirection handoffs.</p>
        <p>After more than five hours, the game ended with Hacettepe winning, 15-12, on a short field goal (appropriate for the soccer-crazed nation). Some Warriors wept. Others threw their helmets in disgust. But paraphrasing a Little League cliché, it was not whether they won or lost, it was that they played here at all. I was thankful to be halfway around the world at the invitation of a stranger, making new friends based on an almost Neanderthal-level bond: You like football. Me like football. We be friends.</p>
        <p>Most of all, I was happy to return home and report that when it comes to the ever-growing list of places that have discovered our sport and hope to see it flourish, Turkey, for all its inevitable growing pains, most definitely belongs.</p>
        <p>CHEERING SECTION Mark St. Amant is the author of ''Just Kick It: Tales of an Underdog, Over-Age, Out-of-Place Semi-Pro Football Player.'' E-mail: cheers@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Mark St. Amant is the author of ''Just Kick It: Tales of an Underdog, Over-Age, Out-of-Place Semi-Pro Football Player.'' E-mail: cheers@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
