<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Moondoggie Needs an Intervention</title>
    <meta content="0603play-entertain" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Play" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/sports/playmagazine/0603play-entertain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852067"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ENTERTAINMENTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cincinnati (Ohio)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hawaii</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milch, David, Warren, Robert Penn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Surfing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio/Cincinnati</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Surfing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surfing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Cincinnati (Ohio)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Hawaii</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Home Box Office</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Beach Boys</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Milch, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Warren, Robert Penn</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE6D91030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1335" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Moondoggie Needs an Intervention</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Moondoggie Needs an Intervention</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CARR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To surf, a small verb lacking filigree or urgency, belongs to magical realism as much as to sport. Hawaiians, who were perhaps the first surfers, prayed for good conditions and venerated those who could truly harness a wave. Mark Twain wrote rapturously of his first encounter with surfing, watching a native Hawaiian ''face the shore and wait for a particularly prodigious billow to come along; at the right moment he would fling his board upon its foamy crest and himself upon the board, and here he would come whizzing by like a bombshell!'' When people started to explore the Internet, which promised endless possibility to anyone with a computer, they called it surfing.</p>
        <p>The magic and the promise aren't quite so sunny in the newest series from HBO, ''John From Cincinnati,'' which makes its debut on June 10, right after the final episode of ''The Sopranos.'' Despite being set in the Southern California surfing scene, the show is less about mastering the waves than surviving amid them. The first episode is filled with conflicts, scams, addiction and corruption, all familiar concerns to anyone who knows the work of its executive producer, David Milch, who created ''NYPD Blue'' and, more recently, ''Deadwood.'' And there are the usual compelling sidebars and memorable characters -- a lawyer named Dickstein, a retired cop who looks after birds and humans, gangsters in beach casual.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The surfers in HBO’s new show “John From Cincinnati” won’t be hanging 10 with Gidget anytime soon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To surf, a small verb lacking filigree or urgency, belongs to magical realism as much as to sport. Hawaiians, who were perhaps the first surfers, prayed for good conditions and venerated those who could truly harness a wave. Mark Twain wrote rapturously of his first encounter with surfing, watching a native Hawaiian ''face the shore and wait for a particularly prodigious billow to come along; at the right moment he would fling his board upon its foamy crest and himself upon the board, and here he would come whizzing by like a bombshell!'' When people started to explore the Internet, which promised endless possibility to anyone with a computer, they called it surfing.</p>
        <p>The magic and the promise aren't quite so sunny in the newest series from HBO, ''John From Cincinnati,'' which makes its debut on June 10, right after the final episode of ''The Sopranos.'' Despite being set in the Southern California surfing scene, the show is less about mastering the waves than surviving amid them. The first episode is filled with conflicts, scams, addiction and corruption, all familiar concerns to anyone who knows the work of its executive producer, David Milch, who created ''NYPD Blue'' and, more recently, ''Deadwood.'' And there are the usual compelling sidebars and memorable characters -- a lawyer named Dickstein, a retired cop who looks after birds and humans, gangsters in beach casual.</p>
        <p>The surfers in ''John From Cincinnati'' are an obsessive, emotionally gimped bunch whose only good choices seem to be made in the water. The rest of life baffles them. The family of famous, world-class surfers at the heart of the show, the Yosts, seems to have a gene for dysfunction -- along with one for truly heavy surfing skills -- that it passes down from generation to generation. The first three episodes suggest that the show will echo the weave of sacred and profane that made ''Deadwood'' so hard to look away from. In that series, set in a gold-rush-era Deadwood, in the Dakota Territory, an ad hoc tribe formed around the pursuit of gold and sorted itself over three seasons through power plays, intrigue and, when those didn't do the trick, gunfire and a trip to an omnivorous hog pen. The people in ''John'' are at the end of that Western expansion, at the final frontier where the land meets the water in this instance, the compromised and polluted ocean waters off the grubby border town of present-day Imperial Beach. And where Butchie Yost (Brian Van Holt), who once dominated the waves, is now a loser slamming dope in a decrepit motel, his former greatness serving as little more than an indictment of his current circumstances.</p>
        <p>Near the end of the first episode, there's a moment when the land recedes as Butchie and his son, Shaun (Greyson Fletcher), paddle out with John (Austin Nichols), who is probably not from Cincinnati. He was found wandering along the border with Mexico, but he seems to come from points beyond. He is something of an idiot, prone to simply repeating what is said to him. But as the waves and the Killers swell on the soundtrack (''I got soul, but I'm not a soldier''), John shows that he's a physical savant as well as an idiot. He duck-dives through the incoming surf on the way out, then grabs a wave and makes sure-footed pumps up to the crest before leaving its grasp against a brilliant setting sun, only to land gracefully and begin riding anew. A sense of possibility, of the limitless horizon you can only see from the top of the wave, gives the dark proceedings a hopeful lilt.</p>
        <p>Milch is an intellectual descendant of Robert Penn Warren's; he lectured in English literature at Yale, from which he had graduated Phi Beta Kappa and summa cum laude. He has also played the horses and conducted extensive personal research into illicit pharmacology -- he has talked repeatedly about his experiences as an addict. All of Milch's endeavors reflect waves in one form or another, and are deepened by the expansive, complicated life that created them. You can see where he might find similarities -- and the stuff of drama -- in the pursuits of getting high and catching a wave. ''I've learned making this show that the essence of surfing is so compelling that it makes other parts of life pale by comparison,'' Milch told me in April. ''You end up chasing that first experience, a devil's bargain that is all part of the wave.''</p>
        <p>Few who watch ''John From Cincinnati'' will find themselves humming a Beach Boys song, but then surfing has a muddled cultural legacy. The movies ''Big Wednesday'' (1978) and ''Point Break'' (1991) earned some street cred among hard-core surfers for getting at least part of it right. Yet the '60s TV show ''Gidget,'' with its cheesy, low-tech glories depicting Sally Field on a surfboard, is also solidly lodged in the pop culture. And no one is going to mistake ''John'' for the epic, sensual tableau of ''Blue Crush,'' a 2002 movie awash with bikinis and wave-borne catfights: verisimilitude is important to Milch's show. A host of world-conquering surfers -- among them Brock Little,</p>
        <p>Dan Malloy, Shane Beschen and the rising rock star of the sport, the 12-year-old John John Florence -- were brought in to make sure that the surfer-speak and action seems credible. (When I spoke to Milch this spring, he was in the middle of a shoot on Imperial Beach and was having trouble capturing the essence of surfing on film.</p>
        <p>''It may be frustrating, but it's also good,'' he said. ''I think it brings you to an understanding that you are just a visitor, that the wave will do what it wants to and that you just have to go with it.'')</p>
        <p>To get things right, Milch also tapped Kem Nunn to be one of the show's writers. Nunn is the author of several novels often labeled as surf noir; these include ''The Dogs of Winter'' and ''Tijuana Straits,'' which is set in the same borderland territory as ''John From Cincinnati.'' In Nunn's work, even the garden spots have their shadows. ''When you think of down and gritty, you think of the slums of Detroit,'' Nunn told me. ''But in Southern California, a place that is very funky and dangerous can be beautiful, with palm trees.''</p>
        <p>''John From Cincinnati'' embraces that underbelly of surfing, which may be closer to the essence of the sport. The leisure elites whose hunts for monster waves are powered by tow-in watercraft and the platinum Visa cards in their Quiksilver shorts are nowhere in sight. Mitch Yost (Bruce Greenwood), the patriarch of the family, and his wife, Cissy (Rebecca De Mornay), spend a lot of time staring down the allure of a sport that has turned their son, Butchie, into a persistent adolescent unable to parent his own son. Shaun -- played by a member of the famous Fletcher family of surfers -- is a quiet natural who surfs in the same way birds fly, with little effort but jaw-dropping effect.</p>
        <p>''John From Cincinnati'' is not a show that will spark a new generation of hobbyists -- board sales will not spike no matter how successful it is -- yet it may turn our attention once again to the aquatic cowboys in our midst. Anyone who has wasted a day sitting on a beach watching and wondering how people find a way to stand on water will find his gaze locked on the show for the same reason. It seems impossible that a doofus like John can pull it off, but then surfing has always represented one of the outer edges of human engagement with Newton'slaws.</p>
        <p>The misfits who inhabit ''John From Cincinnati'' seem so ill-suited to terrestrial concerns that you half expect the polarity of the waves to reverse and carry the surfers out into a vast, watery expanse where human concerns shrink to a mere speck and then finally disappear.</p>
        <p>David Carr is a reporter and columnist for The New York Times.</p>
        <p>ENTERTAINMENTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
