<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Trial, Colonel's Role in Haditha Questioned</title>
    <meta content="03haditha" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/world/middleeast/03haditha.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852014"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="REACH OF WAR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Haditha (Iraq)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Al Qaeda (Terrorist Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Von Zielbauer, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Conlin, Christopher C (Lt Col)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chessani, Jeffrey R (Lt Col)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Military Personnel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Personnel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Haditha (Iraq)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Al Qaeda</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E3DA1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="622" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Trial, Colonel's Role in Haditha Questioned</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Investigator Faults Colonel for Actions During Killings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL von ZIELBAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Von Zielbauer, Paul</byline>
      <dateline>CAMP PENDLETON, Calif., June 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Col Christopher Conlin is Marine infantry officer investigating accusations against Lt Col Jeffrey R Chessani, former battalion commander in charge of marines who killed 24 Iraqi civilians at Haditha in 2005; he criticizes Chessani's decision to remain miles away during battle with insurgents linked to Al Qaeda (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Marine infantry officer investigating accusations against a former battalion commander in charge of marines who killed 24 Iraqi civilians in 2005 on Saturday implicitly criticized the commander's decisions to remain miles away during an hours-long battle with insurgents linked to Al Qaeda.</p>
        <p>The investigating officer, Col. Christopher Conlin, a former battalion commander in Iraq, is the presiding officer at the hearing for Lt. Col. Jeffrey R. Chessani, who is charged with dereliction of duty for failing to properly investigate and report the civilian deaths to his superiors. During a Nov. 19, 2005, battle in and around Haditha, Iraq, a dangerous Sunni-Arab region in Anbar Province west of Baghdad, Colonel Chessani remained in his battalion's combat operations center, about seven miles from where Marine units were engaged in the heaviest fighting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Marine investigating officer implicitly criticized a commander’s decisions to remain miles away during a battle with insurgents in and around Haditha, Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Marine infantry officer investigating accusations against a former battalion commander in charge of marines who killed 24 Iraqi civilians in 2005 on Saturday implicitly criticized the commander's decisions to remain miles away during an hours-long battle with insurgents linked to Al Qaeda.</p>
        <p>The investigating officer, Col. Christopher Conlin, a former battalion commander in Iraq, is the presiding officer at the hearing for Lt. Col. Jeffrey R. Chessani, who is charged with dereliction of duty for failing to properly investigate and report the civilian deaths to his superiors. During a Nov. 19, 2005, battle in and around Haditha, Iraq, a dangerous Sunni-Arab region in Anbar Province west of Baghdad, Colonel Chessani remained in his battalion's combat operations center, about seven miles from where Marine units were engaged in the heaviest fighting.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, Colonel Conlin questioned a witness, Maj. Samuel Carrasco, Colonel Chessani's operations officer in Haditha, about whether Colonel Chessani was right to remain that far removed from the battle, during which marines killed many civilians in their homes while hunting insurgents who had bombed their convoy.</p>
        <p>Colonel Conlin told Major Carrasco that he could think of other battalion commanders who would have insisted on being closer to the battle, for tactical and other reasons, instead of directing combat from a Marine base that relied on grainy video feeds from an aerial drone.</p>
        <p>Relying on the drone's video, which offered only narrow views, was like looking at the battlefield through a ''soda straw,'' Colonel Conlin said, adding that he had led a battalion around Najaf, a Shiite holy city south of Baghdad, earlier in the war.</p>
        <p>Colonel Conlin asked Major Carrasco how he would have felt if he were a company commander , instead of a battalion operations officer, fighting the enemy in Haditha while the battalion's commander remained in a combat operations center.</p>
        <p>Major Carrasco said that in that case, he would have been upset.</p>
        <p>The exchange amounted to a rare criticism of an officer accused of a crime by an investigating officer sitting, more or less, in judgment of him.</p>
        <p>In one respect, Colonel Conlin is an unusual choice for presiding officer in a legal hearing. He is not a lawyer, though he is being advised in the hearing by another officer who is. Despite having no experience weighing criminal charges, he is considered by Colonel Chessani's defense lawyers to be someone who could see the harrowing aspects of combat through the eyes of their client, the former commander of the Third Battalion, First Marines.</p>
        <p>For his part, Major Carrasco said he had recommended to Colonel Chessani that he remain at the Marine base during the day's battle, because venturing toward it would be prohibitively dangerous. He said Colonel Chessani agonized about the casualties his marines were taking during the day.</p>
        <p>''I believe that Colonel Chessani had a hard time with those lieutenants getting hit, and those marines being injured,'' Major Carrasco said. ''I could see on his face that it was upsetting him.''</p>
        <p>The major acknowledged that some mistakes were made by his battalion. ''Sir,'' he told Colonel Conlin, ''there is not a day or night that goes by that I don't wish we didn't do a better job.''</p>
        <p>In other testimony on Saturday, the former executive officer of the marine company at Haditha said Colonel Chessani refused to look into questions from a Time magazine reporter about the civilian deaths because he viewed them as a trap.</p>
        <p>''If we follow up with an investigation, it will be an admission of guilt,'' said the officer, First Lt. Adam P. Mathes, recalling what Colonel Chessani told him and other battalion- and company-level officers in a meeting on Jan. 29, 2006, to discuss the reporter's questions.</p>
        <p>REACH OF WAR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
