<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bridge Bombing Increases Tensions in Northern Iraq</title>
    <meta content="03iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/world/middleeast/03iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="REACH OF WAR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kurds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sunni Muslims</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baghdad (Iraq)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kirkuk (Iraq)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Diyala Province (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cave, Damien</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kurds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sunni Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kurds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sunni Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E3DA1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bridge Bombing Increases Tensions in Northern Iraq</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bridge Bombing Increases Tensions in Northern Iraq</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMIEN CAVE; Reporting was contributed by Khalid al-Ansary, Abdul Razzaq al-Saiedi and Muhanad Seloom from Baghdad, Andrew Lehren from New York, and Iraqi employees of The New York Times from Kirkuk and Diyala Province.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cave, Damien</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, June 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bomb blasts damage bridge linking highway from Baghdad with Kirkuk, heightening tensions between Arabs and Kurds and forcing traffic to detour through some of most dangerous areas of Diyala Province; destruction of bridge appears to be part of effort by Sunni insurgents to isolate Kirkuk and limit interaction between residents of different areas and sects (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bomb blasts severely damaged a bridge linking a highway from Baghdad with the northern city of Kirkuk on Saturday, the police and witnesses said, heightening tensions between Arabs and Kurds and forcing traffic to detour through some of the most dangerous areas of Diyala Province.</p>
        <p>An American tank firing at insurgents near Falluja also killed three Iraqi children on Saturday, according to a military statement, and an American helicopter was damaged by gunfire north of Baghdad and forced to land.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bomb blasts severely damaged a bridge linking Baghdad with the northern city of Kirkuk, heightening tensions between Arabs and Kurds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bomb blasts severely damaged a bridge linking a highway from Baghdad with the northern city of Kirkuk on Saturday, the police and witnesses said, heightening tensions between Arabs and Kurds and forcing traffic to detour through some of the most dangerous areas of Diyala Province.</p>
        <p>An American tank firing at insurgents near Falluja also killed three Iraqi children on Saturday, according to a military statement, and an American helicopter was damaged by gunfire north of Baghdad and forced to land.</p>
        <p>In Baghdad, a barrage of mortar shells killed at least seven people.</p>
        <p>The destruction of the Sarha bridge, about 100 miles north of Baghdad and one of the busiest crossings for vehicles moving between the capital and Kirkuk, appeared to be part of an effort by Sunni insurgents to isolate Kirkuk and limit interaction between residents of different areas and sects.</p>
        <p>Salah al-Mufaraji, a prominent tribal leader who lives near the Sarha bridge, said groups aligned with Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia were responsible for the bombing.</p>
        <p>''Gunmen move through the area freely amid the absence of the government and because the security forces can't control the area,'' he said. ''All the people living here have announced allegiance to Al Qaeda out of fear and because they can't confront it.''</p>
        <p>Abbas Hilmi, a taxi driver who travels between Baghdad and Kirkuk, said that damage to the bridge would hurt the already hobbled local economy.</p>
        <p>''It's miserable,'' he said. ''We're taxi drivers. We need the roads.''</p>
        <p>It was the second bridge leading to Kirkuk bombed this week, local leaders said, and it came on a day when a prominent Sunni tribal leader was found dead south of the city after being kidnapped Friday.</p>
        <p>The killing and the bridge bombing reflected rising tensions in the oil-rich area between Kurds and Sunni insurgents who oppose Kurdish plans to make the area part of the north's Kurdish-controlled region.</p>
        <p>The Iraqi Constitution calls for a referendum on the issue this year and Iraqi and American officials have predicted that violence will increase before the vote.</p>
        <p>Increasing attacks are likely to heighten tensions with Iraq's northern neighbor, Turkey, which has complained bitterly in recent weeks that Iraq has done nothing to control a Kurdish militant group, the Kurdistan Workers' Party, in southern Turkey. Turkey says that the United States, its NATO ally, should do more to force Iraq to control the Kurds.</p>
        <p>Kurdish leaders have rejected the demands. On Saturday, Masood Barzani, president of Iraq's Kurdish area, said, ''Turkey does not have the right to interfere'' in Kirkuk.</p>
        <p>Also north of Baghdad, gunmen killed two people, including a teacher, near a prison north of Baquba, in Diyala Province, the police said. An Iraqi soldier was also killed and four others were wounded by a roadside bomb in Muqdadiya.</p>
        <p>Residents said that frustration with the violence committed by Sunni extremists appeared to be rising in the province, but its impact is questionable.</p>
        <p>On Friday, in southern Baquba, a Sunni cleric called for joint Sunni-Shiite prayers. Only four Shiites attended, but according to several witnesses, who declined to be named, the cleric spoke harshly of Al Qaeda and called upon all of the area's armed groups to unite against it.</p>
        <p>Gunmen standing outside the mosque said they were preparing to fight back and had asked the American military for help.</p>
        <p>From the Feb. 14 start of the new security plan for Iraq to the end of May, 43 American service members died in Diyala, six more than in the same period last year, according to an analysis of military counts.</p>
        <p>Despite the recent decision by American commanders to funnel additional troops into the area, and initial signs of local resistance, there have been few signs of improvement.</p>
        <p>An American helicopter forced to make a precautionary landing in Diyala on Saturday was the second to be downed by gunfire this week.</p>
        <p>On Monday, gunmen shot down a helicopter, killed its two pilots, then detonated roadside bombs that killed six soldiers who rushed to recover their comrades and the aircraft.</p>
        <p>Their deaths added to the toll for May, already the third-deadliest month for American forces since the war started in March 2003. On Saturday, the United States military reported that another soldier was killed in a roadside bombing on Wednesday in Baghdad, raising the total deaths in May to 127.</p>
        <p>The military said the tank assault in Falluja that killed three children was being investigated. A statement said the tank fired at insurgents trying to set up roadside bombs.</p>
        <p>In Baghdad, at least 18 mortar shells landed on the residential area of Fadhil in central Baghdad, a Sunni enclave in mostly Shiite eastern Baghdad that has the been site of battles between the Iraqi Army, Shiite militias and Sunni gunmen for months.</p>
        <p>Wamidh Salah, a neighborhood leader, said that seven people from two families were killed and that 25 were wounded.</p>
        <p>''The houses in the neighborhood are old and small,'' he said. ''So mortar shells cause enormous damage, more than in other areas.''</p>
        <p>REACH OF WAR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
