<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mussina-Nieves Battery Loses Steam in Boston</title>
    <meta content="03murray" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/sports/baseball/03murray.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Clemens, Roger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EFDA1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="873" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mussina-Nieves Battery Loses Steam in Boston</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Promising Start Fades Fast for Mussina-Nieves Battery</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The most expensive groin in baseball history rose up and knocked the Yankees back another step yesterday.</p>
        <p>After debating when they should implement their $28 million S.O.S. (Save Our Season) plan with Roger Clemens, the Yankees learned yesterday that the old pitcher -- and I do mean old, as in age -- will be unable to make his first start, as scheduled, tomorrow night in Chicago. His groin got him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Realistically, the Yankees were already probably too far gone for Roger Clemens to spark a turnaround. Now there is even less reason to think he can be their savior.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The most expensive groin in baseball history rose up and knocked the Yankees back another step yesterday.</p>
        <p>After debating when they should implement their $28 million S.O.S. (Save Our Season) plan with Roger Clemens, the Yankees learned yesterday that the old pitcher -- and I do mean old, as in age -- will be unable to make his first start, as scheduled, tomorrow night in Chicago. His groin got him.</p>
        <p>Clemens, who turns 45 in August, injured his groin in his most recent minor league start last Monday and has been unable to shake the injury. The Yankees don't know how long it will set him back; they said they would have a better idea when their medical people see him tomorrow in Tampa, Fla. But the delay isn't the point.</p>
        <p>Clemens had groin problems when he was significantly younger, and the older he is, the more susceptible he is to recurrences, and the longer he will need for recovery.</p>
        <p>If it's any consolation to the Yankees -- and they would say it is not -- they do not have to pay him at the rate of $28 million for the season ($153,005.46 a day) until he begins pitching for them.</p>
        <p>Realistically, the Yankees are probably too far gone for Clemens to spark a turnaround to a season that has turned disastrous. Now there is even less reason to think he can be their savior.</p>
        <p>Mike Mussina has not been their savior. Younger than Clemens by six years and millions of dollars poorer, Mussina started two games against the Red Sox in 12 days after the Yankees won the opening games of the two series. The Yankees lost both times, undermining any chance they had of making a major dent in the large lead the Red Sox had amassed over them. That lead stands at 13 1/2 games.</p>
        <p>Mussina offered hope in the second start. On May 22 at Yankee Stadium, Manny Ramírez batted against Mussina with two on and one out in the first inning and slugged a home run. In Saturday's game, Ramírez batted against Mussina with two on and one out in the first inning and grounded into a double play.</p>
        <p>Manager Joe Torre tried something different. Instead of having Jorge Posada, the regular catcher, catch Mussina, Torre substituted Wil Nieves, the backup catcher.</p>
        <p>A veteran of 11 minor league seasons and 50 major league games, Nieves had worked three of Mussina's starts, and Mussina had a 2-0 record and 2.08 earned run average. In the four starts that Posada caught, Mussina had an 0-3 record and 9.00 E.R.A.</p>
        <p>Posada did not mind the rest and, as a matter of fact, slammed a three-run homer as the designated hitter. For his part, the 29-year-old Nieves eagerly accepted the assignment to handle Mussina.</p>
        <p>''For whatever reason, Moose feels real comfortable with me,'' Nieves said. ''I just try to give him a good target, low and on the corners. It's just weird.''</p>
        <p>But in the end, it wasn't successful. The magic did not last beyond the second inning.</p>
        <p>Melky Cabrera gave the Yankees a 1-0 lead with a home run in the second inning, but the Red Sox tied the score in the third and went ahead with two runs in the fourth. Mussina, though, saved the worst for the sixth.</p>
        <p>The Yankees erupted for four runs in their half of the sixth for a 5-3 lead. When a team has a big inning and snatches the lead, it is up to the pitcher to hold the other team in its half of the inning and maintain the lead. It provides a psychological advantage, as well as a scoring advantage.</p>
        <p>Mussina did not hold the lead -- not for an inning, not for a minute. Mike Lowell led off the Red Sox sixth by crushing a home run over the left-field wall. Jason Varitek, the next batter, drove the 87-mile-an-hour fastball that Mussina threw two pitches later over the center-field fence.</p>
        <p>''We had the lead three times and lost the lead three times,'' General Manager Brian Cashman said when he was asked if the game was deflating. ''We had a game we could've controlled and didn't control it, and that's deflating.''</p>
        <p>Torre said he thought a 29-minute rain delay in the Red Sox' half of the fourth inning hurt both Mussina and Curt Schilling, the Boston starter.</p>
        <p>''Moose looked like he had a little better command than Schill,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>''Then bang-bang.''</p>
        <p>Those were the Lowell and Varitek home runs exploding over Fenway's outfield wall.</p>
        <p>''I probably would have taken him out after the first home run,'' Torre said, ''except his numbers against Varitek are so good that I decided to leave him in, and he hit the home run.''</p>
        <p>Mussina was not the losing pitcher, but as a pitcher he was a loser. Once again he was called on to move the Yankees forward, and instead he contributed significantly to a move that can be best described as a to-the-rear march.</p>
        <p>Mussina wasn't in the game in the ugly seventh inning, when the Red Sox scored five runs in their 11-6 victory. But he had already done his damage, and now who knows when Clemens will show up to try to clean the mess.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
