<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thousands Wait to Hear Ousted Pakistani Justice</title>
    <meta content="03pakistan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/world/asia/03pakistan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Islamabad (Pakistan)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Abbottabad (Pakistan)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gall, Carlotta</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chaudhry, Iftikhar Muhammad (Chief Justice)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Musharraf, Pervez (Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Pakistan</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Musharraf, Pervez</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE7DA1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thousands Wait to Hear Ousted Pakistani Justice</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Thousands Wait to Hear Ousted Pakistani Justice</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARLOTTA GALL; Salman Masood contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gall, Carlotta</byline>
      <dateline>ABBOTTABAD, Pakistan, Sunday, June 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pakistan's suspended chief justice, Iftikhar Muhammad Chaudhry, leads cavalcade of about 100 cars jammed with lawyers and political supporters on 75-mile trip from Islamabad to Abbottabad, continuing to protest his dismissal by Gen Pervez Musharraf; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pakistan's suspended chief justice led a cavalcade of about 100 cars jammed with lawyers and political supporters on a 75-mile trip from Islamabad on Saturday, continuing to protest his dismissal by Gen. Pervez Musharraf two months ago.</p>
        <p>It was the first trip outside of the capital by the justice, Iftikhar Muhammad Chaudhry, since his trip to Karachi three weeks ago. Violence between his supporters and those of General Musharraf broke out upon his arrival in Karachi, leaving more than 40 people dead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pakistan’s suspended chief justice led a cavalcade of cars on a 75-mile trip, continuing to protest his dismissal by Gen. Pervez Musharraf two months ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pakistan's suspended chief justice led a cavalcade of about 100 cars jammed with lawyers and political supporters on a 75-mile trip from Islamabad on Saturday, continuing to protest his dismissal by Gen. Pervez Musharraf two months ago.</p>
        <p>It was the first trip outside of the capital by the justice, Iftikhar Muhammad Chaudhry, since his trip to Karachi three weeks ago. Violence between his supporters and those of General Musharraf broke out upon his arrival in Karachi, leaving more than 40 people dead.</p>
        <p>The government, lawyers' associations and political parties have blamed one another for the deaths.</p>
        <p>On Friday, the government banned protests in the capital, but there was no attempt to stop Mr. Chaudhry's convoy as it left Islamabad on Saturday morning for Abbottabad, where he was to speak to the bar association.</p>
        <p>Along the route, hundreds of people stood waiting at every junction and small town.</p>
        <p>When the long motorcade passed, they tossed rose petals at Mr. Chaudhry's car, played drums and chanted, ''Until independence for the judiciary, the fight goes on!'' and ''Go! Musharraf Go!''</p>
        <p>''This is not just a movement of lawyers, but this is for you, to bring equality for you,'' Ahmed Khan, one of the lawyers representing Mr. Chaudhry, told a rally at the town of Haripur at midafternoon. ''That's why the chief justice is going around the country and why we want him reinstated.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chaudhry never left his car and did not speak to the crowds along the way.</p>
        <p>When he arrived in Abbottabad at 11:30 p.m., thousands lined the streets to welcome him.</p>
        <p>The opposition parties led by the former prime ministers Benazir Bhutto and Nawaz Sharif were out in force, as well as religious parties and other smaller group.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of lawyers waited for hours in an Abbottabad park, listening to speeches and poetry and dancing in the aisles and on stage to a popular song whose refrain refers to General Musharraf: ''Uncle, why don't you take off your uniform and go back home? Why don't you take your pension and go back home?''</p>
        <p>The chief justice finally began to speak at 2 a.m. Sunday.</p>
        <p>He told he lawyers that the judiciary should come forward as a strong institution that people could trust.</p>
        <p>''You are waging an immortal struggle for the independence of the judiciary and the supremacy of law and the Constitution,'' he said. ''You have given a lot of sacrifices, but you are not alone. The judiciary and the ordinary people are standing shoulder to shoulder with you.''</p>
        <p>He spoke of human rights and freedom of speech, citing articles of the a Constitution.</p>
        <p>The government did not try to stop the political rallies along the way in support of Mr. Chaudhry, and the police provided security.</p>
        <p>Government pressure was applied instead to the private media channels that have been following him on his tour of the country.</p>
        <p>The government media-regulating agency warned all television channels that live coverage of events was not permitted, apparently to prevent them from showing Mr. Chaudhry's speech and the rowdy cheering and chanting against General Musharraf and the government. By midafternoon, no channel was reporting live from the event.</p>
        <p>''We are encouraged and invigorated with the spirit of this reception,'' Ali Ahmed Kurd, one of lawyers representing the chief justice in his challenge against dismissal, speaking at Haripur, the main town on the way to Abbottabad and about halfway through the trip. ''If things continue like this there will be no general or commander any more.''</p>
        <p>He railed against the military commanders running the country and moves by the government to clamp down on the news media. ''If you close these channels, can you close off the people's voice from Karachi to Khyber?'' he asked the crowd.</p>
        <p>At Haripur, students, workers and retirees who turned out to hear the lawyers' speeches complained of many things, including rising prices, the increasing gap between rich and poor, the failing education system, support for the United States global campaign against terrorism and the injustice of military rule.</p>
        <p>''The work of the army is to defend the country, not rule the country,'' said Amir Shehzad, 22, a chemical engineering student at Haripur. ''There is a revolution happening. We are facing for many years a military dictatorship and people want democracy.''</p>
        <p>He said that his father, a security guard, supported the family on $60 a month and that the family could barely get by.</p>
        <p>''It's very difficult for people to live because of inflation,'' Taher Mehmud, 25, a teacher, said. ''Musharraf was welcomed at the beginning, but because of his policies people feel distanced from him.''</p>
        <p>Throughout the day, those interviewed along the route seemed to think that General Musharraf should not stay in power much longer. They called for elections, rather than a continuation of military rule.</p>
        <p>''People do support the lawyers because they are talking about justice,'' said Mubarak Dad Abbassi, 57, a government employee from Rawalpindi, early in the day, adding of Mr. Chaudhry: ''I do think there was an injustice to him. People say he should be reinstated and Musharraf should go.''</p>
        <p>Later in the morning, a 24-year-old shopkeeper, Muzzafar, in the town of Taxila, said: ''It is difficult for Musharraf now, everybody wants change. We want someone who is a fair person, who controls the prices. That is the concern of the ordinary man. It seems the time is up for military rule.''</p>
        <p>At dusk, as the convoy passed Havelian, the last town on the way to Abbottabad, a banner-waving youth yelled, ''The president is shameless!''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
