<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Mets' Fill-In Lineup Brings Down the Diamondbacks</title>
    <meta content="03mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/sports/baseball/03mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852008"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Arizona Diamondbacks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Randolph, Willie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E5DA1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="829" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Mets' Fill-In Lineup Brings Down the Diamondbacks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Mets’ Fill-In Lineup Brings Down the Diamondbacks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID PICKER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rubén Gotay had an old-fashioned case of ants in his pants before the Mets played the Diamondbacks yesterday. Gotay, a reserve infielder who can also play the outfield in a pinch, knew that several starters were injured. He hoped Manager Willie Randolph would insert him into the starting lineup. Gotay checked and double-checked the lineup board in the Mets' clubhouse, but it was not set.</p>
        <p>Gotay needed to burn off some steam, so he headed to the batting cage. On his way out of the clubhouse, Randolph pulled him aside to let him know that he would be starting at second base and batting sixth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rubén Gotay, a reserve infielder, blasted a three-run homer to help snap the Diamondbacks’ eight-game winning streak.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rubén Gotay had an old-fashioned case of ants in his pants before the Mets played the Diamondbacks yesterday. Gotay, a reserve infielder who can also play the outfield in a pinch, knew that several starters were injured. He hoped Manager Willie Randolph would insert him into the starting lineup. Gotay checked and double-checked the lineup board in the Mets' clubhouse, but it was not set.</p>
        <p>Gotay needed to burn off some steam, so he headed to the batting cage. On his way out of the clubhouse, Randolph pulled him aside to let him know that he would be starting at second base and batting sixth.</p>
        <p>Randolph probably then went looking for the next antsy reserve. For the second consecutive day, the Mets started five backups. But unlike Friday's 5-1 loss to the Diamondbacks, when their bats fell silent, the Mets' reserves made plenty of noise yesterday.</p>
        <p>No one was louder than Gotay, who blasted a three-run homer to secure a 7-1 victory at Shea Stadium and help snap the Diamondbacks' eight-game winning streak.</p>
        <p>''It's not easy,'' Gotay said about the anxiety reserves often face before games. ''At the same time, it's no excuse. You got to come to the field ready.''</p>
        <p>The other backups who started were David Newhan (left field), Endy Chávez, (center), Ben Johnson (right) and Ramón Castro (catcher). Castro's presence meant that Paul Lo Duca had a day off, but the other backups were needed because of injuries.</p>
        <p>The backups combined for six hits, five runs batted in and three runs.</p>
        <p>''What a job by the bench,'' Randolph said to members of the news media after the game. ''I told you guys before the game that my bench, they want to win as much as anyone.''</p>
        <p>On Friday, the Mets spoiled a fine outing by John Maine, mustering a measly four singles -- only one of which escaped the infield. This time, they capitalized on a sensational performance from Jorge Sosa, who allowed one run and five hits over six and two-thirds innings. He struck out four and walked one.</p>
        <p>Sosa (5-1) has been a pleasant surprise for the Mets this season, allowing two runs or fewer in all but one of his six starts. He has been something of an enigma in his career. Sosa was 13-3 in 2005 for the Atlanta Braves, but last season he went 3-11 for Atlanta and the St. Louis Cardinals.</p>
        <p>But after being called up from Class AAA New Orleans on May 5, Sosa has displayed the form he showed two seasons ago.</p>
        <p>The Diamondbacks (33-24) took a lead on Eric Byrnes's bases-empty homer in the third inning. But Sosa then retired 13 of the next 16 batters. He was replaced in the seventh inning after walking Miguel Montero on four pitches. Sosa tipped his cap as he walked off the field to a standing ovation. It was Cap Day at Shea, and many of the fans in attendance tipped their caps back.</p>
        <p>''After I gave up the homer, I made my adjustments with all my pitches,'' Sosa said through an interpreter. ''I was working ahead in the count. I was throwing all my pitches for strikes.''</p>
        <p>In the fourth inning, the Mets (35-19) scored three runs against Arizona starter Liván Hernández to take a lead they did not relinquish. Carlos Delgado smacked a solo home run, Newhan stroked a run-scoring single and Johnson hit a sacrifice fly. When Newhan singled, the Diamondbacks trailed for the first time in 45 innings.</p>
        <p>In the seventh inning, Gotay stepped to the plate with runners at second and third. He clobbered a hanging slider from reliever Juan Cruz for a home run to right field.</p>
        <p>''I know I hit it pretty good,'' said Gotay, who was 3 for 4 and scored twice.</p>
        <p>The Mets did not need a backup at third base. After missing Friday's game with back spasms, David Wright started and went 1 for 3.</p>
        <p>Carlos Beltrán is still day to day with a bruised knee, and Shawn Green (broken foot) is aiming to come off the disabled list June 10.</p>
        <p>But the news on Moises Alou was not as promising. He is still hampered by a strained left quadriceps.</p>
        <p>Alou had been feeling better most of last week, but he felt pain while running yesterday. He had been planning to return during the Mets' three-game series against the Philadelphia Phillies, which starts Tuesday at Shea. He will see a doctor tomorrow and no longer has a timetable.</p>
        <p>As long as the Mets receive contributions from their backups, Alou can take all the time he needs to recover. The Mets have been coping with injuries all season, yet they continue to find ways to win.</p>
        <p>The Mets have a day off tomorrow, so Randolph may start another lineup filled with backups today. The backups will probably check the lineup board with a healthy dose of unease.</p>
        <p>''We have a great bench,'' Castro said. ''We're here for a reason.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
