<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Offense and Defense, Lowell Leaves His Mark</title>
    <meta content="03redsox" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/sports/baseball/03redsox.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Lowell, Mike</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE5DA1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Offense and Defense, Lowell Leaves His Mark</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On Offense and Defense, Lowell Leaves His Mark</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, June 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>During the Boston Red Sox' 11-6 victory against the Yankees on Saturday at Fenway Park, Mike Lowell tormented the Yankees in just about every way possible.</p>
        <p>His hitting was powerful and productive; his fielding was flawless and sometimes subtle; and his base running was unusually violent and consequential.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>During the Boston Red Sox’ 11-6 victory against the Yankees on Saturday at Fenway Park, Mike Lowell tormented the Yankees in just about every way possible.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>During the Boston Red Sox' 11-6 victory against the Yankees on Saturday at Fenway Park, Mike Lowell tormented the Yankees in just about every way possible.</p>
        <p>His hitting was powerful and productive; his fielding was flawless and sometimes subtle; and his base running was unusually violent and consequential.</p>
        <p>Lowell had left Friday's game after being hit on the left hand with a 93-mile-an-hour fastball from Chien-Ming Wang. He returned less than 24 hours later to drive in four runs with three hits, one of them a home run.</p>
        <p>At third base, Lowell fielded four ground balls: two of them started double plays; another was a bare-handed pickup and quick throw that retired Melky Cabrera.</p>
        <p>On the bases, Lowell body-blocked second baseman Robinson Canó in the fourth inning with a shoulder to the chest while trying to break up a double play. Later, he sent first baseman Doug Mientkiewicz to the hospital when his thigh hit Mientkiewicz's head accidentally on a failed double-play attempt.</p>
        <p>That came during the decisive seventh inning, when the Red Sox scored five runs to surge ahead. Lowell, who reached second on the play, returned to first as the groggy Mientkiewicz was lifted onto a motorized vehicle.</p>
        <p>''I feel bad for Doug, you don't want anything like that to happen,'' Lowell said. ''We go way back. I played against him when I was 15 years old in high school. I wanted to say something.''</p>
        <p>But Lowell declined because, he said, medical personnel were being so careful with Mientkiewicz's head.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to get in contact with him, though,'' Lowell said. ''He knows me well enough.''</p>
        <p>Lowell's mood was less somber when discussing the collision with Canó. ''It's a clean play and it's kind of ironic,'' he said. ''That's what the Yankees taught me.''</p>
        <p>Lowell was referring to his years in the Yankees' farm system, from 1995 through 1998, which ended with eight games in a Yankees uniform. They traded him to Florida after the 1998 season for Todd Noel, Mark Johnson and Ed Yarnall, three players no longer as valued.</p>
        <p>Lowell, 33, has been undervalued since then, despite three All-Star Game appearances and one Gold Glove award.</p>
        <p>When the Marlins traded him to Boston in 2005 in a multiplayer deal that also sent pitcher Josh Beckett to the Red Sox, it was said that Lowell was included only because Florida needed to lose a large contract ($9 million a year) for a player in decline.</p>
        <p>In his first season with the Red Sox, Lowell hit .284. This season he is hitting .337, more than 60 points above his career average. He has 11 home runs and 45 runs batted in.</p>
        <p>Lowell, a survivor of testicular cancer, has a degree in finance from Florida International University. He once negotiated for a clause in his contract to let him out of his deal if the Marlins failed to obtain financing for a new stadium.</p>
        <p>In 1999, four months after his wedding, Lowell learned that he had cancer. According to a Boston Globe article earlier this year, he asked the doctor at the time, ''When am I going to die?''</p>
        <p>He is of Cuban and Puerto Rican heritage and sometimes surprises new Latin-American teammates with his fluent Spanish. His father was a dentist and a baseball player whose family left Cuba after the revolution led by Fidel Castro.</p>
        <p>He sometimes uses surprise and humor. Lowell has twice succeeded in performing the hidden-ball trick, retiring unsuspecting runners at third base in 2004 and 2005. He has a full head of dark hair that is beginning to go show gray and a neatly trimmed goatee.</p>
        <p>After Saturday's game, he wore a gray T-shirt that said ''Red Sox Strength.'' When a reporter asked him what he had said to Derek Jeter as they walked back to toward second base after the injury to Mientkiewicz, Lowell answered with a deadpan look and a reference to Friday's game.</p>
        <p>''I told him I made one play off him yesterday and he has Wang hit me in the hand,'' Lowell said.</p>
        <p>When some listeners were not too sure how to take his remark, Lowell looked at one of the press credentials and finished his thought (and at least one of their articles) by adding, '' 'Ha, ha, ha,' he said jokingly.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
