<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Overcoming the U.S. Open</title>
    <meta content="0603play-open" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Play" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <person class="indexing_service">Furyk, Jim, Mickelson, Phil</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5D91030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1474" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Overcoming the U.S. Open</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Once a year, professional golfers are faced with a course that makes them look like mortals. The United States Open is the sport's four-day stress test, a marathon of frayed nerves, gnashed teeth and shocking scores. (Just ask Phil Mickelson.) Mike Davis of the United States Golf Association is charged with preparing this year's Open -- to be held this month at Oakmont, near Pittsburgh -- just as he was last year at Winged Foot. Playing in his 13th Open, Jim Furyk, the 2003 champion, will try to survive the ordeal. Here, the two men discuss some peculiarities of golf's toughest tournament.</p>
        <p>A WHOLE NEW MIND-SET</p>
        <p>The United States Open is golf at its most counterintuitive. Though length off the tee and a willingness to take risks are the tools that win your typical PGA Tour tournament, the Open rewards accuracy and patience. A desire to take dead aim at the flagstick must be tamped down in favor of shooting for the center of the green. The season-long quest for birdies must be replaced by a yearning for par -- not to mention an acceptance of bogeys.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Once a year, professional golfers are faced with a course that makes them look like mortals. The United States Open is the sport's four-day stress test, a marathon of frayed nerves, gnashed teeth and shocking scores. (Just ask Phil Mickelson.) Mike Davis of the United States Golf Association is charged with preparing this year's Open -- to be held this month at Oakmont, near Pittsburgh -- just as he was last year at Winged Foot. Playing in his 13th Open, Jim Furyk, the 2003 champion, will try to survive the ordeal. Here, the two men discuss some peculiarities of golf's toughest tournament.</p>
        <p>A WHOLE NEW MIND-SET</p>
        <p>The United States Open is golf at its most counterintuitive. Though length off the tee and a willingness to take risks are the tools that win your typical PGA Tour tournament, the Open rewards accuracy and patience. A desire to take dead aim at the flagstick must be tamped down in favor of shooting for the center of the green. The season-long quest for birdies must be replaced by a yearning for par -- not to mention an acceptance of bogeys.</p>
        <p>It took Jim Furyk a few years to come to terms with this reality. ''In the past, I let the conditions and the course setup bother me,'' Furyk says. ''I didn't play well because of it.'' In the three Opens leading up to his victory in 2003, at Olympia Fields outside Chicago, he placed 60th, tied for 62nd and missed the cut. In the three championships since, he has fared much better, tying for for 48th, 28th and 2nd. Most crucial to Furyk's victory was his ability to grind out pars, accept bogeys and limit the costly mistake. All of which can be humbling. In 1999, John Daly became so frustrated with the course setup at Pinehurst that he smacked his ball while it was still rolling back to him on a green and swore he would never play a U.S. Open again. (This proved an empty threat. Daly was back the next year; he shot 83 the first day and withdrew in disgust.)</p>
        <p>At the high-scoring Open in 1974, dubbed ''the Massacre at Winged Foot,'' the championship chairman, Sandy Tatum, famously noted that the U.S.G.A. was not trying to humiliate the best golfers in the world; it was trying to identify them. So the key, according to Furyk, is for a golfer to recognize that other competitors are making bogeys, too. ''I don't know if you ever really defeat a U.S. Open course,'' he says. ''You just kind of survive and try to play better than anyone else that week.''</p>
        <p>SLIPPERY, SLANTED GREENS</p>
        <p>Oakmont members joke that the U.S.G.A. actually slows down the greens for the championship. There is some truth to that. Mike Davis, the senior director of rules and competitions for the U.S.G.A., says Oakmont is such a tough course, highlighted by quirky, undulating greens, that he has to guard against letting the course become too harsh -- especially with players hitting long approach shots to the greens. The speed of the greens will run from 13 to 13.5 on the Stimpmeter (a device that measures green speed), slower than the occasional 15 the greens have been rumored to play at for members.</p>
        <p>''Oakmont is a trickier course to set up than Winged Foot,'' Davis says. ''Oakmont's greens are bigger, but they have more subtle undulations. They are the scariest greens we have for a U.S. Open.'' Those undulations add speed, making it difficult to stop putts. Some of Oakmont's greens also slope away from the player as he stands on the fairway, meaning that incoming shots could bounce or roll off the back of the green.</p>
        <p>Furyk says that leaving yourself an uphill putt will be a must. ''The thing that sticks out to me more than anything else is that a lot of . . . the greens are running away from the player,'' he says. He cites hole Nos. 1, 3, 6 (shown directly above), 10 and 12 as the most prominent examples. ''It's not that you can't make putts from above the pin, but there will be times when you have to be defensive-minded,'' he says. If that fails, there are always drastic measures a player can take -- say, missing the green on purpose. ''You might try to get it over those greens and chip back uphill,'' Furyk says. ''From what I remember, Ben Hogan had a quote where he tried to knock it over No. 1 a couple of days so he could pitch back on and make par.''</p>
        <p>REALLY, REALLY DEEP ROUGH</p>
        <p>In setting up his first Open last year at Winged Foot, Mike Davis introduced a graduated system for the rough that he plans to reprise at Oakmont. It's simple and devilishly effective: the farther off the fairway a tee shot travels, the thicker the rough a golfer will have to play out of. A year ago, an intermediate cut of rough nearest the fairway stood about 1.5 inches high in a strip 6 feet wide. The next 20 feet of rough stood about 4 inches. Balls that veered even farther off line found a swath of deadly 6-inch grass. Davis says that Oakmont's rough should be almost the same but that the exact height depends on the weather -- a wet course means softer greens and easier play. ''If we anticipate soft conditions, we'll let the rough get a little longer,'' he says. ''If we get firm conditions, [it] will be a little less.''</p>
        <p>Different roughs pose different problems. In the light stuff, a player can have a hard time controlling the ball and determining how high or far it will fly, whereas in thicker grass, a club can twist, spraying shots wildly off target. ''The worst thing you can do,'' Furyk says, ''is try to hit a heroic shot and end up in the rough again.''</p>
        <p>With that in mind, Furyk sometimes hits a wedge out of the deepest rough, just to get his ball back on the fairway. If he thinks he can advance the ball to the green, then he makes a swing adjustment (illustrated at right). ''I'll play it slightly back in my stance and push my hands slightly forward,'' he says. ''That will get me hitting down on the ball a little more on a descending blow. I'm trying to make solid contact, and the ball is not going to have a lot of spin. I want the ball to land short, start tumbling, and try to run it up on the greens. Rarely in a U.S. Open do you see guys flying balls on the green and stopping them out of that rough.''</p>
        <p>THIS IS A PAR 3?</p>
        <p>If there's one hole to watch at this year's tournament, it's the eighth (depicted above). At 288 yards -- it can be stretched to 300 if the conditions are right -- Oakmont's notorious par 3 will be the most discussed hole of the championship. That's how Davis wants it. ''I can't wait to hear what the players and media say,'' he says. '' 'The U.S.G.A. has lost their marbles on this one.' '' The slightly downhill hole was lengthened from 250 yards because its day-to-day length is just too easy for today's pros, who are not only stronger but also wield more technologically advanced (and thus longer-hitting) equipment than yesterday's players.</p>
        <p>In the 1960s, players needed 3-woods and drivers to reach the green (though Jack Nicklaus could get there with a 1-iron). At the 2003 United States Amateur championship, also played at Oakmont, they were hitting 4- and 5-irons. At the hole's new length, Jim Furyk says, golfers will stand on the tee not even thinking about birdies; he figures that a par each day will leave you ahead of the field. ''If you happen to make 2, more power to you,'' he says. ''If you make a 4, a lot of people in the field will make 4. You're trying to set the hole up so you make a bunch of 3's.'' Furyk says no one will purposely lay up, as Billy Casper famously did all four days on the long par-3 third at Winged Foot in winning the 1959 United States Open. ''But I think some guys will have to because they can't get there.''</p>
        <p>In the weeks leading up to the Open, opinion among Furyk's touring peers was mixed. ''I think it's too long for a par 3,'' opined Adam Scott, who hit a 3-wood on the hole during a recent practice round. As for last year's champion, Geoff Ogilvy, 288 yards is only a number: ''It doesn't really matter because par is irrelevant.'' His point could apply to any of the Open's frustrating quirks. At the end of the day, everyone is playing the same course.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
