<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Yankees, It's One Body Blow After Another</title>
    <meta content="03yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/sports/baseball/03yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852042"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Clemens, Roger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lowell, Mike</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EFDA1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="989" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Yankees, It's One Body Blow After Another</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Defeat Feels Like Yet Another Body Blow for Yankees</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, June 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There have been so many days like this, so many games when the bad news piles so high for the Yankees that the loss on the field seems secondary, and almost inevitable.</p>
        <p>That was how it was on a deflating Saturday at Fenway Park, where the Yankees lost to the Boston Red Sox, 11-6; learned of a setback for Roger Clemens; and watched helplessly as their first baseman, Doug Mientkiewicz, stuck his head into the path of a charging base runner, Mike Lowell, and had to be carted off the field. He was placed on the disabled list with a fractured wrist, a sprained neck and a mild concussion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees’ loss dissolved any momentum they had after winning Friday, and brought them back to where they stood before this series: seven games under .500, 13½ out of first place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There have been so many days like this, so many games when the bad news piles so high for the Yankees that the loss on the field seems secondary, and almost inevitable.</p>
        <p>That was how it was on a deflating Saturday at Fenway Park, where the Yankees lost to the Boston Red Sox, 11-6; learned of a setback for Roger Clemens; and watched helplessly as their first baseman, Doug Mientkiewicz, stuck his head into the path of a charging base runner, Mike Lowell, and had to be carted off the field. He was placed on the disabled list with a fractured wrist, a sprained neck and a mild concussion.</p>
        <p>That was the ugliest play of a seventh inning in which Derek Jeter made two errors, Bobby Abreu misplayed a fly ball and Scott Proctor issued three walks, two intentional. The Red Sox scored five runs, took the lead and never returned it.</p>
        <p>''You give other clubs extra outs and it's dangerous,'' Yankees Manager Joe Torre said. ''You give that club extra outs and it's suicide.''</p>
        <p>Lowell, the Red Sox third baseman, drove in four runs and has 45 runs batted in, as many as his Yankees' counterpart, Alex Rodriguez. Every Red Sox batter had a hit except Kevin Youkilis, and he walked three times.</p>
        <p>For the Yankees, who lost three leads, the outcome dissolved any momentum they had after winning on Friday, and brought them back to where they stood before the series: seven games under .500, 13 1/2 out of first place in the American League East. The Red Sox have the best record in the majors, at 37-17.</p>
        <p>''This was a grind-out win for us,'' Boston starter Curt Schilling said. ''It seems like every time we play them, it takes your entire lineup and almost your entire bullpen to get through it every night with both these teams.''</p>
        <p>Schilling and Mike Mussina faced each other in the opener of the 2001 World Series. But Schilling is 40 now, Mussina 38, and their stuff is not as sharp as it once was. Factor in a 29-minute rain delay in the fourth inning, and the game was fated to be decided by the bullpens.</p>
        <p>Both starters pitched into the sixth inning but could not get an out then. Mussina had a 5-3 lead, thanks largely to a three-run homer by Jorge Posada that had chased Schilling. But the lead disappeared on homers by Lowell and Jason Varitek, leaving Mussina discouraged. His erratic season continues.</p>
        <p>''It's very frustrating, and I'm really getting tired of it,'' Mussina said. ''One game's good, one game's bad, two games are good, two games are bad. I've never pitched this way, and I don't like pitching this way. I can't stand it. I've got to work on a lot of things to try to be more consistent. I've got to get to six or seven innings with good results more often.''</p>
        <p>Torre said he would have pulled Mussina after Lowell's home run, but he liked the matchup of Mussina and Varitek. In 59 career at-bats against Mussina, Varitek had no home runs and a .119 average. But he hit an 87-mile-an-hour fastball off the backdrop in center field to tie the score.</p>
        <p>Proctor got out of the inning and stayed in for the seventh after Jeter homered to give the Yankees a 6-5 lead. But Proctor has struggled against the Red Sox -- in eight games this season, he has a 12.71 earned run average -- and the seventh inning was more of the same.</p>
        <p>David Ortiz continued his assault on the Yankees with a drive to the right-field warning track that Abreu misplayed. Abreu, who does not run into walls, got close to the wall but seemed to misjudge where the ball would land. It fell just to his left for a double.</p>
        <p>That foreshadowed an unsightly inning in which Proctor would face seven batters and allow no other hard-hit balls.</p>
        <p>After Ortiz's double, Proctor walked Manny Ramírez intentionally and then threw four balls in a row to Youkilis, whom he hit on Friday to draw an ejection. That brought up Lowell, who chopped a spinning grounder to Robinson Canó at second base.</p>
        <p>Canó tossed the ball awkwardly to Jeter, who caught it for the force out and spun away, hurrying his throw and bouncing it. The throw was behind the bag, up the baseline, and as Mientkiewicz reached back for it, his head collided with Lowell's leg, knocking Mientkiewicz to the ground, face first, where he lay motionless as the ball trickled away.</p>
        <p>Two runs scored to give Boston a 7-6 lead, but of greater concern was Mientkiewicz, who hardly moved. He finally sat up as Torre, a trainer and the team doctor attended to him. Torre said Mientkiewicz was dazed but never lost consciousness and was responsive to the trainer.</p>
        <p>A cart drove Mientkiewicz off the field, and he spent the night at Massachusetts General Hospital, where he received a cast on his wrist. He could be out a significant period of time.</p>
        <p>''It was scary,'' Cashman said. ''It was a pretty significant blow.''</p>
        <p>Jeter was charged with an error for the throw, and after another intentional walk, he booted a grounder by Wily Mo Peña for his second error. That brought up Coco Crisp, who blooped a single in front of Melky Cabrera in center, making the score 8-6.</p>
        <p>''Everyone was out there trying to do anything they could,'' Proctor said. ''It's just amazing. I can't even explain it.'' He added later, ''It's an embarrassing inning.''</p>
        <p>A sacrifice fly and a single off Brian Bruney pushed the Red Sox' lead to 10-6, and the Yankees could not come back against Hideki Okajima or Jonathan Papelbon. They had no hits after Jeter's home run, but Torre, at least, found a way to think positively.</p>
        <p>''The fight on this club is here now,'' he said. ''That's something for us to hang on to.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
