<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>James Lowers His Profile And Raises His Team to Finals</title>
    <meta content="03pistons" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852051"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7D91030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1058" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>James Lowers His Profile And Raises His Team to Finals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <dateline>CLEVELAND, June 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LeBron James hurled the ball with all his rippling strength high into the rafters, and the confetti -- like everything and everyone else here -- soon followed on cue in Cleveland.</p>
        <p>James was the rainmaker, catapulting the Cleveland Cavaliers into the N.B.A. finals for the first time with a 98-82 victory over the Detroit Pistons in Game 6 of the Eastern Conference finals, the easiest and most surprising victory by far in the series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LeBron James hurled the ball with all his rippling strength high into the rafters, and the confetti -- like everything and everyone else here -- soon followed on cue in Cleveland.</p>
        <p>James was the rainmaker, catapulting the Cleveland Cavaliers into the N.B.A. finals for the first time with a 98-82 victory over the Detroit Pistons in Game 6 of the Eastern Conference finals, the easiest and most surprising victory by far in the series.</p>
        <p>For a child from nearby Akron who grew up hearing fans boo Cavaliers teams, James saw the night as pure fantasy. At 22, he called it just ''the first step to greatness.''</p>
        <p>James and his Cavaliers are going to meet the three-time N.B.A. champion San Antonio Spurs in the championship series beginning Thursday.</p>
        <p>The Cavaliers relied on a rookie, Daniel Gibson, known as Boobie, who piled in a game-high 31 points, 19 in the fourth quarter. He hit all five of his 3-pointers.</p>
        <p>''There is no way we would be in the Eastern Conference finals or win the Eastern Conference finals if this was a one-man show,'' James said. ''It has never happened in N.B.A. history when one guy has done it all.''</p>
        <p>As jaw-dropping as James's singular night was in Game 5, when he scored 48 points -- and 29 of his team's last 30 points -- to lift the Cavaliers to victory in double overtime, so too was his calculated performance this night, if only because of its shocking contrast.</p>
        <p>Double and triple-teamed by the Pistons, James passed. He rebounded. And he didn't care that he shot 3 for 11, scoring 14 points from the free-throw line.</p>
        <p>''I believe as a complete basketball player, I played better tonight,'' James said. ''Just because of the simple fact how big it was. We needed to win this game and not go back to Detroit.</p>
        <p>''People have always criticized the way I play the game of basketball because I'm a team-first guy. Guys stepped up, this is what it's all about, a complete team win.''</p>
        <p>That used to be Detroit's mantra, back when defense was their calling card. On a night when the scoreboard, shot clock and horn shorted out at the end of the first quarter, the Pistons soon fizzled in the fourth. Entering Game 6, the players were grumbling about coaching strategies, they were seen arguing with an assistant coach on the bench and they called players-only meetings.</p>
        <p>But when the Pistons' Rasheed Wallace completely lost his composure, arguing a call with 7 minutes 44 seconds remaining, he picked up two technical fouls and was ejected from the game.</p>
        <p>The Cavaliers led, 81-69 and that was the symbolic end for Detroit. James inaugurated a new era of Eastern Conference basketball. ''It's our time,'' he said.</p>
        <p>James did not pour in the points, as he did Thursday night. Instead, it was Gibson that got to the Pistons.</p>
        <p>''Gibson had a phenomenal series for them,'' Pistons Coach Flip Saunders said. ''LeBron kills you one game and you do not want him to go off, and then Daniel made every big shot.''</p>
        <p>Saunders rested his starting guards at the beginning of the fourth quarter, and the Cavaliers took advantage of the backcourt miscues and went on a 12-1 run. Gibson began with two 3-pointers and the Cleveland crowd roared, sensing the special occasion. James's 3-point play gave the Cavaliers a 9-point lead and they never let up.</p>
        <p>After the game, James rushed to center Zydrunas Ilgauskas, the player who has been with the Cavaliers the longest, during all the losing. ''I told Z, I'll do my best to get you to the finals, one step at a time,'' James said.</p>
        <p>This would be Cleveland's glory night, helping sooth over a history of sports heartbreak in the city.</p>
        <p>Since their Game 2 defeat, the Cavaliers rallied around being a ''no excuse'' team. They never lost again.</p>
        <p>Technical difficulties? No excuses. Tough defense? No problem. Instead, the Pistons and Cavaliers reversed roles. The Pistons had a players-only meeting after Game 5, hoping to spark a sense of urgency, but also to clear the tense air.</p>
        <p>''The way our team is, it's always been one to point fingers at each other,'' Saunders said. ''It's important for players to not be afraid to hold another player accountable. Everyone has to know that they have a responsibility to live up to.''</p>
        <p>If the Pistons relied on each other, then the Cavaliers were all but obsequious to James. James's teammate Drew Gooden called him ''Video Game James,'' from that Game 5 performance, which James endorsed, even if he preferred the King James nickname.</p>
        <p>''I absolutely know exactly what he means,'' James said before the game. ''You do a lot of stuff on video games that you some times can't do in real life.''</p>
        <p>But on this night, when the Pistons double and triple-teamed him as soon as he caught the ball, James was going to have to rely on his real-life teammates to score.</p>
        <p>In the first quarter, James had 5 assists and 5 rebounds.</p>
        <p>Just one game after scoring his career playoff-high, James had a playoff-low shots attempted in the first half -- just two. He did take 11 free throws, making 9 of them, setting the tone for the night.</p>
        <p>The Pistons unleashed their frustrations early, with prodding from Cleveland's Sasha Pavlovic.</p>
        <p>Chris Webber, after becoming entangled with Pavlovic, was called for a technical. Pavlovic and Hamilton, coming to Webber's aid, were hit with double technicals with 3:29 left and Cleveland trailing, 19-18.</p>
        <p>The Cavaliers went on a 9-2 run to finish the quarter ahead, 27-21. And then came the technical malfunctions. After the delay, the public address announcer had to announce how much time was left on the shot clock, counting down from 10 seconds.</p>
        <p>The Cavaliers were temporarily rattled, making just 4 of 18 field goals in the second quarter as the Pistons tied the game at 48 by halftime.</p>
        <p>The Pistons had been here before, they boasted, having compiled a 6-1 record in Game 6 situations on the road in the last five years. But their previous loss came to Miami last year, and sent the Heat to the finals.</p>
        <p>The Pistons unraveled last year, too, and set the stage for the superstar, Dwyane Wade, to emerge.</p>
        <p>This year, it is James's time. He has already seized the stage.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
