<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Teams Are Warned, but Proctor Avoids Discipline</title>
    <meta content="03pins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/sports/baseball/03pins.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852011"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Proctor, Scott</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Youkilis, Kevin</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Watson, Bob</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E4DA1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="592" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Teams Are Warned, but Proctor Avoids Discipline</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Teams Are Warned, but Proctor Is Off Hook</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, June 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scott Proctor insisted after Friday's game that he had not intentionally thrown at the Red Sox' Kevin Youkilis when he hit him with a pitch in the ninth inning. The benches and bullpens emptied, and Proctor was ejected. But Bob Watson sided with Proctor.</p>
        <p>Watson, baseball's vice president for on-field operations, told General Manager Brian Cashman on Saturday morning that Proctor would not be suspended or fined. Watson had disciplined Proctor for throwing behind a hitter last month, when Proctor's intent was obvious.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Baseball’s vice president for on-field operations told Yankees General Manager Brian Cashman that pitcher Scott Proctor would not be suspended or fined for hitting a Red Sox player with a pitch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Scott Proctor insisted after Friday's game that he had not intentionally thrown at the Red Sox' Kevin Youkilis when he hit him with a pitch in the ninth inning. The benches and bullpens emptied, and Proctor was ejected. But Bob Watson sided with Proctor.</p>
        <p>Watson, baseball's vice president for on-field operations, told General Manager Brian Cashman on Saturday morning that Proctor would not be suspended or fined. Watson had disciplined Proctor for throwing behind a hitter last month, when Proctor's intent was obvious.</p>
        <p>''The umpires are professional,'' Proctor said. ''They know when it's on purpose and when one gets away, generally. You can't go out there and not pitch inside. You have to let the hitters know that you can throw inside, but without the intent of hitting them.''</p>
        <p>Watson did tell Cashman that the pitchers would be watched closely Saturday after five batters were hit in Friday's game. Manager Joe Torre said he had no problems with the pregame warning.</p>
        <p>''I don't think any of those last night were intentional,'' Torre said, ''but I can understand the warning aspect on the M.L.B. side.''</p>
        <p>The umpires were clearly on alert in the first inning, when the Yankees' Mike Mussina threw a curveball inside to Dustin Pedroia and was immediately visited by the plate umpire, Phil Cuzzi.</p>
        <p>ORTIZ LEAVES NO ROOM FOR ERROR -- In five seasons with the Red Sox, David Ortiz has never been hit by a pitch by the Yankees. Ortiz is rarely hit by anyone, actually -- he has been hit only 11 times in more than 600 games for Boston.</p>
        <p>There is a theory in the clubhouse that the Yankees' pitchers should get Ortiz to move his feet in the batter's box -- not by hitting him, but by pitching more aggressively inside.</p>
        <p>The problem with that, said Johnny Damon, who played with Ortiz for three seasons, is Ortiz's thunderous power on inside pitches.</p>
        <p>''I think teams are afraid that if they make a mistake, they'll be throwing it right into his wheelhouse, and he'll hit a home run,'' Damon said. ''That's a big reason why a lot of teams don't go all the way in.''</p>
        <p>Joe Torre said that while pitchers have a better chance against Ortiz if their inside pitches have movement, it is still a dangerous place to pitch him. ''You don't want something on the fat of the bat,'' Torre said. ''On the inside part of the plate, he'll kill you.''</p>
        <p>Ortiz came into the season with a .309 career average against the Yankees, his best against any American League team, and after going 2 for 4 on Saturday, he is batting .405 against the Yankees this season.</p>
        <p>TORRE SETS RECORD STRAIGHT -- Some in the Yankees' organization were unhappy with Joe Torre for criticizing Alex Rodriguez's play in Toronto on Wednesday, when he shouted at a fielder and distracted him from catching a pop-up. Torre, in turn, was incensed at the way his comments were portrayed in an early edition of The Daily News on Saturday. ''The headline said I told Alex to shut up,'' Torre said at the start of his pregame remarks. ''At no time do I remember saying that. I'd like to believe when people buy a paper in New York, they're reading the truth, because I take your role very seriously in getting the news to them. It bothers me.''</p>
        <p>Torre, who had called the play inappropriate, said he told Rodriguez of his comments after making them on Friday, and Rodriguez was fine with them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
