<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vaulter Gives Up College but Quickly Learns to Excel</title>
    <meta content="03track" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/sports/othersports/03track.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070608T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852036"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TRACK AND FIELD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pole Vault</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DA1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="960" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vaulter Gives Up College but Quickly Learns to Excel</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Vaulter Gives Up College but Quickly Learns to Excel</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>People wondered whether Jenn Stuczynski should have her head examined when she gave up studying for an advanced degree in psychology in the fall of 2005 to pursue a career in the pole vault.</p>
        <p>A driver with a learner's permit had more experience in locomotion than Stuczynski did with a pole on the runway. She had taken up the event less than a year earlier, as her basketball career at Roberts Wesleyan College, an N.A.I.A. university in Rochester, was winding down.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>People wondered whether Jenn Stuczynski should have her head examined when she gave up studying for an advanced degree in psychology to pursue a career in the pole vault. Not anymore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>People wondered whether Jenn Stuczynski should have her head examined when she gave up studying for an advanced degree in psychology in the fall of 2005 to pursue a career in the pole vault.</p>
        <p>A driver with a learner's permit had more experience in locomotion than Stuczynski did with a pole on the runway. She had taken up the event less than a year earlier, as her basketball career at Roberts Wesleyan College, an N.A.I.A. university in Rochester, was winding down.</p>
        <p>When Stuczynski, a 6-foot forward, told a high school coach in her hometown, Fredonia, N.Y., of her plans, she said he laughed.</p>
        <p>Stuczynski was not amused. ''I thought, Go ahead and laugh; I'll show you,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Last night at the Reebok Grand Prix on Randalls Island, Stuczynski showed everybody, becoming the first American woman to vault 16 feet despite a persistent crosswind that seemed to vex the other vaulters, many of whom left the pit glaring at the dancing ribbons that served as their wind gauge.</p>
        <p>After clearing 14-7 and 15-3 on her first attempts to seal the victory, Stuczynski took three stabs at 16 feet, building the drama with each near miss until she cleared the bar on her final try to eclipse by one and a half inches the American record she set last month in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>The only woman who has vaulted higher is the Russian Yelena Isinbayeva, who holds the world record, 16-5 1/4. Stuczynski then tried to vault over Isinbayeva. The bar was raised to 16-6, and she came tantalizingly close to clearing it on the second of her three attempts.</p>
        <p>''I'm really excited,'' Stuczynski said, adding, ''I wanted to be the first American to clear 16 feet because everybody remembers the first.''</p>
        <p>The swirling winds that made Stuczynski's pursuit of the world record more difficult helped the sprinter Tyson Gay a little too much. Gay was timed in 9.76 seconds in the 100 meters, one-hundredth of a second under the world record, but the wind was 2.2 miles an hour; the allowable limit is 2.0.</p>
        <p>The night's featured race was supposed to be the men's 110-meter hurdles, which boasted a deep field that included the world-record holder, Liu Xiang of China, and Dominique Arnold, the American-record holder. But the race went off without Arnold, who was disqualified for a false start.</p>
        <p>''No excuses,'' said Arnold, who walked forlornly down the track as Xiang blazed to victory in 12.92 seconds, tying the United States All-Comers' record. ''Races like this you want to be a part of no matter where you finish.''</p>
        <p>Americans finished 1-2 in the mile, with Alan Webb winning in 3 minutes 52.94 seconds, followed by Bernard Lagat in 3:53.88. Matt Centrowitz, an 18-year-old high school senior from Annapolis, Md., was 11th, in 4:03.40.</p>
        <p>In one respect, it does not seem to faze Stuczynski to be trying to clear world-record heights. Both of her American-record efforts, she said, were far from technically perfect. ''I know I can put better jumps together,'' she said.</p>
        <p>What does give Stuczynski pause is to consider that it was only a few years ago that she watched a student-athlete at Roberts Wesleyan vault 12 feet and was so awestruck she asked him if he was going to the Olympics.</p>
        <p>The pole-vault event is filled with stories of women being discovered, Lana Turner-style, and transformed into stars. Stacy Dragila competed in the rodeo and the heptathlon before she was talked into trying the pole vault. Isinbayeva, the reigning Olympic champion, was a gymnast for 10 years before switching sports when she was 15.</p>
        <p>Athletic pursuits came easily to Stuczynski, who played golf, softball and basketball and ran track. She scored 1,819 points at Roberts Wesleyan to set a basketball team record, but it was her performance in a pickup basketball game that caught the eye of Rick Suhr, a track assistant.</p>
        <p>Suhr, whose specialty then, as now, was the pole vault, saw Stuczynski hold her own in a game against men, took note of her long-limbed and lithe frame, and the wheels in his head started turning. He approached her after a basketball practice, and their initial conversation, as Suhr recalled, went like this:</p>
        <p>''Have you ever thought of pole-vaulting?''</p>
        <p>''No, I don't do that.''</p>
        <p>Suhr approached her three weeks later, this time appealing to her ego. ''Jenn, you have been good at a lot of things,'' he recalled telling her. ''But you have never been great. I think you can be a great pole-vaulter.''</p>
        <p>After mulling over what he said, Stuczynski realized Suhr had a point and agreed to give pole-vaulting a try. He spoon fed her the technique.</p>
        <p>''You know the saying, how do you eat an elephant?'' Stuczynski said. ''One bite at a time. That's how it was.''</p>
        <p>She won the event at the 2005 indoor nationals and dropped out of college a few months later to train full time. To support herself, Stuczynski worked eight-hour shifts stocking shelves at her father's grocery store in Fredonia. She commuted two hours each way to Rochester, where she lived out of a suitcase in an upstairs bedroom in Suhr's house.</p>
        <p>Toward the end of 2005, Suhr sat Stuczynski down and said, ''I believe in you 100 percent, but we're running out of money.'' He told her he was going to remortgage his house to help defray traveling costs until she could secure an endorsement contract that would cover her expenses.</p>
        <p>''I remember that day,'' Stuczynski said. ''I was so nervous.''</p>
        <p>In months, she vaulted over 15 feet multiple times and was signed by Adidas. After she broke the American record, one of the many congratulatory messages she received was from the high school coach who had laughed at her decision to switch sports.</p>
        <p>TRACK AND FIELD</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 8, 2007, Friday  Because of an editing error, a sports article on Sunday about the Reebok Grand Prix track and field event on Randalls Island referred incorrectly in some copies to the wind speed during the 100-meter dash. It was recorded at 2.2 meters a second, not miles an hour. The allowable wind speed for a world record to count in the event is 2.0 meters a second, not miles an hour.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 8, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, a sports article on Sunday about the Reebok Grand Prix track and field event on Randalls Island referred incorrectly in some copies to the wind speed during the 100-meter dash. It was recorded at 2.2 meters a second, not miles an hour. The allowable wind speed for a world record to count in the event is 2.0 meters a second, not miles an hour.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
