<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rallying Support for an Ottawa Rally</title>
    <meta content="03ottawa" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/sports/hockey/03ottawa.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852044"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Ottawa Senators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Toronto Maple Leafs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stanley Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stanley Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ottawa Senators</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Toronto Maple Leafs</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Hockey League</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03EFDA1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="822" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rallying Support for an Ottawa Rally</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Senators Try to Rally in Hockey-Bruised Ottawa</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <dateline>OTTAWA</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At a pep rally May 24 to celebrate the Senators' advance to the Stanley Cup finals, several thousand people filled the plaza at City Hall and the mayor declared Ottawa ''Swaggerville,'' trying to wash away its image as the sleepy national capital full of easily bruised hockey fans.</p>
        <p>The Senators were far from the hoopla, practicing in their arena, Scotiabank Place, 20 miles southwest of Ottawa in the suburb of Kanata. No fans were waiting in the parking lot for autographs and, aside from the banner for the Stanley Cup playoffs hanging on the side of the arena that faces the highway, there was little indication that the team being honored downtown was skating inside.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Ottawa Senators hope that their long-awaited appearance in the Stanley Cup finals can help the team step out of the shadow of the Toronto Maple Leafs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At a pep rally May 24 to celebrate the Senators' advance to the Stanley Cup finals, several thousand people filled the plaza at City Hall and the mayor declared Ottawa ''Swaggerville,'' trying to wash away its image as the sleepy national capital full of easily bruised hockey fans.</p>
        <p>The Senators were far from the hoopla, practicing in their arena, Scotiabank Place, 20 miles southwest of Ottawa in the suburb of Kanata. No fans were waiting in the parking lot for autographs and, aside from the banner for the Stanley Cup playoffs hanging on the side of the arena that faces the highway, there was little indication that the team being honored downtown was skating inside.</p>
        <p>''The unfortunate part of it is, you are involved but you can't be involved,'' said Senators Coach Bryan Murray, who grew up in Shawville, Quebec, about 50 miles northwest of Ottawa. ''I think the players recognize the level of excitement, the phone calls you get from friends, the e-mails you get. You might not go in the city, but you understand what's happening. I think the whole area is caught up in this, and it's great.''</p>
        <p>[The Senators returned home for Game 3 of the finals Saturday night, earning their first victory of the best-of-seven series, 5-3, against the Anaheim Ducks.]</p>
        <p>There is a bit of a disconnect in Ottawa, the capital Canadians are reluctant to rally around, its image interwoven with the unpopular federal government. And the Senators have often made it difficult for their fans to rally around them, for reasons deeper than their decision to build an arena in a far-flung suburb.</p>
        <p>The Senators, an expansion franchise that began play in 1992, has reached the playoffs every season since 1996-97. They built powerful teams that looked terrific in the regular season, only to flop in the playoffs. Adding insult, four of the playoff losses were to the Toronto Maple Leafs. The Senators cannot seem to escape the Leafs' shadow in Ontario. Ottawa reached the Eastern Conference finals once, in 2003; the team lost in the first round five times.</p>
        <p>The Senators hope that their long-awaited appearance on the N.H.L.'s biggest stage can help wash away some of those memories.</p>
        <p>''The fans have had some high expectations for us,'' center Jason Spezza said, ''and we haven't been able to reach them in the past. I think now it's like letting the air out of the balloon. They feel very comfortable with where we are and the opportunity we have. Everybody really seems to be hopping on board and really supporting us.''</p>
        <p>The city has draped itself in the team's signature red. A fleet of taxis patrols downtown with Senators flags flapping from the windows. The Westin hotel painted ''Go Sens Go'' on its facade in big red letters.</p>
        <p>Ottawa came with a few built-in disadvantages in its quest to carve a niche in Canada's hockey universe. It had a successful franchise early in the 20th century, winning 11 Stanley Cups from 1903 to 1927. Financial problems plagued the Senators in the 1930s before the team was sold to owners in St. Louis who folded it a year later.</p>
        <p>The Senators re-emerged in the expansion era of the early '90s. In the interim, Toronto and Montreal built Canada's dynasty franchises, and Edmonton created an era of its own in the '80s, the Wayne Gretzky years.</p>
        <p>The new Senators played in the aging Ottawa Civic Center downtown for their first four seasons. A new arena was built in Kanata, pulling the team from the heart of the city.</p>
        <p>Although the franchise became successful remarkably quickly, their postseason failures became maddening. A first-round loss in 2004, when the Senators were the No. 2 seed, cost Jacques Martin his coaching job, and ushered in Murray.</p>
        <p>Murray came home after coaching four other N.H.L. franchises, including Anaheim, and took the Senators' quest to heart. ''Coming from here,'' said Murray, 64, ''this is what I hoped at some time in my career would happen, that we would get a chance to get the team to the finals and the city would rally around it.''</p>
        <p>[The finals began on two sobering notes, and the fans who gathered at Scotiabank Place to watch the games being played in Anaheim had little to celebrate. But a few hundred fans still met the team Thursday when it arrived at the airport after the loss in Game 2. The car flags are still flapping. The Westin continues to exhort the team in big red letters.]</p>
        <p>''Everyone knows the history,'' forward Dany Heatley said. ''It feels good to be a part of it. It feels good for guys who have been here for the whole time. It feels good for the city, seeing the support we're getting. They've waited a long time for it. It's a great feeling, but at the same time, you might as well win it if you get this far.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
