<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Heat of a Rivalry, Collegial Bonds Stay Strong</title>
    <meta content="03vecsey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/sports/baseball/03vecsey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852043"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Times</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cashman, Brian</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Epstein, Theo</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mientkiewicz, Doug</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EFDA1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Heat of a Rivalry, Collegial Bonds Stay Strong</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In the Heat of a Rivalry, Collegial Bonds Stay Strong</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While Brian Cashman of the Yankees spoke of injury and loss, Theo Epstein of the Red Sox was walking through the ancient catacombs under Fenway Park. The two general managers in the most intense rivalry in all of baseball made eye contact.</p>
        <p>Epstein, with concern on his face, wanted to know the condition of Doug Mientkiewicz, who had been racked up in a collision at first base and was taken to the hospital for observation, groggy-looking but apparently able to move his limbs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Red Sox beat the Yankees Saturday, but for General Managers Brian Cashman and Theo Epstein, the condition of Doug Mientkiewicz, who had been racked up in a collision during the game, was more important.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While Brian Cashman of the Yankees spoke of injury and loss, Theo Epstein of the Red Sox was walking through the ancient catacombs under Fenway Park. The two general managers in the most intense rivalry in all of baseball made eye contact.</p>
        <p>Epstein, with concern on his face, wanted to know the condition of Doug Mientkiewicz, who had been racked up in a collision at first base and was taken to the hospital for observation, groggy-looking but apparently able to move his limbs.</p>
        <p>''I'll give you a call when I find out,'' said Cashman, a month short of 40. Epstein, still only 33, slipped out a back door. Later, Cashman learned that Mientkiewicz would need to go on the disabled list with a fractured wrist, a sprained neck and a mild concussion.</p>
        <p>This is the hidden side of the Boston-New York competition that has pitchers buzzing fastballs high and tight on hitters, and runners low-bridging fielders, and fans feeding off the turbulent history between the Yankees and the Red Sox, as current as this weekend.</p>
        <p>Yet Athens and Sparta it is not. The Sox won yesterday, 11-6, to move back to 13 1/2 games ahead of the Yankees, but the health of one of the players was more important.</p>
        <p>''Dougie helped them win a World Series,'' Cashman said quietly, referring to the defense Mientkiewicz contributed to the Red Sox' 2004 championship, when he caught the final out and, for that matter, tried to keep the ball.</p>
        <p>The bonds extend in all different directions. Yesterday, Derek Jeter had one of those up-and-down days, lofting a Bucky Dent kind of fly atop the scoreboard (with eagle's-perch seats that were not there on Dent's great day in 1978) to put the Yankees ahead, 6-5, in the seventh inning. Jeter has been a vital part of this rivalry since 1995, and he knows that things change fast, particularly in Fenway.</p>
        <p>Minutes later, Jeter was part of the play that got Mientkiewicz creamed at first base. Robinson Can贸 made a high throw on a double-play ball, forcing Jeter to perform a pirouette at second base, with Kevin Youkilis bearing down on him.</p>
        <p>Jeter accomplished the force at second base, but his off-balance throw bounced near first, and the nimble Mientkiewicz sprawled in the dirt, not quite able to hold on to the ball. At that point, Mike Lowell, clipped Mientkiewicz with his left leg as he crossed first base, a total accident.</p>
        <p>While the medical staff administered to Mientkiewicz, Lowell stood a few yards from his fallen opponent and commiserated with Jeter. Lowell came up in the Yankees' organization and was a teammate of Jeter's for eight games in 1998. Now they were both professionals, members of the same lodge, holding no grudges, just worried about a colleague.</p>
        <p>Yet these are the same teams that piled onto the field Friday night after Scott Proctor hit Youkilis with a high, hard one, and Youkilis and the umpire detected intent. In the melee, Mientkiewicz rushed in from first base, not to fight but to try to calm Youkilis, a teammate in 2004. Blessed are the peacemakers.</p>
        <p>Earlier yesterday, Lowell dumped Can贸 in the baseline with a football-style block while trying to bust up a double play. Part of the game, everybody said. Can贸 had been in the baseline and was fair game. To his credit, Can贸 understood it, took his lumps and jogged off the field.</p>
        <p>Both teams played hard and fair, but when it was over, the Yankees had lost again. Jeter made a second error later in that seventh inning. Manager Joe Torre said he detected more spunk in his team ''the last few days,'' but the Yankees' 23-30 record goes along with shoddy defense in the outfield, the sloppy pitching and the tendency to make mistakes at important times. During the game, they learned that Roger Clemens had injured his ancient groin and would not be making his season debut tomorrow in Chicago.</p>
        <p>''We can't worry about Roger,'' Jeter said, adding that the Yankees had stayed positive even when they fell behind.</p>
        <p>''It's not like anybody's quitting,'' Jeter said. ''This is one of those games when you can't have enough runs. The wall gets closer late in the game. And you can't give them extra outs. I didn't help us in that seventh inning.''</p>
        <p>Jeter said he was not even aware that Youkilis had been steaming in on him on the botched throw. He tends to play in his own bubble of concentration, not even making much commotion when the Red Sox and other teams hit him on occasion, trying to move him off the plate. He has a feel for the game that includes chatting with Lowell moments after the collision. The old days are long gone.</p>
        <p>This was evident as Cashman stood outside the Yankees' clubhouse and discussed the injury to Mientkiewicz and the delay in getting Clemens, both of them former Red Sox. The fans have every right to expect intensity on the field. But under the stands, there was a look between two young general managers that said that even in the midst of another Yankee-Red Sox series, there is plenty of room for compassion.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
