<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Legal Debate In Guantánamo On Boy Fighters</title>
    <meta content="03gitmo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/us/03gitmo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852006"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Guantanamo Bay Naval Base (Cuba)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Al Qaeda (Terrorist Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glaberson, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Khadr, Omar Ahmed</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Speer, Christopher James (Sgt)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Guantanamo Bay Naval Base (Cuba)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Afghanistan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Al Qaeda</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E5DA1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Legal Debate In Guantánamo On Boy Fighters</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Legal Debate in Guantánamo on Boy Fighters</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GLABERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glaberson, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US military prosecutors say that Omar Ahmed Khadr is Al Qaeda operative, spy and killer who must be held accountable for killing Sgt Christopher J Speer in 2002 and for other bloody acts he committed in Afghanistan; Khadr was 15 at time; his age is at center of legal battle that will begin with arraignment at Guantanamo Bay, Cuba, of Khadr, whom legal experts describe as first child fighter in decades to face war-crimes charges; defense lawyers argue that child fighters are victims of warfare, rather than war criminals; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The facts of Omar Ahmed Khadr's case are grim. The shrapnel from the grenade he is accused of throwing ripped through the skull of Sgt. First Class Christopher J. Speer, who was 28 when he died.</p>
        <p>To American military prosecutors, Mr. Khadr is a committed Al Qaeda operative, spy and killer who must be held accountable for killing Sergeant Speer in 2002 and for other bloody acts he committed in Afghanistan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The case of the youngest detainee at Guantánamo Bay has implications as large as the growing ranks of child fighters worldwide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The facts of Omar Ahmed Khadr's case are grim. The shrapnel from the grenade he is accused of throwing ripped through the skull of Sgt. First Class Christopher J. Speer, who was 28 when he died.</p>
        <p>To American military prosecutors, Mr. Khadr is a committed Al Qaeda operative, spy and killer who must be held accountable for killing Sergeant Speer in 2002 and for other bloody acts he committed in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>But there is one fact that may not fit easily into the government's portrait of Mr. Khadr: He was 15 at the time.</p>
        <p>His age is at the center of a legal battle that is to begin tomorrow with an arraignment by a military judge at Guantánamo Bay, Cuba, of Mr. Khadr, whom a range of legal experts describe as the first child fighter in decades to face war-crimes charges. It is a battle with implications as large as the growing ranks of child fighters around the world.</p>
        <p>Defense lawyers argue that military prosecutors are violating international law by filing charges that date from events that occurred when Mr. Khadr was 15 or younger. Legal concepts that are still evolving, the lawyers say, require that countries treat child fighters as victims of warfare, rather than war criminals.</p>
        <p>The military prosecutors say such notions may be ''well-meaning and worthy,'' but are irrelevant to the American military commissions at Guantánamo. Mr. Khadr is one of only three Guantánamo detainees to face charges under the law establishing the commissions, passed by Congress last year.</p>
        <p>''International law,'' the Justice Department asserted in a court filing in the case last week, ''does not prohibit an individual under 18 from being prosecuted for war crimes.'' Even so, prosecutors said that if they won a conviction, they would seek something less than a life term, given Mr. Khadr's age. He is 20 now.</p>
        <p>Whatever the outcome, his case seems destined to become a landmark, though some scholars say not enough attention has been given to its importance. ''What is the precedent that we are setting with this unique step?'' asked Peter W. Singer, a senior fellow at the Brookings Institution who has written about child fighters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khadr's case offers a snapshot of relatively new questions surrounding the legal treatment of child fighters globally, though advocates for children have tended to focus less on young terrorists and more on children who fight in civil wars, like Ishmael Beah, whose best-selling memoir, ''A Long Way Gone: Memoirs of a Boy Soldier,'' recounts his bloody days as a child soldier in Sierra Leone's civil war.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khadr may not be the most sympathetic figure for those pressing for the more forgiving interpretation of international law. He was born in Canada to a family with such deep Al Qaeda ties that some newspapers there have called them Canada's first family of terrorism.</p>
        <p>He is the youngest detainee at Guantánamo Bay, nearly blind in one eye from injuries sustained during the July 2002 firefight in which Sergeant Speer was mortally wounded and another American soldier was severely injured. Last week, Mr. Khadr said he wanted to fire all of his American lawyers, and some of them said they understood why he might distrust Americans after five years at Guantánamo.</p>
        <p>Still, they argue that war-crimes prosecutors should focus on the adults who press children into service, not on the children themselves. The charges against Mr. Khadr, they said in a recent court filing, cross a line in the treatment of children that no other country has crossed ''in modern history.''</p>
        <p>The prosecutors, they say, included in their charges acts that occurred when Mr. Khadr was younger than 10. Mr. Khadr ''was subject to undue adult influences,'' said Muneer I. Ahmad, an associate professor at the American University Washington College of Law, who has represented Mr. Khadr.</p>
        <p>''If Omar had had his free choice,'' Professor Ahmad said, ''what he would have chosen to do is ride horses, play soccer and read Harry Potter books.''</p>
        <p>It is an appeal to emotion that the prosecutors are likely to meet with their own. Sergeant Speer left a wife and two small children. His widow, Tabitha, said in an e-mail exchange with a reporter last week that Mr. Khadr's youth entitled him to no special consideration.</p>
        <p>''Given the opportunity, he would do it all over again,'' she wrote. ''He was trained to do exactly what he did, regardless of his age.''</p>
        <p>To the prosecutors, Mr. Khadr is the essence of a young man who should be held to adult standards. American officials say his father, Ahmed Said Khadr, who was killed in a shootout with Pakistani forces in 2003, was a senior deputy to Osama bin Laden.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Khadr's brothers is in a wheelchair as a result of that 2003 shootout; another told the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation ''we are an Al Qaeda family.'' Ahmed Khadr traveled internationally from Canada under the auspices of handling charity money for Muslims. In the mid-1990s, he was held for a time in Pakistan on suspicion of helping finance the bombing of the Egyptian embassy in Islamabad.</p>
        <p>After he was released, the Khadrs and several of their six children moved from Canada to Afghanistan, where they lived at times in the same compound as Osama bin Laden, officials have said. ''All of the children were indoctrinated into the Al Qaeda way of thinking,'' said the chief military prosecutor at Guantánamo, Col. Morris D. Davis of the Air Force.</p>
        <p>After Sept. 11, Mr. Khadr made deliberate choices to join Al Qaeda and eventually to kill Sergeant Speer, Colonel Davis said in a recent interview. ''There is a difference,'' Colonel Davis said, ''between a 15-year-old who makes a spur-of-the-moment decision and someone who made a long-term choice.''</p>
        <p>Captured bloody and bullet-riddled after the firefight that killed Sergeant Speer, Mr. Khadr has been held at Guantánamo since 2002. At least three other juveniles, perhaps as young as 12, were also held there for a time. But they were released in January 2004, the military said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khadr's lawyers have said in court that he has been subject to physical and psychological torture that exploited his youth, another example of what they say is a violation of international principles that children be accorded special protections.</p>
        <p>In legal filings, the lawyers have asserted, for example, that an interrogator at Guantánamo told Mr. Khadr when he was 17 that if he did not cooperate he would be sent to Egypt where he would be confronted by ''Soldier No. 9,'' a man who the interrogators said would be sent to rape him.</p>
        <p>Asked about the accusations, a Pentagon spokesman, Cmdr. Jeffrey D. Gordon, said they ''may be raised by counsel during the course of the trial'' but he would not discuss the specifics of the accusations. Commander Gordon added that detainees ''have frequently made allegations of abuse while in detention in order to garner public support.''</p>
        <p>In their filings, the prosecutors concede that some treaties require special treatment of children caught in warfare. Some of those treaties, they noted, have not been ratified by the United States, and others do not specifically ban prosecution of combatants who are 15 or older.</p>
        <p>Some legal experts acknowledge that it is difficult to define precisely what international law requires in the treatment of child fighters. It is a fluid discipline, with few enforcement mechanisms, and there are inconsistent precedents and treaty provisions.</p>
        <p>But even those who say there is no bar to the war crimes prosecutions of youthful fighters say the growing use of child fighters around the world means that Mr. Khadr's case could become pivotal.</p>
        <p>''More and more child soldiers are being recruited, and they are committing heinous crimes. This is an issue the international community is going to have to confront,'' said Michael A. Newton, a former military prosecutor and expert on the law of war who teaches at Vanderbilt University Law School.</p>
        <p>The two sides in the Khadr case interpret some international legal documents differently. One subject on which they differ is a treaty to which the United States is a party, a 2002 United Nations agreement dealing with child fighters.</p>
        <p>The defense notes that the agreement requires countries to demobilize captured child fighters and to provide assistance for their physical and psychological recovery ''and their social reintegration.''</p>
        <p>The defense lawyers say that means sending them home. That would be inconsistent with the potential life term Mr. Khadr faces on charges of murder, attempted murder, spying, conspiracy and providing material support for terrorism.</p>
        <p>But government lawyers note that the child-soldier treaty does not expressly rule out war crimes prosecutions for juveniles. Another international child-soldier provision that has become a central issue in Mr. Khadr's case is a law approved by the United Nations for the prosecution of war crimes after the Sierra Leone civil war in the 1990s. It specifically provides that ''persons of 15 years of age'' and older can be charged with war crimes.</p>
        <p>Colonel Davis said that was a significant precedent. ''If the United Nations has signed on to the principle that people who are 15 can be prosecuted for war crimes,'' he said, ''the notion that we're blazing a new trail with Mr. Khadr is a false assumption.''</p>
        <p>But the former chief war crimes prosecutor for Sierra Leone, David M. Crane, said in an interview that soon after he was appointed by Secretary General Kofi Annan of the United Nations in 2002, he announced that he would not prosecute anyone under 18.</p>
        <p>Mr. Crane, a former senior Pentagon legal official who is now a professor at Syracuse University Law School, said the Sierra Leone civil war included a catalogue of horrific acts by teenagers and children. But he said he concluded that warriors under 18 did not have the intellectual and emotional maturity to be prosecuted for war crimes.</p>
        <p>''I called them as much victims as the people they raped, maimed and mutilated,'' he said.</p>
        <p>One person who has reached a different conclusion about the culpability of child fighters is Layne Morris, a housing administrator in a Salt Lake City suburb. Mr. Morris is a former Army Special Forces sergeant, who, like Mr. Khadr, is half-blind because of the firefight that day outside Khost, Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>On a recent day, Mr. Morris remembered the stream of shots from AK-47s inside a compound a coalition patrol had surrounded. He remembered the hand grenades that kept coming over the wall. And he described the feeling of the shrapnel that took half his sight.</p>
        <p>He said the battle did not unfold quickly, as it sometimes seems in the retelling. American forces surrounded the compound. And then they waited. Some women from the compound emerged and were allowed to leave, Mr. Morris said. A boy fighter would have had the chance to walk out of the gate, too, he said.</p>
        <p>There were shots. And more waiting, as the Americans called for air support.</p>
        <p>Anyone who was inside had a choice of fighting or surrendering, he said, including Mr. Khadr.</p>
        <p>''There is just no way you can say this is a poor befuddled, brainwashed kid,'' Mr. Morris said. ''This is a kid who made a whole lot of decisions on his own.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
