<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Familiarity Is Breeding Fraternity for Coaches</title>
    <meta content="03cavs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/sports/basketball/03cavs.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852045"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/San Antonio Spurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Basketball Assn</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Cleveland Cavaliers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">San Antonio Spurs</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Brown, Mike</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EEDA1030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="894" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Familiarity Is Breeding Fraternity for Coaches</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Familiarity Is Breeding Fraternity for Coaches</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <dateline>CLEVELAND, June 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Earlier in the playoffs, Cavaliers Coach Mike Brown got a telephone call before a game.</p>
        <p>It was a San Antonio game, not a Cleveland game, and Spurs Coach Gregg Popovich was calling to check in with his protégé, Brown. Such is the N.B.A. fraternity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hank Egan, now Cavaliers Coach Mike Brown’s assistant, coached for eight years in San Antonio, winning a title with the team in 1999.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Earlier in the playoffs, Cavaliers Coach Mike Brown got a telephone call before a game.</p>
        <p>It was a San Antonio game, not a Cleveland game, and Spurs Coach Gregg Popovich was calling to check in with his protégé, Brown. Such is the N.B.A. fraternity.</p>
        <p>''We have a great relationship,'' Brown said, referring to Popovich, for whom he spent three years as an assistant, earning a championship ring in 2003. ''We talk from time to time. He'll call and check up on me, I'll call and ask for advice. He'll call to say 'good win,' and I'll do the same.</p>
        <p>''I learned a lot from him, and I grew a lot while working for him, and I continue to look at him as a mentor and a guy that can help me out.''</p>
        <p>As the Western Conference champion Spurs waited at home to see whether they would reprise the 2005 N.B.A. finals against the Detroit Pistons or play the Cavaliers, the team with the blooming superstar in LeBron James, Popovich's crew knew the team from Ohio would be more familiar.</p>
        <p>Hank Egan, now Brown's assistant, was an assistant for eight years in San Antonio, winning a title with the team in 1999.</p>
        <p>Danny Ferry, the Cavaliers' general manager, was San Antonio's director for basketball operations from 2003 to 2005. The Cavaliers' assistant general manager, Lance Blanks, worked for five years in the Spurs' front office.</p>
        <p>To become the northern version of the Spurs, winners of three N.B.A. titles in eight seasons, Brown knows the Cavaliers have a ways to go.</p>
        <p>In their third appearance in the Eastern Conference finals, and the first in 15 years, the Cavaliers defeated Detroit, 98-82, on Saturday night to win the best-of-seven series by 4-2. This season marked the first time the Cleveland franchise had led a conference finals.</p>
        <p>Brown said: ''We got to be put in situations like this, where there is something we have to go take, not just go play, but we have to go take it and earn it. We have to succeed in situations like this.</p>
        <p>''We have to continue to have a core, identify a core and keep that core together and just add winning pieces to the core.''</p>
        <p>It does not hurt to have the No. 1 draft pick to anchor that core. Brown realized quickly in San Antonio how lottery fortune can change a franchise -- whether the selection is David Robinson, Tim Duncan or James.</p>
        <p>Brown, 37, makes no secret of deferring to James, saying during this series how he lets James take over the huddle, suggest when to practice and even what plays to run. It is hard to argue when James scores 48 points, including 29 of his team's final 30 points, as he did in Game 5's 109-107 victory in double overtime.</p>
        <p>At the beginning of Duncan's career, Brown said, he had Robinson to guide him. James is learning mostly on his own.</p>
        <p>''With LeBron coming of age and helping this organization grow, this team grow, to the level it's at now,'' Brown said, ''you can see the maturity year after year after year, in terms of not only his play, but his demeanor on the floor, off the floor, and his play at a high level.''</p>
        <p>Brown only hoped James would take him as far as San Antonio.</p>
        <p>BILLUPS MAKES PROMISE -- Pistons point guard Chauncey Billups is not known for guarantees. His teammate Rasheed Wallace usually takes care of them.</p>
        <p>But Billups had seen enough film, and enough highlights of LeBron James's 48-point romp in Game 5, in which he stripped the Pistons of their defensive identity, not to mention their dignity. James waltzed through the lane virtually untouched for astounding one-handed dunks at the end of the game.</p>
        <p>This was not Detroit basketball, at least as Billups had known it.</p>
        <p>On Saturday morning, Billups came as close to a guarantee as he ever had. ''No, that won't happen again,'' he said. ''I won't say the kid can't get 40. He won't get the 40 like that again, not on us. He can get 40 fading away and all that, tip your hat. He won't get it on us.''</p>
        <p>James scored only 20 points on Saturday night, but the Cavaliers still won.</p>
        <p>WALKING THE STREETS -- Had Antonio McDyess, the toughest inside presence for the Pistons, not been ejected in the first quarter of Game 5 for his flagrant foul on Anderson Varejao, LeBron James may not have sauntered to the basket so easily.</p>
        <p>''He's our warrior man,'' Billups said of McDyess. ''He's in there crying. That hurt us in a bad, bad way.''</p>
        <p>McDyess talked to his teammates with tears in his eyes at halftime, then left the arena. McDyess said he spent the fourth quarter and overtime of Game 5 walking his neighborhood streets in frustration.</p>
        <p>''My friend kept texting me, saying they're in overtime again,'' he said Saturday. ''I didn't want to see it. I told him I didn't want the update.''</p>
        <p>McDyess was relieved that he was not suspended for Game 6.</p>
        <p>''I didn't deliberately try to go for his head or anything,'' he said of Varejao. ''I was actually trying to go for the ball. The ball was right by his head; I realized, oh, it's a foul, so I went ahead and had a hard foul.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
