<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Just Like Us -- Only Better</title>
    <meta content="0603play-mickelson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Play" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/03/sports/playmagazine/0603play-mickelson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852072"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mickelson, Phil, Woods, Tiger, Singh, Vijay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Mickelson, Phil</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Singh, Vijay</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E5D91030F930A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="4078" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Just Like Us -- Only Better</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Just Like Us  Only Better</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES MCGRATH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Was there ever a golf moment at once more horrific and more riveting than Phil Mickelson's meltdown on the final hole of last year's United States Open at Winged Foot Golf Club? You couldn't watch, and at the same time you couldn't not watch.</p>
        <p>Not to dwell on painful memories, but some traumas won't go away. Here was the new, reformed Phil, the one who had supposedly curbed his appetite for risky, all-or-nothing shots, coming off victories at the P.G.A. Championship and the Masters. A victory at Winged Foot would make him just the second golfer in 50 years to claim three majors in a row and would erase once and for all his reputation for poor decisions under fire, for being the kind of golfer who once caused Jack Nicklaus to say, ''Phil's a nice player, he's a good player, but he's not a great champion.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Phil Mickelson may be doomed to play golf’s second banana, but that’s what makes him so interesting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Was there ever a golf moment at once more horrific and more riveting than Phil Mickelson's meltdown on the final hole of last year's United States Open at Winged Foot Golf Club? You couldn't watch, and at the same time you couldn't not watch.</p>
        <p>Not to dwell on painful memories, but some traumas won't go away. Here was the new, reformed Phil, the one who had supposedly curbed his appetite for risky, all-or-nothing shots, coming off victories at the P.G.A. Championship and the Masters. A victory at Winged Foot would make him just the second golfer in 50 years to claim three majors in a row and would erase once and for all his reputation for poor decisions under fire, for being the kind of golfer who once caused Jack Nicklaus to say, ''Phil's a nice player, he's a good player, but he's not a great champion.''</p>
        <p>Mickelson prepared for the 2006 Open with unusual thoroughness, traveling to Winged Foot, in Mamaroneck, N.Y., several times with both of his gurus: Rick Smith, his swing coach, and Dave Pelz, his short-game tutor. He and Smith even decided that Mickelson would carry two drivers to deal with Winged Foot's many doglegs: one to fade the ball (or, since Mickelson is a lefty, bend the ball's flight to the left) and one to draw it right. And for three days it all paid off. Mickelson struggled a bit off the tee, but he putted beautifully and was the co-leader after 54 holes. On Sunday, he sprayed the ball all over the place, hitting just two fairways all afternoon, but somehow he ham-and-egged his way out of Winged Foot's ankle-grabbing rough and arrived at the 18th tee with a one-shot lead. Then the wires short-circuited, and there was a blackout up in Phil's control tower.</p>
        <p>Against the better judgment of everyone -- his caddie, Bones Mackay, one would hope; certainly the announcer Johnny Miller up in the broadcast booth; and all of us at home in our living rooms, screaming, ''No, no, Phil! Not the driver!'' -- he took out one of the big sticks and once again blocked his tee shot to the left, so far this time that it bounced off a hospitality tent. The lie wasn't terrible (the ball came to rest in grass that had been trampled down by spectators), but the way to the green was cut off by trees. The sensible thing, the smart thing, was for him to hit a wedge back onto the fairway and then nail his third shot close enough to the flagstick for a one-putt par or, worst case, a two-putt bogey and a playoff. Instead, as he had so often before, Mickelson tried the impossible, heroic shot, a high fade around the treetops. His ball thwacked into a trunk so hard that the TV camera in the blimp overhead temporarily lost track of it and swirled around madly before discovering it practically back at Mickelson's feet. He tried the same shot again and overcooked it this time, sending the ball into a bunker behind the green. An indifferent sand shot, a chip, a putt -- double bogey, and there went the U.S. Open. Mickelson's eyes can sometimes burn like coals, but now they were glassy and his face was ashen. ''I'm still in shock that I did that,'' he said afterward. ''I am such an idiot. I can't believe I did that.''</p>
        <p>What made this collapse so awful to watch is that most of us have been there. There is something about golf that brings out the inner dolt, at once beating you down and also cruelly lifting you up, making you believe, against all evidence to the contrary, that you can do what you cannot. Every now and then, you pull off the impossible shot -- the one that ricochets off the equipment shed just as you planned, or that carries the parking lot and ducks under the power line before skipping onto the green -- and the blissful feeling that results is what keeps us coming back to the golf course. But failure, far more common, occasions crippling pangs of disgust and self-loathing: How could I be so stupid?</p>
        <p>The difference between Phil Mickelson and the rest of us is that (1) he plays golf for a living, and a crazy shot that doesn't work costs him a lot more than a lost golf ball, and (2) he is an idiot who happens to be the second-best golfer in the world. (He and Vijay Singh have 31 PGA Tour victories each as of this writing, but Singh is seven years older than Mickelson, who will turn 37 on the Saturday of this year's U.S. Open, which begins on June 14.) The best golfer in the world is, of course, Tiger Woods, with 57 Tour wins, and it has, sadly, become the defining fact of Mickelson's career that the gap between him and Woods is almost unfathomable. Not only is Woods not an idiot, but for long stretches he has come closer to perfection than any other golfer who has ever lived. As Mickelson put it in ESPN magazine this spring: ''The reality is, even if I play at the top of my game for the rest of my career and achieve my goals -- let's say, win 50 tournaments and 10 majors, pretty difficult to do, since I'd need 20 more wins, including seven more majors -- I still won't get to where Tiger is right now. So I won't compare myself with him. It makes no sense.''</p>
        <p>Not that he cares, but in a Tiger-less world we might appreciate Mickelson less. Tiger plays a game we can only marvel at, with that perfect physique and unwavering focus. Phil, flabbier and streakier, plays one we can almost recognize -- he's just like us, only better. And on a tour where the key to winning these days seems more and more to be to turn yourself into a zombie, Mickelson's occasional failings are welcome proof of humanity. He may be an idiot sometimes, but he's our idiot.</p>
        <p>Woods and Mickelson, we gather, are not overly fond of each other. That was apparent, most obviously, in their pairing at the 2004 Ryder Cup, where the team format, requiring them to play with, not against, each other, proved to be practically toxic and brought out the worst in both of them. To a certain extent, in fact, Mickelson has fashioned himself as the anti-Tiger. Back in 2002, for example, when he was still encumbered with the label ''Best Player Never to Win a Major,'' he said: ''I love winning and I love competing, but there's more to life than that. I don't want to shortchange myself or my potential. But it's not like I've been one-dimensional in my approach to the game, that the one and only thing is to become the greatest player of all time.''</p>
        <p>Over the years, as if in contrast to the private and single-minded Woods, Mickelson has been at great pains to show us Phil the Family Man. His wife and kids are surely the most visible and best known in all of golf, and are adorable almost to the point of insufferableness: beautiful, blond Amy, who looks as if she just stepped from the pages of the golf wives catalog, and the three towheaded moppets, Amanda, Sophia and Evan, who come tumbling onto the green whenever he wins. ''Well, that's O.K.,'' he has said Amanda told him after the Winged Foot debacle. ''Second's pretty good. You want some pizza?'' (Woods is now married, of course, and awaiting the birth of his first child, but he chose his spouse not from the golf wives catalog, which consists of cheerleader types, but from the Swedish-bikini-models catalog, and unlike Mickelson, who leads a somewhat visible private life, he is as remote and as mysterious as a head of state.)</p>
        <p>Mickelson has also criticized Woods for using inferior equipment. (He meant it as a sort of backhanded compliment, explaining that Woods won despite his golf clubs, but it rankled the touchy Woods nonetheless, in a way that you suspect wouldn't have bothered Mickelson had the tables been turned.) And unlike Woods, who has always been a fitness buff, Mickelson only recently hired a strength-and-fitness coach. In the old days he would brag about being a stranger to the gym. (It used to show, too, in an embonpoint that rivaled Colin Montgomerie's.) But the oddest bit of anti-Tigerhood happened in April, when Mickelson fired Rick Smith, his longtime swing coach, and replaced him with Butch Harmon, who used to be Woods's coach and in fact engineered the swing that earned Woods seven majors. (Woods dumped him in 2002 for reasons that are still a little mysterious but may have had to do with a feeling that Harmon was taking too much credit for his protégé's success.) Right away, the golf blogs began churning: Was this treachery and disloyalty on Phil's part? A deliberate dis of Tiger, implying that he had been too quick to drop the teacher who got him where he is?</p>
        <p>Probably neither. Unlike Woods, who took three years to put his game back together under his new coach, Hank Haney, Mickelson appears to be in search of a quick fix. Rick Smith is among the most cerebral of golf coaches, as is Pelz, who used to be a NASA scientist, and both are mild mannered. Harmon, though a legendary teacher, is old school and leather-lunged. People who know him say that, far from deferring to Mickelson, he may even browbeat him into doing things the Harmon way. Presumably, Mickelson understands that and, at this point, is ready to try anything.</p>
        <p>A sudden, impulsive change like this is also very much the Mickelson style. It used to be rumored that he was a serious gambler, betting tens of thousands of dollars, or hundreds of thousands -- or millions even, depending on which blog you believe -- on sporting events and at the baccarat tables in Las Vegas. On the one hand, these stories always seemed a little hard to square with Mickelson's image as a clean-cut, down-to-earth family man, so devoted to his wife that as she neared the end of her pregnancy with their first child he took a beeper with him to the 1999 U.S. Open, fully prepared to walk off the course if she went into labor. Whatever else he is, Mickelson is clearly not a self-destructive head case like John Daly, who really has lost millions. Nor does he display any of the bored, regal aloofness of Michael Jordan, another famous gambler.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, there is Mickelson's high-rolling behavior on the golf course. ''Playing conservative stinks,'' he once said, and that risky recovery shot at Winged Foot was just one of many chances he has taken over the years, shooting right at treacherous pin positions, hacking long approaches out of deep rough, flopping wedge shots over trees or else scooting them under low-hanging branches. Mickelson's boyhood role model was the flashy Seve Ballesteros, and it shows. The only shot that does not come easily to him is the lay-up. The Winged Foot disaster reminded many of another go-for-broke decision, this one at the Bay Hill Invitational in 2002. On the par-5 16th hole, he went left with his drive, into the rough, and instead of pitching back onto the fairway he swung for the green with a 4-iron, a shot that was almost all carry over water. The ball drowned and with it Mickelson's chances of catching Woods, who was leading by one stroke.</p>
        <p>Afterward, Mickelson defended himself, saying: ''I am not going to play this game without the enjoyment, without the fun, that I have right now. The fact is that if I change the way I play golf, I won't play to the level I have been playing. So I won't ever change. Not tomorrow, or at Augusta or the U.S. Open or any tournament.''</p>
        <p>Some observers have suggested that Woods actually brings out the gambler in Mickelson (and in several other golfers, for that matter). Since Woods so seldom makes mistakes, the theory goes, you have to take chances in order to beat him. There may be something to this, but the evidence is also that Mickelson likes to play this way -- he gets off on it. You can see it in that cocky little one-handed twirl he sometimes gives the club before undertaking a difficult shot and in the way he stares the ball all the way down to its target. He still remembers what we hackers learn very early on: that risky golf is much more fun. So there's water out there -- who wants to hit a cautious iron off the tee when there's a chance for the Big Dog to bite off a serious mouthful?</p>
        <p>And of course Mickelson plays this way because he can -- he makes many more of these low-percentage shots than he misses. What sometimes gets overlooked in the Woods-Mickelson discussion is that Mickelson, too, was a child prodigy, almost equally gifted and with more advantages. His father, an airline pilot, built Phil his own practice green and sand trap in the backyard. (It was also his father who inadvertently turned Phil, a natural righty, into a lefty; as a toddler, Phil insisted on facing his dad and mirroring his swing.) Practicing in the yard for hours on end, Mickelson perfected his patented ''flop'' shot -- the one that goes straight up and then drops straight back down, with hardly any parabola -- and all the other techniques that make him now arguably the greatest wedge player ever. In 1980 he won the Junior World Championship, for boys 9 and 10, and he went on to a gilded career at Arizona State, leading his team to three N.C.A.A. championships and receiving for three years straight the Haskins Award, given to the outstanding college golfer. He won the United States Amateur in 1990, the first lefty ever to do so, and in 1991, while still an amateur, he won a PGA Tour event, the Northern Telecom Open in Tucson. He turned pro at the 1992 United States Open at Pebble Beach and was thought at the time to be the most promising college golfer since Nicklaus.</p>
        <p>And then, though he began racking up Tour victories, there was the long, agonizing wait for a major. Second, by just a stroke, to Payne Stewart in the 1999 United States Open. Second, again by a stroke, to David Toms in the 2001 P.G.A. Championship. Second to Woods in the 2002 Open at Bethpage, on Long Island. Lots of top 5s and top 10s, and also not a few majors where he just crashed and burned -- the 2002 British Open at Muirfield, for example, where he finished tied for 66th. When he finally broke through -- on his 43rd try -- at the 2004 Masters, birdieing five of the last seven holes and making that lurching little leap of celebration, it was a moment both touching and immensely relieving, for those of us at home almost as much as for Mickelson. Thank goodness, we got that over with!</p>
        <p>Who knows why it took so long? Golf is like that sometimes. But if you have a gloomy, Calvinist streak, you might argue that in Mickelson's case all that talent and wizardry was a mixed blessing, and came at a price. It enabled him to get away with some things that maybe he shouldn't have. What the experts and the swing doctors are now saying, at any rate, is that Mickelson is a great golfer who doesn't have a particularly great swing. It's far from an ordinary mortal's swing, but unlike the strokes that all the young Tour players seem to be equipped with these days, it's not without some visible flaws. He has a long, wide takeaway with a very late wrist cock, and at the top he goes way past parallel. It's a huge superstructure, supported by a lower body that's not always as still as the diagnosticians would like, with a tendency for his right knee to kick out, and Mickelson gets away with it all, according to Rick Smith, because he has such great hands and can bring the clubface back to square at the last instant. Smith nevertheless worked on getting Mickelson to tighten his swing and reduce the number of moving parts, and the presumption is that Harmon will do the same, even more aggressively. Everyone would like to see that backswing grow a little shorter. The great question, of course, is how much you can tinker before Phil stops being Phil. By the third day of the Players Championship last month, you could see that his swing with the driver was already a little different -- more efficient but less fluid. On Sunday he seemed much more comfortable.</p>
        <p>Not everyone appreciates Mickelson's particular brand of self-conscious wholesomeness and niceness. The golf writer John Feinstein once compared him to Eddie Haskell, Wally Cleaver's smarmy friend. In 2006, GQ published ''The Ten Most Hated Athletes,'' a list that ranked Mickelson eighth, and in a recent Golf.com poll that asked 71 Tour members whom they least like to play with, he finished tied for second, with Ben Crane and Garrett Willis (but way behind the annoying Rory Sabbatini, who locked in first place with 25 percent of the vote). This is not to say he has no friends on the Tour; the players he does hang out with are unflashy and famously decent: Tom Lehman, Lee Janzen, Justin Leonard, Jeff Sluman. The PGA Tour, we should remember, is sometimes a breeding ground of jealousy and resentment. For all its apparent glamour, it's really a two-tiered caste system, with the top players -- the Woodses, Mickelsons, Davis Loves and the like -- existing on a different plane from the rest. They get the best tee times, the brand-new courtesy cars, the armies of willing gofers. If you're a journeyman, flying commercial from stop to stop, bunking with your caddie in a Motel 6, it must drive you batty to see Mickelson come soaring in on the Gulfstream II along with Amy and the kids. You seldom get to exchange more than a word or two with him, because unless you can claw your way up the leaderboard, your day is done before the telecast begins and before Mickelson even shows up at the course.</p>
        <p>Mickelson is famous, nonetheless, for staying around after work and patiently signing autographs. The fans like him, even if the pros do not, and the depth of their affection was never more apparent than during the 2002 Open at Bethpage, the first time the championship was held on a truly public course -- a muni, if you like. The galleries were bigger, louder, rowdier than they usually are at a golf tournament, with lots of New Yorkers on hand, and they immediately embraced Phil, rooting him on as Tiger's underdog and hollering encouragement as he strode down the fairway. He responded with that cockeyed, slightly goofy grin of his and by shyly touching his visor. When he took it off, to wipe his brow, you again realized -- it's always a surprise, somehow -- that he looks a little like Hugh Grant, only not so pretty.</p>
        <p>It is doubtless of small consolation to Mickelson, but the truth is that he is charming and appealing -- lovable even -- in a way that Woods never will be. And he's more fun to watch. There's something a little scary about the ferocity with which Tiger works -- the concentration, the determination. He doesn't need a gallery, you often feel, because his competitive fires are already burning with such intensity. He may not even notice that we're there -- except when some jerk snaps a picture at the wrong moment and then gets the death glance in return.</p>
        <p>Phil, on the other hand, seems to enjoy our presence -- to feed on it -- and he rewards our attention by being such an open book. You can tell how his round is going just by looking at him -- the gleams of pleasure or else the sighs, the little head shakes. Always there's the thrilling, unspoken question: Is the knucklehead going to emerge?</p>
        <p>After the Open last year, the rest of Mickelson's season was pretty much a bust. He tied for 22nd at the British Open at Royal Liverpool and for 16th at the P.G.A. Championship at Medinah in Illinois, and was never really in the hunt for either. He was dismal at the Ryder Cup, held at the K Club in Ireland, scoring just a scant half-point in five outings. People began to talk about Winged Foot as the kind of disaster that a golfer might never come back from.</p>
        <p>This year began in similarly dispiriting fashion; he didn't even make the cut at the FBR Open in early February. A week later, however, he won the AT&amp;T at Pebble Beach (against an admittedly weak field). He lurked around for a while at the Masters, but then took himself out of it by finishing with a 5-over round of 77 on Sunday. After signing up with Harmon, he finished tied for third place twice and then had a very solid win at the Players, at the Tournament Players Club at Sawgrass, in Florida, the so-called fifth major (because the field is so strong), where the course doesn't even particularly suit him. He got steadily better over the weekend and showed us appealing flashes of both old and new. On Saturday, for example, he pulled off a classic heart-stopper at the par-4 10th hole by threading his second shot through a tiny gap in some palm fronds. The shot was so risky he didn't even tell Bones Mackay what he had in mind, lest the caddie try to talk him out of it. But on Sunday, nursing a three-shot lead, he didn't just leave the driver in the bag on the 18th hole, where water loomed all the way up the left side, waiting to swallow a push or a block. He hit a hybrid club off the tee, which for Mickelson is like cinching your pants up to your chin with both a belt and suspenders, and then gave us an extra little frisson by knocking his second shot much too close to the green-side lagoon. It was his partner, in fact, the 24-year-old Sean O'Hair, who played like Mickelson. Trailing by two, O'Hair declined to play safe and went right at the pin on 17, the famous island green. He made a perfect swing -- except he was so pumped that his shot ended up in the drink. Far from chastened, he was defiant afterward and said, ''I didn't bust my butt for four days for second place.'' Where have we heard that before?</p>
        <p>That Harmon could be the answer in such a short time seems too good to be true. Swing changes for a player at Mickelson's level are a matter of tiny adjustments, not massive overhauls, and sometimes take months to implement. On the other hand, he's now on a roll, for whatever reason, and is presumably focused on this year's United States Open -- at Oakmont Country Club, outside of Pittsburgh -- with singular ambition and determination. Woods, on the other hand, threatened at both the Masters and the Players but never looked dominant. He struggled with his putter and hit a lot of tee shots that were mirror images of Mickelson's poor ones -- pushes and blocks to the right.</p>
        <p>Oakmont is -- if such a thing is possible -- an even tougher track than Winged Foot. It's a grinder's course, and the only way to score there is to stay in the fairways. For Mickelson, a win is by no means out of the question, and it's hard to imagine an outcome that would be more gratifying to the fans. But we -- and he -- are going to hear about last year until we're sick of it. The best thing Mickelson could do would be to tune all of that out -- and take the other Phil, the one with the crazed look in his eye, and lock him in a room somewhere until the weekend is over. If he gets out, well, we'll recognize him right away, because he's so closely related to the nut job inside our own brainpans.</p>
        <p>Charles McGrath is a writer at large for The New York Times and the former editor of the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
