<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: Diagnosis; Full-Body Failure</title>
    <meta content="17wwln--diagnosis.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/magazine/17wwln-diagnosis-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Diagnosis"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wilson's Disease</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanders, Lisa (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Diagnosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E4DC173FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1381" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: Diagnosis; Full-Body Failure</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Full-Body Failure</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lisa Sanders, M.D.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanders, Lisa (Dr)</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lisa Sanders column on diagnosis of Wilson's disease in young woman whose whole body showed signs of shutting down and whose life was saved only by liver transplant; photos; drawing (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>1. Symptoms</p>
        <p>''There's a young woman sick as hell in the I.C.U. -- if you have time,'' read the note left on Dr. Steven Walerstein's desk chair. It was late on a Friday afternoon and Walerstein, the medical director at Nassau University Medical Center in East Meadow, N.Y., was already going to be late for his weekly racquetball game. But he would come back. Stuck behind a desk far too much of the time, he was drawn to what promised to be a tough case.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The young woman was dying, but no one couldfigure out why  until one doctor found a new wayof looking at things.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>1. Symptoms</p>
        <p>''There's a young woman sick as hell in the I.C.U. -- if you have time,'' read the note left on Dr. Steven Walerstein's desk chair. It was late on a Friday afternoon and Walerstein, the medical director at Nassau University Medical Center in East Meadow, N.Y., was already going to be late for his weekly racquetball game. But he would come back. Stuck behind a desk far too much of the time, he was drawn to what promised to be a tough case.</p>
        <p>It was early evening by the time Walerstein got to see the patient. She was young -- the chart said 22, but the slender figure surrounded by life-support equipment appeared even younger. She looked tired and sick and very, very yellow -- highlighter yellow. He introduced himself and asked her to tell him when all this started.</p>
        <p>It began, she told him, with a root canal, maybe a month ago. The tooth kept bothering her, even after two different antibiotics. Then she started noticing blood in her stools. At first it was just an occasional episode, but then, a few days before she came to the hospital, the trips to the bathroom became more frequent and the blood more obvious. She felt feverish and tired. She had a headache; she was nauseated. She spent a couple of days in bed and felt well enough at least to take a shower. When she looked in the mirror, she barely recognized the yellow face that looked back. Even the whites of her eyes were yellow. That scared her. That's when she came to the hospital.</p>
        <p>At first, the doctors thought it was viral hepatitis. But tests indicated that it wasn't. Walerstein examined the patient. She was febrile, her skin hot and dry. Her lips were parched and cracked. Her abdomen was distended but soft, and he could feel the firm edge of an enlarged liver a couple of inches below her rib cage.</p>
        <p>2. Investigation</p>
        <p>Her chart was filled with numbers that testified to how very ill she was. It seemed that every test they ran was abnormal. Her white blood count was very high, suggesting that she might have an infection. And she had barely half the amount of blood she should have. Walerstein saw that she had already received several transfusions, and she was still profoundly anemic -- something in her system was destroying the blood as fast as it could be pumped in. Her kidneys weren't working. Her blood wasn't clotting, and her urine and stool were stained deep red with uncontrollable bleeding. She was dying, and no one knew what was killing her.</p>
        <p>These are the most difficult cases -- patients who have so many things going wrong that it's nearly impossible for a doctor to process them all at the same time. The current theory focused on the bloody diarrhea. She'd had two courses of powerful antibiotics before coming to the hospital. For reasons that are not well understood, antibiotics put you at risk for becoming infected with the bacteria known as clostridium difficile, familiarly called C. diff. The bacteria cause a devastating diarrhea and a severe systemic illness that can be fatal. They'd looked for the dangerous toxin made by the bacteria but hadn't found it. Still, the test is notoriously unreliable. The I.C.U. team started antibiotics to treat C. diff. in case the result was wrong. But doctors still weren't satisfied with the diagnosis. Too many pieces didn't seem to fit.</p>
        <p>Dr. Tom Manis, the senior nephrologist, was brought in because the patient's kidneys were badly damaged. As he read through the chart, he became increasingly alarmed. The team was right -- their diagnosis didn't fit well at all. For one thing, C. diff. colitis was usually a disease of the sick and elderly. The patient was young and had been healthy. And C. diff. couldn't account for the profound jaundice and the persistent destruction of her red blood cells. Of greatest concern to Manis was that the patient was getting worse. ''I was unhappy with the way the case was going,'' he told me later. ''I started talking with all the smart people I could find.'' He added, ''That's why I left the note for Steve.''</p>
        <p>Walerstein was a general internist, admired for his broad knowledge of medicine. If he didn't know the answer right off the bat, he was known to ask questions that would lead to the answer. And this young woman needed an answer, or she would die. Having examined the patient and her chart, Walerstein took a moment to step back and look for some kind of pattern buried in the chaotic assemblage of numbers and tests. Everyone else started with the bloody diarrhea. Maybe that was the wrong way to think about it. The fact that the patient's blood was not clotting made Walerstein think that her liver was no longer working -- the liver makes most of the protein that causes blood to coagulate. So she had liver failure. And her red blood cells were being destroyed. That combination stirred something in his memory.</p>
        <p>Doctors inhabit a world of books and journals, but perhaps the most important way we learn clinical medicine, the medicine we use in the care of our patients, is through what we call pearls -- pearls of wisdom. These are information couplets that link one or two clinical observations and an action. If this, then think or do that. Hippocrates, the father of medicine, published the first volumes of these practical aphorisms. The information has changed, but the delivery system has not.</p>
        <p>3. Resolution</p>
        <p>Walerstein recalled having heard about a disease that featured both liver failure and anemia in some lecture years ago. He hurried to the library to see if he was remembering this pearl accurately. Yes! Liver failure and this unusual kind of anemia were caused by an inherited condition known as Wilson's disease. Patients with this genetic defect lack an important piece of chemical machinery in the liver, so they can't get rid of copper, an essential mineral naturally found in the diet. The excess copper builds up in the liver and other organs and destroys them. Usually this is a slow process, but occasionally, for reasons that are still not understood, the liver suddenly shuts down, dumping a lifetime's worth of stored copper into the bloodstream. Once there, the copper destroys red blood cells. The flood of damaged red cells injures the kidneys. In this form, it's a universally fatal disease with only one cure -- a new liver. This patient needed a liver transplant immediately.</p>
        <p>But first Walerstein had to confirm the diagnosis. Late on a Friday night it would be difficult to measure the amount of copper in her blood -- his hospital laboratory didn't even do that test. But there was another way to diagnose this disease. Patients will often accumulate copper in their eyes. Sometimes it can be seen with the naked eye, a golden brown ring at the very outermost edge of the iris. He hurried back to the I.C.U. He couldn't see any evidence of these rings, but maybe an ophthalmologist could. ''It's not often that you call the ophthalmologist at 8 p.m. on a Friday'' to do an emergency examination, Walerstein told me. ''I'm sure he thought I was nuts -- until he did the exam.'' As soon as Walerstein had the results, he dashed into the patient's room to tell her what they'd found.</p>
        <p>She was transferred that night to New York Presbyterian Hospital. Patients with the greatest need get priority in the transplant line. Without a new liver, she would die. Not long after, she received an organ and survived.</p>
        <p>But what would have happened if Walerstein had been out of town that day or hadn't come back? Would this condition have been diagnosed? Would the patient have survived? Neither doctors nor patients like to consider how much of medicine depends on chance. Contingency and coincidence can be as important in the moments between life and death as knowledge and skill. No doctor knows everything. Hippocrates's well-known aphorism expresses this ancient truth: ''Life is short, the art, long . . . judgment is difficult. It is not enough for the physician to do what is necessary . . . the circumstances must be favorable.''</p>
        <p>Diagnosis</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
