<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Going Nose-to-Nose With a Great White</title>
    <meta content="17explore" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/travel/17explore.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854933"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="EXPLORER: SHARK DIVING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sharks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diving and Divers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dyer Island (South Africa)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hammer, Joshua</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Snorkeling and Diving</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa/Cape Town</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Diving and Divers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sharks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diving and Divers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Cape Town (South Africa)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EFDC173FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Going Nose-to-Nose With a Great White</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Going Nose-to-Nose With a Great White</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSHUA HAMMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hammer, Joshua</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joshua Hammer travel article on scuba diving expedition to glimpse great white sharks in waters of Indian Ocean off Dyer Island, near Kleinbaai, South Africa; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was not the most comfortable position in which I had ever found myself. Encased inside a ten-foot-long aluminum cage that dangled off the side of the dive boat, submerged up to my neck in 57-degree sea water, I peered with difficulty through a fogged-in scuba mask at the placid Indian Ocean. My feet rested on a thick metal bar about three feet below the surface; my knees were propped up against my chest. Though a wet suit kept my body reasonably well insulated, my exposed hands were freezing and turning numb.</p>
        <p>I had been stuck in this awkward pose, alongside three other divers, for nearly an hour, waiting to catch a glimpse of a great white shark in its natural habitat. Already three people had given up and clambered out of the cold water and back onto the boat, named Shark Team, but I wasn't ready to call it quits. I rubbed my hands together, and absent-mindedly wrapped my fingers around the front bars of the cage, prompting a warning from Grant Tuckett, our guide on this morning-long expedition, that I risked having them bitten off. Then, Mike Ledley, another crew member aboard the Shark Team, shouted out: ''Shark! Get ready!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Going into a shark cage allows visitors to view the predators underwater, and if lucky, to observe them from just inches away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was not the most comfortable position in which I had ever found myself. Encased inside a ten-foot-long aluminum cage that dangled off the side of the dive boat, submerged up to my neck in 57-degree sea water, I peered with difficulty through a fogged-in scuba mask at the placid Indian Ocean. My feet rested on a thick metal bar about three feet below the surface; my knees were propped up against my chest. Though a wet suit kept my body reasonably well insulated, my exposed hands were freezing and turning numb.</p>
        <p>I had been stuck in this awkward pose, alongside three other divers, for nearly an hour, waiting to catch a glimpse of a great white shark in its natural habitat. Already three people had given up and clambered out of the cold water and back onto the boat, named Shark Team, but I wasn't ready to call it quits. I rubbed my hands together, and absent-mindedly wrapped my fingers around the front bars of the cage, prompting a warning from Grant Tuckett, our guide on this morning-long expedition, that I risked having them bitten off. Then, Mike Ledley, another crew member aboard the Shark Team, shouted out: ''Shark! Get ready!''</p>
        <p>I took a gulp of air and dropped below the surface, 12 pounds of lead weights strapped around my wet suit to counter my natural buoyancy. Feet wedged at the bottom of the cage, I pressed my mask against a face-wide aperture between the bars and waited for a monster to swim into view. The visibility in the water, which was thick with sand and algae blooms, was less than three feet. On the deck, the crew dragged ropes tied with fresh bait -- shark liver, chunks of yellowfin tuna -- around the boat, trying to lure the great white into proximity. ''Here he comes,'' Mr. Ledley yelled.</p>
        <p>Like many people, I've been fascinated by great white sharks since even before Peter Benchley and Steven Spielberg stirred up our primal fears back in the 1970s. But until I ventured out on this shark safari in South Africa, I'd never seen one of these fearsome creatures in the flesh.</p>
        <p>As any shark researcher will tell you, great whites, or carcharadon carcharias, are among the world's most nomadic creatures -- one was recently tracked from South Africa to western Australia and back over a period of nine months, a distance of 12,000 miles -- which means that they are almost impossible to keep alive in captivity. (Rare exceptions have been young white sharks kept for short periods at the Monterey Bay Aquarium in Monterey, Calif., before being released into the wild.)</p>
        <p>So just about the only way to view them -- unlike reef, hammerhead, or tiger sharks, all common denizens of aquariums from Boston to Cape Town -- is in the wild.</p>
        <p>Nearly 40 years ago , the makers of the documentary ''Blue Water, White Death,'' including the American author Peter Matthiessen, pioneered the use of shark-viewing cages at the Dangerous Reef in southern Australia, shooting from the safety of their aluminum enclosures, the most extraordinary footage ever made of great whites in their natural environment.</p>
        <p>In the last 15 years, ''cage diving'' has gone commercial. Thousands of tourists a year are now squeezing into wet suits and plunging into shark-infested waters off Australia and South Africa for an intimate look at the predators, which grow as long as 25 feet, can weigh more than a ton, and live between 30 and 50 years.</p>
        <p>Shark researchers consider the waters around Dyer Island, four miles off the South African coast near the town of Kleinbaai, to be one of the best spots in the world to view the great white.</p>
        <p>The island, named after an African-American who lived there in the early 19th century, collecting seagull droppings to sell to mainland farmers, is home to about 50,000 to 60,000 Cape fur seals. Migrating great whites by the thousands swarm through Shark Alley around Dyer during the South African winter -- July through September -- to feed on seal pups, one of the predator's primary food sources. The sharks are less plentiful during the rest of the year, but there is never a time when they completely disappear.</p>
        <p>''Dyer Island is the only place in the world where shark viewing takes place the whole year round,'' said Mr. Tuckett, who worked as a paramedic before a lifelong fascination with great whites deposited him in Kleinbaai, about a two-hour drive from Cape Town, five years ago.</p>
        <p>I set off for my shark diving expedition in early February, the height of the tourist season in South Africa and, conversely, the worst time of the year for shark viewing. The seal population thins out during this period, and the frigid ocean currents during the southern hemisphere's summer keeps most great whites away; sharks, like people, prefer temperate waters. But shark-dive operators had told me that it's rare even in February not to encounter sharks at all. (At the height of the shark-viewing season, in July and August, one can see hundreds.)</p>
        <p>I arrived at White Shark Projects, one of eight operators in Kleinbaai, at 7:30 on a Sunday morning, just in time for a quick breakfast with 17 other tourists, and a briefing from Mr. Tuckett about shark behavior. He reminded us that the great white's reputation as a maneater is ill founded. There are only ''between 50 and 60'' shark attacks against humans each year, he said, only four or five fatalities. As Mr. Tuckett wryly pointed out, ''more people die from eating sharks than from being bitten by them.''</p>
        <p>We pushed off from the dock at 8:30 on an overcast morning and skimmed across the bay for 20 minutes to the marine reserve. Crew members lay anchor, winched the cage into place on the starboard side of the boat, baited lines, and scattered chum -- minced fish and shark liver blended with brine. Then we waited. The fierce summer sun burst through the clouds and it grew uncomfortably hot; the constant rocking motion sickened two passengers, a Turkish businessman and an elderly German woman, and both had to be taken back to shore by a rescue boat. Others sucked on lollypops to counteract the onset of seasickness.</p>
        <p>A few minutes after the evacuation, Mr. Tuckett shouted ''Shark!'' I scanned the nearby water and, with a thrill, I glimpsed an image straight out of the 2003 film ''Open Water'': a curved dorsal fin knifing with great speed toward the boat. All 16 of us rushed to starboard and, as the vessel tilted dangerously, we watched the first great white shark of the morning swim toward the bait lines just below the surface. He was a modest six feet long, and though the water was murky, I could clearly make out his torpedo-like shape, beady eyes, and conical snout. The creature lunged for the bait, missed it, then dove out of sight.</p>
        <p>Many of my fellow passengers elected to observe the proceedings from the relative comfort of the boat deck; I opted for the cage, which allows one to view the predators underwater, and if lucky, to observe them from just inches away. I got into my wet suit and lowered myself into the enclosure, wincing as the frigid seawater seeped through every seam in the wet suit. Mr. Ledley closed the lid of the cage. There I waited, squirming with discomfort, trying to ward off the advancing chill. ''Now I know how a hamster feels,'' said one of my fellow captives, staring dully through the bars. Then, nearly an hour into my ordeal, Mr. Ledley shouted ''Shark!'' and told us to submerge.</p>
        <p>I held my breath and stared in the depths. Thirty seconds passed. A minute. Finally I rose gasping to the surface. ''We couldn't get him close enough,'' said Mr. Ledley apologetically. By now I'd had enough. Shivering, disappointed, I hoisted myself to the deck, peeled off my wet suit, and luxuriated in the noonday sun.</p>
        <p>A minute later, I heard a yell. Whirling around to starboard, I saw a dreadlocked crew member gesticulating wildly. Just beneath the surface a massive gray missile was hurtling toward us. The crew member pulled the bait line toward the boat; the creature kept coming. Then, amazingly, the great white lurched out of the ocean, eyes bulging, jaws snapping, teeth flashing. A 10-foot-long gray mass of muscle and cartilage, he twisted left, then right, in furious pursuit of the bloody chunk of yellowfin. The water frothed around him as he lunged for the bait, and as he slammed his massive body back down into the ocean, cold spray washed over all of us. Some of the passengers screamed in excitement. It reminded me of the climactic scene in ''Jaws,'' when the great maneater hurls himself out of the Atlantic and devours Robert Shaw on the deck of his boat.</p>
        <p>A few seconds later, the monster was gone, and shortly after that, we started our return to shore. We had glimpsed only three sharks in the course of the morning -- about par for the month of February. But those few thrilling seconds had made the entire three-hour wait aboard the Shark Team worthwhile.</p>
        <p>GETTING UP CLOSE</p>
        <p>HOW TO GET THERE</p>
        <p>South African Airways flies from Kennedy Airport in New York to Cape Town, via Johannesburg. A recent Web search showed round-trip fares starting at about $1,355.</p>
        <p>DIVE INFORMATION</p>
        <p>The village of Kleinbaai, a two-hour drive from Cape Town, is the South Africa's cage-diving Mecca. The road near the harbor is lined with dive-boat operators, all of which run daily, and sometimes twice-daily, expeditions to the great white feeding grounds around Dyer Island. You can book with them directly, or go, as I did, through a tour agent, which locates available boats on the date you want to go</p>
        <p>A morning or afternoon trip costs roughly 1,200 rand (about $165.50 at 7.25 to the dollar) and includes a pickup and drop off in Cape Town, breakfast or lunch, boat transport, on-board snacks, sunblock, and all dive equipment. Peak season is June through September, when booking well in advance is recommended. The off-season runs between December and March</p>
        <p>TOUR AGENTS</p>
        <p>Shark Alley Dive &amp; Travel Centre Shop 22, Gateway Centre, Gansbaai; (27-28) 384-3763 or (27-82) 459-5522, or janeen@sharkbookings.com.</p>
        <p>TOUR OPERATORS</p>
        <p>White Shark Projects,  White Shark Lodge, 16 Geelbek Street, Kleinbaai; (27-28) 384-1774 or (27-76) 245-5880, bookings@whitesharkprojects.co.za</p>
        <p>White Shark Diving Company, Kleinbaai; (27-82) 559-6858 or (27-21) 671-4777, or info@sharkcagediving.co.za</p>
        <p>Great White Shark Tours, Gansbaai; (27-83) 300-2138; brian@sharkcagediving.net.</p>
        <p>EXPLORER: SHARK DIVING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
