<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Milan</title>
    <meta content="17hours" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/travel/17hours.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854932"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="36 HOURS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Milan (Italy)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Italy</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Fred A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/36 Hours</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Milan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Milan (Italy)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDC173FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1590" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Milan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">36 Hours in Milan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRED A. BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Fred A</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fred Bernstein travel article on 36-hour visit to Milan, Italy; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MILAN doesn't cater to tourists. Its many pleasures are intended mainly for the Milanese, who are expert at making -- and spending -- money. This is the home, after all, of Armani and Prada. But step outside the central shopping district and you'll find a growing number of stores that showcase young fashion and furniture designers. There's also an exploding restaurant scene. Sri Lankan food may be as easy to find as anything cooked alla Milanese (battered and fried). In fact, the only meal that may elude you is ''The Last Supper.''</p>
        <p>Friday</p>
        <p>4 p.m.  1. Top Design  Milan is all about design, and until July 1 the Palazzo Reale, a museum in the city's center (Piazza Duomo, 12; 39-02-875-672; www.comune.milano.it/palazzoreale), has a terrific exhibition of Italian furniture from 1900 to 2000. The show, ''Rooms With a View,'' offers an eye-catching primer on the sometimes surreal styles that have made Milan the global center of furniture design. If you aren't already a devotee of, say, Futurism or Memphis, you will be by the time you leave the building. Admission is 9 euros, or about $12.40 at $1.38 to the euro.</p>
        <p>5:30 p.m.  2. James Bond Meets Armani  Now that you know where Italian design has been, see where it's going, at the shops nearby along the Via Alessandro Manzoni. The brightest include Sawaya &amp; Maroni (No. 11; 39-02-8639-5218; www.sawayamoroni.com) for furniture and lighting by Zaha Hadid, the Pritzker Prize-winning architect who shuns right angles. Just a few blocks away is the Bulgari Hotel (Via Privata Fratelli Gabba, 7B; 39-02- 805-8051; www.bulgarihotels.com ), which, thanks to another star architect, Antonio Citterio, is the type of place where James Bond and Giorgio Armani might meet for a martini. (Call ahead to get past the front gate.) Share a caprese (mozzarella with tomatoes and basil, served with a delicious eggplant purée) for 15 euros.</p>
        <p>8 p.m.  3. Tuscany in Milan  Brera is one of the city's quaintest neighborhoods, and La Torre di Pisa (Italian for the Leaning Tower of Pisa) is one of Brera's quaintest restaurants, a Tuscan-style trattoria that's always packed (Via Fiori Chiari 21/5; 39-02-874-877). You can't go wrong with the wonderfully spicy spaghetti alla puttanesca (10 euros) and the Robespierre, a hot platter of sliced Fiorentina steak, potatoes and vegetables (52 euros for two). After dinner, stroll Brera's lovely streets, many of which are cobblestone and closed to traffic.</p>
        <p>10 p.m.  4. Freaking It Up  The Metro may stop running and taxis are hard to get, but the Milanese don't let that stop them from enjoying the city's abundant night life. Nor should you. Try the cocktails at Living, a chic, black-painted lounge with huge windows facing the lush Parco Sempione (Piazza Sempione, 2; 39-02-3310-0824; www.livingmilano.com). If you're in the mood for some boogeying, stroll a few doors down to the Freak Bar (Via Agostino Bertani, 16; 39-02-331-4726; www.freakbar.it).</p>
        <p>Saturday</p>
        <p>10 a.m.  5. Till You Drop  Prada, Dolce &amp; Gabbana and Bulgari. You may have bought them at your local mall, but it's time to pay homage at the mother ships along Via Della Spiga. The store designs are often stunning, like the upside-down interior at Viktor &amp; Rolf (Via Sant'Andrea, 14; 39-02-796-091; www.viktor-rolf.com), with chandeliers rising from the floor and chairs hung from the ceiling. Don't miss it. A short cab ride away is another retail strip, Corso Como, anchored by 10 Corso Como (39-02-2900-2674; www.10corsocomo.it), a fabled boutique where you can watch customers fight over 300-euro tank tops. You'll fare better at its nearby outlet store (Via Tazzoli, 3), where relative sanity prevails: a gray T-shirt by Alexander McQueen was marked down on a recent visit to a mere 100 euros. For labels that nobody has heard of (yet), sneak over to Via Maroncelli, where you'll find some of the city's most innovative furniture and fashion stores like Galleria M. K. (No. 2; 39-02-655-1035; www.galleriamk.com), Labo.Art (No. 14; 39-02-365-23461; www.laboart.com) and Shopping Lifts Spirit (No. 3; 39-02-290-63125).</p>
        <p>1 p.m.  6. Haute Cuisine  Hungry from all the shopping? Head to Giorgio Armani's personal mall, which fills an entire block (Via Alessandro Manzoni, 31; 02-39-7231-8600; www.armani.com). In addition to the requisite Armani clothing stores, look for Armani Libri (books), Armani Dolci (chocolates), Armani Nobu (Japanese food) and, for an unforgettable lunch, Caffè Emporio Armani. The second-floor restaurant serves artistically arranged dishes like seared tuna with toasted almonds and mustard ice cream (25 euros). You'll find yourself -- as is everyone around you -- taking pictures of the food before you eat it. If you arrive by 1 p.m., there will be plenty of tables; by 2 p.m., there won't be any.</p>
        <p>2:30 p.m.  7. Date With a Masterpiece  Tickets to see Leonardo's ''Last Supper,'' in a refectory at Santa Maria delle Grazie (39-02-8942-1146; www.cenacolovinciano.org), sell out months in advance. To protect the painting from excess humidity, the number of visitors is strictly limited. Luckily, the tour company Zani Viaggi (39-02-867-131; www.zaniviaggi.it) will get you in to see it for the price of a 50-euro tour. A guide will walk you to Milan's twin centerpieces: the Duomo, among the largest cathedrals in the world (and very possibly the most beautiful), and the Galleria Vittorio Emanuele, an astonishing glass-covered arcade built in 1867. Your appointment with Leonardo's masterpiece is at 5:30 p.m. The electronic doors open precisely at that time, and again 15 minutes later to let you out. The 50 euros will seem like a bargain -- unless you were saving up for that McQueen T-shirt.</p>
        <p>8 p.m.  8. Bring Your Opera Glasses  It's curtain time at La Scala (Piazza della Scala; 39-02-7200-3744; www.teatroallascala.org), the most fabled opera house in the world. For a seat on the orchestra level, expect to spend a fortune. But a 66-euro perch, on a row near the ornately painted ceiling, offers a passable view. Wear formal attire; you're there for glamour, and you have to do your part. The inside of the theater was recently renovated by the Swiss architect Mario Botta, prompting some criticism because a circular addition competes with the original facade. Happily, the interior is pretty much unchanged from 1778.</p>
        <p>10:30 p.m.  9. Dining Under Glass  For some of the best people and architecture watching in Milan, cross the street from La Scala to the Galleria Vittorio Emanuele, where an outdoor table at Biffi (No. 92; 39-02-805-7961; www.biffigalleria.it) puts you under the great glass dome. Order a glass of wine, ignore the nearby McDonald's and marvel at the 19th-century details you missed earlier in the day, including the astonishing frescoes and caryatids overhead. The osso buco with risotto Milanese isn't bad either (26 euros). After dinner, follow the crowds in any direction until you find a great gelato.</p>
        <p>Sunday</p>
        <p>10 a.m.  10. Hello, Young Lovers  To see Milanese at leisure, walk to the sprawling Parco Sempione, north of the Duomo. There you'll find soccer players, skateboarders, joggers and couples in deep embrace. Stroll farther north until you see the Arco della Pace, an early 19th-century triumphal arch that commemorates Napoleon's victories (it faces Paris). Then circle back to the Torre Branca, a bullet-shaped tower at the park's edge that was designed by the Italian architect Gio Ponti in the 1930s. Three euros buys a ticket to the 300-foot-high observatory, which offers views of the Duomo below and, on a clear day, the Alps.</p>
        <p>11:30 a.m.  11. Venice in Milan  Ride a taxi (or, better yet, a bicycle) to the Navigli, a fascinating neighborhood bordered by two canals, which were planned in part by Leonardo da Vinci and were central to Milanese commerce until the mid-20th century. The more picturesque of the two canals is the Naviglio Grande. If it is the last Sunday of the month, a flea market will line the waterway, but even if it's not, you'll revel in what feels like the trendiest neighborhood -- in Venice. There are many fascinating shops, including Nipper (Ripa di Pta. Ticinese, 69; 39-02-837-6947), which sells mid-20th-century clocks, telephones and other gizmos.</p>
        <p>1 p.m.  12. Your Last Meal  Make your way to Kitchen (Via Scarlatti, 7; 39-02-2951-3679), a terrific Italian restaurant with an Asian staff (an increasingly common sight in a city that imports much of its labor). Serve yourself from the cold antipasto bar; a plate piled high with shrimp, calamari and succulent cooked vegetables is just 5.50 euros. Afterward, walk up the street to Milan's Central Station, an over-the-top, Mussolini-era building. It's a must-see, even if you're not leaving by train.</p>
        <p>THE BASICS</p>
        <p>Many major airlines have service between New York to Milan, starting at $1,075 round trip for travel in mid-July. The 40-minute train ride from Malpensa airport to Milan's Cadorna station (11 euros, or about $15.20 at $1.38 to the euro) couldn't be easier. Once in town, buy a 10-ride pass (9.20 euros) for the efficient Metro and bus system. Or try two wheels. Milan is a great city for cycling; it's compact and as flat as a tiramisù. Noleggio, near the train station (Via Ponte Seveso, 33; 39-02-6707-2145; awsbici@fastnetweb.it), rents mountain bikes for 11 euros a day.</p>
        <p>The Hotel Andreola (Via Scarlatti, 24; 39-02-670-9141; www.andreolahotel.it), on a quiet street near Central Station, is a steal. Rooms are small, but service is expansive. Doubles from 119 euros.</p>
        <p>The Park Hyatt Hotel (Via Tommaso Grossi, 1; 39-02-882-11234; www.milan.park.hyatt.com) is just a few feet from the tourist-packed Duomo and, yet, thanks to its courtyard design, feels utterly secluded. Doubles from 510 euros.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Step outside the central shopping district and you’ll find a growing number of stores that showcase young fashion and furniture designers. And an exploding restaurant scene.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MILAN doesn't cater to tourists. Its many pleasures are intended mainly for the Milanese, who are expert at making -- and spending -- money. This is the home, after all, of Armani and Prada. But step outside the central shopping district and you'll find a growing number of stores that showcase young fashion and furniture designers. There's also an exploding restaurant scene. Sri Lankan food may be as easy to find as anything cooked alla Milanese (battered and fried). In fact, the only meal that may elude you is ''The Last Supper.''</p>
        <p>Friday</p>
        <p>4 p.m.  1. Top Design  Milan is all about design, and until July 1 the Palazzo Reale, a museum in the city's center (Piazza Duomo, 12; 39-02-875-672; www.comune.milano.it/palazzoreale), has a terrific exhibition of Italian furniture from 1900 to 2000. The show, ''Rooms With a View,'' offers an eye-catching primer on the sometimes surreal styles that have made Milan the global center of furniture design. If you aren't already a devotee of, say, Futurism or Memphis, you will be by the time you leave the building. Admission is 9 euros, or about $12.40 at $1.38 to the euro.</p>
        <p>5:30 p.m.  2. James Bond Meets Armani  Now that you know where Italian design has been, see where it's going, at the shops nearby along the Via Alessandro Manzoni. The brightest include Sawaya &amp; Maroni (No. 11; 39-02-8639-5218; www.sawayamoroni.com) for furniture and lighting by Zaha Hadid, the Pritzker Prize-winning architect who shuns right angles. Just a few blocks away is the Bulgari Hotel (Via Privata Fratelli Gabba, 7B; 39-02- 805-8051; www.bulgarihotels.com ), which, thanks to another star architect, Antonio Citterio, is the type of place where James Bond and Giorgio Armani might meet for a martini. (Call ahead to get past the front gate.) Share a caprese (mozzarella with tomatoes and basil, served with a delicious eggplant purée) for 15 euros.</p>
        <p>8 p.m.  3. Tuscany in Milan  Brera is one of the city's quaintest neighborhoods, and La Torre di Pisa (Italian for the Leaning Tower of Pisa) is one of Brera's quaintest restaurants, a Tuscan-style trattoria that's always packed (Via Fiori Chiari 21/5; 39-02-874-877). You can't go wrong with the wonderfully spicy spaghetti alla puttanesca (10 euros) and the Robespierre, a hot platter of sliced Fiorentina steak, potatoes and vegetables (52 euros for two). After dinner, stroll Brera's lovely streets, many of which are cobblestone and closed to traffic.</p>
        <p>10 p.m.  4. Freaking It Up  The Metro may stop running and taxis are hard to get, but the Milanese don't let that stop them from enjoying the city's abundant night life. Nor should you. Try the cocktails at Living, a chic, black-painted lounge with huge windows facing the lush Parco Sempione (Piazza Sempione, 2; 39-02-3310-0824; www.livingmilano.com). If you're in the mood for some boogeying, stroll a few doors down to the Freak Bar (Via Agostino Bertani, 16; 39-02-331-4726; www.freakbar.it).</p>
        <p>Saturday</p>
        <p>10 a.m.  5. Till You Drop  Prada, Dolce &amp; Gabbana and Bulgari. You may have bought them at your local mall, but it's time to pay homage at the mother ships along Via Della Spiga. The store designs are often stunning, like the upside-down interior at Viktor &amp; Rolf (Via Sant'Andrea, 14; 39-02-796-091; www.viktor-rolf.com), with chandeliers rising from the floor and chairs hung from the ceiling. Don't miss it. A short cab ride away is another retail strip, Corso Como, anchored by 10 Corso Como (39-02-2900-2674; www.10corsocomo.it), a fabled boutique where you can watch customers fight over 300-euro tank tops. You'll fare better at its nearby outlet store (Via Tazzoli, 3), where relative sanity prevails: a gray T-shirt by Alexander McQueen was marked down on a recent visit to a mere 100 euros. For labels that nobody has heard of (yet), sneak over to Via Maroncelli, where you'll find some of the city's most innovative furniture and fashion stores like Galleria M. K. (No. 2; 39-02-655-1035; www.galleriamk.com), Labo.Art (No. 14; 39-02-365-23461; www.laboart.com) and Shopping Lifts Spirit (No. 3; 39-02-290-63125).</p>
        <p>1 p.m.  6. Haute Cuisine  Hungry from all the shopping? Head to Giorgio Armani's personal mall, which fills an entire block (Via Alessandro Manzoni, 31; 02-39-7231-8600; www.armani.com). In addition to the requisite Armani clothing stores, look for Armani Libri (books), Armani Dolci (chocolates), Armani Nobu (Japanese food) and, for an unforgettable lunch, Caffè Emporio Armani. The second-floor restaurant serves artistically arranged dishes like seared tuna with toasted almonds and mustard ice cream (25 euros). You'll find yourself -- as is everyone around you -- taking pictures of the food before you eat it. If you arrive by 1 p.m., there will be plenty of tables; by 2 p.m., there won't be any.</p>
        <p>2:30 p.m.  7. Date With a Masterpiece  Tickets to see Leonardo's ''Last Supper,'' in a refectory at Santa Maria delle Grazie (39-02-8942-1146; www.cenacolovinciano.org), sell out months in advance. To protect the painting from excess humidity, the number of visitors is strictly limited. Luckily, the tour company Zani Viaggi (39-02-867-131; www.zaniviaggi.it) will get you in to see it for the price of a 50-euro tour. A guide will walk you to Milan's twin centerpieces: the Duomo, among the largest cathedrals in the world (and very possibly the most beautiful), and the Galleria Vittorio Emanuele, an astonishing glass-covered arcade built in 1867. Your appointment with Leonardo's masterpiece is at 5:30 p.m. The electronic doors open precisely at that time, and again 15 minutes later to let you out. The 50 euros will seem like a bargain -- unless you were saving up for that McQueen T-shirt.</p>
        <p>8 p.m.  8. Bring Your Opera Glasses  It's curtain time at La Scala (Piazza della Scala; 39-02-7200-3744; www.teatroallascala.org), the most fabled opera house in the world. For a seat on the orchestra level, expect to spend a fortune. But a 66-euro perch, on a row near the ornately painted ceiling, offers a passable view. Wear formal attire; you're there for glamour, and you have to do your part. The inside of the theater was recently renovated by the Swiss architect Mario Botta, prompting some criticism because a circular addition competes with the original facade. Happily, the interior is pretty much unchanged from 1778.</p>
        <p>10:30 p.m.  9. Dining Under Glass  For some of the best people and architecture watching in Milan, cross the street from La Scala to the Galleria Vittorio Emanuele, where an outdoor table at Biffi (No. 92; 39-02-805-7961; www.biffigalleria.it) puts you under the great glass dome. Order a glass of wine, ignore the nearby McDonald's and marvel at the 19th-century details you missed earlier in the day, including the astonishing frescoes and caryatids overhead. The osso buco with risotto Milanese isn't bad either (26 euros). After dinner, follow the crowds in any direction until you find a great gelato.</p>
        <p>Sunday</p>
        <p>10 a.m.  10. Hello, Young Lovers  To see Milanese at leisure, walk to the sprawling Parco Sempione, north of the Duomo. There you'll find soccer players, skateboarders, joggers and couples in deep embrace. Stroll farther north until you see the Arco della Pace, an early 19th-century triumphal arch that commemorates Napoleon's victories (it faces Paris). Then circle back to the Torre Branca, a bullet-shaped tower at the park's edge that was designed by the Italian architect Gio Ponti in the 1930s. Three euros buys a ticket to the 300-foot-high observatory, which offers views of the Duomo below and, on a clear day, the Alps.</p>
        <p>11:30 a.m.  11. Venice in Milan  Ride a taxi (or, better yet, a bicycle) to the Navigli, a fascinating neighborhood bordered by two canals, which were planned in part by Leonardo da Vinci and were central to Milanese commerce until the mid-20th century. The more picturesque of the two canals is the Naviglio Grande. If it is the last Sunday of the month, a flea market will line the waterway, but even if it's not, you'll revel in what feels like the trendiest neighborhood -- in Venice. There are many fascinating shops, including Nipper (Ripa di Pta. Ticinese, 69; 39-02-837-6947), which sells mid-20th-century clocks, telephones and other gizmos.</p>
        <p>1 p.m.  12. Your Last Meal  Make your way to Kitchen (Via Scarlatti, 7; 39-02-2951-3679), a terrific Italian restaurant with an Asian staff (an increasingly common sight in a city that imports much of its labor). Serve yourself from the cold antipasto bar; a plate piled high with shrimp, calamari and succulent cooked vegetables is just 5.50 euros. Afterward, walk up the street to Milan's Central Station, an over-the-top, Mussolini-era building. It's a must-see, even if you're not leaving by train.</p>
        <p>THE BASICS</p>
        <p>Many major airlines have service between New York to Milan, starting at $1,075 round trip for travel in mid-July. The 40-minute train ride from Malpensa airport to Milan's Cadorna station (11 euros, or about $15.20 at $1.38 to the euro) couldn't be easier. Once in town, buy a 10-ride pass (9.20 euros) for the efficient Metro and bus system. Or try two wheels. Milan is a great city for cycling; it's compact and as flat as a tiramisù. Noleggio, near the train station (Via Ponte Seveso, 33; 39-02-6707-2145; awsbici@fastnetweb.it), rents mountain bikes for 11 euros a day.</p>
        <p>The Hotel Andreola (Via Scarlatti, 24; 39-02-670-9141; www.andreolahotel.it), on a quiet street near Central Station, is a steal. Rooms are small, but service is expansive. Doubles from 119 euros.</p>
        <p>The Park Hyatt Hotel (Via Tommaso Grossi, 1; 39-02-882-11234; www.milan.park.hyatt.com) is just a few feet from the tourist-packed Duomo and, yet, thanks to its courtyard design, feels utterly secluded. Doubles from 510 euros.  36 HOURS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
