<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Like Father?</title>
    <meta content="17lives.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="74" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/magazine/17lives-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854919"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Lives"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Korean-Americans</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woo, Sun J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E5DC173FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Like Father?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Like Father?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sung J. Woo</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Woo, Sun J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sun J Woo article on his distant relationship with his father, who brought family to America after failure of his once-booming business in South Korea (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a little while, my father had it all: a loving wife, three healthy kids and a booming import-export business in Seoul that brought in so much cash that the president of Korea awarded him a medal of achievement. But then the gas crisis of 1973 bankrupted his company, and a year later he left my mother, sisters and me for the United States to regain his financial footing. He knew it wouldn't be easy, but he had some old contacts and a brother in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a little while, my father had it all: a loving wife, three healthy kids and a booming import-export business in Seoul.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For a little while, my father had it all: a loving wife, three healthy kids and a booming import-export business in Seoul that brought in so much cash that the president of Korea awarded him a medal of achievement. But then the gas crisis of 1973 bankrupted his company, and a year later he left my mother, sisters and me for the United States to regain his financial footing. He knew it wouldn't be easy, but he had some old contacts and a brother in New York.</p>
        <p>Seven long years later, our family was finally going to be reunited. As we made our final approach to Newark Airport, my mother reassured me that my inability to remember my father was not a big deal. I'd just turned 4 when he left, but it still bothered me that I had no recollection of him at all.</p>
        <p>After passing through customs, we walked toward a crowd of eager people waiting behind cordons of velvet rope. I scanned one face after another, wondering if I'd missed him somehow, and then suddenly he was there, the man I'd seen in photographs.</p>
        <p>He'd grown older and fatter, that much was obvious. But there was something else too, in the way he held himself. As he waited for us to reach him, he smiled and crossed his arms.</p>
        <p>''Hello, son,'' he said, shaking my hand.</p>
        <p>The last seven years had been an incredible struggle for him. He'd muddled through the basics of the English language, but he was still functionally illiterate. To make matters worse, he was staying illegally in the country with an expired visa, living under the constant threat of immediate deportation.</p>
        <p>Despite these difficulties, he set up an Oriental gift shop near the Jersey Shore with the help of his brother. I realize now that I should have been proud of his accomplishments, but back then I was deeply disappointed. We'd left behind all that we knew, and for what? A dingy two-bedroom apartment where I slept on a pullout couch; work after school and on the weekends, at a store where the ceiling leaked every time it rained. Why were we here?</p>
        <p>''Because,'' my mother said, ''we're a family. And families stick together.''</p>
        <p>There was much sticking during that first year. In those family photo albums from Korea, there were a large number of my father fishing in freestone rivers for sogari, the mandarin fish, and now, on our days off from the store, we drove to the piers of Long Branch and fished. While my mother and sisters set out our lunch, my father taught me the mechanics of hooking worms and casting lines, and I pretended to care. For me, fishing, with its endless waiting, was the distillation of boredom. And every time we came back without a catch, I saw my father again as a failure.</p>
        <p>As it turned out, I didn't have to wait long for these family fishing trips to end, because my father came down with kidney disease the following year. The solution was home dialysis, which meant attaching a permanent catheter to his midsection. Every four hours, he emptied out his makeshift bladder into a bag. He tried to fish after recovering from surgery, but he tired quickly and soon gave it up altogether.</p>
        <p>His doctors gave him 10 years to live, and for most of those years, my father made it easy for me to dislike him. Like many older Asian men, he was by and large emotionally distant. We never had a single conversation of consequence. I have no idea how he came to love Japanese food, and I doubt he knew which baseball team I followed. We never once hugged.</p>
        <p>When I was away at college, we hardly spoke. The few times we did, it was about business, student-loan rates and tuition bills. Strangely enough, the distance had a positive effect on the way I viewed my father. Before college, our relationship existed solely through the silence of our eyes. I saw him read the newspaper and he saw me in front of the television, but now that I was away, I began to consider him with perspective. I started to feel sympathy for him, for his rise to greatness and his fall to oblivion. He'd gone through a lot, and soon his life would be over.</p>
        <p>Still, we remained a mystery to each other. Certainly it wasn't for a lack of opportunities. Twice a month I drove down to their apartment for dinner, and after the meal, while my mother washed the dishes and cleaned the kitchen, my father and I sat on the sofa. Sometimes we watched television; sometimes he read the paper. There was no reason that I couldn't have tried to start a real conversation -- asked him a question I asked people every day: ''How are you doing?''</p>
        <p>But I never did. I didn't do it when he was healthy; I didn't do it when he was on his hospital bed before he died. And I have no idea what he might have said.</p>
        <p>Lives Sung J. Woo lives in New Jersey and has recently completed his first novel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Sung J. Woo lives in New Jersey and has recently completed his first novel.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
