<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The New Lady Chatterley: Sober, Sensual, French</title>
    <meta content="17lim" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/movies/17lim.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854965"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lim, Dennis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lawrence, D H (David Herbert) (1885-1930)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ferran, Pascale</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Lady Chatterley (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Lady Chatterley's Lover (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals/Tribeca Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tribeca Film Festival (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tribeca Film Festival (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tribeca Film Festival (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Lawrence, D H</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Lady Chatterley (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E4D7173FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1683" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The New Lady Chatterley: Sober, Sensual, French</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The New Lady Chatterley: Sober, Sensual, French</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNIS LIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lim, Dennis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on new French film of D H Lawrence's novel Lady Chatterley's Lover, directed by Pascale Ferran; differences between this version and previous ones discussed; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE years have not been kind to Lady Chatterley. Nor for that matter have the movies. Scandalous in her day, the sexual adventuress of D. H. Lawrence's best-known novel has matured into something of a pop-culture joke, remembered less as a symbol of erotic liberation than a soft-core staple of late-night cable.</p>
        <p>Notwithstanding an early, relatively staid 1955 French adaptation, starring Danielle Darrieux and made while the book was still contraband in the United States and Britain, film versions of ''Lady Chatterley's Lover'' have favored the heavy-breathing, bodice-busting approach to period romance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The latest film version of “Lady Chatterley” is D. H. Lawrence without the heavy breathing and the bodice ripping.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE years have not been kind to Lady Chatterley. Nor for that matter have the movies. Scandalous in her day, the sexual adventuress of D. H. Lawrence's best-known novel has matured into something of a pop-culture joke, remembered less as a symbol of erotic liberation than a soft-core staple of late-night cable.</p>
        <p>Notwithstanding an early, relatively staid 1955 French adaptation, starring Danielle Darrieux and made while the book was still contraband in the United States and Britain, film versions of ''Lady Chatterley's Lover'' have favored the heavy-breathing, bodice-busting approach to period romance.</p>
        <p>The British provocateur Ken Russell, who had successfully tackled Lawrence with his film ''Women in Love'' in 1969, directed a sudsy ''Chatterley'' mini-series for the BBC in 1993. Trashier still was a 1981 version that featured Sylvia Kristel, the leggy star of the popular ''Emmanuelle'' films. There have been Japanese and Italian renditions; the '70s soft-core craze even produced a contemporary spinoff, ''Young Lady Chatterley.''</p>
        <p>The newest ''Chatterley'' -- a nearly three-hour French-language adaptation, directed by Pascale Ferran -- effectively wipes the slate clean. ''Lady Chatterley,'' which opens Friday, is both sober and sensual, not just a world away from the high-toned smut of its predecessors but also, in its directness and simplicity, an anomaly in the elaborately ornamented genre of the costume drama. In France it has won widespread critical acclaim and five César Awards.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ferran's film is based not on the definitive ''Lady Chatterley's Lover,'' which Lawrence published himself in Italy in 1928, but on an earlier version of the novel. He wrote it three times in two years, while suffering from the tuberculosis that killed him in 1930. All three versions concern the intense affair between a frustrated young aristocrat and her virile gamekeeper, but the second ''Chatterley,'' the one Ms. Ferran has adapted, is not as polemical as the third. The class differences between the lovers are more pronounced, but the lovers themselves are less inclined to subject their relationship to anguished analysis.</p>
        <p>The signal quality of Ms. Ferran's ''Lady Chatterley,'' as implied by its abbreviated title, is the sharpened focus on the heroine, Constance (played by Marina Hands). The first ''Chatterley'' film directed by a woman, it is also the only one that, in its contemplative way, honors Lawrence's radical ambitions. His biographer John Worthen notes that Lawrence considered ''Lady Chatterley's Lover'' ''a bit of a bomb'' and described it in positively anarchic terms: ''Let's hope it'll explode and let in some air.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ferran argues for the continued relevance of Lawrence's stance. ''The book is no longer scandalous today,'' she said in an interview in April, while in New York for the Tribeca Film Festival. ''But its view of sexuality is still in the extreme minority. It's on the side of joy and the flourishing of the body. It considers sexuality without guilt, which is completely opposite to the puritanism of Lawrence's time and also to the neo-puritanism, so to speak, of our time.''</p>
        <p>''Lady Chatterley's Lover'' occupies an awkward place in the history of modern sexual consciousness. The first legal publication of an unexpurgated edition in the United States in 1959, and in Britain the following year after a landmark obscenity trial, coincided with the dawn of the sexual revolution. Philip Larkin's famous verse about sex beginning in 1963 -- ''Between the end of the Chatterley ban/And the Beatles' first LP'' -- reinforces the connection. But changing attitudes led to the declining reputation of the book and its author.</p>
        <p>''In the '60s Lawrence was all the rage,'' said Sarah Cole, who teaches English at Columbia University and specializes in 20th-century British literature. ''By the end of the '70s that status had begun to change, thanks mostly to feminist reappraisals of his work. 'Lady Chatterley's Lover' was once viewed as a revolutionary story of sexual liberation but came to be seen as a troubling story of female subservience.'' Ms. Ferran discovered Lawrence via an essay by the French philosopher Gilles Deleuze. She made her way through the major novels while preparing another film a few years ago.</p>
        <p>Shortly after that project foundered she came upon the second version of ''Chatterley'' and, she said, ''fell in love instantly.'' Published in French as ''Lady Chatterley and the Man in the Woods'' and in English as ''John Thomas and Lady Jane'' (the lovers' pet names for their genitals), that version had, she thought, aged better than the third.</p>
        <p>The attraction to Lawrence is in keeping with Ms. Ferran's generation of filmmakers. She is part of a loose collective -- Arnaud Desplechin (''Kings and Queen'') is the best known -- who attended Idhec (Institute des Hautes Études Cinématographiques) film school in Paris and have occasionally worked together.</p>
        <p>''It's a very particular generation,'' said Emmanuel Burdeau, editor in chief of the influential journal Cahiers du Cinéma, which ranked ''Lady Chatterley'' as its No. 4 film of 2006. ''They share an admiration for Anglo-American literature and an intellectual approach to cinema combined with the belief that it is possible to gain success without making any concessions. François Truffaut remains the model: an artist who was able to attract an audience.''</p>
        <p>''Lady Chatterley'' is only Ms. Ferran's third film in a dozen years. She won the Camera d'Or prize for best first feature at the 1994 Cannes Film Festival for ''Coming to Terms With the Dead'' (and returned to the festival last month as jury president of the Certain Regard section) but in the years since, apart from a 1996 television movie, has failed to get projects off the ground. The difficulty of financing a certain kind of French movie -- the so-called auteur film -- was something she addressed in February at the César ceremony, in a fiercely eloquent speech, which became national news, denouncing the present system as a ''betrayal'' of the French cinematic heritage.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ferran's decision to adapt ''Chatterley'' stemmed from her realization that the story could still pose a challenge to convention. ''It would not be a shocking film, but it would remain transgressive,'' she said. ''Lawrence's view that sexuality is not shameful, that it's part of life -- you would think that these issues have been resolved, but if you look at films today, the modern tendency is to show an animalistic sexuality. This representation puts desire on the side of destruction and death. It separates the issue of sexuality from the issue of feeling. It disassociates the mind and the body.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Burdeau said that the movie's tone of calm affirmation was what set it apart. ''One had been used for so many years to seeing films that dealt hysterically with 'desire' and 'the body' that this came as both a joy and a relief,'' he said. '' 'Lady Chatterley' is a film that says yes, but in a very smooth and self-assured way.''</p>
        <p>For a film about torrid passions ''Lady Chatterley'' is often curiously placid. It takes in the material presence of bodies and the rhythms of the natural world with a meditative alertness that bears little resemblance to Lawrence's loquacious pantheism. ''The novel has a restless verbal energy that is entirely occluded here,'' Ms. Cole said. ''There is something lovely and rich in this silent world, but it is not particularly Lawrentian.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ferran's almost Buddhist approach can be traced to a film that she called her ''guiding light'': ''Blissfully Yours'' (2002), by the Thai director Apichatpong Weerasethakul. Little seen but revered by cinephiles, Mr. Weerasethakul's film is a serene, enigmatic reverie that, like ''Lady Chatterley,'' features several uninhibited instances of alfresco sex in verdant settings.</p>
        <p>The half-dozen sex scenes in ''Lady Chatterley'' -- all intricately choreographed, some unfolding almost in real time -- serve as milestones in the portrait of a relationship. Each one provides an insight into the mind-set of the characters. Before the shoot Ms. Ferran rehearsed extensively with her lead actors, Ms. Hands and Jean-Louis Coulloc'h, who plays the gamekeeper Parkin, paying special attention to the mechanics of the intimate scenes.</p>
        <p>''All three of us were very prudish,'' she said. ''To remove that petrifying fear, we worked through the sex scenes as if they were important dialogue scenes, but with gestures replacing words.''</p>
        <p>To get her actors comfortable with physical contact, she also had them work with a butoh dancer. ''They would act like animals or play with their bodies,'' she said. ''It was useful, and it also introduced humor into the situation.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ferran's sex scenes are arguably an improvement on Lawrence's; for starters there's a lot less talking. She also deftly handles Lawrence's obsession with the phallus -- his preferred term was ''godhead'' -- in a moment that shifts the emphasis from male worship to female pleasure. After a few fully clothed fumbles, the couple spend their first night together, and as they disrobe by candlelight, Constance gently but firmly asks for a full frontal view of her lover.</p>
        <p>''That scene for me is about the birth of intimacy,'' Ms. Ferran said. ''The night before, they're two human beings. The next morning, they're a couple. It was important to capture the advent of the gaze, when one dares to look at the other. When a young woman sees an erect penis for the first time, it's an event.''</p>
        <p>Discreetly stripped of Lawrence's more antiquated ideas, Ms. Ferran's ''Chatterley'' seems to take its cue from one of his alternate titles for the book: ''Tenderness.'' ''For all the joy of sexual awakening and fulfillment, the novel is really very dark, very embittered, in some ways very sad,'' Ms. Cole said. ''The film by contrast seems exuberant. The atmosphere, physical and psychological, is much healthier and happier than what we find in the novel.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ferran said she was compelled to underscore the utopian aspect: ''It's the most beautiful love story in the world because it's the most revolutionary.'' But more than anything, she said, she had hoped to conjure the novel's elemental power.</p>
        <p>''It's a story everybody recognizes,'' she said. ''It's almost a founding myth. But when you read the book, you have the impression that this is the first time it's being told.'' She added, ''I thought maybe I could make a film that felt like that.''</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
