<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now; First-Family Values</title>
    <meta content="17wwln--lede.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854929"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Traub, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, Laura</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E4DC173FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="998" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now; First-Family Values</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By James Traub</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Traub, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>James Traub says this season's candidates for president have marriages and marital histories that mirror those of most Americans, unlike George and Laura Bush, whose marriage seems like throwback to days of The Dick Van Dyke Show; says it is not too much to hope that different kind of first family could blur sharp line of red-blue antagonism over 'family values'; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's a good bet that whoever moves into the White House in January 2009 will offer the American people a more contemporary tableau of family life than the one we have witnessed for the last six years. George and Laura Bush seem to be an admirably well-suited and loving couple, the very model of a first family (minus a few untoward events involving the kids). They're a throwback couple, like Rob and Laura Petrie from ''The Dick Van Dyke Show'' -- one amiable and slightly buffoonish, the other tolerant and wryly exasperated. The fictional Laura (played by Mary Tyler Moore) was a lot goofier than the real one; but each knew her place, which was in the home, by the side of her man.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's a good bet that whoever moves into the White House in January 2009 will offer the American people a more contemporary tableau of family life than the one we have witnessed for the last six years. George and Laura Bush seem to be an admirably well-suited and loving couple, the very model of a first family (minus a few untoward events involving the kids). They're a throwback couple, like Rob and Laura Petrie from ''The Dick Van Dyke Show'' -- one amiable and slightly buffoonish, the other tolerant and wryly exasperated. The fictional Laura (played by Mary Tyler Moore) was a lot goofier than the real one; but each knew her place, which was in the home, by the side of her man.</p>
        <p>The kind of high-achieving people who vie to run the Western democracies nowadays tend to have marriages with a more complex dynamic. Some have quasi marriages or even nonmarriages: the recent presidential election in France pitted a man whose wife had apparently abandoned him for a fling against a woman who hasn't married the father of her children. A complex union does not, of course, have to be a fractious one. Tony and Cherie Blair seem as loving and well suited as the Bushes, but in her role as attorney, Cherie Booth, as she is still known professionally, sued her husband's government a few years back over regulations governing parental leave. The British, accustomed to stultifying propriety in the role of first spouse, were shocked, but they seem to have gotten over it.</p>
        <p>Americans, of course, recoiled from their own version of the First Power Couple, at least until Hillary Clinton learned to channel the spirit of Betty Crocker. The Bushes offered a return to an increasingly abnormal ''normalcy.'' Indeed, among the current crop of candidates for 2008, only a few conform to the Rob and Laura model (though none, perhaps thankfully, to the Nicolas and Cecilia Sarkozy model). Among the Republicans, John McCain is divorced and remarried, while Rudy Giuliani has been divorced and remarried twice. The uxorious ex-mayor told Barbara Walters that his new wife, Judith, would sit in on the cabinet meetings of a Giuliani administration ''if she wanted to'' and would be involved in the formulation of policy ''to the extent she wants to be.'' Meanwhile, Fred Thompson, who cut a wide swath through Washington in his single days, and Newt Gingrich, a veteran of two divorces and three marriages, seem prepared to join the race over the next few months.</p>
        <p>The Democratic field, meanwhile, offers highly educated baby boomers who married their equals in talent and professional ambition -- the Tony and Cherie model. (Perhaps we have a new red-blue typology here -- Multiply Married vs. Power Couple.) We are, of course, intimately familiar with the epic soap opera that is Bill and Hillary (or rather, in its new incarnation, Hillary and Bill). But there was always something archaic about the episodes involving a philandering husband and a wife waving the frying pan. The sleek, high-octane Barack and Michelle Obama come much closer to a contemporary ideal; the fact that they are black carries the additional message that race is no longer an absolute bar even to the most elevated cultural status. And we can only hope that, should John Edwards become president, his wife, Elizabeth, afflicted with Stage 4 cancer, has the chance to show that cancer does not necessarily preclude leading a full, fearless life.</p>
        <p>Strictly for entertainment value, any of these couples, or even noncouples, should be preferable to George and Laura and Barney. But of course in this country, unlike almost anywhere in Europe, the first family plays a larger and more solemn role. The occupants of the White House are traditionally taken to incarnate some kind of social ideal. And that ideal is almost inherently an archaic one, since the presidency itself is one of the original institutions of the republic, and we have come to invest in it something of the awe due to royalty. American women have grown accustomed to juggling work and home, while American men have had to grudgingly cede the lord-and-master role their fathers had taken for granted; but in George and Laura's White House, it's still 1960. We may not have a Cherie Booth in 2009, but it's a safe bet that Bill Clinton won't be publishing his chocolate-chip-cookie recipe should he become first spouse; and Judith Giuliani, minister without portfolio, would offer quite a decisive contrast to her predecessor.</p>
        <p>Divorce, of course, is old hat. Ronald Reagan had one, and he still provided as debonair and chivalrous an image of comportment as John F. Kennedy. But Reagan seemed unmarked by life; so, too, the Bushes, who appear to have emerged high and dry from the waves of social change that have washed over the American family in the last few generations. Those many Americans who have been knocked around by life (43 percent of first marriages end in divorce within 15 years) might appreciate a White House couple with a few dents and dings. Ruefulness is a virtue too little appreciated in politics. Fred Thompson has something of that battered countenance, though we may learn that looks can be deceiving. And Elizabeth Edwards offers the wisdom of the twice-born: even before her cancer recurred, she seemed to emanate lived experience.</p>
        <p>I don't think it's too much to hope that a different kind of first family could also blur the sharp line of red-blue antagonism. The endless fight over ''values'' always seems to pit two idealized states against each other -- the prelapsarian world of ''the intact family'' against the liberatory culture of ''the '60s.'' Who actually lives in one of these worlds -- besides the current tenants of the White House? Wouldn't it be to our benefit to scramble those boundaries? If someone's going to argue for prayer in the schools, let it be a twice-divorced Catholic president -- or, for that matter, an urbane and worldly black first couple.</p>
        <p>James Traub, a contributing writer, last wrote for the magazine about Al Gore</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">James Traub, a contributing writer, last wrote for the magazine about Al Gore</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
