<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Funny Pages III: Sunday Serial; Doors Open: Chapter 6: The New Mike</title>
    <meta content="17funny--serial.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/magazine/17funny-serial-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854915"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="The Funny Pages | Sunday Serial"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rankin, Ian</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Doors Open (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E5DC173FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2577" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Funny Pages III: Sunday Serial; Doors Open: Chapter 6: The New Mike</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">‘Doors Open’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ian Rankin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rankin, Ian</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chapter 6 of Ian Rankin's novel Doors Open; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It occurred to Allan Cruikshank that the reason he made a good banker was that he was intrinsically boring. He had never taken a risk in his life. This meant he was cautious and prudent, and therefore good at not losing his clients' money. But banking had also made him cynical. It was a truism that those who already had money would find it easy to increase their wealth, and they never seemed very grateful for Allan's work on their (often unmerited) behalf. Some of the High Net Worth individuals on his books owned three or four homes, yachts, racehorses, private islands and numerous works of art. Yet they seemed to appreciate very little, being too busy amassing yet more. He found them dull and blinkered, and wondered if they thought of him the same way. Then there were his fellow account executives at First Caledonian Bank, some of whom hardly registered his existence. The chief executive had met him a dozen times, yet never seemed to remember him. With a drink in one hand and a canapé in the other, he would regale Allan time and again with the same anecdote, while Allan smiled and tried to sound interested throughout and surprised by the predictable punch line.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This week, Chapter 6: It occurred to Allan Cruikshank that the reason he made a good banker was that he was intrinsically boring</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It occurred to Allan Cruikshank that the reason he made a good banker was that he was intrinsically boring. He had never taken a risk in his life. This meant he was cautious and prudent, and therefore good at not losing his clients' money. But banking had also made him cynical. It was a truism that those who already had money would find it easy to increase their wealth, and they never seemed very grateful for Allan's work on their (often unmerited) behalf. Some of the High Net Worth individuals on his books owned three or four homes, yachts, racehorses, private islands and numerous works of art. Yet they seemed to appreciate very little, being too busy amassing yet more. He found them dull and blinkered, and wondered if they thought of him the same way. Then there were his fellow account executives at First Caledonian Bank, some of whom hardly registered his existence. The chief executive had met him a dozen times, yet never seemed to remember him. With a drink in one hand and a canapé in the other, he would regale Allan time and again with the same anecdote, while Allan smiled and tried to sound interested throughout and surprised by the predictable punch line.</p>
        <p>I want something he can't have, Allan thought to himself. I want something none of my feckless clients could ever own.</p>
        <p>But he didn't want to go to jail.</p>
        <p>These past few nights, he had been waking in a sweat, adrenaline shuddering through him. How many years would he serve for his part in the scheme? Would it all be worthwhile for just a couple of handsome paintings -- paintings he could never show to anyone, never boast about to clients, colleagues, boss? Then again, his ex-wife had chided him for years that he was dull. His conversation was dull, his cooking was dull, his dress sense was dull.</p>
        <p>And his lovemaking, too.</p>
        <p>When she moved out, he realized he loved her. But by then she had found a new man, a younger model who wore black lamb's-wool polo-necks and a smugly permanent half-smile. This didn't keep Allan from calling her every few days for a catch-up, suggesting lunch at various trendy bistros. She seemed to have been already wined and dined at each of them.</p>
        <p>Well, there was one thing Allan could do that Mr. Lamb's-Wool couldn't: Pull off the perfect crime. Which was why, despite the sweats and bad dreams and queasiness in his daytime gut, he was determined to go ahead with the heist.</p>
        <p>''Sure?'' Mike asked him as they climbed the stairs to Westie's top-floor apartment.</p>
        <p>''Positive,'' Allan replied, hoping he had convinced his friend.</p>
        <p>They stood for a moment outside Westie's door, catching their breath, eyes locked on each other. Then Mike gave a slow nod before ringing the bell, and Allan went back to the important job of controlling his heart-rate. Westie, however, looked more nervous than either of them, something Mike was quick to point out.</p>
        <p>''Your fault,'' the student snapped back. ''Know how much sleep I've had this past week? I'm running on caffeine, cigarettes and the odd Bloody Mary.''</p>
        <p>''Tabasco or Worcestershire Sauce?'' Allan asked. Westie just glared at him. They were in the living room by now. It smelled of fresh paint, varnish, wood. Westie had used old wood where possible for the stretchers -- no need for frames, they would be swapping them on the day. Where old wood hadn't been available, he had stained new wood with several coats of instant coffee.</p>
        <p>''Works like a charm,'' he explained. He actually seemed prouder of this than of the copied paintings themselves, but as Allan studied them, he could see they were marvelous, and this was the very word he uttered, Mike making a noise of agreement while Westie just shrugged.</p>
        <p>''Told you I could do it,'' he said, lighting a cigarette from the butt of an old one. He gave a hacking cough, and pushed the hair back from his eyes.</p>
        <p>''You need a lie-down,'' Mike told him.</p>
        <p>''Try stopping me,'' Westie snorted.</p>
        <p>''Just as soon,'' Mike continued, ''as you've done No. 8.''</p>
        <p>Westie glowered. ''We said seven.''</p>
        <p>''Another shareholder has come on board.''</p>
        <p>The two of them began to argue, Allan watching in silent appraisal of Mike. His friend had changed, had grown into the role he was now playing -- deal maker, tough guy, criminal. Maybe he had been spending too much time with Chib Calloway, but Allan thought it went further. Mike was enjoying himself, for the first time in an age. The electricity that surged through Allan's body was surging through Mike's too, but to very different effect. Mike was ready for anything.</p>
        <p>A tall man, Mike had always had a slightly round-shouldered posture, as if embarrassed by his size. But now he was more comfortable, shoulders back, spine stiffened. He made eye contact more readily and spoke slowly but with authority. This was what he was like in business, Allan thought. This was how he got where he was. Which meant that selling the company had brought Mike cash, but only at the cost of his vigor. Problem was, Allan liked this new Mike a little less. In the past, they had gossiped like fishwives, telling jokes and sharing anecdotes. Now it seemed the heist was their only currency. And afterward -- was it likely to galvanize their friendship or drive a wedge into it? Allan was almost afraid to ask. So he watched and listened instead and wondered about Chib Calloway. He had argued against the gangster's involvement until giving in to the combined will of Mike and the professor. Still, he knew it was a mistake.</p>
        <p>Mike had brought photocopied sheets with him, detailing the paintings whose replicas were now lined up on separate easels in front of them. Gissing would give final approval -- he, after all, was the expert -- but Mike wanted to check that Westie hadn't been tempted to add any flourishes to the forgeries: no soft-drink cans or airplanes tucked into a corner of the canvas.</p>
        <p>''These are good,'' Mike said. Westie accepted the reiterated praise with a slight bow, and Allan knew the artist would complete the necessary eighth canvas. Mike had brought along five possibles, cherry-picked by Gissing as being valuable but obscure and relatively easy to copy. Westie was sifting through the photos of the candidates.</p>
        <p>''I like this,'' he said, waving one toward Mike.</p>
        <p>''Whichever's easiest,'' Mike replied. Then to Allan: ''What do you think?''</p>
        <p>Allan was caught unawares by the question. ''Think?'' he echoed.</p>
        <p>''About these.'' Mike jabbed a hand toward the easels.</p>
        <p>''Marvelous,'' Allan could only repeat, studying the canvases and aware of Mike's eyes on him. But then he caught a movement and straightened up.</p>
        <p>''What the -- ''</p>
        <p>''Smile for the birdie.'' Allan heard the voice of a young woman. She was standing in the doorway, a video camera aimed into the room.</p>
        <p>''Who's this?'' Mike asked Westie.</p>
        <p>''This is Alice.'' But it was the young woman who answered. She was lowering the camera now. ''And you're Mike and Allan. Thing is, you know Westie, know his full name, where he lives . . . and he knows almost nothing about you.''</p>
        <p>Mike looked at Westie. ''Anything you've not told your girlfriend?''</p>
        <p>''Why would he keep a secret from me?'' She sauntered into the room, making a show of perusing the paintings before pecking Westie on the cheek. ''So, so talented.'' She turned to Mike. ''The camera's by way of insurance: our way of making sure we're all in this together.''</p>
        <p>''We?'' Mike couldn't help echoing.</p>
        <p>''I'm just looking out for Westie's best interests,'' Alice said.</p>
        <p>''I know you,'' Allan stated quietly. ''I've seen you at the Filmhouse.''</p>
        <p>She acknowledged this with a smile but was not to be deflected. ''Westie says you offered him a cash payment. As you can see, he's earned every penny. He also -- against my wishes -- wants to play a part in the raid, and for that you'll give him a painting. Is that how you understand it?''</p>
        <p>''You want it in writing?''</p>
        <p>She shook her head. ''But something up front would seem to be in order . . . shall we say 12 and a half?''</p>
        <p>Mike patted his pockets. ''I don't seem to have that sort of cash on me.''</p>
        <p>''You could write a check, but that would mean us knowing your surname.'' Her smile now was full of mischief. Mike's face hardened, and he slipped his hands into his pockets. Allan could imagine the right hand curling into a fist. When Mike spoke, his voice was an ominous monotone.</p>
        <p>''I can get you the money, but I'd want something in exchange.''</p>
        <p>''This?'' Alice guessed, waving the camera. Mike nodded slowly. ''It's a nice piece of kit,'' she said, examining it. ''Not sure I could bear to part with it.''</p>
        <p>''Your decision,'' Mike stated, brushing something invisible from his tailored jacket. ''Just so long as you know. . . . '' He paused for effect. ''You're part of this now, and that means our futures are linked.''</p>
        <p>''One falls, we all fall?'' Alice offered.</p>
        <p>''That's right,'' Mike answered, and though his eyes were boring into Alice's, Allan couldn't help feeling the whole exchange could just as easily be aimed at him.</p>
        <p>''Your boss is getting good at losing us,'' Detective Inspector Ransome said. He was seated in a coffee shop on the High Street, just up from the Scottish Parliament, talking into his cellphone. The man he was talking to was seated three tables away. They held eye contact and their phones to their faces but couldn't risk an actual meeting.</p>
        <p>''That's because he won't let Johnno or me drive,'' Glenn said.</p>
        <p>''You think he's suspicious?''</p>
        <p>''If I thought he was on to me, I'd have packed my passport by now.''</p>
        <p>''He's the one who'll be going away, Glenn,'' Ransome said. ''Leaving his empire going begging.''</p>
        <p>''And you'll just let me take over? How do I know you won't try shafting me, same as you're doing to him?''</p>
        <p>''I will try shafting you, Glenn,'' Ransome said with a grin. ''But you'll be top dog, not just a bag-carrier. And you'll be wise to me.'' He broke off eye contact long enough to lift his coffee mug to his mouth. The liquid was scalding and tasted mainly of frothed milk.</p>
        <p>''Is that the latte?'' Glenn asked.</p>
        <p>Ransome nodded. ''What've you got?''</p>
        <p>''Hot chocolate with whipped cream.''</p>
        <p>''Sounds disgusting.'' Ransome wiped foam from his upper lip. ''So what's Chib up to, Glenn?''</p>
        <p>''Dunno.''</p>
        <p>''Thanks for sharing.''</p>
        <p>''No need to get sarcastic,'' Glenn said. ''He's up to something, though.''</p>
        <p>''You just said he wasn't.''</p>
        <p>''What I said was, I don't know what he's up to.''</p>
        <p>''But there is something?''</p>
        <p>Glenn nodded. The door opened and both men looked around, checking the new arrival. Just a young mother pushing a buggy.</p>
        <p>''They should ban kids from places like this,'' Glenn said, staring at the table of mothers and infants who were greeting this latest arrival.</p>
        <p>''And students,'' Ransome added, looking to where a solitary teenager, small coffee long finished, had spread laptop and coursework over a table intended for four. ''But then the place would be half-empty,'' the detective relented, ''and we'd stick out all the more.''</p>
        <p>''Suppose so,'' Glenn agreed.</p>
        <p>''So, now . . . maybe we can get back to your employer?''</p>
        <p>''He's keeping me and Johnno out of it.'' Glenn sounded aggrieved, and Ransome knew now why the man had asked for a meeting: he had some steam to blow off. ''But a couple of the pubs we've been to, he's been asking about kids.''</p>
        <p>''Kids?''</p>
        <p>Glenn saw that he had been misunderstood. ''Hooligans. Tearaways. Not kiddie kids.''</p>
        <p>''So give me some names.''</p>
        <p>Glenn shook his head. ''They're just first names, Billy and Teddy and things like that.''</p>
        <p>''So what does he want them for?''</p>
        <p>''Dunno.''</p>
        <p>''Are you being put out to pasture, Glenn?''</p>
        <p>Even at a distance, Ransome felt the power of the big man's stare. ''Nobody's putting me out of the game, Mr. Ransome.''</p>
        <p>''All the same, he's gathering up a team; got to be a reason.''</p>
        <p>''I'll keep my ears open.'' Glenn seemed to hesitate. ''Could be he's offering a hit.''</p>
        <p>Ransome's eyes widened. ''Who's he planning to whack?''</p>
        <p>''Might not be . . . but there's this big tattooed guy, a foreigner. . . . He's here to collect a back payment.''</p>
        <p>''And Chib's unwilling?''</p>
        <p>''Four apprentice thugs with pool cues might be his way of thinking.'' Glenn paused again. ''I don't think they'd cause Hate too many problems, though.''</p>
        <p>Ransome thought he had misheard. ''Hate?'' he repeated.</p>
        <p>''What he calls himself,'' Glenn confirmed.</p>
        <p>''Chib was disappointed,'' Mike said, ''when I told him the National Collection doesn't stretch to Vettriano.''</p>
        <p>Robert Gissing snorted into his drink. The two men were seated in an anonymous Edinburgh bar near the railway station. It was a no-nonsense place, meant for drinkers only: no TV or jukebox; potato chips alone to stave off hunger. Three old-timers were seated on stools at the bar itself, while Mike and Gissing had taken the table farthest from the door.</p>
        <p>''Vettriano isn't universally admired,'' Gissing said.</p>
        <p>''Popular, though,'' Mike countered.</p>
        <p>Gissing gave a twitch of the mouth by way of agreement. ''So what exactly is our gangland friend settling for?''</p>
        <p>''An Utterson.''</p>
        <p>'' 'Dusk on Rannoch Moor'?''</p>
        <p>''That's the one.''</p>
        <p>''Good riddance.'' Gissing took another gulp of sour red wine. He looked ready to explode, while Mike was growing calmer with each passing day.</p>
        <p>''It'll be fine,'' Mike said.</p>
        <p>''My boy, of course it will.'' The professor broke into a smile. ''You don't think I'm having doubts?''</p>
        <p>''A lot could go wrong. Chib says he's hand-picked the crew to help us, but all the same. . . . ''</p>
        <p>''And the disguises?''</p>
        <p>Mike lifted his own glass. ''In hand.''</p>
        <p>''The van?''</p>
        <p>''Stolen this morning and safely garaged. Fake license plates are probably being installed as we speak.''</p>
        <p>''Surprised you're not there to watch, Michael. You do seem to have developed a . . . taste . . . for all of this.''</p>
        <p>''Maybe a little,'' Mike conceded.</p>
        <p>''You'll be sorry when it's over?''</p>
        <p>Mike just shrugged. ''Either that or a convicted felon with Chib Calloway as my unhappy cellmate.''</p>
        <p>Gissing raised a hand. ''Let's not even go there.''</p>
        <p>The two men laughed and concentrated on their drinks. One more day to go. Mike didn't know how he would pass the hours. They had gone over the plan a dozen times. They knew what they had to do, and how much time would be available. But there were factors they couldn't control. Mike wondered if that was why he felt so calm: a case of que sera sera. All he knew was when Chib delivered the guns and handed him the Browning pistol, he felt a thrill of pleasure. The weight and heft, the oiled blackness: a work of art in itself. He wasn't allowed toy guns as a kid his mother's ruling but bananas, bits of wood, even a boomerang sent by an aunt in Australia had served the same purpose.</p>
        <p>Shifting againstthe back of his chair, he could feel the Browning tucked into his waistband. When the door to the bar opened, admitting another drinker, Mike thought back to that day in the auction house.</p>
        <p>When one door opens, another closes. . . .</p>
        <p>And vice versa, obviously.</p>
        <p>The Funny Pages | Sunday Serial</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
