<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Returning To Broadway On Celestial Roller Skates</title>
    <meta content="17piep" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/theater/17piep.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070617T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Piepenburg, Erik</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beane, Douglas Carter</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Xanadu (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Xanadu (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Beane, Douglas Carter</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E1D7173FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="800" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Returning To Broadway On Celestial Roller Skates</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Returning to Broadway on Celestial Roller Skates</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Erik Piepenburg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Piepenburg, Erik</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Erik Piepenburg interviews Douglas Carter Beane, who wrote book for forthcoming Broadway musical of movie Xanadu; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Douglas Carter Beane is having a Broadway moment. His play ''The Little Dog Laughed,'' a Faustian tale about a closeted actor navigating the demands of Hollywood hustlers, was nominated for a Tony Award for best play. (It lost to ''The Coast of Utopia.'') Julie White, the show's caustically funny leading lady, won the Tony for her performance as the actor's conniving agent. Mr. Beane, whose other plays included ''As Bees in Honey Drown,'' has also written the book for the new stage adaptation of the 1980 movie musical ''Xanadu,'' which starred Olivia Newton-John as a beautiful, breathy muse named Kira (Kerry Butler plays her on Broadway) who comes to earth to help an artist open his dream roller disco and had songs by the Electric Light Orchestra. The show is scheduled to open at the Helen Hayes Theater on June 26.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Douglas Carter Beane, who wrote the book for the new stage adaptation of the film “Xanadu,” discusses roller skating on Broadway and the world of “Xanadu” fanatics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Douglas Carter Beane is having a Broadway moment. His play ''The Little Dog Laughed,'' a Faustian tale about a closeted actor navigating the demands of Hollywood hustlers, was nominated for a Tony Award for best play. (It lost to ''The Coast of Utopia.'') Julie White, the show's caustically funny leading lady, won the Tony for her performance as the actor's conniving agent. Mr. Beane, whose other plays included ''As Bees in Honey Drown,'' has also written the book for the new stage adaptation of the 1980 movie musical ''Xanadu,'' which starred Olivia Newton-John as a beautiful, breathy muse named Kira (Kerry Butler plays her on Broadway) who comes to earth to help an artist open his dream roller disco and had songs by the Electric Light Orchestra. The show is scheduled to open at the Helen Hayes Theater on June 26.</p>
        <p>Mr. Beane sat down with Erik Piepenburg before the Tonys to discuss roller skating on Broadway, the world of ''Xanadu'' fanatics and why it's never a good idea to tempt Zeus. An extended audio slide show narrated by Mr. Beane is at nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Why Do 'Xanadu'?</p>
        <p>A lot of people would say that ''Xanadu'' would not be the first choice to bring to the legitimate stage for its many apparent faults. But the score to me is tremendous. The Electric Light Orchestra has become my favorite band.  You kind of go with it. It's a crazy, wonderful premise. What was wrong with the movie was that the dialogue was particularly bad, and the structuring of the screenplay was particularly banal. Happily, that's what I do. I do dramatic structure, and I do comedic, dramatic dialogue. It seemed that I could actually lend the one thing that it needed.</p>
        <p>Greek Is the Word</p>
        <p>My approach to this material was not to do a '' 'Grease' is to the '50s what 'Xanadu' is to the '80s'' version. Camp and winking were going to be a part of it; that was inevitable. What I was interested in was making fun of the lowest of art forms, which would be a bad movie from the '80s, and the highest of art forms, which would be a classical Greek drama, and mixing them all together. Because Kira is a muse, that allowed me to do my parody of an Edith Hamilton translation of a very serious play. The evening is based on a classical Greek structure.  I don't expect anyone to leave the Helen Hayes Theater going: ''Beane's done it. He's structured a classical Greek drama.'' But that was my idea, that it could be this fun, smart, silly, stupid time all at the same time.</p>
        <p>St. Newton-John</p>
        <p>What's fascinating is how many reasonably intelligent, creative people are obsessed with ''Xanadu.'' I know the head writer of the Steven Colbert show is a ''Xanadu'' freak. Isaac Mizrahi loves ''Xanadu.'' Chip Kidd, the great book cover designer, is a ''Xanadu'' nut.  Because of this project, people will come and say, ''Are you doing 'I'm Alive'?'' -- which is a number from the show. I say ''We're doing 'Fool Country,' '' which is a really obscure number from the movie, and they just quiver as if it were a religious experience.</p>
        <p>On Wheels</p>
        <p>I had seen roller skates onstage before in ''Starlight Express,'' which was in such a huge theater that somehow it became numb to me, that people were on this really dangerous surface doing anything. So when the possibility of the Helen Hayes became a reality I was excited. The way the set is, it goes into the auditorium. It's just so intimate. Even if you're in the last seat of the balcony, you're closer than you are in a good seat at the Hilton Theater. It has this kind of theater vibe. We incorporate the architecture of the theater within the storytelling.</p>
        <p>In the Now</p>
        <p>I would say that this particular time in my life is probably one of the best times in my life, which I say not tempting the gods. You don't want Zeus to find out, because he'll send Hermes down to give me new information. I have a Tony nomination for a play, and a lot of people are very excited that it was nominated at all, that it was remembered, that it was recalled. That means a lot to me.</p>
        <p>My partner and I have adopted a little boy, and we're going to be picking up our second child. As an agent at William Morris said, ''Kids are the only things that haven't been overhyped.'' They are pure joy.  I'm sure I'll need to do a movie soon to support all those children, so I'll be miserable again soon. Don't worry, envious people.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 17, 2007, Sunday  An article in Arts &amp; Leisure today about the playwright Douglas Carter Beane includes an outdated reference to the opening of ''Xanadu.'' The musical's opening has been postponed, with a date still to be determined. It will not open on June 26.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 17, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article in Arts &amp; Leisure today about the playwright Douglas Carter Beane includes an outdated reference to the opening of ''Xanadu.'' The musical's opening has been postponed, with a date still to be determined. It will not open on June 26.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
