<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Kids' Invention That Rocks (and Scoops)</title>
    <meta content="17colliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/17colli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854999"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE ISLAND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Feces</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geese</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kilgannon, Corey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EFDB143FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="871" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Kids' Invention That Rocks (and Scoops)</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Kids’ Invention That Rocks (and Scoops)</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Corey Kilgannon</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kilgannon, Corey</byline>
      <dateline>MASSAPEQUA PARK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Corey Kilgannon The Island column on team of four female students from Birch Lane Elementary School that invented wheeled receptacle that is pushed along field to scoop up droppings left by geese into plastic bag; invention was chosen as one of eight finalists for Christopher Columbus Awards, nationwide competition for students' innovations addressing local problems; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NECESSITY being the mother of invention, is it any wonder the Pooper Scooper Plow 2000 was born at Birch Lane Elementary School -- conceived by a group of students, no less?</p>
        <p>The school sits near John J. Burns Park, an expanse of playing fields that is a favorite destination of geese on the South Shore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A device for cleaning up goose droppings developed by a group of sixth graders on Long Island is a finalist in a national competition for local innovations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NECESSITY being the mother of invention, is it any wonder the Pooper Scooper Plow 2000 was born at Birch Lane Elementary School -- conceived by a group of students, no less?</p>
        <p>The school sits near John J. Burns Park, an expanse of playing fields that is a favorite destination of geese on the South Shore.</p>
        <p>The geese seem to favor Birch Lane's fields as an auxiliary grazing area, so in addition to the three R's, Birch Lane students are left pondering a fourth: Removin'. As in, how to remove the estimated 70,000 pounds of droppings left each year by the growing gaggle of geese on school grasslands.</p>
        <p>''Every time we'd go outside for recess or gym, the field was covered with goose poop, and we'd track it all through school and it would even get into our stuff,'' said Arielle Dhaim, 12, a sixth grader. She and three friends were assigned in October by their science teacher, Brian Mulcahy, to create a solution for a local problem.</p>
        <p>They chose the geese, and their science project became a large receptacle on wheels that is pushed along the field to skim the ground and scoop the droppings into a plastic bag. It was entered in February in the Christopher Columbus Awards, a nationwide competition for students' innovations addressing local problems. In early May, it was chosen out of hundreds of entries, making Team Pooper Scooper one of eight finalists nationwide to compete for a $25,000 grant toward fully developing an invention. The awards group provides an all-expense-paid trip to Disney World, where the contest is being held this week.</p>
        <p>And so, four friends who still think boys have cooties turned a field full of goose droppings into a trip to Disney World. But they also tackled an issue that has stymied the greatest minds of our generation: how to reclaim our grasslands from the geese. Methods have included scary shotgun blasts, border collies, wolf-shaped scarecrows and even killing the birds and oiling their eggs to prevent hatching.</p>
        <p>''We realized we were never going to eliminate the geese, and we didn't want to kill them,'' Arielle said. ''I mean, everyone does it -- you know, poops. You shouldn't be killed for something like that.''</p>
        <p>The team members recently demonstrated their invention on a grassy courtyard. They spread out a bunch of fake droppings made of masking tape and practiced scooping them up.</p>
        <p>The scooper is a prototype and not without its glitches, as a team member, Cassandra Chiocco, 12, learned when she collected a load of the fake droppings on its leading blade, which she then yanked up quickly by a string, flinging the pellets over the metal receptacle and at herself.</p>
        <p>''This is the part you guys are struggling with,'' Mr. Mulcahy said as Grace Hoar, 12, took the helm with similar results.</p>
        <p>''No, you're way too fast,'' Mr. Mulcahy instructed. ''We have to make it so it is not an athletic activity to get it to work.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mulcahy said that among his other students' innovative projects this year were a method of lifting wheelchairs upstairs and a theoretical solution to the Long Island Rail Road's problem with the gap between its trains and some platforms. The other finalists going to Disney World for the national championships this week include teams from Florida, Iowa, New Jersey and Ohio. A team from Texas developed a method of wind turbine-generated electricity to help run water pumps and irrigation systems; one from Washington State created signs with flashing lights to warn people about volcano eruptions.</p>
        <p>The teams will attend the Christopher Columbus Academy run by scientists, engineers and educators this week. The winner will be picked by a panel of scientists and educators.</p>
        <p>The girls said they observed that their school field attracted up to 100 geese a day. Since the average goose relieves itself of about 2 pounds of droppings a day, they figured, that makes 200 pounds a day, or more than 70,000 pounds a year on the field.</p>
        <p>It took three months to design and build the scooper, along with a lot of discussions about the other groups: What he wore, what she said and so forth.</p>
        <p>The team sketched a device resembling something like a small lawnmower or lawn spreader, and began building it at Arielle's house. From the local plumbing store, they bought an electrical junction box to use as the receptacle. They bought fasteners from Ace Hardware, and headed to Staples for the sparkly letter stickers to display the name. At Waldbaum's, they bought a bag of Tootsie Rolls.</p>
        <p>''That was supposed to be the practice poop,'' said Grace, ''but we left them in the box one day in the hot classroom and we came back and they were all melted.''</p>
        <p>Of course, the four girls have all been to Disney World already. Still, it's a thrill this time because they earned it themselves.</p>
        <p>''My sister is so mad because I'm going to Disney because of goose poop,'' said Nicolette Festa, 12.</p>
        <p>Arielle sat on the scooper with her chin on her palm and contemplated her team's rise to the top.</p>
        <p>''I always wanted fame,'' she said, ''but I always hoped it would be for singing and dancing.''</p>
        <p>THE ISLAND E-mail: theisland@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: theisland@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
