<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mosquito Arrives, Its Enemies Divided</title>
    <meta content="17mainliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/17mainli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854992"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PEST CONTROL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wetlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Methoprene (Pesticide)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wetlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wetlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E4DB143FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="848" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mosquito Arrives, Its Enemies Divided</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mosquito Arrives, Its Enemies Divided</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New long-term mosquito control and wetlands management plan in Suffolk County, NY, which would reduce use of pesticides by 75 percent over decade, runs into opposition, mostly over use of larvaecide methoprene; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUFFOLK COUNTY's new long-term plan for mosquito control and wetlands management was supposed to be a breakthrough that would reduce the use of pesticides by 75 percent over 10 years.</p>
        <p>But as the Long Island mosquito season begins, the plan, which includes continued use of a larvicide called methoprene, is running into opposition. The board of supervisors of the Town of East Hampton, for example, passed a resolution last month telling Suffolk it opposes further use of methoprene, which inhibits insect growth, in its saltwater wetlands. It prefers the bacterial agent Bti.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The continued use of a poison used to kill mosquitos on Long Island is running into opposition, just as its buggy season begins.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUFFOLK COUNTY's new long-term plan for mosquito control and wetlands management was supposed to be a breakthrough that would reduce the use of pesticides by 75 percent over 10 years.</p>
        <p>But as the Long Island mosquito season begins, the plan, which includes continued use of a larvicide called methoprene, is running into opposition. The board of supervisors of the Town of East Hampton, for example, passed a resolution last month telling Suffolk it opposes further use of methoprene, which inhibits insect growth, in its saltwater wetlands. It prefers the bacterial agent Bti.</p>
        <p>Suffolk County began spraying methoprene in salt marshes on Tuesday in several locations around Great South Bay and at a county park on Moriches Bay, said Walter Dawydiak, chief engineer for the health department's Division of Environmental Quality and project manager for the long-term plan. No methoprene had been applied in East Hampton salt marshes, Mr. Dawydiak said, because none was yet needed.</p>
        <p>The county says that mosquito efforts are a public health issue, saying mosquito control is essential to holding down human cases of West Nile virus. Under state regulations, the county has the power to override the town in such a case.</p>
        <p>The county's Vector Control Division, a part of the Health Department and the agency responsible for mosquito control, has been applying methoprene in East Hampton's Accabonac and Napeague Harbor wetlands since about 1995, said Lawrence T. Penny, the town's director of natural resources. But concerns have grown about the risks of methoprene to crabs, shrimp, lobster and other organisms, including other insects, and the town says too little is known about it.</p>
        <p>''Our salt marsh dragonfly population has crashed, and we don't know why,'' Mr. Penny said. Though there is no evidence that the use of methoprene was responsible, he said, the decline coincides with the use of the larvicide.</p>
        <p>''It's very troubling,'' he said.</p>
        <p>East Hampton is not alone in its concerns. The State Department of Environmental Conservation, which manages about 2,320 of the 17,000 acres of saltwater wetlands in Suffolk, is setting a high standard for methoprene use on those lands. A temporary permit the state issued to Suffolk for the state-managed wetlands in April allows methoprene ''only when a threat to human health exists, but not for routine mosquito-control purposes,'' the department said in a statement. A criterion is whether West Nile virus or the far more rare Eastern equine encephalitis is found in mosquitoes trapped in the state-managed wetlands.</p>
        <p>Nassau County, which has a less extensive mosquito control program and less acreage to cover than Suffolk, also uses methoprene as a backup for Bti, when Bti is not enough.</p>
        <p>For 2006, New York reported two human cases of West Nile virus in Suffolk County and five in Nassau to the Centers for Disease Control in Atlanta; none were fatal. No cases of Eastern equine encephalitis were reported on the Island.</p>
        <p>Suffolk's health department said 57 mosquito samples tested positive for West Nile last year.</p>
        <p>Suffolk health officials said methoprene protects the public from mosquito-borne diseases, principally West Nile virus, and limits the need for adult pesticide spraying later on.</p>
        <p>''We have the duty to protect the public health,'' said Mr. Dawydiak of the county health department.</p>
        <p>Scott R. Campbell, the chief of the county's Arthropod-Borne Disease Laboratory, said the methoprene dosages the county applied were so small that only the specific mosquito larvae were affected. He said he had seen no study showing that methoprene was harmful in such amounts.</p>
        <p>Other agencies take a more conservative view. The Fire Island National Seashore follows a policy for methoprene similar to the state's. ''We avoid it as much as we can and only want it used when there is an actual disease threat present,'' said Michael T. Reynolds, the superintendent.</p>
        <p>Methoprene prevents mosquito larvae from maturing into adults while remaining as food for mosquito predators.</p>
        <p>In March, the Suffolk County Legislature approved the new long-term plan despite recommendations from its own Council on Environmental Quality that methoprene use be restricted in saltwater wetlands. The legislators for Suffolk's five East End towns and parts of Brookhaven, the Republicans Edward P. Romaine of Center Moriches and Jay Schneiderman of Montauk, voted against the plan. The council also called for a clearer distinction between pesticide use for disease control and for nuisance control.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dawydiak, the plan's project manager, said modeling by the county showed that without methoprene, mosquitoes would increase fivefold, pesticide use on adult mosquitoes would double and death and illness from West Nile virus would soar.</p>
        <p>Kevin McAllister, the president of Peconic Baykeeper, a nonprofit conservation group in Quogue that has opposed county policies on mosquito control and wetlands management, said, ''Obviously it's in their interest to cloak themselves in the public health issue.'' He added, ''It's alarmist behavior to instill fear.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Penny, East Hampton's director of natural resources, said the town had no human cases of West Nile virus, no history of mosquito-related health problems and few complaints about mosquitoes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dawydiak concedes that West Nile virus is ''not commonly found'' in salt marsh mosquitoes.</p>
        <p>PEST CONTROL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
