<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: Consumed; Donk My Ride</title>
    <meta content="17wwln--consumed.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/magazine/17wwln-consumed-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854926"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Consumed"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Walker, Rob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E4DC173FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: Consumed; Donk My Ride</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Donk My Ride</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rob Walker column on donks: American sedans from 1970s that ride on oversized wheels and are often painted in color schemes and with logos derived from pop culture or brands like Hawaiian Punch or Lucky Charms; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The allure of aesthetics has been a fact of automobile design for many decades. But carmakers have never been able to match the inventiveness of some car owners, dating back at least to creators of tangerine-flake objets d'art that Tom Wolfe celebrated in the 1960s. To believe that auto expressionists will run out of gas at some point is to underestimate their ability to create previously unimaginable novelty. Picture, for instance, a 1976 Impala improbably perched on 26-inch wheels and painted in colors inspired by a variety of Hawaiian Punch. This is what's called a donk.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Customized cars that use commercial logos as a creative palette.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The allure of aesthetics has been a fact of automobile design for many decades. But carmakers have never been able to match the inventiveness of some car owners, dating back at least to creators of tangerine-flake objets d'art that Tom Wolfe celebrated in the 1960s. To believe that auto expressionists will run out of gas at some point is to underestimate their ability to create previously unimaginable novelty. Picture, for instance, a 1976 Impala improbably perched on 26-inch wheels and painted in colors inspired by a variety of Hawaiian Punch. This is what's called a donk.</p>
        <p>The donk is a car-customization mash-up, forcing a reconciliation between seemingly contradictory trends. First: the well-established low-rider idea of modifying the suspension on, say, a carefully restored Impala, so that it rides as close to the ground as possible. The second trend is rim inflation, the more recent but evidently unflagging popularity of increasingly large wheels, especially on S.U.V.'s, associated with the blingiest manifestations of hip-hop style. It was apparently in Miami, about six years ago, that somebody decided to marry these notions and modify a classic low-rider car to accommodate oversize rims, according to Brian Scotto, who is the editor of a magazine called Donk, Box &amp; Bubble.</p>
        <p>Technically, Scotto explains, donks are Caprices or Impalas from the years 1971 to 1976. (One theory about the provenance of the name ''donk'' is the resemblance of the Impala logo to a donkey; another is that it derives from a slang term for a shapely posterior.) A similarly customized Caprice or Impala from model years 1977 to 1990 is a box, and '91s through '96s are bubbles, names that reference the cars' silhouettes. Scotto's magazine uses the term hi-risers to cover the entire category, but most any tricked-out boxy '70s sedan is now routinely called a donk. The key is ''really big wheels, wheels that obviously do not fit in the wheel well,'' Scotto continues, adding that these days, you really need 24-inch wheels to qualify.</p>
        <p>The most striking donks have ''themes,'' lifted from pop culture -- or, surprisingly often, branding. The Hawaiian Punch Green Berry Rush donk, built by Mr. Scrape Customs in Sumter, S.C., is a good example: its owner brought along a bottle of the stuff to Mr. Scrape and announced, ''I want it to look like this,'' explains Robbie Casselman, the shop's director of sales and marketing. So the car mimics the screaming green color and includes a custom interior console with Hawaiian Punch labels under plastic, as well as a big logo on the trunk. Mr. Scrape has also built cars with Lucky Charms and Spider-Man themes. In addition to donks with color schemes inspired by Garfield or Sonic the Hedgehog, other logo-themed examples online or in the pages of Donk, Box &amp; Bubble include McDonald's, Newport cigarettes and Aquafina. From what both Scotto and Casselman say, this began largely as a matter of aesthetics and took a quick road to conspicuousness. Borrowing an appealing color combination from striking packaging seems to have led to a way of making form match function in total outrageousness.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scrape has some famous clients, like Thomas Davis, a linebacker for the Carolina Panthers, and has lately been hearing from rap stars and people in the traditional car-innovation breeding grounds of California. But mostly it has been a grass-roots phenomenon. After Florida, donks have been most popular in Georgia, the Carolinas and other Southern states. Outfitting a truly head-turning donk isn't cheap: Casselman says a ''complete build'' costs at least $40,000 and can easily run three times that. But many donk owners don't go that far, or they modify the car by degrees, which makes the car an affordable but still potentially flashy alternative to an Escalade or a Phantom. A huge logo on the door is one blunt way to stand out. (Although, Casselman notes, many donk owners themselves prefer to ''stay discreet,'' identified in magazines only by nicknames and nonexistent hometowns.) ''That's why I see this continuing to grow,'' Scotto says. ''You can buy a box Chevy for $1,000. And once you get that box Chevy, you belong.''</p>
        <p>Similarly, the use of logos seems to have more to do with fitting into donk culture than with brand endorsement. That may change: Scotto's magazine was recently commissioned by Coors Brewing Company to build a Coors Light-themed donk. But for now, the real effect of logo themes comes down to branding the donk itself. ''It kind of gives the car a name,'' Scott says -- albeit a name borrowed from commercial culture. ''All cars that have that kind of theme to them are better known.'' Here, then, is what lies beyond the candy-colored, or even kandy-kolored, hot rod: the Skittles donk.</p>
        <p>Consumed</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
