<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: On Language; Tiers In My Eyes</title>
    <meta content="17wwln--safire.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/magazine/17wwln-safire-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854925"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="On Language"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4DC173FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="975" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: On Language; Tiers In My Eyes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tiers in My Eyes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Safire</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire On Language column on notion of 'top tier' and 'second tier' presidential candidates (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>How would you feel if you were running for president, knocking yourself out on the campaign trail, wheedling money out of people who don't owe you a favor, pressing whatever flesh that deigns to come to hand, answering ''gotcha! questions'' from choleric bloggers with a circulation of two and still -- despite having the most cogent views on urgent issues and seized with an inspiring vision of America -- find yourself consigned to the demeaning dungeon of politics, the second tier?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For those categorized candidates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>How would you feel if you were running for president, knocking yourself out on the campaign trail, wheedling money out of people who don't owe you a favor, pressing whatever flesh that deigns to come to hand, answering ''gotcha! questions'' from choleric bloggers with a circulation of two and still -- despite having the most cogent views on urgent issues and seized with an inspiring vision of America -- find yourself consigned to the demeaning dungeon of politics, the second tier?</p>
        <p>Years ago, the columnist Russell Baker came up with the theory of the Great Mentioner, the mysterious, Oz-like confidential source behind all the descriptions of political figures being ''mentioned for president.'' Today, as we approach the crucial 180th day before the first caucus, the need is evident for a unified field theory of the Great Tiersperson -- the shadowy force that determines who shall be hailed as top-tier and who shall be downmouthed as second-tier, supported by a dwindling band of second-class citizens.</p>
        <p>Questions: 1) Who or what is this Ã1/4ber-electoral force of judgment? 2) What standards does it use in deciding who gets assigned to what tier? 3) Is upward or downward mobility possible in a polity afflicted with tiersmanship? And 4) What's a tier, anyway, and who arranged its rendezvous with this generation of Americans?</p>
        <p>Don't look at me, says a leading pollster. ''The labels are made by the pundit class,'' John Zogby opines. ''It is a conventional wisdom borne out of talking heads talking to talking heads. We often report our results in rank order (sometimes not), but we do not package our results according to 'tiers.' ''</p>
        <p>Another top-tier pollster chosen at random (I presume to be a Great Tiersperson when it comes to pollsters) -- Regina Corso, director of the Harris Poll -- is comfortable with tiersmanship. Is there any ranking lower than second tier? ''If first tier is the top two or three candidates, and second tier is the group of candidates below that who are plausible but not yet 'in the running' for some reason, the third tier would then be those who may not be considered plausible.'' The Democrat Mike Gravel and the Republican Ron Paul get banished to that Siberia.</p>
        <p>Let's take ''running but not 'in the running' '' as an apt definition of second tier. The Democrat Bill Richardson, the New Mexico governor, and the Republican Mike Huckabee, the former governor of Arkansas, are widely assumed to be at the tops of their (second) tiers. What would permit a tier jump? Answers: Media ''buzz''; a hot issue or Reaganesque phrase in the ''cattle show'' appearances; a bounce in fund-raising; or the blooperization of a top-tier candidate followed by the Great Tiersperson's need to fill that third slot.</p>
        <p>Neither pollsters nor pundits nor heavy-hitting endorsers have come forward with a separate category for ''not running but in the running,'' which I designate as ''second tier, once removed.'' Examples are the Democrat Al Gore, the Republican Fred Thompson and the Third Way Michael Bloomberg. (When I put potential candidacy to Mike recently, he grinned. ''A short, Jewish billionaire from New York? C'mon.'')</p>
        <p>The top tier seems to be limited to three candidates, as if the Great Tiersperson ordained a political trinity or the media buzzards' airline baggage did not permit another carrion. This is the Democrats' Clinton-Obama-Edwards tier facing the McCain-Giuliani-Romney tier.</p>
        <p>You now have answers to the first three questions posed near the top of this column. Now to the fourth: Etymology and usage of tier. An e-mailer messages: ''This 'second tier' formulation has been around a long time, of course, but seems to be going through its hyperusage stage, which means the political P.R. people have all glommed onto it.''</p>
        <p>Here goes: Tier, from tire, is of Old French origin, the noun meaning ''rank, order,'' surfacing first in 1569, leading to the verb tirer, ''to draw, drag, elongate, pull'' (maybe that's where ''to pull rank'' comes from). The German noun tier, meaning ''animal; pet,'' is not the source, though the early-primary madness reminds one of a Tiergarten, or zoo.</p>
        <p>Early use is from Time magazine in August 1972, when the liberal Washington lawyer Joseph Rauh suggested a scheme to amend the Constitution so that the president could run independently of the vice president (thereby re-electing Nixon, as expected, but making possible the ouster of Spiro Agnew). ''Thus presidential candidates would compete in one contest,'' Time summarized, ''and vice-presidential opponents run against one another in a second-tier race.''</p>
        <p>(Hmm. Imagine McCain as president looking over his shoulder at Vice President Obama, or Hillary as chief executive with Rudy breathing down her neck. It'll never fly.)</p>
        <p>Third tier achieved its lowly rank in the political pecking order in 1977, as The Washington Post reported that the highest members of the Democratic Party council agreed to donate $5,000 each and bundle another five thou from nine friends. ''The next level of party functionaries agreed to donate $5,000 each, while the third tier of supporters simply purchased the $1,000 dinner tickets.''</p>
        <p>The first use I can find that applied first tier to presidential candidates was in the Times coverage of a June 1982 Democratic midterm conference in Philadelphia. One article dealt with ''the second tier'' of Senators Gary Hart, John Glenn, Ernest Hollings, Alan Cranston and former Florida governor Reuben Askew; another focused on the two front-runners: ''Walter Mondale. . . . For all his energetic campaigning, the former vice president has been slipping in the polls. Could he stay in the first tier with Senator Kennedy?'' Mondale did, won the nomination and forthrightly promised to raise taxes during the campaign, and Reagan clobbered him.</p>
        <p>Let us then (as perorations begin) resist such lumping together by ''the pundit class,'' talking heads sitting gingerly on talking points. Let voters cheerfully choose their favorites with less lemminglike media intermediation. No more tiers</p>
        <p>On Language</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
