<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: Questions for Lou Piniella; Anger Management</title>
    <meta content="17wwln--Q4.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/magazine/17wwln-Q4-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854927"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Questions for Lou Piniella"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Cubs</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Piniella, Lou</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Solomon, Deborah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E4DC173FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: Questions for Lou Piniella; Anger Management</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Anger Management</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Deborah Solomon</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Solomon, Deborah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Deborah Solomon interview with Chicago Cubs manager Loui Piniella, who comments on such things as his displays of anger on ballfield, whether women can manage major league team and why he decided to manage Cubs in view of their bleak record; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the manager of the Chicago Cubs, you were suspended this month after a very public meltdown in which you stormed out of the dugout and kicked dirt on the umpire. But aren't temper tantrums by baseball managers a venerable American tradition? You know what? They probably want the mangers to be more like Stepford wives. If that's what they want, that's O.K. Times have changed. My kicking-dirt episodes are over. You can put them in the archives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Cubs manager talks about the advantages of kicking dirt, what’s wrong with fantasy baseball and why this is his last job.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the manager of the Chicago Cubs, you were suspended this month after a very public meltdown in which you stormed out of the dugout and kicked dirt on the umpire. But aren't temper tantrums by baseball managers a venerable American tradition? You know what? They probably want the mangers to be more like Stepford wives. If that's what they want, that's O.K. Times have changed. My kicking-dirt episodes are over. You can put them in the archives.</p>
        <p>What do you find so satisfying about kicking dirt on another person, a practice you've been known to favor since you managed the Yankees in the '80s? My mentor, Billy Martin, did it. And Earl Weaver did it. I've kicked dirt more out of dissatisfaction than anything else. When I was informed that kicking dirt on somebody can be termed as degrading -- you know, I never thought of it that way.</p>
        <p>Only a day before your own outburst, you were in the dugout when the pitcher Carlos Zambrano became involved in a belligerent exchange that continued in the clubhouse and left Michael Barrett, the catcher, with six stitches in his lower lip. Why didn't you stop them?</p>
        <p>What can a manager do about those things? They're not planned. They're not premeditated. Those were spontaneous acts. Baseball is a competitive sport, and there are a lot of frustrations involved. If you're really successful in this business, you're going to fail 7 out of 10 times.</p>
        <p>People can't accept failure in this country, which probably explains why kids are addicted to fantasy baseball, with its illusion of mastery. I think kids are more in front of the TV now with their video games and their fantasy leagues instead of being out on the baseball diamond or the basketball court or a football field. What I would like to see is more participation instead of just sitting and watching. I would like to see a step back into the past.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, it might be nice if baseball moved into the future by including more women in its ranks. Do you think a woman could be a good manager? If she had a good bench coach, why not? I would think she would need a good hardened professional baseball guy that would help her with the x's and o's during the ballgame. Someone who knew the intricacies in and out of the game.</p>
        <p>Plenty of women already know the intricacies of the game. I'm not sure of that. I think some of the sportswriter women probably think they do.</p>
        <p>Never mind. Who is the smartest baseball player you know? I would say Alex Rodriguez.</p>
        <p>Who are the managers you most respect? Bob Lemon. Bobby Cox has got to be one. My buddy Tony La Russa had a marvelous career. We're both from Tampa. We grew up together in the same neighborhood playing on the same teams.</p>
        <p>Have you read any good books about sports lately? I don't read many sports books. I'd rather read the Bible.</p>
        <p>Do you pray before games? I hate to pray about wins and losses. There are just too many other things in life that are more important to pray for. Our soldiers in Iraq, for one.</p>
        <p>Have you met President Bush? I had dinner with him at the White House this winter, along with George Will, Tim McCarver, Trevor Hoffman, Vernon Wells and spouses.</p>
        <p>Is the president a Cubs fan? Not really, but George Will was.</p>
        <p>Why are the Cubs doing so poorly? I don't know. I've been here a couple of months.</p>
        <p>Why did you decide to manage a team with as bleak a record as the Cubs? I wanted one more challenge in my career. I'm 63 years old, and I don't want to be doing this at 70.</p>
        <p>You always say you're quitting, and then you go back. I'm not going back. This is it. There is no return here. The same way I tell you there will be no more dirt-kicking, this is my last job.</p>
        <p>Deborah Solomon</p>
        <p>Questions for Lou Piniella</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
