<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Funny Pages II: True-Life Tales; Chasing the Dragon</title>
    <meta content="17funny--humor.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/magazine/17funny-humor-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854914"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dating and Courtship</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kine, Starlee</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E5DC173FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="905" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Funny Pages II: True-Life Tales; Chasing the Dragon</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chasing the Dragon</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Starlee Kine</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kine, Starlee</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Starlee Kine article on her sister's weakness for men who are third-rate or even worse at what they do; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Not long ago I went to a family reunion in Nashville. When it was over, my little sister, Laceé, and I were waiting in the airport to fly home -- New York for me and L.A. for her.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Not long ago I went to a family reunion in Nashville. When it was over, my little sister, Laceé, and I were waiting in the airport to fly home  New York for me and L.A. for her.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Not long ago I went to a family reunion in Nashville. When it was over, my little sister, Laceé, and I were waiting in the airport to fly home -- New York for me and L.A. for her.</p>
        <p>She had a copy of US Weekly, and we squeezed into the same seat to look through it together. We saw a picture of skinny little Nicole Richie air-biting into a cheeseburger. I pointed to it but didn't say anything, because I figured any thoughts on Nicole Richie were by now pretty obvious.</p>
        <p>''I know,'' Laceé said. ''She's so sweet, huh?''</p>
        <p>Until that moment I hadn't realized that there were different ways of reading US Weekly.</p>
        <p>Laceé has always been a fan of the underdog. Her first boyfriend was a rapper named Biggie Smalls, but not the one you're thinking of. That Biggie eventually sued my sister's Biggie, so he had to change his name to something else. He chose DJ Shadow. Only not the one you're thinking of.</p>
        <p>When studying in Spain, she fell for the fifth-best Ping-Pong player in the country. I imagine if the first-best had asked her out, or even the third-, she would have just looked at him pityingly. As a rule, you have to be not quite good enough at what you do to be good enough for my sister.</p>
        <p>Nowadays she is a part-time model/part-time aspiring paralegal. At lunch she likes to wander through the nearby food court and text-message me when she sees a celebrity worth mentioning. She once saw Brad Pitt, but I didn't hear about it for a year. It's the minor, forgotten stars who get her excited. It's like those movies in which only the little kids and animals can see the angels: only my little sister can see the grown-up child stars who still walk among us.</p>
        <p>So when she sent me a text reading . . .</p>
        <p>Just saw Randall B. eating sushi. Cuuuute!!!!</p>
        <p>. . . I knew just what she was talking about. Randall Batinkoff was the teenage husband to Molly Ringwald's pregnant teenage wife in the '80s cautionary tale ''For Keeps.'' Laceé and I spent an entire summer watching it on cable. We ran around the house with pillows under our shirts, pretending to be young, expectant high-school mothers.</p>
        <p>One of the biggest fights we ever had was when we bought identical issues of Tiger Beat magazine only to find that Laceé's included a pinup of a particularly smoking Randall Batinkoff (permed hair, pleated acid-washed jeans, braided belt) while mine had been torn out. I offered Laceé everything for that picture (crimping iron, stirrup pants, 67 matching jelly bracelets), but she refused. She wouldn't even hang it up for fear that I'd steal it. She knew that if I couldn't have it, neither could she.</p>
        <p>''Randall looked exactly the same,'' Laceé told me over the phone later. ''I think he's about to have a comeback.'' I didn't have the heart to tell her you can't come back if you've never been there in the first place.</p>
        <p>Laceé's latest underdog is her acupuncturist. His name is Dr. Zee Lo, and he is a full-time doctor of Oriental medicine/part-time aspiring martial-arts star. Dr. Zee, as I like to call him, scraped together as much money as he could to make an actual movie. Laceé was cast as his onscreen love interest, Michelle.</p>
        <p>The movie is called ''Chasing the Dragon.'' Only not the kind of chasing you're thinking of: instead of being addicted to heroin, Dr. Zee is addicted to Bruce Lee.</p>
        <p>I have the DVD, which I can't seem to stop watching. Not because it's so good, or even because it's so bad. In fact, it's almost unfair to judge it in the same terms you would a regular movie. It seems as if you should compare it to something else, like apples or vinyl siding.</p>
        <p>In the movie, when Dr. Zee goes to a Hollywood film-lab, you know it because there is a piece of paper taped to the wall with the words ''Hollywood Film Lab'' on it. The whirlwind shopping-spree scene takes place in a random living room with some wrinkled clothes spread out on a coffee table. Laceé's character's apartment and Dr. Zee's are the same apartment. They don't even bother putting new art on the walls. It's just sometimes his place and sometimes hers.</p>
        <p>My favorite part is the big breakup scene. Laceé's character wants Dr. Zee to give up the trying-to-be-Bruce-Lee thing.</p>
        <p>''You don't need me,'' she tells him. ''You just need your honor.''</p>
        <p>''I can't help it,'' he responds. ''I'm chasing the dragon.'' He pauses to make sure we get that he's referring to the title of the movie. Laceé looks crushed. Even her film persona can't stay with a man who insists on being No. 1. She flees, weeping, as Dr. Zee shuts the door to his/her apartment behind her.</p>
        <p>Having a little sister who stars in a martial-arts movie means having a lot of questions. Questions like ''When we were kids, did you ever look at Randall B. and think, That's going to be me one day?''</p>
        <p>But whenever I ask her anything about the movie, she quickly grows bored. She has seen the movie just once, and now she's over it. It's the inherent problem with loving the underdogs. As soon as you acknowledge their existence, they cease to exist to you.</p>
        <p>Starlee Kine is working on a book about self-help titled ''It IS Your Fault.'' Her last True-Life Tale was about choosing not to hug baby pandas.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Starlee Kine is working on a book about self-help titled ''It IS Your Fault.'' Her last True-Life Tale was about choosing not to hug baby pandas.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
