<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bike Path in Jeopardy As Power Company Balks</title>
    <meta content="17topicliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/17topicli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854994"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="RIGHT OF WAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Port Jefferson (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Wading River (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Island Power Authority</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cotroneo, Nicole</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/North Shore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Long Island Power Authority</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DB143FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bike Path in Jeopardy As Power Company Balks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bike Path in Jeopardy as Power Company Balks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICOLE COTRONEO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cotroneo, Nicole</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island Power Authority decides it will not relinquish its right to develop land that was being considered for eastern portion of Rails-to-Trails bike path between Port Jefferson and Wading River; if LIPA does not grant ownership interest, Suffolk County will be unable to use $2 million federal grant to build path; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GARY WLADYKA often rides a bicycle from his home in Miller Place to his shop, Rocky Point Cycle, two towns east. He pedals along the shoulder of busy Route 25A, where many cyclists are afraid to ride.</p>
        <p>He has been eagerly awaiting a bike path, he said, which Suffolk County has planned to build nearby along an old railway line and away from the dangers and fumes of motor vehicles. But Mr. Wladyka's wait just became longer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Long Island Power Authority has pulled its support for a planned Suffolk County bike path on the site of an unused railroad, likely undermining years of planning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GARY WLADYKA often rides a bicycle from his home in Miller Place to his shop, Rocky Point Cycle, two towns east. He pedals along the shoulder of busy Route 25A, where many cyclists are afraid to ride.</p>
        <p>He has been eagerly awaiting a bike path, he said, which Suffolk County has planned to build nearby along an old railway line and away from the dangers and fumes of motor vehicles. But Mr. Wladyka's wait just became longer.</p>
        <p>More than a half-decade of planning has gone into the proposed Rails-to-Trails bike path, which would run nearly 15 miles between Port Jefferson and Wading River. But in late April, the Long Island Power Authority told the county that it would not relinquish its right to develop land that was being considered for the eastern portion of the path, which would run beneath power transmission lines.</p>
        <p>If LIPA does not grant Suffolk an ownership interest in the property, the county cannot use a $2 million federal grant -- administered by the state -- to build the path, said County Legislator Daniel P. Losquadro, who inherited the project from his predecessor, Martin Haley.</p>
        <p>Mr. Losquadro said, ''The state has said it will not release this money because there is no guarantee this path will remain in public hands for perpetuity.''</p>
        <p>No one expected the power company to pull its support at the final hour, when Suffolk officials were prepared to go public with a bid request for a design consultant and a land appraiser, Mr. Losquadro said.</p>
        <p>Bert Cunningham, a LIPA spokesman, said its decision was based on the need to serve customers.</p>
        <p>''A permanent easement on our property would restrict us from ever using that property for anything we might need,'' he said. ''What happens if we need to put in another transmission line and it needs to go underground? We can't be put in a position that we can't use a transmission right of way for our service.''</p>
        <p>But Michael Cosel of Setauket, who proposed the bike path to Mr. Haley, said he did not accept LIPA's reasoning. If the utility needs to add power lines, it will need a road to get construction vehicles to the site and could share it with bicycles, he said.</p>
        <p>In Massachusetts about seven years ago, Mr. Cosel walked a path sanctioned by the Rails-to-Trails Conservancy, a Washington-based organization that works with communities to turn abandoned rail corridors into trails. Impressed with the idea, he said, he contacted Mr. Haley about converting the abandoned Wading River extension of the Long Island Rail Road Port Jefferson line.</p>
        <p>When the county contacted LIPA about the path, Mr. Cosel and Mr. Losquadro said, the utility was enthusiastic.</p>
        <p>Now that LIPA has withdrawn its support, Mr. Cosel has been meeting with civic associations to gain theirs. Many community leaders say the path would help draw tourists to their swath of the North Shore and help revitalize their downtowns, Mr. Cosel said.</p>
        <p>Diane Burke, the president of the Rocky Point Civic Association, said the bike path would be ''an absolute home run'' for business owners in Rocky Point and surrounding towns. ''People could come and make a day trip of the trail with their families,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Lynne A. Bizzarro, Suffolk's chief deputy attorney, said the county hoped to keep negotiations with LIPA open.</p>
        <p>The western portion of the path -- 3.5 miles between Port Jefferson and Setauket -- still has the green light, Mr. Cosel said. Financed by $7 million in federal and state grants, this section will run along state right of way and not on LIPA land.</p>
        <p>The 11.2-mile eastern portion remains in jeopardy, but Mr. Losquadro has not lost hope. ''I still don't think it's a dead issue,'' he said. ''I think LIPA is being very selfish here. I think they should come forward and willingly participate in this.''</p>
        <p>RIGHT OF WAY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
