<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Making Musical History</title>
    <meta content="17artsliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/17artsli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854995"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Arts and Entertainment"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Synthesizers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Deutsch, Herbert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moog, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipson, Karin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Musical Instruments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Musical Instruments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Moog, Robert</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E3DB143FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="802" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Making Musical History</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Making Musical History</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KARIN LIPSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipson, Karin</byline>
      <dateline>MASSAPEQUA PARK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of and interview with Herb Deutsch, experimental composer from Long Island who, with electrical engineer Robert Moog, developed Moog synthesizer in 1964; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE night in January 1964, Herb Deutsch, an experimental composer from Long Island, and Robert Moog, an electrical engineer from upstate, sat with their wives at a little Italian restaurant in Greenwich Village and excitedly discussed a new idea: What if they created an instrument, a kind of ''portable electronic music studio,'' on which musicians could compose and perform?</p>
        <p>''We were thinking primarily of composers,'' Mr. Deutsch, now professor emeritus of music at Hofstra University, recalled a few weeks ago at his home here. ''That performance part was not that important to Bob and me.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Inter-Media Art Center is preparing to celebrate the Moog synthesizer, which helped launch a music revolution in the 1960s.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE night in January 1964, Herb Deutsch, an experimental composer from Long Island, and Robert Moog, an electrical engineer from upstate, sat with their wives at a little Italian restaurant in Greenwich Village and excitedly discussed a new idea: What if they created an instrument, a kind of ''portable electronic music studio,'' on which musicians could compose and perform?</p>
        <p>''We were thinking primarily of composers,'' Mr. Deutsch, now professor emeritus of music at Hofstra University, recalled a few weeks ago at his home here. ''That performance part was not that important to Bob and me.''</p>
        <p>That conversation in 1964 begat the Moog synthesizer, which helped launch a music revolution that started with the psychedelic rock stars of the 60's and -- several seismic electronic upheavals later -- reached suburbia's kid-next-door, the one with the Japanese keyboard and the garage band.</p>
        <p>The heady early days will be recalled June 29, when the Inter-Media Art Center in Huntington presents ''Herb Deutsch: Celebrating the Music of the Moog Synthesizer.'' The event will be part belated birthday party for Mr. Deutsch (who turned 75 in February), part performance festival with multiple guests and instruments and part recollection of the Moog era, with video segments and some personal reminiscing.</p>
        <p>In this ubiquitously digital age, with synthesizers in everyday objects like computers and tiny cellphones, it's hard to imagine that their predecessors were Rube Goldberg-like nests of ungainly equipment played only within a small world of academic or experimental composers.</p>
        <p>Then along came the Moog (which rhymes with ''vogue''). Though Mr. Deutsch insists he won't dwell on nostalgic anecdotes at IMAC, a good one would be his chance encounter with Mr. Moog at a 1963 music-education conference in Rochester.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moog was then a doctoral candidate in solid-state physics at Cornell University and was exhibiting his $50 kit for making a theremin, the oddball electronic instrument used for spooky ''aliens-have-landed'' sound effects in early science-fiction movies.</p>
        <p>As it happened, ''I had built a theremin in 1962 based on Bob Moog's design,'' Mr. Deutsch explained. They struck up a conversation, and Mr. Deutsch invited his new acquaintance to an avant-garde concert in Lower Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Later, the two cemented their friendship in the Italian restaurant, where the idea for the Moog was born.</p>
        <p>''Herb Deutsch's involvement was crucial,'' said Trevor Pinch, professor of science and technology studies at Cornell and the coauthor of ''Analog Days: The Invention and Impact of the Moog Synthesizer'' (Harvard University Press). Until Mr. Moog met Herb Deutsch, Mr. Pinch said, ''Bob Moog had had very little involvement with the avant-garde and experimental electronic music.''</p>
        <p>Afterward, Mr. Moog began noodling with the new idea and later refined it with Mr. Deutsch in his small theremin factory in Trumansburg. ''He was the electrical engineer; I was the musician,'' Mr. Deutsch recalled. ''I'd say, 'Can we do this?' And he'd say, 'Sure.' ''</p>
        <p>Within weeks, Mr. Deutsch said, ''we had what we knew was going to become the prototype.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Deutsch also began creating what would be the world's first musical composition using the Moog. (That piece, ''Jazz Images,'' will be performed at IMAC.) His colleague was entranced. ''When you took these circuits and your tape recorder down to the basement and you actually put music together -- that blew my mind,'' the inventor says to Mr. Deutsch in ''Moog,'' a 2004 documentary.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deutsch also influenced Mr. Moog to use a conventional keyboard to control the sound -- a means that electronic purists considered far too pedestrian.</p>
        <p>''If there had been no Herb Deutsch, the history of the synthesizer would have looked quite different, because you wouldn't have had the keyboard,'' Mr. Pinch said.</p>
        <p>The Moog wasn't the only synthesizer being developed, but its keyboard immediately transformed the geeky gizmo into an instrument all musicians could recognize.</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Moog was soon working with many other musicians, including Wendy Carlos (then known as Walter, prior to a sex-change operation), whose 1968 recording ''Switched-On Bach'' became a popular sensation and made the Moog famous.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moog and Mr. Deutsch no longer worked together after 1970 and occasionally locked horns over professional issues, though they eventually revived their friendship. (Mr. Moog died in 2005 at 71.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Deutsch continued composing and teaching at Hofstra (where he was twice chairman of the music department). He also worked as a marketing and educational consultant and co-founded the Long Island Composers' Alliance.</p>
        <p>Though his name was not on the Moog, ''it hasn't kept me from being who I am,'' he said. ''It's always exciting to know that I've been a piece of music history -- that I was there.''</p>
        <p>''Herb Deutsch: Celebrating the Music of the Moog Synthesizer'' will be presented June 29 at 8 p.m. at the Inter-Media Art Center, 370 New York Avenue, Huntington. Information: www.imactheater.org or (631) 549-2787.</p>
        <p>Arts and Entertainment</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
