<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Small Detours for Sweet Rewards</title>
    <meta content="17weekend" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/travel/17weekend.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854931"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEEKEND IN NEW YORK: ICE CREAM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice Cream</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kugel, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ice Cream</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Cream</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DC173FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="987" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Small Detours for Sweet Rewards</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Small Detours for Sweet Rewards</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH KUGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kugel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seth Kugel Weekend in New York column on ice cream shops; list; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>VISITORS to New York City rightfully expect everything here to be unique, or at least different: quirky characters, well-known sights, special subway grime and state-of-the-art price gouging by bottled-water vendors, to name a few.</p>
        <p>But after a sweaty summer's day trip to the Statue of Liberty or down Fifth Avenue or up the Empire State Building, sometimes you want only one thing: ice cream. And it can suddenly seem that all you can find are street vendors hawking $3 Good Humor ice cream sandwiches or trucks dispensing drippy Mister Softee cones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a sweaty summer’s day trip to the Statue of Liberty or down Fifth Avenue or up the Empire State Building, sometimes you want only one thing: ice cream.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>VISITORS to New York City rightfully expect everything here to be unique, or at least different: quirky characters, well-known sights, special subway grime and state-of-the-art price gouging by bottled-water vendors, to name a few.</p>
        <p>But after a sweaty summer's day trip to the Statue of Liberty or down Fifth Avenue or up the Empire State Building, sometimes you want only one thing: ice cream. And it can suddenly seem that all you can find are street vendors hawking $3 Good Humor ice cream sandwiches or trucks dispensing drippy Mister Softee cones.</p>
        <p>Be strong: New York has not opened the greatest museums and attracted the best theater and built the highest skyscrapers just to be outdone on its frozen dairy offerings. If you're willing to go a few steps out of your way, you'll find what you're looking for -- much of it native, some with origins in Los Angeles or France or Italy.</p>
        <p>Say you're leaving the Metropolitan Museum of Art, where vendors ply red-white-and-blue-missile-style Popsicles at the bottom of the steps. Upper Fifth Avenue might be barren of stores, but one street over, on Madison, you have three great choices.</p>
        <p>E.A.T., an upscale deli that is part of the Zabar family, dishes out a tart lime sorbet, tiramisù-flavor ice cream dished out with a chunk of ladyfinger, and other flavors ($4 a scoop, $7 for two).</p>
        <p>If you like your ice cream flavors intense, walk two more blocks to La Maison du Chocolat, the French chocolaterie that doubles as a glacerie in the summer ($4 a scoop, with no discount for gluttons). The sorbets and ice creams are as rich as the chocolate: you might think the shop had jammed a whole mango tree into the mango, concentrated a whole strawberry patch into the strawberry, and a squeezed an entire caramel vine (or whatever) into the caramel.</p>
        <p>The choice for the budget-conscious is Sant Ambroeus, an Italian cafe another block down where it's $3 for a scoop, $4 for two. The catch: flavors are labeled in Italian, meaning if you're not sure whether ''pesca'' is fish or peach, you're going to have to ask. (Seafood sorbet lovers, sorry to disappoint: it's the latter.)</p>
        <p>Ice cream seekers returning from the Statue of Liberty have a tougher time: aside from the Battery Park stands, there is little in the way of ice cream nearby if you want only a single serving.</p>
        <p>But who wants just a single serving? You're just paces from Zaytuna, an upscale deli and grocery right across Battery Place (look for the navy blue awning) that stocks two New York ice cream originals: Ciao Bella, which has stores throughout the city, and the new 5 Boroughs ice cream ($5.29 a pint), which comes in flavors like Staten Island Landfill -- brownies, cherries, fudge -- or South Bronx Cha-Cha Chocolate, spiced up with habanero and chipotle peppers. (There's also Häagen-Dazs, which was born in the Bronx in 1961.)</p>
        <p>If you're viewing the World Trade Center site (or shopping at Century 21), try the Ciao Bella store in the Winter Garden at the World Financial Center. The view of ground zero through plate glass in the Atrium gives an unfettered sense of the site from a building that itself was heavily damaged in the attacks of Sept. 11, 2001. The ice cream might become an afterthought, but it's a tasty one, especially if you get the strawberry balsamic.</p>
        <p>Also within walking distance of the World Trade Center site or City Hall is the Soda Shop, an old-fashioned spot for burgers, banana splits and $5 black-and-white milkshakes.</p>
        <p>On the water at the end of Old Fulton Street, the Brooklyn Ice Cream Factory is an obvious choice for those strolling across the Brooklyn Bridge. (Duck off the bridge at your first opportunity and loop around to the right.) The banana split ($8) is pretty basic, but the stunning Manhattan skyline view is one heck of a bell or a whistle.</p>
        <p>If it's bells and whistles you're looking for, end your Fifth Avenue shopping spree (or your horse carriage trip through Central Park) with a walk to Dylan's Candy Bar. In this living Candy Land, $10 sundaes with names like the Candy Bar Blast or Demolition Cookie Derby are pricey, but come with free oohs and aahs from jealous patrons lapping at their $3.99 cones.</p>
        <p>From Times Square, you can walk east to Bryant Park to get a non-cookie-cutter ice cream sandwich (and some tart lemonade) at the chef Tom Colicchio's 'wichcraft stands.</p>
        <p>If you're at the Empire State Building you are just a few blocks from the popular Los Angeles import Pinkberry, purveyors of frozen yogurt in plain or green-tea flavors. Toppings -- you can get three on a $5.50 medium dish -- are (mostly) healthy, from kiwi and mango to coconut and Fruity Pebbles.</p>
        <p>Its competition, a New York original called Crazy Bananas, is just a block away, and the place to go if your need for refreshment is too urgent to wait in Pinkberry's astonishing line.</p>
        <p>WHEN NOTHING ELSE WILL DO  E.A.T., 1064 Madison Avenue (between 80th and 81st Streets), (212) 772-0022; www.elizabar.com.  La Maison du Chocolat, 1018 Madison Avenue (between 78th and 79th Streets), (212) 744-7117; www.lamaisonduchocolat.com. Also at 30 Rockefeller Center (49th Street entrance), (212) 265-9404.  Sant Ambroeus, 1000 Madison Avenue (between 77th and 78th Streets), (212) 570-2211; www.santambroeus.com.  Zaytuna, 17 Battery Place, (212) 871-6300.  Ciao Bella, World Financial Center, (212) 786-4707, and other locations, including Grand Central Terminal; www.ciaobellagelato.com.  Soda Shop, 125 Chambers Street near West Broadway, (212) 571-1100.  Brooklyn Ice Cream Factory, Fulton Ferry landing plaza, (718) 246-3963.  Dylan's Candy Bar, 1011 Third Avenue at 60th Street, (646) 735-0078; www.dylanscandybar.com.  'wichcraft, at Bryant Park (Avenue of the Americas at 42nd Street) and other locations; www.wichcraftnyc.com.  Pinkberry, 7 West 32nd Street between Fifth Avenue and Broadway, (212) 695-9631; www.pinkberry.com.  Crazy Bananas, 6 East 32nd Street (between Fifth and Madison Avenues), (212) 532-1040; www.crazybananasnyc.com.</p>
        <p>WEEKEND IN NEW YORK: ICE CREAM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
