<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Screenwriters With No Complaints</title>
    <meta content="17ciep" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/movies/17ciep.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854964"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cieply, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McFeely, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markus, Christopher</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">You Kill Me (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">You Kill Me (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E4D7173FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1024" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Screenwriters With No Complaints</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Two Screenwriters With No Complaints</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL CIEPLY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cieply, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on new film You Kill Me, written by two screenwriters, Stephen McFeely and Christopher Markus, who have collaborated amicably for dozen years; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOMETIMES, lore to the contrary notwithstanding, it is good to write for the movies. Especially if you are sipping a soy latte or an Arnold Palmer on a sunny day in the Los Feliz district (a place up the street sells ''vibrational bliss''), with a partner who can grab your thoughts in midair, bobble them around and hand them back before you finish the sentence.</p>
        <p>''I like movies fine, but we're not film school people, so this isn't ---- '' Christopher Markus began, to which Stephen McFeely added, ''A route to director or going to parties,'' because, Mr. Markus concluded, ''I really want to write, and it's the only thing I'm good at.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Co-writers for a dozen years now, Christopher Markus and Stephen McFeely are among the blessed few who get paid to write Hollywood pictures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOMETIMES, lore to the contrary notwithstanding, it is good to write for the movies. Especially if you are sipping a soy latte or an Arnold Palmer on a sunny day in the Los Feliz district (a place up the street sells ''vibrational bliss''), with a partner who can grab your thoughts in midair, bobble them around and hand them back before you finish the sentence.</p>
        <p>''I like movies fine, but we're not film school people, so this isn't ---- '' Christopher Markus began, to which Stephen McFeely added, ''A route to director or going to parties,'' because, Mr. Markus concluded, ''I really want to write, and it's the only thing I'm good at.''</p>
        <p>Miraculously the tag-team conversation tracked.</p>
        <p>Co-writers for a dozen years now, Mr. Markus and Mr. McFeely, both 37, are among the blessed few -- about 1,800 are counted in any given year by the Writers Guild of America, West -- who get paid to write Hollywood pictures. They are already credited with a big one, ''The Chronicles of Narnia: The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe,'' which took in nearly $750 million at the worldwide box office when Disney released it 18 months ago. Two years ago they won an Emmy for their HBO film, ''The Life and Death of Peter Sellers,'' and they have two more ''Narnia'' movies on the way.</p>
        <p>In a brave bit of counterprogramming from IFC Films, their much smaller effort ''You Kill Me'' will open June 22 against Universal's flood-filled big-budget comedy ''Evan Almighty,'' with Steve Carell. Budgeted at about $4 million, ''You Kill Me'' is a black comedy that features Ben Kingsley as an alcoholic hit man who fears he will never kill again if he doesn't stop drinking.</p>
        <p>It was written years ago by the pair, who dreamed up its premise in 1995 while finishing a master's program in writing at the University of California, Davis.</p>
        <p>But it was not actually their first script. That honor belongs to a thriller set in the Napa Valley, which they stuffed in a drawer without ever showing it publicly.</p>
        <p>''We don't talk about that,'' said Mr. McFeely, who had the soy latte and light red hair and beard. To which Mr. Markus, with the Arnold Palmer, for whom hair is no longer much of an issue, added, ''It was just terrible.''</p>
        <p>It is probably safe to say that no serious Hollywood writer remains untouched by the special madness of a craft that sent Faulkner to the bottle, confused William Goldman and led Ben Hecht to write the charmingly titled novel ''I Hate Actors!'' But if the false starts and Barton Fink moments seem suddenly far away for Mr. Markus and Mr. McFeely, that owes much to ''You Kill Me,'' which became a calling card.</p>
        <p>That script got its writers a first agent, opened the door to producers' suites and then helped them leave day jobs: Mr. McFeely was temping a lot at Nickelodeon, while Mr. Markus served as second assistant to a film distribution executive. But the two men quickly learned that nothing is so rare in Hollywood as a truly new idea: That screenplay was long regarded as unmakable by those who found the notion of killer comedy a bit too familiar after ''Grosse Pointe Blank'' in 1997, ''Analyze This'' in 1999 and ''Analyze That'' in 2002.</p>
        <p>''It suddenly became very 'done,' '' Mr. Markus said of a gimmick that had seemed fresh when the two were teaching themselves from books by the screenwriting gurus Lew Hunter and Syd Field.</p>
        <p>Circulating as a writing sample, however, the script attracted fans, about a dozen of whom are now listed among the producers of ''You Kill Me.'' The manager-producer Mike Marcus, once a power at the Creative Artists Agency, helped connect the project with another producer, Carol Baum. Ms. Baum then became a conduit to Mr. Kingsley, around whom the director John Dahl (''Joy Ride,'' ''Rounders'') and his colleagues collected a surprisingly substantial cast that includes Téa Leoni, Luke Wilson, Dennis Farina and Bill Pullman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pullman, as it happened, had once hired Mr. Markus and Mr. McFeely to write a screenplay called ''Screenland,'' about a real-life Southern California murder. That script is still unproduced, but it added to a growing web of connections that have recently boosted the pair into the rarefied stratum of screenwriters who work, quite a lot.</p>
        <p>''For several years, we've been making movies and not writing scripts,'' Mr. McFeely said, acknowledging their good fortune in seeing a series of films, beginning with the Peter Sellers biography, march to production.</p>
        <p>The two have been helped along by a professional affability that marks some of the more successful Hollywood writers of their generation. One pair of young peers, Roberto Orci and Alex Kurtzman, last year went so far as to preview their ''Transformers'' script to a panel of fellows, something not entirely common among wary pros in the past. In a similarly open spirit, Mr. Markus and Mr. McFeely allowed Mr. Marcus, the producer, to push the idiosyncratic ''You Kill Me'' around the Hollywood circuit for years on a handshake, and without much expectation, at least on their part, of results.</p>
        <p>''We thought, 'You're crazy, but if it makes you happy,' '' Mr. Markus said.</p>
        <p>Oddly enough, their starter script made it to the screen with few changes, thanks in part to its low budget and hurry-up production schedule, and to a rather relaxed sense that its peculiar story about a Polish gangster in recovery would never shake the world. ''Why change it, because it's not going to open in the end of June against 'Evan Almighty'?'' Mr. Markus said of the prevailing attitude.</p>
        <p>More seriously, Mr. Marcus, the producer, noted that Mr. Dahl was fiercely protective of the screenplay. ''He just defended the script tooth and nail,'' he said. So to an unusual degree the movie belongs to those who dreamed it up. Even its settings, San Francisco and Buffalo, are personal: Mr. McFeely grew up in one city, Mr. Markus in the other.</p>
        <p>And for the moment, at least -- ''Knock wood,'' Mr. McFeely said -- it is indeed good to write for the movies.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
