<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Those Eyes. That Grin. Those Ding Dongs.</title>
    <meta content="17evans" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/arts/television/17evans.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854980"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DVD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Evans, Greg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Estrada, Erik</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CHiPs (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Estrada, Erik</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E0D7173FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Those Eyes. That Grin. Those Ding Dongs.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Those Eyes. That Grin. Those Ding Dongs.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GREG EVANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Evans, Greg</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes 1977-83 motorcycle-cop television series CHiPS, starring Erik Estrada, which has recently been released on DVD; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN nearly every episode of the first season of ''CHiPs'' a Volkswagen Beetle the color of a blood orange putters somewhere in the background, riding down the highway or parked at an illicit auto chop shop. An odd thing to notice, perhaps, but then, the featherweight 1977-83 motorcycle-cop series, which gave television one of its earliest and most popular Latino action heroes in Erik Estrada, leaves plenty of room for a not-unsatisfied mind to wander. Take it from someone who has counted (for a while anyway) the Beetles in it.</p>
        <p>And take this: Worse shows than ''CHiPs'' have been saved by lesser forces than the cut of Mr. Estrada's uniform or the swagger behind his smile. In a year when the suicide of the ''Chico and the Man'' star Freddie Prinze pretty much obliterated TV's headlining Hispanic population, Mr. Estrada in 1977 was as exotic as he was likable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“CHiPs,” the featherweight 1977-83 motorcycle-cop series starring Erik Estrada, leaves plenty of room for a not-unsatisfied mind to wander.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN nearly every episode of the first season of ''CHiPs'' a Volkswagen Beetle the color of a blood orange putters somewhere in the background, riding down the highway or parked at an illicit auto chop shop. An odd thing to notice, perhaps, but then, the featherweight 1977-83 motorcycle-cop series, which gave television one of its earliest and most popular Latino action heroes in Erik Estrada, leaves plenty of room for a not-unsatisfied mind to wander. Take it from someone who has counted (for a while anyway) the Beetles in it.</p>
        <p>And take this: Worse shows than ''CHiPs'' have been saved by lesser forces than the cut of Mr. Estrada's uniform or the swagger behind his smile. In a year when the suicide of the ''Chico and the Man'' star Freddie Prinze pretty much obliterated TV's headlining Hispanic population, Mr. Estrada in 1977 was as exotic as he was likable.</p>
        <p>Ubiquitous if not familiar playing street toughs and gang members on the episodic television of the era, Mr. Estrada was cast on ''CHiPs'' against his usual type, playing Officer Francis Llewellyn Poncherello, better known as Ponch. The swarthy half of the show's dark-and-fair buddy equation, Ponch was the crucial ingredient of an inflexibly formulaic show. His every quirk -- from a diet of chocolate Ding Dongs to the beagle eyes that defused the temper of his by-the-book sergeant -- was designed to seduce the young viewers (boys mostly, at least at first) who were susceptible to its easy charms. Ponch (even the name is waggish as a puppy's) stood in for all the pre-teenage boys stuck home watching ''CHiPs'' at 8 on a Saturday night. And for their sisters: the underwear model's torso that Mr. Estrada displayed in many, many episodes.</p>
        <p>The show itself was a genial enough combination of ''Adam-12'' and ''Starsky &amp; Hutch,'' though neither of those had the temperament for guest appearances by both H. R. Pufnstuf and Phyllis Diller. The light action series followed the adventures, both on and off the road, of two Kawasaki-riding officers of the California Highway Patrol (hence, CHiPs). Younger readers, be warned: The words ''action'' and ''adventure'' might suggest to you a level of action and adventure mostly absent on ''CHiPs,'' and not just because gunplay was virtually nonexistent. Essentially the show, when not fixating on chrome or skidding cars, tagged along with Ponch and his partner as they snaked through freeway traffic and youthful bachelorhood, handing out tickets, busting low-stakes criminals and flirting with the tannest in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Playing Hutch to Mr. Estrada's Starsky was Larry Wilcox, the blond and, no getting around it, blander Officer Jon Baker. The early episodes struck a fair balance between the streetwise Ponch and his more stable, country-boyish partner, but eventually ''CHiPs'' couldn't help showing which son was the favorite. In fairness to Mr. Wilcox, easily the more polished actor, few mortals could have fared any better sharing four lanes of pavement with as shameless an attention seeker as the toothsome Mr. Estrada.</p>
        <p>Occasionally the show's writers tried to sex up the Baker character, giving him an apartment in a singles condo development, where the only things swinging seem to be the hanging ferns. His brown and orange one-bedroom unit is as fussy as the living rooms many ''CHiPs'' fans were no doubt eager to escape.</p>
        <p>Compare that with Ponch's messy abode, a mobile home stocked with a gumball machine, guitar and dumbbells. This hideout was a kid's idea of bachelor paradise, not to mention the spiritual precursor to the boathouse Don Johnson's Sonny Crockett would soon share with an alligator on ''Miami Vice.'' The prominent N.R.A. poster in Ponch's RV marked an attention to macho detail neutered in Jon's fussy plaid-pillowed condo.</p>
        <p>In uniform, though, Jon was the more responsible, if less well fitted, generally showing the ropes to a greener Ponch. A typical episode -- and no small part of the show's comfort-food appeal, even today, is that every episode is so thoroughly typical, one suspects the red VW might have been an ingredient in the strict recipe -- would have the partners on the lookout for a Rolls-Royce thief, say, or a purse-snatching tow-truck driver preying on stranded female motorists. In one oddball episode a menacing, mud-throwing lunatic causes no end of roadside drama.</p>
        <p>And those were the serious crimes. The series, especially early on, pushed the slapstick button pretty frequently: Ponch meets up with a spilled truckload of glue or a leaking canister of nitrous oxide. To get a good sense of the difficulties inherent in finding laughs in crime and highway collisions, watch the episode called ''Crack Up.'' An injured Jon shares a hospital ward with a crying-on-the-inside ex-vaudevillian joke machine played by Ms. Diller. Here was a cop show trying for texture.</p>
        <p>GREG EVANS</p>
        <p>DVD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
