<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Woman Warriors</title>
    <meta content="Egan.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/books/review/Egan-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855317"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Thompson, Jean</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Throw Like a Girl: Stories (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E4DF1F30F934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Woman Warriors</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Woman Warriors</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER EGAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THROW LIKE A GIRL</p>
        <p>Stories.</p>
        <p>By Jean Thompson.</p>
        <p>291 pp. Simon &amp; Schuster.</p>
        <p>Paper, $13.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The characters in Jean Thompson’s stories are smart and strong, but drawn to subpar men.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THROW LIKE A GIRL</p>
        <p>Stories.</p>
        <p>By Jean Thompson.</p>
        <p>291 pp. Simon &amp; Schuster.</p>
        <p>Paper, $13.</p>
        <p>To appreciate the delicious irony of the title of ''Throw Like a Girl,'' Jean Thompson's boldly unconventional new story collection, you need to consider it in context: in the title story, two college friends have reunited in New York, where one of them is living with her dyspeptic boyfriend, known to the reader as ''What's-his-name.'' One night, after What's-his-name has been especially pillish, the young women begin picking up chunks of broken sidewalk and hurling them at him. ''He couldn't ignore us any longer when we hit him, pretty hard, once between his shoulder blades and then beneath his ear,'' Thompson writes. What's-his-name's shrill response before running away -- ''You're crazy, you know that? Besides, you throw like a girl!'' -- prompts hilarity from the women. ''You're so much smarter than me,'' says What's-his-name's girlfriend. ''I don't see you with a jerk.''</p>
        <p>''That's because I'm alone,'' the narrator replies.</p>
        <p>Welcome to the feminine cosmos of ''Throw Like a Girl,'' whose population includes some of the most domineering dames to appear in recent fiction. We're talking women who say things like (a mother describing her daughter's boyfriend in ''Holy Week''): ''He was narrow-chested and his hips were so skinny that they seemed only a kind of attachment mechanism for his penis.'' Or (in ''A Woman Taken in Adultery''): ''We were at a dinner party. Me with my husband, who I had trained to sit up and beg food from the table.'' Girl children are equally corrosive; the first story, ''The Brat,'' begins, ''She hated her mother and she hated her father too, at least when he was around to be hated.''</p>
        <p>Yet for all their rhetorical bluster, the girls and women in Thompson's fourth story collection are mostly trapped, helpless and unfulfilled. What's-his-name's girlfriend ends up marrying him, divorcing him, becoming an alcoholic and dying of breast cancer, alone, in her 40s. ''Throw Like a Girl'' finds Thompson preoccupied with a paradox: why do tough, independent-minded women who know they're smarter than the men around them still end up needing those losers, thus engineering their own disappointment? Thompson explores this question in restless, contrarian prose whose bristling energy seems almost to fight with the lines that contain it -- often to electrifying effect. Of an overzealous boss in ''A Normal Life,'' she writes, ''He instituted weekly staff meetings where coffee and violently sugared pastries were served.'' In ''The Brat,'' she writes, ''Her mother went to hug her and there was a moment when their bodies jostled together like cattle in a chute and that was awful, awful.''</p>
        <p>Thompson appears to have made a pact with her crusty protagonists to renounce every literary convention traditionally perceived as feminine: sentimentality, pathos, sincerity, melodrama. This approach marks a departure from her last story collection, the masterly ''Who Do You Love,'' a finalist for the National Book Award, in which she teased away her characters' edginess and grit to reveal the vulnerable shapes of their hope. In ''Throw Like a Girl,'' Thompson's range feels narrower and more extreme, and the results are more erratic. Some of the collection's biggest satisfactions happen line by line, thanks to Thompson's effortless ability to tip her prose into the universal. ''The sadness had gotten too deep inside of me,'' the protagonist of ''The Family Barcus'' says. ''That first sadness, which comes from family, and never entirely goes away.'' These stories abound with absent fathers -- mothers, too -- who create a kind of template for loss in the girls who miss them. In ''Hunger,'' a young woman wonders about her institutionalized mother: ''Had she ever done mother things, held and rocked her, sung songs, counted her fingers and toes? It's nothing Leslie can call to mind, but she thinks it must have happened. You had to know a thing in order to miss it. Her mother is the thing lost, the shape of her hunger.''</p>
        <p>Hunger, both sexual and emotional, is the driving force in many of the women here, but it's a hunger real life can't satisfy. Again and again they fall for illusions that will only hurt them later. Primary among these is adultery. ''At the outset of an affair you look at crowds of dreary people, and you know you seem just as ordinary as any of them, and yet you have this whole hidden life blazing up inside you,'' says the narrator of ''A Woman Taken in Adultery.'' ''And maybe they do too, maybe the world is full of jolly secrets, and people are more interesting than you believed. But they aren't.'' This same discovery is the occasion for ''A Normal Life,'' about a man and a woman in an adulterous affair who break up their own families, alienating their children, only to find, once they've married each other, that the frisson is gone. Eventually the wife escapes to Thailand, where she tries to help a former prostitute now working with a Christian relief organization, but that, too, proves disillusioning. ''She'd had some goopy notion of self-sacrifice, or maybe it was self-punishment, of making amends. Living humbly in service to others. Being worthy of redemption. So much for that.''</p>
        <p>Thompson has set herself a punishing technical challenge in this volume; a literary system without sentiment or faith is one in which the basic machinery of most short-story writing -- transformation, epiphany, self-discovery -- can't function. As a result, these stories have a pleasantly drifty, off-kilter feel, with events accreting slowly and then suddenly, sometimes randomly. As always, the pitfalls of the strategy are laid bare in the weakest stories, like ''The Inside Passage,'' about a woman wandering around Alaska, compulsively phoning the married man who has dumped her. Here, the lack of dramatic payoff feels simply flat, and the verbal swagger of Thompson's protagonist becomes monotonous. But in some of the best stories, like the title story, or ''The Five Senses,'' or ''Lost,'' about a doomed love affair between a young woman and a Vietnam vet, Thompson's resistance to more conventional emotional structures feels bracing and strange. The most successful stories in ''Throw Like a Girl'' tend to be those in which some years pass, allowing retrospect to afford its own wise synthesis.</p>
        <p>It's a testament to Thompson's writing that she's able to wrest so much variety and entertainment from a rather scourged patch of literary landscape. Now that she's done it, I'm hoping she'll let some of the ''girl'' back into her throw.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Egan's most recent novel, ''The Keep,'' will be published in paperback this summer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jennifer Egan's most recent novel, ''The Keep,'' will be published in paperback this summer.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
