<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Birdies, Bogeys and Stogies</title>
    <meta content="17goods" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/business/17goods.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855183"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OPENERS: THE GOODS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koerner, Brendan I</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burkholder, Wayne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/The Goods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Operations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cigars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cigars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0DA153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="606" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Birdies, Bogeys and Stogies</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Birdies, Bogeys and Stogies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRENDAN I. KOERNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Koerner, Brendan I</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on HeaterHolder, curved piece of stainless steel meant for cradling lighted cigar that can be attached to golf bag; inventor Wayne Burkholder estimates he has sold about 250 of devices priced at $25; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRANSCONTINENTAL airline travel can be excruciatingly dull, especially for passengers without iPods, laptops or adequate reading material. But the tedium of a six-hour flight can also be the mother of invention, as Wayne Burkholder discovered in the fall of 2005.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burkholder and his family were on a red-eye flight from San Francisco to Boston, and he had neglected to pack any books or entertainment gadgets. ''I read all the magazines in the back of the seat, then thought, 'Well, what do I do now?' '' said Mr. Burkholder, who lives in Middleboro, Mass. So he asked the flight attendant for a stack of cocktail napkins, on which he sketched out ideas for a product that he had long dreamed of inventing: a cigar holder that attaches to a golf bag.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tedium of a six-hour flight can be the mother of invention, as Wayne Burkholder discovered in the fall of 2005.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TRANSCONTINENTAL airline travel can be excruciatingly dull, especially for passengers without iPods, laptops or adequate reading material. But the tedium of a six-hour flight can also be the mother of invention, as Wayne Burkholder discovered in the fall of 2005.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burkholder and his family were on a red-eye flight from San Francisco to Boston, and he had neglected to pack any books or entertainment gadgets. ''I read all the magazines in the back of the seat, then thought, 'Well, what do I do now?' '' said Mr. Burkholder, who lives in Middleboro, Mass. So he asked the flight attendant for a stack of cocktail napkins, on which he sketched out ideas for a product that he had long dreamed of inventing: a cigar holder that attaches to a golf bag.</p>
        <p>By the time his plane landed at Logan Airport in Boston, he had designed the HeaterHolder, a curved piece of stainless steel meant for cradling a lighted stogie. The product, he said, solves a quandary faced by countless weekend golfers who enhance their recreation with tobacco.</p>
        <p>''Out on the golf course, there's really not a good place to put your cigar,'' said Mr. Burkholder, a sales director for a school supply company. Many golfers, he observed, balance their cigars on their carts, but this is hardly a foolproof method. And if a stogie drops to the grass, it should probably be thrown out because golf courses use chemicals to maintain their greens and fairways, he said.</p>
        <p>In 2003, Mr. Burkholder's wife, Suzanne, bought him a fold-up cigar holder designed for golfers. Though appreciative of the gift, Mr. Burkholder wasn't impressed with the product's performance. ''It was a pain in the neck,'' he said, describing how he had to stick the holder in the ground at every hole, much as he would a golfing tee.</p>
        <p>On that 2005 flight to Boston, the solution came to him: take advantage of the rain-hood snap. This button, included on virtually all golf bags, secures a cover that keeps clubs from getting soaked. But the snap isn't used in pleasant weather, which is precisely when golfers smoke cigars. Mr. Burkholder designed the HeaterHolder to fasten onto this small protrusion.</p>
        <p>He took his best napkin drawing to a metal-stamping shop in Providence, R.I., and had some prototypes made. He distributed them to friends and asked for feedback, while also testing a few himself.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burkholder was flummoxed by how easily the early HeaterHolders could be lost: if he brushed his bag against a tree or shrub, the holder would sometimes pop free. So he added a fail-safe device: a safety chain that clips onto a bag's main strap.</p>
        <p>The HeaterHolder, which went on sale last December, is a bit of a manufacturing Frankenstein: the metal curves are made in Providence, the chains in Attleboro, Mass., and the snaps in Cranston, R.I. Assembly takes place in Mr. Burkholder's dining room.</p>
        <p>He estimates that he has sold about 250 of the HeaterHolders, priced at $25, primarily through his Web site, HeaterHolder.com. They are also available at a few retail stores, including Jack's Tobacco in Brookfield, Wis.</p>
        <p>Sales picked up sharply, Mr. Burkholder said, after the HeaterHolder was featured in an issue of Cigar Aficionado magazine.</p>
        <p>He also sells fancier versions of the product: one with a gold finish goes for $125, and one in solid sterling silver is priced at $225. He said these costlier holders were meant to appeal to golfers' wives, as birthday or Christmas gifts for their husbands.</p>
        <p>Of course, women who enjoy puffing stogies while golfing are free to buy HeaterHolders for their own use.</p>
        <p>OPENERS: THE GOODS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
