<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Rush Is On to Improve the Giants' Defense</title>
    <meta content="17giants" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/sports/football/17giants.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855256"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Philadelphia Eagles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Philadelphia Eagles</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Lewis, Tim</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Strahan, Michael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Umenyiora, Osi</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDF123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Rush Is On to Improve the Giants' Defense</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Rush Is On to Improve the Giants’ Defense</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., June 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Coaching the Giants' defense is new for Steve Spagnuolo, but watching the Giants' defense is not.</p>
        <p>Spagnuolo spent eight seasons as an assistant coach with the Philadelphia Eagles, a team the Giants play at least twice every season. Hired as the Giants' defensive coordinator in January, he says the team has the personnel to improve significantly over last season's disappointing defensive unit, which ranked 25th among the N.F.L.'s 32 teams.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Former Eagles linebackers coach and new Giants defensive coordinator Steve Spagnuolo is looking for the team to have a more consistent pass rush.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Coaching the Giants' defense is new for Steve Spagnuolo, but watching the Giants' defense is not.</p>
        <p>Spagnuolo spent eight seasons as an assistant coach with the Philadelphia Eagles, a team the Giants play at least twice every season. Hired as the Giants' defensive coordinator in January, he says the team has the personnel to improve significantly over last season's disappointing defensive unit, which ranked 25th among the N.F.L.'s 32 teams.</p>
        <p>''We're trying to find who we are, and what we are,'' Spagnuolo said after the Giants completed a three-day minicamp Friday. ''I look at it as a great challenge and I'm excited about it.''</p>
        <p>Spagnuolo replaced Tim Lewis, who was fired in January and is now a defensive backs coach with the Carolina Panthers. As a linebackers coach with the Eagles, Spagnuolo worked under the defensive coordinator Jim Johnson, who likes to blitz as much as any coach in the league.</p>
        <p>While Spagnuolo may not completely adopt Philadelphia's blitz-happy approach, he is looking for the Giants to have a more consistent pass rush. Mathias Kiwanuka, who had 4 sacks and 23 quarterback hurries as a rookie defensive end last season, has been converted to linebacker. Switching Kiwanuka to linebacker will put him on the field with the Giants' two best pass rushers, defensive ends Michael Strahan and Osi Umenyiora. Kiwanuka welcomed the change.</p>
        <p>''I'm involved a lot more now than I was at defensive end,'' Kiwanuka said. ''It's fun. You get your hands on the ball. You want the sacks, you want the interceptions, you want the big hits, all that stuff. I'm happy to be on the field and working toward a starting spot.''</p>
        <p>Coach Tom Coughlin has been impressed with Kiwanuka's approach to the position switch.</p>
        <p>''We are to the point now where he is a presence out there,'' Coughlin said. ''When he rushes, he is obviously a difficult guy to block, and also he is a difficult guy to get the ball over when he is rushing. We have gone into some of our different packages, and he has been able to show that he is comfortable getting himself aligned properly.</p>
        <p>''We have a ways to go. He has to learn, he has to play it. He has to be put in situations where he has to make split-second decisions. He has to be able to fire from any position and not tip his intentions.''</p>
        <p>Some players complained that Lewis was too critical during the final stages of his tenure. Spagnuolo's more even-tempered approach seemed to be an early hit.</p>
        <p>''He's more of a teacher than a screamer,'' defensive end Justin Tuck said. ''We haven't seen that screaming side of him yet. But he's hands on, with every position, every facet. He's correcting everybody. That's a good thing. Sometimes you get a defensive coordinator who might favor a certain position. It's early, but from the early perspective, you have that sense that he's an all-around defensive coordinator.''</p>
        <p>Whenever the football hit the ground during minicamp, defensive players were required to recover it and run the other way, even if the play had been blown dead. The Giants forced 28 turnovers last season, but that paled in comparison to the Chicago Bears, who forced a league-leading 44.</p>
        <p>''That's our big focus this year, creating more turnovers,'' Tuck said. ''You win football games like that. It's been a emphasis in this minicamp. We want to be an up-in-your-face, blitzing, attacking, turnover-causing defense. If we're blessed enough to stay healthy this year, I feel you're going to see the Giants' defense of old resurface.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't seem like we have a new coordinator. Guys are real comfortable with the system. We're excited to get to training camp.''</p>
        <p>The Giants will need a healthy Strahan if they are to improve on defense. He missed seven games last season with a foot injury. Strahan did not participate in individual drills during minicamp, but Spagnuolo sounded confident Strahan would be ready when the Giants report to training camp July 27.</p>
        <p>''I got a lot of respect for Mike Strahan, and I'm pretty certain of what he is,'' Spagnuolo said. ''Playing against him, he's a class act, and he assured me the other day he'd be ready to go. He just kind of gave me that wink.''</p>
        <p>Coughlin also received positive vibrations from Strahan.</p>
        <p>''This guy is very proud, he loves to play,'' said Coughlin. ''Let's face it, he is an exceptional athlete. He has been able to do this for as long as he has done it. To me, he is determined to come back and have another outstanding year, and we are all rooting like heck for him.''</p>
        <p>Once the Giants begin the season, they will have a far better read on their defense. But the players departed minicamp ready to embrace Spagnuolo's changes.</p>
        <p>''If I had to use one word, I'd say we'll be more of an attacking defense,'' Tuck said. ''He wants to utilize the speed that we have. His defense fits our personnel, and we're excited.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
