<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shirley Lasker and Stephen Fox</title>
    <meta content="17vows" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/fashion/weddings/17vows.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855097"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS: VOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lasker, Shirley (Shirley Fox)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fox, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/Vows</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DB153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="880" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shirley Lasker and Stephen Fox</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shirley Lasker and Stephen Fox</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC V. COPAGE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>POLITICALLY, Dr. Stephen Fox and Shirley Lasker are a close match -- both wear their activism on their sleeve. You'd think, then, that romance between the two would be smooth sailing.</p>
        <p>It wasn't. Take December 2004, for instance. That's when Dr. Fox, who heads Star Kids, a Rockland County-based sports program for youths facing drug and other problems, first told Ms. Lasker, a councilwoman in Clarkstown, N.Y., that he wanted more than a political alliance with her.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Stephen Fox and Shirley Lasker married at the Chart House restaurant in Dobbs Ferry, N.Y. Rabbi Renée Feller led the ceremony overlooking the Hudson River, before 92 guests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>POLITICALLY, Dr. Stephen Fox and Shirley Lasker are a close match -- both wear their activism on their sleeve. You'd think, then, that romance between the two would be smooth sailing.</p>
        <p>It wasn't. Take December 2004, for instance. That's when Dr. Fox, who heads Star Kids, a Rockland County-based sports program for youths facing drug and other problems, first told Ms. Lasker, a councilwoman in Clarkstown, N.Y., that he wanted more than a political alliance with her.</p>
        <p>He proceeded to woo Ms. Lasker, but with extreme caution. ''I was just getting out of a marriage, and she was just extricating herself from a relationship,'' said Dr. Fox, 64. He said that ''wishful thinking'' had colored his three previous marriages. ''I'd take a few attributes that I liked, mainly physical, and make up the rest,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lasker, 57, whose first marriage had ended in divorce in 1989, was impressed by his honesty. ''He'd made mistakes in the past, and I related to that,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The couple first met at a July 2004 gathering of the Clarkstown Town Council, which was deciding whether the town should buy a local boatyard.</p>
        <p>Dr. Fox, a retired podiatrist and a longtime boater, attended the meeting to support the purchase. He wanted Star Kids to start a maritime ecology program at the boatyard.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lasker, who is also a special education teacher at the Orange-Ulster Boces in Goshen, N.Y., found her way to politics as a leader of a fight in the 1990s against what was planned to be one of the country's largest malls, in West Nyack, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lasker said her activism was rooted in being the child of Holocaust survivors. ''I've always felt that you have to do something to make life better,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Although Ms. Lasker lost the mall fight (but succeeded in helping to limit its size), the effort ultimately inspired her to run for office.</p>
        <p>Dr. Fox's evolution began in 1992, when macular degeneration was diagnosed in his left eye. He was then forced to give up his surgical practice and reinvent himself.</p>
        <p>He tried his hand at building modular houses, which proved to be far more ''complicated, difficult and contentious'' than expected, he said, adding of his workmen, ''They'd look at me and say, 'Yo, Cupcake, hand me that hammer.''</p>
        <p>In 2002, while volunteering as a skate guard at an ice rink, he said he noticed, ''There were no Hispanic, Asian or black kids on the ice, even though they are in the community.'' He started Star Kids, modeling it after a hockey program in Harlem.</p>
        <p>The day after he attended the Clarkstown meeting in 2004, Dr. Fox called Ms. Lasker -- not yet to romance her, but to pitch Star Kids and his boatyard idea. As they began meeting regularly, Ms. Lasker was becoming smitten with him, she recalled.</p>
        <p>''He's dynamic, charismatic,'' she said. She told him she had left her boyfriend, hoping that Dr. Fox ''would take the bait.'' She recalled his reply: ''I have a friend you might be interested in.''</p>
        <p>But a few months later he, too, was smitten, at first by her commitment to social causes. He then noticed she had ''terrific lips, great skin,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Over the next year and a half, Ms. Lasker and Dr. Fox cautiously engaged in a series of what Dr. Fox called ''interviews.'' They talked about how their personal, professional and financial goals meshed, as well as their recreational preferences.</p>
        <p>One issue Ms. Lasker had to think hard about was his previous marriages. ''He didn't blame his ex's the way some men do,'' she said. ''The way he explained it, he learned a lot about the choices he made, and that reassured me.''</p>
        <p>But in the spring of last year, when he told her he wanted to retire in the Southeast, that assurance unraveled. She told him she could retire early from teaching, but not abandon her commitment to Clarkstown or move away from her children, Rebecca Fisher, now 29, and David Fisher, 27. Dr. Fox said he discussed the situation with a men's group he attends and concluded that, ''I can either get my way or be with her.''</p>
        <p>He chose her. But when he suggested that they live together, she would have none of it. ''Without the commitment of marriage, it's too easy not to work on a relationship, and to just walk away,'' she said. Last summer the pair traveled on his cabin cruiser, Fox Tales, and visited the New England coast.</p>
        <p>''By the end of the summer I was more in love with her than ever,'' he said. In August, while anchored at Point Judith, R.I., he said: ''I dropped to one knee on the sand at sunset in front of a bunch of strangers and proposed. She said, 'Yes.' ''</p>
        <p>They married June 10 at the Chart House restaurant in Dobbs Ferry, N.Y. Rabbi Renée Feller led the ceremony overlooking the Hudson River, before 92 guests, including Ms. Lasker's children and Ryan, Dr. Fox's 20-year-old son.</p>
        <p>''Too often, right after the wedding, come the therapy bills,'' Dr. Fox said. But because they had asked each other all of the difficult questions in their ''interviews,'' he said, beaming, ''We don't have to do it in our lives.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS: VOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
