<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prenatal Scare</title>
    <meta content="Seymour.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/books/review/Seymour-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855328"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Nature of Monsters, The (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E3DF1F30F934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="856" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prenatal Scare</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Prenatal Scare</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIRANDA SEYMOUR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE NATURE OF MONSTERS</p>
        <p>By Clare Clark.</p>
        <p>382 pp. Harcourt. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Clare Clark’s historical novel, a mad scientist experiments on pregnant women.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE NATURE OF MONSTERS</p>
        <p>By Clare Clark.</p>
        <p>382 pp. Harcourt. $25.</p>
        <p>Clare Clark's first novel, published in 2005, was inauspiciously -- but accurately -- titled. ''The Great Stink'' offered a richly imagined re-creation of Victorian London's sewers, a murky labyrinth in which a mildly crazy ex-soldier, newly employed as an engineer, discovers a corpse and finds himself suspected of murder. Praised for the ingenuity of its plotting, this accomplished book also won plaudits for the authenticity of its detail and its almost queasily intense exuberance. Clark, who paid generous acknowledgment to the inspiration of Peter Ackroyd's pyrotechnic style, joined him as a highflier, soaring through a dreamscape of her own imagining, yet grounding it in the bricks, mortar and mud of a well-researched past. Her strikingly well-written book was also huge fun to read.</p>
        <p>Second novels, when they follow such a promising start, tend to disappoint. But not this time. In ''The Nature of Monsters,'' Clark again shows an impressive ability to combine historical accuracy with vivid language and a strong plot, confirming her claim to a place in historical city-lit by returning to London for a tale of mystery, skulduggery and (in what seems set to become a hallmark of her work) intensely described physical sensation. Her initial inspiration, revealed in an author's note, was a visit to Sir Christopher Wren's masterpiece, the dome of St. Paul's Cathedral, with which the architect crowned his re-creation of the London skyline after the ravages of the Great Fire of 1666.</p>
        <p>This audacious image looms above an absorbing narrative that derives much of its drama from the superstition still governing the medical world 50 years after the fire. In the energetic, speculative, socially mobile urban society of the early 18th century, maternal impression, the idea that a child's appearance was directed by the mother's experiences, found advocates among London physicians as easily as it did among myth-fed country folk. Credulous pamphlets, proposing that one glimpse of a showman's monkey might cause a pregnant woman to give birth to an ape, were keenly debated. Some medical men even believed that a controlled environment -- the use of fear, aggression, threats and isolation -- could bring about the breeding of a monster.</p>
        <p>Clark's prologue hints at just such a birth. In the year of the Great Fire, a pregnant woman escapes the flames and gives birth to a boy, Grayson Black, whose face is hideously disfigured by a scarlet birthmark. His obsession, as a grown man, is with proving the connection between a blemished body and the mother's experience.</p>
        <p>Black, the demented apothecary, is the only one-dimensional element in Clark's absorbing novel. She shows more skill in choosing her narrator -- a shrewd, tough country girl to whom, when she is sent to London as the apothecary's servant, the world of the city will seem alien and terrifying, yet also exhilarating. Showing the city through Eliza Tally's astonished eyes, Clark enables her readers to hear, smell and feel the clamor of teeming streets, thrusting bodies and probing hands. Deftly, Clark conjures up her minor characters -- a chandler's wife, ''chins shivering like a pork jelly upon their dish of lace'' -- with a vivacity that sometimes threatens to undermine her leading players: Eliza the pregnant narrator; Mary, the simple-minded girl whose fate as a young mother and victim Eliza will take into her own hands; and, in the dark, furtive world of Swan Street, tucked beside St. Paul's, the apothecary who dreams of plucking monsters from his servants' bellies.</p>
        <p>This is not a book for the fainthearted; some of its images are both disquieting and memorable. (In one startling scene, Mary mourns the savagely butchered corpse of a pet monkey, which she has nursed as her own baby, at the breast.) The language sometimes feels contrived: in one of its many incarnations, the cathedral dome displays its lead struts as fingers pressing down upon a still-dark skull, mimicking the apothecary's attentive care of his monster-breeders. It may also seem a little too good to be true that simple-minded Mary, despite her misshapen face and body, should have a disposition of angelic sweetness, and that it should be this saintly halfwit who teaches sharp-witted Eliza the nature of love.</p>
        <p>But such quibbles come to mind only after the spell of Clark's story has begun to wear off. What remains -- and provides a more lasting pleasure -- is the remarkable way that life has been breathed into the past. Arriving in London, Eliza prepares herself for a city close to hell, a place whose very name conveys a whiff of brimstone to her apprehensive mind. Instead, standing astonished on the heights of Hampstead Hill and gazing down at the dome that floats in majesty above the smoke-laden city, she registers the unexpected sweetness of air after rain, of ''the green river taste of freshly washed skies.'' The image can't be bettered. It's apt, precise and lovely.</p>
        <p>As a storyteller, Clark is endowed with verve and intelligence, but her larger gift, dazzlingly in evidence throughout both her fine novels, lies in the originality of her imagination. She gives us a world that feels alive and intense, magnificently raw.</p>
        <p>Miranda Seymour's latest book is ''In My Father's House: Elegy for an Obsessive Love.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Miranda Seymour's latest book is ''In My Father's House: Elegy for an Obsessive Love.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
