<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Will Blackstone Have the Honor of Its Own Tax Law?</title>
    <meta content="17deal" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/business/yourmoney/17deal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DEALBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/DealBook</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Blackstone Group</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Fortress Investment Llc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Baucus, Max</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Grassley, Charles E</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Schwarzman, Stephen A</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00EEDA153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Will Blackstone Have the Honor of Its Own Tax Law?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Will Blackstone Have the Honor of Its Own Tax Law?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAST week, Uncle Sam made his first foray into possibly raising taxes on the private equity and hedge fund industry with what Wall Street has dubbed ''the Blackstone bill.''</p>
        <p>After suggesting for months that a new tax regime might be imposed on the two booming sectors, Senator Max Baucus, the Montana Democrat who leads the Senate Finance Committee, and Senator Charles E. Grassley of Iowa, the ranking Republican member, introduced a bill on Thursday paving the way for an increase on any publicly traded funds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Uncle Sam has made his first foray into possibly raising taxes on the private equity and hedge fund industry with what Wall Street has dubbed “the Blackstone bill.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAST week, Uncle Sam made his first foray into possibly raising taxes on the private equity and hedge fund industry with what Wall Street has dubbed ''the Blackstone bill.''</p>
        <p>After suggesting for months that a new tax regime might be imposed on the two booming sectors, Senator Max Baucus, the Montana Democrat who leads the Senate Finance Committee, and Senator Charles E. Grassley of Iowa, the ranking Republican member, introduced a bill on Thursday paving the way for an increase on any publicly traded funds.</p>
        <p>In practice, however, the bill hardly casts a wide net. It appears to be seeking only one big fish: Stephen A. Schwarzman, the chief executive of the Blackstone Group. Mr. Schwarzman has spent the last week on a road show drumming up interest from investors for his firm's initial public offering of stock, which had been scheduled for as early as next week.</p>
        <p>The offering is already laboring under the impact that escalating interest rates would have on Blackstone's finances and deal making. The addition of a possible tax increase could mean that the offering's valuation could be reduced -- possibly as much as 20 percent -- or delayed. Blackstone, citing the ''quiet period'' for stock offerings, declined to comment.</p>
        <p>An aide for the Senate Finance Committee, who requested anonymity, scoffed at the idea that the tax proposal was specifically aimed at Mr. Schwarzman. ''I wouldn't say that,'' the aide said, adding that Blackstone has been pummeled enough and its ''ears are already bleeding.'' Senator Baucus and Senator Grassley would not comment beyond the statement they made Thursday.</p>
        <p>The bill would increase the tax rate to 35 percent from 15 percent on publicly traded partnerships that derive most of their income from asset management and financial services, effectively treating such firms -- Blackstone is one of the most prominent -- as ordinary corporations.</p>
        <p>But the bill hardly touches the private equity and hedge fund industry as a whole because it goes after only publicly traded firms -- and virtually all private equity firms and hedge funds are private. Only about a handful of publicly traded firms would be affected by the bill. The biggest is the Fortress Investment Group. Even then, those firms would not have to pay the increased tax rate until 2012, and by then some new senator might come along and seek to repeal the measure. Despite the time lag, Fortress lost 7.7 percent of its stock market value last week.</p>
        <p>Of course, the bill would indirectly affect all the other private equity firms and hedge funds that have been chomping at the bit to go public. A virtual traffic jam had been forming on the initial-public-offering runway behind Blackstone. Now, those firms are likely to reconsider.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwarzman agrees; he said Thursday that he believes that the government is ''going to try and stop future offerings from happening.''</p>
        <p>If other private equity firms, like the Carlyle Group and Apollo Management, decide against going public -- or decide to do so instead in Europe, where they can avoid the tax increase -- the greater transparency that regulators, analysts and investors have been avidly seeking from funds will probably not happen.</p>
        <p>From a purely economic perspective, the proposed law would be unlikely to raise more than a modicum of money for the Treasury, but then again, legislators are not pursuing this matter just to fill government coffers. Even so, there is a possibility that publicly traded fund companies would fork over far more in taxes to Uncle Sam than they now do as privately held firms.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwarzman has courted controversy with his audacious displays of wealth -- his glowingly chronicled 60th birthday party has been cited -- and that may be one reason legislators have taken greater notice of how he and his private equity colleagues operate. But Blackstone also just sold a major stake in the firm to the Chinese government. That makes Mr. Schwarzman a tricky target for federal legislators because they may have to contend with White House officials, who lauded the transaction.</p>
        <p>Other unresolved issues surround the tax bill. Chief among them, perhaps, is that it does not address how to tax ''carried interest,'' the euphemism for the hefty performance fees that fund managers haul in. Private equity executives now pay only capital gains rates on those fees instead of ordinary income taxes like virtually every other corporate executive in the nation.</p>
        <p>If private equity firms remain private -- and the two senators don't propose another bill that seeks to prevent private equity executives from counting carried interest at capital gains rates -- they will be back to where they started. The Blackstone bill will have been simply an exercise in political headline writing.</p>
        <p>Whether Senator Baucus and Senator Grassley consider the bill to be a prelude to a larger effort that goes after carried interest remains unclear; the Senate aide said, ''I wouldn't call this a first step -- we continue to look at the issues.''</p>
        <p>So, at least for now, Uncle Sam is not showing his hand.</p>
        <p>DealBook also has a newsletter and a Web site, nytimes.com/dealbook, that is updated continuously when markets are open.</p>
        <p>DEALBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
