<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As the Hits Add Up for Jeter, The Yanks Keep Glavine Stuck in a Rut</title>
    <meta content="17yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/sports/baseball/17yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855275"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Glavine, Tom</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jeter, Derek</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rivera, Mariano</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E3DE123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As the Hits Add Up for Jeter, The Yanks Keep Glavine Stuck in a Rut</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">4 Hits for Jeter as Yankees Keep Glavine in a Rut</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Derek Jeter was the most valuable player when the Yankees beat the Mets in the 2000 World Series, and he has never stopped torturing the team across town. Of all the players who have batted at least 200 times against the Mets, Jeter has the best batting average.</p>
        <p>The Yankees overcame three deficits in the early innings yesterday, and Jeter put them ahead for good with a two-run homer in an 11-8 victory at Yankee Stadium. The fourth-inning homer was the second of four hits for Jeter, whose .383 career average against the Mets leads all hitters, according to the Elias Sports Bureau.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After silencing the Yankees in a combined shutout on Friday, the Mets’ pitching looked helpless Saturday as Tom Glavine failed in his fifth attempt at his 296th career victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Derek Jeter was the most valuable player when the Yankees beat the Mets in the 2000 World Series, and he has never stopped torturing the team across town. Of all the players who have batted at least 200 times against the Mets, Jeter has the best batting average.</p>
        <p>The Yankees overcame three deficits in the early innings yesterday, and Jeter put them ahead for good with a two-run homer in an 11-8 victory at Yankee Stadium. The fourth-inning homer was the second of four hits for Jeter, whose .383 career average against the Mets leads all hitters, according to the Elias Sports Bureau.</p>
        <p>''The atmosphere is a lot of fun,'' Jeter said. ''The fans get into it. You can't help but enjoy playing in these games. It gets tiring and old answering the same questions leading up to the series, but playing in them is pretty fun.''</p>
        <p>For the rest of the players, the game was more about survival than fun. It took 3 hours 43 minutes, in addition to a 40-minute rain delay, and 22 runners were left on base. Both starters pitched poorly, with the Mets' Tom Glavine failing in his fifth attempt at victory No. 296, and the Yankees' Tyler Clippard earning a trip to Class AAA after the game.</p>
        <p>In the ninth inning, a tuneup for Mariano Rivera turned tenuous when the Mets scored twice, bunching five singles in a span of seven batters. The last hit came from José Reyes, who flicked three two-strike fouls before driving in a run. Reyes, usually a switch-hitter, batted right-handed to counter Rivera's cutter.</p>
        <p>''I only faced him one time, from the left side, and he broke my bat,'' Reyes said. ''I wasn't going to let that happen again.''</p>
        <p>Reyes's hit brought up Carlos Beltrán as the go-ahead run with the bases loaded and two out. But Beltrán popped out on a foul ball to catcher Jorge Posada on the first pitch, ending the game. The outing might have seemed shaky, but Rivera was not concerned.</p>
        <p>''I was throwing strikes,'' said Rivera, who allowed his first runs since the last series against the Mets, on May 20. ''They put the ball in play and found the holes. You can't control where the ball goes.''</p>
        <p>Control was a big problem for the starters, especially Clippard, who twice walked Reyes on five pitches to lead off innings. Both times -- in the first and the third -- Reyes stole second and scored.</p>
        <p>''I let him get in my head a little bit, and I tried to be too fine,'' Clippard said. ''That was my fault.''</p>
        <p>With a second-inning homer by Rubén Gotay in between, the Mets had three runs in three innings off Clippard, and a 3-2 lead. But it did not last long. Alex Rodriguez erased it with his 26th homer, a two-run blast deep into the Mets' bullpen in left field in the bottom of the third.</p>
        <p>With the Yankees leading, 4-3, it was Clippard's turn to volley back the lead. He did so on a two-run homer by Ramón Castro in the fourth, and two Mets singles followed. Manager Joe Torre called for Luis Vizcaíno, who is quietly showing why he was so useful for other teams the past few seasons.</p>
        <p>Vizcaíno retired Reyes and Beltrán to escape more trouble, then worked a scoreless fifth. Scott Proctor fired two more scoreless innings after him.</p>
        <p>''Everybody was knocking him,'' Proctor said of Vizcaíno, who has shaved more than a run from an earned run average that was 7.33 two weeks ago. ''Yeah, he probably hasn't pitched to his potential, but Vizzy's a great pitcher. You don't get that many years in the league and have the years that he's had without very quality stuff. He's going to be counted on down the stretch.''</p>
        <p>Vizcaíno said he plays catch every day with Rivera, who has helped him keep his fingers on top of his slider, instead of wrapping them around it, which flattens the spin. The adjustments have led to five scoreless outings in a row; the bullpen as a whole had a streak of 211/3 scoreless innings until yesterday.</p>
        <p>Vizcaíno (3-1) was the pitcher of record when Jeter connected against Glavine with two out and one on in the fourth. Jeter bashed a first-pitch fastball, at 85 miles an hour, into the runway beside the left-field bullpen for his fifth home run of the season.</p>
        <p>''The previous at-bat, he threw me the same pitch on the first pitch, and I took it,'' Jeter said. ''That time, I decided to swing.''</p>
        <p>Glavine left after a leadoff double in the fifth by Posada, who scored when Robinson Canó singled off Scott Schoeneweis. Guillermo Mota allowed two runs and Aaron Sele one, putting the Mets in a big hole.</p>
        <p>Except for Clippard's starts, the Yankees' starters have worked at least six innings every game since June 5. A rested bullpen has been more effective. ''Not everybody's clicking, but we've got enough guys to get through some tough situations,'' Proctor said. ''As a whole, we're pitching better, and the starters are doing phenomenal.''</p>
        <p>Clippard will no longer be part of that rotation. The Yankees invested $46 million during the off-season in Kei Igawa, who seems to have smoothed his mechanics and refined his changeup at Class AAA Scranton.</p>
        <p>An outfielder, Kevin Thompson, will join the team until Igawa's turn in the rotation, and Clippard, 22, will continue to develop in the minors after going 3-1 with a 6.33 E.R.A. in six starts. ''You don't want anybody to lose confidence,'' Torre said, ''especially a youngster, because then it turns into wasting a whole year.''</p>
        <p>At 34-32, there is purpose to the Yankees' season in the majors. Their crosstown rivals will be off the schedule after tonight, and a summer-long pennant race awaits.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
