<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Picking Up The Pieces</title>
    <meta content="Wagner.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/books/review/Wagner-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855332"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Ondaatje, Michael</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Divisadero (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E2DF1F30F934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1186" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Picking Up The Pieces</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Picking Up the Pieces</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERICA WAGNER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DIVISADERO</p>
        <p>By Michael Ondaatje.</p>
        <p>273 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Divisadero” is a series of narratives that calls itself, perhaps for convenience’ sake, a novel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DIVISADERO</p>
        <p>By Michael Ondaatje.</p>
        <p>273 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
        <p>I come from Divisadero Street,'' Anna tells us in Michael Ondaatje's fifth novel. ''Divisadero, from the Spanish word for 'division,' the street that at one time was the dividing line between San Francisco and the fields of the Presidio. Or it might derive from the word divisar, meaning 'to gaze at something from a distance.' ''</p>
        <p>This claim about Anna's origins, which arrives midway through Ondaatje's restless book, we know to be false. For the story begins in Anna's childhood, as she grows up on a farm in Northern California with her father, her sister, Claire, and an adopted farmhand, Coop -- only four years older than the sisters, who are, ostensibly, twins. And yet this too is not quite the truth, because Anna's mother died at 23, giving birth to Anna; her father (perhaps strangely, but this is Ondaatje's coincidental world) brings home another baby whose mother died as she was born and raises them together. ''It was a field hospital on the outskirts of Santa Rosa, and to put it brutally, they owed him a wife, they owed him something.'' The title of the first part of this first section is ''The Orphan,'' and that might be supposed to refer to Coop, rescued as a toddler by Anna's parents from a neighboring farm when his own family was murdered by a hired hand. But in the world of this novel, whose characters yearn for connection only to be thwarted, it might refer to any of them -- divided from one another, somehow always set at a distance.</p>
        <p>''Divisadero'' is a series of narratives that calls itself, perhaps for convenience' sake, a novel. I'm not sure that it is, in fact, a novel; but then I wouldn't be happy calling it a book of linked stories, either. Ondaatje is a writer who likes to blur form, as he did in his 1982 memoir, ''Running in the Family.'' (Note, in his list of previous works, the relaxed category ''Fiction and Memoir.'') So we have a book in three sections: ''Anna, Claire and Coop,'' ''The Family in the Cart'' and ''The House in Dému,'' three tales loosely braided together like slack rope. The first section is the longest, effectively the first half of the book, and is a bleakly moving rendering of lives disrupted by brutality and loss.</p>
        <p>Coop falls, of course, for one of the sisters he's raised with; it happens to be Anna, the true daughter, and while her blood-link to her father is the source of their love's tragic outcome, the youthful desire that Ondaatje conjures gives the believable feeling that this was simply an unfortunate accident. Anna and Coop are discovered by her father, and Coop, who'd escaped murder as a boy, almost falls victim as a young man. Anna saves her lover by nearly committing murder herself, then flees to become ''the person formerly known as Anna,'' forever in shadow. ''Her past is hidden from everyone. She has never turned to a lover or friends when they speak about families (and she always inquires of their families) and spoken of her childhood.''</p>
        <p>It is this hiding that sets the rest of the book's mechanism in motion. Anna is, in truth, the orphan -- at least, this is how she sees herself, in flight from her past. ''Those who have an orphan's sense of history love history,'' she says. She buries herself in archives, ''where art meets life in secret,'' a wonderful phrase. She discovers the work of a French poet, Lucien Segura, who wrote in Dému, in the Gers region of France, until one day he simply disappeared: ''His voice with the wound in it kept haunting me,'' which hardly seems surprising. But this is not a novel of surprise: it is one of looping intersection, of unlikely encounters that carry the force of the author's conviction. Yes, it must be so -- some pattern wills it to be. Is it credible that, much later, Claire should happen upon Coop, once again nearly dead from a beating, purely by chance?</p>
        <p>Ondaatje demands a reader's trust, an acceptance that a work of fiction can accommodate the peculiar alignments that bless and bedevil everyday life. How convenient the collection of characters in Villa San Girolamo in ''The English Patient,'' how lucky the pairing of pathologist and archaeologist in ''Anil's Ghost.'' If that kind of thing tries your patience, Ondaatje may not be the novelist for you. And yet, I'd argue, pay closer attention and you may think he's on to something. He is a poet as much as (or even more than) he is a novelist, and the crosscurrents of his writing flow and ripple against each other as poems might. Sequences of images set themselves out in their individual beauty and lucidity; sometimes how they fit into the whole is almost beside the point.</p>
        <p>Anna (whose name echoes that of Hana in ''The English Patient'') takes herself off to the Gers to live in the house where Segura had lived at the end of his life; there she meets Rafael, a guitar-playing Gypsy with pockets full of wild herbs whose love begins to heal her. He is also her connection to Segura: and the final two sections of the book are the vanished writer's own story of love, loss and brokenhearted redemption. Ondaatje's fascination with the metaphor of blindness (think of the burned Almasy, temporarily unable to see, in ''The English Patient,'' or Ananda in ''Anil's Ghost,'' who paints eyes on statues of Buddha and whose craft might restore the identity of one long dead) is once again in evidence here: Segura is half-blinded as a boy in a freak accident involving a dog bursting through a pane of glass. But his injury is the beginning of the fractured love affair that will haunt his life, and the works of fiction he will create, in secret, to resurrect a vanished passion.</p>
        <p>Give in to Ondaatje and his language will seduce you. Sometimes his particularity can be overbearing: Coop's later career as a cardsharp is marked by poker hands laid out on the page; I found them annoying, but then again I don't play. A conversation between Coop and a cardplaying friend about Styron and ''Sophie's Choice'' similarly seems forced; a reference to the Persian Gulf war a distraction. Ondaatje is at his best let loose in the dream world of his warmblooded imagination. Because of this the second half of the book -- Segura's story, and the story of Rafael's family -- is more satisfying than the first, more vivid in its evocation of the French countryside and a vanished way of life.</p>
        <p>It's no good wishing a novel were different than it is; but the brokenness of Ondaatje's tale can be frustrating. Still: ''Divisadero.'' What did we expect? It's possible to believe that Ondaatje's method of mosaic more accurately reflects the untidy turns life tends to take; his characters make unfortunate decisions but then, so do we. There is something endearingly human about this book, for all its art: who can't forgive a hopeless romantic?</p>
        <p>Erica Wagner's most recent book is ''Seizure,'' a novel. She is literary editor of The Times of London.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Erica Wagner's most recent book is ''Seizure,'' a novel. She is literary editor of The Times of London.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
