<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Graduate, 84, World Was Her Classroom</title>
    <meta content="17noticedweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/17noticedwe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855048"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NOTICED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Verplanck (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Furfaro, Natalie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Di Pierro, Marianne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Falkenstein, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E6D6143FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="526" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Graduate, 84, World Was Her Classroom</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Graduate, 84, World Was Her Classroom</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELLE FALKENSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Falkenstein, Michelle</byline>
      <dateline>VERPLANCK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Natalie Rose Lombardo Furfaro, 84, of Verplanck, NY, whose daughter, Marianne Di Pierro, convinced Jonathan Thomas, principal of Valhalla High School, that her mother deserved high school diploma; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A PETITE, white-haired woman who turns 85 in August, Natalie Rose Lombardo Furfaro sat in the living room of her small, tidy house and talked about getting her high school diploma this Thursday.</p>
        <p>Ms. Furfaro was 5 when she came to America from Cittanova, Italy, and she dropped out of Valhalla High School a decade later, in 1936, after her freshman year, to go to work. ''My parents needed help, and people thought girls didn't need an education,'' she said. ''I felt terrible.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Verplanck.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A PETITE, white-haired woman who turns 85 in August, Natalie Rose Lombardo Furfaro sat in the living room of her small, tidy house and talked about getting her high school diploma this Thursday.</p>
        <p>Ms. Furfaro was 5 when she came to America from Cittanova, Italy, and she dropped out of Valhalla High School a decade later, in 1936, after her freshman year, to go to work. ''My parents needed help, and people thought girls didn't need an education,'' she said. ''I felt terrible.''</p>
        <p>The effort to secure Ms. Furfaro a diploma began in late January, when her oldest daughter, Marianne Di Pierro, called Jonathan Thomas, the principal of Valhalla High School. Dr. Di Pierro, director of the Graduate Center for Research and Retention at Western Michigan University in Kalamazoo, asked Mr. Thomas if he would consider giving a diploma to her mother, an avid reader who has been devoted to learning throughout her life. ''I feel my mother had the potential for greatness,'' she said. ''She would have been a wonderful professor or a great attorney, had the opportunity been there.''</p>
        <p>At Mr. Thomas's request, Dr. Di Pierro wrote a letter explaining why her mother deserved the honor. She wrote that by the age of 12, Ms. Furfaro was managing her family's finances and filing their taxes. After leaving school at 15, she worked as a dental assistant, followed by a job blowing glass tubes for hearing aids. She resisted her mother's entreaties to marry young, finally settling down with another Italian immigrant, Paul Furfaro, at 25.</p>
        <p>''My mother instilled in her five children a profound love of reading and the arts,'' Dr. Di Pierro wrote to Mr. Thomas. ''We are two daughters and three sons, all of us educated and in the professions.  In some way, perhaps, we lived out her long-cherished dream of a formal education.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Pierro went on to write, ''As a family, we would like to celebrate her life by providing her with the graduation she never enjoyed.''</p>
        <p>The letter was signed by Dr. Di Pierro and Ms. Furfaro's other four children: Linda Imperato, a kitchen design consultant; John Furfaro, a lawyer; Paul Furfaro, an artist and teacher working on his Ph.D.; and Peter Furfaro, a General Electric executive with an M.B.A.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thomas reviewed Ms. Furfaro's high school record -- he called her ''a good student with average to above-average grades'' -- and considered her 17 years as a religious instructor at St. Patrick's Parish in Verplanck, where she has lived for nearly 50 years. Mr. Thomas's superintendent, Diane Ramos-Kelly, agreed that Ms. Furfaro deserved a diploma. ''The kids in the senior class think it's terrific,'' Mr. Thomas said.</p>
        <p>When Dr. Di Pierro first told her mother what she had done, she was not pleased. ''I didn't want the notoriety,'' Ms. Furfaro, a widow since 2000, said. But she added that she had gotten used to the idea, and the thought that her presence at graduation might inspire another member of the class of 2007 to keep learning makes her smile.</p>
        <p>''I feel that children should go to school,'' she said, ''because that's something you will always have.''</p>
        <p>NOTICED</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
