<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Port Authority Needs More Openness, Governors Say, and They Have a Plan</title>
    <meta content="17port" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/17port.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855276"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Port Authority of New York and New Jersey</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E3DE123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="649" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Port Authority Needs More Openness, Governors Say, and They Have a Plan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Port Authority Needs More Openness, Governors Say, and They Have a Plan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The governors of New York and New Jersey are seeking an end to most secret meetings and want greater disclosure on how contracts are awarded at the powerful agency that operates the two states' major bridges, tunnels and airports in the New York metropolitan area.</p>
        <p>In an eight-page letter dated tomorrow, Gov. Eliot Spitzer of New York and Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey propose 23 measures for the agency, the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The governors of New York and New Jersey are seeking an end to most secret meetings and want greater disclosure on how contracts are awarded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The governors of New York and New Jersey are seeking an end to most secret meetings and want greater disclosure on how contracts are awarded at the powerful agency that operates the two states' major bridges, tunnels and airports in the New York metropolitan area.</p>
        <p>In an eight-page letter dated tomorrow, Gov. Eliot Spitzer of New York and Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey propose 23 measures for the agency, the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey.</p>
        <p>The measures would ban most closed-door meetings, protect the awarding of contracts from ''inappropriate lobbying,'' disclose ''outside business dealings'' of top officials and detail the pay of the 20 highest-paid staff members, according to the letter, which was released yesterday.</p>
        <p>Lilo Stainton, Mr. Corzine's press secretary, said there was no arm-twisting implicit in the letter and no particular incident or issue that prompted the proposal. She characterized the request as part of a collaborative effort with the authority, which last year opened meetings to the public, held public votes by officials and started listing its contracts on its Web site.</p>
        <p>The governors head the authority and each appoints 6 of the 12 commissioners. The chairman of the authority, Anthony Coscia, ''has been quite a leader'' on making the authority more open, Ms. Stainton said.</p>
        <p>''The governors feel very strongly that the commissioners will implement this immediately,'' perhaps as early as this week, she said.</p>
        <p>But Richard L. Brodsky, a New York assemblyman and a frequent critic of the Port Authority, said the governors' proposals, which call for an amendment of the authority's bylaws, did not go far enough.</p>
        <p>''That's a way for governors to keep legislatures out of the picture,'' said Mr. Brodsky, a Democrat from Westchester.</p>
        <p>Rather than rely on the authority to change its practices, he said, both states should pass laws to require more accountability from the Port Authority and to appoint an inspector general to investigate wrongdoing. The authority, Mr. Brodsky said, has been an agency ''uncontrolled by laws or democratic institutions.''</p>
        <p>The authority has an operating budget of more than $5 billion. It operates Kennedy, La Guardia and Newark Liberty International airports; a seaport at the Port of Newark; the bus terminals in Midtown Manhattan and at the George Washington Bridge; the Holland and Lincoln Tunnels and the George Washington Bridge; and is overseeing rebuilding of the World Trade Center site, which it owns.</p>
        <p>Stephen Sigmund, chief of public and government affairs for the authority, said, ''We continue to make the Port Authority more open and more transparent, and we will continue to work with'' the governors ''to implement these changes in the coming weeks.''</p>
        <p>The governors' proposal is intended to correct a quirk in the running of the authority, which was established 86 years ago.</p>
        <p>Even though New York and New Jersey have similar laws reducing secrecy in government, those laws do not apply to the authority, which is a bistate agency with headquarters in Manhattan. Its decisions, like a short-lived plan to place a Geico billboard at the George Washington Bridge toll plaza, have occasionally annoyed lawmakers of one or both states.</p>
        <p>Last October, Mr. Coscia, the chairman, ordered less secrecy in governance, but the policies could conceivably be rescinded by his successor. The governors want the changes to be made permanent through an amendment of the authority's bylaws.</p>
        <p>In their letter, the governors proposed that the authority's audit committee ''conduct an external audit of the Port Authority annually.''</p>
        <p>The governors also wanted the commissioners to disclose ''any outside business dealings that Board members, their employers, or their immediate family members have had with the Port Authority during the previous year, and require executive staff to do the same.''</p>
        <p>The governors also wanted the board to ''identify, list the compensation of, and set forth the educational background and professional experience of the 20 highest-paid Port Authority executive staff members.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
