<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LIVING IN/Ocean Hill-Brownsville, Brooklyn; At Long Last, Developers Show an Interest</title>
    <meta content="17livi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/realestate/17livi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855087"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Living In | Ocean Hill-Brownsville, Brooklyn"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Brooklyn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E7DE153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LIVING IN/Ocean Hill-Brownsville, Brooklyn; At Long Last, Developers Show an Interest</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Long Last, Developers Show an Interest</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER BLEYER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A DENSELY packed 1,200-acre swath of central Brooklyn, Ocean Hill-Brownsville is not among the neighborhoods to have been swept up in the borough's recent renaissance.</p>
        <p>Its older housing stock is generally less elegant and well preserved than that in nearby Bedford-Stuyvesant. Its streets are not lined with charming cafes or whimsical boutiques. Its empty lots are not sprouting slick, glass-sheathed condominiums.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hundreds of new homes have budded in Ocean Hill-Brownsville recently, anchoring even more homeowners in the area.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A DENSELY packed 1,200-acre swath of central Brooklyn, Ocean Hill-Brownsville is not among the neighborhoods to have been swept up in the borough's recent renaissance.</p>
        <p>Its older housing stock is generally less elegant and well preserved than that in nearby Bedford-Stuyvesant. Its streets are not lined with charming cafes or whimsical boutiques. Its empty lots are not sprouting slick, glass-sheathed condominiums.</p>
        <p>Yet Ocean Hill-Brownsville has undergone its own striking transformation since the 1960s and '70s, when its upwardly mobile population swiftly decamped to the suburbs, public services declined, crime spiked and the neighborhood became synonymous with urban poverty and decay.</p>
        <p>In the 1980s and '90s, thousands of low-cost row houses were built under what is known as the Nehemiah program in Ocean Hill-Brownsville as well as in neighboring East New York. The tidy single-family homes, built on vacant city-owned land with construction loans from a consortium of churches, were quickly occupied, and the program was celebrated as a success in helping to stabilize the blighted neighborhood with committed homeowners.</p>
        <p>With much of Brownsville's underused land stocked with Nehemiah homes, subsidized development in the last few years has been concentrated closer to Ocean Hill, the section of the conjoined neighborhoods north of Eastern Parkway. Hundreds of new homes have budded there recently, anchoring even more homeowners in the area.</p>
        <p>Brenda Russell is one of those homeowners. A statuesque woman with a throaty laugh, she seized an opportunity last year to buy a three-story, two-family tawny brick row house with a single-car garage and prim backyard on St. Mark's Avenue.</p>
        <p>Ms. Russell, a 48-year-old auditor and divorced mother of two who had been renting an apartment in Mill Basin, bought her house for $305,000, with the help of a $70,000 city subsidy. Her own vague impression of Ocean Hill-Brownsville has undergone a shift since she moved in a year ago.</p>
        <p>''I heard it had a lot of gang activity, but so far I haven't seen that,'' she said on a sunny Sunday afternoon, smiling and waving at neighbors who passed in front of her house. ''I was just happy to get started again.''</p>
        <p>Police data confirm that crime is less rampant and that the area no longer fully deserves its notorious reputation. In the 73rd Precinct, which encompasses Ocean Hill-Brownsville, murder rates fell 63 percent from 1990 to 2005; robberies were down 79 percent; and felony assaults decreased 51 percent. Still, crime remains a sobering fact. In 2005, there were 22 murders, and 597 robberies and 562 felony assaults were reported.</p>
        <p>Those who review Ocean Hill-Brownville's recent history generally laud its improvements and express optimism about its future. Its renewal has been affirmed lately by the presence of private developers building on scores of vacant lots scattered throughout the area. Local housing advocates consider the situation positive as long as the city continues to balance the neighborhood with subsidized homes.</p>
        <p>''The notion that the area now attracts builders who want to build at market is astounding compared to where it was in the '80s,'' said Michael Gecan, a senior organizer for East Brooklyn Congregations, the church consortium that facilitated the Nehemiah homes beginning in the '80s. ''That's a reality that no one would have predicted 25 years ago.''</p>
        <p>What You'll Find</p>
        <p>A largely African-American community of 85,000, according to the last census data, Ocean Hill-Brownsville is capped by Broadway to the north, a jagged boundary of Saratoga Avenue, Ralph Avenue and East 98th Street to the west and Van Sinderen Avenue and the Long Island Rail Road to the east. Its southern edge is scooped up by Linden Boulevard.</p>
        <p>South of Pitkin Avenue is a cluster of towering New York City Housing Authority projects whose surrounding streets are populated with hundreds of low-lying Nehemiah homes. Many of those shipshape two-story brick houses have gated driveways, finished basements and lovingly tended gardens.</p>
        <p>The Ocean Hill side is endowed with three-story limestones, brownstones and brick buildings, some stripped of architectural ornament. Dispersed around the area are rows of handsome new two-family homes that illustrate the sevenfold leap in residential construction permits issued from 2000 to 2003. The construction, some say, has had an unintended consequence of inspiring others to spiff up their own properties with new windows and the like.</p>
        <p>''If you're next to a newly constructed house, you're going to invest some money into upgrading yours,'' said Viola D. Greene-Walker, the district manager of Brooklyn Community Board 16, which represents Ocean Hill-Brownsville.</p>
        <p>One phenomenon in its infancy in the neighborhood is the conversion of rental buildings into condominiums, according to Rene Santiago, a sales director for Massey Knakal Realty Services. He cited one such conversion of a 16-unit building on Thomas Boyland Street and predicted that there would be more to come.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people who own homes in the area and have been there a long time are tired of dealing with three floors and tenants,'' Mr. Santiago said. ''They think, 'Let me buy a condo; it's easier to maintain.' ''</p>
        <p>Also novel in the area is the emergence on a half-acre lot at the intersection of Eastern Parkway and Atlantic Avenue of a $13 million 41-unit condominium complex by Habitat for Humanity. The three energy-efficient buildings, for which ground was broken earlier this month, will be the group's largest and greenest project to date in New York and will be built largely by volunteers and future residents. Josh Lockwood of the local Habitat chapter, said that 4,000 applications to live in the condo had already been received.</p>
        <p>A persistent complaint in the neighborhood is that retailing has not kept pace with residential development. Pitkin Avenue, once among Brooklyn's most fashionable shopping destinations, remains heavily patronized. But results of a residents' survey released last year by the Brooklyn Economic Development Corporation underscored a desire for a greater variety of goods and services, including restaurants, bookstores, gift stores and banks.</p>
        <p>Margaret Nelson, the director of real estate programs for the economic development organization, said she was ''optimistic that once retailers understand the demand, they will take advantage of going into this market and serving residents.''</p>
        <p>What You'll Pay</p>
        <p>''Brownsville is one of the neighborhoods that haven't gotten the boom other neighborhoods have,'' said Alen Zhitomirsky, a senior listing agent for Foxtons. ''You can find great deals that you can't find anywhere else in Brooklyn.''</p>
        <p>Still, prices have appreciated considerably for homes in Ocean Hill-Brownsville since the '80s, when the Nehemiah houses sold for as little as $65,000. Mr. Zhitomirsky noted that a three-bedroom house on Lott Avenue had recently closed for $353,000, and a four-bedroom house on Strauss Street for $367,000. Average prices for single-family homes are generally $350,000 to $400,000, he said.</p>
        <p>Among two- and three-family homes, those built with public subsidies are generally $400,000 to $450,000, according to Mr. Santiago of Massey Knakal, while those built privately cost $600,000 to $650,000.</p>
        <p>''There's demand for two- and three-family homes,'' he said, ''and people buying these are normally from the area or people getting priced out of Bed-Stuy.''</p>
        <p>Rents are typically around $900 for a one-bedroom, $1,100 for a two-bedroom and up to $1,300 for a three-bedroom, Mr. Santiago said.</p>
        <p>What to Do</p>
        <p>Ocean Hill-Brownsville's largest park is the 10-acre Betsy Head Memorial Playground, which includes tennis courts, baseball fields, a running track, a pavilion and one of the city's 11 Works Progress Administration-era swimming pools built under Robert Moses.</p>
        <p>The Brownsville Recreation Center on Linden Boulevard has a swimming pool, weight room, computer room and other indoor offerings.</p>
        <p>Shopping is sparse, though residents throng historic Pitkin Avenue for sportswear, shoes and cellphones. Block parties are popular in the summer, often drawing extended families into the street with booming sound systems, festive dancing and grills laden with hot dogs and ribs.</p>
        <p>The Schools</p>
        <p>There are at least 16 public elementary schools in Ocean Hill-Brownsville, including Public School 155 on Herkimer Street and Public School 41 on Thatford Avenue.</p>
        <p>Public School 156 on Sutter Avenue reopened in 2003 in a striking new building encased in brick and glass with a 450-seat auditorium, two science labs and wireless technology.</p>
        <p>At Teachers Preparatory High School, a middle and high school on Bristol Street, 80 percent of students passed the state Regents exam in English in 2006, versus 50 percent citywide. In math, 82 percent received passing scores, compared with 54 percent citywide.</p>
        <p>The History</p>
        <p>An agrarian expanse of countryside in the 1800s, the area underwent a population boom after the Fulton Street elevated train made it more accessible in 1889. The neighborhood became a virtual mirror of the Jewish Lower East Side, crammed through the 1940s with synagogue-goers and political radicals, historical accounts show. After World War II, residents drained to the suburbs. Towering public housing projects were concentrated in Brownsville, and the area experienced a steep decline along with municipal neglect. A dispute in 1968 involving the Ocean Hill-Brownsville school district and the United Federation of Teachers led to three teachers strikes and became emblematic of the wrenching racial division of the era.</p>
        <p>The Commute</p>
        <p>Subway lines lace through the neighborhood. On the northern edge of Ocean Hill are the J and Z lines, which join with the A, C and L lines at Broadway Junction station. Farther south, the elevated No. 3 train makes three stops in Brownsville.</p>
        <p>From the East New York stop on the Long Island Rail Road, Flatbush Avenue and Jamaica Station are both about 10 minutes away. After a transfer at Jamaica, Midtown Manhattan is a 20-minute ride away.</p>
        <p>Going Forward</p>
        <p>Subsidized housing safeguards Ocean Hill-Brownsville as an enclave for low-wage families, but the neighborhood sorely needs an influx of diverse retailing to help it thrive.</p>
        <p>Living In | Ocean Hill-Brownsville, Brooklyn</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
