<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Olmert Assails Hamas and Vows Cooperation With Abbas</title>
    <meta content="17olmert" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/world/middleeast/17olmert.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855264"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Bank</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fatah</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershner, Isabel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olmert, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abbas, Mahmoud (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <location class="online_producer">West Bank</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Gaza Strip</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Fatah, Al</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Hamas</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5DE123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1255" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Olmert Assails Hamas and Vows Cooperation With Abbas</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Olmert Assails Hamas and Vows Cooperation With Abbas</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER and ISABEL KERSHNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershner, Isabel; Erlanger, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, June 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prime Min Ehud Omert says Israel will 'cooperate fully' with new government installed by Palestinian Pres Mahmoud Abbas; suggests that it would hand over $562 million in withheld tax and customs duties to help Fatah turn West Bank into model for Palestinian future; Olmert photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Olmert of Israel, deploring the ''brutality of the Palestinians against their own people,'' said that Israel would ''cooperate fully'' with a new government installed by the Palestinian president, Mahmoud Abbas.</p>
        <p>A Fatah government, shorn of Hamas, ''can be a new opening,'' Mr. Olmert said, suggesting that Israel would hand over $562 million in withheld tax and customs duties to help Fatah turn the West Bank into a model for the Palestinian future, even if Gaza was lost to extremism with last week's takeover of the territory by Hamas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Israel’s prime minister, deploring the “brutality of the Palestinians against their own people,” said that a Fatah government, shorn of Hamas, “can be a new opening.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Olmert of Israel, deploring the ''brutality of the Palestinians against their own people,'' said that Israel would ''cooperate fully'' with a new government installed by the Palestinian president, Mahmoud Abbas.</p>
        <p>A Fatah government, shorn of Hamas, ''can be a new opening,'' Mr. Olmert said, suggesting that Israel would hand over $562 million in withheld tax and customs duties to help Fatah turn the West Bank into a model for the Palestinian future, even if Gaza was lost to extremism with last week's takeover of the territory by Hamas.</p>
        <p>''I am willing to cooperate with Abu Mazen if there will not be a Hamas government and meet all my commitments, including all the financial commitments, no question about it,'' Mr. Olmert said, using a name by which Mr. Abbas is known. ''To give it to a Hamas government is reckless. To give it to a Fatah government is an opportunity.''</p>
        <p>And in remarks that were unprecedented for a sitting Israeli prime minister, Mr. Olmert spoke explicitly about the pain suffered by Palestinian refugees and their families who fled or were forced to flee their homes in the war of 1948-49. While not accepting responsibility for a war the new Israeli state did not start, he said, ''It's time for Israel to deal seriously, openly and generously with the suffering of the Palestinians that has taken place over many years as part of the conflict between us and them.''</p>
        <p>''We do want to say to the Palestinians,'' he said, ''that we are not indifferent to what happened to them.''</p>
        <p>As part of any future peace settlement, he said, ''We want to take part in an effort to effectively deal with this issue'' in a way ''that will not create more suffering but perhaps bring an end to this chapter in the relations between the two peoples.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Olmert remained firm in saying that no Palestinian refugees or their descendants would be able to return to the state of Israel, but he clearly appeared to want to soften the message, speaking about Israel's need to recognize the refugees' suffering and hinting at compensation, though he offered no details. Mr. Olmert spoke in a 40-minute interview on Thursday with The New York Times in his Tel Aviv office, as Hamas was completing its violent takeover of Gaza and before flying to the United States to meet with President Bush on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Those meetings will be vital in shaping a joint strategy to deal with the victory by Hamas, regarded as a terrorist group by both countries, and the blow suffered in Gaza by Mr. Abbas and Fatah, who favor peace with Israel.</p>
        <p>In the interview, which was embargoed for Sunday publication, Mr. Olmert was alternately gracious and prickly, and appeared preoccupied with the fast-moving events in Gaza.</p>
        <p>He tried to find opportunity in the likely separation of the political future of the West Bank from that of Gaza.</p>
        <p>''I think the government and the authority that Abu Mazen holds in the West Bank can create an opportunity for an entirely different way of living for those who live in the West Bank,'' Mr. Olmert said. ''That can be the platform upon which a somewhat different Palestinian realization of what's good and what's bad, what's preferred and what's not, can emerge.''</p>
        <p>After the Hamas conquest and the failure of the Palestinian national unity government negotiated in March, Mr. Olmert said: ''I suggest we look at things in a much more realistic manner and with less self-deceit. A democracy which is based on terror and on brutal killing of opponents is not a democracy. Even if it received more votes, in a way that is totally now irrelevant to the realities of life of that population.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Olmert was expecting continued pressure from the Bush administration and Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice to maintain talks on a ''political horizon'' for a future Palestinian state with Mr. Abbas, but he was clearly feeling that his own pessimism about Mr. Abbas's ability to deliver had been warranted.</p>
        <p>He said that he and Mr. Bush agreed on the need for creating a Palestinian state, and he agreed with Ms. Rice's ''desire to push things forward rapidly.'' But the Fatah collapse in Gaza changes the conversation, not only with Mr. Abbas, but also with the Americans, Mr. Olmert implied.</p>
        <p>''The real aggravation we sometimes have is not in the basic perception of what needs to be done in the territories, between us and the Palestinians,'' Mr. Olmert said of his talks with Washington. ''I guess the only difference that sometimes exists is between the assessment of the real opportunities and how one can deal with these, and how difficult it is to change things when the main agent of change doesn't have the willpower that he should have.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Olmert likes Mr. Abbas but does not think much of him as a leader. He insists that it is Mr. Abbas who is reluctant to have regular meetings with Israel, and who is conditioning them on the return of the confiscated tax money. ''I don't think I need to pay cash for every meeting in order to discuss the common future of the Jews and the Palestinians in this part of the world,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Olmert also implicitly criticized the American policy of funneling arms to Mr. Abbas's Presidential Guard in Gaza, one of the many elite Fatah forces that fought badly in Gaza, if at all.</p>
        <p>''I look at the Fatah fighting now in Gaza, and I don't see any of the commanders in the area,'' he said. ''Where have they been? Where have they disappeared? Why are they not in Gaza? How can one expect that the Fatah will prevail if all their commanders are away outside the region altogether or in the West Bank?'' Everyone wants to ''help the moderates and provide them with weapons,'' he said. ''But it's another thing to ask yourself, if I'm going to give weapons and these weapons are going to be taken by Hamas, what am I doing?''</p>
        <p>Asked if the Hamas victory in Gaza marked the failure of the American and Israeli policy to isolate Hamas diplomatically and financially and boost Fatah through aid and weapons, Mr. Olmert said that ''this policy was never exercised to the fullest.'' Appearing annoyed, he said, ''Hamas was not really ever isolated entirely.''</p>
        <p>Palestinian leaders of Fatah, he said, collaborated with Hamas: ''To sit in the back rooms and make all the deals with Hamas and then go outside and say, we are by ourselves, we are not part of it -- it doesn't work. What it did was help create a stronger basis for Hamas.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Olmert, who came to power effectively in January 2006 and was elected two months later with a mandate to pull more Israeli settlers out of the occupied West Bank, was badly damaged by last summer's war against Hezbollah. He was sharply criticized in a partial report put out by a government commission, and successfully resisted calls for his resignation.</p>
        <p>But with a new defense minister -- the former prime minister and new Labor Party leader Ehud Barak -- and a successful campaign to elect Shimon Peres as Israel's next president, Mr. Olmert is considered to have a new beginning as prime minister, at least until the autumn. Asked if his chair felt more comfortable now, Mr. Olmert bristled. ''This chair, to be honest,'' he said, leaning back and staring at his questioner, ''it's quite comfortable anyway.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
