<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Manny and the Socialites: Let's Roll</title>
    <meta content="17manny" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/fashion/17manny.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855212"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E5D7153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Manny and the Socialites: Let's Roll</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Manny and the Socialites: Let’s Roll</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLEN SALKIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''ARE you O.K. that we're shooting the Ricola man in front of the Diebenkorn?'' asked Jay Peterson, the co-director of a music video made to promote a book about a male nanny.</p>
        <p>He was asking his cousin Holly Peterson for approval to film a dwarf dressed in a Swiss yodeling costume lip-synching about emasculation in front of a multimillion-dollar painting by the Abstract Expressionist Richard Diebenkorn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Holly Peterson is promoting her new book, “The Manny,” by making a mock-rap video to push a friend’s book.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''ARE you O.K. that we're shooting the Ricola man in front of the Diebenkorn?'' asked Jay Peterson, the co-director of a music video made to promote a book about a male nanny.</p>
        <p>He was asking his cousin Holly Peterson for approval to film a dwarf dressed in a Swiss yodeling costume lip-synching about emasculation in front of a multimillion-dollar painting by the Abstract Expressionist Richard Diebenkorn.</p>
        <p>It was that kind of day.</p>
        <p>The floor-to-ceiling abstract blue painting hangs in the entryway of the opulent apartment of Ms. Peterson's father at River House on East 52nd Street.</p>
        <p>The apartment was being used as a set for the video to promote Ms. Peterson's book, ''The Manny,'' whose publisher hopes it will be this summer's version of ''The Devil Wears Prada,'' a catty peek into a privileged world. Both novel and video are about a handsome male nanny who has an affair with a frustrated Upper East Side television producer.</p>
        <p>''Yes,'' answered Ms. Peterson. ''Fine.''</p>
        <p>By the standards of the day, and of Ms. Peterson's life, nothing could be more normal than a dwarf and a Diebenkorn. Earlier, the socialite Tinsley Mortimer was filmed opining on the beauty of a certain manny's rear end.</p>
        <p>Later there would be a sex scene starring Carole Radziwill, the author of ''What Remains,'' a memoir that chronicles her friendship with John F. Kennedy Jr. and Carolyn Bessette, and also the untimely death of her husband (a cousin of Mr. Kennedy's).</p>
        <p>Ms. Peterson's ability to deliver a revealing, if bizarre, slice of high society both on the page and for the book's promotion may explain, more than any literary credentials, why she received a $1 million advance for this book and a second yet-to-be-written novel.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mortimer said she had agreed to appear in the video because Ms. Peterson was friends with Gigi Mortimer, her sister-in-law.</p>
        <p>''Anything for Holly,'' Ms. Mortimer said as a makeup woman powdered her face.</p>
        <p>She was asked to stand on a balcony to deliver her line about the manny's backside. The two directors, Mr. Peterson and Michael Jaffe, instructed Ms. Mortimer to bite her lip in a sultry manner.</p>
        <p>''I don't do sexy very well, you guys,'' she protested, her flowery baby-doll dress billowing in a warm summer wind off the East River 11 stories below. ''I feel more comfortable being cute.''</p>
        <p>Then she bit her lip, pouted and delivered the line in 10 different sexy tones.</p>
        <p>The finished video, which is to be posted on YouTube, features a steamy rap song with oodles of socialite cameos. The actress Karen Duffy stars as the manny-hiring and -bedding wife, complaining in rhyme that none of her help can school her son Dylan properly: ''Got a driver from Jamaica, a tailor from Hong Kong, got a super from 'Rica, a maid named Wong,'' she raps.</p>
        <p>Ms. Peterson paid the socialites, who also include Jennifer Creel and Cristina Greeven Cuomo, the vice chairwoman of Niche Media, in a form of currency she said they would understand: She bought them each a snakeskin clutch from Bergdorf Goodman.</p>
        <p>''I knew they were game girls,'' Ms. Peterson said. ''I wasn't asking the traditional waspy preppy types. You have to be a hambone to do this -- I am one and I recognize one.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Peterson is the daughter of Peter G. Peterson, a Commerce secretary during the Nixon administration, who is projected to get $1.9 billion when the equity firm he helped establish two decades ago, the Blackstone Group, makes its initial public offering this month.</p>
        <p>''The Manny'' started as an article that Ms. Peterson wrote for The New York Times in 2002. It chronicled the popularity of male nannies among an Upper East Side set eager to expose their sons to the sort of informal knowledge about sports and girls that nannies and workaholic fathers were not delivering.</p>
        <p>Ms. Peterson wrote a draft of a novel based on the article and hired an agent. A highly contested auction ensued, with Dial Press making the highest bid. ''One of the main things publishers look for, especially with potentially commercial books,'' said Sara Nelson, the editor of Publishers Weekly, ''is a promotable author, an author who is attractive, an author who is connected, an author who has some sort of platform and might be able to get some coverage for the book, and this author has all that. Who she is definitely has some bearing on her getting this contract.''</p>
        <p>But Susan Kamil, the vice president and editorial director of Dial Press, downplayed that angle. Ms. Kamil said that she bought ''The Manny'' primarily because editors loved the characters and the story. Ms. Peterson's contacts in society and the media world were a secondary consideration. ''No matter how much you can generate a windmill and a hype around a book,'' Ms. Kamil said, ''in the final analysis what matters is if the book connects to the reader on the page.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Ms. Peterson, 42, is well positioned to generate a windmill. She was a writer for Talk magazine, a producer for a decade at ABC News and is a contributing editor at Newsweek.</p>
        <p>''I have a unique perch from which to write about this world,'' said Ms. Peterson, who lives with her husband, an investment banker, and their three children on Park Avenue near 72nd Street. ''I've got a big fat toe in it. Most people in this world don't write about it and most journalists don't see it.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Peterson is willing to embarrass her class of mothers for a multitude of overconsumptive sins, such as alluding to ownership of a private plane by ostentatiously using the phrase ''It's wheels up at 3 p.m.,'' and dressing their sons in lederhosen to mimic the famous image of John-John Kennedy in suspenders at the White House.</p>
        <p>''Until I met Tina Brown I was against using my Rolodex,'' Ms. Peterson said. ''I was all about going to Russia and pulling five all-nighters in a row to get a story in order to prove I could work hard and I wasn't just Pete Peterson's daughter.''</p>
        <p>Then Ms. Brown told Ms. Peterson she should use her access to the rich and famous to land better stories. ''Just call them, grease the wheels, make it easier,'' Ms. Peterson recalled Ms. Brown saying.</p>
        <p>In March, Liz Smith mentioned ''The Manny'' in her column when chronicling a sighting of Ms. Peterson lunching at Michael's with Ms. Brown. The book has cover blurbs from successful chroniclers of high society like Plum Sykes, Candace Bushnell and Dominick Dunne.</p>
        <p>F. Scott Fitzgerald was not available because he is dead.</p>
        <p>In England, where the book was published a few months ago, actual reviewers gave it mixed notices. The Daily Telegraph wrote that Ms. Peterson made the main character's rarefied existence sympathetic, but that ''The Manny'' feels ''more like a collection of newspaper pieces than a coherent narrative.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Peterson's mix of Upper East Side money and a more downtown sensibility can put her at the center of some bizarre scenes.</p>
        <p>In late afternoon, Ms. Radziwill, who spent 15 years working for ABC news, arrived on the set from a long lunch with Jon Bon Jovi, whom she had interviewed for her monthly ''Lunch Date'' column in Glamour magazine. Ms. Peterson introduced her real-life manny, whose name is John Margaritis but who goes by Sunshine. She had met him when he taught her children to surf last summer in Southampton.</p>
        <p>''He's a manny and a personal assistant and soon to be a clothing mogul,'' Ms. Peterson said to Ms. Radziwill. ''We've never had an affair,'' she added.</p>
        <p>Ms. Peterson said she is helping Sunshine, 20, start his own line of T-shirts.</p>
        <p>''He's going to be in Vogue,and we're trying for Hamptons magazine,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''Really?'' Ms. Radziwill said. ''What are the T-shirts going to say on them?''</p>
        <p>''Sunshine,'' said Sunshine. ''With an umbrella. It's sick. You'll love it.''</p>
        <p>''I have my own million-dollar idea for T-shirts,'' she replied. ''They'll say 'It's the oxytocin, stupid.' ''</p>
        <p>Sunshine was stumped.</p>
        <p>''It's this bonding hormone,'' said Ms. Radziwill, who has not remarried. ''People think they're in love, but it's just this hormone the body releases after sex to make you feel in love.''</p>
        <p>The manny in the video is played by a 29-year-old male model named Johannes Huebl. He is known as Joe Hotness on the society party circuit, Ms. Peterson said.</p>
        <p>Soon it was time for Ms. Radziwill to shoot her bedroom scene with Mr. Huebl. She stripped down to a black negligee with stockings held up by garters. The German-born model's blue eyes twinkled as he undid his shirt and revealed a stomach like a glacier-polished stretch of the German Lowland.</p>
        <p>On the night stands in the bedroom were ceramic lamps shaped like fighting cocks, pastel-painted tail feathers erect.</p>
        <p>At the instruction of Mr. Peterson Ms. Radziwill snuggled close to Mr. Huebl and put her palm on his broad, tan chest. It was left to her where to put her elbow, which she rested on an area just below the snap of his jeans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Huebl then uttered his final line: ''It's good to be the manny'' and smiled knowingly into the camera.</p>
        <p>The director yelled cut. Ms. Peterson had what she wanted.</p>
        <p>As the others left the room, Ms. Radziwill stayed on the bed with Mr. Hotness. ''Should we do one without the jeans?'' she asked.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 24, 2007, Sunday  An article last Sunday about Holly Peterson, the author of the novel ''The Manny,'' misstated the relationship of her friend Gigi Mortimer to Tinsley Mortimer, who appears in a video promoting the book. Their husbands are cousins; the two women are not sisters-in-law.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
