<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reagan on Reagan</title>
    <meta content="Phillips.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Washington; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/books/review/Phillips-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855325"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Reagan, Ronald Wilson</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Reagan Diaries, The (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E3DF1F30F934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reagan on Reagan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Reagan on Reagan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN PHILLIPS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE REAGAN DIARIES</p>
        <p>By Ronald Reagan.</p>
        <p>Edited by Douglas Brinkley.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 767 pp.</p>
        <p>HarperCollins Publishers. $35.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The diaries show Ronald Reagan as a more active and alert chief executive than his detractors care to admit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE REAGAN DIARIES</p>
        <p>By Ronald Reagan.</p>
        <p>Edited by Douglas Brinkley.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 767 pp.</p>
        <p>HarperCollins Publishers. $35.</p>
        <p>Not since the 19th century has a United States president kept a diary through his entire White House tenure, and this volume tells us more about Ronald Reagan than many of his biographies. Besides which, not a few interpretive bits of gold are sprinkled amid the grit and gravel of diplomatic niceties, Congressional consultations and after-dinner entertainments.</p>
        <p>Five large, leatherbound diary books -- the editor Douglas Brinkley likens them to a half set of an encyclopedia -- had to be boiled down by about two-thirds to yield this one volume. Except when Reagan was in the hospital, he produced an entry for each day, usually a page written in a clear hand with few portions crossed out. Brinkley, in his introduction, is broadly admiring of Reagan's clarity and persistence.</p>
        <p>For the passages omitted from ''The Reagan Diaries,'' Brinkley provides terse topical summaries. This does leave anyone tracking a line of thought with unfortunate gaps, but the editing is skilled enough that scholars and journalists will be able to follow important threads back to the original volumes.</p>
        <p>On the surface, there is no overload of political or historical substance here. Ronald and Nancy Reagan (she is rarely far from his thoughts, even if not at hand) initiated the diaries not as journals of governing but as memory books. ''We just wanted a way to capture the moment and our feelings before we were whisked on to the next day,'' Nancy said. After they returned to California in 1989, they would often read and reminisce in their den after dinner.</p>
        <p>That said, political and historical implications abound. I voted for Ronald Reagan twice, and the diaries do not make me regret that I did, but his approach to his office had both strengths and weaknesses. One strength manifest in these diaries is that Reagan, especially in his first term, was a more active and alert chief executive than his detractors care to admit. That involvement leaps out of his descriptions time after time, whether he was balancing relations between Israel and the moderate Arab states or brokering fiscal policy within the various factions of the Republican Party or within Congress as a whole.</p>
        <p>By way of example, for the first 17 months, Reagan was having problems with Alexander Haig, his first secretary of state. Haig had been Richard Nixon's last chief of staff, and in the months before Nixon's midsummer 1974 resignation, the ego-driven Haig had come to think of himself as the de facto policy maker. That did not work with Reagan, and his entry for June 25, 1982, noted that he had decided to accept Haig's resignation after Haig had acknowledged disagreements between them. ''Actually, the only disagreement was over whether I made policy or the Sec. of State did.''</p>
        <p>The diaries also shed quite a bit of light on the former California governor's particular brand of Republican politics. He made periodic negative references to some of the Republican Party's moderates -- Senators Charles Mathias, Bob Packwood and Lowell Weicker, for example. However, he was equally critical (or more so) of New Right and supply-side stalwarts like Richard Viguerie; Howard Phillips; William Simon; Senators Jesse Helms, Gordon Humphrey and Bill Armstrong; and the weekly conservative magazine Human Events. To Reagan, the Sun Myung Moon-owned Washington Times is ''becoming as R. Wing as The Post is L. Wing.''</p>
        <p>Much as he favored tax cuts and spending reductions, he drew a line at supporting zealots in the House of Representatives like Jack Kemp and Newt Gingrich, explaining to himself why he thought their economic proposals were simplistic. Reagan thought Kemp was particularly uncollaborative and unhelpful. The conservative breed he favored included California money men who were his old friends; Wall Street mavericks like Treasury Secretary Donald Regan and William Casey, the director of central intelligence; moderate conservatives like James Baker III and Howard Baker (two of his choices for White House chief of staff); George Shultz and Henry Kissinger in foreign affairs; Margaret Thatcher and her colleagues in Britain; and the East Coast, somewhat Tory-type American conservatives centered around William F. Buckley's National Review. By 1984, he was frequently talking to -- and heeding -- former President Nixon.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the ultimate indication of where Reagan stood was his increasing support for Vice President George H. W. Bush as his political heir. I can't remember a single sentence in ''The Reagan Diaries'' that was critical of Bush. By late 1984, just after his landslide re-election, he noted that Howard Baker had inquired whether he would be neutral in the race for the Republican nomination in 1988. On Nov. 27, 1984, Reagan told himself what he probably had not told Baker: ''When the time comes I'm afraid that my heart will be with George B. if he makes the run.'' Nowhere does he discuss Bush's internal White House influence, but it was probably great, especially in matters relating to foreign policy and the Central Intelligence Agency.</p>
        <p>When it came to the ''liberal'' press, Reagan rarely has much good to say in these pages. During his first term, favorite epithets included ''irresponsible,'' ''demagogic'' and ''lynch mob.'' His anger appeared to slacken in 1983 and 1984, but returned in 1985 and in the years thereafter with complaints about the coverage of his visit to the German World War II cemetery in Bitburg, United States policy in Central America and the Iran-contra scandal. By his last year in the White House, his disgruntlement was often encapsulated in a single word: ''phony.''</p>
        <p>Family and religion were two subjects that received a great deal of Reagan's attention. Brinkley underscores the importance of family to Reagan when he writes in his introduction that ''rarely can one turn a page without realizing that Ronald Reagan's marriage to Nancy was the cornerstone of his life.'' The intensity of the marriage, however, seemed to complicate the two parents' relations with the children, especially Ron and Patti.</p>
        <p>Reagan's religion, in turn, comes across as important, but quirky. Entries for early 1981 include references to Armageddon being in the air. Reagan also sets down his strong feelings that the fetus is a living human being and that the Shroud of Turin is authentic. He was obviously bothered by his limited church attendance, especially in the wake of the 1981 assassination attempt, as we can glean from his comments about how ''elaborate security measures'' made his visits ''a hazard to others.'' On the quirky side, the 1988 flap over the Reagans' interest in astrology gave some church groups pause -- the Southern Baptist Convention briefly considered withdrawing the speaking invitation it had extended to him -- and it must be said that Reagan's easy dismissal of the astrology question in these diaries is too brief to be convincing.</p>
        <p>If the president's love for his wife suffuses the diaries, so does his affection for the movie business and his old Hollywood friends. In scores of entries, the highlight of a day seems to be the visit he enjoyed with Claudette Colbert, or the tribute to Fred Astaire he attended, or a song performed at the White House by Mary Martin or the movie -- sometimes one of his own -- he watched after dinner. And apparently he was neverhappier than when he was riding at Camp David, Quantico or his California ranch -- probably 30 to 40 horse-riding references occur over the years -- or chopping wood at the ranch. This was Reagan's world, and revisiting it as frequently as he could obviously cheered and relaxed him.</p>
        <p>But it's entries like these that make me think Brinkley's favorable interpretations of Reagan and the diaries go a bit too far. In many ways, the Reagan presidency was successful. However, if any central weakness leaps out of this book, it is Reagan's tendency to view the presidency and its challenges in terms of personal media performance and people-to-people salesmanship. The Great Communicator thought so much about the image of his office that many of the entries show him preening like a peacock over public approval and perceived milestones. Consider these four comments selected from about two dozen: ''The speech was very well received. ... It got the most applause of any U.S. presidential address to the U.N.'' ''Addressed the Japanese Diet. ... P.M. said no other head of state had ever received such applause.'' ''I am the 1st Am. Pres. to ever address the European Parliament.'' ''At 7:30 on our way to the annual Prayer Brkfst. ... Billy Graham called me a Pastor to the Nation.''</p>
        <p>Obviously, this attention to public relations often related to genuine principles and firm policy objectives -- anti-Communism, reduced government, balanced budgets, support for deployment of the MX missile system, commitment to the right-wing contras in Nicaragua, dislike for Muammar el-Qaddafi of Libya and many more. Or to seemingly sincere stands that could turn into stubborn causes -- like refusing to cancel his visit to the Bitburg cemetery.</p>
        <p>Still, the diaries do seem to confirm that Reagan had an ingrained habit of substituting public relations for serious policy. For example, instead of fighting disease and ill health with a program to fill the huge gaps in national health insurance coverage, he chose to meet or visit children and adults suffering from dangerous illnesses and empathize with them. Likewise, he thought he could transcend his reputation as a president uninterested in civil rights by calling on a black family or meeting with black clergymen (''This may be a breakthrough''). After the Supreme Court justice Thurgood Marshall labeled him a racist, he wrote in his diary that ''My record &amp; the record of this admin. on such matters is out ahead of any other admin. in our history.''</p>
        <p>From 1986 on, Reagan's presidency suffered from the Iran-contra scandals, during which he appeared out of the loop, and from widespread perceptions that he was getting too old, that his capacities were ebbing. Reporters claimed he now needed to be given a script for the meetings he attended. Perhaps hints of his later Alzheimer's were showing, and scholars may well get a better picture of his mental acuity from the five full volumes of diaries. However, my sense is that the entries for 1987 and 1988 do reveal fewer days of heavy policy engagement and a schedule edging toward that of a ceremonial chief executive. By the end of his second term he was, after all, in his late 70s.</p>
        <p>Partly because of his people sense and his media skills, Reagan may well be remembered as the most successful president of the 1968-2008 period. But readers of ''The Reagan Diaries'' may find themselves becoming eerily aware of something missing. Nowhere does this popular president speak of the challenges of the approaching millennium, of history and its turning points, of the squeeze on the same middle class that provided him with enormous support or the transformation of the American economy as manufacturing gave way to speculation and finance. These, apparently, were not his concerns.</p>
        <p>Kevin Phillips is the author, most recently, of ''American Theocracy: The Perils and Politics of Radical Religion, Oil and Borrowed Money.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Kevin Phillips is the author, most recently, of ''American Theocracy: The Perils and Politics of Radical Religion, Oil and Borrowed Money.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
