<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Teamsters Official Is Expected to Succeed Indicted President of Central Labor Council</title>
    <meta content="17labor" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/17labor.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855280"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York City Central Labor Council</org>
        <org class="online_producer">International Brotherhood of Teamsters</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gambino Crime Family</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE2DE123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="903" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Teamsters Official Is Expected to Succeed Indicted President of Central Labor Council</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Teamsters Official Is Expected to Succeed Indicted President of Central Labor Council</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gary La Barbera, who helped lead efforts to clean up a Teamsters local once controlled by the Gambino crime family, has been tapped to become the next president of the New York City Central Labor Council.</p>
        <p>Mr. La Barbera would succeed Brian M. McLaughlin, who headed the council, the nation's largest municipal labor council, until he was indicted in October on charges of obtaining $2.2 million through embezzlement, fraud and bribes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gary La Barbera will succeed Brian M. McLaughlin as president of the New York City Central Labor Council.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gary La Barbera, who helped lead efforts to clean up a Teamsters local once controlled by the Gambino crime family, has been tapped to become the next president of the New York City Central Labor Council.</p>
        <p>Mr. La Barbera would succeed Brian M. McLaughlin, who headed the council, the nation's largest municipal labor council, until he was indicted in October on charges of obtaining $2.2 million through embezzlement, fraud and bribes.</p>
        <p>The council's nominating committee selected Mr. La Barbera last month to head the official slate, several top labor officials said, and the more than 400 delegates are expected to elect him when they gather on June 25. For now, he is running unopposed. Mr. La Barbera, 47, has a reputation as a corruption fighter. He was named trustee in 1996 to oversee Teamsters Local 282, a onetime Gambino fief that represents nearly 4,000 cement truck drivers and other construction industry drivers.</p>
        <p>For the past three years, he has also headed the Teamsters district council for metropolitan New York, which represents 100,000 truck drivers, warehouse workers and other Teamsters.</p>
        <p>Unhappy with the way so much power was concentrated in Mr. McLaughlin, who became council president in 1995, delegates are also expected to approve a new constitution in which the council's president and executive director divide responsibilities and the president is limited to one three-year term.</p>
        <p>Previous presidents headed the council's board and ran the council day to day, but under the new constitution, the president will be board chairman and the executive director will serve as chief operating officer, running operations day to day. The new constitution makes the presidency a part-time, unpaid position.</p>
        <p>The new constitution also calls for creating a 10-person executive committee, drawn from the council's 40-member board and comprising some of the city's top labor leaders, to advise the president and executive director.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of a historic change to move away from a structure that is centered on one individual and open things up and diffuse power to a larger group of people,'' said Denis M. Hughes, president of the New York State A.F.L.-C.I.O.</p>
        <p>After the F.B.I. raided the labor council's offices in March 2006, John J. Sweeney, president of the national A.F.L.-C.I.O., asked Mr. Hughes to step in to help oversee the labor council and revamp its constitution and structure.</p>
        <p>The council, which represents more than one million New York union members, is part of the A.F.L.-C.I.O. and helps oversee and coordinate union activities in politics, lobbying and organizing.</p>
        <p>''I think they have restructured the labor council in a way that will make it much stronger,'' Mr. Sweeney said.</p>
        <p>In an unusual move, the council's nominating committee picked Mr. La Barbera as presidential nominee even though he is an official in a union, the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, which was one of several that quit the A.F.L.-C.I.O. two years ago and joined the rival Change to Win labor federation.</p>
        <p>Randi Weingarten, president of the city's teachers union and a member of the council's board, said, ''This is a pretty big indicator of how well the A.F.L.-C.I.O. unions and the Change to Win unions are working together in this city.''</p>
        <p>Mr. La Barbera joined the Teamsters in 1981 when he became a forklift operator at a King Kullen warehouse on Long Island.</p>
        <p>''Unions are relevant,'' he said on Friday. ''The reality is unions give people the opportunity to move into the middle class. Beyond wages, unions are also about health benefits, pension benefits, dignity in the workplace and safety in the workplace.''</p>
        <p>Mr. La Barbera is registered to vote as a Democrat but says he has supported Republicans he considers worker-friendly, including United States Representative Peter King of Long Island and former Gov. George E. Pataki. Last November, he backed Eliot Spitzer, a Democrat, for governor.</p>
        <p>Even though Mr. La Barbera has long lived and worked in the suburbs -- he lives in Wantagh, and Local 282 is based in Lake Success -- he says he has the experience to run an urban labor council.</p>
        <p>For a decade, he said, he has been ''deeply engrossed in urban issues'' as president of the Teamsters council and head of a local that represents truck drivers throughout the metropolitan area.</p>
        <p>The council's new president will work closely with Ed Ott, the executive director. Mr. Ott was the political director but was promoted last August when Mr. McLaughlin took a paid leave. After Mr. McLaughlin was indicted, the leave became an unpaid one, although, not having been convicted of anything, he technically remains council president until next week's vote.</p>
        <p>As executive director, Mr. Ott has pushed to increase union organizing, reach out to immigrant workers and improve labor's effectiveness in political campaigns.</p>
        <p>The nominating committee selected Jack Ahern, business manager of Operating Engineers Local 30, to become the council's executive vice president. Under the proposed constitution, the executive vice president will provide aggressive financial oversight and will succeed the president after three years.</p>
        <p>Some labor leaders voiced concern that in a city teeming with black, Hispanic and Asian workers, the labor council's top three officials would all be non-Hispanic white men.</p>
        <p>''Diversity is an issue of extreme concern to some of our affiliates and to our own leadership, and we're working to get better at it,'' Mr. Ott said. ''We now have a form of term limits, and that should give every board member a real shot at running this organization.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
