<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Endings Without Endings</title>
    <meta content="17mcgr" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/weekinreview/17mcgr.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855209"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="IDEAS &amp; TRENDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Home Box Office</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E7D7153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Endings Without Endings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Endings Without Endings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES McGRATH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HUH? The black screen at the end of the series-concluding episode of ''The Sopranos'' last Sunday caused thousands of viewers to leap from the couch and smack the cable box, suspecting a loose connection. So many sent e-mail messages to HBO that the company's Web site was temporarily jammed, and debate over the meaning and worthiness of this particular ending has continued on the blogs and next to the water cooler.</p>
        <p>Depending on whom you listen to, the blackout at the very end of ''The Sopranos'' was either sublimely appropriate, the perfect summation of the show's complexity and ambiguity, or else the biggest gimmick since Bob Newhart, at the end of his second TV series, woke up in bed next to Suzanne Pleshette, the wife on his first series, and announced that it had all been a dream. In an interview with The Star-Ledger of Newark, David Chase, the creator of ''The Sopranos,'' said that he hadn't intended the ending to trick viewers or mess with their minds, but he nevertheless disembarked for France before the final episode was shown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“The Sopranos” finale outraged viewers. But it’s not the first work to end in the mid...</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HUH? The black screen at the end of the series-concluding episode of ''The Sopranos'' last Sunday caused thousands of viewers to leap from the couch and smack the cable box, suspecting a loose connection. So many sent e-mail messages to HBO that the company's Web site was temporarily jammed, and debate over the meaning and worthiness of this particular ending has continued on the blogs and next to the water cooler.</p>
        <p>Depending on whom you listen to, the blackout at the very end of ''The Sopranos'' was either sublimely appropriate, the perfect summation of the show's complexity and ambiguity, or else the biggest gimmick since Bob Newhart, at the end of his second TV series, woke up in bed next to Suzanne Pleshette, the wife on his first series, and announced that it had all been a dream. In an interview with The Star-Ledger of Newark, David Chase, the creator of ''The Sopranos,'' said that he hadn't intended the ending to trick viewers or mess with their minds, but he nevertheless disembarked for France before the final episode was shown.</p>
        <p>Why do we care so much about how television series -- or novels or movies, for that matter -- finish up?</p>
        <p>In ''The Sense of an Ending,'' a classic text of literary theory, the critic Frank Kermode says we crave endings for the same reason that some religious sects look forward to the Apocalypse -- because it's the ending that gives shape and meaning to the otherwise random events that precede it.</p>
        <p>Hollywood has typically taken this yearning for closure to mean that all resolutions must be happy and no thread can be left loose -- unless, of course, there's a chance for a sequel. But from episode to episode, and season to season, ''The Sopranos'' defied this convention, as it has so many others, dangling loose ends in a way that put additional pressure on the finale. There were literalists who tuned in Sunday still hoping to learn what had become of that Russian gunman stumbling around in the snow.</p>
        <p>Not that all great works obey the rules about ending, however. Haydn loved to toy with expectation. Some of his quartets have false climaxes, the way a lot of Stephen King movies do, and then start up again, while his ''Farewell'' Symphony famously concludes not with a grand resolution but with a long dying fall.</p>
        <p>Equally famously, ''Finnegans Wake'' ends midsentence, and so does ''The Tale of Genji,'' the 11th-century Japanese novel, though scholars are still debating whether that's intentional or the result of an unfinished manuscript. Deliberate or not, the ending works, in part because ''Genji'' is among the most ''Soprano''-like of texts -- an extended family saga, about the son of an imperial father, in which the plot often meanders and people suddenly drop out and then reappear years later, just as they do in life.</p>
        <p>To the idea of irresolution -- the idea of life as a plot that goes on and on and then stops, still in medias res -- the ''Sopranos'' ending added ambiguity, another time-honored convention. It's the principle behind the ending of Charlotte Brontë's ''Villette,'' to take one of many examples, which she rewrote at the urging of her father so that it's left for the reader to decide whether or not the heroine's true love, M. Paul, dies in a shipwreck.</p>
        <p>To judge from the blogs, viewers are about equally divided as to whether that blackout represents the end of consciousness and the darkness of the grave -- meaning that Tony does indeed get whacked in the end -- or is simply a dramatic fade-out on a diminished but ongoing family situation, with Carmela as morally compromised as ever, Meadow as clueless, and A. J. no closer to growing up than when the series began. In this reading there is closure of at least one sort, though: Tony is at last finished with analysis.</p>
        <p>If you were fashionably inclined, you could also give the ending a meta-reading. What is that dark screen but an image of the darkness that was there before you turned your TV on in the first place?</p>
        <p>In this interpretation we are reminded, the way we are reminded, say, by all the textual gimmicks in ''Tristram Shandy,'' that what we have been attending to is a construct -- a show, in this case. Not only that, but we also realize that Tony never lived in West Caldwell, N.J., at all, but inside our sets, where he resides still, granted a gift that is about the last that we would ever have expected for him: immortality.</p>
        <p>IDEAS &amp; TRENDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
