<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Close to Mexico As the County Gets</title>
    <meta content="17dineweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/17dinewe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855026"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/WHITE PLAINS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sunset Grille (White Plains, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Denitto, Emily</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E3D7143FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Close to Mexico As the County Gets</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">As Close to Mexico as the County Gets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EMILY DeNITTO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Denitto, Emily</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Emily DeNitto reviews Sunset Grille in White Plains, NY; hotos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE first thing you'll notice about Sunset Grille in White Plains is the tortilla chips automatically placed at each table. Thicker and darker than the usual fare, they have a richer, nuttier taste as well. The green and red salsas that accompany them are different, too. They lack the electric color and processed taste of most Mexican restaurants' offerings.</p>
        <p>That's because it's all made fresh right in Sunset Grille's kitchen. Greg Cortelyou, the executive chef, goes through 120 to 200 pounds of tomatillos a week for the sauces. The chips -- and all the masa, or corn dough -- are made from scratch with a corn mill that Mr. Cortelyou and Scott Faupel, the owner, traveled to the Midwest to find.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sunset Grille in White Plains serves a welcome blend of authentic homestyle Mexican cooking fused with upscale contemporary cuisine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE first thing you'll notice about Sunset Grille in White Plains is the tortilla chips automatically placed at each table. Thicker and darker than the usual fare, they have a richer, nuttier taste as well. The green and red salsas that accompany them are different, too. They lack the electric color and processed taste of most Mexican restaurants' offerings.</p>
        <p>That's because it's all made fresh right in Sunset Grille's kitchen. Greg Cortelyou, the executive chef, goes through 120 to 200 pounds of tomatillos a week for the sauces. The chips -- and all the masa, or corn dough -- are made from scratch with a corn mill that Mr. Cortelyou and Scott Faupel, the owner, traveled to the Midwest to find.</p>
        <p>Their dedication to the fresh and housemade doesn't stop there: drinks are all prepared with fresh-squeezed juices; seasonal ingredients, like the soft shell crab that was recently cooked tempura style then added to a light and delicious corn chowder, are sought out.</p>
        <p>These are not the Tex-Mex dishes most county residents are familiar with. There are no hard-shell tacos or ground beef stuffings. Instead, Sunset Grille is attempting a welcome blend of authentic homestyle Mexican cooking fused with upscale contemporary cuisine in the tradition of Rosa Mexicano in Manhattan or Border Grill in Santa Monica, Calif.</p>
        <p>Most of their efforts succeed. The crispy pastry empanada, a traditional South American appetizer that's often filled with beef, came stuffed with lump crab meat and was served with perfectly ripe avocado and a tasty mango salsa. A common tilapia filet entree was transformed into something special by a green plantain crust, chili potato gratin and pineapple guajillo sauce. And the grilled Angus sirloin -- a great cut, cooked exactly as ordered -- was raised considerably by the spiciness of a chile de arbol chimichurri sauce.</p>
        <p>Not everything at Sunset Grille is complicated. Tacos can come filled with citrus marinated pork and grilled pineapple, but they are also offered with simple shredded chicken, tomatoes and onions or with grilled steak and some salsa for a light unadorned taste. The green market chopped salad is another straightforward and terrific choice: sweet beets mixed with the bite of raw onion and crunchy celery played off chunks of soft avocado in an herb vinaigrette.</p>
        <p>For an entree, the masa tasting platter is a good sampling of different tastes. It includes a chicken taco, cheese enchilada, red or green tamale and a panucho -- a corn tortilla topped with refried beans and egg, citrus marinated chicken, pickled red onion and cotija cheese. The chile relleno was one of the best I've ever tasted. Earthy pignola nuts enhanced the cheese and chicken stuffing while sweet raisins contrasted seductively with the spicy salsas on top. The red snapper Veracruz style was a wonderfully rendered classic, tweaked by a little twist of toasted almonds.</p>
        <p>A roasted salmon fillet special came with too much achiote barbecue sauce, but even this was remedied with the swipe of a fork. The sauce itself was a subtle but flavorful pleasure.</p>
        <p>Whatever you order, don't ignore the specialty drinks. The wine list is fairly basic (though plans to expand it with more California brands are under way) and you can always order sangria, an imported beer or one of the dozen-plus tequilas. But I'd try something like the housemade horchata offered recently. This rice-based nonalcoholic drink was like tasting liquid rice pudding.</p>
        <p>Several of Sunset Grille's desserts are standouts as well. Coconut flan, accompanied by delicious shortbread cookies, had the perfect texture -- firm but yielding -- and a rich satisfying taste. A chocolate torte with Kahlúa whipped cream and berries was a similarly intense, moist treat.</p>
        <p>Sunset Grille</p>
        <p>68 Gedney Way  White Plains  (914) 227-9353  www.sunsetgrilleny.com</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE -- Colorful and light, with murals, an exposed brick wall and blond wood tables and chairs. Three dining areas allow for slightly different experiences. Not wheelchair accessible; several steps at entrance and between dining areas.THE CROWD Mixed. More families in the two dining areas separate from the bar.</p>
        <p>THE BAR -- The pulse of the main dining room. Terrific margaritas, over a dozen choices of tequila, and several specialty drinks, like the nonalcoholic rice-based horchata. The basic wine list will soon be enhanced with more California brands. Most offerings come by the glass; bottles are $24 to $45.</p>
        <p>THE BILL -- Lunch entrees, $6 to $17; dinner entrees, $17 to $25. All major credit cards accepted.</p>
        <p>WHAT WE LIKE -- Guacamole, ceviche, empanada, tamales, corn chowder with soft shell crab (special), fried calamari; chopped salad; red snapper Veracruz, masa tasting platter, chile relleno, grilled Angus sirloin; rhubarb crisp (special), coconut flan, chocolate torte.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO -- Lunch: Monday to Friday, noon to 4 p.m. Dinner: daily, 5:30 to 10 p.m. Happy hour: Monday to Friday, 4 to 7 p.m. Reservations recommended on weekends.</p>
        <p>Reviewed June 17, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/WHITE PLAINS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
