<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lauren Doyle, Andrew Exnicios</title>
    <meta content="17Doyle" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/fashion/weddings/17Doyle.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855114"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Doyle, Lauren Melissa (Lauren Melissa Exnicios)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Exnicios, Andrew Smith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EFDB153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="644" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lauren Doyle, Andrew Exnicios</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lauren Doyle, Andrew Exnicios</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lauren Melissa Doyle and Andrew Smith Exnicios, both captains in the United States Army, were married yesterday morning. The Rev. Eric J. Albertson, a Roman Catholic priest and an Army chaplain, performed the ceremony at the Woodlawn Chapel at Fort Belvoir, Va.</p>
        <p>The bride, 27, is serving as a judge advocate at Fort Carson, Colo. Next month she will be reassigned to Fort Belvoir. She graduated cum laude from Fairfield University and received her law degree from Washington University.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lauren Melissa Doyle and Andrew Smith Exnicios, both captains in the United States Army, were married yesterday morning. The Rev. Eric J. Albertson, a Roman Catholic priest and an Army chaplain, performed the ceremony at the Woodlawn Chapel at Fort Belvoir, Va.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lauren Melissa Doyle and Andrew Smith Exnicios, both captains in the United States Army, were married yesterday morning. The Rev. Eric J. Albertson, a Roman Catholic priest and an Army chaplain, performed the ceremony at the Woodlawn Chapel at Fort Belvoir, Va.</p>
        <p>The bride, 27, is serving as a judge advocate at Fort Carson, Colo. Next month she will be reassigned to Fort Belvoir. She graduated cum laude from Fairfield University and received her law degree from Washington University.</p>
        <p>She is the daughter of Dianne and Mark Doyle of Willimantic, Conn. Her father is a regional sales representative in Willimantic for Dealer Profit Center, a firm in Floral Park, N.Y., that represents companies selling extended warranties and other products to car dealerships. Her mother is an assistant treasurer of the NewAlliance Bank based in New Haven and is the manager of branches in Storrs and Hebron, Conn.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, also 27, is a civil affairs officer. Next week he is to report for two weeks of training at Fort Jackson, S.C., and will then be stationed at Fort Bragg, in Fayetteville, N.C., while awaiting an assignment overseas. He graduated from Duke and last month received his M.B.A. from the University of California, Berkeley.</p>
        <p>He is the son of Meredith and James Exnicios of Manassas, Va. His mother retired as a special education teacher at Quantico Middle/High School at the Marine Corps base in Virginia. His father retired as an Army Reserve colonel and judge advocate and now serves as a civilian lawyer with the Department of the Navy in Arlington, Va.</p>
        <p>The couple met in South Bend, Ind., when they served as a bridesmaid and a groomsman at the wedding of mutual friends, Clarence and Kelly Lee, in December 2004.</p>
        <p>''Clarence had told me that he thought I would really like her,'' Captain Exnicios said. ''She was thinking of going into the Army, she was Catholic like me and had a sense of humor similar to mine. It was nice to meet someone in my social circle who understood the choice I had made years earlier to join the Army.''</p>
        <p>''At the rehearsal, I saw three or four bridesmaids lined up and I thought, I really hope that one is Lauren.''</p>
        <p>It was.</p>
        <p>And her first impression? ''I knew this was someone special,'' Captain Doyle said.</p>
        <p>After their friends' wedding, they parted, as he was stationed in Lawton, Okla., and she was in basic training in Charlottesville, Va. They remained in contact daily through e-mail and in March he traveled to Washington to meet her for their first official date.</p>
        <p>In May 2005, his Army service was up, and he was attending Berkeley, while she was stationed at Fort Carson, near Colorado Springs. After two years apart, they were planning to move together to Seattle where he had accepted a job with Amazon and she began negotiations for a transfer.</p>
        <p>It was not to be. Last September, he was recalled to active duty. ''It was a total shock,'' she said. ''We thought that chapter of Andrew's life was over.'' As a military lawyer, she helped him fill out paperwork to win deferment, which was extended to the end of this month, and they decided to marry sooner than planned.</p>
        <p>The bride who said she had always envisioned ''a large church wedding with lots of attendants and big poufy dresses'' scaled back her plans to a small family event at her in-laws' house. One uncle was recruited to serve as photographer, another uncle and aunt were to provide the music and cousins were to act as waiters and bartenders for the reception.</p>
        <p>''This isn't the wedding I dreamed of as a little girl,'' she said, ''but it certainly helped me to see what is really important, that Andrew and I get married and have our families witness it. In the end, that's all we'll remember.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
