<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Young Beyond Its Years</title>
    <meta content="17boite" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/fashion/17boite.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855131"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOÎTE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drunken and Reckless Driving</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drunken and Reckless Driving</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E7DA153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="518" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Young Beyond Its Years</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Young Beyond Its Years</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MONICA CORCORAN</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY say that Hollywood hot spots age faster than dogs, and by such standards, the lounge Teddy's should be a lame old hound. But this club, situated within the Roosevelt Hotel that opened in 2005 and shuttered for a few months in 2006, has yet to develop even a limp.</p>
        <p>On a recent Friday night outside the hotel, 20 or so hopefuls fidgeted beyond the velvet rope. (It's hard to look carefree when rejection looms.) The local Internet celebrity Cory Kennedy stood away from the throng and pleaded to the doorman with her saucer-shaped eyes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Teddy’s, a lounge within the Roosevelt Hotel that opened in 2005 and shuttered for a few months in 2006, is running strong.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEY say that Hollywood hot spots age faster than dogs, and by such standards, the lounge Teddy's should be a lame old hound. But this club, situated within the Roosevelt Hotel that opened in 2005 and shuttered for a few months in 2006, has yet to develop even a limp.</p>
        <p>On a recent Friday night outside the hotel, 20 or so hopefuls fidgeted beyond the velvet rope. (It's hard to look carefree when rejection looms.) The local Internet celebrity Cory Kennedy stood away from the throng and pleaded to the doorman with her saucer-shaped eyes.</p>
        <p>''Go on home, Cory,'' the bouncer said gently, but firmly. She shook her head and moped off.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kennedy, 17, is not the only one being turned away lately. ''The door people everywhere in Hollywood are being really strict with IDs now,'' said Sivan Goldstein, 24, who at 11:30 p.m. was lounging by the hotel's pool bar, known as the Tropicana. ''It's changed since the Lindsay incident.''</p>
        <p>The incident, in which the actress Lindsay Lohan, 20, crashed her car in Hollywood and was arrested at 5:30 a.m. on May 27 on charges of drunk driving, has stirred the night life world here. Days after the incident, the State Alcoholic Beverage Control Board said it would investigate the possibility that she was served illegally and that it is seeking a 15-day license suspension of the Hollywood nightclub Mood. A hearing is pending. (Ms. Lohan was not spotted at Teddy's before being arrested.)</p>
        <p>''The only person whose ID I haven't swiped is Steve Bing,'' said Med Abrous, the director of entertainment for Thompson Hotels, which operates Teddy's. ''That's because he has a full head of gray hair.''</p>
        <p>Actually, Mr. Bing, a movie producer who is 42, wouldn't blend in here. On this night, most patrons looked too young to shoulder a mortgage, and didn't seem particularly circumspect about consumption. Bottles of Patrón tequila and buckets of Champagne on ice decorated the tables marked ''reserved'' and surrounded by chocolate leather booths. It felt like something out of ''Catcher in the Rye'' 56 years later. Holden Caulfield would have squirmed as cliques of shaggy-haired men and lithe red-lipped young women formed around him.</p>
        <p>Was the fate of Ms. Lohan affecting anyone's behavior?</p>
        <p>''It's too bad that there's no transportation in Los Angeles and drivers are so expensive,'' said Annie Zee, 21, a student from New York. ''I feel like I need to be more responsible about drinking when I visit here, but '' She winked and sidled off to dance.</p>
        <p>Teddy's  7000 Hollywood Boulevard; (323) 436-7000</p>
        <p>GETTING IN -- There is always a list, though bouncers do make exceptions; Thursday is the hardest night to gain entry.</p>
        <p>DRESS CODE -- Cocktail dresses with Marc Jacobs pumps for women; skinny ties with skinny jeans and sneakers for men.</p>
        <p>DJ PICKS -- ''I Can't Explain'' by the Who, ''Dirty Deeds Done Dirt Cheap'' by AC/DC.</p>
        <p>SIGHTINGS -- Christina Aguilera, Orlando Bloom.</p>
        <p>SIGNATURE DRINK -- Millionaire Mojito, with 10 Cane Rum and Veuve Clicquot; $18.</p>
        <p>BOÎTE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
