<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>We Can't Just Duck and Cover</title>
    <meta content="l17bomb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855229"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E0D7153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1051" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>We Can't Just Duck and Cover</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''After the Bomb,'' by William J. Perry, Ashton B. Carter and Michael M. May (Op-Ed, June 12):</p>
        <p>It is important that all generations of Americans face up to the implications of the detonation of a nuclear device in a major city. The horrors of Hiroshima and Nagasaki should be constantly on our minds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''After the Bomb,'' by William J. Perry, Ashton B. Carter and Michael M. May (Op-Ed, June 12):</p>
        <p>It is important that all generations of Americans face up to the implications of the detonation of a nuclear device in a major city. The horrors of Hiroshima and Nagasaki should be constantly on our minds.</p>
        <p>I worked on the Manhattan Project as a chemical engineer during World War II, and the total destruction of the bomb is still with me every day. Unfortunately, the true terror is almost incomprehensible and for many is easily put aside.</p>
        <p>The danger is not just for American cities; all corners of the earth are at risk. It has become painfully apparent that in the long run, the leaders of the world are incapable of controlling future use of the bomb.</p>
        <p>Our only hope for preventing future use of nuclear bombs is to establish foolproof, worldwide control of the materials that go into them.</p>
        <p>Is a meaningful program of control still possible? Yes. Do-able? Yes. Would it be expensive? Very. Is it necessary? Absolutely.</p>
        <p>The clock continues to tick.</p>
        <p>Norman D. Carter  Poughkeepsie, N.Y., June 12, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In their article about what's to be done in case of ''a nuclear weapon one day going off,'' William J. Perry, Ashton B. Carter and Michael M. May touched only lightly on the need for ''forceful efforts to prevent'' such a ''day from coming.'' They do say that those efforts should have been ''more forceful than we have seen in recent years.''</p>
        <p>In other words, the current administration, preoccupied with its fantasies, has willfully failed in its duty to defend and protect. And we the people, with our watchdogs of democracy, are just basically going along.</p>
        <p>Valentin Lyubarsky  Brooklyn, June 12, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>This assessment of the aftereffects of a nuclear attack on a major city, let's say New York, seems a bit cool and dispassionate. If a nuclear bomb went off in Midtown, a bomb big enough to cause fires for miles and irradiate a major portion of the city while winds whipped poison clouds hither and yon, millions of people would panic and flee. Period.</p>
        <p>What terrified civilian would put up with being corralled by the police, Army or National Guard? For that matter, what police officer or soldier or firefighter would listen to orders to stay in an irradiated city?</p>
        <p>There are only two things that those of us in likely target areas can hope for: we're never attacked with a nuclear device because our security forces are on the ball -- or, we die quickly.</p>
        <p>Arthur Chertowsky  Brooklyn, June 12, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>None of us can imagine the depth of rage and desire for vengeance that would sweep this country if the United States were attacked with a nuclear bomb. I have to believe that even the most liberal president would retaliate against someone with nuclear weapons.</p>
        <p>Whom would we attack if we didn't know who attacked us? The America I know would use this to strike out at those enemies we perceive as supporters of terrorism. Today, Iran and Pakistan would have to be at the top of that list. The clock is ticking, not just for America, but for those countries that find sport in encouraging global terror.</p>
        <p>Gordon Sell  Flemington, N.J., June 12, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>We will probably have to wait for a more responsible and competent administration before we can expect federal agencies to develop plans for coping with a nuclear attack. But as a New Yorker, I have long been distressed that we have never received any information from the city on what to do if a nuclear, chemical or conventional attack occurred.</p>
        <p>I am shocked that parents have never received information from the schools about how they plan to deal with children in school in the aftermath of an attack.</p>
        <p>It is somewhat heartening to learn that simply sheltering in basements for the first few days after a nuclear attack would increase survival rates, but the basements of my apartment building and my children's school are crowded with rubbish and have no stock of essential supplies.</p>
        <p>In the absence of any information, panic will ensue, maximizing fatalities.</p>
        <p>Richard Seager  New York, June 12, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Should people be alarmed about the country's preparedness for a nuclear attack? All anyone has to do is look at the response to Katrina.</p>
        <p>Victims of ill-preparedness were imprisoned in the Superdome, and some were forced back into the devastated city at gunpoint by hostile neighboring police.</p>
        <p>Two years later, state and federal governments have offered token or no relief to the hurricane's victims and have done little or nothing toward rebuilding viable neighborhoods, while the prognosis for the rebuilt levee system is pretty grim.</p>
        <p>Look what the Sept. 11 attacks have done to our constitutional protections and to the civilized values that once found torture repellant.</p>
        <p>After a nuclear attack, I'm afraid the curtain will come down on all of our tomorrows.</p>
        <p>Paul Bloom  San Francisco, June 12, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>William J. Perry, Ashton B. Carter and Michael M. May say that over the past five years ''terrorism has surged into a mass global movement and seems to gather strength daily as extremism spills out of Iraq into the rest of the Middle East, Asia, Europe and even the Americas.''</p>
        <p>Why isolate the last five years? This extremist movement became mass and global after spilling out of Afghanistan in the early 1990s, when it began broadly recruiting and plotting major attacks around the world.</p>
        <p>These included the 1993 World Trade Center bombing; a 1995 plot in the Philippines to blow up 12 American jets over the Pacific; the 1998 African embassy bombings; the 2000 U.S.S. Cole bombing; and the Sept. 11, 2001, attacks. The destructive power of the movement remains limited only by the weapons it can get its hands on.</p>
        <p>Has the Iraq war exacerbated the threat? Yes. But let's not fool ourselves into thinking that the 1990s was a period of comparable calm.</p>
        <p>Stuart Gottlieb  New Haven, June 12, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is director of the policy studies program at Yale University.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
