<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With a Big Name Out, A New Favorite Emerges</title>
    <meta content="17open" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/sports/golf/17open.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">PGA Tour Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Mickelson, Phil</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Watson, Bubba</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E0DE123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="779" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With a Big Name Out, A New Favorite Emerges</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With a Big Name Out, a New Favorite Emerges</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa., June 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After the early exit of one of the fan favorites, Phil Mickelson, the crowds at Oakmont Country Club threw their voices behind another lovable American left-hander, who is trying to win his first United States Open.</p>
        <p>Bubba Watson, a small-town guy who hits a long ball, was the people's choice during the third round Saturday. Playing in the last twosome of the day, along with the second-round leader, Ángel Cabrera, Watson took the lead at one-over-par with a birdie at No. 7, only to give it back with a triple bogey at No. 9.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After the early exit of one of the fan favorites, Phil Mickelson, the crowds at Oakmont Country Club threw their voices behind Bubba Watson.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After the early exit of one of the fan favorites, Phil Mickelson, the crowds at Oakmont Country Club threw their voices behind another lovable American left-hander, who is trying to win his first United States Open.</p>
        <p>Bubba Watson, a small-town guy who hits a long ball, was the people's choice during the third round Saturday. Playing in the last twosome of the day, along with the second-round leader, Ángel Cabrera, Watson took the lead at one-over-par with a birdie at No. 7, only to give it back with a triple bogey at No. 9.</p>
        <p>Watson is not like Mickelson, who has 29 PGA Tour victories to steel him from Oakmont Country Club's cruel tricks. As he walked to the 10th tee, the fans lining the hole did their best to reinforce his confidence.</p>
        <p>''Bubba, walk that off,'' someone said.</p>
        <p>After conferring with his caddie, Watson hit the next tee shot, a perfectly struck 4-iron that landed in the fairway.</p>
        <p>''You're right there, man,'' a fan said as Watson walked down the fairway. ''C'mon, Bubba, get it back!'' shouted another.</p>
        <p>Watson hit his approach in the first cut of the rough, about 30 feet in front of the pin. He two-putted from there to make par, then played the remaining eight holes at one-over to salvage a four-over-par 74.</p>
        <p>After three rounds, Watson is tied for third place with Paul Casey, Stephen Ames and Justin Rose at five-over 215. They are three strokes behind the leader, Aaron Baddeley, who shot a 70 while playing in the group immediately ahead of Watson, and one shot behind Tiger Woods.</p>
        <p>It was a sign of how much Watson has grown as a golfer this week that he did not lose his composure in the greenside rough at No. 9.</p>
        <p>Watson knew as soon as he saw where his second shot landed that he was in trouble. He did not bother studying the shot from every angle; he simply stepped up and hit it. He was not being impatient, it was just that the shot was darn near impossible.</p>
        <p>''The first lie was really fluffy,'' he said. ''I was trying to blast it like a bunker shot. That's all you can do.''</p>
        <p>All Watson managed to do was advance the ball five feet, which meant he was also hitting the next shot from the rough, from an even tougher lie. He hit the ball thin and it rolled off the green on the opposite side. He chipped up and two putted for a 7.</p>
        <p>In the past, Watson has let bad shots derail his rounds. As he trudged to the 10th tee, his caddie delivered a pep talk. He told him that if he could hang in there, he would still be in good shape. Watson did and, with 18 holes to play, he is.</p>
        <p>His wife, Angie Watson, who played basketball with the Charlotte Sting in the W.N.B.A., marveled at how calm her husband remained. ''No doubt he's shown a lot of patience,'' she said. ''It's surprising to me because if it was me out there playing golf, I don't know if I'd be able to continue. It's just remarkable to me.''</p>
        <p>By persevering, Watson, who grew up in Bagdad, Fla., took a big step toward convincing himself he is worthy of playing alongside the world's best golfers.</p>
        <p>''It showed that I can do it,'' he said. ''I got 18 holes, I played some of the best golf I ever played.''</p>
        <p>Watson is self-deprecating, almost to a fault. He has become friends with Woods, which frankly amazes him. ''He's been nothing but nice to me,'' Watson said. ''I don't know why. Maybe he feels sorry for me or something.</p>
        <p>''After the first round he told me to be patient. He came out yesterday and said to do the same thing, just keep going. He sees a young guy who struggles a little bit, and he's been nice so far, until I start beating him I guess.''</p>
        <p>Watson laughed and the reporters hanging on his every word laughed with him. He has blown through this Open like a fresh breeze, regaling people with stories of passing the long hours between his rounds playing H-O-R-S-E with his wife and acting as if a bad round of golf was still a great way to make a living.</p>
        <p>''He's got a lovable personality,'' Angie Watson said. ''That's one of the reasons that I married him. I think he shows more character and more realism in the media center than a lot of other people.'' She added, ''He's very, very real and I think that's what people embrace and that's what people love about him.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
