<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Potter Fans Are on Board, Eagerly Awaiting the Finale</title>
    <meta content="17potternjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/17potternj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855066"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Newark (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Scholastic Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rowling, J K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aspan, Maria</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Newark Public Library</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Scholastic Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rowling, J K</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EFD6143FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="730" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Potter Fans Are on Board, Eagerly Awaiting the Finale</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Potter Fans Are on Board, Eagerly Awaiting the Finale</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARIA ASPAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Aspan, Maria</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scene at Newark Public Library's main branch described as Harry Potter fans visit Knight Bus, re-creation of magical ride in book series sponsored by Scholastic; libraries and bookstores across New Jersey are planning midnight parties for July 21 release of Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows, seventh and last book in series by J K Rowling; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE story's conclusion is still more than a month away, but New Jersey is already in the throes of Harry Potter mania.</p>
        <p>Libraries and bookstores across the state are planning midnight parties for July 21, when ''Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows,'' the seventh and last book in J. K. Rowling's series, will finally be released. On July 11, the film adaptation of the fifth book, ''Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix,'' will arrive in theaters. For impatient readers, events like the one at the library here last Saturday are already fueling the anticipation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Libraries and bookstores across New Jersey are planning midnight parties for the release of the seventh and final Harry Potter novel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE story's conclusion is still more than a month away, but New Jersey is already in the throes of Harry Potter mania.</p>
        <p>Libraries and bookstores across the state are planning midnight parties for July 21, when ''Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows,'' the seventh and last book in J. K. Rowling's series, will finally be released. On July 11, the film adaptation of the fifth book, ''Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix,'' will arrive in theaters. For impatient readers, events like the one at the library here last Saturday are already fueling the anticipation.</p>
        <p>More than 150 Harry Potter fans of all ages came to the Newark Public Library's main branch to visit the Knight Bus, an earthbound re-creation of the magical ride in the books. The bus, which is sponsored by Scholastic, the books' American publisher, was parked outside the library, slightly incongruous and very purple against the building's stone facade.</p>
        <p>The library's afternoon of Potter-related activities, which included a magic show and a chance for children to have their picture taken with a Muggle in costume as the owl Hedwig, was one of many events taking place across the state as New Jersey prepares to say goodbye to Harry.</p>
        <p>The bus was decorated inside and out to resemble the ''violently purple'' triple-decker bus that ferries wizards around Harry Potter's England. The interior was divided into a waiting area, decorated with plastic torches, purple curtains and a sign counting down the days to July 21.</p>
        <p>Visitors could browse the bookshelves filled with editions of Harry Potter, while waiting for their chance to crowd into the back room, barely bigger than a closet, where they could record 20-second videos about the books to be posted online at Scholastic's Web site (www.scholastic.com/harrypotter).</p>
        <p>The fans waited cheerfully in line, some in costume, some carrying books, some dragging parents and others dragging children. ''It's bittersweet,'' said Katie Boryeskne, 13, of Sparta, who was wearing a witch's hat and clutching a tattered copy of the third book while waiting to board the bus.</p>
        <p>According to her mother, Lori, Katie has already persuaded her family to curtail a shore vacation so that she can go to a midnight book party on July 21. ''I'm of course really excited, but also sad,'' Katie said.</p>
        <p>Michelle Krzykalski, 35, of Beverly, who teaches high school science in Hamilton Township, was carrying her 3-year-old daughter, Grace. Each wore a witch's robe and glittery eye shadow.</p>
        <p>''I hope to share Harry Potter with my children. It helps your imagination,'' said Ms. Krzykalski, who also has a young son. She added that, as her husband is not a fan, she planned to go to a midnight party, ''probably by myself, maybe dressed up,'' to get the seventh book on July 21. ''Just thinking about it makes me teary-eyed,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The Newark library was the only New Jersey stop on the Knight Bus's national tour, which began in New York City on June 1 and was expected to make 37 stops at libraries across the country before July 21.</p>
        <p>''Harry Potter fans love talking to each other, and this was a way to go into the communities and get fans talking to each other by video,'' said Sara Sinek, a spokeswoman for Scholastic who was at the library.</p>
        <p>Online communication is already a large part of the Harry Potter experience. Many of the people waiting to board the bus said that they rely on Web sites like MuggleNet.com or The-Leaky-Cauldron.org to get the latest news or to read and write ''fan fiction'' stories about the book and its characters. And some area libraries are paying attention to that.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot of kids doing fan fiction online, so I thought we could highlight local fan fiction,'' said Jessica Trujillo, the young adult librarian at the New Brunswick Free Public Library, which is running a Harry Potter writing contest this month. Children who enter can write a short story describing themselves interacting with the Harry Potter characters; winners, selected at random, will receive copies of the last book at the library's party on July 21.</p>
        <p>That deeply invested Harry Potter community may be good news for Harry and his friends, who will continue to thrive online and among readers, regardless of their official ultimate fates. As Ms. Trujillo said, ''There are so many stories outside the books.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
