<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prospect Yearns For Some Peace And Quiet</title>
    <meta content="17pope" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/sports/ncaabasketball/17pope.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855301"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEFDE123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1739" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prospect Yearns For Some Peace And Quiet</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Basketball Prospect Yearning for Peace and Quiet</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THAYER EVANS</byline>
      <dateline>ALIQUIPPA, Pa.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Herb Pope rises early each morning and dribbles a basketball to a nearby park. Along the way, he passes trash-filled yards and abandoned homes with boarded-up windows.</p>
        <p>Abandoned by his parents as a youngster, he had a tortuous journey in becoming one of the nation's top high school power forwards. He endured upheaval while living with relatives, friends and foster parents. He changed schools nearly every year. And he survived violence, including a shooting during a dispute in March.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Herb Pope is eager for a new beginning at New Mexico State University after a tortuous journey in becoming one of the nation’s top high school power forwards.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Herb Pope rises early each morning and dribbles a basketball to a nearby park. Along the way, he passes trash-filled yards and abandoned homes with boarded-up windows.</p>
        <p>Abandoned by his parents as a youngster, he had a tortuous journey in becoming one of the nation's top high school power forwards. He endured upheaval while living with relatives, friends and foster parents. He changed schools nearly every year. And he survived violence, including a shooting during a dispute in March.</p>
        <p>A graduate of Aliquippa High School, he is eager for a new beginning in college. Pope, 18, said he chose to attend New Mexico State over universities with more established basketball programs like Oklahoma, Maryland and Texas partly to make it difficult for people from Aliquippa to visit. [He was scheduled to leave Saturday for Las Cruces to start summer school.]</p>
        <p>''I'm trying to leave,'' said Pope, who once committed to nearby Pittsburgh. He carried a 3.0 grade point average in high school and averaged 19.7 points, 11 rebounds and 3.9 assists last season.</p>
        <p>On this June morning, barking dogs and chirping birds appeared to be the only other living things on Davis Street.</p>
        <p>''If you come out in the morning time, you don't see anything,'' Pope said.</p>
        <p>But later on Davis Street, a prostitute haggled over a payment, drug deals took place in broad daylight and crack addicts staggered aimlessly. It is also the hub of bloodshed in Plan 11, a section of this athlete-rich western Pennsylvania town of about 12,000 where shots are fired almost every day.</p>
        <p>Pope was unfazed by the empty beer bottles strewn about Jessie Belle Walker Park. The 6-foot-9, 217-pound Pope shot 3-pointers and occasionally dunked. His 30-minute workout was remarkable, considering that about two months earlier he was shot once in his left forearm, once in his thigh and twice in his abdomen. Pope said he was hospitalized for nearly two weeks and lost 37 pounds. He said two of the bullets remain in his body.</p>
        <p>On his way from the park to home, where he lives with an aunt and uncle, Amy Pope-Smith and Ronald Smith, a gunshot rang out in the distance before 8 a.m., a reminder that not everyone in Plan 11 was asleep.</p>
        <p>Pope endured a tumultuous childhood.</p>
        <p>''He comes from a dysfunctional family,'' said his father, Herbert Pope Sr., a recovering crack addict. ''He basically raised himself. It's amazing. He's got a hell of a story to tell.''</p>
        <p>Yet the outgoing Pope also had his share of missteps. Last summer, during an off-court altercation at a Florida tournament, he punched an assistant coach on his A.A.U. team.</p>
        <p>Pope said he acted in self-defense. New Mexico State Coach Reggie Theus confirmed that the A.A.U. coach had initiated the fight. Still, some colleges, most notably Louisville, backed off recruiting Pope.</p>
        <p>''He's an inner-city kid that is not going to take any stuff from anybody,'' Theus, a former N.B.A. star, said in a telephone interview. ''Unfortunately, a lot of times the inner-city kids, the first thing they think with a problem is knocking the guy out, which is not all bad, to a point.''</p>
        <p>In March, after his high school team squandered a 14-point lead in the final four minutes to lose in the state Class AA championship game, Pope dropped his runner-up medal on the ground and walked away, a decision he said he regrets.</p>
        <p>Scout.com rated Pope as the class of 2007's 34th-best player and 9th-best power forward. But based on his talent, he should have been a top-10 player, said Dave Telep, the Web site's national basketball recruiting analyst.</p>
        <p>He can score inside with his back to the basket as well as from the perimeter. A deft passer and steady dribbler, he likes to slash to the hoop and can single-handedly start and finish fast breaks.</p>
        <p>His ability was perhaps best exemplified by a 10-second stretch in a game last season: He had two blocks, a layup and a dunk, Aliquippa Coach Marvin Emerson said.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview, Telep said: ''He's a matchup problem. I'm not even sure what position Herb Pope really is because he can do so many different, unique things.''</p>
        <p>But Telep added: ''It's time for Herb to cast everything else aside, look basketball straight in the eye and ask himself how far he wants this game to take him. That's how good Herb Pope is.''</p>
        <p>Pope had to overcome great odds to play basketball. At 4, he developed a bone infection in his leg and doctors told his parents that he would never walk again, said his mother, Juanita Raines. Pope overcame the ailment, but his childhood was not carefree.</p>
        <p>His father, in prison for drug and theft offenses during much of Pope's youth, was released last summer. His mother has a long arrest record. She pleaded guilty to trespassing the day before Pope was shot and is facing charges of theft and writing bad checks, according to court documents.</p>
        <p>''They just abandoned me,'' Pope said of his parents. ''I don't got no grudge against them. Hopefully, they come around to doing right for themselves.''</p>
        <p>As a child, Pope said, he sometimes went hungry and often depended on meals at the homes of friends. He sought solace in daily outdoor pickup games, playing until it became too dark to see the basket.</p>
        <p>''Normal kids don't have to worry about their next meal, the police, the fighting at their house and all that crazy stuff,'' Pope said. ''It was hard.''</p>
        <p>In fourth grade, Pope, who was nearing 6 feet, was placed in foster care, where he remained through fifth grade. In seventh grade, he was expelled from school for fighting.</p>
        <p>Mike Shontz, whose son played basketball with Pope, served as Pope's guardian from eighth grade until he started his sophomore year in high school.</p>
        <p>''Herb's got a lot of issues, but his family is probably the biggest issue,'' Shontz said in a telephone interview. ''They never did anything for this kid. Nothing.''</p>
        <p>By Pope's count, he attended eight schools after third grade, including three high schools. At Shontz's urging, Pope spent his freshman year at the national basketball power Montrose Christian School in Maryland, where he lived with an assistant coach.</p>
        <p>Emerson, who coached Pope for three years at Aliquippa High, said they occasionally clashed when Pope was a sophomore but never had any physical confrontations.</p>
        <p>''He's a wonderful kid,'' Emerson said. ''He's a wonderful person. The kid is a joy to be around. He's very intelligent, very articulate. He listens and is very coachable.''</p>
        <p>He added that ''a couple of things happened in his life'' that weren't his fault. ''He was a child,'' he said. ''Just because he was 6-9 doesn't make him a grown man.''</p>
        <p>Pope and his reputation were hurt when he was shot at a party in Aliquippa about 2:45 a.m. on March 31, hours before he was scheduled to leave for the Roundball Classic in Chicago, an all-star game for the nation's top high school players.</p>
        <p>According to the police, Pope and a friend refused to give Tremayne Foster, 21, of Aliquippa a ride home from the party. Foster then punched Pope, who was in the front passenger seat of a sport utility vehicle.</p>
        <p>When Pope got out of the vehicle and tried to defend himself, he was shot four times by 19-year-old Marcus Longmire of Pittsburgh, according to the police. After two bullets hit him, Pope said, he blocked his face with his arms. That probably saved his life because his left forearm took a bullet intended for his head.</p>
        <p>The fourth bullet hit Pope as he fled into nearby woods. He then crawled down a 20-foot embankment and hitched a ride to a local hospital, where he told the police that Longmire had shot him.</p>
        <p>''It was hard to tell because when you grow up in this environment, you always grow up with the mentality of, 'Snitches get stitches,' '' Pope said. ''But at the time when it happened you're thinking you're going to die. I wouldn't have told if I knew I wasn't going to die, and then it'd get dealt with however it'd get dealt with.''</p>
        <p>Longmire was charged with attempted homicide, two counts of aggravated assault, two counts of simple assault and a firearms violation, a Beaver County Jail official said, and is being held on a $500,000 bond.</p>
        <p>Detective Sgt. Don Couch, who investigated the shooting, said Pope's basketball ability made him a target in Aliquippa.</p>
        <p>''Herb is singled out because of jealousy,'' Couch said in a telephone interview. ''Herb is singled out because Herb has a chance.''</p>
        <p>The Aliquippa police have responded to one other call involving Pope during his high school years, Couch said. Pope was ticketed for harassment after he and an uncle fought over clothing, Couch said.</p>
        <p>''Herb is no gun toter, no drug-slinging dealer or nothing like that,'' Couch said. ''He's a happy-go-lucky guy.''</p>
        <p>Pope said that his temper had mellowed and that he was reborn the day of the shooting. He said he dreams of earning a college degree, owning a real estate company and becoming a sports agent, not just playing in the N.B.A., as he once did.</p>
        <p>''That was a chapter that closed in my life that put everything and all my animosity and all my childhood worries behind me,'' Pope said of the shooting. ''This is my second chance.''</p>
        <p>He said he planned to talk with a therapist at college. Although Pope has recovered physically, he is concerned that he may not be the same basketball player when he steps on the court next season.</p>
        <p>''That's probably my biggest fear,'' he said.</p>
        <p>With improved ball-handling and defense, Theus said, Pope could blossom into a player similar to Scottie Pippen, a former N.B.A. All-Star. He said he was unconcerned about Pope's past.</p>
        <p>''I know he's a good kid and things happen,'' said Theus, who visited him Pope in the hospital. ''People have perceptions that are not reality.''</p>
        <p>Pope spent much of his last days in Aliquippa sitting on his porch on Spaulding Street, trying to avoid trouble.</p>
        <p>As he sat, the ground shook as music blared from cars whose drivers often stopped to ask about his health and pending departure for New Mexico State.</p>
        <p>''Hopefully I make it there,'' Pope said. ''I hope nothing happens from now until whenever I'm supposed to leave to go down there. It worries and bothers me.''</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
