<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Manhattan House Divided</title>
    <meta content="17Deal1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/realestate/17Deal1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BIG DEAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/The Big Deal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1DF153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1235" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Manhattan House Divided</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Manhattan House Divided</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSH BARBANEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BREAKING up is hard to do, particularly for the developers of one of the most ambitious and expensive condominium conversions ever: the redevelopment of the Manhattan House, a complex with 582 apartments on a full square block on East 66th Street and Third Avenue.</p>
        <p>The state attorney general approved sales at the $1.1 billion conversion this spring. But sales have been stalled while the project's general manager, N. Richard Kalikow, a real estate investor and developer, has been feuding in court and out with his partner, Jeremiah W. O'Connor Jr., the managing partner of O'Connor Capital Partners, a private equity firm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Breaking up is hard to do, particularly for the developers of one of the most ambitious condominium conversions ever: the redevelopment of the Manhattan House.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BREAKING up is hard to do, particularly for the developers of one of the most ambitious and expensive condominium conversions ever: the redevelopment of the Manhattan House, a complex with 582 apartments on a full square block on East 66th Street and Third Avenue.</p>
        <p>The state attorney general approved sales at the $1.1 billion conversion this spring. But sales have been stalled while the project's general manager, N. Richard Kalikow, a real estate investor and developer, has been feuding in court and out with his partner, Jeremiah W. O'Connor Jr., the managing partner of O'Connor Capital Partners, a private equity firm.</p>
        <p>Last week, a State Supreme Court judge ordered that one partner buy the other out, under the terms of their agreement. But lawyers for Mr. Kalikow immediately filed a notice of appeal, and in the meantime are attempting to block the judge's order.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Connor asked the court to order the buyout, while, according to associates, Mr. Kalikow was trying to put together investors to help him take over the huge project and refinance it.</p>
        <p>The project has long faced legal challenges from angry tenants who have been living in the building during a year of messy renovations. But the court papers show that the project has also been troubled by cost overruns, along with disputes over the marketing campaign, access to the project records and even its Web site design.</p>
        <p>The project is being marketed by Prudential Douglas Elliman, but with the sponsors in disarray, there have been no reports of contracts signed at Manhattan House. While most developers prefer to build with other people's money, the papers show that for many months the construction has been paid for by regular ''capital calls,'' in which the partners provide cash to meet construction costs. The project's lender refused to provide construction loans after the partners were unable to work out an agreement to provide a $30 million letter of credit to deal with the cost overruns, court papers say.</p>
        <p>Yet with the huge demand for luxury apartments in Manhattan and with prices on the rise, it is not clear whether the dispute reflects financial distress or a struggle by one side or the other to capture a greater share of the rising potential profits.</p>
        <p>In the court papers, Mr. O'Connor's lawyer, Max R. Shulman, argued that Mr. Kalikow and his team had mismanaged the project, and with the partners unable to agree, Mr. O'Connor had the right to demand that Mr. Kalikow either buy him out or agree to be bought out. ''It cannot be known how many sales and how much revenue have been and will continue to be lost as a result,'' he said in court papers of the management.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kalikow's lawyer, Mitchell A. Karlan, said the objections were a ruse, raised in bad faith to force Mr. Kalikow out of the deal and capture all the profits just as sales were beginning.</p>
        <p>He said the issues raised in court were many months old and were brought up just before the final approved offering plan, known as the ''black book,'' was distributed to tenants in the building, triggering the beginning of sales. Once sales began, Mr. Kalikow's share of the returns would eventually rise to as much as 40 percent from about 20 percent, he said.</p>
        <p>The court decision would give Mr. Kalikow the first right to buy out his partner, and if he refused, Mr. O'Connor could buy him out. But because Mr. O'Connor and his investors put far more cash into the project than Mr. Kalikow did -- $119 million versus $31 million, according to court papers -- Mr. Kalikow would have to raise more money for the buyout.</p>
        <p>Under the ruling last Tuesday by Justice Bernard J. Fried of State Supreme Court in Manhattan, Mr. O'Connor was required to post a $30 million bond to cover any potential damages that might eventually be owed to Mr. Kalikow under future court rulings. Once the payment is made, Mr. Kalikow will be given 30 days to decide whether to buy out Mr. O'Connor or give up his own interest in Manhattan House. At the hearing, Mr. O'Connor's lawyers said they would post the $30 million in a few days, but that was before a notice of appeal was filed.</p>
        <p>Special Houses In Search of Buyers</p>
        <p>ALTHOUGH only three town houses have sold for more than $30 million in all of Manhattan, and only a dozen or so for more than $20 million, the seemingly endless appetite of the wealthiest New Yorkers for ever more luxurious homes has given new hope to town house owners.</p>
        <p>Take, for example, a stretch of Riverside Drive near West 107th Street, where three unusual town houses in various shapes, sizes and historical detail are now on the market with asking prices of $10 million, $15 million or $30 million. Take your pick.</p>
        <p>It is an area once so run-down that many town houses came to be occupied by institutions or single-room-occupancy hotels -- just a few blocks from what many brokers considered the limits of where middle-class Manhattanites would buy. Even today, a buyer might have to walk more than a mile to find a comparable sale at current asking prices.</p>
        <p>Yet the owners of these properties and their brokers say that the surging market is coming to them and that they will sell if only they can find a buyer to fall in love with these special houses.</p>
        <p>''There was a time when these mansions were the most sought-after homes in the city,'' said Hans Smit, a professor at Columbia Law School and an expert in international arbitration, who first saw what is known as the Schinasi Mansion while riding his bicycle through the area in the late 1970s. He bought it for $325,000.</p>
        <p>The mansion, at 351 Riverside Drive at West 107th Street, is perhaps the only free-standing privately owned mansion in Manhattan, according to Mr. Smit's brokers, Diane Abrams and Felise Gross of Brown Harris Stevens. It is 41 feet wide, on a lot that is 59 feet wide, with a French Renaissance facade made up of white marble, and intricate interior details restored on two floors. The asking price is $30 million, and Mr. Smit said he was willing to wait for his price.</p>
        <p>Next door, at 352 Riverside Drive, is a house owned by James B. Rogers Jr., a founder with George Soros of the Quantum Fund. Mr. Rogers bought the house for $107,300 in 1977 and is now asking $15 million for it. The house is 26 feet wide on a lot 41 feet wide, and is rich in restored and original detail, according to a listing by Clare Brown, an agent at Leslie J. Garfield &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Then, just below West 106th Street, Graciela Chichilnisky, a math professor at Columbia, is asking around $10 million for her 20-foot-wide house. It is now listed by Ms. Abrams and Ms. Gross, though it has been through a series of brokers and price changes.</p>
        <p>Dexter Guerrieri, the president of Vandenberg Real Estate, which specializes in town houses, said that while prices had been rising rapidly, brokers and sellers sometimes fell in love with their own listing prices. ''The water finds its own level in the end,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smit is more upbeat. ''If one of these houses gets its price,'' he said, ''the others will quickly sell too.''</p>
        <p>BIG DEAL E-mail: bigdeal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: bigdeal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
