<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lessons in Giving, and Getting, More</title>
    <meta content="17RparentingNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855051"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PARENTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Our Lady of Loretto Church (Hempstead, NY)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Island Harvest (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winerip, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Muscarella, Ignatius</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E6D6143FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1158" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lessons in Giving, and Getting, More</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINERIP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Winerip, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>MINEOLA, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Winerip Parenting column on lessons lawyer Ignatius Muscarella is trying to instill in his children as they volunteer at Island Harvest, largest hunger relief organization on Long Island, and thanks expressed by Tracy, single mother of two who relies on gifts of food and other items from Our Lady of Loretto in Hempstead, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S not a lot. ''It doesn't take much time,'' says Ignatius Muscarella. It's not hard to do. Still, every Tuesday for many years now, Mr. Muscarella has given up his lunch hour to deliver surplus food to a soup kitchen.</p>
        <p>He is a 50-year-old lawyer who clerks for a State Supreme Court judge. Dressed in his work clothes -- starched white shirt, tie, suspenders, dark suit -- he rushes out of the courthouse here at 12:45, hops into his Hyundai Sonata, then drives to the back entrance of nearby Winthrop Hospital. He pulls a large cooler out of his trunk and hurries into the hospital kitchen, where Annette Cambria, the sous-chef, leads him into a walk-in freezer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S not a lot. ''It doesn't take much time,'' says Ignatius Muscarella. It's not hard to do. Still, every Tuesday for many years now, Mr. Muscarella has given up his lunch hour to deliver surplus food to a soup kitchen.</p>
        <p>He is a 50-year-old lawyer who clerks for a State Supreme Court judge. Dressed in his work clothes -- starched white shirt, tie, suspenders, dark suit -- he rushes out of the courthouse here at 12:45, hops into his Hyundai Sonata, then drives to the back entrance of nearby Winthrop Hospital. He pulls a large cooler out of his trunk and hurries into the hospital kitchen, where Annette Cambria, the sous-chef, leads him into a walk-in freezer.</p>
        <p>''I got seafood Newburg, chicken piccata  um  more piccata  and  um  '' she says.</p>
        <p>''Vegetarian lasagna?'' Mr. Muscarella asks.</p>
        <p>''No,'' says Ms. Cambria. ''Chicken something.'' Try as she may, Ms. Cambria can never predict exactly how much food the hospital's patients, visitors and staff will eat. ''It's not a science,'' she says, ''The patient census goes up and down, the weather  I'm not the weatherman.''</p>
        <p>This day, she has saved 17 frozen baking tins of food for him. Mr. Muscarella loads the now-full cooler back into his trunk and drives south a few miles to Hempstead, delivering the tins to a free lunch program at Jackson Memorial A.M.E. Zion Church. By 1:45, he's back at his desk, eating a turkey sandwich. ''We just delivered over 100 pounds,'' he says. ''How many people did we just feed.''</p>
        <p>For 15 years Mr. Muscarella has volunteered for Island Harvest, the largest hunger relief organization on Long Island, a nonprofit that moves seven million pounds of surplus food a year from places like supermarkets and restaurants to soup kitchens, homeless shelters and food pantries. He does it because ''you have to,'' he says. ''That we can ease suffering -- we have to appreciate what we have and give back.''</p>
        <p>The other big reason he does it is so he can make his kids do it. ''You're trying to set their moral compass,'' he says. ''You can tell them about stuff or, if you want the experience to last, you do it together.'' And so, several times a year, he and his wife, Anne, a ballet teacher, round up the usual suspects -- C.J., 17, Leigh Anne, 14, and Charlie, 12 -- and march them out to load Christmas turkeys into trucks or stack cans in the Island Harvest warehouse or stand in front of a supermarket handing out food-drive fliers.</p>
        <p>His children assume he does this because he's pro-torture.</p>
        <p>''Usually it's a Saturday,'' says his daughter C.J. ''It's the one day we can --''</p>
        <p>''Sleep,'' says Leigh Anne.</p>
        <p>They see their dad's mania for food drives as a major facet of his greatest character flaw: frugality.</p>
        <p>''Dad doesn't believe in waste,'' Charlie says. ''One piece of lettuce left and he'll go psycho.''</p>
        <p>''Dad does coupons,'' C.J. says.</p>
        <p>''He saves every plastic utensil,'' says Leigh Anne. ''You can't throw away a plastic fork in this house.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Muscarella predicted this is what his kids would say, and he remained unfazed: ''Are there grumblings? Yes. The key is to get them to commit to do something far enough in advance so it's not real yet. And then, when it comes, you say, 'You can't go to the movies, you promised.' ''</p>
        <p>Through the family's church, First Presbyterian of Baldwin, Leigh Anne and her dad worked overnight at a homeless shelter in Manhattan. ''I didn't want to go, and then it ends up not bad,'' she says. ''Everyone's like, 'Don't talk to the homeless, don't look at them.' My pastor's like, 'If you just give them a smile, it will make their day better.' ''</p>
        <p>C.J. has been doing food drives with her dad for so long, she can't remember when she started. ''It just seems like I've always done it,'' she says. These days, she often drags her boyfriend, John, along. ''It's not like he says, 'Yes, I want to go.' It's like, 'O.K.' '' They've been on dates to fetch surplus food from King Kullen and Costco.</p>
        <p>As to whether she would rather be doing something else, she says, ''Oh, yeah.''</p>
        <p>Next year, C.J. starts college at Towson University in Maryland, several states away. Her dad won't be able to force her into any more food drives.</p>
        <p>''I'll probably do something like this in college,'' she says. ''If I don't, he'll track me down by phone.''</p>
        <p>TRACY, 35, doesn't know how she and her two boys, ages 6 and 12, would live without the food pantry at Our Lady of Loretto in Hempstead. She lives nearby and has been coming every week since her older son was born. She is a single mother who walks with a cane, and says the three of them live on her $600 disability check and $59 in food stamps a month.</p>
        <p>''I got five herniated disks from my car accident,'' she says. She did not want her full name or her sons' names used. ''I wouldn't want people to know how needy I am,'' she says.</p>
        <p>Though she's never heard of it, Island Harvest supplies a significant portion of the groceries to this food pantry. There's a chance that the two big bags of nonperishables she takes home every week -- half her family's food, she says -- passed through the Muscarella family's hands at some point.</p>
        <p>Last week, her younger son had scarlet fever and strep throat. ''He was burning up with 104 and diarrhea,'' she says. A friend drove her to a hospital emergency room, and the next day she came into the pantry: ''I brought my hospital papers to show them. It said drink lots of fluids. I got grapefruit juice, I got lemon water. I got -- what's that athlete drink?'' Gatorade.</p>
        <p>The pantry also stocks used clothes and housewares. All the clothes Tracy had on for her interview, including her new size-81/2 sneakers, came from Our Lady of Loretto. ''Last visit, I got sandals for both boys, books, three shirts, dinner plates.''</p>
        <p>Summer is coming, and it's the hardest time for her family. During the school year, her boys get free breakfast and lunch at school, but in summer, when they're home, she says, it's tough to make the food last.</p>
        <p>This is her hope for her sons: ''To see how hard it is for their mother and to have a better chance to go out there and get more.''</p>
        <p>Some weeks, she says, she doesn't have the money for the Laundromat. ''So I come here, get a new outfit for my child. They got pretty much of everything. Christmas, you don't worry. Every child can get a toy and an outfit. They give you a turkey, canned goods, everything.</p>
        <p>''Here they make you feel more than welcome,'' she says. '''Everyone's got a smile: 'Good morning. How you doing? How's your child doing?' ''</p>
        <p>PARENTING E-mail: parenting@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: parenting@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
