<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Best Seat Above the House</title>
    <meta content="x17cheer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/sports/baseball/x17cheer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855247"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CHEERING SECTION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Traffic Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Traffic Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E6DF123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Best Seat Above the House</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Best Seat Above the House</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VINCENT M. MALLOZZI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jim Maloney Jr. gave me a lift to Yankee Stadium on Thursday so that I could enjoy a seat he has been using for the past 25 years.</p>
        <p>Maloney picked me up at Republic Airport on Long Island and we set out for the Bronx.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jim Maloney Jr. is the chief pilot for Goodyear blimps and still gets a high hovering over major sports scenes like the World Series and the Super Bowl.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jim Maloney Jr. gave me a lift to Yankee Stadium on Thursday so that I could enjoy a seat he has been using for the past 25 years.</p>
        <p>Maloney picked me up at Republic Airport on Long Island and we set out for the Bronx.</p>
        <p>''We should be there in about 40 minutes,'' Maloney, 64, said as he pressed pedals to metal on a cloudy day. ''You can't beat the view.''</p>
        <p>On our way to the land of pinstripes, we passed Shea Stadium in Flushing, Queens, while traveling about 30 miles an hour. I was clutching my car seat as Maloney opened his window to glance at the ballpark, and his wavy white hair began flapping in a cool breeze.</p>
        <p>''I was at Game 6 of the 1986 World Series here,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That night, Mookie Wilson's 10th-inning ground ball squirted between the legs of Boston's Bill Buckner to give the Mets a stunning comeback victory over the Red Sox.</p>
        <p>''I nearly jumped out of my seat,'' Maloney said.</p>
        <p>If he had, he would have needed a parachute.</p>
        <p>Maloney is the chief pilot for Goodyear blimps. Although he has a dual doctorate in electrical engineering and computer science from Southern California, he is a chip off the old airship. Maloney's father, Jim Sr., was a Goodyear blimp pilot from 1936 until he retired in 1976.</p>
        <p>After all the nautical miles, Maloney still gets a high hovering over major sports scenes like the World Series and the Super Bowl, as well as tennis, auto, golf, yachting and horse racing events. He lists New York, Los Angeles, San Francisco, Cleveland, St. Louis and Atlanta as cities where he most enjoys taking in the sights.</p>
        <p>''I've flown over ballparks and stadiums in just about every state east of the Rockies, and each time, I still get a thrill doing it,'' said Maloney, who usually takes television crews up, up and away in his seven-seat balloon to capture picture-perfect aerial views. ''As a sports fan, I consider myself pretty lucky to have a job like this.''</p>
        <p>Before I knew it, Maloney and I were holding steady about 1,500 feet above La Guardia Airport. An air traffic controller speaking into our headsets reminded us that we could not fly over Yankee Stadium while a game was being played. It was about 3:30 p.m., and the Yankees and the Arizona Diamondbacks were still on the field.</p>
        <p>''We have a little time to kill,'' said Maloney, his feet working the two rudder pedals that turn the blimp while his right hand turned the elevator wheel that allows it to go up and down. ''Let's head over to Manhattan.''</p>
        <p>He pointed the nose of the blimp south and began sailing above the Hudson. We flew over the Upper West Side and Central Park. Amid a dizzying array of skyscrapers, we buzzed past the big W perched atop the W hotel, then the big M perched atop the Milford Plaza, and I wondered for a second if we weren't flying upside down.</p>
        <p>We gazed around Times Square and observed the people on the observation deck of the Empire State Building. The blimp began to bob and weave a bit above Madison Square Garden, where Ali once fought Frazier.</p>
        <p>We grew silent over ground zero, then we spun slowly around the Statue of Liberty before heading uptown toward Yankee Stadium, its lights glowing beyond the deep green expanse of Central Park. The sun began to break through the clouds.</p>
        <p>Air traffic controllers at La Guardia cleared us to fly over the Stadium. Maloney, a Yankees fan, has seen the team win numerous playoff and World Series games in the past decade, all while flying higher than the highlights.</p>
        <p>We circled Yankee Stadium twice, marveling at tarps with the interlocking NY logo that adorned the pitcher's mound and the first-base on-deck circle, the American flag fluttering in the sky below us, and the new Yankee stadium under construction next door.</p>
        <p>Larry Chambers, one of 12 pilots on the Goodyear blimp roster, called Maloney ''the M.V.P. of our team.''</p>
        <p>''As a pilot, Jim is in a class all his own,'' said Chambers, 61, who lives in Pompano Beach, Fla., where one of the three Goodyear blimps is based. ''His piloting skills are next to perfect. And he has one of the most brilliant minds I know.''</p>
        <p>The other blimps fly out of Los Angeles and Akron, Ohio, Maloney's base. He and his wife live in North Canton, Ohio.</p>
        <p>From 1,000 feet up, it was easy to see why Maloney cherishes his seat. No long ticket lines or traffic jams, no obstructed views, no other fans to contend with. Just a seat in the sky with a view of a baseball diamond glistening in the summer sun.</p>
        <p>''Believe it or not, I'm not a sailboat kind of guy,'' Maloney said. ''I drive a Corvette. In fact, I like everything about life fast, except when I'm up here in the blimp, and especially when I'm enjoying a game.''</p>
        <p>CHEERING SECTION E-mail: cheers@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: cheers@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
