<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Roommates Who Almost Weren't</title>
    <meta content="17hunt" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/realestate/17hunt.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855076"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE HUNT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Brooklyn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/The Hunt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E0DF153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1082" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Roommates Who Almost Weren't</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Roommates Who Almost Weren’t</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE COHEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS soon as Chris Roan and Justin Fluck become colleagues -- as advertising salesmen at the satirical newspaper The Onion -- they became friends. Later, they became roommates. The first was effortless. The second, not so much.</p>
        <p>Of the two Midwesterners, Mr. Roan was the first to arrive in New York, in the fall of 2004, a few months after graduating from Carleton College near his native Minneapolis. He initially took a job as an executive recruiter, then began working at The Onion's New York office in the summer of 2006.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two roommates searched Williamsburg and Greenpoint for the perfect balance of bars, restaurants and culture.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS soon as Chris Roan and Justin Fluck become colleagues -- as advertising salesmen at the satirical newspaper The Onion -- they became friends. Later, they became roommates. The first was effortless. The second, not so much.</p>
        <p>Of the two Midwesterners, Mr. Roan was the first to arrive in New York, in the fall of 2004, a few months after graduating from Carleton College near his native Minneapolis. He initially took a job as an executive recruiter, then began working at The Onion's New York office in the summer of 2006.</p>
        <p>He rented a room in Bushwick, Brooklyn, for $650, ''my best option at the time,'' he said. ''It was social death; once I was home, there was no chance I was going out.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fluck (pronounced Fluke), a graduate of the University of Illinois at Chicago, had been working in The Onion's Chicago office for several years. He was transferred to New York a year ago. In a day, he rented a 300-square-foot studio on St. Marks Place for $1,440.</p>
        <p>The rent ''was killing me,'' Mr. Fluck said. So was the trek to the fifth floor. He planned his schedule around Luther, his dog, who was walked three times a day.</p>
        <p>In the spring, they decided to hunt for a two-bedroom rental together for $1,500 a month. Or was that $2,000? It depended on which one you asked.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fluck, 26, drew up a list of criteria, including a neighborhood rife with the right kind of bars, restaurants and culture. His list was ''so vague I wasn't sure exactly what it meant,'' Mr. Roan said.</p>
        <p>Along with lower rent, Mr. Fluck's list included proximity to subways, dog runs and lots of that bar/restaurant/culture stuff. He was willing to give up the East Village, in his opinion the coolest place ever, for Williamsburg, Brooklyn, the second coolest.</p>
        <p>''I was resistant to moving to Williamsburg because it was overly trite for someone in my demographic,'' said Mr. Roan, 26. ''Justin was concerned about proximity to nightlife and excitement and all those things I feel too old for.''</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Roan was willing to pay a few hundred dollars more for a less distant neighborhood, his concern was price. He was cautious because he works partly on commission.</p>
        <p>The two saw several places in East Williamsburg, where one real estate agent touted apartments for their ''punk rock appeal.'' It seemed like a gimmick to cover up for dumpy places.</p>
        <p>Another agent seemed desperate to rent a place on a seamy block. They were shown unacceptable places with ugly carpets, weird smells or adjacent bedrooms.</p>
        <p>''We did a really good job deciding against places,'' Mr. Fluck said. ''There were always solid reasons that made it easy to say no.''</p>
        <p>They differed on a spacious sixth-floor walk-up for $1,900. Mr. Fluck refused, despite the incomparable location on Havemeyer Street near Black Betty and Luna Lounge, two popular bars.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roan offered to walk Luther every day in exchange for a break on the rent. ''There was a lot of that -- I will make accommodations for your lifestyle if you ease up on the price for me,'' he said. ''Justin was being kind of a princess about it.''</p>
        <p>Their differences bubbled up. ''He wasn't going to find anything in my price per square foot, and I wasn't going to find anything in his bars per square foot,'' Mr. Roan said.</p>
        <p>Proximity to those bars was important for work, Mr. Fluck argued. Bars advertise in The Onion, so he felt it only fair to patronize them. Besides, ''it is fun being at bars -- you meet girls,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roan half agreed. ''I do think bars are great places to meet girls,'' he said. ''I don't find living near them makes it easier or harder to conduct business with them.''</p>
        <p>Then there was that problematical list. ''Justin kept saying no,'' Mr. Roan said. ''It's not that his reasons were unfounded, but they were not things I cared about. I thought he would be more flexible than he turned out.''</p>
        <p>The two hit bottom one horrendous evening when an agent showed them an unfinished apartment unavailable for several weeks. It began to rain as they slogged from South Williamsburg to North Greenpoint to see yet another unfinished place, this one far from the train.</p>
        <p>They were defeated, exhausted and wet. They had one week before they had to move. Mr. Fluck's lease was expiring, and Mr. Roan's room was already rented to someone else.</p>
        <p>They discussed hunting separately. Mr. Roan worried about betraying his friend. But ultimately, Mr. Fluck remained chipper. ''I knew we were eventually going to find something,'' he said. ''We could always settle.''</p>
        <p>Then came a big, bright place for $1,750 on a semicommercial block of Maujer Street. ''I thought it was killer, totally great,'' Mr. Roan said. It was near a taco place and a bar. So he was stunned when Mr. Fluck said no. The bar wasn't cool.</p>
        <p>''I was, like, give me three good bars and three good restaurants -- give me some go-to places I can go to -- and I will be fine,'' Mr. Fluck said. ''I don't want to walk a mile to go to a good bar. I want a neighborhood where I can feel content staying there for the weekend.''</p>
        <p>The real estate agent, Roman Popescu of the N. C. Pepe Corporation, wasn't surprised. ''That is usually how it goes with roommates,'' he said. ''One likes the place and the other picks it apart.''</p>
        <p>So Mr. Roan figured his friend would also find something wrong with the next place that Mr. Popescu showed them -- a five-room railroad-style flat for $1,800 on Withers Street.</p>
        <p>This time, Mr. Fluck said yes -- to the welcoming front stoop, the big kitchen, the far-apart bedrooms, the three nearby dog runs and the right kind of neighborhood, which he rated 70 percent Old World and 30 percent hipster.</p>
        <p>''It's so old school that the video rental place doesn't have a drop-off slot,'' he said. (Drop-off locations include the deli or hairdresser down the street.) But there were also three bars, three pizza places and even a White Castle-Church's Chicken combo.</p>
        <p>The two split Mr. Popescu's fee of nearly $2,600. Mr. Fluck pays $925 for the bigger room with the bigger closet, while Mr. Roan pays $875.</p>
        <p>Both are happy with their new home. ''Justin was very picky and needy,'' Mr. Roan said, ''but now that we are settled in, he requires no maintenance at all.''</p>
        <p>THE HUNT E-mail: thehunt@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: thehunt@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
