<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A High-Tech Center Moves Into Baltimore, and Residents May Be Driven Out</title>
    <meta content="17baltimore" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/us/17baltimore.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070626T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855242"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biotechnology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baltimore (Md)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Johns Hopkins Hospital (Baltimore)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">East Baltimore Development Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simmons, Melody</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland/Baltimore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biotechnology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biotechnology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Baltimore (Md)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EFD6153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="728" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A High-Tech Center Moves Into Baltimore, and Residents May Be Driven Out</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A High-Tech Center Moves Into Baltimore, and Residents May Be Driven Out</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELODY SIMMONS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Simmons, Melody</byline>
      <dateline>BALTIMORE, June 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>About 400 families in East Baltimore are awaiting relocation as workers clear part of 100-acre site for $1.4 billion project that will convert once-blighted neighborhood into biotechnology center linked to Johns Hopkins Hospital; project will also include 2,200 new and renovated housing units and generate 6,000 jobs and millions of dollars in tax revenue for city and state; East Baltimore Development Inc, nonprofit organization, is in charge of project; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For nearly three decades, Charlotte Johnson witnessed the drug dealing and violence on the streets in front of her modest row house in East Baltimore. She rode it out only to face a new challenge today -- the community's transformation under the largest planned urban renewal in the country, which could soon drive her out of the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>''It's like taking a piece of my heart out,'' said Ms. Johnson, 54. ''All I'm asking for is just to give me a house in the place for the house you are taking.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>City officials believe a new biotechnology research center could play a major role in turning around a once-blighted neighborhood and attracting additional development.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For nearly three decades, Charlotte Johnson witnessed the drug dealing and violence on the streets in front of her modest row house in East Baltimore. She rode it out only to face a new challenge today -- the community's transformation under the largest planned urban renewal in the country, which could soon drive her out of the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>''It's like taking a piece of my heart out,'' said Ms. Johnson, 54. ''All I'm asking for is just to give me a house in the place for the house you are taking.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Johnson is one of 400 families awaiting relocation as workers clear part of the 100-acre site for the $1.4 billion project. It will convert the once-blighted neighborhood into a biotechnology research center linked to the nearby Johns Hopkins Hospital. It will also include 2,200 new and renovated housing units and generate 6,000 jobs and millions of dollars in tax revenue for the city and state.</p>
        <p>City officials believe the project could play a major role in turning around the city and attracting additional development.</p>
        <p>''It's a new city within a city,'' said Anthony J. Ambridge, a former Baltimore city councilman turned private developer. ''It's a long-term project, and the dividends won't be paid for years.''</p>
        <p>But for residents of the neighborhood, the change is bittersweet.</p>
        <p>Ms. Johnson said the thick dust stirred up by the construction just across the street from her front steps had often made her ill. She also worries about giving up the house her parents bought in 1955 for $5,000. With some buyout packages already offered at an average of $153,000, Ms. Johnson, out of work and on disability, said she will not be able to afford a house in the new community, where prices are expected to start at $250,000.</p>
        <p>''It truly hurts because of the history behind this house,'' she said. ''My parents gave me this place to keep in the family.''</p>
        <p>For a year, bulldozers have been clearing blocks pockmarked by a 70 percent vacancy rate and carrying the nickname Badlands since the crack epidemic of the 1980s.</p>
        <p>This summer, the first new housing units will open -- an apartment complex for older residents, followed in the fall by apartments for firefighters, police officers, teachers and nurses.</p>
        <p>The project is a public-private partnership mixing $250 million in city, state and federal money with $1.2 billion in private investment, said Jack Shannon, executive director of East Baltimore Development Inc., the nonprofit organization in charge of the project. The Annie E. Casey Foundation, a nonprofit group based in Baltimore, has committed $55 million, $8.5 million of which will go toward relocating families. Johns Hopkins, which will lease a majority of space in the biotechnology park, has committed more than $30 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shannon said the project would spread out over 30 square blocks and hold up to two million square feet of office and research space. The goal of the new housing units, he added, is to create a mixed-income community.</p>
        <p>Longtime residents remain skeptical.</p>
        <p>Donald Gresham, once homeless and now the owner of a two-story row house, said his annual salary of about $10,000 would prevent him from returning to the community as a homeowner. Even though Mr. Shannon has promised to offer gap financing for qualified residents who want to return from a no-interest equity mortgage pool, Mr. Gresham, a community activist who heads the Save Middle East Action Committee, said he was not interested.</p>
        <p>''My hope for the future is that I would be able to have a home that is affordable,'' he said. ''I'm looking for security, to know that I have a secure life after this is over. And if I don't get that, I'm going to be really mad.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Shannon acknowledged the frustrations. Over the past year, workers from East Baltimore Development have helped relocate 396 families from the site, showing them homes and apartments available for purchase and rent in surrounding city neighborhoods. It remains unclear whether they will return to their former neighborhood once new housing opens up.</p>
        <p>''For better or worse, we're pushing the frontier here,'' said Mr. Shannon, a former member of the Camden, N.J., school board who later worked for Edward G. Rendell when he was mayor of Philadelphia. ''We're trying to build day in and day out, interaction by interaction, meeting by meeting, a level of trust.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 26, 2007, Tuesday  An article on June 17 about a redevelopment project in Baltimore that has displaced some longtime residents misstated the amount of space Johns Hopkins University will occupy in the project's research park. It has agreed to lease about a third of the space in the park's first building, not ''a majority of space'' in the park. The article also misstated the lowest price for new housing in the development. While the bulk of the housing will indeed start at $250,000, some one-bedroom units are expected to be available for about $200,000, although prices have not been set.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 26, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article on June 17 about a redevelopment project in Baltimore that has displaced some longtime residents misstated the amount of space Johns Hopkins University will occupy in the project's research park. It has agreed to lease about a third of the space in the park's first building, not ''a majority of space'' in the park. The article also misstated the lowest price for new housing in the development. While the bulk of the housing will indeed start at $250,000, some one-bedroom units are expected to be available for about $200,000, although prices have not been set.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
