<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Guru for Achieving And Enjoying the Good Life</title>
    <meta content="17peoplectCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/17peoplect.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855038"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SELF-HELP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stoddard, Alexandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boynton, Cynthia Wolfe</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">You Are Your Choices (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">HarperCollins Publishers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Stoddard, Alexandra</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E1D7143FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Guru for Achieving And Enjoying the Good Life</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Guru for Achieving and Enjoying the Good Life</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CYNTHIA WOLFE BOYNTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Boynton, Cynthia Wolfe</byline>
      <dateline>MADISON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Alexandra Stoddard, 65, who comments on her latest self-help book, You Are Your Choices: 50 Ways to Live the Good Life; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALEXANDRA STODDARD, a self-help author and interior designer, has a hard time warming up to people who don't admit to at least one messy closet.</p>
        <p>''Life is messy,'' said Ms. Stoddard, a Connecticut native and a longtime resident of Stonington who earlier this year published her 25th book, ''You Are Your Choices: 50 Ways to Live the Good Life'' (HarperCollins).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first part of Alexandra Stoddard’s career focused on beautifying rooms, but what she is really interested in now is beautifying lives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALEXANDRA STODDARD, a self-help author and interior designer, has a hard time warming up to people who don't admit to at least one messy closet.</p>
        <p>''Life is messy,'' said Ms. Stoddard, a Connecticut native and a longtime resident of Stonington who earlier this year published her 25th book, ''You Are Your Choices: 50 Ways to Live the Good Life'' (HarperCollins).</p>
        <p>''Worrying about perfection is no way to live,'' she said at a recent book signing. ''Life is confusing, chaotic and untidy, but also very wonderful if you know how to make it that way.''</p>
        <p>To Ms. Stoddard, this ''wonderfulness'' comes from learning how to say no, living in the moment and not worrying about being perfect, among other ''healthy choices.'' The result, she said, is the good life: A life where you laugh easily, smile often and feel happy -- ideally, every day.</p>
        <p>It's how she lives, she said, and what she hopes to help others do, too.</p>
        <p>Although the first part of her career focused on beautifying rooms, what she is really interested in now is beautifying lives.</p>
        <p>She has appeared on television with Oprah Winfrey, Barbara Walters and Katie Couric, but said it was her interaction with, and affect on, noncelebrities that mattered most. ''I'm such a believer in taking care of ourselves,'' she said. ''Happiness should be everyone's goal. What a privilege it is to help people transform and attain it, which I truly believe is possible.</p>
        <p>''Do I sound kooky and idealistic?'' she added, laughing. ''Well, that's because I am.''</p>
        <p>Dressed in a bright silk Oriental jacket as vibrant as she is, Ms. Stoddard, a 65-year-old grandmother of three who also has a Manhattan apartment, recently shared some of the suggestions she offers in her latest book to a crowd of more than 75 at R. J. Julia bookstore in Madison. Looking more like a ballerina at the barre than an author at a lectern, Ms. Stoddard seemed to captivate both the men and women in the audience. Her straight, shoulder-length brown-and-gray hair bounced wildly as she explained why she tries to skip instead of walk, jump rather than stand. ''You have to grasp the enthusiasm of life,'' she said, her face and hands as expressive as her words.</p>
        <p>Many leaned in and nodded as she spoke.</p>
        <p>With chapters in ''Choices'' like ''Have as few regrets as possible'' and ''Faster isn't better,'' her advice is more philosophical than practical, Ms. Stoddard explained. But that is because, when it comes to happiness, each person needs to find his or her own way. ''I don't believe in sharing recipes,'' Ms. Stoddard said, ''because the things that make one person happy may not work for another -- though, obviously, I do share the things that work for me.''</p>
        <p>Those things -- surrounding herself with flowers; working less and reading more; indulging in travel and treats -- have led to some criticism. Several customer reviews of her books posted to Amazon.com call her advice ''unrealistic'' and ''unattainable'' for anyone without a large bank account, or who struggles to make ends meet.</p>
        <p>Yet don't tell that to Jane Kahn, 46, a schoolteacher in Greenwich. Not only has she read ''at least 20'' of Ms. Stoddard's books, but she has taken time off from work to travel as far as Washington to see her speak. For Ms. Stoddard's talk at R. J. Julia, Ms. Kahn arrived more than two hours early to assure a front-row seat.</p>
        <p>''I guess you could call me a 'devotee,' '' said Ms. Kahn. ''Really, Alexandra has changed my life -- not just with her words, but with her energy. She's taught me not to save the special moments for special occasions. Instead, to see every day as special.''</p>
        <p>The owner of R. J. Julia, Roxanne Coady, said she believed that many people were hungry for the more enjoyable and meaningful life that Ms. Stoddard encouraged, but needed guidance on how to attain it.</p>
        <p>Mary Sullivan, 62, who lives in Connecticut and Florida, said she had been a fan of Ms. Stoddard's for four decades. The best advice she has taken from her is this: Choose well most of the time. ''That means you don't need to be perfect, but do the best you can,'' she said. ''That's down to earth, and something you can attain.''</p>
        <p>SELF-HELP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
