<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pure Gilbert and Sullivan? No. But Still a Glorious Thing.</title>
    <meta content="17theatnjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/17theatnj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855067"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Paper Mill Playhouse (Millburn, NJ)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siegel, Naomi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilbert, William S (Sir) (1836-1911)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sullivan, Arthur S (Sir) (1842-1900)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Pirates] (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Pirates of Penzance, the (Operetta)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Paper Mill Playhouse</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EFD6143FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="501" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pure Gilbert and Sullivan? No. But Still a Glorious Thing.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pure Gilbert and Sullivan? No. But Still a Glorious Thing.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NAOMI SIEGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siegel, Naomi</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Naomi Siegel reviews Pirates]--adaptation of Gilbert and Sullivan classic Pirates of Penzance at Paper Mill Playhouse in Millburn, NJ; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Unbuckle your swashbuckle, channel your inner Johnny Depp and prepare to have a blast at ''Pirates!'' -- a delightful new adaptation of Gilbert and Sullivan's classic ''Pirates of Penzance'' at the Paper Mill Playhouse in Millburn.</p>
        <p>Cornwall's rocky shore has given way to a sun-drenched Caribbean island setting, and a pirate curse (borrowed from ''Ruddigore'') has been added as dramatic spice. Co-produced by Connecticut's Goodspeed Opera House and the Paper Mill, this ''Pirates'' takes the beloved operetta to rollicking heights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Paper Mill Playhouse’s “Pirates of Penzance” takes the beloved operetta to rollicking heights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Unbuckle your swashbuckle, channel your inner Johnny Depp and prepare to have a blast at ''Pirates!'' -- a delightful new adaptation of Gilbert and Sullivan's classic ''Pirates of Penzance'' at the Paper Mill Playhouse in Millburn.</p>
        <p>Cornwall's rocky shore has given way to a sun-drenched Caribbean island setting, and a pirate curse (borrowed from ''Ruddigore'') has been added as dramatic spice. Co-produced by Connecticut's Goodspeed Opera House and the Paper Mill, this ''Pirates'' takes the beloved operetta to rollicking heights.</p>
        <p>The show is billed as ''a fully-staged theatrical concert with costumes, choreography and sword fighting,'' a format popularized by the ''Encores!'' series at City Center in New York. Gordon Greenberg, Nell Benjamin and John McDaniel are credited with conceiving this version, tweaking the score and book to inject the kind of energy and visual pizazz that takes into account the conventions of contemporary musical theater. Still, when the last pirate has swaggered his final swagger and the maidens have tittered their final titter, it's the wit and satire of the original Gilbert and Sullivan that lift the show into the realm of memorable entertainment.</p>
        <p>The cast of characters, all old friends, remain endearing in their new iteration. There's duty-bound Frederic, who, through the error of his bawdy, loving but less than competent nursemaid, Ruth, is apprenticed until his 21st birthday to a pirate instead of a pilot. His master, the outrageous Pirate King, combines dastardly derring-do with a soft spot for any orphan, real or feigned, who crosses his path.</p>
        <p>One such self-proclaimed orphan is Major-General Stanley, governor of the island and father to a bevy of six vacuous blond beauties and to their sister, Mabel, who is dark-haired and, therefore, predictably brainy yet socially awkward. Mabel's adventuresome spirit and feminist sensibility inspire her to act boldly in claiming Frederic's heart.</p>
        <p>From the opening strains of the overture to the big finish, ''Pirates!'' is well served by its musically gifted cast under Mr. Greenberg's spirited direction. Andrew Varela gives camp a good name with his deliciously over-the-top performance as the Pirate King; he flirts with the audience and struts his stuff in the best rock-star fashion. As Frederic, the charming Barrett Foa transforms a potentially insipid character into a winsome hero. Mabel, played wisely and radiantly by the vivacious Farah Alvin, lights up the stage at each entrance.</p>
        <p>Liz McCartney as Ruth invigorates the role of the good-hearted slattern with her audacious manner, and Gerry McIntyre brings down the house as the Sergeant sounding the call to battle in ''Tarantara!''</p>
        <p>But the true star turn is offered by Ed Dixon as Major-General Stanley. With extraordinary diction and sure-fire comic timing -- Shawn Gough's musical direction is outstanding -- Mr. Dixon gives a performance that rivals the Savoyards of old.</p>
        <p>Gilbert and Sullivan would no doubt be proud, ''for it is, it is a glorious thing'' to see this Pirate King.</p>
        <p>''Pirates!'' is at the Paper Mill Playhouse, Brookside Drive, Millburn, through July 8. Information: (973) 376-4343 or at papermill.org.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
