<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Downtown, an Amenities Rivalry</title>
    <meta content="17post" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/realestate/17post.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855082"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="POSTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07EEDF153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="643" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Downtown, an Amenities Rivalry</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Downtown, an Amenities Rivalry</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. HUGHES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH a thud, 75 Wall Street, a huge hotel-and-luxury-condominium building, has landed in the financial district -- another residential offering typical of the area, where it seems a weekend's-worth of amenities can be experienced in the course of an elevator ride.</p>
        <p>Developers and brokers say that because the district's streets lack many basic services, they must rely on lavish amenities rather than floor plans to seal deals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Because the financial district lacks many basic services, developers and brokers must rely on lavish amenities rather than floor plans to seal deals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH a thud, 75 Wall Street, a huge hotel-and-luxury-condominium building, has landed in the financial district -- another residential offering typical of the area, where it seems a weekend's-worth of amenities can be experienced in the course of an elevator ride.</p>
        <p>Developers and brokers say that because the district's streets lack many basic services, they must rely on lavish amenities rather than floor plans to seal deals.</p>
        <p>''What we often do in emerging markets is create a fuller lifestyle proposition,'' said James Lansill, a senior managing director at the Corcoran Sunshine Marketing Group who focuses on downtown.</p>
        <p>A conversion of a brick former office tower at Pearl Street, 75 Wall is the most recent of a group of amenity-laden projects planned for the area. It is to have 250 hotel rooms, part of Hyatt's new Andaz brand, and atop them 349 condos.</p>
        <p>Its units range from 500-square-foot studios to 4,000-square-foot four-bedrooms and are priced from $490,000 to $8 million. In two weeks, 20 percent of them have sold, according to Ben Hakimian, a principal of the Hakimian Organization, the developer.</p>
        <p>It is the extras that have made the real difference, he said. Housekeepers from the hotel can make residents' beds and press their shirts, while on the 43rd-floor roof deck, residents can soak in outdoor tubs, cook dinner on gas grills and bury their toes in a sandy ersatz beach.</p>
        <p>''Within the complex, you can have any kind of lifestyle you want,'' Mr. Hakimian said.</p>
        <p>Among the half a dozen other new condo projects in the area is the William Beaver House, which has 330 units of new construction, at the corner of William and Beaver Streets. On amenities, said its developer, André Balazs, ''we can match them or beat them all.'' Nine of the building's 47 stories have gone up.</p>
        <p>Already, Mr. Balazs had promised handball and squash courts, valet parking, and a 44-bed -- yes, bed -- cinema that can transform into a disco. Then, last week, he announced a 160-seat restaurant from Giorgio DeLuca, a founder of Dean &amp; DeLuca, which will serve meals round-the-clock to residents and walk-ins alike.</p>
        <p>So far, William Beaver has sold 34 percent of its units, Mr. Balazs said. It has everything from studios to three-bedrooms, priced from $900,000 to $2.6 million.</p>
        <p>In late April, the Setai, a 167-unit conversion at 40 Broad Street, unveiled its sales office, which has a long mahogany bar, terra cotta floors, and glass wine-display-cases as part of a residents-only club that will encompass two floors and 30,000 square feet.</p>
        <p>A restaurant opening in the Setai this fall will allow some walk-in clientele -- though only for a limited time, to generate sales interest, said Jonathan J. Breene, a founding partner of the Setai Group.</p>
        <p>''When somebody raises the bar down here,'' Mr. Breene said, ''everybody else has to meet it.'' So far, he said, 35 percent of the units in the Setai have sold. Prices range from $700,000 for a studio to $6.75 million for a three-bedroom.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the most attractive amenity at 25 Broad Street, which will have 346 condos in a palazzo-style, 21-story building, is the architecture itself, said Kent M. Swig, the president of Swig Equities, the developer. Even the fire stairs are to be made of marble, he said.</p>
        <p>But he isn't relying solely on stone alone. The 10,000-square-foot ground-floor common area is to include a bamboo garden, a children's play space, and a business center with fax and package services.</p>
        <p>''Amenities are critical,'' Mr. Swig said. Units in his building range from one- to three-bedrooms, priced from $865,000 to $2.6 million; 10 percent have sold since March, he said.</p>
        <p>With all the rival construction, competition for buyers has intensified this spring. But Mr. Swig welcomes it.</p>
        <p>''The more buildings there are down here, the more people,'' he explained, ''and the better off the neighborhood.''</p>
        <p>POSTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
