<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Merman of La Scala</title>
    <meta content="17POSS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/fashion/17POSS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855130"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="POSSESSED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Snorkeling and Diving</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Diving and Divers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diving and Divers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Cousteau, Jacques</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E7DA153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Merman of La Scala</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Merman of La Scala</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID COLMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the grand jeté of life, no one can help but be aware of the inexorable downward tug of gravity.</p>
        <p>As aware as you are, though, consider how much more keenly the leaping ballerinas and ballerinos of the world feel the tow with every move they make. For example, Alessandra Ferri, the principal at American Ballet Theater who is retiring this year, has been defying gravity for decades. You can't blame her for wanting to go out flying, which is surely one of the reasons she asked Roberto Bolle to come from Milan to accompany her in ''Manon'' and ''Romeo and Juliet'' this month. Onstage Mr. Bolle is strong and nimble enough to toss her around like a kitten.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alessandra Ferri, the principal at American Ballet Theater, has been defying gravity for decades but loves scuba diving just as much.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the grand jeté of life, no one can help but be aware of the inexorable downward tug of gravity.</p>
        <p>As aware as you are, though, consider how much more keenly the leaping ballerinas and ballerinos of the world feel the tow with every move they make. For example, Alessandra Ferri, the principal at American Ballet Theater who is retiring this year, has been defying gravity for decades. You can't blame her for wanting to go out flying, which is surely one of the reasons she asked Roberto Bolle to come from Milan to accompany her in ''Manon'' and ''Romeo and Juliet'' this month. Onstage Mr. Bolle is strong and nimble enough to toss her around like a kitten.</p>
        <p>He gets plenty of solo flight time himself, a sight that, despite the sad and stirring Massenet score, seems more superhero than tragic hero. At 6-foot-2, he leaps and soars as though drawing power from the Krypton sun. But as Mr. Bolle, 32, will tell you with a sigh: Would that it were so.</p>
        <p>''We every day fight with gravity,'' he said last week. ''We are always working very hard with the ballon'' -- that is, the balletic ideal of floating in air -- ''to get that suspension in the air for a fraction of a second, to give the impression of winning over gravity. It looks easy onstage, but it's very hard to achieve, especially for a tall boy like me. Shorter guys have more facility with suspension.''</p>
        <p>Such lightness having been a weighty responsibility for the 25 years Mr. Bolle has studied ballet, it is not a surprise that he likes to let go and let gravity do its best. ''I am so careful all the time -- I like doing something different and dangerous,'' he said. He has skied down sand dunes in Dubai, jumped from a 30-foot Philippine waterfall, and has not ruled out parachuting.</p>
        <p>But on a trip to the Philippines in 1998, he discovered a gentler sport that could actually let him truly escape the clutches of his archenemy. ''Scuba diving was like discovering a whole new world,'' he said. ''The feeling of freedom in the water is incredible. It's like a vacation from gravity.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolle does not get much joy out of merely watching ballet. ''I don't appreciate it,'' he said, ''I just make comparisons, and think, 'How could I do that better?' ''</p>
        <p>So the only way he can immerse himself in that magic is to visit the undersea world of Jacques Cousteau, who, along with the French engineer Émile Gagnan, invented the self-contained underwater breathing apparatus in 1943. Mr. Bolle has rented its descendants countless times over the last decade, in countless locations. (He has no interest in the burdens of owning it -- the only bit of gear he packs is a brief Armani swimsuit.) With scuba gear strapped to his back and a mask on his face, he can finally experience the intoxication of being a spectator.</p>
        <p>''You have no time, no noise,'' he said of being underwater. ''It's a magical world -- you have the fish, the plants, the coral, the color that comes from the sun. It's like floating; it's hard to describe. I almost laugh that I am actually able to be down there. I feel like a kid in an amusement park.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolle grants that in many ways his life is already enviable. ''To live this life and dance in beautiful theaters -- I am very spoiled in a way.''</p>
        <p>Even so, he knows well how each ballet ends and practices long how each jump lands. What makes scuba diving so inviting is that all laws, not just gravity, seem suspended. ''There's a feeling that anything can happen,'' he said.</p>
        <p>On earth, they call that modern dance.</p>
        <p>POSSESSED</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
