<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Children's Books / Young Adult</title>
    <meta content="McGrath.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/books/review/McGrath-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855322"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Children's Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E3DF1F30F934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="805" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Children's Books / Young Adult</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Children’s Books | Young Adults</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES MCGRATH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BEOWULF</p>
        <p>Adapted and illustrated by Gareth Hinds.</p>
        <p>Unpaged. Candlewick Press.</p>
        <p>Cloth, $21.99; paper, $9.99. (Ages 10 and up)</p>
        <p>BEOWULF</p>
        <p>A Hero's Tale Retold.</p>
        <p>Adapted and illustrated by James Rumford.</p>
        <p>Unpaged. Houghton Mifflin Company. $17.</p>
        <p>(Ages 9 to 12)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>What recommends “Beowulf” to children is that it’s a first-rate horror yarn, featuring slaughter, dismemberment and underwater sword fights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BEOWULF</p>
        <p>Adapted and illustrated by Gareth Hinds.</p>
        <p>Unpaged. Candlewick Press.</p>
        <p>Cloth, $21.99; paper, $9.99. (Ages 10 and up)</p>
        <p>BEOWULF</p>
        <p>A Hero's Tale Retold.</p>
        <p>Adapted and illustrated by James Rumford.</p>
        <p>Unpaged. Houghton Mifflin Company. $17.</p>
        <p>(Ages 9 to 12)</p>
        <p>Beowulf,'' a 3,000-line epic poem composed early in the eighth century, is the first significant text written in English, or in what eventually became English. What interests scholars about the story is its place in our linguistic development, and also the way it blends both Christian and pagan details. But what recommends ''Beowulf'' to children -- and to older readers who haven't lost a child's delight in stories that are both scary and gory -- is that it's also a first-rate horror yarn, featuring slaughter, dismemberment and underwater sword fights.</p>
        <p>There are not one but three monsters: Grendel, a man-eating ogre who snacks nightly on sleeping Danes until Beowulf, the story's hero, sails over from what is now Sweden and rips his arm off; Grendel's mother, a fearsome swamp creature, hell-bent on avenging her creepy son; and a treasure-hoarding dragon, who was the inspiration for some of Tolkien's winged worm-things.</p>
        <p>The story is so powerful and so elemental that it has inspired countless retellings -- in movies, cartoons, even an opera. There have also been a couple of comic-book versions, and working from this tradition, the graphic novelist Gareth Hinds has reimagined ''Beowulf'' as a kind of superhero tale. Grendel here bears a passing relationship to the monster in the ''Alien'' movies: he has the same elongated snout, the same dripping, needlelike teeth. Beowulf when we first see him looks long-faced and sleepy, but when he doffs his robe on the night when he is to fight with Grendel, and girds himself in a belted, Depends-like garment, we see that this guy is ripped. He has the V-shaped torso, the lats, the delts, the bulging thigh muscles of, say, Captain America or Green Arrow.</p>
        <p>The narration is an adaptation of A. J. Church's 1904 prose translation, which is sufficiently antique-sounding that it can pass for basic Olden-speak, the lingua franca of so many fantasy novels these days. When Beowulf gets into an argument with Unferth, a jealous rival at the Danish court, for example, he says, ''Surely the ale-can has wrought with thee, friend Unferth, that thou hast said such things.'' But great stretches of this ''Beowulf'' take place with no words at all, except the occasional ''SMASH,'' ''SSWACK'' and ''SKUTCHLP.'' Hinds stages great fight scenes, choreographing them like a kung-fu master and then drawing them from a variety of vantage points, with close-ups, wide angles and aerial views. In its way, the result is as visceral as the Old English, which was consciously onomatopoeic, and by changing his palette for each of the poem's three sections he evokes its darkening rhythm. Beowulf at the end, old and spent, looks a little monstrous himself, with age spots to rival Mr. Burns's on ''The Simpsons,'' and this is not out of keeping with the subtext of the poem, which is that except in memory and legend nothing lasts for very long.</p>
        <p>James Rumford's ''Beowulf: A Hero's Tale Retold'' (coming out later this summer) is quieter and more realistic. Rumford's inked-in watercolor drawings devote attention to domestic details of the Danish court -- pets, houses, the fire pit the king sits at. Grendel on first view, a smudgy figure wading in a swamp, seems sort of forlorn, and as far as combat voyeurism goes, the illustrations are pretty chaste. You learn more here from reading than from looking, which was surely the author's intention. He has very cleverly adapted the story in a style that except for a few necessary imports like ''ogre,'' ''dragon'' and ''giant'' relies on Anglo-Saxon words, and the result is both a not-bad approximation of the original and easily comprehensible to readers in, say, the fourth and fifth grades, who can linger over passages like: ''A deep wound now opened up on Grendel's shoulder and widened. The sinews were bursting, the arm bones loosening. There was only one way out. The ogre tore himself free and ran one-armed into the night!''</p>
        <p>An even better text is Michael Morpurgo's ''Beowulf'' (Candlewick, $17.99), which came out last year. The illustrations, by Michael Foreman, are a little pallid and storybookish, with at least one -- a depiction of Grendel's mother as a grass-skirted fashion disaster with scaly green breasts -- that is apt to elicit snickers rather than shudders. But Morpurgo, a distinguished British author of children's books, preserves much of the oddness and complexity of the original, and, though his text is in prose, even some of the poetry. Of the three versions it's also the clearest about Grendel's motivation: it drives him mad, eavesdropping at the banquet hall, that the Danes have the gift of telling stories.</p>
        <p>Charles McGrath, a former editor of the Book Review, is a writer at large for The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Charles McGrath, a former editor of the Book Review, is a writer at large for The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
