<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mirth, in Honor of Dad</title>
    <meta content="17age" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/fashion/17age.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855132"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AGE OF DISSONANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Emotions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Emotions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Morris, Bob</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E7DA153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mirth, in Honor of Dad</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mirth, in Honor of Dad</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB MORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morris, Bob</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Father's Day is here, and I'm still getting used to not having my father around.</p>
        <p>He died at this time last year, lending even more potency to today. But the strange thing is that for me, this Father's Day isn't about feeling mournful. It's a day for feeling liberated. My sunny father's last year, when he was ailing, was one of such profound and atypical depression that his death was a blessing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Father’s Day is here, and I’m still getting used to not having my father around.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Father's Day is here, and I'm still getting used to not having my father around.</p>
        <p>He died at this time last year, lending even more potency to today. But the strange thing is that for me, this Father's Day isn't about feeling mournful. It's a day for feeling liberated. My sunny father's last year, when he was ailing, was one of such profound and atypical depression that his death was a blessing.</p>
        <p>Maybe that is why the imposed veil of grief had been so complicated. After a few days of crying, I felt so relieved for both him and me that a disconcerting levity set in.</p>
        <p>Yet, well-meaning friends kept calling with somber voices, asking if I was doing O.K. It was all I could do to tell them I'd be fine if only they'd allow me to say so.</p>
        <p>Is it necessary to act out unhappiness for others to see? Did I mourn correctly? What exactly are the protocols of mourning?</p>
        <p>Not long ago, rules were more clearly defined. Widows wore black crepe veils that, according to etiquette guides, served as shields for grieving mourners, and as a protective curtain of respectability for those who should have been feeling mournful but were not. Now, at a time when one-year mourning periods for parents are not even universally observed, it is hard to know exactly what to do.</p>
        <p>People are also living longer, but not necessarily in ways that provide anything but worry and heartache for themselves and their care-giving families.</p>
        <p>''His death wasn't the tragedy, his sickness was,'' said my Aunt Sylvia about my father. ''By the time he actually died, we were prepared for it because we'd been mourning him all year.''</p>
        <p>She said that soon enough life would resume for me, and it did. But here comes today, when all of it opens up again to inhale like a night-blooming perennial on a vine.</p>
        <p>What to feel now? Gratitude, yes, for the amusement, inspiration and encouragement my Dad provided. But also well-being.</p>
        <p>''There's mixed feelings and never one pattern to mourning,'' said Leonard Shengold, the author of ''Haunted by Parents'' and a New York psychoanalyst who thinks that feelings of levity in the year after a parent's death aren't that uncommon.</p>
        <p>''You can feel someone is better off dead than alive, and not be able to admit it,'' he said. ''But Father's Day can still affect you deeply. You have to come to terms with both the father you knew at the end of his life and the one you knew at the beginning.''</p>
        <p>The one I knew at the beginning? That was the guy who came home from his law practice tired but thrilled to read my brother and me bedtime stories in a rocking chair. That was the father who made tape recordings of every school concert as if they were the Boston Pops. Who was so encouraging he made it easy to succeed.</p>
        <p>Not everyone had it so good. Bernard Cooper, whose memoir ''The Bill From My Father'' chronicles a dad so difficult he sued his family and invoiced the author for clothing, food and education, is relieved not to have to worry about Father's Day. ''If you didn't know what he wanted he could get really upset,'' Mr. Cooper said.</p>
        <p>While it is nice to know he will not be served with a subpoena now that his father is not around, today also brings regret. ''I still wonder how I could have sustained a better relationship,'' Mr. Cooper said. And I wonder if I bounced back too quickly after my father died. These questions come up today, and will for the rest of my life.</p>
        <p>Last Sunday was the unveiling of the footstone, a Jewish tradition that marks the end of a year of mourning. My brother and I worried about what was appropriate. Who to invite? What to do after the rabbi's prayers? Writing a speech seemed too formal for conjuring the spirit of such an informal man. So I handed out lyrics by Allan Sherman, the shticky 1960s parody writer who my father revered and channeled to the end.</p>
        <p>We had a little sing-along, and the appropriate sobriety of the occasion became something far more evocative of the joyful soul we adored. Family members told stories, none of them profound.</p>
        <p>The meaning was all in our amusement. Laughter, not tears were our tribute.</p>
        <p>So you'll have to forgive me. On Father's Day, I don't mourn my Dad at all. I celebrate him. Here's hoping you get to do the same with yours while he is still alive.</p>
        <p>AGE OF DISSONANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
