<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Park Brings New Ways for A's to Spend</title>
    <meta content="17chass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855239"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Oakland Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E0D6153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Park Brings New Ways for A's to Spend</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In only a few years, the Oakland Athletics expect to be doing business in a far different way than, as a low-revenue team, they have had to do it.</p>
        <p>''If we can get a ballpark the way we're trying to do it, with the management talent we have,'' Lew Wolff said, ''we can have a consistent cash flow that would allow us to have a shot at being a little more like a dynasty like they used to have, at least a semidynasty.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In only a few years, the Oakland Athletics expect to be doing business in a far different way than, as a low-revenue team, they have had to do it.</p>
        <p>''If we can get a ballpark the way we're trying to do it, with the management talent we have,'' Lew Wolff said, ''we can have a consistent cash flow that would allow us to have a shot at being a little more like a dynasty like they used to have, at least a semidynasty.''</p>
        <p>In his third season as owner of the Athletics, Wolff looks forward to the construction of a revenue-producing park in Fremont, Calif., expected to be completed by 2011. Put money in the hands of the team's general manager, Billy Beane, and it could become a dangerous weapon.</p>
        <p>In his 10-year tenure as general manager, Beane has not known what it is like to have money to spend. The prospect of suddenly having money, in fact, raises the question of what effect it could have on Beane. Will he know what to do with it? Will he react to it like a child let loose in a candy store and go wild, snatching one of everything in sight? Or will he shun the money and go on doing his business in his tried-and-true way?</p>
        <p>''I think I'm the only owner who wants to spend more than the general manager,'' Wolff said in the living room of his suite at the Carlyle in Manhattan, one of the properties of his hotel ownership group. ''The man loves business. He loves to lecture investment bankers and at universities. He's a business voyeur. I think he will be very disciplined. He enjoys the theory of substitution.''</p>
        <p>Beane has had plenty of practice with substitution, just as his mentor, Sandy Alderson, did. In the past decade, the Athletics have lost an all-star team of players to free agency or pre-emptive trades:</p>
        <p>Mark McGwire, Jason Giambi, Johnny Damon, Jermaine Dye, Miguel Tejada, Tim Hudson, Mark Mulder, Barry Zito, Jason Isringhausen.</p>
        <p>''I don't mind spending money,'' Beane said. ''It's not spending money. It's spending it on the right people.''</p>
        <p>They would include many of those departed players.</p>
        <p>''It would be nice to keep what you want to keep,'' Beane said. ''The biggest difficulty in Oakland isn't saying, 'Go out and sign free agents.' The most difficult thing is not being able to maintain what you create. We want to be able to keep those players through the prime of their careers instead of losing them in the prime of their careers.''</p>
        <p>Wolfe said he and Beane agreed on certain aspects of signing players.</p>
        <p>''I don't think Billy or myself are comfortable with six- or seven-year contracts,'' Wolfe said. ''I don't think we'd give a pitcher a seven-year contract.''</p>
        <p>Across the bay in San Francisco, the Giants' owner, Peter Magowan, and General Manager Brian Sabean gave Zito, the Athletics' most recent émigré, a seven-year contract.</p>
        <p>Wolff said: ''We still want to try staying with the rule of thumb that if your salaries are 50 percent of your revenues, you're probably making money and you're conforming to what the total baseball partnership should do. So I think we could keep players we would otherwise lose.''</p>
        <p>One thing Beane won't do, Wolff said, is make decisions unilaterally.</p>
        <p>''We talk about every signing,'' Wolff said. ''Billy has a budget; he doesn't have to bother me. But he wants everybody's opinion who is close to him. It keeps me more active than I thought I would be.''</p>
        <p>Wolff never wanted to buy a baseball team. He owned a piece of the St. Louis Blues and the Golden State Warriors, but owning a baseball team, he said, ''wasn't a passion of mine.''</p>
        <p>He became involved because of a college fraternity brother, a fellow named Selig, Bud to his friends.</p>
        <p>''My office got a call from Bud, who invited me to a World Series game between the Angels and the Giants,'' Wolff related. ''I had not seen Bud since he became commissioner. I was coming back from Paris, and I said fine. I flew to San Francisco and I went to the game with Bud, which meant a police escort. I've had six police escorts in my life, all with Bud.''</p>
        <p>Completing the purchase in April 2005, Wolff found in the Oakland organization what he felt were two top-notch executives, Beane and the president, Michael Crowley.</p>
        <p>''It's a wonderfully run team because of Billy and Mike,'' he said. ''It's budgeted beautifully. We've made money all three years. Both Billy and Mike were free agents. Any change of ownership they could leave.''</p>
        <p>Wolff made sure they didn't leave. He extended their contracts and gave them equity in the team, Beane 4 percent and Crowley a smaller piece.</p>
        <p>''I think it's the two best signings I've done,'' Wolff said.</p>
        <p>Just last week Wolff went even further, giving the two executives seven-year contracts.</p>
        <p>''When you work for Lew, everybody feels they're a part of what's going on,'' Beane said. ''He creates that type of loyalty. With Lew I'll never leave Oakland. I couldn't have a better relationship with anyone.''</p>
        <p>Wolff is the eighth owner in Athletics history. One of his predecessors was the inimitable and controversial Charlie Finley. How would he prefer to be known, Wolff was asked, as a successor to Finley or as Selig's fraternity brother?</p>
        <p>''That's easy,'' Wolff said, laughing. ''I'd rather be known as the fraternity brother of Bud Selig.''</p>
        <p>Struggles at Plate Are Over</p>
        <p>One day Jason Kendall, the next Alex Gordon.</p>
        <p>In rapid succession Kendall, the Oakland catcher, and Gordon, Kansas City's rookie third baseman, attained a .200 batting average for the first time this season. It took nearly two and a half months, but every major leaguer who would qualify for the batting title by averaging 3.1 plate appearances for his team's games has reached .200.</p>
        <p>Kendall got there with a flurry of hits. A two-hit game Tuesday night took him to .199, and the next night, in his 57th game, he collected three hits, raising his average to .210. Having broken his personal barrier, he decided not to stop there, banging three more hits Thursday and going to .219. It was as if he had never been below .200.</p>
        <p>Gordon hit a home run in his last at-bat Wednesday night, finishing the game at .199. The next night, in his 60th game, Gordon singled in his second at-bat, raising his average beyond the magic mark to .202, then hit a home run, taking him to .206. He later flied out and struck out, ending the game at .204.</p>
        <p>Eclipsing the Stars</p>
        <p>The names James Shields and Justin Germano aren't as familiar as Barry Zito and Dontrelle Willis, but they have done a far better job for their teams than those two more heralded pitchers.</p>
        <p>Shields, a second-year pitcher for Tampa Bay, has a 6-1 record for a team whose won-lost record is 10th in the American League. No other Devil Rays starter has two more victories than losses. Before incurring his first loss Friday night, Shields, a 25-year-old right-hander, had won his last three starts with a 2.70 earned run average. His E.R.A. for the season is 3.30.</p>
        <p>Germano, a 24-year-old right-hander, has a 5-0 record and 2.36 E.R.A. in seven starts for San Diego since being promoted from the minor leagues May 7. He had 56 days of major league service with the Padres and Cincinnati before this season.</p>
        <p>The Reds traded him to Philadelphia for Rhéal Cormier on the trading deadline last season, and the Padres claimed him off waivers from the Phillies last March.</p>
        <p>Bannister Excels With Royals</p>
        <p>Brian Bannister lost in the competition for a spot in the Mets' rotation, but he has found a job in the Kansas City rotation and is flourishing at the same time the winners of the Mets' competition have experienced trouble for the first time this season.</p>
        <p>The competition did not take place in spring training. By that time the Mets, seeking to bolster their bullpen, had traded Bannister to the Royals for Ambiorix Burgos.</p>
        <p>Bannister lost out after missing most of last season with a hamstring injury. The injury had nothing to do with the fact that the Mets' brain trust liked Oliver Pérez and John Maine more than Bannister.</p>
        <p>Bannister began the season in the minors but was recalled to join the rotation April 24. He lost three of his first six starts and won none, compiling a 4.54 E.R.A. But he has won his last three starts, allowing only one earned run in 22 innings for a 0.41 E.R.A.</p>
        <p>Murray Repeats Performance</p>
        <p>Eddie Murray can't hold a job, as a hitting coach that is. The Los Angeles Dodgers fired Murray on Thursday, prematurely ending his second season as their hitting coach. The Cleveland Indians fired Murray as their hitting coach in the middle of his fourth season in 2005.</p>
        <p>Neither team gave a reason for the dismissal, but Murray suffered from the syndrome that undermines the ability of former superstars to be effective coaches or managers. They were great players because they had innate hitting or pitching ability, and they have difficulty dealing with players with less talent. They can't accept the inability of players to do what came naturally to them.</p>
        <p>In Murray's case, he knew what hitters had to do to improve, and when they didn't follow his instructions or couldn't carry out his ideas, he became offended, and his reaction alienated the players. He lost the players, and the teams were left with no choice but to make changes.</p>
        <p>It was not just mere coincidence that he was jettisoned around the same time of the season: June 5 by the Indians, June 14 by the Dodgers.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
