<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Leaders Tumble Back; Woods Is There To Meet Them</title>
    <meta content="17golf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/sports/17golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">PGA Tour Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Baddeley, Aaron</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EFDE123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Leaders Tumble Back; Woods Is There To Meet Them</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">As Leaders Tumble Back, Woods Is There to Meet Them</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa., June 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the foothills near Pittsburgh and in the crucible of golf, a former child prodigy named Aaron Baddeley chased a glimmering sunset and tried to grasp a slippery lead in the 107th United States Open.</p>
        <p>On his final hole Saturday at Oakmont Country Club, with shadows crisscrossing a lopsided green, Baddeley drew back his putter blade from 15 feet and sent his golf ball trundling into the hole.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tiger Woods began the third round of the U.S. Open five shots off the lead. On Saturday, however, he moved into second place behind Aaron Baddeley.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the foothills near Pittsburgh and in the crucible of golf, a former child prodigy named Aaron Baddeley chased a glimmering sunset and tried to grasp a slippery lead in the 107th United States Open.</p>
        <p>On his final hole Saturday at Oakmont Country Club, with shadows crisscrossing a lopsided green, Baddeley drew back his putter blade from 15 feet and sent his golf ball trundling into the hole.</p>
        <p>With a short fist pump and a wide smile, Baddeley made a birdie that increased his lead in the championship and won him a place in the final group with Tiger Woods. ''It's perfect,'' said Baddeley, whose par 70 gave him a total of two-over 212 and two-stroke lead over Woods, who shot 69. ''If you had asked me which player in the world I'd like to play with, it's Tiger. He's the best player in the world, but I feel like I'm playing nicely.''</p>
        <p>Baddeley, a 26-year-old from Australia who once tore up the amateur circuit, held a three-shot lead over Paul Casey (72), Stephen Ames (73), Justin Rose (73) and Bubba Watson (74). Ángel Cabrera (76), who held the lead after 36 holes, stood four shots back, along with Jim Furyk (70) and Steve Stricker (68). David Toms (73), Stuart Appleby (71) and Niclas Fasth (75) trailed by five.</p>
        <p>On a third consecutive day that had Oakmont roaring, Baddeley surged into position to be the second straight Australian to win the Open, following Geoff Ogilvy's feat last year at Winged Foot. To get there, Baddeley will have to overcome a bunched-up, international leader board. No player is closer to him on the board than Woods, who had his best ball-striking round to move into contention for his 13th major championship -- although he has never come from behind after 54 holes to win.</p>
        <p>Baddeley, who played with Woods in the Masters in 2000 and missed the cut, is a different and better player now.</p>
        <p>After seeing his career mostly fizzle after turning professional in 2000, Baddeley won his first PGA Tour event last year at the Verizon Heritage and his second in February at the FBR Open.</p>
        <p>But on the tee boxes Sunday, he will be standing alongside Woods, who may be peaking. Woods put together one of the best rounds of the championship, hitting 17 of 18 greens and 9 of 14 fairways.</p>
        <p>But he knew it could have been better.</p>
        <p>After hitting every green in his first 17 holes, he pushed his drive into a fairway bunker on the right at No. 18, and he could advance his ball only to the fairway. Woods then hit a pitch shot to 15 feet, but he missed his putt for par. It was his only bogey of the round.</p>
        <p>''I hit a lot of good putts that just grazed the edge,'' he said. ''You just don't want to end on a dropped shot. I'd be miffed if I hit bad putts, but I hit good ones.''</p>
        <p>Woods, who trailed Cabrera by five shots going into Saturday's round, made a quick push up the leader board. He easily skirted the Church Pews bunker between the third and fourth holes and ended up with birdies on both. He then ran off 13 pars in a row.</p>
        <p>''I felt like I could control my ball all day,'' Woods said. ''This golf course does not lend itself to a lot of birdies.''</p>
        <p>Oakmont continued to play firm and fast, but a Friday night watering of the greens by officials of the United States Golf Association kept the course under control. Ian Poulter, who shot 72 and stood at 11-over, said the greens were noticeably slower than they were Friday.</p>
        <p>''You could see they have given them a little douse of water,'' he said. ''It is playing fair -- too fair, to be honest. I would have liked to have seen it extremely hard and hope guys tumbled back.''</p>
        <p>Several players did, anyway. Cabrera seemed to come unglued after holding the overnight lead as he sprayed shots around the course and had to play several from ankle-deep rough.</p>
        <p>On a leader board stacked with newcomers and rising stars, Woods spelled out a key advantage he might have over his lesser-known competitors Sunday. ''They're going to deal with emotions that they've probably never dealt with before,'' he said. ''It helps to have experience. I've been there before, and I know what it takes.''</p>
        <p>Other than Woods, only Furyk, Toms and Vijay Singh, who was six shots back, were players in contention who have won a major title.</p>
        <p>Watson grabbed the outright lead through eight holes, only to spin out of control on the 477-yard par-4 ninth.</p>
        <p>With an iron in his hands from the middle of the fairway, Watson pushed his approach into the deep rough to the left. When he tried to hit a chip shot, his ball remained in the rough. Playing quickly, Watson sent his fourth shot over the green and into more rough. His fifth shot finally found the green, but he left it 15 feet short. After missing his putt, he tapped in for a triple-bogey 7.</p>
        <p>''I had one bad swing, and that's all it takes,'' he said. ''I mean, as good as I can hit the ball, that's how good I hit today. I still made that one triple and it derailed me a little bit.''</p>
        <p>Baddeley will face his own pressures Sunday, namely in the form of Woods and a golf course with no sympathy. They will be the biggest 18 holes of his career.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, I'm going to deal with some emotions because I've never been in this position before,'' Baddeley said.</p>
        <p>''But I've worked my whole life to be in this position, so I'm going to embrace it.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
