<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Elegy for Three Sisters. Chekhov? No, Wasserstein.</title>
    <meta content="17theaterweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/17theaterwe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Schoolhouse Theater (Croton Falls, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gold, Sylviane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wasserstein, Wendy (1950-2006)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sisters Rosensweig, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Schoolhouse Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wasserstein, Wendy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E2D7143FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Elegy for Three Sisters. Chekhov? No, Wasserstein.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Elegy for Three Sisters. Chekhov? No, Wasserstein.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SYLVIANE GOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gold, Sylviane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sylviane Gold reviews Schoolhouse Theater production of Wendy Wasserstein play The Sisters Rosensweig; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There's a moment in Act II of Wendy Wasserstein's ''Sisters Rosensweig'' in which Geoffrey Duncan, the bisexual theater director, mourns all the friends he has lost to AIDS: ''I've seen too many lights that never had their chance to glow burn out overnight. I've tried for years to make sense of all this, and all I know is life is random.'' Today, those lines stand as a lament for Ms. Wasserstein herself, whose inimitable voice was prematurely stilled last year, when she died of lymphoma at 55.</p>
        <p>There's always been a streak of melancholy in her plays, peeking now and again from behind that familiar smokescreen of warmth and humor. In ''The Sisters Rosensweig,'' the sadness is very close to the surface -- and not just because we watch this 1992 play knowing that its author will never write another. It was no accident that Ms. Wasserstein chose to repeatedly invoke Chekhov's mopey heroines pining for Moscow, as the three Rosensweig girls gather to celebrate a birthday in the elegant London townhouse of the eldest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sadness in Wendy Wasserstein’s “Sisters Rosenweig” is very close to the surface.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There's a moment in Act II of Wendy Wasserstein's ''Sisters Rosensweig'' in which Geoffrey Duncan, the bisexual theater director, mourns all the friends he has lost to AIDS: ''I've seen too many lights that never had their chance to glow burn out overnight. I've tried for years to make sense of all this, and all I know is life is random.'' Today, those lines stand as a lament for Ms. Wasserstein herself, whose inimitable voice was prematurely stilled last year, when she died of lymphoma at 55.</p>
        <p>There's always been a streak of melancholy in her plays, peeking now and again from behind that familiar smokescreen of warmth and humor. In ''The Sisters Rosensweig,'' the sadness is very close to the surface -- and not just because we watch this 1992 play knowing that its author will never write another. It was no accident that Ms. Wasserstein chose to repeatedly invoke Chekhov's mopey heroines pining for Moscow, as the three Rosensweig girls gather to celebrate a birthday in the elegant London townhouse of the eldest.</p>
        <p>For all their differences -- and there are many -- these three sisters are hugely successful. Sara, who owns the house, is a high-powered banker; Gorgeous, visiting from an upscale Boston suburb, has become a minor celebrity with a local talk show; Pfeni, Ms. Wasserstein's fictionalized stand-in, is a globe-trotting, crusading writer.</p>
        <p>Like Ms. Wasserstein herself, they've all traveled far from the Brooklyn where they grew up. But they are dogged by ambivalence about that distance, which has separated Sara and Pfeni from their Jewish roots and from Gorgeous, who did what was expected of her and hews to her traditions (as well as to certain traditional ethnic stereotypes). The choices they made have not prevented disappointment, however, and the men in (and out) of their lives are particular sources of pain. Despite all the bubbling affection in the play, and its reminders of the optimistic political mood surrounding the dissolution of the Soviet empire, Pamela Moller Kareman's production at the Schoolhouse Theater in Croton Falls underlines the work's elegiac tone.</p>
        <p>Partly it's a result of the casting. Milica Govich softens the hard edges of Sara, so that her snobbery and Anglophilia seem less a spectacular trompe l'oeil stunt than an unfortunate inevitability. And as Pfeni, Mollie O'Mara manages to suggest the weariness and anxiety that lie beneath the character's chipper facade, as her long-term, long-distance romance with Geoffrey reaches its inevitable end.</p>
        <p>The men, too, play down the humorous aspects of their characters in favor of nuance. Geoffrey is written as a flamboyant, compulsive entertainer, but Neal Mayer imbues the manic scenes with a tinge of sober desperation. And Steve Perlmutter, as the outspoken New York furrier who falls hard for the much-married, resistant Sara -- ''a hard woman,'' he keeps saying -- accentuates Mervyn's hangdog tendencies rather than his combative ones.</p>
        <p>Only Amy Marcs's Gorgeous, the garrulous middle sister, gets all the laughs embedded in the play. All bristling shoulders and nasal intonations, Gorgeous is endearingly dotty; but there's an underlying tension in her life, too.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wasserstein, whose writing for The New York Times I had occasion to edit, liked her plays to be what Gorgeous would call ''funsy.'' But she didn't want them to be mere entertainments. In ''The Sisters Rosensweig,'' perhaps the most overtly autobiographical of them, she explored the disjunctions and connections that make families both entertaining and heartbreaking.</p>
        <p>John Pollard, who did such a magnificent job designing a grubby Mississippi kitchen for another trio of sisters at another birthday party, in the Schoolhouse production of ''Crimes of the Heart'' in April, is now doing posh rather than rundown. With its silk brocade antiques and Chinese vases brimming with flowers, Sara's house is fit for royalty. And, thanks to Ms. Wasserstein's writing, royals do indeed reside there.</p>
        <p>''The Sisters Rosensweig,'' by Wendy Wasserstein, is at the Schoolhouse Theater, 3 Owens Road, Croton Falls, through June 24. Information can be found at (914) 277-8477 or schoolhousetheater.org.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
