<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Unpleasant Trudge Toward Baseball's Record Books</title>
    <meta content="17land" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/us/17land.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855244"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THIS LAND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Francisco Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barry, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bonds, Barry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Columns/This Land</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFD6153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="922" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Unpleasant Trudge Toward Baseball's Record Books</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Unpleasant Trudge Toward Baseball’s Record Books</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN BARRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barry, Dan</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dan Barry column holds that Barry Bonds of San Francisco Giants, with 747 home runs to his credit, needs just 9 more to break most storied record in sports; maintains that this could have been wonderful story if federal investigators were not looking into whether Bonds lied to grand jury about steroid use; contends that this has created awkward year that Major League Baseball deserves, given its long reluctance to tackle issue of performance-enhancing drugs; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One by one, men who earn their living by playing baseball enter the carpeted sanctum of the San Francisco Giants clubhouse. They shrug into uniforms and prepare for another night shift, though no night is just another night anymore, thanks to the man now at the threshold.</p>
        <p>He does not saunter in, as his critics would have it. He simply walks in, tall and broad-chested, with a shaved head that some say is larger than it used to be, though for reasons unrelated to his ego. As he moves, people in the room make furtive cellphone calls. He's here, they whisper. Yeah, he's in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With all that is swirling around him, Barry Bonds seems to find true serenity only in the few square feet of the batter’s box.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One by one, men who earn their living by playing baseball enter the carpeted sanctum of the San Francisco Giants clubhouse. They shrug into uniforms and prepare for another night shift, though no night is just another night anymore, thanks to the man now at the threshold.</p>
        <p>He does not saunter in, as his critics would have it. He simply walks in, tall and broad-chested, with a shaved head that some say is larger than it used to be, though for reasons unrelated to his ego. As he moves, people in the room make furtive cellphone calls. He's here, they whisper. Yeah, he's in.</p>
        <p>He, of course, is Barry Bonds, and at 42 he may well be both the best and the most disliked hitter in baseball history. Considering the many gifted athletes and reprobates to precede him to the batter's box, this is no small feat. If statisticians tracked unpleasantness, he'd be at the tail end of a 22-year streak.</p>
        <p>He passes a small, round table, on which sits a copy of The San Francisco Chronicle, face up. The headline reads, ''As Milestone Nears, Bonds Probe Drags,'' and is accompanied by a photograph of Bonds from behind, the number 25 emblazoned across his expansive back, a black bat at rest on his left shoulder. If the story is a strike, Bonds does not swing; he just keeps walking.</p>
        <p>As testament to his status, or to his isolation, Bonds maintains a large corner locker made virtually private by its close proximity to a wide pillar. The space includes a lounge chair, a large television and an unwelcoming ambience that signals to teammates: There is only one Giant.</p>
        <p>He opens a cardboard box containing black bats, freshly shipped, and pulls them out one at a time, removing the plastic from their barrels and waving them in half-swings, as if testing their kinetic potential. He selects a couple, meticulously wraps tape around their handles, then tests their feel again.</p>
        <p>At the moment he seems focused on this essential tool of his trade, but later, in a brief audience, he delights in dispelling all romance about The Bat -- as if celebrating the instrument deflects attention from the virtuoso.</p>
        <p>''The bat ain't the player, bro','' he says. ''Let it go.''</p>
        <p>Barring injury, suspension, or an Act of God, this brooding ballplayer in a lounge chair, the difficult-to-like Bonds, will soon surpass the well-liked Hank Aaron in career home runs, breaking the most storied record in sports. With 747 home runs to his credit, he needs just 9 more.</p>
        <p>His could have been a wonderful story on many levels, the least flattering of which would merely have been the lesson not to confuse athletes for heroes. Instead, that Chronicle headline shouts from the clubhouse table about a protracted federal investigation into whether Bonds lied to a grand jury about steroid use, drowning out a song playing over the sound system called ''I Heard a Rumor.''</p>
        <p>He has professed his innocence as troubling grand jury information has become public, as a former girlfriend has recalled his curious habits -- as Greg Anderson, his trainer and a documented steroids enabler, sits for months in prison, held in contempt for refusing to testify against his multimillionaire buddy Barry, who used to throw him a few bucks now and then.</p>
        <p>But as Bonds attributes his astounding late-career achievements, including an unprecedented 73 home runs in 2001, to nutrition and weight training, people cannot help but stare at his bulked-up body. Is it a trick of the suspicious mind, or does his very head look larger?</p>
        <p>All this has created the awkward year that Major League Baseball richly deserves, given its long reluctance to tackle the matter of performance-enhancing drugs. For now the baseball establishment is acting like chagrined parents preparing for a shotgun wedding, while Aaron says he plans to be golfing on the blessed day.</p>
        <p>Consider, then, what it must be like to be Barry Bonds at this moment: the focus of a criminal investigation, the target of national jeers, the despoiler of sacred statistics, the latest loneliest man in baseball. But among his many gifts, it seems, beyond the keen eyesight and perfect swing, there is this: the preternatural ability to compartmentalize.</p>
        <p>On this night, at AT&amp;T Park, more than 37,000 fans arrive to share in what the Giants organization, though not Major League Baseball, is calling the ''Road to History.'' They watch Bonds move from the dugout to left field and back again, not quite walking, not quite jogging, his every step a study in the economy of energy.</p>
        <p>On this night, children lean over the dugout lip with baseballs and pens, and chirp like nestlings, ''Barry, Barry,'' innocent of the knowledge that Bonds is hoarding his own memorabilia, much to the consternation of the Hall of Fame. (''I'm not worried about the Hall,'' he recently said. ''I take care of me.'')</p>
        <p>And on this night, Bonds bats four times, as calm in the batter's box as a man at a bus stop. The opposing team walks him intentionally twice, rather than suffer the consequences of one of his swings. He also hits a line-drive single, his 1,468th, and a rocketing double, his 594th, that nearly clears the wall in right-center field. No one else hits with such command.</p>
        <p>With all that is swirling around him, Bonds seems to find true serenity only in the few square feet of the batter's box. Asked later what he hears when he steps up to bat, he says, ''Blank.''</p>
        <p>THIS LAND</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
