<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some May See City's Tax Cut As Anything But</title>
    <meta content="17taxes" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/17taxes.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070620T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855304"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EEDE123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1358" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some May See City's Tax Cut As Anything But</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Some May See City’s Tax Cut as Anything But</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When their property tax bills start arriving this week, New Yorkers may be expecting to benefit from a 7 percent tax rate cut for the city's homeowners.</p>
        <p>But the across-the-board tax cut, as promised by Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg and the City Council, does not mean that every homeowner's tax bills will shrink. Some will save hundreds of dollars. But because of the arcane tax structure, others, like Marie Smith, who lives in a 22-year-old ranch house on Staten Island, will actually see their taxes rise in the fiscal year that starts July 1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An across-the-board tax cut, as promised by Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg and the City Council, does not mean that every homeowner’s tax bills will shrink.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When their property tax bills start arriving this week, New Yorkers may be expecting to benefit from a 7 percent tax rate cut for the city's homeowners.</p>
        <p>But the across-the-board tax cut, as promised by Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg and the City Council, does not mean that every homeowner's tax bills will shrink. Some will save hundreds of dollars. But because of the arcane tax structure, others, like Marie Smith, who lives in a 22-year-old ranch house on Staten Island, will actually see their taxes rise in the fiscal year that starts July 1.</p>
        <p>The prospect of paying more next year, on top of a 27 percent increase in her bill over the last two years, puzzled Ms. Smith, 66, a retired city employee. ''It will be very confusing,'' she said. ''They really shouldn't call it a 7 percent cut. People are going to think they're getting 7 percent off.''</p>
        <p>Under the city budget that was approved on Friday, the average tax on a co-op will be rising slightly next year, the average house will pay slightly less, while the average condominium will get a break of $415. City officials will almost certainly face plenty of perplexed property owners.</p>
        <p>The new tax cut produces uneven outcomes because of the complex way that different homes are assessed, and when those assessments are rising, as they have been, the impact of a decrease in tax rates is blunted.</p>
        <p>''I don't think anyone's going to have an exactly 7 percent lower bill,'' said George Sweeting, deputy director of the New York City Independent Budget Office. But he added, ''Well, out of about a million people, I guess at least one person is.''</p>
        <p>How does a tax cut for all result in higher taxes for some? The answer lies buried within layer upon layer of provisions and countermeasures inserted by state and local politicians in a system that was devised more than a quarter-century ago. In trying to protect owners of single-family houses -- read: voters -- from big year-to-year jumps in their taxes, elected officials have created a camel of a system where the tax burden falls unevenly and inconsistently on different types of residences. In short, owners of houses have traditionally been given breaks at the expense of owners of apartments in co-op buildings and condominiums.</p>
        <p>Over the years, officials have tried to reduce some of that inequity by tweaking the tax formulas. Those changes have resulted in a system that is daunting even for its closest observers.</p>
        <p>''You're about to enter a jungle,'' warned Glenn S. Pesanen, an adjunct associate professor of political science at Lehman College of the City University of New York, who has written about city taxes for years.</p>
        <p>The new tax cut is an effort to roll back part of the 18.5 percent tax rate increase imposed in two steps in 2003 and 2004, which produced an overall tax rate of 12.28 percent on all property, according to Mr. Sweeting. Property in the city is divided into four classes: two of them residential, one commercial, and one for utilities, with each class having a different tax rate.</p>
        <p>But the 7 percent cut on the overall rate does not mean that the tax rate for each property class will go down by 7 percent.</p>
        <p>In fact, the rate for house owners will drop by only 4.25 percent, while the rate for condo and co-op owners will decline by 6 percent. The rate for office buildings, stores and other commercial properties will drop by 8.5 percent. (In addition to the property tax cuts, the budget also renews the $400 property tax rebates for homeowners.)</p>
        <p>And rate changes alone do not determine the tax bills people receive. The rates are applied to a portion of the assessed values that the city recalculates once a year using a complex set of rules, most of which are mandated by state law. The law limits how much individual assessments can rise each year and how much the overall tax burden borne by each class of property can change from year to year.</p>
        <p>The assessed value of a house, for example, cannot rise more than 6 percent in a year or 20 percent over three years, no matter how much house prices are rising.</p>
        <p>In one case, the city's Department of Finance estimated that the value of a single-family house in Carroll Gardens, Brooklyn, rose by almost 50 percent last year to $1.4 million. But the taxes on that house, which are about $3,000 this year, will decline next year because the assessed value could not rise any further and the tax rate is coming down.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Ms. Smith, whose house is worth less than half as much and is appreciating at a slower rate, will pay slightly more. Her tax bill -- even with the rate cut -- will rise by about $70 next year from the $1,520 she is paying this year on the Ward Hill home she shares with her mother. She is already paying $321 more in property taxes this year than she paid two years ago, she said.</p>
        <p>''They've been going up every year,'' Ms. Smith said.</p>
        <p>To further complicate comparisons, houses are not assessed in the same way as condos or co-op apartments. To assess a house's value, the city uses data on recent sales of comparable houses. But for condominiums and co-ops, the city tries to determine what they would be worth if they were rental units.</p>
        <p>That process yields values for co-ops and some condos that are far below what they would sell for, Mr. Sweeting said, particularly in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''There's no doubt about it that one of the reasons we have a system like we do in New York is that it's just politically very unpalatable to raise people's property taxes,'' said Stephen Raphael, a real estate lawyer in Manhattan who owns a co-op apartment but benefited for decades from the low taxes on a brownstone in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Mr. Raphael said he sold that house for more than $1 million a few years ago but was still paying only about $3,000 annually in property taxes. In the 20-odd years he owned it, he said, its value increased tenfold but its assessment rose by less than 50 percent.</p>
        <p>The process is so complicated that even Larry S. Kopp, the president of the real estate tax committee of the Association of Residential Boards, said he could not predict what will happen to the taxes on his co-op on East 69th Street -- and he is the president of the building's board.</p>
        <p>What Mr. Kopp said he did know was that co-ops have been getting squeezed for the last several years while house owners were protected from rising taxes. ''If they're holding single-family houses capped, they've got to get it from somewhere,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Because the assessed values of apartments can rise faster than those of houses, he said, tax bills on apartments have been going up faster. And co-op assessments can rise faster than the assessed values of condos.</p>
        <p>That is why, according to the City Council's figures, the average condominium will get a break of more than $400 next year, while the average co-op will pay a bit more.</p>
        <p>Mary Ann Rothman, executive director of the Council of New York Cooperatives and Condominiums, said she expected apartment owners to be happy about the tax cut, especially owners of condos, whose assessments have generally been higher than those of co-ops because their buildings were built more recently.</p>
        <p>''This is our first real relief,'' Ms. Rothman said. ''Basically, people are very, very pleased. For so many years, we've seen taxes go up and up and up.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Rothman said she also was glad to hear that the new tax rates had been set in time to send out the bills this week with the correct charges on them.</p>
        <p>In past years, the first bills of the new tax year arrived using the previous year's rates, then later bills were adjusted to make up the difference. Showing the new rates from the start will help reduce some of the confusion about how the city taxes its residents, she said.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 20, 2007, Wednesday  Because of an editing error, an article on Sunday about the various factors that will offset New York City's 7 percent across-the-board cut in property taxes referred incorrectly in some copies to a state law that limits the amount that the assessed value of a house can rise each year. It can rise no more than 6 percent in a year or 20 percent over five years -- not over three years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 20, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article on Sunday about the various factors that will offset New York City's 7 percent across-the-board cut in property taxes referred incorrectly in some copies to a state law that limits the amount that the assessed value of a house can rise each year. It can rise no more than 6 percent in a year or 20 percent over five years -- not over three years.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
