<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PAPERBACK BEST SELLERS: June 17, 2007</title>
    <meta content="Bestpaper.fiction" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855311"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E5DF1F30F934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1135" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PAPERBACK BEST SELLERS: June 17, 2007</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended June 2, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended June 2, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>05,06,64</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  On</p>
        <p>Week  List  FICTION</p>
        <p>1  7  WATER FOR ELEPHANTS, by Sara Gruen. (Algonquin, $13.95.) A young man -- and an elephant -- save a Depression-era circus.</p>
        <p>2  117  THE KITE RUNNER, by Khaled Hosseini. (Riverhead, $15.95 and $14.) An Afghan-American returns to Kabul to learn how a childhood friend has fared.</p>
        <p>3  1  ANGELS FALL, by Nora Roberts. (Jove, $7.99.) A woman newly arrived in the Wyoming mountains claims to have witnessed a murder, but only one man believes her.</p>
        <p>4  5  THE HUSBAND, by Dean Koontz. (Bantam, $7.99.) A man whose wife has been kidnapped has 60 hours to come up with a huge ransom.</p>
        <p>5  10  THE ROAD, by Cormac McCarthy. (Vintage, $14.95.) A father and son travel in post-apocalypse America.</p>
        <p>6  50  THE MEMORY KEEPER'S DAUGHTER, by Kim Edwards. (Penguin, $14.) A doctor's decision to send his newborn daughter, who has Down syndrome, to an institution haunts everyone involved.</p>
        <p>7  1  BEACH ROAD, by James Patterson and Peter de Jonge. (Warner Vision, $9.99.) A lawyer defends a high school basketball star suspected of murder.</p>
        <p>8  8  Suite FRANÃAISE, by IrÃ</p>
        <p>ne Némirovsky. (Vintage, $14.95.) Two novellas about life in France under the Nazis, by an author who died at Auschwitz.</p>
        <p>9  1  the man from stone creek, by Linda Lael Miller. (HQN, $7.99.) A tale of love and outlaws set in an Arizona border town in 1903.</p>
        <p>10  1  BLACK ORDER, by James Rollins. (Harper, $7.99.) Operatives of Sigma Force become entangled in a modern-day Nazi experiment.</p>
        <p>11  1  SLEEPING WITH FEAR, by Kay Hooper. (Bantam, $7.50.) A woman investigating occult activity wakes up covered in blood, with no memory of what happened.</p>
        <p>12  7  THE 5TH HORSEMAN, by James Patterson and Maxine Paetro. (Warner, $14.99.) Detective Lindsay Boxer and the Women's Murder Club investigate unexplained deaths at a San Francisco hospital.</p>
        <p>13  2  THE COLD MOON, by Jeffery Deaver. (Pocket Star, $9.99.) Detectives Lincoln Rhyme and Amelia Sachs investigate murders committed by a criminal mastermind called the Watchmaker.</p>
        <p>14  1  THE MacGREGORS: ROBERT &amp; CYBIL, by Nora Roberts. (Silhouette, $7.99.) Two tales -- ''The Winning Hand'' and ''The Perfect Neighbor'' -- in one volume.</p>
        <p>15  2  BEWARE A SCOT'S REVENGE, by Sabrina Jeffries. (Pocket, $6.99.) A woman is kidnapped in Scotland by her father's sworn enemy, a man she has long desired.</p>
        <p>16*  15  THE ALCHEMIST, by Paulo Coelho. (HarperSanFrancisco, $13.95 and $13.) A Spanish shepherd boy travels to Egypt in search of treasure.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  On</p>
        <p>Week  List  NONFICTION</p>
        <p>1  19  EAT, PRAY, LOVE, by Elizabeth Gilbert. (Penguin Books, $15.) A writer's yearlong journey in search of self takes her to Italy, India and Indonesia.</p>
        <p>2  73  THE GLASS CASTLE, by Jeannette Walls. (Scribner, $14.) The author recalls a bizarre childhood during which she and her siblings were constantly moved from one bleak place to another.</p>
        <p>3  9  BLINK, by Malcolm Gladwell. (Back Bay, $15.99.) The author of ''The Tipping Point'' explores the importance of instinct to the workings of the mind.</p>
        <p>4  32  90 MINUTES IN HEAVEN, by Don Piper with Cecil Murphey. (Revell, $12.99.) A minister on the otherworldly experience he had after an accident.</p>
        <p>5  3  THE FINAL MOVE BEYOND IRAQ, by Mike Evans. (Frontline, $14.99.) The author, a political conservative, says America should act decisively in confronting radical Islam and restricting Iran's nuclear plans. ()</p>
        <p>6  18  THREE CUPS OF TEA, by Greg Mortenson and David Oliver Relin. (Penguin Books, $15.) A former climber builds schools in Pakistan and Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>7  146  THE TIPPING POINT, by Malcolm Gladwell. (Back Bay/Little, Brown, $14.95.) A journalist's study of social epidemics, otherwise known as fads.</p>
        <p>8  19  THE MEASURE OF A MAN, by Sidney Poitier. (HarperSanFrancisco, $14.95.) The movie actor's spiritual autobiography.</p>
        <p>9  67  NIGHT, by Elie Wiesel. (Hill &amp; Wang, $9.) The horrors of Auschwitz and Buchenwald.</p>
        <p>10  6  MAYFLOWER, by Nathaniel Philbrick. (Penguin Books, $16.) How America began, from the author of ''In the Heart of the Sea.''</p>
        <p>11  16  THE YEAR OF MAGICAL THINKING, by Joan Didion. (Vintage, $13.95.) The author's attempts to come to terms with the death of her husband and the grave illness of their only daughter.</p>
        <p>12  11  STUMBLING ON HAPPINESS, by Daniel Gilbert. (Vintage, $14.95.) A Harvard professor explores why people can't predict what will make them happy.</p>
        <p>13  4  ARMED MADHOUSE, by Greg Palast. (Plume, $15.) A collection of articles about the ''war on terror,'' the 2008 election and other topics by an investigative reporter.</p>
        <p>14*  4  POSSIBLE SIDE EFFECTS, by Augusten Burroughs. (Picador, $14.) Autobiographical essays from the author of ''Running With Scissors.''</p>
        <p>15  19  THE FREEDOM WRITERS DIARY, by the Freedom Writers with Erin Gruwell. (Broadway, $13.95.) Students considered ''unteachable'' write about their lives; the basis for the movie ''Freedom Writers.''</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  On</p>
        <p>Week  List  Advice, How-to and Miscellaneous: Hardcover</p>
        <p>1  21  THE SECRET, by Rhonda Byrne. (Atria/Beyond Words, $23.95.) The law of attraction as a key to getting what you want.</p>
        <p>2  5  THE DANGEROUS BOOK FOR BOYS, by Conn Iggulden and Hal Iggulden. (Collins/HarperCollins, $24.95.) Skipping stones, tying knots and other essential activities -- video games not included.</p>
        <p>3  4  REPOSITION YOURSELF, by T. D. Jakes. (Atria, $24.) How to grow spiritually and materially by putting faith into action.</p>
        <p>4  1  THE 4-HOUR WORKWEEK, by Timothy Ferriss. (Crown, $19.95.) Tips for restructuring your life so that it's not all about work.</p>
        <p>5  1  THE ABS DIET FOR WOMEN, by David Zinczenko with Ted Spiker. (Rodale, $24.95.) Six weeks to a flatter belly, from the editor in chief of Men's Health.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  On</p>
        <p>Week  List  Advice, How-to and Miscellaneous: Paperback</p>
        <p>1  1  THE BOOK OF USELESS INFORMATION, by Noel Botham and the Useless Information Society. (Perigee, $12.95.) Facts and figures, ideal for connoisseurs of pointless knowledge.</p>
        <p>2  325  RICH DAD, POOR DAD, by Robert T. Kiyosaki with Sharon L. Lechter. (Warner, $16.95.) Teaching one's children how to get rich and stay rich. ()</p>
        <p>3  69  1,000 PLACES TO SEE BEFORE YOU DIE, by Patricia Schultz. (Workman, $18.95.) A guide to travel.</p>
        <p>4  316  WHAT TO EXPECT WHEN YOU'RE EXPECTING, by Heidi Murkoff, Arlene Eisenberg and Sandee Hathaway. (Workman, $13.95.) Advice for parents-to-be. ()</p>
        <p>5  8  THE FIVE LOVE LANGUAGES, by Gary Chapman (Northfield, $13.99). How to communicate love in a way a spouse will understand.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
