<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Power of Teaching</title>
    <meta content="17boss" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/business/yourmoney/17boss.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855179"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="JOBS: THE BOSS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ing Group (Internationale Nederlanden Groep Nv)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murphy, Kathleen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olsen, Patricia R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/The Boss</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Careers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Human Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E0DA153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="749" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Power of Teaching</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Power of Teaching</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHLEEN MURPHY; As told to Patricia R. Olsen.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Murphy, Kathleen; Olsen, Patricia R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kathleen Murphy, chief executive of US Wealth Management at ING, in The Boss column, on some of her life experiences; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I GREW up with two sisters and three brothers in a traditional Irish-Catholic family. My father thought it was the girls' job to clean up after dinner and the boys' job to mow the lawn. Over time, my sisters and I educated him.</p>
        <p>I was on my high school swimming team, which won the Connecticut state championship three out of the four years I was there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“My father thought it was the girls’ job to clean up after dinner and the boys’ job to mow the lawn,” said Kathleen Murphy. “Over time, my sisters and I educated him.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I GREW up with two sisters and three brothers in a traditional Irish-Catholic family. My father thought it was the girls' job to clean up after dinner and the boys' job to mow the lawn. Over time, my sisters and I educated him.</p>
        <p>I was on my high school swimming team, which won the Connecticut state championship three out of the four years I was there.</p>
        <p>I wasn't a natural, though. When I was 5 or 6, all the kids in the neighborhood joined the swim team at the town pool. Everyone was better than I was. I was so terrible that one day the staff thought I had drowned.</p>
        <p>I was the only one who stuck with it, though. I was really into it in the late 1970s when the East German women won the Olympics. I'd swim two hours before school and two or three hours afterward, and I also lifted weights.</p>
        <p>My brother who was three years older was captain of the basketball team. At one point, I could bench-press more than he could.</p>
        <p>I also flipped burgers at Burger King in high school. I learned that it was real work. My next job was locker-room attendant at the town pool, so I could get my homework done.</p>
        <p>Last year, I took part in a program developed by the State Department and Fortune in which senior female executives mentor younger women from developing countries. I mentored Farzana Chowdhury of Bangladesh. She runs the microfinance division of her country's largest bank and supervises over 1,000 people.</p>
        <p>I brought her with me to a company meeting on diversity. Part of diversity is color and gender, but it's also about style and thought and experience. Farzana had gotten divorced at an early age, which can be a challenge for women in a traditional country like Bangladesh.</p>
        <p>Hearing about her experiences gave our employees a better appreciation of the business and political challenges facing developing countries. On the other hand, she was impressed at how candid we are in this country about what management has to do to increase diversity.</p>
        <p>I was supposed to go to Bangladesh to speak to the country's business community, but I had to cancel because of the political unrest in the country. Whenever I travel on business, I send my 4-year-old son a postcard. All children love to get mail. He posts the cards on a big wall map. It's a way for us to stay connected, and he also learns geography.</p>
        <p>I have a plaque on my desk that says ''Thou Shalt Not Whine.'' On the back is a bumper sticker that says ''Well-Behaved Women Rarely Make History,'' which only I can see.</p>
        <p>When I speak to women's groups, I hit home on their financial security. They don't focus on it enough, and I understand why. People are working hard, and retirement planning is an intimidating topic. But women live longer than men. If they start focusing on their security too late, they can never catch up.</p>
        <p>Children's issues have always been my passion. When I retire, I'll continue to focus on helping underserved children have a better future. There are so many who don't get the right start. I had a very comfortable life and was not underserved at all. But there were people throughout my childhood who reached out their hands. It made a huge difference in my future. Confidence is so important. When people push you to do your best, it opens up possibilities.</p>
        <p>I had a history teacher in high school who thought I should be on a different track. He got together with a couple of other teachers and put me in all advanced-placement classes. As a result, I graduated first in my high school class and was able to graduate from college in three years and save a year's tuition.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, he sent a note through the general e-mail of our company's Web site. He had seen my name and wanted to know if I was the Kathleen Murphy he had taught 20 years ago. He just wanted to say hello and know how I was doing. He had taken such a personal interest in me. Teachers can change the face of a nation.</p>
        <p>KATHLEEN MURPHY  C.E.O., U.S. Wealth Management, ING Group</p>
        <p>BIRTH DATE  Jan. 27, 1963</p>
        <p>HOMETOWN  Wallingford, Conn.</p>
        <p>FAVORITE VACATION  Any beach</p>
        <p>LUNCH  Usually a Balance Bar, while multitasking</p>
        <p>JOBS: THE BOSS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
