<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rejecting Calls for Restraint, Gunmen Blow Up Another Sunni Mosque in Basra</title>
    <meta content="17baghdad" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/world/middleeast/17baghdad.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070621T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sunni Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosques</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Curfews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Basra (Iraq)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Samarra (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cave, Damien</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mosques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sunni Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sunni Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Curfews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E0DF123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="989" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rejecting Calls for Restraint, Gunmen Blow Up Another Sunni Mosque in Basra</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Despite Calls for Restraint, Sunni Mosque Is Bombed in Southern Iraq City</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMIEN CAVE; Ali Adeeb, Khalid al-Ansary and Ahmad Fadam contributed reporting from Baghdad, and Iraqi employees of The New York Times from Basra.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cave, Damien</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, June 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gunmen blow up another Sunni mosque in Basra after ordering police to flee, and despite curfew imposed by Iraq's central government; blast--second Sunni mosque razed in two days--suggests that Shiite militias have rejected calls for restraint from Iraqi leaders after explosions toppled revered Shiite shrine in Samarra; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hooded gunmen clad in black blew up another Sunni mosque in the southern city of Basra on Saturday after ordering the police at the mosque to flee, and despite a curfew imposed by Iraq's central government, witnesses and security officials said.</p>
        <p>The blast at the Ashrah al-Mubashra mosque in central Basra -- the second Sunni mosque razed in two days -- suggested that Shiite militias south of the capital had rejected calls for restraint from Iraqi leaders after explosions Wednesday toppled two minarets at a revered Shiite shrine in Samarra.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hooded gunmen clad in black blew up another Sunni mosque in the southern city of Basra, suggesting that Shiite militias had rejected calls for restraint.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hooded gunmen clad in black blew up another Sunni mosque in the southern city of Basra on Saturday after ordering the police at the mosque to flee, and despite a curfew imposed by Iraq's central government, witnesses and security officials said.</p>
        <p>The blast at the Ashrah al-Mubashra mosque in central Basra -- the second Sunni mosque razed in two days -- suggested that Shiite militias south of the capital had rejected calls for restraint from Iraqi leaders after explosions Wednesday toppled two minarets at a revered Shiite shrine in Samarra.</p>
        <p>The latest attack heightened tensions between Sunni and Shiite officials, and for some, seemed to confirm that Iraq's central government had lost the ability to exert much influence, not just on areas of the Kurdish north, but also on majority-Shiite strongholds in the south.</p>
        <p>''The security situation is out of control in the city,'' said Wael Abdul Latif, a Shiite former governor of Basra and member of the Iraqi List, a moderate party headed by Ayad Allawi. ''The power of the state is weak, and the forces of the Interior Ministry and Defense Ministry are confused and afraid even though handling such matters requires toughness.''</p>
        <p>The attack occurred around 8 a.m., witnesses and a Basra security official said, when at least a half-dozen men approached the mosque in four vehicles, including a minibus loaded with explosives. They said the gunmen told the Iraqi security forces guarding the mosque to leave, which they did. Then the gunmen packed the building with explosives.</p>
        <p>After the blast collapsed the building into dust and rubble, the gunmen celebrated and cheered, according to several witnesses who refused to give their names for fear of reprisals. The police, they said, did not immediately respond.</p>
        <p>Sunni religious leaders and politicians said the attack reflected the troubling militia infiltration of the Iraqi Army and police departments and the risks of relying on a mostly Shiite force to protect a country of many sects and ethnicities.</p>
        <p>''This tells us that there is a huge penetration into the security forces in Basra by militias, and this was admitted by the emergency force commander there,'' said Ahmed Abdul Ghafour al-Samaraie, who runs the Sunni Endowment, which oversees Iraq's Sunni mosques. ''If the army ignores the militia and lets them enter the mosques and do what they want then it is a catastrophe, and if the army knows what they aim at doing then it is a bigger catastrophe.''</p>
        <p>It was unclear on Saturday whether the defiance in Basra would spread. The majority-Shiite city is dominated by several rival Shiite groups, who periodically fight for control, yielding what officials and residents describe as a high degree of disorder. A government-imposed curfew that prohibited vehicles from traveling on the city's roads has not been universally enforced, residents said. On Saturday, cars sped by police checkpoints without concern.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, in other cities like Baghdad, curfews since Wednesday's attack in Samarra have largely minimized high-profile sectarian reprisals. A handful of Sunni mosques have been shot at or bombed, but there have been no reports of casualties.</p>
        <p>And on Saturday, as Iraqi security forces north of Samarra conducted raids, in which four people were killed and 20 insurgents were arrested, two of Iraq's most powerful Shiite clerics issued statements lamenting the loss of Muslim shrines rather than calling for vengeance.</p>
        <p>Hamid al-Khafaf, a spokesman for the office of Grand Ayatollah Ali al-Sistani, Iraq's most revered Shiite cleric, said: ''His eminence strongly condemns and denounces the attacks on the mosques of Talha Bin al-Zubair and al-Ashrah al-Mubashra in Basra. He calls on all citizens to prevent, as much as they can, such attacks on all shrines and mosques.''</p>
        <p>The populist cleric Moktada al-Sadr, whose Mahdi militia was blamed for much of the violence that followed last year's attack on the Samarra shrine, called on his supporters to hold a peaceful march to the site next month. His latest message was another example of Mr. Sadr's makeover from sectarian rabble-rouser to nationalist demagogue. On Saturday, there were hints that some Sunni and Shiite officials not typically aligned with Mr. Sadr would follow the pattern.</p>
        <p>Mr. Samaraie of the Sunni Endowment asked Iraqis to ''be united and love each other and block the road before those holding foreign agendas.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Latif, the Shiite former Basra governor, said Shiites were playing into the hands of Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia and other Sunni groups believed to be responsible for the Samarra attacks. ''Al Qaeda did not attack Talha or al-Ashrah mosques but those who did are following the ideas of Al Qaeda,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He added that Basra's separation from the central government's rule of law would only hurt the area.</p>
        <p>''Let's assume that one of the neighboring countries, Iran or Saudi Arabia, invaded Basra,'' he said. ''Would the militias be able to stand up against them? They won't last for an hour.''</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in Iraq, an American soldier died south of Baghdad Friday when a roadside bomb blew up near his patrol, the American military said in a statement. Three others were wounded.</p>
        <p>The American military also announced Saturday that the military identification cards of two missing soldiers abducted last month were found on June 9 in a suspected insurgent safe house near Samarra.</p>
        <p>Five days before that, the Islamic State of Iraq, an umbrella insurgent group that includes Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia, released a video showing images of the cards that belong to Specialist Alex R. Jimenez, 25, and Pvt. Byron W. Fouty, 19.</p>
        <p>It was unclear if the two soldiers had ever been at the house; American troops found computers, video production equipment, rifles and ammunition, the military said in a statement. Two soldiers were wounded by sniper fire as the troops approached the house, but when the unit arrived, they found no one inside.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 21, 2007, Thursday  An article on Saturday about the bombing of a Sunni Arab mosque near the southern Iraqi city of Basra misstated the name of the mosque. (The error was repeated in an article on Sunday about violence in Iraq.) It is the Talha Bin Obeidallah Mosque, not Talha Bin al-Zubair.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 21, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article on Saturday about the bombing of a Sunni Arab mosque near the southern Iraqi city of Basra misstated the name of the mosque. (The error was repeated in an article on Sunday about violence in Iraq.) It is the Talha Bin Obeidallah Mosque, not Talha Bin al-Zubair.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
