<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Children's Books</title>
    <meta content="Von--Drasek.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/books/review/Von-Drasek-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855331"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Children's Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E2DF1F30F934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="805" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Children's Books</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Children’s Books</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA VON DRASEK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NO TALKING</p>
        <p>By Andrew Clements.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 146 pp.</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster Books for</p>
        <p>Young Readers. $15.99.</p>
        <p>(Ages 8 to 12)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>NO TALKING.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NO TALKING</p>
        <p>By Andrew Clements.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 146 pp.</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster Books for</p>
        <p>Young Readers. $15.99.</p>
        <p>(Ages 8 to 12)</p>
        <p>Andrew Clements set the standard for the school story in 1996 with his first novel, ''Frindle,'' which went on to sell more than two million copies. The classic school story is set in elementary or middle school, and the characters are people whom readers can identify with. Most of these stories take place in Middle America, but they can also be set in an urban environment. The kids are not seriously troubled, their parents aren't dead, missing or on drugs. All of these accounts are plausible.</p>
        <p>''Frindle'' hits every note right. The protagonist is Nick, a fifth grader who, in trying to sidetrack his dictionary-loving teacher, finds himself in a battle of nerves as he tries to get a made-up word for a writing implement, frindle, into common usage. Nick succeeds beyond his wildest dreams. In the real world too, a recent online search of Wiktionary brings up frindle:</p>
        <p>Noun, frindle</p>
        <p>1. A pen.</p>
        <p>2. from novel ''Frindle'':$) frin-dle (frin' dl). n. 1. an implement used to make permanent marks on a writing material. (arbitrary coinage by Nicholas Allen $(the$) fictional character from above-mentioned book$)) see ''pen.''</p>
        <p>Clements nails everyday classroom culture. The smallest misunderstanding can skyrocket out of proportion. When you're a kid, you don't often have the whole story, or the big picture. Sometimes the grown-ups are conspiring against you.</p>
        <p>He also understands that stories can be humorous without their themes being trivial. In ''The Landry News,'' he examines what happens if the teacher not only loses control of a class but also abdicates responsibility for it. In ''Lunch Money,'' a kid obsessed with turning a profit finds a friend and a higher purpose. ''The Report Card'' digs into the world of high-stakes testing. And Clements actually has a novel titled ''The School Story.''</p>
        <p>His teachers aren't ''Charlie Brown''-type monoliths. They're individuals with their own quirks and anxieties, and they don't always agree. Clements matter-of-factly demonstrates that teachers can be petty and single-minded; a principal can apologize to a student for overreacting. His kids are cruel, kind, bullying, angry, joyful, delightful, tall, short, impulsive, thoughtful, smart, funny. He captures a broad spectrum of human behavior; the gossipy mean girl can also be surprisingly generous.</p>
        <p>Clements's uncomplicated language allows kids to read up on students in higher grade levels. If his fifth graders seem a little young, it's because he's aware that third and fourth graders are reading these books.</p>
        <p>''No Talking'' is Clements's best school story since ''Frindle.'' Teachers and students will recognize the book's noisy gang of fifth graders. This cohort is so obnoxiously raucous that teachers dread lunch duty. No, really, these kids were deafening in the first, second, third and fourth grades.</p>
        <p>The educators entrusted with lowering the ear-splitting level have nicknamed the students ''the Unshushables.'' A few teachers have already stopped making any effort to quiet them, because it's November, and in just six months the Unshushables will be off to junior high.</p>
        <p>That is until Dave Packer, a leading loudmouth, bets Lynsey Burgess, another title-holding talker, that she can't possibly be quiet. The exact throwdown goes ''If you had to shut up for five minutes, I bet the whole top of your head would explode!'' A few ''oh yeahs'' later and the wager spirals into a boys-versus-girls contest, with no talking at school or at home for two whole days. If a teacher asks a direct question, it can be answered in only three words; any words above that will be counted as points against the team.</p>
        <p>In the first period after lunch, Mrs. Marlow, a veteran science teacher, receives short, odd answers to her questions about the homework: ''I used ... math,'' ''I did ... comparing,'' ''Barrels of oil,'' ''Um ... the first day.'' There's no shouting, no questions, no painful, boisterous distractions and no whispering.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Marlow knows something is up but has no idea what. Luck turns her way when she confiscates a note from Lynsey to Dave, gloating that ''Um'' counted as a word, so he cost the boys a whole point. With that piece of information, Mrs. Marlow figures out that the kids are in some kind of competition to keep quiet. She decides to keep this piece of intelligence to herself, to allow the kids their experiment.</p>
        <p>The big question is, Do students have the right to remain silent? Clements's amusingly detached omniscient narration takes no sides in this contest of wills, not only pitting boys against girls, but also teacher against teacher, teacher against principal, and principal against students as they all negotiate their way through an eerily near-silent 48 hours. At the joyously deafening conclusion, the resemblance to an actual school is entirely coincidental, and remarkable.</p>
        <p>Lisa Von Drasek is the children's librarian of the Bank Street College of Education.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Lisa Von Drasek is the children's librarian of the Bank Street College of Education.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
