<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Experiment in Chemistry: A Blend of Oil and Water</title>
    <meta content="17nascar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/sports/othersports/17nascar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855300"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Earnhardt, Dale</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gordon, Jeff</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFDE123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="905" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Experiment in Chemistry: A Blend of Oil and Water</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nascar Watches as Team Blends Oil and Water</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIV BERNSTEIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beer cans rained down on Jeff Gordon's No. 24 Chevrolet back on April 29, when he accomplished the unthinkable, winning at Talladega Superspeedway to surpass the beloved Dale Earnhardt and move into sixth place on the career Nascar victory list. It was messy and mean, and perfectly in keeping with fans that are maniacally devoted to all things Earnhardt.</p>
        <p>But now, to the dismay of the faithful, the son of a legend has dared to link arms with Gordon. Dale Earnhardt Jr. announced Wednesday that he would race for Hendrick Motorsports beginning in 2008, and that means he and Gordon -- the anti-Earnhardt -- will be teammates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dale Earnhardt Jr. announced Wednesday that he would race for Hendrick Motorsports beginning in 2008, and that means he and Jeff Gordon  the anti-Earnhardt  will be teammates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Beer cans rained down on Jeff Gordon's No. 24 Chevrolet back on April 29, when he accomplished the unthinkable, winning at Talladega Superspeedway to surpass the beloved Dale Earnhardt and move into sixth place on the career Nascar victory list. It was messy and mean, and perfectly in keeping with fans that are maniacally devoted to all things Earnhardt.</p>
        <p>But now, to the dismay of the faithful, the son of a legend has dared to link arms with Gordon. Dale Earnhardt Jr. announced Wednesday that he would race for Hendrick Motorsports beginning in 2008, and that means he and Gordon -- the anti-Earnhardt -- will be teammates.</p>
        <p>It may be easier to imagine Budweiser and Pepsi agreeing to blend. And more palatable for some.</p>
        <p>''I think he might lose a couple fans just because of Jeff Gordon driving for Hendrick's, because there are some fans that are saying, 'There's no way,' '' said Sharon Weddington, 49, of Mooresville, N.C., a fan who stood by her driver as she stood outside JR Motorsports awaiting the announcement that made it official.</p>
        <p>It's going to be an adjustment for everyone, and a costly one for the Earnhardt fans who wish to replace all of their red No. 8 Budweiser gear if he shifts sponsors and car numbers. But what will this mean to the rivalry? And can they happily coexist under the same roof?</p>
        <p>In the giddy aftermath of the announcement, few expressed worries.</p>
        <p>''I'm happy for Junior and for Hendrick Motorsports,'' Gordon told reporters Friday as teams prepared for today's Nextel Cup race at Michigan International Speedway. ''I'm looking forward to having him as a teammate.''</p>
        <p>The same optimism was expressed last Wednesday when the announcement was made.</p>
        <p>''My job is to get the best talent out there,'' said Hendrick, the owner of the race team, who says there will be no personality problems among the all-star collection of drivers he has assembled, including the 2006 Cup champion, Jimmie Johnson. ''You know, I want to protect the brand. I want to protect Junior's image and who he is, but I want to give him the best stuff. And he's going to have to beat those guys, anyway. They are going to have to beat him, anyway, no matter if he's with our team or somewhere else.</p>
        <p>''Once again, on the racetrack, it's kind of everybody for themselves. My job is to give them the best equipment to get that done.''</p>
        <p>These days, Earnhardt and Gordon are most competitive off the track and in the marketplace. Earnhardt is the clear winner when it comes to moving merchandise. He is No. 1 among all drivers, generating about 35 percent of all sales; Gordon is a distant second.</p>
        <p>On the racetrack, their rivalry has never quite reached the level of enmity Gordon and Earnhardt inspired in the 1990s when they were winning seemingly every race and every title. The fans were a reflection of the rivalry back then; now they are the embodiment of it. On the track, Dale Jr. vs. Gordon has yet to muster the same passion.</p>
        <p>But oddly, that could possibly change when they become teammates. For the first time in his career, Earnhardt will have equipment that is identical to Gordon's at every track on every weekend. They will have the same engineering support and the same notes on how to prepare their racecars for competition each week. If Hendrick Motorsports maintains its current dominance of the sport -- its drivers have 10 victories in 14 Nextel Cup races this year -- that means Earnhardt and Gordon are likely to spend a lot of time at the front of the pack next year.</p>
        <p>As Earnhardt playfully chided Gordon during the news conference Wednesday, ''We'll be in equal equipment, so he can't make any excuses.''</p>
        <p>That can only enhance the rivalry, not weaken it. Earnhardt also sent a message to his fans allaying any fears that he might suddenly go soft on Gordon. The rivalry, such as it is, is still on.</p>
        <p>''We do have a personal competition; if you want to call it a rivalry, fine,'' Earnhardt said. ''But I like to outrun Jeff. Jeff is one of the best that's ever been in our sport. He's fun to race with and especially when you beat him, it's a good feeling. It's a good feeling when I outrun my father or anyone else of that magnitude, you know what I mean.</p>
        <p>''So I think that will still be there. I think that I'll still have that in me, just as an Earnhardt, you know, to beat Jeff Gordon.''</p>
        <p>As for Gordon, he plans to continue doing what he always does: winning races and infuriating Earnhardt's legion of fans. And he knows exactly how they will react when he does it again next year.</p>
        <p>''When it comes down to the race and who is going to win, we want it really, really bad,'' Gordon said. ''And we're willing to trade a little paint for that. Nothing's going to change with Dale Earnhardt Jr. coming to our organization, either.</p>
        <p>''The bottom line is this: When he goes out there and he starts being competitive week in and week out on a consistent basis and battling for championships and hopefully one day wins the championship for Hendrick Motorsports, all the fans are going to be following him and they're still going to be booing me.''</p>
        <p>Some things will never change.</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
