<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bosede Gbadegesin, Oreoluwa Adeyemi</title>
    <meta content="17gbadegesin" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070624T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855144"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gbadegesin, Bosede Ikeolu (Bosede Ikeolu Adeyemi)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Adeyemi, Oreoluwa Adetunji</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DA153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="244" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bosede Gbadegesin, Oreoluwa Adeyemi</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bosede Ikeolu Gbadegesin, a daughter of Felicia and Segun Gbadegesin of Mitchellville, Md., was married yesterday afternoon to Oreoluwa Adetunji Adeyemi, the son of Kemi and Solomon Adeyemi of Greensboro, N.C. The Rev. Joel Ojelade, a Baptist minister, performed the ceremony in Memorial Chapel at the University of Maryland in College Park, Md.</p>
        <p>The couple have known each other since elementary school in Ile-Ife, Nigeria. Both of their families immigrated to the United States, and the couple met again as college students in Cambridge, Mass. She was at Harvard and he was at Massachusetts Institute of Technology.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bosede Ikeolu Gbadegesin, a daughter of Felicia and Segun Gbadegesin of Mitchellville, Md., was married yesterday afternoon to Oreoluwa Adetunji Adeyemi, the son of Kemi and Solomon Adeyemi of Greensboro, N.C. The Rev. Joel Ojelade, a Baptist minister, performed the ceremony in Memorial Chapel at the University of Maryland in College Park, Md.</p>
        <p>The couple have known each other since elementary school in Ile-Ife, Nigeria. Both of their families immigrated to the United States, and the couple met again as college students in Cambridge, Mass. She was at Harvard and he was at Massachusetts Institute of Technology.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gbadegesin, 29, was, until May, a senior international lawyer at the Millennium Challenge Corporation, a government agency that provides grants to poor countries. She will begin working next month as an associate in the London office of the New York law firm White &amp; Case. She received bachelor's and law degrees from Harvard and graduated magna cum laude from both schools. Her father is a professor of philosophy at Howard University in Washington and was chairman of the philosophy department. Her mother is a special-education teacher at Moten Elementary School in Washington.</p>
        <p>Mr. Adeyemi, 30, is an investment banking associate at HSBC in London. He received both a bachelor's degree and an M.B.A. from M.I.T. His father retired as an associate professor of chemistry at North Carolina Agricultural and Technical State University in Greensboro, and is the senior pastor at Christ Apostolic-Mount Bethel Church in Greensboro.</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 24, 2007, Sunday  Because of an editing error, a report last Sunday about the marriage of Bosede Ikeolu Gbadegesin and Oreoluwa Adetunji Adeyemi referred incorrectly to the academic honor given to the bride by Harvard, from which she holds both bachelor's and law degrees. Although she did indeed graduate magna cum laude as an undergraduate, she did not do so as a law student.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 24, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, a report last Sunday about the marriage of Bosede Ikeolu Gbadegesin and Oreoluwa Adetunji Adeyemi referred incorrectly to the academic honor given to the bride by Harvard, from which she holds both bachelor's and law degrees. Although she did indeed graduate magna cum laude as an undergraduate, she did not do so as a law student.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
