<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unlikely Problem: Anchor of Rotation Drags Mets Down</title>
    <meta content="17murray" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/sports/baseball/17murray.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855273"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Glavine, Tom</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Pérez, Oliver</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE4DE123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="881" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unlikely Problem: Anchor of Rotation Drags Mets Down</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Unlikely Problem: Anchor of Rotation Drags Mets Down</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Tom Glavine doesn't get to 300 this season, the Mets aren't going anywhere -- not to the World Series, not to the National League Championship Series, not to the playoffs period.</p>
        <p>Now, it may be outrageous to suggest that the Mets cannot reach the playoffs with the team they have. Only a couple of weeks ago they were easily the best team in the league. But they have stumbled, and badly. That in itself, however, does not offer a reason why the Mets can't make the playoffs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Tom Glavine doesn’t get to 300 career wins this season, the Mets aren’t going anywhere  not to the World Series, not to the National League Championship Series, not to the playoffs period.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If Tom Glavine doesn't get to 300 this season, the Mets aren't going anywhere -- not to the World Series, not to the National League Championship Series, not to the playoffs period.</p>
        <p>Now, it may be outrageous to suggest that the Mets cannot reach the playoffs with the team they have. Only a couple of weeks ago they were easily the best team in the league. But they have stumbled, and badly. That in itself, however, does not offer a reason why the Mets can't make the playoffs.</p>
        <p>That's where the Glavine factor enters the picture. It might be outrageous even to raise the possibility that Glavine could not gain his 300th career victory this season. He has 19 or 20 starts remaining, and he has to win only 5 of them. But four weeks ago he needed five more wins, and he still needs five more wins.</p>
        <p>Worse, the last two losses of his five-game losing streak have been his worst performances of the season. Detroit battered him last Sunday, and the Yankees knocked him around yesterday in an 11-8 victory over the Mets at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>In compiling a 5-2 record in his first 10 starts, Glavine allowed 23 earned runs in 601/3 innings for a 3.43 earned run average. In his five starts since that stretch, Glavine, a 41-year-old left-hander, has given up 23 earned runs in 29 innings, a 7.14 E.R.A.</p>
        <p>During this staggering stretch for Glavine, the Mets have won 8 games and lost 13. The other starters have also struggled at times. But Glavine is the staff leader. He sets the tone; he is the role model for a staff made up mostly of pitchers still proving themselves.</p>
        <p>Oliver Pérez, John Maine and Jorge Sosa are not automatic by any means. They have all been terrific at times and have countered the preseason argument that the Mets didn't have enough pitching. Pérez, Maine and Sosa would be an unlikely trio for the Mets to march behind into October, but they have demonstrated the ability to make that march.</p>
        <p>But they won't make it without Glavine leading them and carrying the Mets' banner. As if a 7.14 E.R.A. in five starts weren't bad enough, Glavine has developed a second bad habit. His first bad habit was giving up runs early in games. Opponents scored a preponderance of runs against him in the first and second innings. Glavine's second bad habit is giving up leads the Mets have taken in early innings.</p>
        <p>In yesterday's game, Glavine committed that sin not just once, as he had done in each of his previous two starts, but three times -- count 'em: one, two, three.</p>
        <p>''You never like doing it,'' Glavine said after the game. ''I never liked my team giving me the lead and have me give it back.''</p>
        <p>The Mets scored a run in each of the first two innings against Tyler Clippard for a quick 2-0 lead. Glavine, though, gave up two runs in the Yankees' half of the second.</p>
        <p>The Mets scored another run against Clippard in the third inning for a 3-2 lead, but two batters into the Yankees' third, Glavine did it again. Bobby Abreu singled, then Alex Rodriguez crushed his major league-leading 26th home run.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to get a fastball in, and I thought I got it in,'' Glavine said. ''I think he was looking for it there and got it and didn't miss it.'' Glavine would have yet one more opportunity to hold a lead, and he would fail a third time. Ramón Castro cracked a two-run homer in the fourth inning against Clippard, putting the Mets in front, 5-4.</p>
        <p>The Mets figured to be able to score against Clippard, and they figured to get the better of the pitching matchup, probably the most lopsided in the three-game series. But Glavine did not do his part in making that likelihood a reality.</p>
        <p>Armed with the 5-4 lead, he gave up a single to Miguel Cairo with one out in the fourth, and one out later Derek Jeter drilled his fifth home run of the season. The Yankees led, 6-5, and Glavine got no more chances to relinquish a lead. Three to a customer is enough.</p>
        <p>''The one to Derek was more of a mistake,'' Glavine said, comparing that pitch to the one he threw Rodriguez. ''It was up and over the plate more.''</p>
        <p>Generally, Glavine didn't get many of his pitches where he wanted them. He threw 44 strikes and 40 balls. A good ratio is considered two strikes for every ball.</p>
        <p>''Maybe sometimes you can get away with it,'' Glavine said. ''The way these guys are swinging the bat, you're not going to have a one-to-one ratio, balls and strikes, and get away with it.''</p>
        <p>In his last five starts, all defeats for the Mets, Glavine gave up 7 runs in the first three games and 16 in the last two.</p>
        <p>''The first inning was O.K.,'' he said, dissecting his latest outing. ''After that, each inning I felt progressively more uncomfortable. You're battling each pitch to try making an adjustment and nothing's clicking. It wasn't there on consecutive pitches, which is a problem, and that's what I'll work on.''</p>
        <p>For the Mets' pennant hopes, Glavine needs to work quickly.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
