<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Cranes Are Back, And So Are the Tenants</title>
    <meta content="17sqft" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/realestate/commercial/17sqft.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855173"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SQUARE FEET: SPOTLIGHT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bellevue (Wash)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Eddie Bauer (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Neiman Marcus Stores</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shevory, Kristina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions/Western States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington/Seattle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Seattle (Wash)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (State)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E1DA153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1186" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Cranes Are Back, And So Are the Tenants</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Cranes Are Back, and So Are the Tenants</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KRISTINA SHEVORY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shevory, Kristina</byline>
      <dateline>BELLEVUE, Wash.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bellevue, Wash, is experiencing construction boom; dozen or so contruction cranes loom over works sites in city's downtown; some 2.2 million square feet of office space, some of it speculative, and more than 2,500 apartments and condominiums are under construction; Microsoft is expanding its offices in Bellevue; Eddie Bauer has chosen city for its new headquarters; Neiman Marcus is opening its first Pacific Northwest store in city; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CONSTRUCTION cranes quickly disappeared from the skyline of this affluent city near Seattle, office vacancy rates shot up as high as 28 percent and developers postponed once-ambitious projects when the dot-com boom went bust six years ago. Bellevue had become a city where no developer seemed to want to be.</p>
        <p>''Everything was too good to be true, and then reality came through,'' said Kemper Freeman, the president and chief executive of Kemper Development, one of Bellevue's largest land owners and developers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bellevue, whose fortunes rose and fell with those of the technology industry, has been staging a comeback.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CONSTRUCTION cranes quickly disappeared from the skyline of this affluent city near Seattle, office vacancy rates shot up as high as 28 percent and developers postponed once-ambitious projects when the dot-com boom went bust six years ago. Bellevue had become a city where no developer seemed to want to be.</p>
        <p>''Everything was too good to be true, and then reality came through,'' said Kemper Freeman, the president and chief executive of Kemper Development, one of Bellevue's largest land owners and developers.</p>
        <p>But this city, whose fortunes rose and fell with those of the technology industry, has been staging a comeback.</p>
        <p>Nowadays, a dozen or so construction cranes loom over work sites in Bellevue's downtown. Some 2.2 million square feet of office space, some of it speculative, and more than 2,500 apartments and condominiums are under construction, according to the Bellevue Downtown Association, a nonprofit group. Projects like Mr. Kemper's Lincoln Square, a 1.4-million-square-foot development with hotel rooms, condominiums, an office tower and a shopping mall, have been restarted and are near completion.</p>
        <p>Already, companies are planning to move into Bellevue, which is about 10 miles east of Seattle and, in the 2000 census, had a population of almost 110,000. Microsoft is expanding its offices here, while Eddie Bauer has chosen the city for its new headquarters and Neiman Marcus is opening its first Pacific Northwest store here.</p>
        <p>''If you look at the companies leasing downtown, these aren't imaginary companies,'' said Matt Terry, the director of planning and community development for Bellevue, referring to some of the dot-com businesses that once set up headquarters in the city, then quickly folded. ''That speaks well for Bellevue's economic future, and that's very different from the past.''</p>
        <p>Bellevue was riding high in the late 1990s. Dot-com companies leased thousands of square feet of space, developers rolled out plans for as many as two dozen buildings, rents soared and vacancy rates fell to less than 2 percent. Then the national recession, combined with the dot-com implosion, sent the city's office market reeling. Some companies went under or shrank, while work on projects like Lincoln Square was halted.</p>
        <p>Those days now seem a hazy memory. Attracted by a resurgence in job growth, lofty rents and one of the lowest office vacancy rates in the country, developers have been streaming back to Bellevue. An affluent population, nearby freeways and plenty of land have also sweetened the city's appeal.</p>
        <p>In the first quarter this year, office vacancy rates stood at 4.5 percent, among the lowest levels since 2000, according to a report released last month by Colliers International, a commercial real estate brokerage firm. The rate in Seattle, by comparison, was 9.3 percent in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>Tom Woodworth, a senior investment director at Schnitzer West, a Bellevue developer, said he was not surprised by Bellevue's rebound. ''This is where the jobs are and where there's developable land,'' Mr. Woodworth said.</p>
        <p>Schnitzer West had no tenants signed up last year when it began construction in downtown Bellevue on the Bravern, a 1.6 million-square-foot mixed-use complex with three floors of high-end retailers and 450 condominiums, and the Advanta Office Commons, three seven-story buildings east of downtown.</p>
        <p>Local real estate brokers had privately questioned whether the company would be able to fill its space because of competing projects under construction. But Schnitzer proved the naysayers wrong in April, when Microsoft agreed to lease a total of 1.3 million square feet in the Bravern and Advanta.</p>
        <p>The lease -- the biggest in the region, according to local real estate brokers -- made Microsoft the largest tenant downtown and gave Bellevue an added boost of confidence. Microsoft will start moving 4,000 new or existing employees into Advanta by year-end; it expects to move into the Bravern by the end of 2008.</p>
        <p>Microsoft also has plans to take over 320,000 square feet in Lincoln Square, which is expected to be completed by this summer. Lou Gellos, a company spokesman, said Microsoft was halfway through an ambitious expansion program that will add a third more space, or 3.1 million square feet. The company has been running out of room at its crowded campus located nearby in Redmond.</p>
        <p>Big leases have resurrected Bellevue's office market before. Equity Office Properties Trust, which once controlled about a third of the city's downtown office space, used cheap rents to attract Symetra Financial, a spinoff of Safeco Insurance, and drugstore.com to downtown Bellevue three years ago, a move that helped to kick-start the leasing market. Then Mr. Freeman persuaded Eddie Bauer to lease 200,000 square feet at Lincoln Square for its new headquarters. A building boom was born.</p>
        <p>Investors are also pouring money into the city. This year, there were $2.6 billion in real estate transactions, versus $34 million six years ago, according to Real Capital Analytics, a real estate consulting company. Sales prices have soared, to an average of $376 a square foot this year from $146 in 2001. In Seattle, prices average $364 a square foot, according to Real Capital.</p>
        <p>Brickman Associates, a private equity firm based in New York, bought its first building in Bellevue last fall. The company won a bidding war for Civica Office Commons, a midrise office building, paying $175.7 million, or $575 a square foot. Only 18 months earlier, Civica had been sold by Schnitzer West for $462 a square foot, or around $141 million, to Investcorp, an investment company based in New York.</p>
        <p>''Rents are really pushing in the right direction for landlords,'' said Michael Bernstein, an executive vice president and director of acquisitions at Brickman. ''We've seen a 10 percent rise in the last six months and we expect a material increase in the next six months.''</p>
        <p>RENTS in downtown Bellevue currently average $33.07 a square foot, compared with $29.29 in downtown Seattle, and are expected to climb even higher this year, according to Colliers. Gerding Edlen Development of Portland, Ore., has chosen Bellevue for its first project in Washington State, called Bellevue Towers. It will have 540 condos ranging from $400,000 for a studio to $10 million for a penthouse.</p>
        <p>Upscale retailers and restaurants have also started moving in. Neiman Marcus will open a store in Bellevue this fall; it will be the first in the Pacific Northwest for the company, which was attracted by the number of wealthy residents in the area, said Wayne Hussey, a senior vice president for store development at Neiman Marcus. For the area of King County east of Lake Washington, where Bellevue is located, the median household income was $82,228 last year, versus $57,378 in Seattle, according to Scarborough Research, a consumer research firm.</p>
        <p>For its part, Bellevue is planning to build midblock crosswalks, plant more trees and start a free bus service that will circle the downtown, to help make it more pedestrian-friendly.</p>
        <p>These improvements, however, cannot seem to come fast enough for the local businesses. ''The fear is that the investment community will not stay and other areas will become more attractive,'' said Leslie Lloyd, president of the Bellevue Downtown Association. ''We want to make sure when the boom is past, the infrastructure is in place.''</p>
        <p>SQUARE FEET: SPOTLIGHT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
