<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>European Pro Has History To Overcome</title>
    <meta content="17roberts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/sports/golf/17roberts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855279"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Selena Roberts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">PGA Tour Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2DE123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="883" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>European Pro Has History To Overcome</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">European Contender Has History to Overcome</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The American hecklers of Britain's Paul Casey have vanished with time to where the starter can announce his name at the most Yankee Doodle of golf tournaments without anyone hurling a tomato.</p>
        <p>In fact, Casey tipped his cap to a United States Open gallery cut from the Rush Limbaugh demographic when he was treated to impressive applause on the first tee at Oakmont yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Britain’s Paul Casey was once cast as an anti-American golfer. Yet now he longs for love, American-style.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The American hecklers of Britain's Paul Casey have vanished with time to where the starter can announce his name at the most Yankee Doodle of golf tournaments without anyone hurling a tomato.</p>
        <p>In fact, Casey tipped his cap to a United States Open gallery cut from the Rush Limbaugh demographic when he was treated to impressive applause on the first tee at Oakmont yesterday.</p>
        <p>He was once cast as anti-American. He now longs for love, American-style.</p>
        <p>Such adoration comes unconditionally for Tiger Woods, product of the American way. He is a dreamy symbol of self-made success with 12 major titles, of corporate excess with $100 million a year in endorsements, of celebrity status with TV ratings attached to his presence.</p>
        <p>Woods need not grovel for attention. He doesn't have to provide autographs or smiles, or banter with spectators. He can curse the course or exit in a huff, needing only his greatness to define his charisma.</p>
        <p>Woods left everyone swooning again yesterday. In a mesmerizing surge to second from 13th with a score of 69, Woods used his drivers as divining rods to find the fairways. And even on the putts he missed, the dimples of the ball came within an air kiss of the cup. On the 18th green, saliva might have been exchanged as his putt dangled on the lip for his only bogey of the day.</p>
        <p>Woods wasn't on top of the leader board, but he was lurking, two shots behind the leader, Aaron Baddeley, and one shot ahead of the third-place Casey.</p>
        <p>''Right in the mix,'' Woods said. ''I'm right there.''</p>
        <p>If the thick gallery around Woods looked like Woodstock's mosh pit, the crowd following Casey was more lounge-act size. The cozier group suited him. He could hear everything they said, all of it kind. Casey had to be pleased -- in a Sally Field kind of way -- that they liked him, they really liked him.</p>
        <p>''Get 'em, Paul,'' a man shouted from the concession stands along the first fairway.</p>
        <p>Another screamed ''66,'' a reference to the unfathomable red score Casey posted Friday, when the elite were bleeding black.</p>
        <p>''They were wishing me on to score a 63,'' Casey said after posting a solid 72 in the third round.</p>
        <p>''It was never going to happen, but it was a nice thought by them.''</p>
        <p>The warm embrace has been a long time coming. At a moment when this nation is not listed in the world's T-Mobile Fave Five, Casey is still asking to be forgiven for bashing America during his European froth at the 2004 Ryder Cup.</p>
        <p>''Oh, we properly hate them,'' he told a British tabloid in reference to the Americans.</p>
        <p>And yet, here was Casey, living stateside in Scottsdale, Ariz., as a former links star at Arizona State, as the boyfriend of an all-American girl next door, as a resident of John McCain country. But Casey sounded as if he was a lonely Brit of couth among cowboys.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes they infuriate me,'' Casey said in his bizarre 2004 rant. ''In Scottsdale, it's not so bad because the people there have traveled and you can have civilized conversations with them, but the vast majority of Americans simply don't know what is going on. They have no concept of the U.K., for instance.''</p>
        <p>Sipping from the Ryder Cup adrenaline left Casey like a barfly who spends the next day nursing a hangover and making a dozen apologies. So sorry. Meant no harm.</p>
        <p>Titleist did not forgive him. It yanked its sponsorship from Casey. He did not forgive himself, either. Casey spiraled into a depression amid deep regret. Of course he didn't hate America. Of course it had provided the stage for his career. What was he thinking?</p>
        <p>Casey slipped down the money list in 2005 and reached out to a psychologist for help in dealing with his remorse and the hecklers that dogged him on the PGA Tour.</p>
        <p>His fractured state of mind appears healed. His 66 in the second round on Friday was not the first time he flashed bouts of brilliance. At the Masters, when paired with Woods on the second day, he fired a 68.</p>
        <p>On that day, he beat Woods. At the Open? Who knows?</p>
        <p>''It's Tiger,'' Casey said. ''He usually changes things. If I'm paired with him, that will be fantastic. I've played well with him before. If I'm not paired with him, we'll have a monstrous crowd around us because everyone will be waiting for Tiger.''</p>
        <p>He grinned at the thought of being surrounded today, when he will play in the group ahead of Woods. Certainly, much of the support and adulation will be funneled toward Woods, the American crowd's celebrity son, but Casey will find a few cheers, as well.</p>
        <p>He will be playing for a European breakthrough. ''It has been too long since a European won a major,'' Casey said. But he will also be performing to mend any remaining wounds caused by his big mouth. With his gracious words about the crowds, with every tip of the cap and autograph offered, Casey is finding a nice reception.</p>
        <p>''I've never had an issue with the American fans,'' Casey said. ''And I've been having a great time over here for a long time. They've been tremendous.''</p>
        <p>What's more American than forgiveness?</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
