<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fatah, Routed in Gaza, Reinforces Hold on West Bank</title>
    <meta content="17mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/world/middleeast/17mideast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855263"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza Strip</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Bank</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fatah</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hamas</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Ian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">El-Khodary, Taghreed</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">West Bank</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Gaza Strip</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Fatah, Al</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Hamas</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Abbas, Mahmoud</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE6DE123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="674" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fatah, Routed in Gaza, Reinforces Hold on West Bank</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fatah, Routed in Gaza, Reinforces Hold on West Bank</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN FISHER and TAGHREED EL-KHODARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">El-Khodary, Taghreed; Fisher, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, June 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fatah moves to consolidate control over West Bank after being crushed in Gaza; seizes public buildings, including parliament, and prepares to swear in new government that does not include Hamas; US says it is prepared to restart direct aid to new government; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Fatah faction, crushed this week in Gaza, moved to consolidate control over the West Bank on Saturday, seizing public buildings, including the parliament, and preparing to swear in a new government that did not include its rival, Hamas.</p>
        <p>The United States, meantime, worked swiftly to shore up the weakened Palestinian president, Mahmoud Abbas of Fatah. The American consul in Jerusalem, Jacob Walles, met with Mr. Abbas on Saturday and said that, now that Hamas was not part of the government, the United States was prepared to restart direct aid -- even if the new government's control was limited to the West Bank.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fatah seized public buildings and prepared to swear in a new government that did not include Hamas in moves that seemed to solidify the split between Palestinians.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Fatah faction, crushed this week in Gaza, moved to consolidate control over the West Bank on Saturday, seizing public buildings, including the parliament, and preparing to swear in a new government that did not include its rival, Hamas.</p>
        <p>The United States, meantime, worked swiftly to shore up the weakened Palestinian president, Mahmoud Abbas of Fatah. The American consul in Jerusalem, Jacob Walles, met with Mr. Abbas on Saturday and said that, now that Hamas was not part of the government, the United States was prepared to restart direct aid -- even if the new government's control was limited to the West Bank.</p>
        <p>''I expect that we are going to be engaged with this government,'' Mr. Walles was quoted as telling The Associated Press after the meeting. He said he expected an announcement about the aid to be made within the week. The United States and other Western governments cut off direct aid to the Palestinian Authority after Hamas, classified as a terrorist organization by the United States and the European Union, won legislative elections last year.</p>
        <p>Compared with the five days of fighting between the groups, which left nearly 120 people dead, Saturday was relatively calm, although there was little stability in either Gaza or the West Bank.</p>
        <p>On Saturday morning, hundreds of Fatah supporters tried to flee Gaza through the Erez crossing into Israel. Many made it through, according to witnesses and Israeli radio, but others scattered after Hamas gunmen, who had set up roadblocks to prevent people from leaving, fired over their heads to scare them away.</p>
        <p>''We all ran away after Qassam shot at us,'' said Said Badawi, 23, a driver who said he was at the checkpoint at the time. He was referring to the Qassam Brigades, the military wing of Hamas.</p>
        <p>In the West Bank, armed Fatah supporters stormed the parliament in Ramallah as well as government buildings in Hebron and Nablus that the two groups had shared as part of the now-disbanded unity government. News agencies reported that buildings controlled by Hamas, including charity and political offices, had been seized.</p>
        <p>The seizures in the West Bank seemed to solidify the split between Palestinians after the fighting ended Thursday with Hamas, an Islamic group, in full control of the crowded coastal strip of Gaza. They also seemed to raise the risk of violence spreading to the West Bank, where the secular and nationalist Fatah is dominant, but Hamas retains pockets of strength and some armed fighters, though the Israeli Army keeps them largely underground.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, Mr. Abbas dismissed the Hamas-led unity government amid the fighting that led to Hamas's takeover of Gaza. On Saturday, he continued work to assemble a new government that would control only the West Bank, which contains an estimated 2.5 million Palestinians, compared with 1.5 million in Gaza.</p>
        <p>After the meeting with Mr. Walles, the American consul, one Palestinian official was quoted as saying that the condition for renewed financial aid was that no one with ties to Hamas be included in the government. Also on Saturday, Avi Dichter, Israel's minister for public security, told the Israeli station Channel 2 TV that Israel would allow food and other basic supplies into the Gaza Strip through border crossings.</p>
        <p>Meantime, Ismail Haniya of Hamas, who had served as the prime minister in the government that Mr. Abbas dismissed, told the French newspaper Le Figaro that Hamas would not seek to set up a rival government that claimed legitimacy over all Palestinians. ''Gaza belongs to all the Palestinian people and not just Hamas,'' he was quoted as saying.</p>
        <p>A day after looters sacked the official presidential compound and other Fatah buildings in Gaza, the house in Gaza of Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader who died in 2004, was also entered forcibly. But guards protected the house of Mr. Abbas, raising the green Hamas flag over it but preventing looting -- even leaving in place a photograph of Mr. Abbas with President Clinton at the signing of the Oslo peace accords in 1993.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
