<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CHILDREN'S BEST SELLERS: June 17, 2007</title>
    <meta content="Bestkids.paperback" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/books/bestseller/0617bestchildren.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E4DF1F30F934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1185" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CHILDREN'S BEST SELLERS: June 17, 2007</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Children’s Books</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended June 2, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books. All four children's lists appear each week on the Book Review's Web site. Publishers have provided the age designations for their best-selling children's titles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>1. BAD DOG, MARLEY!, by John Grogan. Illustrated by Richard Cowdrey2. FANCY NANCY, by Jane O’Connor 3. FANCY NANCY AND THE POSH PUPPY, by Jane O’Connor 4. FLOTSAM, by David Wiesner 5.  PIRATES DON’T CHANGE DIAPERS, by Melinda Long</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended June 2, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books. All four children's lists appear each week on the Book Review's Web site. Publishers have provided the age designations for their best-selling children's titles.</p>
        <p>05,05,06,64</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  On</p>
        <p>Week  List  PICTURE BOOKS</p>
        <p>1  5  BAD DOG, MARLEY!, by John Grogan. Illustrated by Richard Cowdrey. (HarperCollins, $16.99.) A yellow Lab's misadventures; based on Grogan's memoir. (Ages 3 to 8)</p>
        <p>2  73  FANCY NANCY, by Jane O'Connor. Illustrated by Robin Preiss Glasser. (HarperCollins, $15.99.) A glamour girl takes her family out for a night on the town. (Ages 4 to 7)</p>
        <p>3  10  FANCY NANCY AND THE POSH PUPPY, by Jane O'Connor. Illustrated by Robin Preiss Glasser. (HarperCollins, $16.99.) What kind of dog is best for a fancy girl? (Ages 4 to 7)</p>
        <p>4  31  FLOTSAM, by David Wiesner. (Clarion, $17.) The things that wash up on the beach; a story in pictures. (Ages 4 to 7)</p>
        <p>5  13  PIRATES DON'T CHANGE DIAPERS, by Melinda Long. Illustrated by David Shannon. (Harcourt, $16.) To recover treasure, a crew of pirates first has to baby-sit. (Ages 4 to 8)</p>
        <p>6  2  the wandmaker's guidebook, by Ed Masessa. Illustrated by Daniel Jankowski. (Tangerine/Scholastic, $19.99.) Proper care and manufacture of magic wands. (Ages 7 to 10)</p>
        <p>7  5  A GOOD DAY, written and illustrated by Kevin Henkes. (Greenwillow/HarperCollins, $16.99.) A bad day turns around. (Ages 3 to 5)</p>
        <p>8  5  MARS NEEDS MOMS!, written and illustrated by Berkeley Breathed. (Philomel, $16.99.) Milo appreciates his mother a little more after Martians want to take her home. (Ages 4 to 8)</p>
        <p>9  21  LIBRARY LION, by Michelle Knudsen. Illustrated by Kevin Hawkes. (Candlewick, $15.99.) A lion obeys the library rules until there's good reason not to. (Ages 5 to 8)</p>
        <p>10  2  GINGER &amp; PETUNIA, written and illustrated by Patricia Polacco. (Philomel, $16.99.) An elegant lady and her elegant pet pig. (Ages 4 to 8)</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  On</p>
        <p>Week  List  CHAPTER BOOKS</p>
        <p>1  43  NEW MOON, by Stephenie Meyer. (Megan Tingley/Little, Brown, $17.99.) A human and a vampire continue their love affair; a sequel to ''Twilight.'' (Ages 12 and up)</p>
        <p>2  1  WARRIORS FIELD GUIDE, by Erin Hunter. (HarperCollins, $15.99.) An insider's look at the ''Warriors'' fantasy series. (Ages 9 to 12)</p>
        <p>3  7  DIARY OF A WIMPY KID, written and illustrated by Jeff Kinney. (Abrams, $12.95.) The travails of adolescence, in cartoons. (Ages 9 to 12)</p>
        <p>4  3  SUMMER BALL, by Mike Lupica. (Philomel, $17.99.) At basketball camp, Danny Walker's not the best player around anymore; a sequel to ''Travel Team.'' (Ages 9 to 12)</p>
        <p>5  6  THE SIGHT, by Erin Hunter. (HarperCollins, $16.99.) Three kits study to lead their clan; first in a new ''Warriors'' series. (Ages 10 to 14)</p>
        <p>6  19  THE INVENTION OF HUGO CABRET, written and illustrated by Brian Selznick. (Scholastic, $22.99.) A novel ''in words and pictures''; an orphaned thief must decipher his father's last message. (Ages 9 to 12)</p>
        <p>7  60  THE BOOK THIEF, by Markus Zusak. (Knopf, $16.95.) A girl saves books from Nazi book-burnings and shares them with a Jewish man. (Ages 14 and up)</p>
        <p>8  5  MARLEY, by John Grogan. (HarperCollins, $16.99.) A yellow Lab's misadventures; adapted from Grogan's memoir ''Marley &amp; Me.'' (Ages 8 to 12)</p>
        <p>9  2  THE ALCHEMYST, by Michael Scott. (Delacorte, $16.99.) Twins must help an immortal alchemist protect his book of spells from an evil sorcerer. (Ages 12 and up)</p>
        <p>10  5  PANTS ON FIRE, by Meg Cabot. (HarperCollins, $16.99.) A high school girl's constant lies come back to haunt her. (Ages 12 and up)</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  On</p>
        <p>Week  List  PAPERBACK BOOKS</p>
        <p>1  42  TWILIGHT, by Stephenie Meyer. (Megan Tingley/Little, Brown, $8.99.) The new girl falls in love with a vampire. (Ages 12 and up)</p>
        <p>2  2  THE UNFORGETTABLE, by Cecily von Ziegesar. (Little, Brown, $9.99.) Prep school politics; an ''It Girl'' novel. (Ages 14 and up)</p>
        <p>3  12  ELDEST, by Christopher Paolini. (Knopf, $12.99.) Eragon in the land of elves; Book 2 in the Inheritance trilogy. (Ages 12 and up)</p>
        <p>4  8  PIRATES OF THE CARIBBEAN: AT WORLD'S END, by T. T. Sutherland. (Disney, $4.99.) The pirates form alliances for a final battle against Davey Jones; a movie tie-in. (Ages 9 to 12)</p>
        <p>5  7</p>
        <p>DON'T YOU FORGET ABOUT ME, by Cecily von Ziegesar. (Little, Brown, $10.99.) Is this the end of the Gossip Girl crew? (Ages 14 and up)</p>
        <p>6  17  MUGGLENET.COM'S WHAT WILL HAPPEN IN HARRY POTTER 7, by Ben Schoen et al. (Ulysses, $13.95.) Predictions from a leading fan Web site. (Ages 8 and up)</p>
        <p>7  16  IT's NOT EASY BEING MEAN, by Lisi Harrison. (Little, Brown, $9.99.) Actually, it's easier than you might think. A ''Clique'' novel. (Ages 14 and up)</p>
        <p>8  1  PRINCESS ACADEMY, by Shannon Hale. (Bloomsbury USA, $7.95.) A mountain girl hopes she will be chosen as the prince's bride-to-be. (Ages 9 to 12)</p>
        <p>9  1  NANCY DREW, by Daniela Burr. (Simon Spotlight, $5.99.) After moving to Hollywood, Nancy investigates the unsolved murder of an actress; a movie novelization. (Ages 9 to 12)</p>
        <p>10  9</p>
        <p>SPIDER MAN 3: THE JUNIOR NOVEL, by Jasmine Jones. (HarperEntertainment, $4.99.) Peter vs. black goo; a movie tie-in. (Ages 9 to 12)</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  On</p>
        <p>Week  List  SERIES</p>
        <p>1  1  MAXIMUM RIDE, by James Patterson. (Little, Brown, hardcover and paperback.) Winged children try to save the world. (Ages 10 and up)</p>
        <p>2  140  HARRY POTTER, by J. K. Rowling. (Levine/Scholastic, hardcover and paperback.) Trouble at Hogwarts. (Ages 10 and up)</p>
        <p>3  5  PERCY JACKSON &amp; THE OLYMPIANS, by Rick Riordan. (Miramax, hardcover and paperback.) A boy and his demigod friends battle mythological monsters. (Ages 9 to 12)</p>
        <p>4  140  JUNIE B., FIRST GRADER, by Barbara Park. Illustrated by Denise Brunkus. (Stepping Stone/Random House, hardcover and paperback.) Adventures in school. (Ages 4 to 8)</p>
        <p>5  50  PENDRAGON, by D. J. MacHale. (Aladdin, hardcover and paperback.) A teenage boy travels through time and space. (Ages 10 and up)</p>
        <p>6  32  CHARLIE BONE, by Jenny Nimmo. (Scholastic, hardcover and paperback.) A king's descendants learn magic. (Ages 9 to 12)</p>
        <p>7  140  MAGIC TREE HOUSE, by Mary Pope Osborne. Illustrated by Sal Murdocca. (Stepping Stone/Random House, hardcover and paperback.) Children travel in time. (Ages 6 to 9)</p>
        <p>8  105  THE SISTERHOOD OF THE TRAVELING PANTS, by Ann Brashares. (Delacorte, hardcover and paperback.) Four friends share magical pants. (Ages 12 and up)</p>
        <p>9  2  EMILY WINDSNAP, by Liz Kessler. (Candlewick, hardcover and paperback.) A human-mermaid hybrid juggles her worlds. (Ages 9 to 12)</p>
        <p>10  10  SEPTIMUS HEAP, by Angie Sage. (Tegen/HarperCollins, hardcover.) Lost at birth, a boy fulfills his destiny as a wizard. (Ages 9 and up)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
