<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rell Orders Inspections Of Trees on Parkways</title>
    <meta content="17weekctCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/17weekct.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855045"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Meadowlands Sports Complex (East Rutherford, NJ)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westport (Conn)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Stamford (Conn)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Haven (Conn)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Wilbur Cross Parkway (Conn)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Merritt Parkway (Conn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Clairol</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Procter &amp; Gamble Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Amtrak (National Railroad Passenger Corp)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metro-North Commuter Railroad</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Transit</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rell, M Jodi (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/New Haven</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0D7143FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="938" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rell Orders Inspections Of Trees on Parkways</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Week in Connecticut</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF HOLTZ</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Week column; Connecticut Gov M Jodi Rell, following accident in which couple died when tree fell on car on Merritt Parkway in Westport, orders State Department of Transportation to set up tree inspections along Merritt and Wilbur Cross Parkways; Procter &amp; Gamble announces that Clairol hair color manufacturing plant in Stamford will close by early 2010 and most of 415 production jobs will be eliminated; Connecticut Department of Transportation announces it is working with Amtrak, Metro-North and New Jersey Transit to provide train service from New Haven to Meadowlands in East Rutherford, NJ, for Giants and Jets home games in two years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. M. Jodi Rell ordered the State Department of Transportation last Monday to set up tree inspections along the Merritt and Wilbur Cross Parkways after a New York couple were killed last weekend when a tree fell on their car on the Merritt in Westport.</p>
        <p>The driver, Joseph J. Stavola, 46, and his wife, Jeanne C. Serocke, 44, of Pelham, were killed as they were traveling south near Exit 42 about 9:15 p.m. on June 9, said Lt. J. Paul Vance, a state police spokesman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. M. Jodi Rell ordered the State Department of Transportation last Monday to set up tree inspections along the Merritt and Wilbur Cross Parkways after a New York couple were killed last weekend when a tree fell on their car on the Merritt in Westport.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. M. Jodi Rell ordered the State Department of Transportation last Monday to set up tree inspections along the Merritt and Wilbur Cross Parkways after a New York couple were killed last weekend when a tree fell on their car on the Merritt in Westport.</p>
        <p>The driver, Joseph J. Stavola, 46, and his wife, Jeanne C. Serocke, 44, of Pelham, were killed as they were traveling south near Exit 42 about 9:15 p.m. on June 9, said Lt. J. Paul Vance, a state police spokesman.</p>
        <p>Lieutenant Vance said the couple's children, whose names and ages were not given, were taken to Norwalk Hospital, where they were treated for nonlife-threatening injuries.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Rell's order came at the request of Westport's first selectman, Gordon F. Joseloff, who said last Tuesday that another tree fell on the parkway in the same area on May 5, but did not cause any injuries.</p>
        <p>''I asked her to take a look to see if there's anything that we're not doing that we could be doing,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Adam Liegot, a spokesman for the governor, said that while the transportation department regularly inspects trees along the two highways, ''this incident clearly shows that more needs to be done.''</p>
        <p>Kevin Nursick, a spokesman for the transportation department, said the tree that fell last weekend was a white pine that was two feet in diameter with a trunk that was 33 feet from the shoulder of the road. ''There were no overt signs that it was compromised structurally,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nursick said the department had 850 maintenance workers who every day look for potential problems, including hazardous trees, along state roads. He said about 200 trees have been cut down along the Merritt in the last year and a half.</p>
        <p>Clairol to Leave Plant In Stamford by 2010</p>
        <p>Clairol's manufacturing plant in Stamford, which has made hair coloring products since 1940, will close by early 2010, the company announced June 7.</p>
        <p>Brent Miller, a spokesman for Proctor &amp; Gamble, which owns Clairol, said the company was downsizing.</p>
        <p>''We've decided to focus on fewer and bigger sites,'' he said. ''We have operations all over the world, and as a global company, we have to look at where we can generate the most efficiency in scale.''</p>
        <p>There are 615 people working at the Stamford plant, with 415 on the production line and the rest in administrative jobs, Mr. Miller said. He said the administrative workers would be given the opportunity to transfer to other Proctor &amp; Gamble offices.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller said most of the production jobs would be eliminated. He said those workers losing their jobs would be offered severance packages. He said about 180 of the workers would be eligible for retirement.</p>
        <p>Stamford's mayor, Dannel P. Malloy, said Clairol's departure was part of the final phase of the city's transition from manufacturing to other types of industries. He said it would not have an impact on the city's economy.</p>
        <p>''You feel bad for people who are losing their jobs,'' he said. ''But we're bringing in more companies than those that are closing; more jobs are coming than leaving.''</p>
        <p>Proctor &amp; Gamble plans to sell the 30-acre plant on the city's East Side, Mr. Miller said. ''It's really prime real estate in Stamford,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller said the city had treated the company well. ''We look forward to how we can best support the community for the next two and a half years and get to the best possible outcome that we can come to,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Trains to Meadowlands Planned for 2009</p>
        <p>Giants and Jets fans in the state will be able to take a train to games at the Meadowlands starting in 2009.</p>
        <p>The State Department of Transportation announced last Monday that it was working with Amtrak, Metro-North and New Jersey Transit to provide train service from New Haven to the Meadowlands in East Rutherford, N.J., for Giants and Jets home games in two years.</p>
        <p>Under the plan, the trains would use Metro-North tracks to reach New Rochelle, then switch to Amtrak tracks for the trip into Pennsylvania Station in New York and to Secaucus, N.J. Fans would have to take a shuttle train from the Secaucus Junction station to a new station now under construction at the Meadowlands.</p>
        <p>Gene Colonese, rail administrator for the State Transportation Department, said that while he did not have a projection of how many riders were likely to use the service, he believed there was a need for it.</p>
        <p>''There's always a demand to take trains to sporting events because of the traffic congestion associated with them,'' he said.</p>
        <p>New Jersey Transit trains would have to be used for the entire trip, because Metro-North trains are not equipped to run on Amtrak's tracks, Mr. Colonese said.</p>
        <p>Because of a limited number of available trains, the service would most likely operate only for games that start Sundays at 1 p.m., Mr. Colonese said. The cost has not been determined. The trip would take about 90 minutes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Colonese said the service would begin even if the new stadium planned for the Giants and Jets was not ready by the 2009 season.</p>
        <p>''The new station will be integrated into the new stadium,'' he said. ''But it's still within walking distance of the current stadium.''</p>
        <p>Pat Hanlon, a spokesman for the Giants, said in a statement that the trains would help during construction, when 5,000 parking spaces will be lost.</p>
        <p>''We have strongly encouraged our fans to car-pool, and obviously mass transportation is another way to lessen the impact of the loss of parking,'' he said.</p>
        <p>THE WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
