<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Matsuzaka, Not Bonds, Is Monster at Fenway</title>
    <meta content="17redsox" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070619T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855292"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E0DE123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="739" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Matsuzaka, Not Bonds, Is Monster at Fenway</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, June 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Start with one of America's most hitter-friendly stadiums, Fenway Park, and add Barry Bonds, one of baseball's most productive sluggers. What do you get?</p>
        <p>On this Saturday, the 36,381 fans and a national television audience got seven innings of excellent pitching from Daisuke Matsuzaka of the Red Sox and Matt Cain of the Giants. They were as brilliant as the late-afternoon sunshine that made the nation's oldest ballpark glow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Start with one of America's most hitter-friendly stadiums, Fenway Park, and add Barry Bonds, one of baseball's most productive sluggers. What do you get?</p>
        <p>On this Saturday, the 36,381 fans and a national television audience got seven innings of excellent pitching from Daisuke Matsuzaka of the Red Sox and Matt Cain of the Giants. They were as brilliant as the late-afternoon sunshine that made the nation's oldest ballpark glow.</p>
        <p>And because Boston's Manny Ramírez hit a home run over the Green Monster in left field with one out in the fourth inning, the first-place Red Sox earned a 1-0 victory and remained eight and a half games ahead of the second-place Yankees in the American League East.</p>
        <p>''I love it,'' Matsuzaka said through an interpreter when asked about the challenge of a close affair. ''I was able to reach back and reach inside myself and display a side of myself that I haven't been able to show. That said to me, hopefully, that I'm heading in a new and good direction.''</p>
        <p>Matsuzaka (8-5) is already in a pretty good direction, perhaps on track to be named rookie of the year, possibly for 20 victories. Although his previous three starts were defeats, Matsuzaka gave up only two earned runs in each of the last two games.</p>
        <p>Against the Giants, he gave up three hits, had eight strikeouts and three walks, and hit one batter. He was replaced for the eighth inning by Hideki Okajima. Jonathan Papelbon worked the ninth for his 16th save.</p>
        <p>Matsuzaka was surprised to be taken out after 112 pitches.</p>
        <p>''I was able to protect our slim and precious one-run lead,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Cain (2-7) also pitched seven innings, giving up only three hits. Ramírez hit his home run on a 2-1 slider.</p>
        <p>Bonds, 42, making his first trip this weekend to Fenway, went hitless in three at-bats. He was also walked intentionally. His career home run total remained at 747, eight behind the leader, Hank Aaron.</p>
        <p>Bonds was retired twice in critical situations, with men on first and second and nobody out in the sixth and eighth innings. In the sixth, Matsuzaka got him to ground out. In the eighth, Bonds struck out looking against Okajima.</p>
        <p>''That was the biggest pitch,'' Okajima said through an interpreter. The at-bat began with a 2-0 count that caused the Red Sox' pitching coach, John Farrell, to visit the mound. ''Just challenge him,'' Okajima said Farrell told him.</p>
        <p>Bonds did not speak after the game, but Giants Manager Bruce Bochy said, ''I think guys do press a little bit to get the club going and I think that might be the case now.''</p>
        <p>Bonds has hit only two home runs since May 8. He has 13 this season. He is a designated hitter this weekend in an American League park.</p>
        <p>The interleague series is the first meeting of these teams since the 1912 World Series, when the Giants played in New York and Fenway Park was new. The Giants' last visit to this park was in 1915, when they played the Boston Braves, who shared Fenway with the Red Sox.</p>
        <p>For the first two games, the fan reaction to Bonds has been muted, not nearly as hostile as the greeting for Alex Rodriguez of the Yankees two weeks ago. Rodriguez has a contentious history with the Red Sox and their fans, and he plays for a rival in the A.L. East.</p>
        <p>Bonds plays for the last-place team in the National League West. Boston fans seemed to regard Bonds more as a celebrity curiosity. Some of them wore asterisks on their shirts to suggest that any record he sets will be tainted by accusations that he has used steroids.</p>
        <p>Others held up signs with asterisks. Some booed him and chanted ''Ster-oids!'' when he batted. But the booing was almost as loud on Friday as it was on Saturday when the Red Sox chose to walk Bonds intentionally with first base open and a man on second with two outs.</p>
        <p>Some fans cheered him and wore Giants clothing. After Matsuzaka retired Bonds in the sixth inning, he loaded the bases with two outs but struck out Rich Aurilia, who took a 3-2 pitch on the outside part of the plate.</p>
        <p>Referring to facing Bonds, Matsuzaka said: ''He emitted a great aura. I couldn't avoid having to challenge him. At the same time, I felt I wanted to challenge him.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 19, 2007, Tuesday  A sports article in some copies on Sunday about Boston's 1-0 victory against San Francisco referred incorrectly to the history of the interleague series between the Red Sox and the Giants. This was their first meeting since June 2004 -- not since the World Series in 1912, the year they last played each other at Fenway Park.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 19, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A sports article in some copies on Sunday about Boston's 1-0 victory against San Francisco referred incorrectly to the history of the interleague series between the Red Sox and the Giants. This was their first meeting since June 2004 -- not since the World Series in 1912, the year they last played each other at Fenway Park.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
