<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sun's Success Assists Casino and W.N.B.A.</title>
    <meta content="17mainctCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/17mainct.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855037"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Connecticut Sun</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mohegan Sun Casino</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Women's National Basketball Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moseley, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E1D7143FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="978" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sun's Success Assists Casino and W.N.B.A.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sun’s Success Assists Casino and W.N.B.A.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT MOSELEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moseley, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>UNCASVILLE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on success of Connecticut Sun, Women's National Basketball Assn team that came under heavy criticism for allowing casino to buy it; team, whose attendance has continued to grow at Mohegan Sun Arena in Connecticut, is considered one of most successful franchises in league; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOUR years ago, the Women's National Basketball Association came under heavy criticism for allowing a casino to buy a team.</p>
        <p>Now that team, the Connecticut Sun, has a winning tradition and a devoted fan base, and is considered one of the most successful franchises in the league.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Connecticut Sun, owned by the Mohegan Sun Casino, is piling up wins and filling seats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOUR years ago, the Women's National Basketball Association came under heavy criticism for allowing a casino to buy a team.</p>
        <p>Now that team, the Connecticut Sun, has a winning tradition and a devoted fan base, and is considered one of the most successful franchises in the league.</p>
        <p>Attendance has grown every year at the 10,000-seat Mohegan Sun Arena, inside the casino. Last season, the Sun averaged 7,380 fans a game, up from 6,025 in 2003, a 22 percent increase. After three home games this season, average attendance was up sharply, to 8,179 a game.</p>
        <p>The team has posted four straight winning seasons and gone to the league finals two of the last three years. It was off to a 4-4 start this season after a road loss on Wednesday night to the Minnesota Lynx, and will play at home again on June 17 against the Chicago Sky and on Wednesday against the New York Liberty.</p>
        <p>The on- and off-the-court success of the Sun -- the state's only major-league professional sports team -- suggests that, under the right circumstances, sports and gambling can co-exist.</p>
        <p>''There was a little uproar early on, but the reality is we don't offer sports betting here, and you don't have to go through the casino to get to the arena,'' said Mitchell G. Etess, 49, the chief executive of the team and the casino.</p>
        <p>''Casinos aren't this pariah industry anymore,'' he said. ''We're in the hospitality business, and people can deal with the gaming. If they don't want to take the kids to the casino, they don't have to.''</p>
        <p>W.N.B.A. teams have salary caps -- top players are paid $93,000, and team payroll cannot exceed $728,000 -- but the casino has yet to make a profit from the team. Etess would not reveal the extent of the financial losses, beyond saying that the team hoped to make a profit in the next two to three years, but the ancillary revenue and publicity the team has brought to the casino have proved beneficial, he said.</p>
        <p>''It's still a very positive driver of public relations and nonbasketball activities, such as eating and shopping,'' Etess said. ''It creates a tremendous amount of awareness for us. The team really established the fact that the Mohegan Sun is an entertainment company as opposed to just a casino.''</p>
        <p>Etess looked to capitalize on the popularity of the University of Connecticut women's basketball team -- now a five-time national champion -- and the casino's new arena when he approached the Mohegan Tribal Council in 2003 about buying the Orlando Miracle and relocating it to Uncasville.</p>
        <p>At first, he was content to schedule concerts and preseason games by the Boston Celtics in the arena, also envisioning some college basketball doubleheaders. Then the league changed its rules to allow franchises to be located outside of National Basketball Association markets and for owners to come from outside the N.B.A.</p>
        <p>''I started thinking: 'Hmm, how much could it be? Maybe we should think about it,' '' Etess recalled.</p>
        <p>The tribe signed off on the idea, and for $10 million, the Sun became the first independently owned and operated team in the league. The whole process took less than two months to complete, but the hard part for Etess, a neophyte to professional sports, was pulling everything together for the 2003 season opener in less than four months.</p>
        <p>''It was a learning process for all of us,'' said Nykesha Sales, the former UConn star who is the franchise scoring leader. ''We had to all help each other figure out how the program needed to be run. There were a lot of things that made you tilt your head sideways and think: Well, that doesn't make much sense.''</p>
        <p>Added all-star guard Katie Douglas: ''Being the first team without an N.B.A. model was a little hectic, but they did the best they could and treated us first-class. You have the Mohegan Sun casino backing you, so things can't be too bad.''</p>
        <p>The first player the Sun acquired was Rebecca Lobo, another former UConn star. The trade was made to jump-start attendance, but many viewed it as a double-edged sword. ''I think everybody was worried in the beginning that we just wanted to be UConn II,'' Etess said.</p>
        <p>Since then, the Sun has forged its own identity, and only two players on the current roster played for UConn (Sales and forward Asjha Jones, in her fifth season).</p>
        <p>''When I came here, there were two different fan bases,'' Jones said. ''Early on in the team's history, the fans came with UConn gear on, but now they wear Sun gear.''</p>
        <p>That fan base is a mix of young families and seniors, and is approximately 45 percent male, said the team's general manager, Chris Sienko, 41. The W.N.B.A. and the casino share one demographic target: patrons 50 and older.</p>
        <p>One such fan, Sonny Aquino, 62, from Fairfield, took in the Sun's recent home opener, a nationally televised 86-68 loss to the Los Angeles Sparks. With him were his son and grandson, Frank Sr., 40, and Frankie, 16. He said they go to approximately half of the 17 homes games each year and combine the trip with gambling.</p>
        <p>''It's a nice night out,'' Mr. Aquino said. ''It's like a family event for us.''</p>
        <p>Jogita Khilnani, 34, of New Canaan sat with her parents in a free courtside seat, a perk for being a frequent casino patron. ''I was here to gamble, and I just thought I'd drop in,'' she said. ''My parents wanted to see the game, and it's cheaper than gambling.''</p>
        <p>In recent years, the W.N.B.A. teams in Houston, Los Angeles, Washington and Chicago have followed the Sun's lead and become independently owned. Donna Orender, president of the W.N.B.A., said this shows that the league is healthy.</p>
        <p>''We're going into our 11th season,'' she said at the Sun-Sparks game. ''I think that says a lot.''</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
