<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mayor's Turbulent Evening Is Big Case for Small Court</title>
    <meta content="17brawl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/17brawl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855255"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Healy, Jerramiah T</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E0DF123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1107" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mayor's Turbulent Evening Is Big Case for Small Court</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mayor’s Turbulent Evening Is Big Case for Small Court</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN MILLER</byline>
      <dateline>BRADLEY BEACH, N.J., June 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here in this shore town, a land of funnel cake and miniature golf, the talk is not of ocean tides and sand flies but of pepper spray and handcuffs. Not of saltwater taffy and lazy afternoons with Stephen King, but of motions of emergent relief and mornings with a judge.</p>
        <p>On one side of the divide is Jerramiah T. Healy, Jersey City's mayor, who says he was roughed up by a Bradley Beach policeman. On the other are the police, who claim that a disorderly mayor inserted himself into a situation in which he did not belong.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jerramiah T. Healy, the mayor of Jersey City, will stand trial on Monday in a case that pits him against police in Bradley Beach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here in this shore town, a land of funnel cake and miniature golf, the talk is not of ocean tides and sand flies but of pepper spray and handcuffs. Not of saltwater taffy and lazy afternoons with Stephen King, but of motions of emergent relief and mornings with a judge.</p>
        <p>On one side of the divide is Jerramiah T. Healy, Jersey City's mayor, who says he was roughed up by a Bradley Beach policeman. On the other are the police, who claim that a disorderly mayor inserted himself into a situation in which he did not belong.</p>
        <p>When the trial opens on Monday morning, the matter will have dragged out a year and a day since the encounter between the mayor and the policeman.</p>
        <p>In all, there will be 39 pieces of evidence. Twenty witnesses, including the daughter of a local councilman, are on notice that they may be called to testify in a shabby courtroom with folding chairs and a fraying carpet held down by duct tape. There will even be opening and closing statements from lawyers -- a rarity for municipal court -- but no jury. Testimony is to be spread over three days, but that may not be enough.</p>
        <p>''I've had Superior Court cases with a lot less witnesses,'' Jason Shamy, the municipal prosecutor, said after a recent hearing. He waved to his opposing counsel, James Fagen. ''I think Fagen has had capital cases with less witnesses.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Healy has been charged with disorderly conduct, resisting arrest and obstruction of justice. If he receives the maximum penalty for all the charges, he could be imprisoned for a year and a month and owe $2,500 in fines, Mr. Shamy said, although he acknowledged that the punishment could be a good bit short of that.</p>
        <p>It all began about 2 a.m. on a Saturday last June, when Mr. Healy, 56, left his sister's bar, Barry's Tavern, after a meal and several Miller Lites. There in a parking lot near the bar, Mr. Healy said, he saw a man jumping on the hood of a car with a woman inside. He said that he tried to calm the situation, and that when the police came, he tried to explain what had happened.</p>
        <p>But he said that a police officer, Terry Browning, pushed him to the ground, handcuffed him, and sprayed a chemical in both eyes. He also said Officer Browning pushed his wife, Maureen, to the ground, injuring a finger and an ankle.</p>
        <p>But the police have a very different version. They say Mr. Healy repeatedly inserted himself into their investigation into the dispute, even after he was told to back off. Eventually, they said, Mr. Healy resisted arrest and ''became disorderly.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Healy, a former assistant Hudson County prosecutor and municipal court chief judge in Jersey City, said that his father was a bar owner who died trying to break up a fight, and, that in this case, he was confident he would prevail.</p>
        <p>''I've professed my innocence from Day 1,'' he said in a recent interview. ''I've told the truth about this thing from Day 1. I did nothing wrong. I did nothing illegal.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Healy filed a countercharge accusing the officer of abusing him, but the Monmouth County prosecutor threw it out in December.</p>
        <p>This is not the first time Mr. Healy has been at the center of bizarre late-night incidents, or even the first time he has clashed with the police in Bradley Beach. Privately, some officials in Jersey City and long-time allies question the mayor's wisdom in pursuing a case that has opened up questions about his past.</p>
        <p>In 2004, when he was a councilman running for mayor, Mr. Healy was photographed naked on the front porch of his house in Jersey City -- he says he did not remember how he got there -- after drinking what he said were ''six to eight beers'' at a local bar.</p>
        <p>The photos eventually made their way onto the Internet, creating a brief uproar, but Mr. Healy went on to win. Nor did the winning stop there. Just last week, he was elected chairman of the storied Hudson County Democratic Organization.</p>
        <p>In August 1999, Mr. Healy, who owns a home in Bradley Beach, was charged with resisting arrest and obstructing justice, according to court records. David Dellett, a neighbor of Mr. Healy's in Bradley Beach, told The Jersey Journal last year about the 1999 incident, in which he saw four policemen wrestle down a naked Mr. Healy on his porch.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dellett said Mr. Healy would often hold loud parties that featured the playing of ukuleles and the singing of Irish tunes. Last week, a second neighbor, who asked not to be identified, also reported witnessing the same incident on the porch, adding that the mayor had unsuccessfully tried to hold onto a towel wrapped around him.</p>
        <p>Court records show that Mr. Healy pleaded guilty to a minor disorderly person charge and paid $130 in fines and court costs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Healy and his lawyers said they are not concerned about these cases coming up at trial. ''It's totally extraneous,'' said Joseph V. Kealy Jr., one of his three lawyers. ''Totally irrelevant. The only issue is what happened on the night in the lot next to Barry's bar.''</p>
        <p>In this latest incident, the officer at the center of the dispute, Terry Browning, who lives in neighboring Neptune with his mother, will be called as a witness.</p>
        <p>''I know my son,'' said his mother, Doris Browning. ''I know he didn't do anything he shouldn't have done.''</p>
        <p>She also said her son told her that the mayor was trying to throw his weight around on the night of the arrest and asked the officer, ''Do you know who I am?'' Mr. Healy denied making such an assertion.</p>
        <p>Officer Browning has been the subject of legal challenges in the past. In 2004, he was accused of driving his squad car with the lights turned off when he ran into a bicyclist named Israel Sanchez, who had just left Barry's Tavern.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sanchez settled the case with the officer and the Bradley Beach police earlier this year for ''north of $1,000, but not a heck of a lot,'' said his lawyer, James W. Taylor. Barry's Tavern helped pick up the lawyer's bills.</p>
        <p>In the end, even Mr. Healy's lawyers acknowledge that not much good will come from the case.</p>
        <p>''There are going to be no winners here,'' Mr. Kealy said. ''We are certain that the mayor will have been exonerated. But nobody wins here, the mayor -- Mr. Healy -- the officer in the case, the town of Bradley Beach. No one.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
