<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BEST SELLERS: June 17, 2007</title>
    <meta content="Besthard.fiction" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855314"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E4DF1F30F934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1245" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BEST SELLERS: June 17, 2007</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended June 2, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>THE DIANA CHRONICLES, by Tina Brown. (Doubleday, $27.50.) The former New Yorker editor perceptively highlights the media's role in the sordid domestic drama that pitted the Princess of Wales against Britain's royal family.</p>
        <p>NINE, by Andrzej Stasiuk. Translated by Bill Johnston. (Harcourt, $23.) This Polish ''existential crime novel'' vividly evokes the scamming subsistence culture of the Warsaw underworld.</p>
        <p>LONG TIME LEAVING: Dispatches From Up South, by Roy Blount Jr. (Knopf, $25.) Literate, good-humored essays on Southern culture.</p>
        <p>THE PERFECT MAN, by Naeem Murr. (Random House; paper, $13.95.) The British-Indian hero of this novel comes of age in racist 1950s Missouri.</p>
        <p>THE AGE OF ABUNDANCE: How Prosperity Transformed America's Politics and Culture, by Brink Lindsey. (Collins/HarperCollins, $26.95.) Affluence breeds libertarianism, Lindsey argues.</p>
        <p>RELIGIOUS LITERACY: What Every American Needs to Know -- and Doesn't, by Stephen Prothero. (HarperSanFrancisco, $24.95.) A professor laments our declining knowledge of religion.</p>
        <p>THE SUSHI ECONOMY: Globalization and the Making of a Modern Delicacy, by Sasha Issenberg. (Gotham, $26.) Sushi, and particularly the bluefin tuna, as an example of ''good'' globalization.</p>
        <p>THE ZEN OF FISH: The Story of Sushi, From Samurai to Supermarket, by Trevor Corson. (HarperCollins, $24.95.) An often amusing history.  THE COLLECTED STORIES, by Leonard Michaels. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $26.) Larky and profane, Michaels's sexually kinetic short stories stand alongside those of his best Jewish contemporaries, Grace Paley and Philip Roth.</p>
        <p>SYLVIA, by Leonard Michaels. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux; paper, $13.) A fictionalized memoir, first published in 1992, about Michaels's first wife, Sylvia Bloch, whose troubled life ended in suicide.</p>
        <p>TRAVELS WITH HERODOTUS, by Ryszard Kapuscinski. Translated by Klara Glowczewska. (Knopf, $25.) The only memoir by the Pole who was perhaps the world's best literary journalist.The full reviews of these and other recent books are on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended June 2, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>THE DIANA CHRONICLES, by Tina Brown. (Doubleday, $27.50.) The former New Yorker editor perceptively highlights the media's role in the sordid domestic drama that pitted the Princess of Wales against Britain's royal family.</p>
        <p>NINE, by Andrzej Stasiuk. Translated by Bill Johnston. (Harcourt, $23.) This Polish ''existential crime novel'' vividly evokes the scamming subsistence culture of the Warsaw underworld.</p>
        <p>LONG TIME LEAVING: Dispatches From Up South, by Roy Blount Jr. (Knopf, $25.) Literate, good-humored essays on Southern culture.</p>
        <p>THE PERFECT MAN, by Naeem Murr. (Random House; paper, $13.95.) The British-Indian hero of this novel comes of age in racist 1950s Missouri.</p>
        <p>THE AGE OF ABUNDANCE: How Prosperity Transformed America's Politics and Culture, by Brink Lindsey. (Collins/HarperCollins, $26.95.) Affluence breeds libertarianism, Lindsey argues.</p>
        <p>RELIGIOUS LITERACY: What Every American Needs to Know -- and Doesn't, by Stephen Prothero. (HarperSanFrancisco, $24.95.) A professor laments our declining knowledge of religion.</p>
        <p>THE SUSHI ECONOMY: Globalization and the Making of a Modern Delicacy, by Sasha Issenberg. (Gotham, $26.) Sushi, and particularly the bluefin tuna, as an example of ''good'' globalization.</p>
        <p>THE ZEN OF FISH: The Story of Sushi, From Samurai to Supermarket, by Trevor Corson. (HarperCollins, $24.95.) An often amusing history.  THE COLLECTED STORIES, by Leonard Michaels. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $26.) Larky and profane, Michaels's sexually kinetic short stories stand alongside those of his best Jewish contemporaries, Grace Paley and Philip Roth.</p>
        <p>SYLVIA, by Leonard Michaels. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux; paper, $13.) A fictionalized memoir, first published in 1992, about Michaels's first wife, Sylvia Bloch, whose troubled life ended in suicide.</p>
        <p>TRAVELS WITH HERODOTUS, by Ryszard Kapuscinski. Translated by Klara Glowczewska. (Knopf, $25.) The only memoir by the Pole who was perhaps the world's best literary journalist.The full reviews of these and other recent books are on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>05,05,06,64</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  Last  On</p>
        <p>Week  Week  List  FICTION</p>
        <p>1  1  2  A THOUSAND SPLENDID SUNS, by Khaled Hosseini. (Riverhead, $25.95.) A friendship between two women in Afghanistan against the backdrop of 30 years of war; from the author of ''The Kite Runner.''</p>
        <p>2  2  2  THE OVERLOOK, by Michael Connelly. (Little, Brown, $21.99.) The Los Angeles detective Harry Bosch tangles with the F.B.I. and Homeland Security as he tries to solve the case of a murdered physicist with access to radioactive materials.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>1  THE GOOD GUY, by Dean Koontz. (Bantam, $27.) In a case of mistaken identity, an ordinary man finds himself at the center of a murder plot.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>29  FOR ONE MORE DAY, by Mitch Albom. (Hyperion, $21.95.) A troubled man gets a last chance to reconnect and restore his relationship with his dead mother.</p>
        <p>5  3  4  THE 6TH TARGET, by James Patterson and Maxine Paetro. (Little, Brown, $27.99.) In San Francisco, children are disappearing, and Detective Lindsay Boxer and the Women's Murder Club investigate.</p>
        <p>6  4  3  INVISIBLE PREY, by John Sandford. (Putnam, $26.95.) The Minneapolis detective Lucas Davenport finds connections between the murder of several elderly residents and a political scandal.</p>
        <p>7  6  7  THE CHILDREN OF HÃRIN, by J. R. R. Tolkien. Edited by Christopher Tolkien. Illustrated by Alan Lee. (Houghton Mifflin, $26.) In Middle-earth, an evil lord wants to destroy his rival's children.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>1  SACRIFICE, by Karen Traviss. (Del Rey/Ballantine, $25.95.) Jacen, the son of Han and Leia Solo, must murder someone close to him to become a Sith lord; a ''Star Wars'' novel.</p>
        <p>9  5  3  BAD LUCK AND TROUBLE, by Lee Child. (Delacorte, $26.) Jack Reacher must discover who is hunting down members of a team of former military investigators.</p>
        <p>10  7  5  THE YIDDISH POLICEMEN'S UNION, by Michael Chabon. (HarperCollins, $26.95.) A detective investigates a neighbor's murder in a Jewish settlement in Alaska.</p>
        <p>11  8  6  SIMPLE GENIUS, by David Baldacci. (Warner, $26.99.) Two former Secret Service agents investigate a scientist's murder while one battles her own demons.</p>
        <p>12  12  13  NINETEEN MINUTES, by Jodi Picoult. (Atria, $26.95.) The aftermath of a high school shooting reveals the fault lines in a small New Hampshire town.</p>
        <p>13*  9  5  RANT, by Chuck Palahniuk. (Doubleday, $24.95.) The ''oral biography'' of a serial killer.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>1  LAWMAN, by Diana Palmer. (HQN, $24.95.) An F.B.I. agent discovers that the trail of the escaped child predator he is tracking leads in an unexpected direction.</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>2  FALLING MAN, by Don DeLillo. (Scribner, $26.) The effect of 9/11 on a middle-class Manhattan family.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  Last  On</p>
        <p>Week  Week  List  NONFICTION</p>
        <p>1  1  2  THE ASSAULT ON REASON, by Al Gore. (Penguin Press, $25.95.) How the Bush administration has degraded the political environment through secrecy, fear and the rejection of fact-based reasoning.</p>
        <p>2  2  2  THE REAGAN DIARIES, by Ronald Reagan. Edited by Douglas Brinkley. (HarperCollins, $35.) Selections from the 40th president's daily White House diaries.</p>
        <p>3  4  5  GOD IS NOT GREAT, by Christopher Hitchens. (Twelve, $24.99.) Religion as a malignant force in the world.</p>
        <p>4  3  8  EINSTEIN, by Walter Isaacson. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $32.) A biography based on newly released personal letters.</p>
        <p>5  6  16  A LONG WAY GONE, by Ishmael Beah. (Sarah Crichton/Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $22.) A former child soldier from Sierra Leone describes his drug-crazed killing spree and his return to humanity.</p>
        <p>6  8  5  ANIMAL, VEGETABLE, MIRACLE, by Barbara Kingsolver with Steven L. Hopp and Camille Kingsolver. (HarperCollins, $26.95.) The novelist and her family spend a year eating homegrown or local food; an argument for sustainable agriculture.</p>
        <p>7  5  4  PRESIDENTIAL COURAGE, by Michael Beschloss. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $28.) Profiles of nine presidents who had the courage to make unpopular decisions.</p>
        <p>8  7  3  JESUS OF NAZARETH, by Benedict XVI. (Doubleday, $24.95.) The pope discusses Jesus' identity as revealed in the Gospels.</p>
        <p>9*  9  7  WHERE HAVE ALL THE LEADERS GONE?, by Lee Iacocca. (Scribner, $25.) The former C.E.O. of Chrysler protests the lack of political and business leadership on issues like health care and energy policy.</p>
        <p>10  10  3  RICKLES' BOOK, by Don Rickles with David Ritz. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $24.) A memoir by the insult comedian.</p>
        <p>11  11  6  THE BLACK SWAN, by Nassim Nicholas Taleb. (Random House, $26.95.) The role of the unexpected.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>1  THE CANON, by Natalie Angier. (Houghton Mifflin, $27.) A refresher course on the fundamentals of science.</p>
        <p>13  16  2  BROTHERS, by David Talbot. (Free Press, $28.) An assessment of John F. Kennedy's administration and a plea for a new effort to uncover the truth about his assassination.</p>
        <p>14  14  4  TALES FROM Q SCHOOL, by John Feinstein. (Little, Brown, $26.99.) Inside the 2005 PGA Tour Qualifying Tournament, from the author of ''A Good Walk Spoiled.''</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>106  THE WORLD IS FLAT, by Thomas L. Friedman. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $30.) A columnist for The Times analyzes 21st-century economics and foreign policy.</p>
        <p>16*</p>
        <p>102  FREAKONOMICS, by Steven D. Levitt and Stephen J. Dubner. (Morrow, $27.95.) A maverick scholar and a journalist apply economic theory to nearly everything.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
