<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CALENDAR</title>
    <meta content="17listingsCTCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E0D7143FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2354" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CALENDAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Connecticut this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to ctcal@nytimes.com, or by mail to Connecticut Weekly, 620 Eighth Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10018.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Forget Baghdad,'' directed by Samir. In Arabic and Hebrew, with English subtitles. Monday at 6:30 p.m. Free. New Haven Public Library, 133 Elm Street. (203) 946-8130.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Mr. Fish and Lisa Lou's Super Circus Stuff,'' circus performers. June 23 at 11 a.m. $5 to $15. Stamford Theater Works, 200 Strawberry Hill Avenue. (203) 359-4414.</p>
        <p>West Hartford ''Color Play: The Art and Science of Color and Light.'' Explore light and holographic refraction. Ages 12 and under. Through June 17. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. The Children's Museum, 950 Trout Brook Drive. (860) 231-2824.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Bethel The Mike Leventhal Quartet, jazz. June 17 at 5 p.m. $10 minimum. Pizzeria Lauretano, 291 Greenwood Avenue. (203) 792-1500.</p>
        <p>East Hartford Celtic Spring, Irish American dance and fiddle music. Friday at 7:30 p.m. $15 to $20; $12, students. East Hartford Community Cultural Center, 50 Chapman Place. (860) 528-1458.</p>
        <p>Fairfield Musica Plenti, nine-member vocal chamber ensemble. June 17 at 7 p.m. $17. Stanley Clarke, fusion jazz. Thursday at 7 p.m. $67. Fairfield Theater Company, 70 Sanford Street. (203) 259-1036.</p>
        <p>Falls Village Music Mountain Summer Music Festival: Peter Serkin and the Bard Festival String Quartet, chamber music. June 17 at 1 p.m. $200 to $25. Music Mountain, 225 Music Mountain Road. (860) 824-7126.</p>
        <p>New Haven Bill Frisel Trio, jazz guitar. Monday at 8:30 p.m. $30. Firehouse 12, 45 Crown Street. (203) 785-0468.</p>
        <p>New Haven International Festival of Arts and Ideas: Cyro Baptista and Beat the Donkey, South American music. June 17 at 8 p.m. Free. New Haven Green. (203) 776-7331.</p>
        <p>New Haven  Pianist Jason Moran and the Bandwagon, jazz. June 17 at 2 and 7 p.m. $25. Off Broadway Theater, 41 Broadway. (203) 624-1824.</p>
        <p>New Haven Dan Zanes and friends, music for families. June 17 at 2 p.m. $4 to $21. Shubert Theater, 247 College Street. (203) 624-1825.</p>
        <p>New London Connecticut Early Music Society presents: Haydn: Sturm und Drang Symphonies. June 17 at 6 p.m. $26. Mozart String Quintets. Friday at 8 p.m. $26. Evans Hall, Cummings Art Center, Connecticut College. (860) 439-2720.</p>
        <p>New Milford The Danbury Brass Band, featuring Alan Raph. June 23 at 8 p.m. $10 to $20. Merryall Center for the Arts, Chapel Hill Road. (860) 354-7264.</p>
        <p>Norwalk Norwalk Recreation and Parks Department Free Summer Concerts: Golden Ages of Jazz Band. June 17 at 3 p.m. Free with park entrance. Calf Pasture Beach, (203) 854-7900.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Litchfield Frances Kiernan talks about her book ''The Last Mrs. Astor: A New York Story.'' Thursday at 7 p.m. Free; registration required. Oliver Wolcott Library, 160 South Street. (860) 567-8030.</p>
        <p>Madison Justin Evans talks about his novel, ''A Good and Happy Child.'' Wednesday at 7 p.m. Ed Offley talks about his book ''Scorpion Down.'' Friday at 7 p.m. R. J. Julia Booksellers, 768 Boston Road. (203) 245-3959.</p>
        <p>Madison  Michael Beschloss talks about his book ''Brave Leaders and How They Changed America.'' Monday at 7 p.m. $2. Scranton Memorial Library, 801 Boston Post Road. (203) 245-7365.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''100 Years of Broadway,'' a musical revue to benefit Playhouse on the Green. Thursday through June 24. $25. Playhouse on the Green, 177 State Street. (203) 333-6211.</p>
        <p>Glastonbury The Phoenix Theater Company: ''Nunsense!'' directed by Patrique Hurd. Through June 17. $18 and $20. Phoenix Theater Company at St. Paul's Hall, 40 Naubuc Avenue. (860) 291-2988.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Nightingale,'' written and performed by Lynn Redgrave, directed by Joseph Hardy. Through July 1. $22 to $42. Hartford Stage, 50 Church Street. (860) 527-5151.</p>
        <p>Hartford Caryl Churchill's ''A Number,'' directed by Steve Campo. Through July 29. $35 to $45; student rush, $10. TheaterWorks Hartford, 233 Pearl Street. (860) 527-7838.</p>
        <p>Milford ''I Hate Hamlet,'' comedy by Paul Rudnick, presented by Eastbound Theater, directed by Keith Padin. Through June 17. $12.50 and $15. Milford Center for the Arts, 40 Railroad Avenue. (203) 878-6647.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''God is a DJ,'' by Falk Richter. Multimedia theater. Wednesday through June 30. $14 to $25. Yale Summer Cabaret, 217 Park Street. (203) 432-1567.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''Man of La Mancha,'' directed by Craig David Rosen. Through July 14. $20 and $24. Ridgefield Theater Barn, 37 Halpin Lane. (203) 431-9850.</p>
        <p>Torrington The Nancy Marine Studio Theater Season: ''A Streetcar Named Desire.'' Through June 17. $10.50 to $15.50. Warner Theater, 68 Main Street. (860) 489-7180.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Mary's Wedding,'' by Stephen Masicotte, directed by Tazewell Thompson. Thursday through July 7. $35 to $55. Westport Country Playhouse, 25 Powers Court. (203) 227-4177.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Lend Me a Tenor,'' by Ken Ludwig. Through June 17. $12 to $16. Westport Town Hall, 110 Myrtle Avenue. (203) 226-1983.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
        <p>Darien  Darien's Father's Day Car Show, vintage and specialty cars. June 17 at 11 a.m. Free registration. Tilley Park, Next to train station and off West Avenue. (203) 656-6671.</p>
        <p>Glastonbury ''Summer Solstice'' celebration with song and dance. Wednesday at 8 p.m. $7 to $5; $20, families. The Connecticut Audubon Society Center at Glastonbury, 1361 Main Street. (860) 633-8402.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Clinton ''In Full Bloom,'' an exhibition of flower-themed art. Through June 24. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Sylvan Gallery, 121 West Main Street. (860) 669-7278.</p>
        <p>Fairfield ''Emptiness,'' an exhibit of welded steel sculptures by Michael Rivera. June 17 through July 29. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Thomas J. Walsh Art Galley, 1073 North Benson Road. (203) 254-4000.</p>
        <p>Greenwich ''Abstraction: American and European Art in the Twentieth Century,'' works by Fernand Léger, George Valmier and others. Through Monday. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Abby M. Taylor Fine Art, 43 Greenwich Avenue. (203) 622-0906.</p>
        <p>Greenwich ''Zip, Bop and Whir: Toys of the 20th Century,'' exhibition exploring the evolution of toy technology. Through July 8. ''Fakes and Forgeries: The Art of Deception,'' over 50 examples of forged Western painting and sculpture. Through Sept. 9. ''Themes and Symbols in the Decorative Arts of China.'' June 23 through Sept. 9. $6 and $7; children 5 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Bruce Museum of Arts and Sciences, 1 Museum Drive. (203) 869-0376.</p>
        <p>Greenwich The Art Students League, works by a variety of students. Through June 24. Greenwich Library, 101 West Putnam Avenue. (203) 622-7900.</p>
        <p>Hartford Works by Shaun Leonardo, Fay Ku, Nadya Volicer and Jillian Conrad. Through July 1. $3; members, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Thursdays and Sundays, 2 to 10 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 2 p.m. to midnight. Real Art Ways, 56 Arbor Street. (860) 232-1006.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Faith and Fortune: Five Centuries of European Masterworks,'' exhibition of European masterworks and sculpture from the museum's collection. Through Dec. 9. ''Connecticut Contemporary,'' group show by 24 local artists. Through Aug. 12. ''For the Love of the Game: Race and Sport in American Art,'' exhibition of sports-themed multi-media works. Through Nov. 1. ''Picasso to Pop: Aspects of Modern Art,'' exhibition of the museum's holdings from many 20th-century genres. Through Nov. 18. $3 to $10; members and children 12 and under, free. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; first Thursdays of the month, 11 a.m. to 8 p.m. Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, 600 Main Street. (860) 838-4058.</p>
        <p>Lakeville Paintings and drawings by Laura Ball, Peter Barrett and Josh Dorman. Through June 24. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Morgan Lehman Gallery, 24 Sharon Road, Route 41. (860) 435-0898.</p>
        <p>Lakeville ''Works on Paper and Assemblages,'' works by Ann Conrad, Constance Old, Eve Stockton and Jane de Jonge. Through June 24. ''Works on Paper and Assemblages,'' with Ann Conrad and others. Through June 30. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m., or by appointment. The White Gallery, 343 Main Street. (860) 435-1029.</p>
        <p>Lakeville ''Arthur Getz: Fine Artist and Illustrator.'' Through June 17. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Tremaine Gallery at the Hotchkiss School, 11 Interlaken Road. (860) 435-4423.</p>
        <p>Mashantucket ''50 Years of Powwow,'' photographs of indigenous people. June 17 through Oct. 9. $15. Hours: Daily, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; last admission, 3 p.m. Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center, 110 Pequot Trail. (800) 411-9671.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Interleaving,'' juried exhibition with works by 16 artists. Through June 17. Free. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Arts + Literature Laboratory, 319 Peck Street. (203) 671-5175.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Cultural Passages: Identity Made Visible,'' juried exhibition. Through June 22. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Creative Arts Workshop, 80 Audubon Street. (203) 562-4927.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Much Joy in Mudville: 150 Years of Connecticut's Irish in Baseball.'' Through September 14. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Sundays, 3 to 5 p.m. Ethnic Heritage Center, 270 Fitch Street. (203) 392-6126.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Walker Evans and Eugène Atget: Documentary Heritage.'' Thursday through July 14. Reception: Thursday at 6 p.m. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, noon to 6 p.m. Exposure Gallery of Photography, 1 Whitney Avenue. (203) 494-9905.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''International Mail Art Exhibition,'' artist-designed postcards from around the world. Through June 27. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. Small Space Gallery, 70 Audubon Street. (203) 772-2788.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Paul Mellon's Legacy: A Passion for British Art,'' more than 250 works from the Mellon Collection. Through July 29. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Yale Center for British Art, 1080 Chapel Street. (203) 432-2800.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Made for Love: Selections From the Jane Katcher Collection of Americana.'' Through Aug. 26. ''What Is a Line? Drawings From the Collection,'' works by Sol LeWitt, Trisha Brown, Agnes Martin and others. Through July 22. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 6 p.m. Yale University Art Gallery, (203) 432-0600.</p>
        <p>New London ''Gas in Glass: The Light Sculptures of Mundy Hepburn.'' ''Expresiones/Expressions: Caribbean and Latin American Art From the Benjamin Ortiz Collection.'' Both through June 24. $3 and $4; children 6 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Lyman Allyn Art Museum, 625 Williams Street. (860) 443-2545.</p>
        <p>Old Lyme ''Tie Me Down,'' abstract expressionists works by Janet Lage. Through July 8. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Diane Birdsall Gallery, 68 Lyme Street. (860) 434-3209.</p>
        <p>Old Lyme ''The Freedom Business: Connecticut Landscapes Through the Eyes of Venture Smith,'' poems by Marilyn Nelson paired with paintings from the museum's collection. Through June 24. ''A Circle of Friends: The Artists of the Florence Griswold Museum.'' Through July 1. $4 to $8; under 6, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Florence Griswold Museum, 96 Lyme Street. (860) 434-5542.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''Tekrar,'' sound installation by David Abir. Through Aug. 12. ''W(E)AVE,'' sound and textile collaboration between Elana Herzog and Michael Schumacher. Through Aug. 12. ''Castles, Dwarfs, and Happychaps,'' work by Arturo Herrera created using the Renaissance technique of pouncing. Through Sept. 2. ''Chrysanthemum Anthems,'' sculpture by Dario Robleto based on American soldiers' experience of wars. Through June 17. $4 to $7, teachers and children under 18, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Aldrich Contemporary Art Museum, 258 Main Street. (203) 438-4519.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''Camera Works,'' a group photography exhibit. Through July 8. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Ridgefield Guild of Artists Gallery, 34 Halpin Lane. (203) 438-8863.</p>
        <p>Roxbury ''People and Places,'' an exhibit of prints and photographs by young artists. Through July 16. Hours: Mondays, noon to 7 p.m.; Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Thursdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 2 p.m. Minor Memorial Library, 23 South Street. (860) 350-21281.</p>
        <p>Simsbury ''Marcia Mead Bailey -- One Person Show.'' Through July 1. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 6 p.m. Arts Exclusive Gallery, 690 Hopmeadow Street. (860) 651-5824.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''Shadows and Substance,'' exhibition of shadow puppets from Turkey, Indonesia, China, India and the United States. Through Nov. 17. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Ballard Institute and Museum of Puppetry, 6 Bourne Place. (860) 486-4605.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''Tradition and Innovation: Latin American Art From the Benton Collection.'' Through June 17. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 4:30 p.m. William Benton Museum of Art, 245 Glenbrook Road. (860) 486-4520.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Metropolitan Escape,'' exhibit of work by Edward Hajdin. Through June 22. Hours: Wednesday through Sunday, 11 a.m. Gallerie Je Reviens, 991 Post Road East. (203) 227-7716.</p>
        <p>Wilton ''Reflections on Gilbert and Bennett,'' four local artists. Through June 29. Hours: Mondays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Tuesday through Thursday, 10 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Saturday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. and Sunday 1 to 5 p.m. Wilton Library, 137 Old Ridgefield Road. (203) 762-3950.</p>
        <p>Woodbury ''Art as Impetus,'' works by Kim Bernard and Tom Driscoll. Through June 24. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Fenn Gallery, 345 Main Street South. (203) 263-3449.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Connecticut this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to ctcal@nytimes.com, or by mail to Connecticut Weekly, 620 Eighth Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10018.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Forget Baghdad,'' directed by Samir. In Arabic and Hebrew, with English subtitles. Monday at 6:30 p.m. Free. New Haven Public Library, 133 Elm Street. (203) 946-8130.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Mr. Fish and Lisa Lou's Super Circus Stuff,'' circus performers. June 23 at 11 a.m. $5 to $15. Stamford Theater Works, 200 Strawberry Hill Avenue. (203) 359-4414.</p>
        <p>West Hartford ''Color Play: The Art and Science of Color and Light.'' Explore light and holographic refraction. Ages 12 and under. Through June 17. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. The Children's Museum, 950 Trout Brook Drive. (860) 231-2824.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Bethel The Mike Leventhal Quartet, jazz. June 17 at 5 p.m. $10 minimum. Pizzeria Lauretano, 291 Greenwood Avenue. (203) 792-1500.</p>
        <p>East Hartford Celtic Spring, Irish American dance and fiddle music. Friday at 7:30 p.m. $15 to $20; $12, students. East Hartford Community Cultural Center, 50 Chapman Place. (860) 528-1458.</p>
        <p>Fairfield Musica Plenti, nine-member vocal chamber ensemble. June 17 at 7 p.m. $17. Stanley Clarke, fusion jazz. Thursday at 7 p.m. $67. Fairfield Theater Company, 70 Sanford Street. (203) 259-1036.</p>
        <p>Falls Village Music Mountain Summer Music Festival: Peter Serkin and the Bard Festival String Quartet, chamber music. June 17 at 1 p.m. $200 to $25. Music Mountain, 225 Music Mountain Road. (860) 824-7126.</p>
        <p>New Haven Bill Frisel Trio, jazz guitar. Monday at 8:30 p.m. $30. Firehouse 12, 45 Crown Street. (203) 785-0468.</p>
        <p>New Haven International Festival of Arts and Ideas: Cyro Baptista and Beat the Donkey, South American music. June 17 at 8 p.m. Free. New Haven Green. (203) 776-7331.</p>
        <p>New Haven  Pianist Jason Moran and the Bandwagon, jazz. June 17 at 2 and 7 p.m. $25. Off Broadway Theater, 41 Broadway. (203) 624-1824.</p>
        <p>New Haven Dan Zanes and friends, music for families. June 17 at 2 p.m. $4 to $21. Shubert Theater, 247 College Street. (203) 624-1825.</p>
        <p>New London Connecticut Early Music Society presents: Haydn: Sturm und Drang Symphonies. June 17 at 6 p.m. $26. Mozart String Quintets. Friday at 8 p.m. $26. Evans Hall, Cummings Art Center, Connecticut College. (860) 439-2720.</p>
        <p>New Milford The Danbury Brass Band, featuring Alan Raph. June 23 at 8 p.m. $10 to $20. Merryall Center for the Arts, Chapel Hill Road. (860) 354-7264.</p>
        <p>Norwalk Norwalk Recreation and Parks Department Free Summer Concerts: Golden Ages of Jazz Band. June 17 at 3 p.m. Free with park entrance. Calf Pasture Beach, (203) 854-7900.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Litchfield Frances Kiernan talks about her book ''The Last Mrs. Astor: A New York Story.'' Thursday at 7 p.m. Free; registration required. Oliver Wolcott Library, 160 South Street. (860) 567-8030.</p>
        <p>Madison Justin Evans talks about his novel, ''A Good and Happy Child.'' Wednesday at 7 p.m. Ed Offley talks about his book ''Scorpion Down.'' Friday at 7 p.m. R. J. Julia Booksellers, 768 Boston Road. (203) 245-3959.</p>
        <p>Madison  Michael Beschloss talks about his book ''Brave Leaders and How They Changed America.'' Monday at 7 p.m. $2. Scranton Memorial Library, 801 Boston Post Road. (203) 245-7365.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''100 Years of Broadway,'' a musical revue to benefit Playhouse on the Green. Thursday through June 24. $25. Playhouse on the Green, 177 State Street. (203) 333-6211.</p>
        <p>Glastonbury The Phoenix Theater Company: ''Nunsense!'' directed by Patrique Hurd. Through June 17. $18 and $20. Phoenix Theater Company at St. Paul's Hall, 40 Naubuc Avenue. (860) 291-2988.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Nightingale,'' written and performed by Lynn Redgrave, directed by Joseph Hardy. Through July 1. $22 to $42. Hartford Stage, 50 Church Street. (860) 527-5151.</p>
        <p>Hartford Caryl Churchill's ''A Number,'' directed by Steve Campo. Through July 29. $35 to $45; student rush, $10. TheaterWorks Hartford, 233 Pearl Street. (860) 527-7838.</p>
        <p>Milford ''I Hate Hamlet,'' comedy by Paul Rudnick, presented by Eastbound Theater, directed by Keith Padin. Through June 17. $12.50 and $15. Milford Center for the Arts, 40 Railroad Avenue. (203) 878-6647.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''God is a DJ,'' by Falk Richter. Multimedia theater. Wednesday through June 30. $14 to $25. Yale Summer Cabaret, 217 Park Street. (203) 432-1567.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''Man of La Mancha,'' directed by Craig David Rosen. Through July 14. $20 and $24. Ridgefield Theater Barn, 37 Halpin Lane. (203) 431-9850.</p>
        <p>Torrington The Nancy Marine Studio Theater Season: ''A Streetcar Named Desire.'' Through June 17. $10.50 to $15.50. Warner Theater, 68 Main Street. (860) 489-7180.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Mary's Wedding,'' by Stephen Masicotte, directed by Tazewell Thompson. Thursday through July 7. $35 to $55. Westport Country Playhouse, 25 Powers Court. (203) 227-4177.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Lend Me a Tenor,'' by Ken Ludwig. Through June 17. $12 to $16. Westport Town Hall, 110 Myrtle Avenue. (203) 226-1983.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
        <p>Darien  Darien's Father's Day Car Show, vintage and specialty cars. June 17 at 11 a.m. Free registration. Tilley Park, Next to train station and off West Avenue. (203) 656-6671.</p>
        <p>Glastonbury ''Summer Solstice'' celebration with song and dance. Wednesday at 8 p.m. $7 to $5; $20, families. The Connecticut Audubon Society Center at Glastonbury, 1361 Main Street. (860) 633-8402.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Clinton ''In Full Bloom,'' an exhibition of flower-themed art. Through June 24. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Sylvan Gallery, 121 West Main Street. (860) 669-7278.</p>
        <p>Fairfield ''Emptiness,'' an exhibit of welded steel sculptures by Michael Rivera. June 17 through July 29. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Thomas J. Walsh Art Galley, 1073 North Benson Road. (203) 254-4000.</p>
        <p>Greenwich ''Abstraction: American and European Art in the Twentieth Century,'' works by Fernand Léger, George Valmier and others. Through Monday. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Abby M. Taylor Fine Art, 43 Greenwich Avenue. (203) 622-0906.</p>
        <p>Greenwich ''Zip, Bop and Whir: Toys of the 20th Century,'' exhibition exploring the evolution of toy technology. Through July 8. ''Fakes and Forgeries: The Art of Deception,'' over 50 examples of forged Western painting and sculpture. Through Sept. 9. ''Themes and Symbols in the Decorative Arts of China.'' June 23 through Sept. 9. $6 and $7; children 5 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Bruce Museum of Arts and Sciences, 1 Museum Drive. (203) 869-0376.</p>
        <p>Greenwich The Art Students League, works by a variety of students. Through June 24. Greenwich Library, 101 West Putnam Avenue. (203) 622-7900.</p>
        <p>Hartford Works by Shaun Leonardo, Fay Ku, Nadya Volicer and Jillian Conrad. Through July 1. $3; members, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Thursdays and Sundays, 2 to 10 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 2 p.m. to midnight. Real Art Ways, 56 Arbor Street. (860) 232-1006.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Faith and Fortune: Five Centuries of European Masterworks,'' exhibition of European masterworks and sculpture from the museum's collection. Through Dec. 9. ''Connecticut Contemporary,'' group show by 24 local artists. Through Aug. 12. ''For the Love of the Game: Race and Sport in American Art,'' exhibition of sports-themed multi-media works. Through Nov. 1. ''Picasso to Pop: Aspects of Modern Art,'' exhibition of the museum's holdings from many 20th-century genres. Through Nov. 18. $3 to $10; members and children 12 and under, free. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; first Thursdays of the month, 11 a.m. to 8 p.m. Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, 600 Main Street. (860) 838-4058.</p>
        <p>Lakeville Paintings and drawings by Laura Ball, Peter Barrett and Josh Dorman. Through June 24. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Morgan Lehman Gallery, 24 Sharon Road, Route 41. (860) 435-0898.</p>
        <p>Lakeville ''Works on Paper and Assemblages,'' works by Ann Conrad, Constance Old, Eve Stockton and Jane de Jonge. Through June 24. ''Works on Paper and Assemblages,'' with Ann Conrad and others. Through June 30. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m., or by appointment. The White Gallery, 343 Main Street. (860) 435-1029.</p>
        <p>Lakeville ''Arthur Getz: Fine Artist and Illustrator.'' Through June 17. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Tremaine Gallery at the Hotchkiss School, 11 Interlaken Road. (860) 435-4423.</p>
        <p>Mashantucket ''50 Years of Powwow,'' photographs of indigenous people. June 17 through Oct. 9. $15. Hours: Daily, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; last admission, 3 p.m. Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center, 110 Pequot Trail. (800) 411-9671.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Interleaving,'' juried exhibition with works by 16 artists. Through June 17. Free. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Arts + Literature Laboratory, 319 Peck Street. (203) 671-5175.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Cultural Passages: Identity Made Visible,'' juried exhibition. Through June 22. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Creative Arts Workshop, 80 Audubon Street. (203) 562-4927.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Much Joy in Mudville: 150 Years of Connecticut's Irish in Baseball.'' Through September 14. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Sundays, 3 to 5 p.m. Ethnic Heritage Center, 270 Fitch Street. (203) 392-6126.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Walker Evans and Eugène Atget: Documentary Heritage.'' Thursday through July 14. Reception: Thursday at 6 p.m. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, noon to 6 p.m. Exposure Gallery of Photography, 1 Whitney Avenue. (203) 494-9905.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''International Mail Art Exhibition,'' artist-designed postcards from around the world. Through June 27. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. Small Space Gallery, 70 Audubon Street. (203) 772-2788.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Paul Mellon's Legacy: A Passion for British Art,'' more than 250 works from the Mellon Collection. Through July 29. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Yale Center for British Art, 1080 Chapel Street. (203) 432-2800.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Made for Love: Selections From the Jane Katcher Collection of Americana.'' Through Aug. 26. ''What Is a Line? Drawings From the Collection,'' works by Sol LeWitt, Trisha Brown, Agnes Martin and others. Through July 22. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 6 p.m. Yale University Art Gallery, (203) 432-0600.</p>
        <p>New London ''Gas in Glass: The Light Sculptures of Mundy Hepburn.'' ''Expresiones/Expressions: Caribbean and Latin American Art From the Benjamin Ortiz Collection.'' Both through June 24. $3 and $4; children 6 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Lyman Allyn Art Museum, 625 Williams Street. (860) 443-2545.</p>
        <p>Old Lyme ''Tie Me Down,'' abstract expressionists works by Janet Lage. Through July 8. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Diane Birdsall Gallery, 68 Lyme Street. (860) 434-3209.</p>
        <p>Old Lyme ''The Freedom Business: Connecticut Landscapes Through the Eyes of Venture Smith,'' poems by Marilyn Nelson paired with paintings from the museum's collection. Through June 24. ''A Circle of Friends: The Artists of the Florence Griswold Museum.'' Through July 1. $4 to $8; under 6, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Florence Griswold Museum, 96 Lyme Street. (860) 434-5542.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''Tekrar,'' sound installation by David Abir. Through Aug. 12. ''W(E)AVE,'' sound and textile collaboration between Elana Herzog and Michael Schumacher. Through Aug. 12. ''Castles, Dwarfs, and Happychaps,'' work by Arturo Herrera created using the Renaissance technique of pouncing. Through Sept. 2. ''Chrysanthemum Anthems,'' sculpture by Dario Robleto based on American soldiers' experience of wars. Through June 17. $4 to $7, teachers and children under 18, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Aldrich Contemporary Art Museum, 258 Main Street. (203) 438-4519.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''Camera Works,'' a group photography exhibit. Through July 8. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Ridgefield Guild of Artists Gallery, 34 Halpin Lane. (203) 438-8863.</p>
        <p>Roxbury ''People and Places,'' an exhibit of prints and photographs by young artists. Through July 16. Hours: Mondays, noon to 7 p.m.; Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Thursdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 2 p.m. Minor Memorial Library, 23 South Street. (860) 350-21281.</p>
        <p>Simsbury ''Marcia Mead Bailey -- One Person Show.'' Through July 1. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 6 p.m. Arts Exclusive Gallery, 690 Hopmeadow Street. (860) 651-5824.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''Shadows and Substance,'' exhibition of shadow puppets from Turkey, Indonesia, China, India and the United States. Through Nov. 17. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Ballard Institute and Museum of Puppetry, 6 Bourne Place. (860) 486-4605.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''Tradition and Innovation: Latin American Art From the Benton Collection.'' Through June 17. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 4:30 p.m. William Benton Museum of Art, 245 Glenbrook Road. (860) 486-4520.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Metropolitan Escape,'' exhibit of work by Edward Hajdin. Through June 22. Hours: Wednesday through Sunday, 11 a.m. Gallerie Je Reviens, 991 Post Road East. (203) 227-7716.</p>
        <p>Wilton ''Reflections on Gilbert and Bennett,'' four local artists. Through June 29. Hours: Mondays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Tuesday through Thursday, 10 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Saturday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. and Sunday 1 to 5 p.m. Wilton Library, 137 Old Ridgefield Road. (203) 762-3950.</p>
        <p>Woodbury ''Art as Impetus,'' works by Kim Bernard and Tom Driscoll. Through June 24. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Fenn Gallery, 345 Main Street South. (203) 263-3449.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
