<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Ugly Part Wasn't His Face</title>
    <meta content="17pubed" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="The Public Editor; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/opinion/17pubed.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE PUBLIC EDITOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/The Public Editor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E5D7153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="940" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Ugly Part Wasn't His Face</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Ugly Part Wasn’t His Face</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Clark Hoyt</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WILLIAM MURPHY, a retired policeman from Evansville, Wis., has been dealt more than his share of life's bad cards.</p>
        <p>He was shot in the head when he was 13, a hunting accident that cost him his right eye. He fell while on duty at the police station in Madison Township one day and knocked out a tooth on the left side of his mouth. He developed heart trouble in his 30s and had to have a heart transplant in his 40s. One of his lungs was later removed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>William Murphy, a retired policeman from Wisconsin, has been dealt more than his share of life’s bad cards. Then, The New York Times published his picture, and a different kind of trouble began.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WILLIAM MURPHY, a retired policeman from Evansville, Wis., has been dealt more than his share of life's bad cards.</p>
        <p>He was shot in the head when he was 13, a hunting accident that cost him his right eye. He fell while on duty at the police station in Madison Township one day and knocked out a tooth on the left side of his mouth. He developed heart trouble in his 30s and had to have a heart transplant in his 40s. One of his lungs was later removed.</p>
        <p>Then, The New York Times published his picture last Sunday, and a different kind of trouble began.</p>
        <p>Murphy is a man with a sense of humor and an indomitable will. ''I'm not a person who gives up on something if I want it bad enough,'' he told me. After all, how many one-eyed men manage to become police officers?</p>
        <p>Recently, Murphy turned his considerable energy to a political cause: defeating the immigration bill under consideration in the United States Senate. Working with a conservative citizens' coalition called Grassfire.org, he called senators and delivered petitions opposing the legislation.</p>
        <p>He came to the attention of The Times because Julia Preston, a reporter whose beat is immigration, believed that his side of the story wasn't being reflected enough in Times coverage of the bill. Preston said her e-mail had been indicating a groundswell of opposition from everyday people with ''a reasonable position, passionately expressed.''</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, June 5, she called Grassfire.org and asked to speak to some activists who would agree to be interviewed. Grassfire.org gave her a list of names, and she called four or five, including Murphy, who ''was a great interview.'' He was articulate, ''very concise, low key.''</p>
        <p>Preston later called Murphy and asked if she could send a photographer to take his picture.</p>
        <p>''I am the ugliest man on earth,'' she said he told her. ''One of my teeth is missing.'' Preston sent the photographer anyway. ''We don't have a beauty standard at The New York Times, and here was this man who expressed himself very eloquently,'' she said.</p>
        <p>That Friday, Preston awoke to news that the immigration bill had come off the tracks in Washington the previous evening. She called Murphy for his reaction. ''Ordinary people like me rose up and put a stop to it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Bingo,'' Preston told herself. He had given her ''a fabulous quote to sort of summarize the whole thing.''</p>
        <p>In New York, photo editors looked at pictures to illustrate Preston's story and chose a color photo of another outspoken opponent of the immigration bill, Monique Thibodeaux, for the front page. For inside the paper, they picked a picture of two congressmen and two leaders of Grassfire.org, all in business suits, and a photo of Murphy, smiling, with a gap where his tooth used to be, sitting beside an American flag on steps outside his house.</p>
        <p>The blogosphere went wild. Two radio talk show hosts in Southern California reproduced the photo of Murphy on their Web site under a headline that said, ''You are not a redneck!'' They accused The Times of portraying anyone against the immigration bill as ''riff-raff like this guy below.'' The words ''redneck'' and ''riff-raff'' never appeared in Preston's article in The Times.</p>
        <p>At The Times, the reader call-in line was overwhelmed. And, at last count by my assistant, Michael McElroy, the public editor had received 1,267 e-mail messages, many with the theme, as one put it, that ''I'm against the proposed Senate bill on immigration, and I have all of my teeth.'' E-mailers called Murphy a ''toothless freak'' and worse -- and these were the people who agreed with him about immigration.</p>
        <p>I asked Michele McNally, the assistant managing editor in charge of photography, why her editors would choose to run a picture of a man missing a tooth when they had to know it could contribute to stereotypes about the kinds of people opposing the immigration bill. She said there had indeed been a discussion about Murphy's appearance: how not to show his missing eye, which looked less flattering.</p>
        <p>''I think it is discriminatory to say all toothless people who represent controversial positions shouldn't be used,'' she said. ''This is a very big country that has a variety of styles and types.''</p>
        <p>I called Murphy to ask what he thought of the picture and all the attention it has received.</p>
        <p>''I feel sorry for the poor photographer,'' he said, laughing. ''If he takes a picture of one side of my face, there's no tooth. If he takes the other side, there's no eye. So what's he going to do?''</p>
        <p>Murphy explained that he used to have a denture and an artificial eye. He can no longer wear either because the antirejection drugs he takes since his heart transplant cause his face to swell.</p>
        <p>''My wife doesn't mind the way I look,'' he said. ''My children don't mind the way I look. If people don't like the way I look, it's their problem, not mine.''</p>
        <p>He said he regretted that people were focusing on his appearance instead of immigration.</p>
        <p>''Am I a redneck? I don't know. Am I willing to speak up? I am. Am I willing to take the derision, as you call it? Yeah, I am,'' he said.</p>
        <p>I think all those people who have been complaining about Murphy's photo owe him an apology. They assumed that, because he was missing a tooth, he was missing a brain. They also assumed that editors at The Times shared their prejudices and were attempting to ridicule opponents of the immigration bill.</p>
        <p>They were wrong on both counts.</p>
        <p>THE PUBLIC EDITOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
