<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Let Me Compare Thee to a Feral Beast</title>
    <meta content="17word" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/weekinreview/17word-ART.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855290"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Word for Word | That Bloody Press"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Blair, Tony</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E0DE123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Let Me Compare Thee to a Feral Beast</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Let Me Compare Thee to a Feral Beast</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARY JO MURPHY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SO, who said it better, the minor poet or the major politician?</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Tony Blair, in one of his era-ending speeches, took on the British news media last week. ''A feral beast,'' he called the press and its modern spawn. (The preferred metaphor of a previous prime minister -- ''harlot'' -- was taken.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain echoed the pastor-poet George Crabbe in expressing his disdain for the news media.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SO, who said it better, the minor poet or the major politician?</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Tony Blair, in one of his era-ending speeches, took on the British news media last week. ''A feral beast,'' he called the press and its modern spawn. (The preferred metaphor of a previous prime minister -- ''harlot'' -- was taken.)</p>
        <p>But nearly 200 years ago, the pastor-poet George Crabbe beat them both to the punch. In ''The Newspaper,'' published in 1812, Crabbe compared the press to bats, insects, bees and ''baneful herbs.'' And not in a good way.</p>
        <p>Every major point in Mr. Blair's speech has its echo in Crabbe's verse. Mr. Blair is no mean phrasemaker, but just as Ginger Rogers did everything Fred Astaire did only backwards and in high heels, the Reverend Crabbe gave Blair's speech in rhymed heroic couplets. Top that, Tony.</p>
        <p>MARY JO MURPHY</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair: The fear of missing out means today's media, more than ever before, hunts in a pack. In these modes it is like a feral beast, just tearing people and reputations to bits.</p>
        <p>Crabbe:</p>
        <p>I sing of News, and all those vapid sheets</p>
        <p>The Rattling hawker vends through gaping streets;</p>
        <p>Whate'er their name, whate'er the time they fly,</p>
        <p>Damp from the press, to charm the reader's eye</p>
        <p>Like bats, appearing, when the sun goes down,</p>
        <p>From holes obscure and corners of the town.</p>
        <p>In shoals the hours their constant numbers bring,</p>
        <p>Like insects waking to th'advancing spring;</p>
        <p>Which take their rise from grubs obscene that lie</p>
        <p>In shallow pools, or thence ascend the sky:</p>
        <p>Such are these base ephemeras, so born</p>
        <p>To die before the next revolving morn.</p>
        <p>Like baneful herbs the gazer's eye they seize,</p>
        <p>Rush to the head and poison where they please:</p>
        <p>Like idle flies, a busy, buzzing train,</p>
        <p>They drop their maggots on the trifler's brain</p>
        <p>Like bees for honey, forth for news they spring,-</p>
        <p>Industrious creatures! ever on the wing;</p>
        <p>Home to their several cells they bear the store,</p>
        <p>Cull'd of all kinds, then roam abroad for more.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair: Scandal or controversy beats ordinary reporting hands down. News is rarely news unless it generates heat as much as or more than light.</p>
        <p>Crabbe:</p>
        <p>These are the ills the teeming press supplies,</p>
        <p>The pois'nous springs from learning's fountain rise;</p>
        <p>Not there the wise alone their entrance find,</p>
        <p>Imparting useful light to mortals blind;</p>
        <p>But, blind themselves, these erring guides hold out</p>
        <p>Alluring lights to lead us far about;</p>
        <p>Screen'd by such means, here scandal whets her quill,</p>
        <p>Here slander shoots unseen, whene'er she will;</p>
        <p>Here fraud and falsehood labor to deceive,</p>
        <p>And folly aids them both, impatient to believe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair: The final consequence of all of this is that it is rare today to find balance in the media. Things, people, issues, stories, are all black and white. Life's usual gray is almost entirely absent. ''Some good, some bad''; ''some things going right, some going wrong'': these are concepts alien to today's reporting. It's a triumph or a disaster. A problem is ''a crisis.'' A setback is a policy ''in tatters.'' A criticism, ''a savage attack.''</p>
        <p>Crabbe:</p>
        <p>So the Sibylline leaves were blown about,</p>
        <p>Disjointed scraps of fate involv'd in doubt;</p>
        <p>So idle dreams, the journals of the night,</p>
        <p>Are right and wrong by turns, and mingle wrong with right.--</p>
        <p>Some champions for the rights that prop the crown,</p>
        <p>Some sturdy patriots, sworn to pull them down;</p>
        <p>Some neutral powers, with secret forces fraught,</p>
        <p>Wishing for war, but willing to be bought;</p>
        <p>While some to every side and party go,</p>
        <p>Shift every friend and join with every foe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair: It is sometimes said that the media is accountable daily through the choice of readers and viewers. That is true up to a point. But the reality is that the viewers or readers have no objective yardstick to measure what they are being told.</p>
        <p>Crabbe:</p>
        <p>A master-passion is the love of news,</p>
        <p>Not music so commands, nor so the Muse:</p>
        <p>Give poets claret, they grow idle soon;</p>
        <p>Feed the musician, and he's out of tune;</p>
        <p>But the sick mind, of this disease possesst,</p>
        <p>Flies from all cure and sickens when at rest.</p>
        <p>Their careless authors only strive to join</p>
        <p>As many words as make an even line;</p>
        <p>As many lines, as fill a row complete;</p>
        <p>As many rows, as furnish up a sheet:</p>
        <p>From side to side, with ready types they run,</p>
        <p>The measure's ended, and the work is done</p>
        <p>And such this mental food, as we may call</p>
        <p>Something to all men, and to some men all.</p>
        <p>Word for Word | That Bloody Press</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
