<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Investing Your Way Out of Poverty</title>
    <meta content="17CIobrien" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/opinion/nyregionopinions/17CIobrien.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855168"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloomberg, Michael R (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Brien, Rourke L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E3DA153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="825" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Investing Your Way Out of Poverty</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Investing Your Way Out of Poverty</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Rourke L. O'Brien</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'Brien, Rourke L</byline>
      <dateline>Washington</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by New American Foundation policy analyst Rourke O'Brien holds that for New York Mayor Michael Bloomberg's new antipoverty plan to work, it needs to be adapted to realities of low-income New Yorkers; offers specific suggestions to help 'conditional cash transfer' program succeed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE mayor of New York's new antipoverty plan, which is scheduled to begin in the fall, will pay as much as $5,000 a year to poor families to help them meet specific goals like getting regular medical checkups, holding down full-time jobs and attending parent-teacher conferences.</p>
        <p>Experience in developing countries shows that such ''conditional cash transfer'' programs are effective in combating poverty. Those who participate wind up with better education, health and life prospects than those who don't. Such a program in Mexico -- the initial inspiration for Mayor Michael Bloomberg's plan -- has had particular success in improving the health of participating children.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Michael Bloomberg must adapt his antipoverty plan to the needs and realities of low-income New Yorkers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE mayor of New York's new antipoverty plan, which is scheduled to begin in the fall, will pay as much as $5,000 a year to poor families to help them meet specific goals like getting regular medical checkups, holding down full-time jobs and attending parent-teacher conferences.</p>
        <p>Experience in developing countries shows that such ''conditional cash transfer'' programs are effective in combating poverty. Those who participate wind up with better education, health and life prospects than those who don't. Such a program in Mexico -- the initial inspiration for Mayor Michael Bloomberg's plan -- has had particular success in improving the health of participating children.</p>
        <p>But for this initiative to work in the United States, Mayor Bloomberg must adapt his plan to the needs and realities of low-income New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>For starters, the city needs to avoid creating another bureaucracy that would eat up money that should go directly to families. Not only should the additional bureaucracy be as lean as possible, the existing service system must be streamlined to ensure that families have access to medical services and job training. Participation in the program should be accompanied by comprehensive information about existing government services and job training opportunities for which individuals in the program may qualify. The city must ensure that these families are taking full advantage of all the services they qualify for and that the additional money isn't used to secure services that the government already provides.</p>
        <p>Evidence from developing countries suggests that conditional cash transfers succeed in promoting better economic behavior only when families have access to the services they need. It may seem like a simple point, but a cash incentive for someone to attend classes in, say, auto repair is ineffective if he does not have access to such a course in his community.</p>
        <p>What's more, cash transfers must be accompanied by some basic financial education so that these families know how to save the money, how to manage their debt and how to set long-term financial goals.</p>
        <p>Mayor Bloomberg has already made financial education a priority in creating the Office of Financial Empowerment, which operates out of the Department of Consumer Affairs, but outreach is vital to ensuring the city's poorest residents understand how to manage their money.</p>
        <p>Thousands of low-income New Yorkers live without access to financial institutions, in part because few banks build branches in low-income neighborhoods. As a result, they pay bills and cash checks through fringe financial institutions that typically charge high fees and push predatory products like payday loans. All recipients in a cash transfer program should be required to have a checking account at a federally insured bank. City employees should assist participants in opening these accounts and the money should be transferred through direct deposit.</p>
        <p>More important, the city must ensure that the money families earn through the program doesn't disqualify them for benefits like food stamps. A family of three can earn a maximum of $22,321 a year and still qualify for assistance, but if the cash transfer is added to this amount, many families will become ineligible and be forced to use the transfer to replace money lost in government assistance. No family can get ahead making less than $25,000 a year, especially in New York. And if families are prudent enough to save cash transfers for long-term goals like buying a house or going to college, those savings should be excluded from the asset limit when determining eligibility for public assistance.</p>
        <p>Asset limits in public assistance programs present a clear disincentive to save; undermining much of the program's potential to move families toward economic self-sufficiency. The program's financial incentives will be lost if every dollar a family earns is accompanied by a corresponding loss in public benefits.</p>
        <p>Instead of limits, the city should provide incentives for families to invest the money they receive through the program in ''productive assets'' like studying for their nursing license at the City University of New York or starting a day-care service out of their homes. Families in the Mexican program who invested about a quarter of all cash transfers into a productive asset increased their standard of living by about 24 percent after six years in the program.</p>
        <p>Finally, as this initiative expands, the mayor should consider investing a portion of the cash transfers directly into banking accounts set up for children in the program. By doing this, these children could tap into the money when they reach adulthood, allowing them to achieve economic independence as adults.</p>
        <p>As a businessman, Mayor Bloomberg understands that the fiscal health of an individual, as for any corporation, is measured not by annual income, but by net worth. With the proper incentives, his antipoverty program can do more than encourage low-income New Yorkers to attain higher levels of education, job skills and physical health. Indeed, it can provide poor New Yorkers with their own financial nest eggs, and allow them to become productive, taxpaying citizens.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Rourke L. O'Brien is a policy analyst at the New America Foundation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Rourke L. O'Brien is a policy analyst at the New America Foundation.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
