<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Connecting With the Voters on Bond Issues</title>
    <meta content="17mainnjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/17mainnj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855085"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SCHOOLS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hunterdon County (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Voorhees (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nussbaum, Debra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02EEDF153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Connecting With the Voters on Bond Issues</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Connecting With the Voters on Bond Issues</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBRA NUSSBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nussbaum, Debra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>North Hunterdon-Voorhees Regional High School District in New Jersey is surveying residents, holding talks with community groups and planning open forums to lay groundwork for bond issue scheduled to be voted on in 2008; last year, only 60 percent of 52 bond proposals were approved statewide, compared with 73 percent of 26 bond issues passed so far this year; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MORE than a year ago, administrators and board members of the North Hunterdon-Voorhees Regional High School District began laying the groundwork for a bond issue. The vote is not scheduled to be on the ballot until 2008, but New Jersey educators know that if they want to win a bond election for school renovations, repairs or construction, they must do their homework.</p>
        <p>Voting on school bonds or budgets is often the only time the public gets to give thumbs up or thumbs down to taxes, and in recent years it has been saying no more often.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Schools face increased skepticism when asking the voters to approve bond issues, so they are putting more effort into their campaigns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MORE than a year ago, administrators and board members of the North Hunterdon-Voorhees Regional High School District began laying the groundwork for a bond issue. The vote is not scheduled to be on the ballot until 2008, but New Jersey educators know that if they want to win a bond election for school renovations, repairs or construction, they must do their homework.</p>
        <p>Voting on school bonds or budgets is often the only time the public gets to give thumbs up or thumbs down to taxes, and in recent years it has been saying no more often.</p>
        <p>With that in mind, North Hunterdon-Voorhees is out to educate voters. The district, which in the last nine years has grown to 3,100 students from 2,100, passed a $12 million bond issue in 2001, and the coming bond issue -- for renovations and energy updates at North Hunterdon and Voorhees High Schools -- may be slightly higher, district officials said.</p>
        <p>''You have to prepare and be meticulous in your planning,'' said Charles M. Shaddow, the district superintendent. ''You have to show your citizens that this is what is needed and that it's not too much and not too little.''</p>
        <p>To that end, the district is surveying residents and talking to community groups, and it will be holding open forums to discuss the plans. It also plans to use the Internet to spread the word.</p>
        <p>''Educating people on the issues is critical,'' said Thomas L. Seidenberger, superintendent of Brick Township Public Schools in Ocean County, where a $4.4 million bond issue for roof work at five schools passed in April. ''We did a lot of work. We sent out letters, and we met with people.</p>
        <p>''Most people understood the problem, but there are some people who just view this as school districts getting deeper into their pockets.''</p>
        <p>In April, 16 of 18 school bond issues on the ballot around the state passed, with $82 million approved by voters. Projects ranged in cost from $997,000 for renovations in Hamilton Township in Atlantic County to $23 million for renovations and additions in the Town of Boonton in Morris County.</p>
        <p>Last year, only 60 percent of 52 bond proposals were approved. But so far this year, in three days of bond elections, 73 percent of 26 bond issues have passed.</p>
        <p>The April vote this year represents ''a real turnaround,'' said Frank Belluscio, spokesman for the New Jersey School Boards Association. But because school construction and renovation is such a local issue, it is uncertain whether the high approval rating will continue, he said. His organization encourages districts to spend at least a year preparing for a bond vote.</p>
        <p>Bond approvals started dropping after 2003, when nearly 80 percent of 93 bond issues passed. In 2004, the approval rate dropped to 67 percent of 71 proposals. In 2005, it was just under 59 percent of 89 proposals.</p>
        <p>School budgets saw a similar trend. In 2003, 62 percent of the budgets in New Jersey's school districts passed. In 2006, that figure was 53 percent. But this April, 78 percent passed. An increase in state aid may have helped more budgets get through, Mr. Belluscio said.</p>
        <p>Much of the 2003 bond success came when $8.6 billion was made available by the state through the Schools Construction Corporation. That money, which was fully committed by 2005, allowed districts to apply for a percentage of the cost of repairs, renovations or new school construction once they passed a bond issue. The state's poorest districts were able to get 100 percent funding for projects, while suburban districts could get up to 40 percent.</p>
        <p>More than 80 percent of the state's 600 districts used money from the Schools Construction Corporation between 2002 and 2005, said Larry Hanover, a corporation spokesman.</p>
        <p>Bond elections are allowed five days a year, in January, March, April (when school budgets are voted on), September and December.</p>
        <p>While only about 15 percent of New Jersey voters typically come out for school budget and school board elections, the turnout for bond issues is usually about 28 percent, Mr. Belluscio said. ''There's a lot more excitement with them,'' he said, because it is easier to explain a bricks-and-mortar proposition.</p>
        <p>But educators said the pressure is on to explain the issues, or voters will reject the tax increases that accompany most bonds.</p>
        <p>''You have to get a buy-in from many groups, and you have to take your story on the road,'' Dr. Shaddow said, adding, ''You have to listen as much as you talk.''</p>
        <p>Voters in Ewing Township passed a $14 million bond issue in April that allowed the district to cancel a lease-purchase agreement on existing buildings and refinance debt. Only 272 of the 1,881 people who voted said no.</p>
        <p>Even though the bond did not increase taxes, it would not have passed without an effort to communicate information to the community, said Dennis Nettleton, the Ewing Public Schools business administrator and board secretary. Mr. Nettleton and Raymond Broach, the superintendent, met with more than 15 school and community groups to explain the proposal.</p>
        <p>''You have to sell a bond issue harder than a budget,'' Mr. Nettleton said.</p>
        <p>The average New Jersey school building is 50 years old, so bond votes will not be going away. Public school enrollment also continues to increase, to almost 1.4 million last year from 1.1 million in 1986.</p>
        <p>Brick Township administrators are beginning research this summer on another bond issue that will face voters in the next year or two, said Dr. Seidenberger, the superintendent.</p>
        <p>''The next challenge is Brick High School, which was built in 1958,'' he said. ''You have to do it right, and there can't be any excess on the project. You have to be open and honest and people need to see the value. You have to give people the facts.''</p>
        <p>SCHOOLS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
