<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tackling Giuseppe Verdi</title>
    <meta content="17peopleweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/17peoplewe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855018"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PERFORMER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Houston Oilers (Defunct Team)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harris, Lawrence</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hershenson, Roberta</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Metropolitan Opera Guild</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Harris, Lawrence</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E4D7143FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="756" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tackling Giuseppe Verdi</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tackling Giuseppe Verdi</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA HERSHENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hershenson, Roberta</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of and interview with Lawrence Harris, former Houston Oilers lineman who switched careers 18 years ago to become opera singer; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ATOP a derrick 300 feet above the Gulf of Mexico, Lawrence Harris decided what to do with his life.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harris, a Texas native, was a professional football player whose career was foundering because of injuries. But since childhood he had also sung, and he sometimes surprised his Houston Oiler teammates with arias in the shower.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawrence Harris gave up professional football to take a shot at professional life in the opera.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ATOP a derrick 300 feet above the Gulf of Mexico, Lawrence Harris decided what to do with his life.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harris, a Texas native, was a professional football player whose career was foundering because of injuries. But since childhood he had also sung, and he sometimes surprised his Houston Oiler teammates with arias in the shower.</p>
        <p>He was on the derrick that night because he was working on an oil rig to keep in shape between seasons. To entertain himself, he was singing opera at the top of his lungs.</p>
        <p>''I never sang on the rigs because of all the testosterone around the place,'' Mr. Harris, now of Yonkers, said. ''But up there no one could hear me but God. I said to myself, this is what I've got to be doing.''</p>
        <p>It was more than 18 years ago that Mr. Harris, who gives his age as ''approaching 50,'' gave up football for a professional life in opera and the promise of a major career. Singing in opera houses from Texas to the Bronx, he has won accolades for his rich baritone -- and awards and grants from the Metropolitan Opera Guild and the Wagner Society of New York.</p>
        <p>At 6 feet 5 inches tall and a solid 300 pounds, Mr. Harris, who is half Choctaw Indian, still appears the very image of the lineman he once was.</p>
        <p>With his stature and striking looks, he makes an imposing figure on the opera stage, where he specializes in dramatic roles. He has an affinity for Verdi and is often cast as Germont in ''La Traviata'' and in the title role of ''Rigoletto,'' which he will sing on June 22 at 8 p.m. and June 23 at 3 p.m. in a New Rochelle Opera production. (In the company's tradition of using double casts, Peter Hakjoon Kim will sing the role on June 23 at 8 p.m. and June 24 at 3 p.m.) The opera will be staged at the Frank J. Auriana Theater in the Mooney Hancock Arts Center of the Ursuline School in New Rochelle. Information is available by calling (914) 576-1617.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harris takes it in stride that people always seem fascinated by the opera singer who used to be a football player. He says it is hard to beat the stereotype that rough sports and soul-shaking art don't mix. In an interview he recalled the reaction of a ''steroid-jock-looking young man'' who heard him talking on the radio at the beginning of his opera career. ''He came up to me and said, 'I really want to thank you for showing that we jocks have a sensitive side, because I like to write poetry,' '' Mr. Harris said. ''For me, that was a touchdown.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Harris says opera singers are commonly viewed as alien creatures. But he says athletes and singers face similar physical and mental challenges.</p>
        <p>''In football, the question is, 'Can we run through that wall over there?' Someone says yes, and you run through it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But singers must also use their bodies to create a maximum impact. ''The opera stage is not like a TV set,'' he said. ''You have to move columns of air and move that voice to fill a large space. At the same time, you must create a character -- like Rigoletto -- who is not just believable but bigger than life.''</p>
        <p>Growing up in a family of gospel singers, Mr. Harris began singing at 4, took private lessons with his junior high school choir teacher and continued studying through his college years at Oklahoma State University. He also studied at the University of Houston during his time with the Oilers. When back, neck and leg injuries persuaded him to stop playing football, he studied in the opera program at what is now Texas State University.</p>
        <p>He and his wife and manager, Renee Guerrero-Harris, say his goal is to sing on the stage of the Metropolitan Opera in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>In between his roles, Mr. Harris and his wife, a pianist, collaborate on an educational program, ''From Football to Opera,'' that is based on his own life. Presented at schools and community centers, it uses storytelling and singing to teach children about imagination, he said.</p>
        <p>''We try to give them the courage to experience the performing arts,'' said Mr. Harris, who has a daughter, 10, and a son, 6, with his wife, and a 29-year-old son from a previous marriage. ''As an ex-pro athlete, I can give them the permission to do something that ordinarily wouldn't be cool.''</p>
        <p>PERFORMER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
