<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Next in Child Prodigies -- the Gamer</title>
    <meta content="17slat" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/weekinreview/17slat.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="IDEAS &amp; TRENDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E7D7153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Next in Child Prodigies -- the Gamer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Next in Child Prodigies  the Gamer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELLE SLATALLA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE a lot of parents, I've always thought the phrase ''child prodigy'' had a nice ring to it.</p>
        <p>Until recently, though, I was thinking along the lines of ''violin prodigy,'' ''tennis prodigy'' and ''child model prodigy.'' But after a few setbacks (one of my children claimed a skin sensitivity to rosin, a second refused to develop a clay-court drop shot and the third pulled me aside on the set to confide that some of the other models ''smell funny''), I realized I might need to consider other possibilities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Considering everything else that children do obsessively, is it bad for them to play Xbox for money?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE a lot of parents, I've always thought the phrase ''child prodigy'' had a nice ring to it.</p>
        <p>Until recently, though, I was thinking along the lines of ''violin prodigy,'' ''tennis prodigy'' and ''child model prodigy.'' But after a few setbacks (one of my children claimed a skin sensitivity to rosin, a second refused to develop a clay-court drop shot and the third pulled me aside on the set to confide that some of the other models ''smell funny''), I realized I might need to consider other possibilities.</p>
        <p>So it was with some interest that I recently learned about another, less conventional route for budding prodigies: video games. Among the quick-thumbed contenders competing in the Major League Gaming Pro Circuit Event in New Jersey last week was a 9-year-old Long Island boy so adept at the Halo 2 shoot-'em-up game that he already has won thousands of dollars in prize money.</p>
        <p>Nicknamed Lil' Poison, Victor M. De Leon III spends about two hours a day honing his Xbox skills in his basement in Holbrook, where as reported in this newspaper recently, ''his tiny thumbs jabbed away at the controller, causing virtual mayhem of gunfire.''</p>
        <p>He finished out of the prize money last week, but already has product endorsements, expense-paid trips to tournaments and a bank account that his father says has almost enough to finance a private-college education.</p>
        <p>One doesn't have to be a visionary on the order of Steve Jobs to foresee the changes that Lil' Poison's success could portend: celebrity gamers gracing the covers of sporting magazines; network-televised video game tournaments (''The Twitchbowl''); and full athletic (or whatever) scholarships to Stanford.</p>
        <p>I could imagine some other things changing, as well. After all, I have my own 9-year-old.</p>
        <p>Me: ''Sweetie, get back on that console. You need to spend another 45 minutes mastering your Half-Life 2 gravity gun moves.''</p>
        <p>Her: ''Please, Mommy, can't I take a break and do my math homework for awhile?''</p>
        <p>Me: ''We've been over this before. How do you expect to get into a good college if you don't reach Level 27?''</p>
        <p>Her: ''But my hand hurts. This leather glove makes it sore.''</p>
        <p>Me: ''Ice it for five minutes.''</p>
        <p>The whole family could get involved. My husband, who never really liked playing sports with the children but who was rather good at Quake in his day, could coach. I can see him now, standing in his sweats with a whistle around his neck, his leather glove raised in exhortation, air typing.</p>
        <p>With luck, my daughter eventually might head down the same path as Johnathan Wendel -- better known to his fans as Fatal1ty -- who has won 10 world titles. He received his first video game when he was 5; now he is in his mid-20s, having amassed $500,000 in prizes and with his own clothing line.</p>
        <p>Of course, my daughter will need a nickname.</p>
        <p>Me: ''How about Chainsaw Chopper?''</p>
        <p>Her: ''I always liked the name Christie.''</p>
        <p>Me: ''O.K., how about X-sanguinator?''</p>
        <p>Her: ''Chloe?''</p>
        <p>I realize my plan may face other resistance, as well. Although for years it's been perfectly acceptable for parents to foster their children's special talents in certain arenas -- national spelling bees, soccer teams that travel to Sweden for tournaments -- there are those who fear the growing popularity of video games will destroy childhoods with the same ease as a Halo 2 player annihilating mutant alien races.</p>
        <p>Some of those naysayers belong to the same camp that in earlier days opposed such subversive ideas as television, comic books and Elvis's pulsating hips.</p>
        <p>As Dmitri Williams, an assistant professor of speech communication at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, put it in a phone interview: ''When a new medium shows up, there is almost always the same patter of reactions to it: Is it going to make us sick? What is it going to take the place of? What is it going to do to culture or morals?''</p>
        <p>Of course, watching Elvis's pelvis gyrate would not expose Chaingun Chloe to hours of violent, bloody content, the dangers of which researchers have been trying to measure for years.</p>
        <p>On one hand, studies show there's no doubt that exposure to violent games contributes to aggression in young children, says Dorothy G. Singer, a Yale senior research scientist and co-author of ''Imagination and Play in the Electronic Age'' (Harvard University Press: 2005). But on the other hand, other factors -- like warm relations with parents, good grades and plenty of friends -- can eliminate the risk, says Douglas A. Gentile, a psychology professor who runs the Media Research Lab at Iowa State University.</p>
        <p>The bigger issue, he said, is that turning a 9-year-old into a world champion of anything could rob her of a well-rounded childhood.</p>
        <p>Which is why I would need to get C'gun Chloe off the couch for some fresh air and physical activity.</p>
        <p>Me: ''Fatal1ty runs three to five miles a day for aerobic training.''</p>
        <p>Her: ''I like to jump rope with my friends.''</p>
        <p>Me: ''Wrap your wrists first.''</p>
        <p>IDEAS &amp; TRENDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
