<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Final Swing Typifies Beltrán's Struggles</title>
    <meta content="17mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/sports/baseball/17mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855272"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Beltran, Carlos</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rivera, Mariano</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Posada, Jorge</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E4DE123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="771" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Final Swing Typifies Beltrán's Struggles</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Final Swing Typifies Beltrán’s Struggles</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The impulse in Carlos Beltrán's brain fired a signal through his spinal column, to his hands, to his legs, that told him to swing at the first pitch from Mariano Rivera. He knew it would be a cut fastball. How could Beltrán not? That's what Rivera does. But when that cutter zipped toward him, darting upward at the last millisecond, Beltrán swung and popped up.</p>
        <p>The ball fell into Jorge Posada's glove, right by the Mets' dugout. Beltrán walked away. The three runners he left on base -- the potential tying runs -- jogged back toward him. Game over. Yankees win, 11-8. Mets lose.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Carlos Beltrán went 0 for 6 against the Yankees on Saturday, failing in four opportunities with runners in scoring position, and stranded nine runners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The impulse in Carlos Beltrán's brain fired a signal through his spinal column, to his hands, to his legs, that told him to swing at the first pitch from Mariano Rivera. He knew it would be a cut fastball. How could Beltrán not? That's what Rivera does. But when that cutter zipped toward him, darting upward at the last millisecond, Beltrán swung and popped up.</p>
        <p>The ball fell into Jorge Posada's glove, right by the Mets' dugout. Beltrán walked away. The three runners he left on base -- the potential tying runs -- jogged back toward him. Game over. Yankees win, 11-8. Mets lose.</p>
        <p>''It was right there, a good pitch,'' Beltrán said. ''But when things go wrong, they're going to go wrong.''</p>
        <p>There were several things for Mets fans to stew about during yesterday's 3-hour 43-minute epic at Yankee Stadium, which, partly because of a 40-minute rain delay, did not end until 5:32 p.m. Tom Glavine had another poor start, and the bullpen, particularly Guillermo Mota, continued to be ineffective. But, for a day at least, the most troubling aspect was Beltrán's continuing struggles, which were only underscored by his ninth-inning at-bat.</p>
        <p>In all, Beltran went 0 for 6, failing in four opportunities with runners in scoring position, and stranded nine runners. This month, he is hitting .143 with one extra-base hit, a home run June 6, and is hitless in his past 15 at-bats with runners in scoring position.</p>
        <p>''Just a few knocks, that's all he needs,'' Mets Manager Willie Randolph said. ''When I talk about hitters and ups and downs, this is all part of the season. He'll get going. He'll get right.''</p>
        <p>This, too, was Randolph's refrain during Beltrán's underwhelming 2005 season, his first with the Mets, when he did not resemble the dangerous middle-of-the-order presence they were expecting. Beltrán revealed later that year that he made a mistake in not going on the disabled list with a left quadriceps injury, and now he is battling similar discomfort in the same leg.</p>
        <p>Beltrán first acknowledged this year's edition of the injury May 6 in Arizona, when he asked out of the lineup a few hours before the game. Since then, he has had two magnetic resonance imaging tests, and fluid extracted.</p>
        <p>The pain has not gotten worse, but it has not gotten better, either. It affects his weight transfer, causing him not to feel balanced at the plate. He is getting out in front of the ball, a problem that could be solved, he said, by continuing to take extra swings in the batting cage.</p>
        <p>''It bothers me; I'm not going to lie,'' Beltrán said. ''I know that I can get better, but it's all a matter of time.''</p>
        <p>The only way the injury will heal is with rest, and he is reluctant to miss any time. But asked if he felt that he could benefit from being placed on the disabled list, he nodded.</p>
        <p>''Probably,'' he said. ''It's time off to get right.''</p>
        <p>General Manager Omar Minaya assembled the lineup with versatile hitters, anticipating that not every player would be hitting well at the same time. The Mets weathered rough stretches from David Wright and Carlos Delgado earlier this season and are facing another one just as Wright, who extended his hitting streak to 17 games yesterday, is appearing more and more comfortable. If Carlos y Carlos were a television pilot, a network probably would not pick it up right now.</p>
        <p>Coming off his four-strikeout performance Friday, Delgado went 2 for 5 and scored a run to raise his batting average this month to .203 and to .224 over all. He acknowledged that he had been trying harder to let the ball travel deeper and that he would like to hit more to the opposite field, but he said that he did not take anything from his two hits yesterday.</p>
        <p>''There's a big difference between your approach and actual execution,'' Delgado said.</p>
        <p>He singled to left to ignite the Mets' ninth-inning rally. They loaded the bases with two outs, drawing to 11-7 when Carlos Gómez's infield single drove in Delgado. Representing the tying run, José Reyes batted right-handed -- to neutralize Rivera's cutter, he said -- and fouled off three pitches after falling behind by 1-2 before ripping a run-scoring single to center. A switch-hitter like Reyes, Beltrán said he did not also consider batting right-handed in that situation because he felt more comfortable hitting from the left side.</p>
        <p>''I don't feel frustrated at all because I'm doing my best,'' Beltrán said. ''Sometimes it happens that way. Today was a rough game. Who knows what tomorrow brings?''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
