<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nassau Working to Close Gap in 2008 Budget</title>
    <meta content="17liweekLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/17liweek.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855001"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drunken and Reckless Driving</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Swimming Pools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Jon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saslow, Linda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Naughton, Eric C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drunken and Reckless Driving</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EEDB143FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1041" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nassau Working to Close Gap in 2008 Budget</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Week on Long Island</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA SASLOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Saslow, Linda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Week column; director Eric Naughton, addressing meeting of Nassau County Legislative Budget Review Committee, says that while some measures proposed to close 2008 budget gap are within county's control, others require state approval; Nassau County lawmakers are considering legislation that would create new crimes of aggravated vehicular assault and aggravated vehicular homicide and toughen penalties against drunken drivers; legislator Jon Cooper proposes law that would require all residential swimming pools in Suffolk County to have alarms installed; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While Nassau County could break even this year with proper management, it has a projected budget deficit of $142 million next year before any corrective measures are taken and a gap of $241 million by 2010, according to Eric C. Naughton, director of the county's Office of Legislative Budget Review.</p>
        <p>That was the message he delivered at a meeting last Monday of the county's Legislative Budget Review Committee, which focused on the first quarter of the 2007 fiscal year and the updated multiyear plan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>While Nassau County could break even this year with proper management, it has a projected budget deficit of $142 million next year before any corrective measures are taken and a gap of $241 million by 2010, according to Eric C. Naughton, director of the county’s Office of Legislative Budget Review.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While Nassau County could break even this year with proper management, it has a projected budget deficit of $142 million next year before any corrective measures are taken and a gap of $241 million by 2010, according to Eric C. Naughton, director of the county's Office of Legislative Budget Review.</p>
        <p>That was the message he delivered at a meeting last Monday of the county's Legislative Budget Review Committee, which focused on the first quarter of the 2007 fiscal year and the updated multiyear plan.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot of work that has to be done before Sept. 15, when the 2008 budget is due,'' Mr. Naughton said. Although some of the measures proposed to close the gap are within the county's control, others are ''iffy'' and require state approval, he said. The latter include a cigarette tax, video lottery terminals and the use of cameras to record the license plates of drivers who run red lights.</p>
        <p>Legislator Lisanne Altmann, the committee chairwoman, said there were no surprises at the meeting.</p>
        <p>''There is no question that the upcoming 2008 budget is the toughest we've faced in a long time,'' she said. ''We've drawn down most of our resources and used up the benefit of a large tax increase in 2002 that raised taxes by almost 20 percent. Now there's a great deal of concern that we'll have to raise taxes again, or as a last-ditch effort, make cuts in services.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Altmann said that the projected $50 million in property assessment refunds was low, but that the biggest risk in the budget was the sales tax revenue, which was lower than expected in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>''We had a 3.9 percent growth in revenues built into the budget, but the actual number was 1.9 percent,'' she said. ''To make our numbers, we would have to have more than 5 percent growth for the rest of the year.''</p>
        <p>But Thomas Stokes, deputy county executive, said that such gloom and doom was unwarranted.</p>
        <p>''A deficit has been predicted every year of the Suozzi administration, and every year we have had a surplus,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Tougher Penalties Sought For Drunken Drivers</p>
        <p>Drunken-driving convictions may soon become felonies in cases where anyone is killed or seriously injured, if a proposed bill becomes law.</p>
        <p>Last month, State Senator Charles J. Fuschillo Jr., of Merrick, and Nassau County District Attorney Kathleen Rice joined forces to introduce legislation that would create new crimes of aggravated vehicular assault and aggravated vehicular homicide with sentences of up to 15 years and 25 years in prison, respectively. The bill passed unanimously in the Senate, and is now in the Assembly, sponsored by Assemblyman Harvey Weisenberg, of Long Beach. If approved, the law would go into effect in November.</p>
        <p>Based on the proposed legislation, the crime of aggravated vehicular homicide would be a Class B felony and could apply to drivers in at least one of the following circumstances: a blood alcohol content of .18 percent or higher (the legal limit is .08 percent); a prior D.W.I. conviction within the preceding 10 years; an accident that caused the death of more than one person; an accident that killed one person and seriously injured another; or driving with a suspended or revoked license from any state. The crime of aggravated vehicular assault would be a Class C felony for drunken or drugged drivers who cause serious physical injury to another, under the same guidelines.</p>
        <p>''Last year there were almost 18,000 people in the United States who lost their lives at the hands of drunk drivers,'' Ms. Rice said. ''We must be willing to criminalize these offenders, and this bill will give D.A.s the tools we need to fight this epidemic and bolster the chance of putting drunk drivers who kill behind bars.''</p>
        <p>Under current law, the charge in these cases is usually second-degree manslaughter, which carries a maximum jail sentence of 5 to 15 years, and many violators get probation.</p>
        <p>Pool-Alarm Law Proposed In Suffolk After Child Dies</p>
        <p>If Suffolk County Legislator Jon Cooper has his way, all residential swimming pools in Suffolk County will soon be required to have alarms installed.</p>
        <p>After the accidental drowning of Anthony Muniz, 3, in a neighborhood pool in Shirley on June 6, Mr. Cooper said he would name his proposal ''Anthony's Law.''</p>
        <p>If approved by the County Legislature, which could happen as soon as Aug. 7, the law would require all pools and hot tubs to have alarms that would detect a person entering the water. It would require an audible poolside alarm and a remote alarm at another location on the premises. The cost for a good-quality alarm ranges from $200 to $350, Mr. Cooper said.</p>
        <p>Current state law, passed last year, requires alarms for all new residential and commercial pools built or modified after Dec. 14, 2006. Older pools are not required to have alarms, but Mr. Cooper said that was unacceptable.</p>
        <p>''That means that in Suffolk County, 98 percent of the pools wouldn't be subjected to the law,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But questions have arisen about enforcement of such a law.</p>
        <p>Suffolk County Executive Steve Levy said that it was unclear whether the health department had the legal authority to enter people's backyards, or the personnel to enforce the law, but that ''Mr. Cooper's proposed legislation deserves a review to find out the legal and practical effects of his bill.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cooper said many laws are difficult to enforce, including those mandating seat belt use and outlawing handheld phones for drivers.</p>
        <p>''But that doesn't mean we shouldn't have them,'' he said. ''Every year, almost 3,000 children under 5 either drown or are critically injured in residential pools. Even if we get half of pool owners to comply voluntarily with the law, just think how many lives can possibly be saved.''</p>
        <p>In Nassau County, Judy Jacobs, the presiding officer, also supports the idea of pool alarms, but said that county law does not cover building codes relating to residential pools. Ms. Jacobs said she recently wrote to leaders in the county's three towns and two cities, calling on them to require that alarms be installed in residential pools to alert pool owners if a child falls into the water.</p>
        <p>THE WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
