<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Heart of Hempstead</title>
    <meta content="LI--Hempstead" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/opinion/nyregionopinions/LI-Hempstead.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855005"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Long Island"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EEDB143FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="571" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Heart of Hempstead</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In the Heart of Hempstead</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hempstead Village has seen two recent attempts to revitalize its streetscape, both well-meaning and both badly flawed. One involved dropping big-box chain stores onto the edges of downtown, in the belief that the answer to tired old blight is fresh new blight. The other is an infusion of cash to put new streetlights and trash cans on Franklin Avenue as it enters Hempstead from Garden City, prettifying one of the most jarring boundaries between rich and poor, white and nonwhite, leafy streets and mean ones that you will see in any part of staunchly segregated Long Island.</p>
        <p>There has to be a better way to fix Hempstead, one that doesn't rely on bloated mega-retailing or street mascara. Mayor Wayne Hall Sr. thinks he has it: he wants to take the entire heart of the village, 26 underachieving acres dominated by car lots, derelict houses, garages and weeds, and rebuild it from the bottom up. He is pushing for a $2 billion development proposal from UrbanAmerica, a Manhattan real estate investment firm, which envisions 600,000 square feet of retail shops, 2,500 condominiums and a performing-arts center. It is a hugely ambitious and hopeful plan, but in a community whose many virtues are obscured by the visible scars of poverty and neglect, hope is a thing worth plunging into.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There has to be a better way to fix Hempstead, one that doesn’t rely on bloated mega-retailing or street mascara.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hempstead Village has seen two recent attempts to revitalize its streetscape, both well-meaning and both badly flawed. One involved dropping big-box chain stores onto the edges of downtown, in the belief that the answer to tired old blight is fresh new blight. The other is an infusion of cash to put new streetlights and trash cans on Franklin Avenue as it enters Hempstead from Garden City, prettifying one of the most jarring boundaries between rich and poor, white and nonwhite, leafy streets and mean ones that you will see in any part of staunchly segregated Long Island.</p>
        <p>There has to be a better way to fix Hempstead, one that doesn't rely on bloated mega-retailing or street mascara. Mayor Wayne Hall Sr. thinks he has it: he wants to take the entire heart of the village, 26 underachieving acres dominated by car lots, derelict houses, garages and weeds, and rebuild it from the bottom up. He is pushing for a $2 billion development proposal from UrbanAmerica, a Manhattan real estate investment firm, which envisions 600,000 square feet of retail shops, 2,500 condominiums and a performing-arts center. It is a hugely ambitious and hopeful plan, but in a community whose many virtues are obscured by the visible scars of poverty and neglect, hope is a thing worth plunging into.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hall argues that lifting his village out of the economic dumps will require a major upgrade of its fragile tax base, now overloaded with small storefronts, tax-exempt churches and empty lots. He says new development will substantially ease villagers' tax burden, one of the highest in a high-tax region. And he points out that with a big bus terminal and the first station on the Long Island Rail Road's Hempstead line, Hempstead is a perfect spot for the kind of pedestrian-friendly, mixed-use development known as smart growth.</p>
        <p>The Hempstead plan does seem to dovetail perfectly with County Executive Tom Suozzi's appealing but highly elusive vision of a New Suburbia, which seeks to rev Nassau's economic engines by rebuilding in depressed downtowns. But that doesn't make it a sure thing. The UrbanAmerica plan is years and many hurdles away from coming true. There is ever-present resistance to change, reinforced in all likelihood by people's low expectations for Hempstead, which has long been neglected terrain effectively walled off from richer Nassau. Mr. Hall's village board is not entirely convinced that big is better, and there are complications in a lingering lawsuit from the village's abandoned foray into big-box development.</p>
        <p>There is also concern that redevelopment will create a gentrified paradise that drives out the poor. The plan envisions market-rate housing for empty-nesters and single professionals, but no housing for poor or working class people. In a county so desperate for affordable housing, that's just wrong.</p>
        <p>Any starry-eyed homebuyer can see potential in a distressed property. Mr. Hall deserves credit for having a vision for Hempstead that is bolder and more far-reaching than most. His challenge now is to have the grit and wisdom to see it through, while making sure that the project treats residents and property owners -- particularly those in the development zone -- with decency and fairness. Mr. Suozzi, Hempstead Town and Albany should support him, and other village officials should work with him to improve the plan. But however the critics might want to challenge, tweak, overhaul or discard Mr. Hall's ambitions, they must offer something better than clinging to the status quo.</p>
        <p>Long Island</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
