<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mad Scionists: Young, Hip And a Bit Less Square</title>
    <meta content="17SCION" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/automobiles/17SCION.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855089"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DESIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Toyota Motor Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E6DE153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1340" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mad Scionists: Young, Hip And a Bit Less Square</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mad Scionists: Young, Hip and a Bit Less Square</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHIL PATTON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN December 2006, while other automakers were getting ready to unveil their new models at the Detroit auto show in January, Scion held a party in Miami. The guests were 300 owners of its cars who were entertained by the musician Ludacris. At the end of the evening, the new Scion xB and xD models were revealed.</p>
        <p>Since it came on the scene five years ago, Scion has made a point of doing things differently. Toyota's youth brand can brag of having the lowest average age, about 30, among its owners and of strong customer loyalty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since it came on the scene five years ago, Scion, Toyota’s youth brand, has made a point of doing things differently.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN December 2006, while other automakers were getting ready to unveil their new models at the Detroit auto show in January, Scion held a party in Miami. The guests were 300 owners of its cars who were entertained by the musician Ludacris. At the end of the evening, the new Scion xB and xD models were revealed.</p>
        <p>Since it came on the scene five years ago, Scion has made a point of doing things differently. Toyota's youth brand can brag of having the lowest average age, about 30, among its owners and of strong customer loyalty.</p>
        <p>The Scion xB shown in Miami is now arriving at dealers and suggests Scion is growing up. The original xB was a small boxy car with attitude. The new one is bigger -- a full foot longer than the last xB, 3 inches wider, about 35 percent roomier, 600 pounds heavier, 55 horsepower stronger and about 10 percent more expensive. It is also less fuel efficient. Fuel economy has declined to 22 city and 28 highway, from 26 city and 30 highway.</p>
        <p>The new box has lost the toaster-on-roller-skates look of the original; the wheels are an inch larger. It is no longer, well, as weird. It is also considerably zippier, especially in passing mode, corners quite respectably and rides much more gently.</p>
        <p>The new xB was designed at Calty, Toyota's design studio in Newport Beach, Calif., and takes its basic shape from the t2B (tall two box) concept, shown at the New York International Auto Show in 2005. The lead designer, Jin Kim of Calty, was senior designer of the more aggressive t2B concept, with its glaring face.</p>
        <p>But the new xB dilutes the line of the t2B so much that from some angles its profile suggests a miniature Land Rover. Its body has been puffed out with conventional fenders and the aggressive face of the t2B concept has been softened into downright amiability.</p>
        <p>Customers can make the new xB boxier using a kit of body panels from Five Axis in Huntington Beach, Calif., which built the t2B show car. That is what some xB owners are planning, judging from postings on Scion Web sites. Others are happy with the new box as is.</p>
        <p>One owner of the first generation xB, Frank Hoelck, 33, of Baltic, Conn., who customized his black xB, said, ''I was beyond thrilled with the new xB. Scion has really listened to what the owners had to say about the first generation xB.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoelck has been a Scion enthusiast since the brand first appeared. He is president of a club of Scion owners. ''I will buy a new xB as soon as this one is paid off,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At a recent press event, Steve Haag, corporate manager of Scion, said that owners had asked for a larger box. Mr. Haag also said that the company expected to sell about 170,000 cars in 2008, compared with 150,000 in 2007, a year when Scion was introducing new models.</p>
        <p>Scion comes from a word meaning offspring. It suggests zion, scythe, science, and overtones of the ''Matrix'' films. The logo is equally referential: Is that a shark fin? a tooth?</p>
        <p>Scion first appeared in 2002 at the New York auto show, when the company showed concept cars. The first production vehicles were shown in Los Angeles in 2003; sales began that June.</p>
        <p>The xB became a symbol of Scion. It was a virtual anticar. The original idea was to create a car as a social space or hangout in Japan, where young people lack privacy at home. In the United States, its anti-aerodynamic shape suggested a lack of interest in speed, acceleration or other values associated with the traditional auto enthusiast.</p>
        <p>Scion has been relentless in marketing its cars. The company has given away truckloads of caps, pens, keychains, magazines and CDs. It has held driver gatherings, concerts and art shows. It has jointly marketed with brands like Zoo York, the skateboarder-inspired fashion label. It appears at import customizer shows like Hot Import Nights.</p>
        <p>Scion has worked hard to wrap itself in music and art. The musical offerings include CDs of musicians like Peanut Butter Wolf and DJ Jazzy Jeff. Scion's art program included a series of shows around the country in which young artists were provided with panels from the cars or scale models of the cars to paint. For the new xB, with its square theme, the company gave the artists square canvases. Scion even opened its own art gallery in Culver City, an area of Los Angeles with an active art scene.</p>
        <p>Scion is pushing the new xB on the Web site want2bsquare.com, and has established presences for the model on the Internet sites Whyville (whyville.net) and Second Life (secondlife.com).</p>
        <p>But for all its viral marketing, Scion has also succeeded on its low prices, especially the tC with with the optional dealer-installed supercharger, a sporty coupe some called ''the baby Lexus.'' Analysts wondered if Toyota could possibly be making money on Scions, which are built in Japan.</p>
        <p>''Are you dumping?'' a journalist asked bluntly at Scion's recent press briefing, referring to the practice of selling cars at a loss to stifle competition or establish market share.</p>
        <p>''No,'' said Mr. Haag . ''Even if we didn't make a dime on it, Scion would have been worth it for what we are learning about marketing and younger customers for the rest of the company.''</p>
        <p>Certainly, Scion has shown Toyota in a new light: not just as a company known more for quality, with often dull if unobjectionable design, but as an innovator in design and marketing.</p>
        <p>But Scion's success also depends on its no-nonsense marketing pitch: few choices, no haggling, a square deal, one-price list. All the buyer picks are the color (there are six for the xB; all interiors are charcoal), transmission and wheel covers.</p>
        <p>Beyond that, Scion emphasizes accessories. Personalization is a crucial part of Scion's marketing and design. ''The car is a blank canvas,'' Mr. Haag said. The company offers both its own accessories, ordered through dealers as Scion Genuine Accessories or from the Optomize  line from others. Mr. Haag said that about half of Scion's customers accessorized their cars and the average spent for each car was around $1,000.</p>
        <p>Not all who bought a Scion in the early days of the brand were 20-somethings. ''I would see people my parents' age in them'' said Mr. Hoelck, the xB owner. ''It is economical, has huge space and is good on gas.''</p>
        <p>If the new xB suggests that Scion is maturing, Mr. Hoelck suggested that may be appropriate. ''The original owners are older now, too,'' he said.</p>
        <p>(For those who want a more basic box, Nissan is planning to bring a version of the Cube it sells in Japan to the United States.)</p>
        <p>''The question I am asked the most is,'' Mr. Hoelck said, '' 'Is it a hybrid?' ''</p>
        <p>Toyota offers hybrid versions of many of its vehicles, and some Scion owners were surprised that it had not introduced a hybrid, which Mr. Hoelck said Scion was considering.</p>
        <p>''It would be a perfect car if it were a hybrid,'' said the designer Karim Rashid, who owns a first generation xB. ''It has enormous room, is easy to handle and park, and frugally beautiful.''</p>
        <p>The 2008 xB is arriving at dealers now. The xD, a new model, built on the Toyota Yaris underpinnings and replacing the xA, arrives in August. It is a hatchback that reflects a dose of boxy design genes as well.</p>
        <p>But today, the box seems almost conventional.</p>
        <p>From the best of Toyota's design -- the innovation behind the Prius and FJ Cruiser -- the new xB seems to take a step back toward the least attractive parts of Toyota's design: the tendency to soften and dilute ideas and themes with the focus on not offending rather than actively pleasing. The original xB was daring, but with this one, Toyota seems to have returned to conservatism. Has it gone back to thinking inside the box?</p>
        <p>DESIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
