<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fusion Fare, With a Seafood Emphasis</title>
    <meta content="17dinenjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/17dinenj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855052"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/FREEHOLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Citrus (Freehold, NJ, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cook, Karla</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Seafood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E6D6143FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="859" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fusion Fare, With a Seafood Emphasis</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fusion Fare, With a Seafood Emphasis</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KARLA COOK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cook, Karla</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Karla Cook reviews Citrus restaurant in Freehold, NJ; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CITRUS is a dramatic kind of place, with high ceilings, pressed-tin walls and vivid murals reminiscent of Mondrian, Miró and Marimekko.</p>
        <p>The food can be dramatic and vivid, too. When this fusion food works, it really works.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Citrus in Freehold is a dramatic place decorated with vivid murals, and the food can be dramatic and vivid, too.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CITRUS is a dramatic kind of place, with high ceilings, pressed-tin walls and vivid murals reminiscent of Mondrian, Miró and Marimekko.</p>
        <p>The food can be dramatic and vivid, too. When this fusion food works, it really works.</p>
        <p>On one Saturday night, the tuna tartare was a luscious mound of tender, sweet meat with just enough ginger, cilantro, scallions and jalapeño to turn the dish from pleasant to memorable. The lemon-ginger crab cake was a light concoction turned slightly exotic with its red-pepper coconut sauce and drips of cilantro oil. Chubby mussels were bathed in a heady broth flavored with sake, coconut milk, cilantro and lime -- with plenty of bread available for sopping.</p>
        <p>On another night, a Thursday, the flavors were there, but fewer dishes had the spark.</p>
        <p>The man behind Citrus is Steven Mezzadri, who opened the 100-seat restaurant in May 2004, after working in New York in finance, cooking at home to replicate meals he had enjoyed in the city and doing informal catering. In the past year, wanting to pursue other culinary interests, he put the restaurant on the market, but the listing expired, and he says he is not actively seeking a buyer.</p>
        <p>In starting Citrus, Mr. Mezzadri wanted a fresh place -- ''a breath of fresh air,'' he says -- and Citrus is that, in its décor and sometimes in its food.</p>
        <p>The menu is simple, with one page for appetizers, one for salads, a third for main courses, and a mini-page for desserts. It's weighted toward seafood -- half the main dishes are seafood, and of seven appetizers, there are only two nonseafood options: a curious little sampler of wrapped or bready items (including a spanakopita takeoff and an egg-roll variation with jerked chicken) and a dish of delicious (though out-of-season) butternut squash ravioli, lightened only with a few bits of grilled asparagus.</p>
        <p>The pistachio-crusted shrimp was tender and juicy but overcoated and out of balance. The tuna tartare that was so excellent on one night seemed more crudely cut on another. The fried calamari, delivered smoking hot, was a fine example of the ubiquitous dish; the mussels were luscious on two tries.</p>
        <p>Salads were overdressed and overgarnished. I wished for bigger bites of romaine in the Caesar, though the Parmesan crisp helped compensate. The calamari salad, tried only once, lacked balance; though the menu promised shaved fennel, my serving lacked the licorice flavor that lured me, and there was a surfeit of gari (sweet pickled ginger, Japanese-style). The passion-fruit vinaigrette couldn't meld the pear, Gorgonzola and baby spinach, and the won-ton crisps seemed out of place. I wished for a chili-pepper burn along with the green papaya and peanut in the Thai salad. Bibb lettuce salad was buried under dried cranberries, and the Tropica salad, with its litchi, toasted macadamia nuts and goat cheese, sounded promising but was uninspired.</p>
        <p>Main dishes generally reached the level of the appetizers, and occasionally exceeded it. Standouts included the seared ahi tuna, a fan of exceedingly fresh slices that was enhanced by the drizzle of wasabi oil and the double citrus of lemon grass and yuzu (also called Japanese citron). Also delicious was the seared and roasted rack of lamb, crusted with rosemary, thyme, Dijon mustard, garlic and onion. The oregano-garlic marinated roasted pork tenderloin was a runner-up, with a glaze flavored with oregano, cumin and more garlic and lime. And the risotto, with almost (but not quite) too much saffron, was beautiful to see and to taste on one night, with its rock shrimp, tiny peas and infusion of Parmesan cheese, and a rich lobster-bonito stock absorbed by the rice. On another night, the rice was undercooked.</p>
        <p>Sides were uneven. A mound of coconut rice beside a crisp duck breast was pleasantly and subtly flavored; a Japanese rice croquette was just sticky. And there weren't enough greens: a serving of a dozen haricots verts is more garnish than vegetable.</p>
        <p>For a sweet finish, choose the molten chocolate cake with raspberry sauce and vanilla ice cream. The heat from the cake sends the ice cream down in luscious, gentle waves -- the best fusion of all.</p>
        <p>Citrus  32 West Main Street  Freehold  (732) 294-0202  www.citrusnj.com</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE Ceilings and walls of pressed, painted tin; vivid murals. Wheelchair access.  THE CROWD Can be a little noisy as the number of diners goes up; servers were affable, but seemed in short supply on one weeknight. A smattering of children.  THE BAR Bring your own.  THE BILL Appetizers, $9 to $12; salads, $7 to $12; main dishes, $19 to $34. All major credit cards.  WHAT WE LIKE Tuna tartare, fried calamari, lemon-ginger crab cakes, butternut squash ravioli with sage cream sauce, lemon grass chili mussels; rack of lamb, New York strip steak, glazed pork loin, seared ahi tuna, rock shrimp risotto; molten chocolate cake with raspberry sauce and vanilla ice cream.  IF YOU GO Dinner: Tuesday to Thursday, 5:30 to 10 p.m.; Friday and Saturday, 5:30 to 11 p.m.; Sunday, 5:30 to 8:30 p.m. Reservations recommended on weekends. Limited street parking, but municipal lots are scattered along Main Street.  Reviewed June 17, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/FREEHOLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
