<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Oakmont, Don't Expect Surprise Winner</title>
    <meta content="17anderson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/sports/golf/17anderson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070621T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855258"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Anderson, Dave</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Palmer, Arnold</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Nicklaus, Jack</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DE123FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Oakmont, Don't Expect Surprise Winner</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Don’t Expect a Surprise Winner at Oakmont</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As golf balls disappear into Oakmont Country Club's whisk-broom rough and slide past the cup on its linoleum-slick greens, the 107th United States Open has been a torturous and tedious march of the world's best players through these hills above the Allegheny River outside Pittsburgh. Not many birdies, too many bogeys.</p>
        <p>But when this Open boils down to the final holes today, the bogeys will be as dramatic as the birdies. And if Oakmont history prevails, a famous and familiar golfer will win.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When this U.S. Open boils down to the final holes Sunday, the bogeys will be as dramatic as the birdies. And if Oakmont history prevails, a famous and familiar golfer will win.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As golf balls disappear into Oakmont Country Club's whisk-broom rough and slide past the cup on its linoleum-slick greens, the 107th United States Open has been a torturous and tedious march of the world's best players through these hills above the Allegheny River outside Pittsburgh. Not many birdies, too many bogeys.</p>
        <p>But when this Open boils down to the final holes today, the bogeys will be as dramatic as the birdies. And if Oakmont history prevails, a famous and familiar golfer will win.</p>
        <p>Occasionally a stranger wins the Open, notably Jack Fleck in 1955 and Orville Moody in 1969, but in six of the seven previous Opens at Oakmont, a marquee name has won -- Jack Nicklaus in 1962 (in an 18-hole playoff with Arnold Palmer), Ben Hogan in 1953, Ernie Els in 1994, Johnny Miller in 1973, Larry Nelson in 1983 and Tommy Armour in 1927.</p>
        <p>And now, this era's most famous and familiar golfer, Tiger Woods, is poised for a mano-a-mano duel in the final pairing with Aaron Baddeley of Australia, the leader by two strokes at two over par. After a 69, Woods was alone in second place, one stroke ahead of Justin Rose of England, Stephen Ames of Canada and Bubba Watson, the long-hitting Floridian.</p>
        <p>The only surprise winner here was Sam Parks Jr., a local club pro at South Hills who played several practice rounds at Oakmont before the 1935 Open, but with a 19-over-par total of 299, he was more survivor than stranger.</p>
        <p>The other six winners here are either in the World Golf Hall of Fame (Nicklaus, Hogan, Miller, Nelson, Armour) or will be (Els). Even four of the second-place finishers are in the Hall (Palmer, Sam Snead, Tom Watson and Harry Cooper).</p>
        <p>The Open at Oakmont has often been a fork in the road of golf history, especially for Nicklaus, Hogan and Miller.</p>
        <p>Nicklaus, a 22-year-old rookie pro in 1962, snatched the torch from Palmer in winning his first of a record 18 majors. Palmer, the son of the pro at the nearby Latrobe Country Club, was a native son and America's most popular golfer. He had played Oakmont occasionally ever since he was 12 years old.</p>
        <p>''All I heard in that day was how great Oakmont was and how much everybody enjoyed playing and this was 1941,'' Palmer said Wednesday during a visit to Oakmont. ''My father and I came here and we played, and it was one of the great thrills of my life.''</p>
        <p>Palmer later won the Western Pennsylvania Amateur at Oakmont, and after having won the Masters for the third time in 1962, as well as the 1960 Open and the 1961 British Open, he was the Open favorite at Oakmont. But he three-putted seven times over 72 holes and three times in the playoff as Nicklaus won, 71 to 74. Nicklaus three-putted once over 90 holes.</p>
        <p>Els won in a playoff in 1994, when he was 24. He defeated Loren Roberts with a par on the 20th hole after each had shot 74 and eliminated Colin Montgomerie, who had struggled to a 78 in the steamy heat. That 1994 Open was also Palmer's last.</p>
        <p>Hogan's six-stroke wire-to-wire victory over Snead in 1953 was the centerpiece of the only same-year Masters-United States Open-British Open triple; even Nicklaus and Tiger Woods have not matched it. It was Hogan's record-sharing fourth United States Open; he also won the 1951 Masters and two P.G.A. Championships for a career total of nine majors.</p>
        <p>Miller's eight-under 63 in 1973 is considered by many historians to be the finest final round in a major. As the NBC television commentator at this year's Open, he returned here to hugs and handshakes.</p>
        <p>''At first, Oakmont I don't think loved it too much,'' Miller said Tuesday, alluding to his nine-birdie round, ''But it brought a lot of notoriety to Oakmont. People keep talking about it; every year they talk about it. So it keeps Oakmont's name out there a little bit more than maybe it would have.''</p>
        <p>Nelson, who also won the 1981 and 1987 P.G.A. Championships, was a Vietnam veteran who didn't begin playing golf until he was 22. After a shaky first 36 holes in 1983, he closed with 65-67, still the Open record for the final 36 holes.</p>
        <p>Sunday's round was stopped by a late thunderstorm. Knowing he had to resume Monday at the par-3 16th hole, Nelson hit 4-wood tee shots on the practice range, but when the siren sounded, he pulled his 4-wood to the far left corner of the green, about 60 feet from the cup. He holed the putt for a birdie 2, the stroke that dethroned Watson.</p>
        <p>In the years before the Masters began in 1934, Armour, known as the Silver Scot, was only the third golfer to win the United States Open, the British Open and the P.G.A. Championship (Walter Hagen and Jim Barnes were the others). He later was a renowned teaching pro at Winged Foot.</p>
        <p>So those have been the names of six Open champions at Oakmont, the names of the golfers that for one tournament conquered this brutally difficult golf course, the names (except for the local boy who made good, Sam Parks Jr.) that have been familiar and famous ever since.</p>
        <p>And today a new name will be added. Maybe a new and different name, but possibly this era's most famous and familiar one.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 21, 2007, Thursday  A picture caption in some copies on Sunday with a Sports of The Times column, about the success of famous players at the United States Open, included incorrect information from The Associated Press about the golfer shown hitting out of sand at the 1953 Open. It was an unidentified golfer; it was not Ben Hogan, who won the tournament. (Research by The Times and by The A.P. failed to produce an identification.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 21, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>A picture caption in some copies on Sunday with a Sports of The Times column, about the success of famous players at the United States Open, included incorrect information from The Associated Press about the golfer shown hitting out of sand at the 1953 Open. It was an unidentified golfer; it was not Ben Hogan, who won the tournament. (Research by The Times and by The A.P. failed to produce an identification.)</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
