<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Basics; Fluent in Politics, but Will It Translate?</title>
    <meta content="17basicA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855206"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E7D7153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Basics; Fluent in Politics, but Will It Translate?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH WHEATON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hablas español?</p>
        <p>That was a question raised when the presidential candidates recently were invited to debate on Univision, the nation's fifth-largest television network and the top Spanish-language outlet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hablas español?</p>
        <p>That was a question raised when the presidential candidates recently were invited to debate on Univision, the nation's fifth-largest television network and the top Spanish-language outlet.</p>
        <p>Two Democrats quickly accepted: Gov. Bill Richardson of New Mexico and Senator Christopher J. Dodd of Connecticut, and for good reason. They're the only two who speak Spanish fluently.</p>
        <p>With the United States growing more diverse, and the world pushed closer by globalization, fluency in a second language might not be a bad job skill for a president.</p>
        <p>Other leaders have found it useful. Angela Merkel, the German chancellor, and Vladimir V. Putin, the Russian president, speak each other's language, she from growing up in East Germany, he from K.G.B. work. Tony Blair, the departing British prime minister, speaks French. Most Middle Eastern heads of state speak English.</p>
        <p>So can any of the other 16 people who have set up presidential exploratory committees speak a language other than English?</p>
        <p>Yes, though only a few, according to a survey of the campaigns. All but the campaigns of Rudolph W. Giuliani responded.</p>
        <p>Three say they speak French: Mr. Richardson, a former ambassador to the United Nations; Mitt Romney, a former Republican governor of Massachusetts; and Mike Gravel, a Democrat and former Alaskan senator. Mr. Romney learned the language as a Mormon missionary. Mr. Gravel grew up in a French-Canadian household.</p>
        <p>Jim Gilmore, a former Republican governor of Virginia, says he speaks German. He was stationed in Germany as an Army counterintelligence officer.</p>
        <p>Then there is Mike Huckabee, a former Republican governor of Arkansas. He can't speak another language, but says he can read Greek, which he studied to become a Baptist pastor.</p>
        <p>Of all languages other than English, though, Spanish would seem to be the one best suited to the nation's political mix.</p>
        <p>Hispanics are the largest minority group in the United States, about 15 percent of the population, and the fastest-growing one, though voter registration and turnout rates are lower than for blacks and whites. Several states with large Hispanic populations, including Florida, California and New York, have moved up their primaries.</p>
        <p>Mr. Richardson, the only Hispanic candidate, grew up speaking Spanish. Mr. Dodd picked it while in the Peace Corps in the Dominican Republic.</p>
        <p>Two potential candidates are studying Spanish, Mayor Michael Bloomberg of New York and Newt Gingrich, the former Republican speaker of the House.</p>
        <p>On a recent trip to Mexico, the mayor fielded questions from reporters and responded in passable Spanish. Mr. Gingrich, who was criticized recently for equating bilingual education with teaching ''the language of living in a ghetto,'' later apologized in Spanish, saying his word choice was poor and he wasn't attacking the language.</p>
        <p>Senator Barack Obama, a Democrat from Illinois, attempted Spanish last year when he delivered his party's Spanish-language radio address. But his Spanish is limited, and the taping of the speech was ''tedious,'' the Chicago Tribune's political blog reported.</p>
        <p>SARAH WHEATON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
