<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Union Street Hall of Fame</title>
    <meta content="17scul" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/nyregion/thecity/17scul.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855158"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: CARROLL GARDENS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Italian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Matarazzo, Santo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Neuman, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E4DA153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="696" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Union Street Hall of Fame</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Union Street Hall of Fame</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM NEUMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Neuman, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Santo Matarazzo, 78, resident of Union Street in Carroll Gardens, Brooklyn; former brownstone restorer turned sculptor comments on his creations, including several prominent figures of Italian descent; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NO one who walks by Santo Matarazzo's neatly kept brownstone on Union Street in Carroll Gardens, Brooklyn, is likely to guess at the personalities gathered inside.</p>
        <p>The first to greet you as you enter the door is Leonardo DiCaprio. Farther along, two former presidents, Bill Clinton and Jimmy Carter, appear perfectly at home in Mr. Matarazzo's cozy den. They share the room with the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr., a youthful Muhammad Ali, Mother Teresa and several prominent figures of Italian descent, including Francis J. Mugavero, the longtime bishop of Brooklyn, and a postwar mayor of Florence named Giorgio La Pira.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Santo Matarazzo decided to retire from doing plaster work on brownstones, he began creating plaster sculptures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NO one who walks by Santo Matarazzo's neatly kept brownstone on Union Street in Carroll Gardens, Brooklyn, is likely to guess at the personalities gathered inside.</p>
        <p>The first to greet you as you enter the door is Leonardo DiCaprio. Farther along, two former presidents, Bill Clinton and Jimmy Carter, appear perfectly at home in Mr. Matarazzo's cozy den. They share the room with the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr., a youthful Muhammad Ali, Mother Teresa and several prominent figures of Italian descent, including Francis J. Mugavero, the longtime bishop of Brooklyn, and a postwar mayor of Florence named Giorgio La Pira.</p>
        <p>It is a varied crowd, about a dozen in all, but Mr. Matarazzo is intimately acquainted with each one of them. He created them with his own hands, in the form of plaster busts and statues.</p>
        <p>Mr. Matarazzo, 78, is a sculptor. He has silvery hair and a workman's leathery hands. But he came to the art late in life -- about five years ago -- and, even more unusual, his apprenticeship came in the unexpected field of brownstone renovation.</p>
        <p>Soon after emigrating from Italy in the early 1950s, he bought the brownstone on Union Street for about $6,500. Few people in the neighborhood at the time realized the potential value of their homes.</p>
        <p>''This was like a slum,'' Mr. Matarazzo said, ''and everybody was running away from here. And I say: 'Why are they leaving? These are beautiful buildings.' ''</p>
        <p>He began renovating his home while working at jobs like carpenter and house painter. Eventually, he took a job building window displays for department stores, but he also began spreading the gospel of brownstone renovation, working on local houses and teaching others what he knew. A craftsman with an Old World sensibility, he restored fine plaster detailing and rebuilt neglected cornices.</p>
        <p>''Everybody,'' he recalled, ''knew me as Mr. Brownstone.''</p>
        <p>Several years ago, however, Mr. Matarazzo, who lives with his wife and adult daughter, decided that he could not keep clambering up ladders to fit moldings onto 14-foot ceilings. He was familiar with plaster from his renovation work, so he taught himself to make plaster busts and statues.</p>
        <p>''I'm not an artist with a certificate,'' he said. ''But I don't think a certificate means anything.''</p>
        <p>His first major project was a seven-foot-tall statue of William Floyd, a signer of the Declaration of Independence who was born on Long Island. Mr. Matarazzo owns a cottage in Mastic Beach, and he was used to seeing Floyd's name on local schools and roads, although no one he asked seemed to know who Floyd was.</p>
        <p>Back in Italy, he said, a historic figure of that sort would merit a statue in the town plaza, and he set out to rectify the oversight. He could not, however, afford to have the large statue cast in bronze, and he told local officials that he would give them the statue for free if they would pay for the casting. A beautification group stepped in and arranged financing, and the statue was erected last fall at a library in Shirley.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Matarazzo began work on the omnium-gatherum of celebrated individuals that now populate his home. He conceded that at times he has to identify one or two of the busts to visitors who do not recognize the subject. ''This isn't photography,'' he said. Sometimes he sits in his den and talks to his statues.</p>
        <p>''I talk to Mother Teresa, I talk to Martin Luther King,'' he said. ''I say to them my problems. People today are busy; you can't talk to them.'' Mr. Matarazzo says he would like to give away more of his statues and see them cast in bronze.</p>
        <p>He thinks that his bust of Dr. King, for example, would make a nice addition to the plaza in front of the State Supreme Court building in Downtown Brooklyn, where it could stand opposite an existing bronze bust of Robert Kennedy. He has raised the possibility with the Brooklyn borough president's office, but he is reluctant to push too hard.</p>
        <p>''I do the work, I want to donate,'' he said. ''Then if they want it, they want it.''</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: CARROLL GARDENS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
