<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Homes Confront Old Burial Grounds</title>
    <meta content="17nati" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/business/yourmoney/17natreal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855080"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NATIONAL PERSPECTIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06EFDF153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Homes Confront Old Burial Grounds</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Homes Confront Old Burial Grounds</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE GALBRAITH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DAC ENTERPRISES, a small, mostly residential developer in Georgia, bought about 118 acres in Hall County, just south of the city of Lula, with the idea of selling lots to builders to put up single-family houses. The transaction, which was completed in 2004, seemed routine for the fast-growing exurb, 50 miles northeast of Atlanta.</p>
        <p>But it turned out that the developer was in for a surprise -- one that he says cost him about $40,000. In one patch of the land, hiding beneath bushes and trees, was a cemetery -- 22 graves dating to the mid-19th century, including one for Neverson Cook, a veteran of the War of 1812. Only two were marked with inscribed stones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the suburbs swell in some Southern states, developers must sometimes grapple with the problem of what to do when an old cemetery lies in the path of the backhoes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DAC ENTERPRISES, a small, mostly residential developer in Georgia, bought about 118 acres in Hall County, just south of the city of Lula, with the idea of selling lots to builders to put up single-family houses. The transaction, which was completed in 2004, seemed routine for the fast-growing exurb, 50 miles northeast of Atlanta.</p>
        <p>But it turned out that the developer was in for a surprise -- one that he says cost him about $40,000. In one patch of the land, hiding beneath bushes and trees, was a cemetery -- 22 graves dating to the mid-19th century, including one for Neverson Cook, a veteran of the War of 1812. Only two were marked with inscribed stones.</p>
        <p>''We did not know it was on the property when we bought it,'' said Ray W. Gunnin Sr., the president of DAC.</p>
        <p>His company hired an archaeologist to determine the number of graves there and the precise boundaries of the cemetery. Mr. Gunnin said the cemetery was cleaned up and a chain-link fence erected -- not a legal requirement, but out of respect for the dead. ''We didn't want people riding bicycles and things like that across the cemetery,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He estimated his company had spent more than $5,000 to define and fence off the graves, which are now neighbors of around 70 new homes -- and said he lost $35,000 because he could not sell the cemetery space, which is on a ''nice little knoll that would have been a choice building lot.''</p>
        <p>Eventually, there will be 88 houses, with prices ranging from $130,000 to $160,000; many are already completed. ''The guy that lives next door to the cemetery thinks it's great,'' said Mr. Gunnin, who has given the homeowner a key to a gate.</p>
        <p>As the population of the suburbs and exurbs in some Southern states swells, developers must sometimes grapple with the problem of what to do when an old cemetery lies in the path of the backhoes.</p>
        <p>The issue is especially prevalent in the South, where ''in much of the 19th century, it was fairly common for families to bury on the property,'' said Thomas Gresham, an archaeologist whose Athens-based company, Southeastern Archaeological Services, assisted Mr. Gunnin. Mr. Gresham said that in his home county, Oglethorpe, there is one small cemetery per square mile.</p>
        <p>Large developers may encounter old cemeteries during a project perhaps once a decade, said Michael Trinkley, the director of the Chicora Foundation, a cemetery-preservation group based in Columbia, S.C.</p>
        <p>Small developers may run into them more often, Mr. Trinkley said, because they are less likely to check fully before buying a site. (In Mr. Gunnin's case, he walked the perimeter before buying the land but did not spot the well-hidden cemetery.)</p>
        <p>The frequency, though, is growing, developers and archaeologists say, as subdivisions and retail centers spread across former farmland.</p>
        <p>''Almost every state, if you discover human remains, requires you to notify the coroner first, to determine whether it is a crime scene,'' Mr. Trinkley said. Some states like North Carolina also require the state archaeologist to be contacted, he said.</p>
        <p>Developers often decide to built around the old graves rather than move them, because it is usually cheaper, less complicated and less likely to upset the public. Before moving them, developers must generally try to find any descendants and consult them. They must pay all costs of a move, and approval is required from the county or city.</p>
        <p>Developers say deciding whether to move graves depends on the number, their location on the land and the value of the property, among other factors.</p>
        <p>Moving a cemetery usually costs about $2,000 a grave, said R. Ward Sutton, a cemetery-services specialist from Rocky Mount, N.C., who moves at least 300 graves a year. Legal procedures can take two to three months, he said, though the developer may fence off the cemetery and continue to work on the rest of the plot.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gunnin said he never considered moving his graves, because of ''the red tape involved, and the legal requirements.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes, though, developers conclude that disinterment is unavoidable. Nancy Kinsey, the executive director of the Walton County Development Authority in Monroe, a town about 50 miles east of Atlanta and 50 miles south of Lula, found a cemetery last year in the middle of a plot of land that the development authority aimed to sell to a private developer.</p>
        <p>The cemetery, which dated back to the late 19th or early 20th century, held the graves of five adults and four children, including one infant. They were discovered after a worker grading the field turned up a skull. There were no markers.</p>
        <p>''I was sort of in the state of shock,'' Ms. Kinsey said. The police investigated, found no crime, and Ms. Kinsey hired Mr. Gresham to assist her.</p>
        <p>This spring, after months of trying inconclusively to identify the deceased, Mr. Gresham dug up the graves. All that was left in them -- including a skull, dentures, a tortoise-shell hair comb and handles left over from the rotted-away wooden caskets -- recently found a final resting place in the neat rows of Monroe's well-kept, modern cemetery, named Hill Haven, and Ms. Kinsey is ordering a small tombstone.</p>
        <p>She said the process cost the development authority $30,000 to $40,000 and took most of a year, though it did not slow development, because it occurred while the site was being readied for sale. A sale is pending.</p>
        <p>Although states generally require a search for descendants, the search does not usually have to be aggressive, said Mr. Trinkley of the Chicora Foundation.</p>
        <p>In the Walton County case, Mr. Gresham did extensive genealogical research, and Ms. Kinsey ran notices in a local publication (as required by law) seeking information about the deceased. When no one came forward with further information, Ms. Kinsey went to the County Superior Court, which gave her permission to move the graves.</p>
        <p>When descendants are found, the decision to move a grave or cemetery may not be an easy one. Milton May, a resident of Winterville, in eastern North Carolina, went through the process last December, when the graves of his great uncle, a Civil War veteran, and his great uncle's family of eight were moved to make way for a commercial development. He had known that the graves, on former family land, were there and had been tending to them.</p>
        <p>''You hate to see things happen, but you realize that time must go on,'' said Mr. May, who consented to reburial of the remains in a town cemetery.</p>
        <p>This was not the first time he had encountered this issue. A few years ago, a subdivision went up next to his grandfather's grave. That cemetery, which was known to developers, was fenced off but not moved.</p>
        <p>The worst-case event would be the desecration of graves -- a misdemeanor or felony in all states. Unscrupulous landowners may remove headstones to make their property more salable and do nothing else, or developers may discover old bones and keep on plowing -- actions that formed the premise of ''Poltergeist,'' a 1982 film in which a neighborhood built atop an old graveyard is haunted because the corner-cutting developer moved the headstones but not the bodies.</p>
        <p>In real life, it is impossible to know the extent of cemetery desecration, especially because many of the old graves are tucked away or forgotten. But Mr. Trinkley said it happened ''far more often than people realize.'' He said he was currently serving as an expert witness in three cases involving alleged grave disturbances.</p>
        <p>The good news, cemetery preservationists say, is that record-keeping is improving. Genealogists and groups like the Sons of Confederate Veterans are gathering data about the locations of local cemeteries and working to create databases or books. ''It's far more difficult for someone to say, 'Oops, I didn't know it was there,' '' said Robert Mitchell, a member of the group, who is a cemetery-preservation advocate.</p>
        <p>Then there is the issue of perpetual care, which can be thorny even for well-kept cemeteries. In Hall County, Ga., Mr. Gunnin is currently trying to persuade the city of Lula to take over his small cemetery.</p>
        <p>Dennis Bergin, the city manager of Lula, praised Mr. Gunnin for being cooperative but said the obligation ''remains that of the developer, as he acquired the land.'' But Mr. Bergin said that he was trying to get descendants of the deceased involved in perpetual care, and that a ''pretty good correspondence'' was under way.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gunnin said he remained concerned about the small cemetery's future. ''Who is going to take care of it when we are not going to do it permanently?'' he said. ''I don't want to own it.''</p>
        <p>NATIONAL PERSPECTIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
