<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hamas May Find It Needs Its Enemy</title>
    <meta content="17smith" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/weekinreview/17smith.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855232"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Hamas</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Fatah, Al</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E0D7153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1290" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hamas May Find It Needs Its Enemy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hamas May Find It Needs Its Enemy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG S. SMITH and GREG MYRE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ISLAMIST fighters of Hamas seized control of Gaza last week. For the first time in the history of the Palestinians' fight for nationhood, there seemed a real possibility that two Palestines rather than one might emerge -- one in Gaza, dominated by Hamas, the other in the West Bank, led by Fatah.</p>
        <p>But Palestinian society is not so simple. There are many historical, economic and tribal loyalties that bind it together, and many of those cross, rather than coincide with, the frontiers of the two territories.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two Palestines could emerge. But don’t write off the chances for unity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ISLAMIST fighters of Hamas seized control of Gaza last week. For the first time in the history of the Palestinians' fight for nationhood, there seemed a real possibility that two Palestines rather than one might emerge -- one in Gaza, dominated by Hamas, the other in the West Bank, led by Fatah.</p>
        <p>But Palestinian society is not so simple. There are many historical, economic and tribal loyalties that bind it together, and many of those cross, rather than coincide with, the frontiers of the two territories.</p>
        <p>In addition, there are compelling reasons why the two communities need unity.</p>
        <p>A look at the history of these territories, how they developed differently over time, and what their populations still share, shows why they are at odds now but also why it might be too early to write off the possibility that this breach can be bridged.</p>
        <p>They have always had distinct traits, culturally and geographically -- the West Bank supporting a landlocked urban and agricultural society, Gaza facing the sea.</p>
        <p>Those differences increased after the creation of Israel in 1948, when Gaza fell under the administration of Egypt and the West Bank was annexed by Jordan.</p>
        <p>Egypt treated Gaza as a Palestinian enclave and encouraged a strong sense of Palestinian identity. Many Gazans who studied in Egypt during those years were influenced, in turn, by the Muslim Brotherhood, whose goal is to establish Islamic theocracies across the Arab world.</p>
        <p>Back in Gaza, some of those men founded Hamas in 1987.</p>
        <p>Jordan, on the other hand, suppressed Palestinian nationalism in favor of Jordanian identity and Palestinians in the West Bank were more influenced by the secular societies of Jordan, Syria and Lebanon, where many went to study. Others traveled even further abroad, bringing back a liberal view of the world.</p>
        <p>By the time the two territories came under Israeli occupation together after the 1967 war, they were very different places. Their separate legal and educational systems weren't consolidated until after the Palestinian Authority was established in the mid-1990s.</p>
        <p>There were high hopes back then that the two territories could be tied together into a Palestinian state. In signing the 1993 Oslo accords, Israel pledged to treat the West Bank and Gaza as ''a single territorial unit'' and guaranteed ''safe passage'' for Palestinians traveling between them.</p>
        <p>A road specifically for Palestinians was established between the West Bank and Gaza, a distance of about 40 miles. It functioned, but sporadically, until the second Palestinian uprising began in September 2000.</p>
        <p>When it was open, the traffic was largely one way, carrying unemployed Gazans to the West Bank in search of work in the better economy there.</p>
        <p>But since Israel withdrew from Gaza in September 2005, effectively severing the remaining links between the two territories, the West Bank and Gaza have grown even further apart.</p>
        <p>Gaza, which has suffered the most economically in the past few years, has become increasingly conservative and increasingly religious, largely due to the growing influence of Hamas.</p>
        <p>Women in Gaza are more likely to be wear full Islamic dress and much less likely to work outside the home than their counterparts in the West Bank. Even in Gaza's large garment factories, the vast majority of the workers sitting behind the sewing machines are men.</p>
        <p>Gaza's cultural life tends to center on the local mosque, and its small anemic economy consists almost entirely of small-scale businesses and jobs provided by the Palestinian Authority.</p>
        <p>The West Bank, meanwhile, has a far richer economic life that includes industry, farming and a service sector. Its cities even have a few cinemas, art exhibitions, decent restaurants and a few night clubs.</p>
        <p>In some ways, the current conflict is a local dispute specific to Gaza.</p>
        <p>When Yasir Arafat returned from exile and established the Palestinian Authority in 1994, he divided his time between the West Bank and Gaza in an attempt to develop unity between the two territories.</p>
        <p>But within two years, his security forces in Gaza, led by Muhammad Dahlan, were cracking down on Hamas leaders. Many Hamas leaders were jailed and their beards shaved to humiliate them. Some claim they were tortured.</p>
        <p>Hamas has never forgiven Mr. Dahlan and other Fatah leaders for the harsh treatment, and those resentments have fueled tension in Gaza ever since.</p>
        <p>When Hamas won national elections last year and formed a government, no one expected Mr. Dahlan's security forces to submit to Hamas control. To counter Mr. Dahlan's power, Hamas organized a security force of its own under the Ministry of the Interior.</p>
        <p>It seemed only a matter of time before the two forces would clash in Gaza's narrow confines. The current crisis began when the Palestinian Authority president and Fatah leader, Mahmoud Abbas, appointed Mr. Dahlan as his national security adviser to oversee all security forces in the Palestinian territories.</p>
        <p>While Hamas is now in control of Gaza and Fatah of the West Bank, neither has achieved total political support in either place, and each organization needs a political presence in both places to remain viable in the long term.</p>
        <p>For now, Hamas appears to be winning, but its latest gains are primarily military, not political. While the movement is popular politically among the urban poor and the young in both the West Bank and Gaza, Fatah remains the stronger movement in the West Bank -- where people are relatively better off and where it has built an extensive system of patronage. It still has support among many moderate Gazans, too.</p>
        <p>Hamas's military victory last week obscures the fact that Fatah has been gaining political support in Gaza over the past year, according to Mouin Rabbani, an analyst at the International Crisis Group in Jordan. He says this may be because a larger percentage of Gazans depend on Fatah finances to make a living. Hamas, meanwhile, has been gaining support in the West Bank because Palestinians there are discouraged by Fatah's corruption and policy failures, Mr. Rabbani says.</p>
        <p>Hamas could face a backlash if Palestinians generally blame it for undermining unity. It could also be blamed for giving Israel, the United States and others further reason to isolate Hamas and work with Fatah in the West Bank at the expense of Hamas in Gaza.</p>
        <p>The Hamas-Fatah divide also cuts across clan lines at a time when clan loyalty has been growing stronger, in Gaza in particular. If political factions only bring more chaos and insecurity, clan loyalties could take over.</p>
        <p>Many ordinary Palestinians are upset with both factions for allowing the feud to spiral out of control and for their inability to work toward the larger goal of Palestinian statehood and the prospects of a secure economic future.</p>
        <p>Unity would be an advantage economically on the most basic levels: Gaza could be an outlet to the world for West Bank products; the West Bank could expand the prospects for jobs and living space for poverty-stricken, overcrowded Gazans.</p>
        <p>After the fighting last week, some people feared that Hamas might try to repeat in the West Bank the military victory that it won over Fatah in Gaza. But it is unlikely that that would sit well with the moderate Arab states that have backed Hamas and recently worked so hard to forge the unity government with Fatah that has now collapsed.</p>
        <p>Hamas could even find itself shut off from Egypt, which is wary of encouraging a movement on its border that is inspired by the Muslim Brotherhood, which Egypt fights at home.</p>
        <p>Palestinians in both the West Bank and Gaza, meanwhile, recognize that Fatah alone holds the lifeline of Western financial support.</p>
        <p>So if military dominance gives Hamas bargaining power, the economic imperative of a unified Palestinian body politic argues, in the end, for some accommodation with Fatah.</p>
        <p>THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
