<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Chance To Focus On Earnings</title>
    <meta content="17mark" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/business/yourmoney/17mark.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855176"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Standard &amp; Poor's Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE1DA153FF934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="541" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Chance To Focus On Earnings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Chance to Focus on Earnings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONRAD DE AENLLE</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Light economic calendar this week should give stock traders chance to look ahead to second-quarter earnings announcements; it might also provide respite from their fixation on bond market (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A LIGHT economic calendar this week should give traders a chance to look ahead to second-quarter earnings announcements. It might also provide a respite from their fixation on the bond market.</p>
        <p>Stocks seem to have plunged and soared on every tick up or down in Treasury bond yields in the last week or so. But while most of the ticks have been up, Stephen Biggar, director of American equity research at Standard &amp; Poor's, predicts that yields will have a minimal effect on current earnings. The yield climb happened fairly late in the quarter, so any significant impact is unlikely to show up until third-quarter statements are released.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A light economic calendar this week should give traders a chance to look ahead to second-quarter earnings announcements.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A LIGHT economic calendar this week should give traders a chance to look ahead to second-quarter earnings announcements. It might also provide a respite from their fixation on the bond market.</p>
        <p>Stocks seem to have plunged and soared on every tick up or down in Treasury bond yields in the last week or so. But while most of the ticks have been up, Stephen Biggar, director of American equity research at Standard &amp; Poor's, predicts that yields will have a minimal effect on current earnings. The yield climb happened fairly late in the quarter, so any significant impact is unlikely to show up until third-quarter statements are released.</p>
        <p>Mr. Biggar expects aggregate earnings for the second quarter to rise by 5 percent for companies in the S.&amp; P. 500-stock index, after an 8 percent gain in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>Among the 10 sectors into which S.&amp; P. divides its 1,500-stock index, which adds 1,000 small and medium-size businesses to the large companies in the 500 index, telecommunications is predicted to be the clear leader. S.&amp; P.'s analysts foresee a 26 percent earnings increase for the sector, compared with the second quarter of 2006, followed by a 20 percent gain for health care and 14 percent for technology.</p>
        <p>The biggest loser will probably be consumer discretionary companies, which include auto manufacturers and home builders; analysts predict a 7 percent earnings decline.</p>
        <p>The only other sector in which earnings are expected to fall is energy -- down 5 percent -- because the comparable quarter was exceptionally strong and will be a tough act to follow.</p>
        <p>It may seem odd, but rising bond yields may be good for share prices, even if they do little to alter earnings for this quarter, Mr. Biggar said. Fearful Wall Street analysts may be inclined to lower their earnings estimates, which could make the numbers seem that much better when companies announce them.</p>
        <p>''It's possible that there's going to be a little trail-off in expectations, given the late uncertainty over higher rates,'' he said. ''I would suspect that people will be overly conservative.''</p>
        <p>Whether interest rates or something else has been the culprit, analysts have underestimated earnings ''essentially every quarter since we came out of the 2001-2002 slump,'' Mr. Biggar noted. ''How can they call it so wrong? That's the game the Street plays.''</p>
        <p>DATA WATCH -- Among the few economic reports likely to capture investors' attention this week is the snapshot of the housing market, due on Tuesday. Housing starts are estimated in a Bloomberg News poll of economists to have fallen in May to an annual rate of 1.470 million units, from 1.528 million in April.</p>
        <p>The outlook is brighter for building permits, which tend to be assigned more weight by economists and investors because they represent future activity. Permits are expected to show an increase to a 1.470 million-unit rate in May, from 1.457 million.</p>
        <p>The Index of Leading Economic Indicators, due on Thursday from the Conference Board, is forecast to show a 0.3 percent gain for May after falling 0.5 percent in April. This bit of data seldom moves the market, however, because the future it aims to foretell has already begun to arrive by the time the report is published.</p>
        <p>MARKET WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
