<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Curb Job</title>
    <meta content="Hamill.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/17/books/review/Hamill-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855319"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Taxi! A Social History of the New York City Cabdriver (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E4DF1F30F934A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1313" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Curb Job</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Curb Job</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETE HAMILL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TAXI!</p>
        <p>A Social History of the</p>
        <p>New York City Cabdriver.</p>
        <p>By Graham Russell Gao Hodges.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 225 pp.</p>
        <p>The Johns Hopkins University Press. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Toil, trouble and the lonesome ride: the story of the New York cabby.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TAXI!</p>
        <p>A Social History of the</p>
        <p>New York City Cabdriver.</p>
        <p>By Graham Russell Gao Hodges.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 225 pp.</p>
        <p>The Johns Hopkins University Press. $25.</p>
        <p>TAXI drivers are the most enduring oppressed minority in New York City history. Race, ethnicity and religion are not sources of the oppression. It lies entirely in the nature of the work. Trapped for about 12 hours each day in the worst traffic in the United States, taxi drivers must suffer the savage frustrations of jammed streets, double-parked cars, immense trucks, drivers from New Jersey -- and they can't succumb to the explosive therapy of road rage. Their living depends on self-control.</p>
        <p>At the same time, they face many other hazards: drunks behind them in the cab, fare beaters, stickup men, Knicks fans filled with biblical despair, out-of-town conventioneers who think the drivers are mobile pimps. Some seal themselves off from the back seat with the radio, an iPod or a cellphone. All pray that the next passenger doesn't want to go from Midtown to the far reaches of Brooklyn or Queens. They hope for a decent tip. They hope to stay alive until the next fare waves from under a midnight streetlamp.</p>
        <p>In this informative, solid history, Graham Russell Gao Hodges traces the story of the cabdrivers from 1907, when the first metered taxis appeared on New York streets, to the present. He writes with obvious sympathy, having driven a hack himself before moving on to academic labors as a historian at Peking University and Colgate. Loneliness is a running theme in ''Taxi!'': if the title were not already taken, Hodges could have called his compact history ''One Hundred Years of Solitude.</p>
        <p>Across 10 decades, taxi drivers have worked alone in the most crowded city in the country. They've had a limited feeling of a shared fate in the taxi garages, or in certain cafeterias. But most of the time, even today, they move by themselves through the streets, alert for fares and dangers, paid to spend their days or nights with people they will never see again. When I was young, most of them had adopted a common strategy against loneliness: a fleeting intimacy with their passengers. This was the era of the cabby as philosopher or comedian, quick to make observations about life itself, or its subdivisions in politics and sports, or to crack wise about women and other mysteries. This form of performance art had two goals: human contact and better tips. Some of the cabbies (most of them Irish, Jewish or Italian) were very smart. Some were very funny. Some were bores. And one morning around 1972, I realized that all of them were gone.</p>
        <p>In the 1990s, I asked Edward Adler about this great turnover. Adler had been a taxi driver, had written a fine book called ''Notes From a Dark Street'' (1962) and had gone on to a successful career as a television writer. He answered: ''They drove cabs so their kids wouldn't have to drive cabs. When their kids finished at the university, they packed it in.''</p>
        <p>That theme also runs through Hodges' history. Few New Yorkers ever longed for taxi driving as a lifelong vocation. In different eras there were different motives: a fast buck to be made during Prohibition, carrying customers or shipments of booze to speakeasies; stopgap work during the first onslaught of the Depression; fill-in work (particularly among women) during World War II, when so many men were off at war or employed by military plants. For some, temporary work did stretch into a lifetime. Others walked away when the crisis had passed.</p>
        <p>A few did make a conscious decision to spend their working lives at the city's most lonesome and nerve-racking job. This minority enjoyed the work, its independence from office or shop, the adventurous feeling that no shift was like any other. After a few years, these drivers cobbled together loans from banks and relatives, and bought their own taxis. More important, they took possession of the precious medallion attached to the hood that made the taxi a licensed vehicle. The number of such medallions was fixed at 13,595 in 1937, in an attempt to limit the taxicabs in New York. Their value continued to grow, even when more medallions were created in the 1990s. The purchase price for individual medallions was about $20,000 in 1960, and by 2004 nearly $293,000. For owner-drivers this was the most important investment of their lives, their only chance at a dignified retirement. They became the equivalent of lifers in the Army.</p>
        <p>The owner-drivers, who worked in the same world as the drivers for the great taxi fleets, became a major problem in the long campaigns to unionize the industry. Hodges tells this part of the story superbly, drawing on accounts in trade and union newspapers, the memoirs of drivers (an enduring genre) and the city's dailies. Certainly there was a need for a strong union. The tens of thousands of drivers who worked for the corporate fleets were subjected to the vagaries of the shape-up, lacked guaranteed income, had no pensions. Things got worse in bad economic times. One of the great left-wing dramas of the Depression was Clifford Odets's ''Waiting for Lefty'' (1935), about New York taxi drivers. It ended with angry shouts of ''Strike! Strike! Strike!''</p>
        <p>But union organization drives and scattered strikes almost all failed, including those led by such labor stalwarts as Mike Quill and Harry Van Arsdale. Owner-drivers who continued working during strikes were often attacked, their tires slashed, their doors torn off by angry strikers. Passengers, including women, were dragged from back seats. But then the furies quickly ebbed. Slogans about solidarity were not matched by reality. Frequently, the need for change clashed with the individualism of the drivers, along with their need to feed and house their families (strike funds were never enough, or nonexistent). And, of course, most owner-drivers saw no justice in agreeing to strike against themselves.</p>
        <p>Over these years, cabdrivers became figures in popular culture. Hodges follows their evolution from the exuberant James Cagney (speaking a bit of Yiddish in the movie ''Taxi'') to Dick Powell (singing opera for his passengers in ''Broadway Gondolier''), all the way to the superb television series ''Taxi,'' with Judd Hirsch, Tony Danza and Danny DeVito, and Martin Scorsese's dark film ''Taxi Driver.'' The tough, fast-talking drivers of the early movies were perfect characters for love stories about class. But by the time Robert De Niro moved into the streets, New York was entering a nightmare phase in which the fatal combination of drugs and guns brought a sense of menace to the city, leading to widespread paranoia among drivers. Their slogan might have echoed De Niro's Travis Bickle: ''You talkin' to me?''</p>
        <p>That paranoia was not provoked by an urban legend; Hodges tells us that driver robberies rose from 438 in 1963 to 3,208 in 1979, and this fed the pervasive hackie racism of the 1970s and '80s. Many drivers refused to stop for African-Americans, switching on the ''off duty'' lights, feigning semiconsciousness. The authorities cracked down. Bulletproof partitions limited the old intimacy of passengers and driver. Plainclothes cops drove taxis, trying to trap criminals. But the sense of danger lasted into the Giuliani years, when violent crime finally began to decline. This was too late for many drivers, who had abandoned taxis forever.</p>
        <p>Today there are still cases of racial profiling, but the situation seems better. One reason: The departed drivers have been replaced by a new generation of hackies -- Indian, Pakistani, Russian, Haitian, African. By 2004, more than 90 percent of medallion drivers were foreign-born. Most drivers can't afford to turn down fares on the absurd basis of skin color. In my experience, most of today's taxi drivers are a silent minority. The days of philosophy are gone, along with the jokes. The need for tips goes on.</p>
        <p>Pete Hamill's 10th novel, ''North River,'' has just been published.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Pete Hamill's 10th novel, ''North River,'' has just been published.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
