<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Phone Cameras May Have Extras, But Don't Toss Your Point-and-Shoot</title>
    <meta content="05cell" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/technology/circuits/05cell.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852355"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PHONES AND PHOTOS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cameras</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cameras</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Nokia Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Samsung Electronics Co</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Motorola Inc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Sanyo Electric Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E2D91130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1098" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Phone Cameras May Have Extras, But Don't Toss Your Point-and-Shoot</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Phone Cameras May Have Extras, but Don’t Toss Your Point-and-Shoot</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROY FURCHGOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Furchgott, Roy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT one time, a cellphone with a built-in camera seemed as unlikely a pairing as a double major in organic chemistry and costume design, but many people now regard camera phones as de rigueur for spontaneous photo-ops. Yet continuous improvements in the camera portions of these devices raise a question for gift-givers: do people even need a regular camera anymore?</p>
        <p>Phone cameras have evolved from 1.3 megapixel point-and-shooters to more complex instruments with two to five megapixels (and even 10 megapixels overseas), built-in zooms, flashes and settings for nighttime shots and in-camera editing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Phone cameras have become more sophisticated, but most still need to focus more on image quality and ease of use.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT one time, a cellphone with a built-in camera seemed as unlikely a pairing as a double major in organic chemistry and costume design, but many people now regard camera phones as de rigueur for spontaneous photo-ops. Yet continuous improvements in the camera portions of these devices raise a question for gift-givers: do people even need a regular camera anymore?</p>
        <p>Phone cameras have evolved from 1.3 megapixel point-and-shooters to more complex instruments with two to five megapixels (and even 10 megapixels overseas), built-in zooms, flashes and settings for nighttime shots and in-camera editing.</p>
        <p>Yet a test of recent and soon-to-be-released phone cameras showed that while it is possible to produce first-rate images, most still need to focus more on image quality and ease of use.</p>
        <p>The number of pixels is not the whole story in photography, but for phone cameras, it is crucial. For instance, a two-megapixel image can make a decent 4-by-5 print. A five-megapixel camera can make a clear 6-by-9 picture or stretch into a slightly coarse 8-by-10.</p>
        <p>Some phones promote their brand-name lenses, but because these camera phones use such tiny, simple lenses the glass shouldn't influence your decision. Instead, try some test shots and ignore the marketing.</p>
        <p>Many phone cameras proclaim their zoom ability, but it's a digital zoom, which is inferior to the optical zoom found on most cameras. Electronically zoomed shots tend to be grainy.</p>
        <p>Still, phones are making headway in their photo features.</p>
        <p>NOKIA N95 -- This is a leader in the United States with its five-megapixel sensor and many features. Like a stand-alone camera, it offers light and focus settings including close-ups, portraits and landscapes. Its manual settings, however, are limited. The ''user defined'' option isn't really about customizing aperture or shutter speed, but a way to make your preferred settings the default.</p>
        <p>Like a camera, the N95 also has a flash, which is effective for short distances, and color effects, which allow for sepia, black and white, ultravivid colors and others. In addition, it has in-camera editing, including a rotate option and a shrink option. It is not currently offered through a carrier, so besides costing about $750, you will need to sign up for a service and add a SIM card. The N95 took a nice shot, but even in bright daylight, images had a slightly purple cast.</p>
        <p>SAMSUNG SYNC -- This is comparatively stripped down, but its two-megapixel camera offers a few extras (about $225, or $25 with a two-year AT&amp;T contract with an online sign-up). The camera has an option for sepia, black and white or negative. A playful feature, called frames, adds an illustration in the foreground so that a person can appear to be in a snow globe or driving a cartoon hot rod. Exposure can be adjusted manually from a four-way toggle, and there is a digital zoom, but it doesn't work when the phone is set to maximum resolution.</p>
        <p>It may be a basic phone camera, but the Sync had the truest color rendition in test photos.</p>
        <p>MOTOROLA RIZR -- The camera controls for the Rizr (about $250 or $99 with a two-year T-Mobile contract) are not in a menu but activated by a four-way toggle. It operates a zoom, lighting-selection controls from indoor to sunny and color effects -- a range from black and white to ''greenish,'' ''reddish,'' ''bluish'' and ''antique'' (orange). These effects tint shots so heavily it is hard to imagine how to use them. While there is no automatic flash, there is a light-emitting diode that acts as a rudimentary flash.</p>
        <p>Rizr photos had a reddish tint, which might have been corrected by changing the setting to ''sunny,'' but all the cameras were tested on the default setting of ''auto.''</p>
        <p>SANYO M1 -- This phone for Sprint (about $249, or $99 with a two-year Sprint contract) has a stubby design, but it offers many photo options in an easy-to-browse menu. For the photographer who knows his way around manual settings, the M1 has much to amuse, including manual white balance and force flash, a mechanism that sets off the flash in any lighting. It also has a ''frames'' feature like the Sync, though it works only on medium- and lower-resolution photos. With a built-in one-gigabyte memory, it may have the largest internal cellphone storage in the United States right now. One perplexing option is that you can turn off the automatic focus, but there is no control for focusing manually -- besides moving the camera forward and back. Photos looked warm and pleasant, without a noticeable tint.</p>
        <p>LG VX8700 -- This model is new and slim, with a case of brushed stainless steel (about $199, or $149 with a two-year Verizon contract). Its features include photometry, allowing you to choose between ''spot metering,'' which reads the light at one particular point in the image, and averaging, which averages the light of the entire scene. If you were taking a picture of a candle, for example, you would want to read the light on the flame, rather than averaging in all the shadow, which would create a photo of a yellow blur in the dark. One unfortunate feature is that if you forget to save a photo, it is erased after you close the phone. Shouldn't it default to save? It does have a nice on-screen brightness adjustment operated through a four-way toggle, and it offers in-camera editing.</p>
        <p>The test image was underexposed and a bit drab. A bigger problem is that the phone uses an uncommon Bluetooth standard, which makes it difficult to transfer photos wirelessly because few computers support this standard.</p>
        <p>Getting the photos from all the phones was fairly simple, after I conquered the learning curve. Only the N95 and the Sync had a side slot for a memory card, which can be put in a card reader for transferring photos easily. All the phones can send pictures to another phone or in an e-mail message, but the pictures are resized to a low resolution unsuitable for printing. All the test phones except the LG could transfer photos easily by Bluetooth at full resolution; it is like attaching a phone to a computer with a cable for downloading; the LG required more work. Some phones, like the Sanyo M1, have pictbridge, which transfers pictures directly to a printer. The Nokia N95 has a Wi-Fi connection for sending photos anywhere on a wireless system.</p>
        <p>These phones may be convenient and can produce fine shots for printing, but they still don't compare with a basic digital point-and-shoot camera.</p>
        <p>Sorry, gift-givers.</p>
        <p>PHONES AND PHOTOS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
