<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Opinions, Far Apart, Underscore Immigration Bill's Obstacles</title>
    <meta content="05deleg" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/nyregion/05deleg.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852369"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1D91130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1127" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Opinions, Far Apart, Underscore Immigration Bill's Obstacles</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Opinions, Far Apart, Underscore Immigration Bill’s Obstacles</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAYMOND HERNANDEZ</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representative José E. Serrano, Democrat of the Bronx, objects to a recent bipartisan proposal on immigration policy because, he says, it would create an underclass of immigrant workers with few rights.</p>
        <p>Representative Peter King, a Republican of Long Island, has a problem with the plan, too, but for an altogether different reason. To him, it amounts to amnesty for legions of illegal immigrants in the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Members of New York’s Congressional delegation are criticizing a recent bipartisan proposal on immigration policy from all sides.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Representative José E. Serrano, Democrat of the Bronx, objects to a recent bipartisan proposal on immigration policy because, he says, it would create an underclass of immigrant workers with few rights.</p>
        <p>Representative Peter King, a Republican of Long Island, has a problem with the plan, too, but for an altogether different reason. To him, it amounts to amnesty for legions of illegal immigrants in the country.</p>
        <p>And in the middle are lawmakers like Senator Charles E. Schumer of New York, who calls the plan a ''fair starting point'' to deal with the question of what to do about the millions of immigrants who are in the country illegally.</p>
        <p>A survey of lawmakers from the New York metropolitan region shows that they are every bit as divided about the comprehensive immigration bill now being considered in Washington as many of their colleagues around the country are.</p>
        <p>The measure, a result of negotiations between the White House and a group of senators from both parties, would offer legal status to most of the nation's 12 million illegal immigrants, increase penalties for employers of illegal immigrants and toughen border security.</p>
        <p>But the diverging views of lawmakers from New York, New Jersey and Connecticut underscore the difficulties, even peril, the plan faces, particularly as it comes under attack from grass-roots opponents on both the right and the left.</p>
        <p>Mr. Serrano, for one, questions whether a compromise on the plan can be reached in the current climate. ''Everybody seems dug in,'' he said in a recent interview. ''Right now, I don't see how it will happen.''</p>
        <p>On the other hand, ''it could turn overnight,'' Mr. Serrano added, referring to the impasse. ''One never knows.''</p>
        <p>The Senate, which began debating the bill in late May, is scheduled to resume debate this week. Critics in both parties have proposed substantial amendments.</p>
        <p>The legislation faces a more uncertain future in the House, which may take the matter up later this summer. Democratic leaders have raised their own objections to it and have said that Mr. Bush will need to deliver a significant number of Republican votes to ensure its passage.</p>
        <p>For many lawmakers in the region, particularly Democrats, one of the most objectionable aspects of the Senate bill is that it would make it harder for legal immigrants in the United States to bring over husbands, wives or children.</p>
        <p>The bill in the Senate would instead give priority to immigrants with specialized job skills, higher education levels and proficiency in English over those with family ties.</p>
        <p>Senators Hillary Rodham Clinton of New York, and Robert Menendez of New Jersey, both Democrats, are among those who have criticized the change in priority. Mr. Menendez, for instance, says that preserving family ties has been at the heart of the nation's immigration policy for decades.</p>
        <p>The two senators have proposed an amendment that would allow legal permanent residents to bring their spouses and children younger than 21 to the United States more quickly.</p>
        <p>''We have a national interest in fostering strong families,'' Mrs. Clinton said at a recent news conference announcing the amendment. ''While there is a big and contentious debate in our country over immigration, this issue should unite us all.''</p>
        <p>Another major area of concern is a provision that would allow hundreds of thousands of temporary foreign workers to be admitted to the country each year without many of the benefits and protections enjoyed by other workers.</p>
        <p>The protests have been especially strong among Democrats in the region, particularly liberals like Mr. Serrano, who are voicing concern that the temporary program creates a legion of workers who could be easily exploited.</p>
        <p>''Any time you set up a guest-worker program with no prospect for residency, you run the risk of creating an underclass of workers,'' Mr. Serrano said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schumer, the senior senator from New York, argues that Congress ought to act on the issue and has voiced support for two major provisions of the bill: one establishing a so-called path to citizenship for illegal immigrants and another imposing tougher sanctions on employers who hire illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>But like others in the delegation, he questions the idea of limiting foreign workers to two-year visas and then requiring them to leave the country for a year once those visas expire. He contends that many immigrant workers might be tempted to stay once their visas expired and, in the process, create yet another new group of illegal immigrants, according to his office.</p>
        <p>Representative Kirsten Gillibrand, a Democrat whose district runs from the mid-Hudson Valley to Lake Placid, raises a related concern about the temporary worker program. Many farmers in her largely rural district depend on immigrant laborers. She said that the provision limiting foreign workers to two-year visas and then making them leave the country for a year would be burdensome for employers.</p>
        <p>Like Senator Schumer, she said it would also lead many immigrants to stay and work illegally in the country once the visas expire. ''To me, it seems unworkable,'' she said. ''You just create another problem.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most contentious provision of the compromise bill in the Senate is one offering legal status to most of the nation's illegal immigrants. To become eligible for legal status, illegal immigrants would be required to pay fines, pass background checks and, usually, hold jobs.</p>
        <p>Some lawmakers say that this is nothing more than amnesty and that it would encourage more illegal immigration. Mr. King, the Republican from Long Island, has taken a much more conservative position on immigration than other members of the region's delegation. He said his office had received as many as 400 phone calls from people who were largely concerned about the legalization program.</p>
        <p>''No matter how they try to define it, that is amnesty,'' he said, referring to the bill and its supporters.</p>
        <p>Mr. King said that before he would consider any legalization program, he would want lawmakers to focus on strengthening border security more aggressively than the compromise bill stipulates.</p>
        <p>In fact, he said he was planning to introduce a bill in the coming weeks that would focus strictly on beefing up border enforcement.</p>
        <p>''We have to get much better control of our borders'' first, he said.</p>
        <p>But Representative Christopher S. Murphy, a freshman Democrat from Connecticut, rejected such a piecemeal approach. Though he objects to specific provisions of the Senate bill, particularly the guest-worker program, Mr. Murphy said Congress must devise a comprehensive plan that includes offering legal status to some illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>Paradoxically, that puts Mr. Murphy, who attacked Mr. Bush relentlessly during last year's campaign, in the president's camp on immigration.</p>
        <p>''Realistically, we are going to have to make a decision about who can stay and who we are going to force back to their country,'' Mr. Murphy said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
