<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Both Parties Expect Corzine's Choice for Chief Justice to Be a Fair and Moderate Voice</title>
    <meta content="05chief" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/nyregion/05chief.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852344"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4D91130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="886" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Both Parties Expect Corzine's Choice for Chief Justice to Be a Fair and Moderate Voice</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Both Parties Expect Corzine’s Choice for Chief Justice to Be a Fair and Moderate Voice</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN and RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, June 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Gov. Jon S. Corzine officially nominated Attorney General Stuart Rabner on Monday as the next chief justice of the New Jersey Supreme Court, he said he expected Mr. Rabner, 46, to ''shape our history long, long after this administration's service under the golden dome has long since passed.''</p>
        <p>But what kind of legacy might a Rabner court have?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Republicans and Democrats alike expect Stuart Rabner to be a moderate voice, given his strong belief in social justice and his record as an aggressive prosecutor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Gov. Jon S. Corzine officially nominated Attorney General Stuart Rabner on Monday as the next chief justice of the New Jersey Supreme Court, he said he expected Mr. Rabner, 46, to ''shape our history long, long after this administration's service under the golden dome has long since passed.''</p>
        <p>But what kind of legacy might a Rabner court have?</p>
        <p>Yes, Mr. Rabner, a career prosecutor, is a registered Democrat. And yes, he was plucked from the United States attorney's office in Newark to work for a governor who is a liberal Democrat, first as Mr. Corzine's chief counsel, then as attorney general.</p>
        <p>But those who know Mr. Rabner from his days at Princeton University, Harvard Law School and the world of federal prosecutors say he is hardly a political animal. In fact, they said he is such a man of integrity that he never played the usual games that might have won him a judgeship in his native Essex County.</p>
        <p>Instead, Republicans and Democrats alike say that Mr. Rabner is committed to being thorough and fair. So they expect him to be a moderate voice, given his strong belief in social justice and his record as an aggressive prosecutor.</p>
        <p>''I think he plays it straight; I don't think he's an ideologue,'' said Joel Suldan, a Harvard classmate who is now a vice president and general counsel at LifeBridge Health in Baltimore. ''He and I have not talked about specific political questions in 20 years, but I can't imagine his using a judicial office to make sudden changes in law. He respects the political process and democracy too much for that.''</p>
        <p>He is also circumspect. On Monday, for instance, Mr. Rabner declined to reveal much about his judicial philosophy during a news conference at the State House.</p>
        <p>He also demurred when asked how he would rate the Supreme Court under Chief Justice Robert N. Wilentz, who served between 1979 and 1996, presiding over what was considered a liberal activist court on issues like housing and education.</p>
        <p>''I'm a fan of a judiciary that approaches issues with no agenda, with no predisposition as to how to resolve questions, but looks at the facts and the legal principles and makes decisions in just that way,'' said Mr. Rabner, who would replace Chief Justice James R. Zazzali. Mr. Zazzali reaches the mandatory retirement age of 70 on June 17.</p>
        <p>Also at Monday's news conference, Mr. Corzine nominated Anne Milgram, 36, the first assistant attorney general, to replace Mr. Rabner as the state's top law enforcement officer. Both Ms. Milgram and Mr. Rabner must first be confirmed by the State Senate. Confirmation hearings before the Judiciary Committee are expected on June 18.</p>
        <p>Even before joining the Corzine administration in January 2006, Mr. Rabner had garnered hearty praise from Republicans, including his former boss, United States Attorney Christopher J. Christie. He also attended the Supreme Court swearing-in of Associate Justice Samuel A. Alito Jr., with whom he had worked at the United States attorney's office.</p>
        <p>Part of the reason for Mr. Rabner's equilibrium may be his background, said Amy Winkelman, now chief of the criminal division in the United States attorney's office. His parents are Holocaust survivors, and he has spoken passionately about the importance of justice. He has also served in the past as president of his synagogue in his hometown, Caldwell.</p>
        <p>''He's just got the strongest moral compass of anyone I know,'' Ms. Winkelman said. ''He's a very careful person, he's a very good listener, and he's very temperate in the remarks that he makes.''</p>
        <p>One example of his Joe Friday approach came in 1993, when he investigated comments about Republicans paying black ministers to suppress black voter turnout made by Ed Rollins, the Republican strategist, who was working for Gov. Christie Whitman. Mr. Rabner concluded that the allegations were not true, and Mr. Rollins later admitted he made up the remarks.</p>
        <p>''I spoke to a number of people who had been questioned, and they felt he was evenhanded in a situation that was high profile and could have been an opportunity to further some political careers,'' said Robert Mintz, a partner in the law firm of McCarter &amp; English, who worked with Mr. Rabner for nine years in the United States attorney's office.</p>
        <p>In another case, Paul Fishman, who was the head of the criminal division in the United States attorney's office when Mr. Rabner joined in September 1986, remembered Mr. Rabner telling him that some vital evidence from the investigation reports and grand jury testimony was illegally obtained and should be suppressed.</p>
        <p>''Now I would expect an assistant who was smart and who had good judgment to reach that conclusion and come to me with it,'' said Mr. Fishman, who recalled few other details of the case or even its outcome. ''But I have to say that it is still a rare event.''</p>
        <p>For all the praise, Mr. Rabner struck a humble tone, saying he was lucky he had gotten to know Mr. Corzine. The two met on Thanksgiving in 2001 while volunteering at a soup kitchen in Newark.</p>
        <p>''I view the position of a judge as perhaps the most noble,'' he said. ''A judge does his or her best to call things straight down the middle without representing any side.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
