<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Questions Are Big, but the Devil's in the Details</title>
    <meta content="05faus" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/arts/music/05faus.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852265"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/South Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/South Carolina/Charleston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/South Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Charleston (SC)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Herskovits, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE4DB1130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="674" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Questions Are Big, but the Devil's in the Details</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Questions Are Big, but the Devil’s in the Details</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES R. OESTREICH</byline>
      <dateline>CHARLESTON, S.C., June 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are operas of action and operas of stasis. But while Pascal Dusapin's ''Faustus, the Last Night'' certainly qualifies as static, it might more accurately be called an opera of suspension. It seems to float, a quality borne out in the staging here at the Sottile Theater as part of the Spoleto Festival U.S.A.</p>
        <p>In David Herskovits's production, with an evocative set by Carol Bailey, Faust's study hovers in the nighttime sky, surrounded by stars and galaxies. Mr. Dusapin's music also hovers and shimmers: an almost continuous, slowly shifting fabric of orchestral sound serves as a backdrop on which to hang the text and periodically swells to the foreground.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Faustus, the Last Night” might be called an opera of suspension. It seems to float, a quality borne out in the staging here at the Sottile Theater as part of the Spoleto Festival U.S.A.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are operas of action and operas of stasis. But while Pascal Dusapin's ''Faustus, the Last Night'' certainly qualifies as static, it might more accurately be called an opera of suspension. It seems to float, a quality borne out in the staging here at the Sottile Theater as part of the Spoleto Festival U.S.A.</p>
        <p>In David Herskovits's production, with an evocative set by Carol Bailey, Faust's study hovers in the nighttime sky, surrounded by stars and galaxies. Mr. Dusapin's music also hovers and shimmers: an almost continuous, slowly shifting fabric of orchestral sound serves as a backdrop on which to hang the text and periodically swells to the foreground.</p>
        <p>The orchestra is truly the star of this show, and happily, the young Ginn Resorts Spoleto Festival U.S.A. Orchestra, conducted by the festival's contemporary-music guru, John Kennedy, was fully up to the task. All those lightly sustained dissonant chords must be fiendishly difficult to keep in tune, or out of tune in just the right way.</p>
        <p>The questing, inconclusive, often inscrutable dialogue between Faust and Mephistopheles is the crux of this one-act work, basically a meditation on the perennial themes of good and evil, light and darkness, knowledge and wisdom, the soul and the universe. It feels as if an immense cosmic terrain were being traversed while the action stands still.</p>
        <p>This ''Faust,'' in Mr. Dusapin's own English libretto, has little to do with Goethe, only slightly more to do with Marlowe. There is no blessed ascent at the end, nor any fiery descent (though a momentary conflagration was introduced here).</p>
        <p>The cast was strong in the final performance on Saturday night, as it needs to be in this work, with its innovative vocal writing often eclipsed by the orchestra or obstructed by overlapping, competing dialogue. John Hancock was particularly strong in the title role, seizing every opportunity to soar. Stephen West was suitably bluff as Mephistopheles. Heather Buck delivered the Angel's strenuous, high-flying lines with aplomb, though her upper register was not entirely free.</p>
        <p>Adam Klein sang the comic role of the drunken Sly effectively, though he sometimes overplayed it. And Daniel Mobbs was the mysterious character Togod (godly or just supercilious?).</p>
        <p>The ethereal nature of Mr. Dusapin's music was in sharp contrast to the unbuttoned percussion works by Karlheinz Stockhausen performed earlier on Saturday evening in the festival's Music in Time series of contemporary concerts, also overseen by Mr. Kennedy. These were works of action, rousing and angular, even though the ostensible drama was rudimentary.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Stockhausen's ''Himmels-Tür'' (''Heaven's Door,'' 2005), a percussionist (Stuart Gerber) raises a ruckus before heaven's gate. He raps on a specially constructed wooden door frame with what appear to be tubular wooden ''sticks'' and stamps his feet; when, at some length, the doors open, he enters and is heard from within, unseen, on a variety of cymbals and gongs, a sort of sonic fireworks. A young girl then enters, and that, quickly, is that.</p>
        <p>In ''Kontakte'' (1959-60), two percussionists, one mostly on piano, again raise a clamor, only to be repeatedly overwhelmed by electronic ''sound projections.'' Even the tone clusters produced with forearm wallops on the piano sound pale beside the electronic flutters, twangs, growls, buzzes, gasps and belches. Here Mr. Gerber was joined by Michael Fowler, the sometime pianist, and Bryan Wolf, the sound projectionist, in a performance of consummate virtuosity.</p>
        <p>Those who missed ''Faustus'' can still hear the music of Mr. Dusapin as part of the next Music in Time program on Tuesday. The week's other highlights include an orchestral concert conducted by Emmanuel Villaume on Tuesday; a presentation of Philip Glass's ''Book of Longing,'' a dramatic setting of poetry by Leonard Cohen, opening on Wednesday; and a production of ''Swan Lake'' by the State Ballet of Georgia, directed by Nina Ananiashvili, opening on Thursday.</p>
        <p>And now that the drenching remnants of Tropical Storm Barry have swept through the Carolinas, perhaps the unusually pleasant weather of the festival's first week will return.</p>
        <p>The Spoleto Festival U.S.A. continues through Sunday; spoletousa.org.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
