<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Making Tunes a Fixture on the Patio</title>
    <meta content="05outside" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/technology/circuits/05outside.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852362"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E1D91130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="997" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Making Tunes a Fixture on the Patio</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Making Tunes a Fixture on the Patio</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IVAN BERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berger, Ivan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOME entertainment systems have been making music outdoors since wind-up phonographs first wound up on the veranda. You can get the same effect today by taking out a portable stereo, but more homeowners are permanently installing speakers outdoors.</p>
        <p>''People are moving to warmer states and living more outdoors,'' said Steve Crawford, chief marketing officer at Sonance, which produces speakers. Plus, he said, ''people with smaller homes like to extend their living space outdoors.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Take the stereo outside with a bit of planning and the right equipment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOME entertainment systems have been making music outdoors since wind-up phonographs first wound up on the veranda. You can get the same effect today by taking out a portable stereo, but more homeowners are permanently installing speakers outdoors.</p>
        <p>''People are moving to warmer states and living more outdoors,'' said Steve Crawford, chief marketing officer at Sonance, which produces speakers. Plus, he said, ''people with smaller homes like to extend their living space outdoors.''</p>
        <p>Don't expect to duplicate indoor-listening quality outside, said Orrin Charm, systems architect at InfiniSys Electronic Architects. ''Not that you can't get great listening there -- you can, for instance, get better imaging when there are no walls around -- but it works best if you consider outdoor music as an environmental element rather than trying to recreate the soundstage you have in your home theater.''</p>
        <p>Filling your yard with music takes plenty of amplifier power and speakers that can handle it -- and the weather, too. How many speakers and how much power you need depends on the size and layout of the space. You will need careful planning to keep your sound from spilling over to your neighbor's yard.</p>
        <p>Weatherproof speakers, most costing $200 to $500 a pair, are made by dozens of companies. It pays to buy brands whose home speakers sound good to you because speakers sound different outdoors -- softer, with less bass and less stereo ambience -- and you will rarely hear speakers under those conditions until you bring them home.</p>
        <p>Most outdoor speakers look like plastic bookshelf speakers, often with paintable finishes, and are mounted in brackets, usually well above ear level. Such speakers, mounted on a building, pole or tree and angled down, can cover a large area with little variation in sound level. Ground-level speakers help fill in where coverage is uneven, or where you need a different sound level, near a loud Jacuzzi, for example.</p>
        <p>Sometimes disguised as rocks, such speakers can be built into planters or other outdoor furnishings, and some can be partly buried for concealment. Flush-mounted wall or ceiling speakers can also be used for fill. Often, Mr. Charm said, the choice is mainly aesthetic.</p>
        <p>Outdoor speakers can sound good, though maximum sound quality is often less important than controlling where that sound goes so it will not disturb neighbors. Mr. Crawford and Mr. Charm both recommend using multiple speakers; with sound sources near each listening area, you need not play any speaker loud enough for its sound to carry far.</p>
        <p>Where you mount and aim your speakers affects sound spill, too. Aiming your speakers at shrubbery, which absorbs sound, gives you better control than directing them at walls that may reflect it. And speakers mounted on your house, firing into your yard, are most likely to project sound beyond your property, Mr. Charm said.</p>
        <p>Wiring outdoor speakers is no trivial matter, he added. You need heavy wire, typically at least 14 gauge or 12 gauge, because outdoor systems require so much amplifier power and cable runs between the amp and speakers can be very long.</p>
        <p>You also will want to waterproof all connections and make sure the wiring does not bring water into the house.</p>
        <p>''Typically, if I design a system, I make sure the wiring reaches its highest point where it enters the house, so water will drain back outside,'' Mr. Charm said. ''I recommend burying your wires 12 to 18 inches below grade, and running your wires in PVC conduit -- there are speaker cables made for direct burial, but gardeners tend to cut anything they can.'' Even in conduits, water can break down the wire's insulation, but wires in conduits are often less difficult to replace.</p>
        <p>Wireless outdoor speakers avoid these problems, getting their signals from radio transmitters connected to your indoor sound system. To save battery power, however, their amplifiers usually deliver only 10 to 20 watts apiece, and they must be plugged in periodically to recharge.</p>
        <p>To control overall volume and change music sources when your sound system is far away indoors, you'll need to use radio-frequency remote controls, whose signals pass through walls and are not swamped by bright sunlight, as infrared remotes' signals are. Universal Remote Controls, Logitech and others make radio-frequency remotes for general use, and some packaged audio systems, like Bose's Lifestyle models, are available with them.</p>
        <p>Keypads for some whole-house audio and entertainment systems can be mounted in weatherproof electrical boxes. Controlling volume or muting the sound in specific areas requires weatherproofed level controls and speaker switches.</p>
        <p>The more elaborate the system, the more sense it makes to hire a professional installer. Tom Cumberland, chief engineer of Axiom Audio, recommends using installers certified by Cedia, a home-installation training and standardization organization. ''Most reputable installers,'' he said, ''will have that information in their Yellow Pages ads or on their Web sites.'' You can also find them through cedia.net.</p>
        <p>''Referrals from a friend are best, though,'' he added. Installers recommended by the dealer you plan to buy from are usually good, especially small local dealers.</p>
        <p>Getting the installer's advice before finishing your purchase will help you find the best equipment for your property. And before you hire an installer, make sure you understand your options, what work is entailed and what it costs.</p>
        <p>''For a simple installation -- two speakers on the house or on-ground speakers near it, an outdoor volume control, and a separate amp -- figure about $1,000 for the labor,'' said Stuart Snowden, president of Stuarts Audio in Westfield, N.J.</p>
        <p>But simple systems like the one Mr. Snowden referred to are not that daunting to install yourself, and manufacturers say most of their customers do just that. Some, in fact, rely on the most basic outdoor-sound solution: lug your living-room speakers out to the patio, run long wires back to your amplifier, and pray that nobody trips on the wires and it doesn't rain. The more you do that, and the heavier your speakers are, the more likely you are to switch to something permanent.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
