<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Federal Appeals Court Rejects Michigan's Ban on a Controversial Method of Abortion</title>
    <meta content="05abort" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/us/05abort.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852311"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Michigan</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E3DA1130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="578" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Federal Appeals Court Rejects Michigan's Ban on a Controversial Method of Abortion</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Federal Appeals Court Rejects Michigan’s Ban on a Controversial Method of Abortion</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIBBY SANDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sander, Libby</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, June 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The State of Michigan's third attempt in a decade to ban a procedure known among anti-abortion activists as partial-birth abortion was declared unconstitutional by a federal appeals court on Monday, less than two months after the Supreme Court narrowly upheld a federal law banning the method.</p>
        <p>The United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit said the Michigan statute, the Legal Birth Definition Act, was worded so broadly that in addition to banning the procedure, it would also prohibit other legal abortion methods.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michigan’s third attempt in a decade to ban partial-birth abortion was declared unconstitutional by a federal appeals court on Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The State of Michigan's third attempt in a decade to ban a procedure known among anti-abortion activists as partial-birth abortion was declared unconstitutional by a federal appeals court on Monday, less than two months after the Supreme Court narrowly upheld a federal law banning the method.</p>
        <p>The United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit said the Michigan statute, the Legal Birth Definition Act, was worded so broadly that in addition to banning the procedure, it would also prohibit other legal abortion methods.</p>
        <p>The court said the Legislature took a ''dragnet approach'' to regulating the procedure, which is known medically as ''intact dilation and extraction'' and involves removing the fetus intact rather than dismembering it in the uterus. The law ''showed no meaningful attempt to comply with the constitutional limitations articulated by federal courts in the area of abortion law,'' Judge Boyce F. Martin Jr. wrote for the court.</p>
        <p>The law did not on its own terms ban any specific type of abortion procedure, Judge Boyce wrote. Instead, it created a protected legal status for a partly delivered fetus that it termed a ''perinate.''</p>
        <p>The decision upheld a 2005 ruling by a federal district judge in Detroit that found the law unconstitutional because it placed ''an undue burden'' on a woman's right to have an abortion by also prohibiting a more common abortion procedure used in the second trimester of pregnancy, known as ''dilation and evacuation.'' The District Court also found that the term ''perinate'' was not a commonly used definition in the medical profession and added to the law's vague language.</p>
        <p>The Sixth Circuit decision comes on the heels of a Supreme Court decision in April, Gonzales v. Carhart, upholding a 2003 federal law, the Partial-Birth Abortion Ban Act, which prohibits the dilation and extraction procedure.</p>
        <p>Seven years ago, in Stenberg v. Carhart, the Supreme Court rejected a Nebraska abortion law banning the procedure involving the intact fetus, saying it unconstitutionally prohibited the more common dilation and evacuation procedure. The court said the restriction placed ''an undue burden'' on a woman's right to have an abortion.</p>
        <p>Michigan's law also contained provisions that would have prohibited abortion procedures beyond the dilation and extraction procedure, the appeals court said Monday. Though Michigan's attorney general issued an opinion shortly after the law was challenged in court in 2005 to clarify the scope of the law and make clear that the Legislature's intent was only to prohibit the dilation and extraction procedure, the appeals court said that the opinion was not binding and did not carry the weight of legal precedent and that the statute's language remained confusing.</p>
        <p>Federal courts have rejected Michigan lawmakers' attempts to regulate the procedure twice before, in 1997 and 2001, for laws passed in 1996 and 1999, respectively.</p>
        <p>Michigan's governor, Jennifer M. Granholm, a Democrat, vetoed the legislation in 2003. More than 400,000 supporters of the bill signed a petition allowing the law to pass without the governor's signature, and the Republican-dominated Legislature quickly passed an identical bill that became law in June 2004.</p>
        <p>Though legislators in Michigan's neighboring state of Ohio passed a ban on the procedure in 2003 that has so far passed muster with the courts and provides clear guidance, the appeals court said on Monday, Michigan lawmakers did not follow their example. Instead, they ''opted to use statutory language that pushed almost every boundary that the Supreme Court has imposed for these types of laws,'' Judge Martin said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
