<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Iraq, Does the Korea Analogy Fit?</title>
    <meta content="l05iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852334"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EEDA1130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="628" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Iraq, Does the Korea Analogy Fit?</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''With Korea as Model, Bush Team Ponders Long Support Role in Iraq'' (news analysis, front page, June 3):</p>
        <p>The strategic mission of the Korean occupation was to draw a line at the 38th parallel and prevent a North Korean attack on the South. In Iraq, the ''38th parallel'' is everywhere and nowhere; our troops will continue to be fruitlessly enmeshed in tribal and sectarian violence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''With Korea as Model, Bush Team Ponders Long Support Role in Iraq'' (news analysis, front page, June 3):</p>
        <p>The strategic mission of the Korean occupation was to draw a line at the 38th parallel and prevent a North Korean attack on the South. In Iraq, the ''38th parallel'' is everywhere and nowhere; our troops will continue to be fruitlessly enmeshed in tribal and sectarian violence.</p>
        <p>For all of its problems, the United States military presence in Northeast Asia was a stabilizing force. The American occupation of Iraq, in contrast, has further destabilized the Middle East. It has created an enormous refugee crisis, enhanced Iranian regional power and encouraged Islamic radicalism.</p>
        <p>Finally, the Bush administration's determination to build permanent military installations throughout Iraq in spite of the opposition of a majority of Iraqis to such a plan underlines the absurdity of the claim that we invaded Iraq to establish democracy there.</p>
        <p>Melissa Macauley  Evanston, Ill., June 3, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is an associate professor of history and Asian and Middle Eastern studies at Northwestern University.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Since no two wars are alike, trolling through history for an Iraq disengagement model is fruitless.</p>
        <p>In Korea, a joint United States-United Nations force repulsed a Communist incursion and left behind a mutually agreed token force as guarantee. In Iraq, the people are on record as wanting the United States to leave, even if not just yet.</p>
        <p>A long-term United States force presence in the Middle East would be continuously destabilizing and present a continuing target for jihadists. History surely warns us about maintaining foreign garrisons in alien lands.</p>
        <p>Norman Getsinger  Flint Hill, Va., June 3, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Let me get this straight. First, the United States incurs the ire of Osama bin Laden and other Islamic jihadists through its military actions in the Persian Gulf and by stationing forces in Saudi Arabia and other Muslim countries.</p>
        <p>Then, after being attacked by Al Qaeda, the United States invades and occupies a country that had nothing to do with 9/11, turning it into a haven for insurgents and terrorists.</p>
        <p>And now, the Bush administration wants to establish a long-term military presence in Iraq to make sure that Al Qaeda and other jihadist groups do not turn it into a base like Afghanistan?</p>
        <p>John S. Duffield  Decatur, Ga., June 3, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Iraq's Curse: A Thirst for Final, Crushing Victory'' (Week in Review, June 3):</p>
        <p>You write, ''Shiites intend to dominate the country entirely, taking what they believe was stripped from them when their revered leader Hussein was murdered in the desert of seventh-century Mesopotamia.''</p>
        <p>People who can carry a grudge for 14 centuries are not likely to forget all about it in a few months at the request of an invading army.</p>
        <p>Whenever the United States leaves Iraq, whether in 2008, 2012 or in 14 centuries, Iraqi blood will flow in rivers until a new incarnation of Saddam Hussein emerges to rule with an iron hand. For all the blood, treasure and heartache, we will have accomplished absolutely nothing.</p>
        <p>Ralph Averill  New Preston, Conn., June 4, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>How long after the fight shifts from Iraq do you think it will take to start in this country on our own soil?</p>
        <p>Any weakening or surrender of will in Iraq will mean certain attacks in the United States, which is already at risk -- note the J.F.K. airport plot and others that have been recently uncovered.</p>
        <p>We are in a war for our survival against Islamic extremism. There are multiple fronts. Iraq is one of these fronts. May we all keep this in mind!</p>
        <p>Bob Jack  North Las Vegas, Nev.  June 3, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
