<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sharing a Hobby, Online and in Person</title>
    <meta content="05clubs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/technology/circuits/05clubs.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852357"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEB CONNECTIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Friendship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Friendship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E2D91130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="975" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sharing a Hobby, Online and in Person</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sharing a Hobby, Online and in Person</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT VILLANO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE compliment came unexpectedly, an appreciation of Wendy Roth's digital photos of the 100-foot-tall, cooled-lava Keremeos columns in British Columbia.</p>
        <p>Ms. Roth, an amateur photographer, had received a number of halfhearted comments during her membership in the photo-sharing Web site Flickr, but this one was different.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like-minded photographers find each other online, then meet off.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE compliment came unexpectedly, an appreciation of Wendy Roth's digital photos of the 100-foot-tall, cooled-lava Keremeos columns in British Columbia.</p>
        <p>Ms. Roth, an amateur photographer, had received a number of halfhearted comments during her membership in the photo-sharing Web site Flickr, but this one was different.</p>
        <p>The person who gave the compliment, Mandy Polson (screen name, MandyOnEarth), seemed passionate about nature and was interested in hiking. She had a Flickr page full of photos of her own -- depicting wildlife in various environments.</p>
        <p>Coincidentally, both women live in Penticton, British Columbia. Ms. Roth (screen name, SoulVision) told Ms. Polson they should meet. ''It just seemed that we had too much in common not to get together,'' said Ms. Roth. ''The whole idea was to shoot photos as a pair.''</p>
        <p>The first time they met, they took photos along a trail that cuts between two lakes outside the city. The second time, they visited Okanagan Lake, where Ms. Polson wanted to photograph migrating Bohemian waxwings. Other trips included an outing to photograph bald eagles.</p>
        <p>''If it wasn't for the Web site, we probably never would have met,'' Ms. Polson said. ''Now I have a new friend who will talk to me about photography, and someone to join me whenever I want to go out and shoot.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Polson and Ms. Roth are not the only photo enthusiasts who have connected through the Internet. Across North America, thousands of amateur and professional photographers are using photo-oriented social networking Web sites to meet and practice their craft.</p>
        <p>Like the women from Penticton, the majority of these photographers came together through Flickr. Sites like Picasa (picasa.google.com), Vazaar (vazaar.com) and PhotoSIG (photosig.com), have attracted followers as well.</p>
        <p>Users call these gatherings meet-ups, and they get together as often as once a week. While most involve pairs or small groups of photographers, some attract dozens of people.</p>
        <p>At the Flickr meet-up in Madison, Wis., for example, a young man named Kieran Nagoda regularly leads 10 to 15 others on what he calls photo walks around the city and surrounding parks. The group convenes at a downtown landmark and fans out to photograph everything from people to landscapes and flowers to buildings. Some participants trade gear to try new equipment. Others act as assistants for friends, holding up a flash on a particular shot.</p>
        <p>''We're there to teach each other and help each other become better photographers,'' Mr. Nagoda, 19, said. ''Meeting in person gives us knowledge we wouldn't be able to get from only meeting online.''</p>
        <p>Atlanta also has an active Flickr group. Members use the Web site to schedule ''photo strolls'' two to three times a month, meeting at destinations like the Atlanta Botanical Garden and the Georgia Aquarium.</p>
        <p>Carissa Craven, a graphic designer, has taken part in these strolls. The crowd is overwhelmingly male, she noted in a recent e-mail exchange, and the outings are a great way to increase skills, acquire technical knowledge and make friends.</p>
        <p>''When you attend these meet-ups, there is always the amusing two-part introduction: 'This is Robert, and he is Wananga on Flickr,' or 'This is April, and she goes by Avril Stylo,' '' Ms. Craven wrote. ''As you meet people, you're hurriedly attempting to mentally match their real-life personalities with what you can remember of their photo stream.''</p>
        <p>Most Flickr fans agreed that the father of the photo meet-up was Bryan Partington, a 26-year-old with the screen name Striatic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Partington worked on some of the earliest versions of the Flickr site and founded one of the first regular meet-ups in Toronto in November 2004. These initial get-togethers were social in nature -- two or three people talking at a pub. As interest grew, Mr. Partington began organizing walkabouts to shoot photos.</p>
        <p>With the Toronto walks established, Mr. Partington left for a tour of the United States in 2005 to visit hundreds of friends from Flickr. Everywhere he stopped, he participated in meet-ups and encouraged members to start photo walks.</p>
        <p>''If you compare the activity to music, it's like a jam session, a communal improvisational thing,'' said Mr. Partington, who now lives in Edmonton, Alberta. ''You're not burdening yourself by thinking about what you're doing. Instead, you're doing things reflexively and experimenting to become a better shot.''</p>
        <p>Still, not every photographer wants to meet with virtual strangers and shoot en masse.</p>
        <p>Phil Cantor, a professional photographer who lives in Montclair, N.J., said that while it was fine to meet with other photographers to talk shop, the process of selecting, framing and capturing a shot is a personal and iconoclastic exercise.</p>
        <p>''Photography is all about your individual vision,'' he said. ''If you ask me, having someone there who also is shooting just muddies the picture.''</p>
        <p>Carolyn Byerly-Dean, an occupational therapist who lives in Oakland, Calif., noted that most photo-sharing Web sites don't reveal much about a person's character. ''Even if you've looked at someone's photos online for months, you don't really know much about that person beyond what you read in a profile,'' said Ms. Byerly-Dean, who said she preferred to take photos alone.</p>
        <p>Many online photo enthusiasts say the benefits of meeting offline far outweigh the risks, even when they're not shooting photos.</p>
        <p>The Aperture Users Professional Network serves as a message board (apertureprofessional.com) for photographers who use Apple hardware and software. Members also schedule get-togethers to discuss technique and try out new gear.</p>
        <p>While most meetings are informal, David Schloss, the group's director, said that some events were structured talks. This April, for example, Bill Frakes, a photographer for Sports Illustrated, spoke to a group of 85 people at the Apple Store in SoHo in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''You're going to learn something whenever you attend a group of creative and eccentric people,'' Mr. Schloss said. ''But on top of making people better photographers, the events also are just a lot of fun.''</p>
        <p>WEB CONNECTIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
