<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>McQuarters Has Clean Cut From a Trend-Setting Past</title>
    <meta content="05giants" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/sports/football/05giants.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852376"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hair</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hair</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Giants</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0D91130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="688" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>McQuarters Has Clean Cut From a Trend-Setting Past</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">McQuarters Has Clean Cut From a Trend-Setting Past</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN BRANCH</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., June 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Those who do not know R. W. McQuarters's name or face may recall his hair.</p>
        <p>For nine N.F.L. seasons, including the past two with the Giants, it sprang from under the back of his helmet, a bundled tassel dancing with every step and obscuring the name sewn on the back of his jersey and the top half of the numbers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Giants defensive back has cut off the dreadlocks he has worn since his rookie year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Those who do not know R. W. McQuarters's name or face may recall his hair.</p>
        <p>For nine N.F.L. seasons, including the past two with the Giants, it sprang from under the back of his helmet, a bundled tassel dancing with every step and obscuring the name sewn on the back of his jersey and the top half of the numbers.</p>
        <p>Along with a few other other defensive backs, including Al Harris and Mike McKenzie, McQuarters helped to sprout a trend that has taken hold among African-American cornerbacks and safeties in the N.F.L. -- a head of dangling dreadlocks, or ''locks,'' as McQuarters prefers to call them, to help add swagger.</p>
        <p>When McQuarters walked into the Giants' locker room this spring, several teammates and team employees walked past him with a generic hello. Only later -- sometimes a few seconds, sometimes a few days -- did they approach him again with wide eyes. ''They'd go, 'You know, man, I didn't even recognize you,' '' McQuarters said.</p>
        <p>On March 21, McQuarters had his first haircut since his rookie season. So much hair came off that he had to get a new helmet, two sizes smaller.</p>
        <p>''I was like a bobblehead in my old one,'' said McQuarters, his pate covered with short bristles.</p>
        <p>McQuarters, 30, always had a somewhat mystical relationship with his hair. He saw it as a literal and figurative extension of himself, part of his personality, persona and look. He remembered when it meshed with his uniform the best -- with an orange jersey of the Chicago Bears, in a game at Dallas a few years ago. He said he always thought that he looked faster, with his hair swinging with every stride.</p>
        <p>''Different energies, relationships that you had in the past, I think all that comes with you in your hair,'' McQuarters said. ''Because it's there. It's always there. It grows. When you cut it off, it's like cutting off some of the past. So it was really like getting rid of all that negativity.''</p>
        <p>He did not detail exactly what he hoped to shed by shearing his hair, which he donated to Locks of Love, a nonprofit organization that provides hairpieces to children who have lost hair because of medical conditions.</p>
        <p>''In eight and a half years?'' he said. ''Oh, yeah, I've been through several negative situations. It was just time for me to change. I turned 30, and it was time.''</p>
        <p>The longest locks in the Giants' locker room now belong to the veteran defensive back Michael Stone, who was signed in the off-season. Stone was a college teammate of McKenzie's at Memphis. ''His hair is about two years longer than mine,'' Stone said of McKenzie, who is now with the New Orleans Saints.</p>
        <p>Stone has not cut his hair in about six years. It is nearly as long as McQuarters's hair was.</p>
        <p>''I just can't cut it off,'' Stone said. ''You grow something so long, you grow attached.''</p>
        <p>A cramped side room adjacent to the Giants' locker room is filled with temporary locker stalls used by rookies who fill the overstuffed off-season roster. Cornerback Darren Barnett, a 23-year-old from Missouri State, has wispy locks that barely tickle the top of his shoulders. He has not cut his hair in two years.</p>
        <p>He said that he was inspired by players like McQuarters, Harris and McKenzie. ''Role models,'' Barnett said. ''Most of the top corners, guys who want to stand out there, have dreadlocks.''</p>
        <p>McQuarters is trying to hang on to a roster spot. He was used primarily as a fifth defensive back in passing situations last season. The Giants used their first-round draft choice in April to select another cornerback, Aaron Ross, who will probably compete with Sam Madison and Corey Webster for the two starting jobs.</p>
        <p>Some of McQuarters's teammates said he looked younger without the hair, and McQuarters joked that he might have bought himself a few more years simply by shedding the hair. Or maybe he is just ready to pass along a growing tradition.</p>
        <p>''It was my time,'' McQuarters said. ''All the young guys coming into the league, they've got locks now.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
