<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Today's Managing Partner In Team Clinton &amp; Clinton</title>
    <meta content="05kaku" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Washington; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/books/review/05kaku.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852273"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bernstein, Carl</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E2DB1130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1328" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Today's Managing Partner In Team Clinton &amp; Clinton</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Today’s Managing Partner in Team Clinton &amp; Clinton</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Woman in Charge  The Life of Hillary Rodham Clinton  By Carl Bernstein  Illustrated. 628 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $27.95.</p>
        <p>Given all the sobering things that have happened since the turn of the millennium -- from the terrorist attacks of 9/11 to the war in Iraq to the Bush administration's efforts to expand executive power and curtail civil liberties -- the sex and real estate follies of the Clinton White House now feel as if they belong to an era long ago and far, far away. Indeed, Carl Bernstein's new biography of Hillary Rodham Clinton often feels like a very long, very slow acid flashback to the 1990s, rehashing and reexamining, in minute detail, matters like Monica, Whitewater, bimbo eruptions and the state of the Clintons' marriage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The disclosures in Carl Bernstein’s biography of Hillary Rodham Clinton amount mainly to embroiderings on already well-known aspects of the Clintons’ lives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Woman in Charge  The Life of Hillary Rodham Clinton  By Carl Bernstein  Illustrated. 628 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $27.95.</p>
        <p>Given all the sobering things that have happened since the turn of the millennium -- from the terrorist attacks of 9/11 to the war in Iraq to the Bush administration's efforts to expand executive power and curtail civil liberties -- the sex and real estate follies of the Clinton White House now feel as if they belong to an era long ago and far, far away. Indeed, Carl Bernstein's new biography of Hillary Rodham Clinton often feels like a very long, very slow acid flashback to the 1990s, rehashing and reexamining, in minute detail, matters like Monica, Whitewater, bimbo eruptions and the state of the Clintons' marriage.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernstein has written a serious, energetically researched and largely fluent book, but there is little new in this volume: its disclosures amount mainly to embroiderings on already well-known aspects of the Clintons' lives.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernstein's overall take on Mrs. Clinton (that her ''experiential openness'' gave her a ''capacity for personal growth and change'' embodied by her decision to run for the United States Senate in New York in the wake of the Monica Lewinsky scandal) is remarkably similar to the conclusions drawn by Gail Sheehy in her 1999 book, ''Hillary's Choice, '' while his observations on the dynamic between Mrs. Clinton and her husband -- that he was the charmer, she was the disciplinarian -- echo remarks made hundreds of times before by reporters as well as former administration insiders like George Stephanopoulos, David Gergen and Dick Morris.</p>
        <p>Unlike the other new Hillary book -- ''Her Way: The Hopes and Ambitions of Hillary Rodham Clinton'' by Jeff Gerth, a former reporter at The New York Times, and Don Van Natta Jr., an investigative reporter at the newspaper -- this volume does not really appraise Mrs. Clinton's record as a senator from New York and sheds no new light on her stance on the Iraq war or her current campaign for the White House.</p>
        <p>In creating a portrait of the former first lady, Mr. Bernstein does a lot of on-the-one-hand and on-the-other-hand. He underscores Mrs. Clinton's intelligence, toughness and resilience but also describes less than attractive traits that have more often been ascribed to George W. Bush: religious convictions that ''to some bordered on a messiahlike self-perception,'' a ''demand for absolute loyalty,'' a discomfort with being challenged.</p>
        <p>He writes that many traits seen in private by her friends -- humor, spontaneity, enthusiasm -- are concealed behind the ''protective shell'' she wears in public, and he describes ''a disconnect between her convictions and words, and her actions.''</p>
        <p>All in all, his book will please neither Friends of Hillary nor Enemies of Hillary: while it is often sympathetic toward the former first lady as an individual grappling with a complex marriage and trying to carry out genuinely held ideals, it is just as often critical of judgment calls she's made on both policy and politics.</p>
        <p>At times Mr. Bernstein tries hard to feel the Clintons' pain. He argues that the couple were ''treated more harshly, and often pursued with different standards and more relentlessly -- during virtually the whole of their occupancy of the White House -- than any president and his wife of the 20th century.'' He contends that many of the ''underlying assumptions'' of the assertions that fueled the investigation into their lives ''were often contextually misleading, exaggerated in significance, and sometimes factually off-base.''</p>
        <p>And he contests arguments that the Clintons' marriage was, at base, some sort of power-sharing alliance, writing of the ''ecstasy'' Hillary felt when she first fell in love with Bill Clinton, and describing ''how good Hillary and Bill could be together, how much fun they had, how they reveled in each other's company, how they connected, the deep commitment they shared to an old-fashioned concept of public service, the belief of each, naïve as it sounded, that together there was a way to make things better for people whose lives were not as blessed as their own.''</p>
        <p>As for right-wing allegations that Mrs. Clinton was some sort of ''leftist ideologue,'' Mr. Bernstein suggests that she was actually very conservative personally. He notes that she attended a women's prayer group (which included Susan Baker, the wife of former Secretary of State James A. Baker III, and Joanne Kemp, wife of the former Republican congressman Jack Kemp) and writes that her ''real-life education and sense of right and wrong (which became more complicated and relativist as she grew older) guided her away from rigid ideology'' and ''led her to reject hard political dogma of any sort (including aspects of feminist theology).''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernstein argues that Hillary Clinton's ''political development reflected more curiosity and openness'' than her husband's and italicizes the pivotal role she played in the former president's rise to power and subsequent troubles, suggesting that Bill Clinton ''often needed to be managed, pushed, reassured, guided, or scolded, depending on the moment, to perform at the level of which he was capable.''</p>
        <p>''With the notable exception of her husband's libidinous carelessness,'' Mr. Bernstein asserts, ''the most egregious errors, strategic and tactical'' of his presidency, particularly in its stumbling first year, are ''traceable to Hillary,'' including, in large measure, the inept staffing of the White House, the disastrous serial search for an attorney general, the Travel Office brouhaha, Whitewater and the alienation of key senators and members of Congress.</p>
        <p>Arguably the most troubling incidents in this book relate to Mrs. Clinton's handling of the administration's failed health care plan. The outlines of this story have been told many times before -- most notably by the former presidential adviser David R. Gergen, who has suggested that Mr. Clinton failed to take control of the health care initiative because he was unwilling to challenge his wife in the wake of reports suggesting that he had used Arkansas state troopers to procure women.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernstein, however, focuses on the battles between Mrs. Clinton and administration budget hawks like Robert Rubin, then head of the newly created National Economic Council and Treasury Secretary Lloyd Bentsen, who were among those who warned the president that ''the deficit would be in danger of exploding if he listened to Hillary'' on health care and urged him to ''settle on a more manageable and incremental approach.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernstein contends that ''Hillary's acceptance of her husband's economic program'' -- which would fuel an economic boom and become a linchpin of his legacy -- ''was forced and grudging at almost every step,'' and implies she willfully resisted modifying her health care plan.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton ''tended to view anyone who criticized her plan, even constructively, as an enemy,'' Mr. Bernstein writes, adding that much to the dismay of Senators Bill Bradley and Daniel Patrick Moynihan, she advised Congressional Democrats that ''the time had come to 'demonize' those who would slow down the health care train for some important roadwork.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernstein reportedly spent eight years working on this portrait of Mrs. Clinton, and in these pages he sometimes sounds defensive, as if heneeded to resort to hyperbole to justify all the time devoted to his subject. He declares, for instance, that Hillary Clinton ''had come to a prominence unique in her time -- settling in a rarefied place never populated even by F .D. R., Princess Diana, Ike, Oprah or Eleanor Roosevelt as, in a great cacophony, people from every station and walk of life (plus talk show hosts and The National Enquirer) fulminated, debated and screamed at one another about her.''</p>
        <p>In the course of a book that weighs in at more than 600 pages, he's created a highly detailed portrait of Hillary Rodham Clinton, but it's a portrait largely made up of incidents and descriptions and theories any regular follower of the news already knows -- a portrait, arriving at a time, in Mr. Bernstein's words, when ''the disastrous presidency of her husband's successor'' is nearing expiration, that seems unlikely to find all that many eager readers.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
