<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Italian Cup Bid a Blend of Passion and Optimism</title>
    <meta content="05sailing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/sports/othersports/05sailing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852347"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="YACHT RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">America's Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">America's Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bertelli, Patrizio</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4D91130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Italian Cup Bid a Blend of Passion and Optimism</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Italian Bid for Top Title Blends Passion With Optimism</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <dateline>VALENCIA, Spain, June 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The race was on. The spinnakers were up in the distance, and it was quiet enough to hear a Cup drop on Luna Rossa Challenge's guest boat.</p>
        <p>Once again, the privileged few had removed their shoes and clambered boisterously aboard in hopes of seeing an Italian victory against Emirates Team New Zealand. Once more, with the race not yet halfway over, the gap was growing between the New Zealanders' stern and Luna Rossa's bow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Emirates Team New Zealand is leading Luna Rossa 3 - 0, but Patrizio Bertelli is not yet conceding.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The race was on. The spinnakers were up in the distance, and it was quiet enough to hear a Cup drop on Luna Rossa Challenge's guest boat.</p>
        <p>Once again, the privileged few had removed their shoes and clambered boisterously aboard in hopes of seeing an Italian victory against Emirates Team New Zealand. Once more, with the race not yet halfway over, the gap was growing between the New Zealanders' stern and Luna Rossa's bow.</p>
        <p>And so the guests Sunday spoke in funereal tones or turned their attention away from the foregone conclusion on the water. Some sprawled in the sun; one opened the Italian newspaper La Gazzetta dello Sport, skipped past the boat racing and went to the horse racing to read about Frankie Dettori's victory in the Epsom Derby.</p>
        <p>That was an Italian success story, but Luna Rossa's silver-haired leader, Patrizio Bertelli, is not yet conceding that his team will not produce another one in the best-of-nine Louis Vuitton Cup finals. For now, with racing to resume Tuesday, Luna Rossa trails the series by 3-0 against an opponent that looks ever more shipshape.</p>
        <p>''We have a team that proved to be strong through other series, and they certainly didn't forget how to sail overnight,'' Bertelli said. ''We still have 40 percent of our chances.''</p>
        <p>Bertelli, once viewed as an interloper, is now a part of the scenery. This is his third consecutive challenge for the America's Cup, sailing's most prestigious prize, and although it is still not his full-time occupation, it remains his obsession.</p>
        <p>''The America's Cup is not logical,'' he said. ''It's the utmost expression of something that's not rational, and maybe that's why it's so appealing to everybody.''</p>
        <p>Bertelli's regular job is running Prada, the company inherited by his wife, Miuccia Prada, that they have transformed into a global tastemaker. Their fashion empire has surrendered territory since the last Cup in 2003, selling off the Jil Sander and the Helmut Lang brands. This is the first time that Bertelli has brought in an outside investor for a Cup campaign. According to a Prada spokesman, Francesco Longanesi Cattani, this year's budget is about $114.3 million, slightly more than last time, with Prada owning 51 percent of the team and Telecom Italia 49 percent.</p>
        <p>Perhaps Bertelli's approach to the Cup is more logical than he maintains. He has not been the biggest spender since his first appearance in 2000. He answers carefully when asked whether the estimated $200 million budget that BMW Oracle Racing had at its disposal should now be viewed as a waste after Luna Rossa's upset victory in the semifinals.</p>
        <p>''The America's Cup is not something you win with money,'' he said. ''It takes the right budget, but to have unlimited access to whatever idea and whatever budget is too messy to manage.''</p>
        <p>With this campaign running smoothly until last week, it remains unclear whether Bertelli, 61, is mellowing. During the last Vuitton Cup, Bertelli dismissed his lead designer, Doug Peterson, after a loss in the opening race. The team failed to get past the semifinals of the challenger series, quite a comedown from their first appearance in Auckland, New Zealand, in 2000 when they reached the America's Cup.</p>
        <p>Bertelli is deeply involved in the design process, and the Luna Rossa is unusually boxy with a comparatively flat bottom and vertical sides. Although there are now doubters about its inherent speed -- particularly after the race Sunday, when Luna Rossa failed to hold its early lead -- Bertelli seems convinced that his team is blazing the right trail.</p>
        <p>''We didn't lose because of boat speed; I don't think so,'' he said. ''Crossing ahead on the first cross is really what matters in this racing. It's so close.''</p>
        <p>Fates have been sealed early here. Though the courses are composed of four legs, two upwind and two downwind, the team that has been leading after the first leg throughout the semifinals and the finals has ended up the winner. With passing opportunities limited, the new helmsman James Spithill's talents are all the more important. Although he has been effective in the prestart during the final and even won the start on Sunday, the Italians have yet to capitalize. The New Zealanders and their helmsman Dean Barker have appeared to have had the better boat, better weather calls and slightly slicker crew work.</p>
        <p>Win or lose, Bertelli, one of the Cup's strong personalities, has strong ideas about the Cup's future. He is against staging it in two years' time, preferring the longer, traditional cycle. ''Two years would take a lot away from this sense of adventure and of the feeling of an exceptional event,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Above all, he wants the challengers to regain more control over their own regatta, which is being run this time by America's Cup Management, an entity created by the defending champion, Alinghi. ''It's O.K. to have an umbrella organization; it makes a lot of sense, but it shouldn't be managed by the defender,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Becoming the defender would certainly make it easier to implement his ideas, but Luna Rossa's chances of even facing Alinghi are growing smaller by the tack.</p>
        <p>''We're building things brick by brick,'' Bertelli said. ''Remember, it took four campaigns for Team New Zealand to finally win the America's Cup.''</p>
        <p>YACHT RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
