<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Donovan's N.B.A. Stay Is Expected to Be Brief</title>
    <meta content="05donovan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/sports/basketball/05donovan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852300"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Orlando Magic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Orlando</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Orlando (Fla)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Florida</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Orlando Magic</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Donovan, Billy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Grant, Anthony</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E6DA1130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="511" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Donovan's N.B.A. Stay Is Expected to Be Brief</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Donovan’s N.B.A. Stay Is Expected to Be Brief</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETE THAMEL and LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just days after Billy Donovan agreed to a five-year, $27.5 million deal to coach the Orlando Magic, it appears he is heading back to the University of Florida.</p>
        <p>The Magic said in a statement yesterday that Donovan was ''conflicted'' about his future. And as every hour passes, the chances become slimmer and slimmer that Donovan will stand on the Magic's sideline.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just days after Billy Donovan agreed to a five-year, $27.5 million deal to coach the Orlando Magic, it appears he is heading back to the University of Florida.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just days after Billy Donovan agreed to a five-year, $27.5 million deal to coach the Orlando Magic, it appears he is heading back to the University of Florida.</p>
        <p>The Magic said in a statement yesterday that Donovan was ''conflicted'' about his future. And as every hour passes, the chances become slimmer and slimmer that Donovan will stand on the Magic's sideline.</p>
        <p>''While Central Florida, the Orlando Magic and Billy were energized with the announcement of his contract signing on Friday, we know there was a different feeling in Gainesville and people have been tugging at him since that time,'' the Magic statement said.</p>
        <p>''Billy is conflicted with those emotions and the opportunity he has ahead in Orlando and in the N.B.A.''</p>
        <p>Florida officials were not talking about a possible Donovan return last night. The athletic director Jeremy Foley told reporters yesterday that he had been advised by counsel not to speak on the matter.</p>
        <p>It remains unclear how easily the Magic will let Donovan out of his contract. The former Miami Heat coach Stan Van Gundy, who interviewed for the Orlando job before it was given to Donovan, is believed to be the leading candidate if Donovan leaves.</p>
        <p>Van Gundy has also interviewed in Sacramento, but Orlando would probably be more attractive to him because of its better nucleus of young talent and the proximity to his family in the Miami area. Throughout the interview process, Van Gundy has made it known that family is a priority. Van Gundy has been out of coaching since December 2005.</p>
        <p>The Donovan saga began Saturday when Foley flew to Richmond, Va., to meet with Virginia Commonwealth Coach Anthony Grant about becoming Donovan's successor.</p>
        <p>Grant, a former assistant under Donovan, was the leading candidate for the job, and it was expected to be a seamless transition. Many of Florida's recruits said they would stick with their commitments because Grant, who left Florida about a year ago, had helped recruit them.</p>
        <p>But Grant released a statement Sunday night saying that he had not had any ''in-person'' contact with Florida. Foley never met Grant because he learned that Donovan was having second thoughts. The story was first reported by Foxsports.com on Sunday night.</p>
        <p>Donovan was close to signing a long-term deal with Florida worth more than $3 million a year before deciding to go to the Magic. He won a second consecutive national championship with the Gators in April.</p>
        <p>In recent years, there have been a handful of coaches who have left jobs soon after accepting them. In April, Dana Altman left Creighton for Arkansas but changed his mind a day after his hiring was announced.</p>
        <p>''Generally, these deals are done kind of fast and in a clandestine manner,'' said Gregg Marshall, who two years ago left Winthrop for the College of Charleston only to return after his introductory news conference.</p>
        <p>Marshall, who is now the coach at Wichita State, added, ''This happens all the time in all kinds of businesses and professions, but usually there's not a press conference involved.''</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
