<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Star Power Backfires, Costing Agency a Client</title>
    <meta content="05adco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/business/media/05adco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852306"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">London (England)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Saatchi &amp; Saatchi</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Publicis Groupe SA</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cobain, Kurt</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Love, Courtney</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E4DA1130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Star Power Backfires, Costing Agency a Client</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Star Power Backfires, Costing Agency a Client</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC PFANNER</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dead celebrities are hot. From Einstein to Elvis and Gene Kelly to Orville Redenbacher, they keep popping up as posthumous pitchmen for everything from cars to cola.</p>
        <p>But when the London office of Saatchi &amp; Saatchi, part of the Publicis Groupe, recently featured images of Kurt Cobain and other dead rock stars in ads for Dr. Martens footwear, the agency and its client got burned.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When a London agency featured images of Kurt Cobain and other dead rock stars in ads for Dr. Martens footwear, it and its client got burned.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dead celebrities are hot. From Einstein to Elvis and Gene Kelly to Orville Redenbacher, they keep popping up as posthumous pitchmen for everything from cars to cola.</p>
        <p>But when the London office of Saatchi &amp; Saatchi, part of the Publicis Groupe, recently featured images of Kurt Cobain and other dead rock stars in ads for Dr. Martens footwear, the agency and its client got burned.</p>
        <p>Courtney Love, Mr. Cobain's widow, grew angry when she heard about the ads, which ran in a small British music magazine, Fact. One ad showed Mr. Cobain, who was the lead singer of the band Nirvana, sitting on a cloud in the sky, draped in robes and shod in Dr. Martens boots.</p>
        <p>''She thinks it's outrageous that a company is allowed to commercially gain from such a despicable use of her husband's picture,'' a spokeswoman for Ms. Love told People magazine.</p>
        <p>It was hardly the first time that Mr. Cobain's image had been used for commercial gain. According to Forbes magazine, which compiles a list of the earning power of dead celebrities, Mr. Cobain came in first last year, just ahead of Elvis Presley, reeling in $50 million for his estate.</p>
        <p>In this case, however, a legitimate use of the photo of Mr. Cobain, along with images of Sid Vicious of the Sex Pistols, Joey Ramone of the Ramones and Joe Strummer of the Clash, went wrong because of a series of missteps and the border-hopping power of the Internet.</p>
        <p>Saatchi &amp; Saatchi said that it found the images in the Corbis photo library and obtained copyright clearance to use them in Britain. Corbis owns the Roger Richman Agency in Beverly Hills, Calif., which arranges licensing deals for a number of deceased celebrities.</p>
        <p>The trouble began when an employee -- disobeying instructions, Saatchi &amp; Saatchi insisted -- submitted the images to www.AdCritic.com, an American ad industry Web site. In the United States, the estates of dead celebrities are allowed to control the use of their images; in Britain, however, lawyers say no approval is needed.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for Saatchi &amp; Saatchi, Eleanor Conroy, said the employee responsible for the breach had been dismissed. Kate Stanners, executive creative director at Saatchi &amp; Saatchi London, said in a statement, ''While we believe the creative is a beautiful tribute to four legendary musicians, the individual broke both agency and client protocol in this situation by placing the ads on a U.S. advertising Web site and acting as an unauthorized spokesperson for the company.''</p>
        <p>Sending an ad to sites like AdCritic is common, particularly when an agency or advertising executive is trying to seed it so that it can spread on the Internet. An ad's creators like to do this in order to generate chatter about their ads, which is helpful when awards season rolls around. Clients rarely complain, because they get free advertising.</p>
        <p>In this case, however, Airwair International, the British company that makes Dr. Martens, was not impressed. It fired Saatchi &amp; Saatchi by canceling its contract with the agency, reportedly worth £5 million, or $9.9 million, over three years.</p>
        <p>David Suddens, chief executive of Airwair, said that when Saatchi &amp; Saatchi approached his company's marketing department in February with sketches outlining the idea for the ads, ''We said firmly, 'No way.' ''</p>
        <p>But dead celebrities are popular in advertising at the moment. Gene Kelly appeared in a recent British commercial for Volkswagen; a digitally generated likeness of Orville Redenbacher is being featured in American ads for the popcorn brand of the same name.</p>
        <p>Mr. Suddens said that Saatchi &amp; Saatchi wanted to give the idea another try; it developed the sketches into proposed ads and showed them to Airwair in April. Executives at the agency said they wanted to have the images published at least once so that they could be submitted for awards, he added. An Airwair executive finally agreed to allow the ads to be used only in Britain, and only in Fact magazine, Mr. Suddens said.</p>
        <p>The company has apologized to Ms. Love, and Mr. Suddens said he was unmoved by the agency's argument that the use of the ads was legitimate in Britain. ''Enough people said it was offensive for us to consider it offensive,'' he said.</p>
        <p>It so happens that Airwair has focused its marketing on a campaign called ''Freedm,'' featuring a Web site, www.freedm2.com, that invites would-be rock stars and other artists to post their creations.</p>
        <p>Many marketing executives have been wary of user-generated content, fearing the loss of the editing that ad agencies provide. In the case of the Dr. Martens ads, however, it was the pros who got the client in trouble.</p>
        <p>ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
