<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Indian Officials to Rule How 'Backward' Group Is</title>
    <meta content="05india" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/world/asia/05india.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rajasthan State (India)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sengupta, Somini</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tribes and Tribalism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tribes and Tribalism</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">India</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E0DB1130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Indian Officials to Rule How 'Backward' Group Is</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Indian Officials to Rule How ‘Backward’ Group Is</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOMINI SENGUPTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sengupta, Somini</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, June 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Government of Indian state of Rajasthan says it will appoint panel to study demands of Gujjars, traditonally pastoralist group that seeks classification as socially and economically deprived tribe to become eligible for more government benefits; this follows week of violent protests by Gujjars that left 14 dead, including police officer; but Minas, largest group in Rajasthan, oppose sharing spoils of tribal backwardness with Gujjars; whether Rajasthan government might recommend that central government classify Gujjars as tribe remains unclear; ultimately, Parliament would have to vote on matter, prospect that is likely to be politically fraught; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They burned buses during the morning rush hour. They threw stones at trains packed with passengers and at the police. By Monday evening, after a week of violent protests that began in tourist-friendly Rajasthan State and ended up here unsettling the nation's capital, the Gujjars got their way.</p>
        <p>The Rajasthan government announced that it would appoint a panel to study the demands of the traditionally pastoralist group that has been clamoring for the right to be considered more ''backward'' than it is.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Gujjars want to be considered more socially and economically deprived and thus become eligible for more affirmative action benefits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They burned buses during the morning rush hour. They threw stones at trains packed with passengers and at the police. By Monday evening, after a week of violent protests that began in tourist-friendly Rajasthan State and ended up here unsettling the nation's capital, the Gujjars got their way.</p>
        <p>The Rajasthan government announced that it would appoint a panel to study the demands of the traditionally pastoralist group that has been clamoring for the right to be considered more ''backward'' than it is.</p>
        <p>Even by Indian protest standards, their fight has been confounding and violent. The violence began a week ago when clashes between protesters and the police left 14 dead, including a police officer. The Gujjars responded by destroying public and private property and cutting off highways and train lines to tourist attractions like the Taj Mahal. By the end, 11 more people had died.</p>
        <p>The Gujjars, officially classified as an ''Other Backward Class'' for the purposes of affirmative action set-asides in public sector jobs, want to be included in the list of Scheduled Tribes, which are considered more socially and economically deprived and thus are eligible for more benefits.</p>
        <p>But the Minas, the largest group in Rajasthan, opposed sharing the spoils of tribal backwardness. They gathered in their strongholds with homemade weapons, warning the government not to cede to Gujjar demands.</p>
        <p>In a news conference on Monday evening, the embattled Rajasthan State chief minister, Vasundhara Raje, said a government-appointed commission, led by a retired state judge, would study the Gujjars' petition and submit recommendations. Gujjar leaders endorsed her action and apologized for the violence.</p>
        <p>''We got what we asked for,'' the Gujjar leader, Kirori Singh Bainsla, told reporters in Jaipur, the state capital.</p>
        <p>The battle is hardly finished. To amend a group's official designation requires central government approval, preceded by an ethnographic inquiry into whether the group is culturally or physically isolated, speaks a distinct dialect and is sufficiently socially and economically backward to merit the change.</p>
        <p>One way to solve the current standoff, scholars have suggested, would be to draw more specific distinctions between those considered ''backward'' and those considered less so, or to take a fresh look at those who, as the sociologist on caste, D. L. Sheth, put it, ''have ceased to be backward.''</p>
        <p>Whether the Rajasthan government, based on the recommendations of a panel, might recommend that the central government classify the Gujjars as a tribe remains unclear. Ultimately, Parliament would have to vote on the matter, a prospect that is likely to be politically fraught.</p>
        <p>The Gujjars, who include both Hindus and Muslims, are by no means all pastoralists these days. Mr. Bainsla, the Gujjar leader, is a retired army colonel who has spent years rallying his group to demand tribe status.</p>
        <p>But then, caste and tribe are not fixed matters in India, either. They are subject to political bargaining. In fact, the trouble with the Gujjars was fueled by a pledge by Ms. Raje, the state's chief minister, during the state election several years ago, to grant tribe status to the Gujjars.</p>
        <p>On Monday, Sachin Pilot, a member of Parliament from the Congress Party and the country's most prominent Gujjar politician, accused Ms. Raje, of the Bharatiya Janata Party, of raising false expectations and failing to contain the violence.</p>
        <p>''You raise hopes, you make promises, you bear the brunt of what happens next,'' Mr. Pilot said Monday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
