<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Once, News Is Positive For Ailing Pitchers</title>
    <meta content="05pins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852405"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E4D81130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="779" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Once, News Is Positive For Ailing Pitchers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, June 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The way this season has gone, the Yankees have learned not to expect too much from their fragile pitchers. But they seem optimistic that Andy Pettitte and Roger Clemens will start the first two games of this weekend's home series against the Pittsburgh Pirates.</p>
        <p>Clemens had a magnetic resonance imaging test in Tampa, Fla., on Monday and was found to have disrupted scar tissue in his right groin. He will throw a bullpen session Wednesday in Tampa.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The way this season has gone, the Yankees have learned not to expect too much from their fragile pitchers. But they seem optimistic that Andy Pettitte and Roger Clemens will start the first two games of this weekend's home series against the Pittsburgh Pirates.</p>
        <p>Clemens had a magnetic resonance imaging test in Tampa, Fla., on Monday and was found to have disrupted scar tissue in his right groin. He will throw a bullpen session Wednesday in Tampa.</p>
        <p>''It leads us to believe he's going to pitch on Saturday,'' Manager Joe Torre said.</p>
        <p>Clemens was first scheduled to start Monday in Chicago but backed off because of lingering fatigue in his groin from his start last Monday for Class AAA Scranton/Wilkes-Barre.</p>
        <p>On Sunday in Boston, his friend Pettitte felt tightness in his lower back while turning to watch the flight of Wily Mo Peña's drive in the third inning. He lasted into the fifth but did not get the decision in the Yankees' 6-5 victory.</p>
        <p>Pettitte said Monday that his back had improved, and he planned to make his start against the Pirates on Friday. But instead of making two bullpen sessions, as he usually does, Pettitte said that he would make only one, on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>''I was concerned, because I've been feeling so good and you don't want anything causing you any discomfort,'' Pettitte said. ''When it happened, the big thing for me was I didn't want to aggravate it and have me out for a long period of time. Honestly, I was just throwing batting practice and hoping I could Houdini my way through it.''</p>
        <p>Pettitte said that he felt pain in the same spot of his lower back during spring training, but the condition was more severe then; he said he could not bend over and told Torre he had difficulty even sitting up.</p>
        <p>''I just told him, 'I don't want you to think you need to pitch Friday; I'd just as soon you feel well enough to do that,' '' Torre said. ''But he's more comfortable that I anticipated him to be.''</p>
        <p>Torre had not spoken with Clemens lately, but Pettitte said that they talked on Saturday, when Clemens decided to take more time before making his Yankees season debut. Pettitte said he told Clemens to take the time he needed.</p>
        <p>''As desperate as we are to get him in the rotation and get him going with all of us, you can't have him go down and be out a while,'' Pettitte said.</p>
        <p>ABREU SETTLES IN AT NO. 3 -- Bobby Abreu was back in the No. 3 spot in the batting order in Monday's 6-4 loss to the White Sox, and Joe Torre said that he planned to keep him there. Abreu reached base in 9 of 15 plate appearances over the weekend in Boston. He went 1 for 2 and walked twice Monday.</p>
        <p>Torre has proclaimed Abreu, who had slumped for a month and a half, to be back to himself before. Torre said that Abreu's at-bat Sunday, when he singled against the left-hander Javier López, convinced him again.</p>
        <p>''I felt good about him before yesterday's game and switched him back to third,'' Torre said. ''And that at-bat, in particular, just reinforced how we think he is.''</p>
        <p>WEIS VISITS CLUBHOUSE -- Charlie Weis, the Notre Dame football coach, stopped by the Yankees' clubhouse before Monday's game and met with Joe Torre and the players. Weis, a native of Trenton, might have gotten his biggest thrill from meeting the bench coach Don Mattingly.</p>
        <p>''You were one of my favorite players ever,'' Weis told him.</p>
        <p>Torre, who entertained New England Patriots Coach Bill Belichick before a spring training game in March, had never met Weis.</p>
        <p>''I didn't realize it, but he said when he was in New England, he was always standing up for the Yankees,'' Torre said. ''He would take the heat for everyone who was a closet Yankees fan. Down-to-earth guy.''</p>
        <p>MINOR LEAGUE STREAK ENDS -- Mitch Hilligoss, a third baseman for the Yankees' Class A team in Charleston, S.C., went 0 for 4 on Sunday to snap a hitting streak of 38 games. The streak established a South Atlantic League record and was the longest in the minor leagues since Orlando Moreno had a 43-game streak for Class AA Louisville in 1961.</p>
        <p>Hilligoss, who leads Yankees minor leaguers with a .326 average, was a sixth-round pick out of Purdue last season. The 2007 draft will be held Thursday, and the Yankees will pick 30th in the first round. General Manager Brian Cashman will be in Tampa to supervise the Yankees' draft, which is run by Damon Oppenheimer.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
