<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When a Picture Is So Good It Deserves a Frame</title>
    <meta content="05frame" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/technology/circuits/05frame.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SHOWING OFF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cameras</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cameras</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1D91130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="942" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When a Picture Is So Good It Deserves a Frame</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When a Picture Is So Good It Deserves a Frame</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILSON ROTHMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rothman, Wilson</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE time is right for buying digital picture frames. More than 30 million digital cameras were sold in the United States last year alone, yet millions of snapshots taken with them are never printed. Instead, they remain stuck on computer hard drives, brought up only by an occasional slide show or screensaver.</p>
        <p>There is a better way to enjoy your photographs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is an elegant way to free snapshots from computer hard drives: the digital picture frame.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE time is right for buying digital picture frames. More than 30 million digital cameras were sold in the United States last year alone, yet millions of snapshots taken with them are never printed. Instead, they remain stuck on computer hard drives, brought up only by an occasional slide show or screensaver.</p>
        <p>There is a better way to enjoy your photographs.</p>
        <p>An evaluation of nine frames found a few winners and more losers, based on subtle differences in style, technical ability and user interface.</p>
        <p>Most of the frames shared certain traits: bright L.C.D.'s, memory-card readers that support most digital-camera formats and, unfortunately, power cords.</p>
        <p>Because they are meant to display still images, these devices are not held to the same criteria as L.C.D.-TVs or computer monitors of the same size. Many frame makers persist in reporting those familiar L.C.D. specifications, like resolution, contrast ratio and maximum brightness, but they had little relevance in quality.</p>
        <p>A surprising number of frames can play MP3s and MPEG movies, and come with infrared remote controls. Those features, however, are often put in at the expense of user interface and visual performance.</p>
        <p>A truly advanced digital frame will connect to the Internet via Wi-Fi, Ethernet or dial-up telephone modem. When they go online, these frames can download photos that you have uploaded to photo-sharing sites, ones sent to you by other people or those shared over the Internet through photo-sharing sites like Flickr.</p>
        <p>But a frame should never be measured by its bonus features. The ideal main priority of a frame is its visual appeal and its simplicity. Connectivity is nice but optional.</p>
        <p>A well-known brand name does not necessarily mean better. At least four of the nine frames -- Aluratek, Coby, PanDigital and Westinghouse -- are based on the exact same blueprint: the same plastic housing with card reader, the same button array in the rear, the same software and the same ability to play MP3s and video files and connect U.S.B. devices.</p>
        <p>They differ in features, screen quality and frame elegance. The 14-inch Westinghouse DPF-1411 ($350) has a sleek ebony trim and no remote control -- the dot of an infrared receiver on its face would mar the aesthetics, a Westinghouse representative said.</p>
        <p>The 15-inch PanDigital Digital Photo frame ($300) has a remote control and an equally beautiful wooden frame. Viewed head-on, the Westinghouse and the PanDigital have tolerably good screens. The PanDigital is easily viewed from many angles in the room, while the Westinghouse screen's color and brightness are distorted when seen from the side.</p>
        <p>The two other frames in this family are cheaply made. The design of the 10-inch Coby DP-102 ($140) made it look too much like a PC peripheral. The 10.5-inch Aluratek ADMPF110 ($180) had wood-and-gilt trim that might be appealing to some and gaudy to others. Both have unattractive screens. Aluratek says its screen is high definition, but the images were pixilated and gritty.</p>
        <p>Digital Foci's 8-inch Image Moments ($200) was in the middle of the pack. Its nice-looking frame made a good first impression, but the screen distorted photos, so that people and objects appeared smushed.</p>
        <p>The right balance of frame and screen is found in the nine-inch Philips Photo Frame 9FF2CME ($200). Philips designed and built its own product, emphasizing usefulness rather than extras. One exception to this approach is an internal battery that provides an hour of use, which is enough time to pass the frame around the living room, like a photo album. The frame's brushed-steel bezel is slick yet versatile for home or office, and is attached magnetically; you can buy other bezels to suit rooms or moods.</p>
        <p>Where Philips is simple, frames from Kodak and Ceiva are sophisticated. Both are designed to display images you can upload to the Internet or send by e-mail or camera phone. Ceiva, which pioneered the connected frame concept more than seven years ago, said a lot of people have its frames connected to phone jacks. (They pay around $100 a year for this service.) In the middle of the night, the eight-inch Ceiva LF-4008 ($200) dials a central server and downloads pictures that you have uploaded or family members have shared.</p>
        <p>For people with broadband connections, the Ceiva LF-4008 connects by Ethernet or Wi-Fi (using adapters sold separately, $25 and $35 respectively). If you, friends or family members all have Ceiva frames and accounts, it is easy to blast photos to each other and even automate the flow. Unfortunately, the Ceiva looks like a digital appliance.</p>
        <p>Kodak took a more traditional route with the EasyShare EX811 ($230), a nondescript glossy black eight-inch frame. In this higher-end model, Kodak integrated Wi-Fi so the frame can connect to Kodak's free EasyShare Gallery. If you have a Wi-Fi network, you can log in directly from the frame to retrieve photos from your stored albums. When albums are shared through the gallery, you can find them. Unlike the Ceiva, the Kodak frame does not alert you to incoming photos.</p>
        <p>Some day, all photo frames may be connected to the Internet, but the technique still has kinks. For the Ceiva and Kodak, you may need tech support getting started. One frame, the Wi-Fi Digital Frame from a start-up called eStarling, highlighted its photo sharing from Flickr and other Web services. But at $249, it was expensive for its size and its screen quality was poor.</p>
        <p>Digital photo frames do not have it easy. It is not enough for them to masquerade as ordinary glass-faced 5-by-7 or 8-by-10 frames -- they must somehow justify their price. But straying too far from their traditional role will lessen their value, as will sacrificing picture quality for perks.</p>
        <p>SHOWING OFF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
