<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Findings Add Nuance To Discussion Of Early Sex</title>
    <meta content="05sex" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health&amp;Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/health/05baka.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852256"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Depression (Mental)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Depression (Mental)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E5DB1130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="725" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Findings Add Nuance To Discussion Of Early Sex</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Findings Add Nuance to Discussion of Early Sex</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS BAKALAR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Girls who have sex at an early age are at slightly greater risk than their peers for feeling depressed, a new study has found. But their self-esteem suffers only if the sex occurs outside a romantic relationship.</p>
        <p>For boys, having sex at an early age does not increase depression or decrease self-esteem.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Recent research reveals how boys and girls react differently to having their first sexual experience.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Girls who have sex at an early age are at slightly greater risk than their peers for feeling depressed, a new study has found. But their self-esteem suffers only if the sex occurs outside a romantic relationship.</p>
        <p>For boys, having sex at an early age does not increase depression or decrease self-esteem.</p>
        <p>''I suspected that there might be negative effects of early sex for some groups,'' said Ann M. Meier, the study's author and an assistant professor of sociology at the University of Minnesota. ''And that's what I found -- but only under very specific circumstances.''</p>
        <p>The findings, the authors say, may have relevance for the abstinence education provision of the welfare reform act of 1996. Programs that are financed through the legislation must teach, among other elements of abstinence, that ''sexual activity outside of the context of marriage is likely to have harmful psychological and physical effects.''</p>
        <p>This study, which appears in the May issue of The American Journal of Sociology, found mixed evidence for that assertion.</p>
        <p>The average age at which teenagers have their first sexual experience steadily decreased during the 1990s, according to background information in the paper, and now almost half of American adolescents report that they have had sex by the time they graduate from high school.</p>
        <p>Using data from a nationally representative study, Dr. Meier selected 8,563 adolescents in grades 7 through 12 who had not had sex at the time of an initial interview. They were reinterviewed one to two years later, answering questions about their emotional and mental health, family background and education, and social and romantic relationships. They also responded to depression and self-esteem questionnaires. By the time of the second interview, 1,265 of the teenagers had had their first sexual experience.</p>
        <p>The average age at first sex varied with ethnicity, from 15.2 years to 17.5, with blacks having sex at the youngest ages and Asians at the oldest. Lower family income also predicted sex at an earlier age.</p>
        <p>Dr. Meier divided the group who had had sex into those whose first sex was earlier than that of other teenagers, those who had sex at the average age, and those who had sex later than average. The study considered only heterosexual intercourse, and the depression scale, which measured only depressive symptoms, was not designed to diagnose clinical depression.</p>
        <p>First sex was associated with a decrease in self-esteem, but only among girls who were younger than the average age and not in a romantic relationship. Girls who had sex at the average age or later had no increased risk for depressive symptoms compared with those who had not had sex.</p>
        <p>There was a significant increase in depressive symptoms among girls who were in short-term relationships that dissolved, and having had first sex in that relationship increased scores on the depression scale compared with girls in similar relationships that had ended without having sex.</p>
        <p>Dr. Meier suggested that it was not so much chronological age that was significant in determining whether sex was psychologically harmful, but rather the deviation from the socially normal age.</p>
        <p>Laura Lindberg, a sociologist and senior researcher at the Guttmacher Institute who was not involved in the study, found this particularly interesting.</p>
        <p>''I think this is a good study,'' Dr. Lindberg said. ''I'm struck at how much you have to recognize that teen sexual behavior occurs in a social context.''</p>
        <p>''One of the big findings here,'' Dr. Lindberg continued, ''is that it's age norms and not the actual age that matters, and these norms vary depending on what group in society you're in.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Meier said that there were well-known negative effects of early sex, like early pregnancy and sexually transmitted diseases. ''But over all,'' she said, ''there are very few effects on mental health, either negative or positive.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Meier acknowledges that the study depends on self-reports, which may result in inaccuracies in the data, although the computer-based interviewing technique used is considered highly reliable.</p>
        <p>Moreover, it was not possible to control for all variables, and the changes in mental health could be caused by factors other than sexual activity. Also, Dr. Meier warned against generalizing the results to populations not included in the study.</p>
        <p>For example, the study did not cover those who had sex before the first interview, a younger group for whom the results might have been different.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
