<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Old N.B.A. Try Is Becoming Cautionary Tale</title>
    <meta content="05araton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/sports/basketball/05araton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852404"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Basketball Assn</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Collegiate Athletic Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Donovan, Billy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4D81130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="965" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Old N.B.A. Try Is Becoming Cautionary Tale</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Old N.B.A. Try Is Becoming Cautionary Tale</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Maybe Rick Pitino shared with Billy Donovan what he best remembers about his last N.B.A. coaching experience, when the grass in Boston looked so much greener than Kentucky's but life with the Celtics left him feeling a discredited shade of blue.</p>
        <p>Maybe in a reported telephone conversation between mentor and disciple Pitino reminded Donovan of how some of the same players who jumped to his every frenzied college command tuned him out as if he were an anthropology professor when they were reunited in the pros.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Billy Donovan’s flip flopping over the Orlando Magic’s offer is a reminder that despite the huge paychecks there is no magic coaching kingdom in the N.B.A.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Maybe Rick Pitino shared with Billy Donovan what he best remembers about his last N.B.A. coaching experience, when the grass in Boston looked so much greener than Kentucky's but life with the Celtics left him feeling a discredited shade of blue.</p>
        <p>Maybe in a reported telephone conversation between mentor and disciple Pitino reminded Donovan of how some of the same players who jumped to his every frenzied college command tuned him out as if he were an anthropology professor when they were reunited in the pros.</p>
        <p>Maybe Pitino, who coached Donovan at Providence and handed him his first post-playing clipboard, told him to stop believing in Disney-for-N.B.A. dollars because there is no magic coaching kingdom in David Stern's league, not even in Orlando, where the Magic recently made Brian Hill their former coach for a second time despite the team's first playoff appearance in four years.</p>
        <p>Though already contracted for five years and $27.5 million to move from reverential Gainesville to landlocked Orlando, Donovan had a change of heart over the weekend, second thoughts about leaving the University of Florida after consecutive national championships.</p>
        <p>The story, still developing, reminds us that nobody quite flip-flops with the flamboyance of a college basketball coach after rethinking the value of enhanced remuneration over continuous adulation.</p>
        <p>''It's difficult when you're dealing with a very successful college coach because they're coming from a situation where they have had everything their own way,'' Joe Taub, a former Nets' managing partner, said yesterday in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>When the inevitable N.B.A. flirtation arises, it is time for Coach Wonderful to say that he relishes the challenge of the next level while he privately worries about the conditions he will find there.</p>
        <p>No matter how many marches he's made to the Final Four, he can't help but wonder if he will succeed any more than a handful of college gurus who have made the jump before him only to discover they preferred their way to the players' way.</p>
        <p>Better than most, Taub and his former associates came to understand the maddening complexities of dealing with the hot and hyper college coach through a series of bizarre experiences that left all parties dazed and confused.</p>
        <p>In 1981, Taub lured Larry Brown away from U.C.L.A. and was rewarded with two winning seasons, or at least one and most of another that disintegrated when Brown negotiated a deal with Kansas near the end of the regular season and, caught in the act, was cut loose before the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Taub was out of the picture, having temporarily sold his stake in the team, when the Nets zeroed in on an N.C.A.A. champion four years later. Like Donovan, Rollie Massimino was fresh off a career-defining achievement, Villanova's 1985 upset of Georgetown. Unlike Donovan, there was no contract signed, only a handshake agreement, along with an appointment to seal the deal and announce it at a news conference several hours later.</p>
        <p>But at a Philadelphia roast for Massimino in the days before the scheduled consummation, Billy Cunningham, the former N.B.A. great and 76ers coach, stood up and needled Massimino, ''I hope you like it on Lovetron.''</p>
        <p>This was a comical reference to the mythical planet created by Nets center Darryl Dawkins, who had played for Cunningham in Philadelphia. Unbeknownst to the Nets, Massimino was already wondering where on earth he was going and getting himself into. The contract went unsigned. The news conference was canceled. More mystifyingly, the Nets still didn't swear off the almighty college coach.</p>
        <p>This was probably because Taub, back on the ownership team, had over the years struck up a close relationship with Pitino, who by the spring of 1996 had rebuilt Kentucky's disgraced program and won his first N.C.A.A. title at -- of all places -- the Meadowlands.</p>
        <p>Taub believed this was fate's matrimonial will. ''We didn't have anything signed, but I thought he was leaving Kentucky,'' he said. ''I really believed he was coming to join us.''</p>
        <p>Pitino proceeded to go to Ireland with a group of Kentucky officials and alumni for a few days of golfing and begging. Naturally, he reconsidered, announcing his decision on a bus to an eruption of cheers.</p>
        <p>Taub then considered Pitino's recommendation of another college coach, the Pitino-like but less likable John Calipari. Unfortunately for the Nets, Calipari didn't change his mind and made everyone miserable for two-plus seasons before he was fired.</p>
        <p>He later landed the job at Memphis, where he has built a national power and added credence to a longtime contention: the Type A sales approach that passes for motivational genius in the college arena is far more likely to fall on deaf professional ears.</p>
        <p>Even Pitino eventually came around to this line of reasoning after failing to restore the Celtics' glory, a task he undertook a year after turning down his friend Taub. Back in the college game at Louisville, winning again, he said it was finally clear to him that he was born to motivate young, impressionable minds.</p>
        <p>These epiphanies do not guarantee lifetime success. The college game is a cutthroat business, too, case-in-point being Massimino.</p>
        <p>When he returned to Villanova, Massimino said, ''I guess I'll be here for life.'' These days, he coaches at tiny Northwood University in South Florida after stops at Nevada-Las Vegas and Cleveland State.</p>
        <p>Billy Donovan doesn't have to worry about that now. He owns the last two national titles and that capital will carry him for a good while.</p>
        <p>He already turned down Pitino's old Kentucky job earlier this spring. Now he is said to be reconsidering $27.5 million and the leap to the pros, confused and making everyone a bit crazy. With all due respect, history suggests this could be a providential about-face that will, in the end, be better for all parties concerned.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
