<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yankees' Revival Takes a Wrong Turn</title>
    <meta content="05yanks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/sports/baseball/05yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852378"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago White Sox</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEFD91130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="904" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yankees' Revival Takes a Wrong Turn</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Yankees’ Revival Takes a Wrong Turn</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, June 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Roger Clemens was supposed to rumble into the Yankees' clubhouse Monday and make everything better. He would have received his pregame rubdown -- analgesic ointment smothered over his legs, back and shoulders, a pitcher's war paint -- and strode to the mound, an old sheriff back in town.</p>
        <p>But Clemens was in Tampa, Fla., working out indoors, throwing in the outfield and having a magnetic resonance imaging test on his fatigued right groin. He hopes to start Saturday, and the rookie Matt DeSalvo started for him here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Roger Clemens was not ready to start Monday, and rookie pitcher Matt DeSalvo gave an uninspiring performance in his place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Roger Clemens was supposed to rumble into the Yankees' clubhouse Monday and make everything better. He would have received his pregame rubdown -- analgesic ointment smothered over his legs, back and shoulders, a pitcher's war paint -- and strode to the mound, an old sheriff back in town.</p>
        <p>But Clemens was in Tampa, Fla., working out indoors, throwing in the outfield and having a magnetic resonance imaging test on his fatigued right groin. He hopes to start Saturday, and the rookie Matt DeSalvo started for him here.</p>
        <p>DeSalvo arrived at the park in jeans and an untucked blue-collared shirt. He ate two bowls of Chex cereal at a table in the middle of the clubhouse. He seemed to have gotten a haircut, which made him look vaguely like a high school student on class picture day. There was a copy of ''The Art of War,'' the ancient Chinese military tome, in his locker.</p>
        <p>It was an unassuming entrance before an uninspiring performance. DeSalvo lasted only an inning and a third at U.S. Cellular Field as the Chicago White Sox defeated the Yankees, 6-4. After the game, he was optioned to Class AAA Scranton/Wilkes-Barre.</p>
        <p>''Some days you throw really, really well in the bullpen, and you come into the game and you wonder, what happened?'' DeSalvo said. ''That's where I was today.''</p>
        <p>White Sox starter Jon Garland was as sharp as DeSalvo was off. With the White Sox' bullpen in shambles -- it has the worst earned run average of any bullpen in the majors -- Garland worked into the ninth, allowing one earned run in eight and a third innings.</p>
        <p>The Yankees, who were coming off a series victory in Boston, managed seven hits and three walks against Garland. They wasted most of their chances until a three-run rally in the ninth that started with a double off the centerfield wall by Hideki Matsui.</p>
        <p>Derek Jeter came up against Bobby Jenks with two outs and a runner on first, but he grounded to shortstop to end the game.</p>
        <p>''We can't make it a habit of falling behind and trying to score four or five runs off other team's closers,'' Jeter said. ''But just because we lost doesn't mean there was a letdown.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees' record fell to 24-31 as they started the second third of their season. If they go 24-30 in the other two thirds, as they did in the first, they will finish with their first 90-loss season since 1991, when Stump Merrill was the manager.</p>
        <p>''This is the time we're going to need to make a charge,'' said Johnny Damon, who snapped an 0-for-15 slump with an infield single in the ninth. ''Last night was huge for us. It just stinks right now. We know we're going to play better in June.''</p>
        <p>DeSalvo, 26, spent two days in the minors after being sent down Friday; he was allowed to return without waiting the required 10 days because a spot opened on the roster with Saturday's injury to Doug Mientkiewicz.</p>
        <p>In five games in May, including four starts, DeSalvo issued 15 walks and struck out 6 in 21 3/5sbquo 4/5 innings. Manager Joe Torre said that DeSalvo was being too tentative, meaning he needed to throw more strikes.</p>
        <p>If that was his charge, DeSalvo failed. He threw 44 pitches, and only 23 were strikes. The White Sox had no extra-base hits against DeSalvo, but he walked one, hit a batter and recorded only four outs.</p>
        <p>''We're asking him to do something he may not be ready to do just yet,'' Torre said. ''I think you've got to sort of give him a pass. Even though, pitching at this level, expectations are high, in all fairness to him, he certainly didn't fit in our plans for this year.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees scored for DeSalvo in the first inning, when Jeter reached on an error by second baseman Tadahito Iguchi and Bobby Abreu doubled to center. With the Yankees poised to score again in the second with two on and no outs, Josh Phelps grounded into his first of two double plays and Melky Cabrera popped out.</p>
        <p>It was still 1-0, but not for long. A single, a hit batter and another single loaded the bases in the bottom of the second inning, and Chicago scored on a forceout at third.</p>
        <p>That brought up the leadoff hitter, Jerry Owens, who bounced a ball to Phelps at first base. Mientkiewicz, a former Gold Glover, might have made a better play, but Phelps threw wildly into the outfield to allow Juan Uribe to score.</p>
        <p>On the play, Joe Crede slid into Jeter, who was covering the bag, then stepped on his foot as Jeter landed hard on the dirt. Torre and a trainer visited Jeter, who tried waving them off and stayed in the game. ''It's fine,'' Jeter said, his standard response for any injury.</p>
        <p>Iguchi singled to make the score 3-1, and Torre had seen enough. He pulled DeSalvo for Ron Villone, who induced a double play from Jim Thome to end the inning. Villone had no such luck in their next encounter, when Thome smashed his 480th career home run, a two-run shot in the fourth that gave Chicago the margin of victory.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>CARL PAVANO will have reconstructive surgery on his right elbow Tuesday in New York, with the Mets' team doctor, DAVID ALTCHEK, performing the operation. Pavano will probably miss 12 to 18 months.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
