<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Musharraf Issues Decree Cracking Down on News Media</title>
    <meta content="05pakistan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/world/asia/05pakistan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852374"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of the Press</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Islamabad (Pakistan)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Masood, Salman</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Musharraf, Pervez (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chaudhry, Iftikhar Muhammad (Chief Justice)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cable Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cable Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of the Press</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Pakistan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Supreme Court</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Musharraf, Pervez</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E0D91130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1013" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Musharraf Issues Decree Cracking Down on News Media</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Musharraf Issues Decree Cracking Down on News Media</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SALMAN MASOOD; Carlotta Gall contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Masood, Salman</byline>
      <dateline>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan, June 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Pervez Musharraf of Pakistan issues decree giving government more powers to shut down independent televison channels; move seen as effort to curb news media coverage of continuing political crisis over his suspension of Chief Justice Iftikhar Muhammad Chaudhry, who has not shied away from challenging government; several news channels say their transmissions were disrupted even before decree was issued, charge denied by government officials; increasing pressure on news media threatens to undo one of Musharraf's accomplishments: allowing some of Pakistan's media to be free from state control; about 200 journalists, lawyers and opposition politicians protest outside office of Pakistan Electronic Media Reguylatory Authority in Islamabad; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an apparent move to curb news media coverage of the continuing political crisis over his suspension of the country's chief justice, Gen. Pervez Musharraf, the president of Pakistan, issued a decree on Monday that gives the government more powers to shut down independent television channels.</p>
        <p>The decree allows a government regulatory agency to make new regulations on its own, to seize broadcast or distribution equipment and seal the premises of organizations that are operating illegally or against regulations. It also allows the agency to suspend broadcasters' licenses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The move was an apparent move to curb media coverage of the continuing political crisis over President Pervez Musharraf’s suspension of Pakistan’s chief justice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In an apparent move to curb news media coverage of the continuing political crisis over his suspension of the country's chief justice, Gen. Pervez Musharraf, the president of Pakistan, issued a decree on Monday that gives the government more powers to shut down independent television channels.</p>
        <p>The decree allows a government regulatory agency to make new regulations on its own, to seize broadcast or distribution equipment and seal the premises of organizations that are operating illegally or against regulations. It also allows the agency to suspend broadcasters' licenses.</p>
        <p>Even before the decree was issued, several news channels said, their transmissions were disrupted across much of the country over the weekend. GEO, the foremost independent channel, said its transmissions across most of Pakistan had been blocked since Sunday. The channel produces one of the country's leading political talk shows. Two other channels also reported heavy interference with their transmissions over much of the country.</p>
        <p>All of Pakistan's independent television channels are transmitted by cable companies, and journalists blamed the government for pressing the cable companies to block or interfere with transmissions.</p>
        <p>''The country is passing through a critical scenario,'' said Shahid Masood, host of the popular GEO talk show, ''Meray Mutabik.'' ''If no talk shows are allowed, if no discussion is allowed,then what is the use of a news channel?'' We are not a party in this dispute. We are just messengers. Why are you shooting the messengers?''</p>
        <p>But government officials deny the claims of interference. Muhammad Saleem, head of public relations and media at the agency that regulates the media, the Pakistan Electronic Media Regulatory Authority, said the government had nothing to do with stopping transmission of news channels. ''There is a dispute between the cable operators and media channels,'' Mr. Saleem said. ''We have no hand in this. We ourselves don't know what the issues between them are.''</p>
        <p>The moves against the television channels and Monday's decree appear to be the president's latest tactics in containing the political fallout from the suspension of the chief justice, Iftikhar Muhammad Chaudhry, who has not shied away from challenging the government. The chief justice's dismissal has added to growing calls for change after seven and a half years of military rule by General Musharraf, who seized power in a coup.</p>
        <p>The news media have given prominent coverage to the chief justice and to the lawyers, judges and opposition political parties around the country who have rallied behind him in his refusal to accept dismissal.</p>
        <p>But on Friday, the Pakistan Electronic Media Regulatory Authority reminded all television channels that live coverage of political events was not permitted by law. As a result, private media channels did not provide live coverage of the chief justice's speech on Sunday in Abbottabad or of the political rallies timed to the visit at which protesters chanted against the president.</p>
        <p>The increasing pressure on the news media threatens to undo one of General Musharraf's accomplishments: allowing some of Pakistan's media to be free from state control. More than 45 independent television channels have sprung up under his rule. Since the news media have aired growing criticism of his dismissal of the chief justice, he has argued that he supports free media but that news organizations should show responsibility.</p>
        <p>The president issued Monday's decree, it said, because Parliament is not in session and ''circumstances exist which render it necessary to take immediate action.''</p>
        <p>In an interview on Monday, Imran Aslam, president of GEO TV, called the government's claims that the transmission blockage was due to disagreements between television channels and cable operators ''convenient, to put it mildly.'' He said live coverage of political events was becoming unacceptable for the government because it ''takes in slogans, fiery speeches and rhetoric.''</p>
        <p>''News channels were asked to resort to recorded coverage and self-censorship,'' Mr. Aslam said. ''It was O.K.; we live in an imperfect world.'' But he said that his channel's coverage had been balanced, and that he thought the government should be able to accept at least some criticism of the type it faced on television talk shows.</p>
        <p>Mr. Masood, the GEO talk show host, said in a telephone interview Monday that his show was blocked Sunday evening as soon as it went on the air. He said he also had received anonymous threatening phone calls and that government officials had told his bosses to put him on paid leave to stop his program. In the show that was to be broadcast Sunday night, his guests -- who took part by telephone -- included a former army chief, a ruling party politician, and a retired judge, all of whom criticized the government of General Musharraf over its handling of the current legal and political crisis.</p>
        <p>Mr. Masood said that the Jang Group, which owns GEO TV, refused to bow to the government pressure and that he had no plans to go on a paid leave.</p>
        <p>Two other channels, Aaj and ARY-One, have reported intermittent blockage of their transmissions since March 9, when the judge was suspended. Mushtaq Minhas, Aaj's chief national reporter, said transmission was blocked in most parts of the country starting Friday, except for a brief period on Sunday. ARY-One faced similar transmission blocks over the weekend, according to the Pakistani news media.</p>
        <p>On Monday, about 200 journalists, lawyers and opposition politicians protested boisterously outside the office of the Pakistan Electronic Media Regulatory Authority here in Islamabad, the capital.</p>
        <p>''PEMRA and the government are fully behind the ban,'' Aroosa Alam, vice president of the Rawalpindi-Islamabad Press Club, was quoted as saying by Agence France-Presse. ''We have won our freedom after a long struggle and nobody can take it back.''</p>
        <p>As an active justice, Mr. Chaudhry took cases involving ''forced disappearances'' -- people believed to have been taken by intelligence agencies without due process.</p>
        <p>In addition, several politically charged cases are likely to come before the high court soon, including one challenging the legality of General Musharraf's holding the posts of both president and chief of the army, and one on whether the present Parliament can re-elect him president.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
