<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sinister Cellphone Brings Marital Pot to Bloody Boil</title>
    <meta content="05ishe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/theater/reviews/05ishe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852275"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ensemble Studio Theater</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Isherwood, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Macleod, Wendy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kohlhass, Kern</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Macvittie, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freni, Edith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rubin, John Gould</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Avers, Brian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Binkley, Pepper</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fenkart, Brian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cho, Julia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whoriskey, Kate</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andres, Jessica Jade</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barall, Michi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Griffith, Kristin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schneider, John Norman</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aronson, Billy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carr, Geneva</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyons, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ruppe, Diana</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shaud, Grant</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Labute, Neil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccarthy, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Delany, Dana</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slezak, Victor</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Marathon 2007 (Theater Festival)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Probabilities, The (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">My Dog Heart (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">First Tree in Antartica, The (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">News, The (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Things We Said Today (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ensemble Studio Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Labute, Neil</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Macleod, Wendy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cho, Julia</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Aronson, Billy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Delany, Dana</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Slezak, Victor</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McCarthy, Andrew</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2DB1130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1252" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sinister Cellphone Brings Marital Pot to Bloody Boil</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sinister Cellphone Brings Marital Pot to Bloody Boil</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES ISHERWOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Isherwood, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Isherwood reviews Series A of Ensemble Studio Theater's Marathon 2007: Wendy MacLeod play The Probabilities, directed by Kern Kohlhass and starring Bruce MacVittie; Edith Freni play My Dog Heart, directed by John Gould Rubin and starring Brian Avers, Pepper Binkley and Brian Fenkart; Julia Cho play The First Tree in Antartica, directed by Kate Whoriskey and starring Jessica Jade Andres, Michi Barall, Kristin Griffith and Jon Norman Schneider; Billy Aronson play The News, directed by Jamie Richards and starring Geneva Carr, Thomas Lyons, Diana Ruppe and Grant Shaud; and Neil LaBute play Things We Said Today, directed by Andrew McCarthy and starring Dana Delany and Victor Slezak; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gasp!</p>
        <p>The swift intake of breath that signals shock, dismay or horror is heard much less often at live theater than at, say, movie houses unspooling the latest adventures in torturing teenagers. Unless the name Martin McDonagh is on the marquee, audiences for stage plays can generally expect to leave the theater with the same number of gray hairs they had going in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Neil LaBute’s “Things We Said Today” is the most skillful entry in the first evening of the Ensemble Studio Theater’s annual two-part marathon of short plays.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gasp!</p>
        <p>The swift intake of breath that signals shock, dismay or horror is heard much less often at live theater than at, say, movie houses unspooling the latest adventures in torturing teenagers. Unless the name Martin McDonagh is on the marquee, audiences for stage plays can generally expect to leave the theater with the same number of gray hairs they had going in.</p>
        <p>So full credit to Neil LaBute for knowing how to get an audience in the gut. In ''Things We Said Today,'' the chief draw and the most skillful entry in the first evening of the Ensemble Studio Theater's annual two-part marathon of short plays, he delivers a simmering pot of marital conflict that rises to a bloody boil at its climax.</p>
        <p>The prolific Mr. LaBute, whose new full-length play, ''In a Dark Dark House,'' opens on Thursday at the Lucille Lortel Theater, delivers here a companion piece of sorts to his solo play ''Wrecks.'' That hourlong riff on the Oedipus story was seen last fall at the Public Theater in a production starring Ed Harris. At about half its length, ''Things We Said Today,'' featuring Dana Delany and Victor Slezak, offers another contemporary variant on a grim tale from old Greece. (Mr. LaBute has already written one latter-day twist on the same story, in the compendium ''bash.'')</p>
        <p>This play depicts a middle-aged man and his wife meeting at a city restaurant after a morning spent independently. She's pregnant and toting a passel of shopping bags. Their comfortable banter about the hectic unpleasantness of the holiday season turns tense when she casually asks to borrow his cellphone to check in with the sitter back in the burbs. He hems and haws, and can't seem to locate it. Maybe it's back at the hotel?</p>
        <p>Maybe it's that bulge in his jacket pocket, she calmly insists. And maybe he doesn't want her to see whom he's been calling this morning. Never mind the gruesome denouement: The scariest thing about ''Things We Said Today'' is how Mr. LaBute coolly reminds us that the everyday device we have all come to rely on so unthinkingly can be a sinister betrayer of the darkest secrets.</p>
        <p>Deftly directed by Andrew McCarthy, the play is fairly standard-issue LaBute in its depiction of the bottomless perfidy of the contemporary male. But Mr. Slezak gives a spot-on performance as a smoothly self-justifying cad whose series of earnest clichés explaining his conduct is almost comic in its comprehensiveness.</p>
        <p>A few samples: ''This is only one little part of me, the man that I am.'' ''I didn't want this to happen.'' ''I'm not defending myself, I'm not; I'm really just saying: 'Hey, honey, it's still me. I'm still the guy you married.' '' ''I'm trying to be adult about this.'' He even stoops to this chestnut: ''Tomorrow is another day, and you and I are going to learn from all this.''</p>
        <p>The smarmy fellow might have guessed what today might bring if he'd been a little more perceptive about his wife's unusual choice of attire. He noted the theatricality of her white tunic dress -- ''a little much for shopping,'' he had observed -- but the distinctly Grecian effect escaped him.</p>
        <p>As the betrayed wife, Ms. Delany is also terrific, gently modulating a performance that might have been a monotonous screech. Her quiet implacability, interrupted only by a few tears suggesting a river of anguish underneath the resigned exterior, is another clue to the play's lurid finish. But judging by that healthy cry of shock at the curtain, few in the audience connected the dots.</p>
        <p>The eruption of life-destroying horror in the commonplace lives of everyday people is a theme common to most of the other plays on the bill, although not one is anywhere near as effective as Mr. LaBute's little shocker.</p>
        <p>''The News,'' by Billy Aronson, is a surreal, meandering comedy about a woman whose response to the diagnosis of an apparently fatal illness is oddly chipper. From the hospital bed where she has received bad news after exploratory surgery, Karen, played with loopy spirit by Geneva Carr, chatters cheerfully to visitors.</p>
        <p>When her husband, George (Grant Shaud), arrives, however, she reacts with frenzied annoyance at his bundle of balloons. Then they make up, and the visitors break into song. Why? Because Mr. Aronson appears to be a disciple of the dark-but-zany school of playwriting exemplified by David Lindsay-Abaire. Alas, even whimsy must be orchestrated coherently.</p>
        <p>Still more obscure is ''My Dog Heart,'' by Edith Freni, a tedious, pretentious and also whimsical drama about that fatal disease of the heart known as love. A healthy young woman (Pepper Binkley) gradually wastes away after catching that bug from a scruffy fellow she meets at a dog park, while a narrator charts the course of her disease. (''Stage Five: We look for support from those we feel are suffering in similar ways.'')</p>
        <p>With overwrought dialogue and overworked medical symbolism, Ms. Freni pursues a bizarre metaphorical connection between the human and canine species that only Mr. LaBute might appreciate.</p>
        <p>Natural disasters of a more sweeping kind figure in ''The Probabilities,'' by Wendy MacLeod, a windy monologue delivered by a weatherman with the soul of a philosopher-poet. Bruce MacVittie ably plays this stern and earnest bringer of news about ''the very unpredictability that is life. The transience that defines what it means to be human.''</p>
        <p>The lesson is embedded in a series of grim stories about fatal encounters with the forces of nature. The moral: In the absence of oracles, best pay attention to the guy with the healthy tan and the pointer on the local news.</p>
        <p>The chilly climes of the polar regions figure symbolically in Julia Cho's ''First Tree in Antarctica,'' the most effective play on the program, aside from Mr. LaBute's entry. Ms. Cho, whose sensitive family drama ''Durango'' was seen at the Public this season, depicts a woman ruminating on persistent dreams of a region she has never visited. The meaning is gradually teased out for us, as we learn of her remorse over the decision to give up a child for adoption.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cho's restrained writing is admirable, but the play feels fragmentary and underdeveloped, ultimately too oblique in its emotional impact to draw forth a sigh. Let alone a gasp.</p>
        <p>Marathon 2007, Series A</p>
        <p>Presented by the Ensemble Studio Theater, William Carden, producing artistic director; Renee Blinkwolt, producer. Costumes by Amela Baksic; sets by Ryan Elliot Kravetz; lighting by Evan Purcell; props design by Amanda J. Haley; sound by Ryan Maeker; production stage manager, Jeff Davolt; associate producers, Justin Quinn Pelegano and Destiny Lilly. At the Ensemble Studio Theater, 549 West 52nd Street, Clinton; (212) 352-3101. Series A through June 20; Series B begins June 15, through June 30. Running time: 2 hours.</p>
        <p>THE PROBABILITIES  By Wendy MacLeod; directed by Karen Kohlhaas.  WITH: Bruce MacVittie (Weatherman).</p>
        <p>MY DOG HEART  By Edith Freni; directed by John Gould Rubin.  WITH: Brian Avers (Oranges), Pepper Binkley (Lady) and Brian Fenkart (Apples).</p>
        <p>THE FIRST TREE IN ANTARCTICA  By Julia Cho; directed by Kate Whoriskey.  WITH: Jessica Jade Andres (Adrienne), Michi Barall (Sylvie), Kristin Griffith (Mary) and Jon Norman Schneider (Shawn).</p>
        <p>THE NEWS  By Billy Aronson; directed by Jamie Richards.  WITH: Geneva Carr (Karen), Thomas Lyons (David), Diana Ruppe (Hillary) and Grant Shaud (George).</p>
        <p>THINGS WE SAID TODAY  By Neil LaBute; directed by Andrew McCarthy.  WITH: Dana Delany (Female) and Victor Slezak (Male).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
