<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Untangling the Choices And Finding Headphones</title>
    <meta content="05ears" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/technology/circuits/05ears.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852360"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="LISTENING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Sennheiser</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2D91130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="803" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Untangling the Choices And Finding Headphones</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Untangling the Choices and Finding Headphones</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARTY KATZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Katz, Marty</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE headphone cords that tether ears to portable music players can carry subtle messages. They may declare, ''I'm hip,'' or, ''I'm above your world -- I'm not part of it.''</p>
        <p>But in theory, at least, the music is the thing, and the earbuds that are packaged with many portable players may be more of a barrier to music appreciation than an asset. Listeners can do better, and the range of choices presents an ideal gift-giving opportunity because it doesn't cost an arm and a leg -- or an ear -- to buy equipment that can be enhancing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Better headphones equal better sound for portable music players.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE headphone cords that tether ears to portable music players can carry subtle messages. They may declare, ''I'm hip,'' or, ''I'm above your world -- I'm not part of it.''</p>
        <p>But in theory, at least, the music is the thing, and the earbuds that are packaged with many portable players may be more of a barrier to music appreciation than an asset. Listeners can do better, and the range of choices presents an ideal gift-giving opportunity because it doesn't cost an arm and a leg -- or an ear -- to buy equipment that can be enhancing.</p>
        <p>''Earbuds cost about 25 cents to make, and they sound like it,'' said Ivy Scull, a marketing vice president at HeadRoom, an Internet retailer of music accessories (at headphone.com).</p>
        <p>Replacement earbuds cost about $10. For a few dollars more, headphones, which come in various styles, can reproduce audio tracks with far greater clarity -- conveying details, textures and directionality. As important, better headphones mean the music is clearly audible at lower, safer volumes. By staving off hearing damage later in life, listeners will still be able to hear subtle sounds, like fingers on frets or page-turning.</p>
        <p>The proliferation of personal music players has led audio-accessory manufacturers into a frenzy of product development, with a dizzying array of features. Technologies to boost bass tones, say, may be enticing but may not create the best listening. Noise-canceling devices require batteries and circuitry that add weight, and they do not work when the battery dies. Headphones with extra bass ports may look good on paper, yet they could be uncomfortable to wear all day.</p>
        <p>While prices quickly escalate into hundreds of dollars, the following basic models are good gifts for the discriminating listener, who may even want different headphones for different purposes. List prices are given; products may be found for less.</p>
        <p>KOSS KEB24 -- These newly released earbuds for $25 are small, light and suitable for all-day wear, travel and indoor workouts (koss.com).</p>
        <p>''It's a new style of earbud that blurs the definition,'' said John Koss, the vice president. ''Instead of sitting in the outer ear, it's more like an inserted model with silicon cushions that tuck into the canal for sound isolation.'' As with more expensive in-ear styles, several cushion sizes are provided.</p>
        <p>SENNHEISER HD201 -- This $30 model is the opposite of earbuds -- big, old-fashioned cup-style headphones that can't be slipped in a shirt pocket (www.sennheiserusa.com). Because they are sealed, these headphones shut out external noise, and the 10-foot cable can reach TVs, computers and video-game players. They will work with personal music players if the volume is cranked up. In the audio world, they are considered sturdy, unsexy performers at a bargain price.</p>
        <p>AKG K26P -- The K26P, $56, is also an outside-the-ear style but can be folded (akg.com). It is known for good bass performance. Padded cans swivel on an adjustable headband, and the ear-covering design is good at blocking outside noise. The efficiency, seal and variable fit create emphatic sound suitable for strenuous outdoor activity.</p>
        <p>D-JAYS -- These crisp, punchy inserted headphones with good bass come with four tip sizes, all for $100 (jays.se). Two cable lengths can be combined to create one long cable, if needed. A relatively new Swedish brand, these are easy to find online.</p>
        <p>ULTRASONE ICAN -- At $129, this model has a sporty design to entice the style-conscious (ultrasone.com). Its sit-on-the-ears padded headset is novel -- the sound is aimed from the front of the head toward the external ear. The intent is to have music seem to come from the front of the listener, as in a live performance, with a surround-sound effect. Other headphones beam straight into the ears from the sides, which yields a more concert-in-the-head experience.</p>
        <p>SHURE'S SE210 -- These inserted headphones, $150, are excellent performers and ideal even for small ear canals (shure.com). Six adapters allow custom fitting. If you want to make a gift of an ear-canal model, the Shure may be the best fit.</p>
        <p>Beyond these headsets are models with better specifications at higher costs. Noise-canceling circuitry can reduce continuous outside noises like air-conditioners or airplane engines. Bluetooth devices like Sony's new $130 DR-BT21G (sony.com) can play wirelessly with remote controls and double as a cellphone headset.</p>
        <p>Comfortable fit is essential. In choosing such a personal gift, a good strategy might be either to select a model that sits outside the ear canal, like earbuds or can types. Models inserted into the canal are popular because they block external noise, and the music is closer to the eardrum. But how well do you know the size of a person's ear canal? And some player-cellphone combination headsets using Bluetooth might have compatibility issues best left to tech-heads to sort out -- with a gift certificate in hand.</p>
        <p>LISTENING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
