<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dominating Dover, Truex Earns First Cup Victory</title>
    <meta content="05nascar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/sports/othersports/05nascar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852313"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E2DA1130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="767" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dominating Dover, Truex Earns First Cup Victory</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dominating Dover, Truex Earns First Cup Victory</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <dateline>DOVER, Del., June 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Martin Truex Jr., the often overlooked teammate of Dale Earnhardt Jr., won his first Nascar Nextel Cup race Monday before half-filled grandstands, just hours after the former Nascar president Bill France Jr. died.</p>
        <p>Despite the low turnout, Truex, a 26-year-old from Mayetta, N.J., beamed when he climbed out of his black Chevrolet and was showered with confetti and beer. This victory, no matter how somber the backdrop, delighted him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Martin Truex Jr., the often overlooked teammate of Dale Earnhardt Jr., won his first Nascar Nextel Cup race Monday before half-filled grandstands.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Martin Truex Jr., the often overlooked teammate of Dale Earnhardt Jr., won his first Nascar Nextel Cup race Monday before half-filled grandstands, just hours after the former Nascar president Bill France Jr. died.</p>
        <p>Despite the low turnout, Truex, a 26-year-old from Mayetta, N.J., beamed when he climbed out of his black Chevrolet and was showered with confetti and beer. This victory, no matter how somber the backdrop, delighted him.</p>
        <p>''If you win at this level, you've beaten the best of the best,'' Truex said.</p>
        <p>Truex overwhelmed the other 42 cars in the field Monday, winning the rain-delayed Autism Speaks 400 at Dover International Speedway by seven seconds over Ryan Newman, who started from the pole. Truex led 216 of 400 laps, including the last 54.</p>
        <p>It was the first victory in 58 Nextel Cup starts for Truex, who will soon become Earnhardt's ex-teammate. Earnhardt announced May 10 that he was leaving Dale Earnhardt Inc., the company founded by his father, Dale Earnhardt.</p>
        <p>But Truex, a two-time Busch Series champion, has begun to show he is capable of becoming a standout in this series. Monday's victory lifted him into 13th place, from 16th, in the standings.</p>
        <p>''I think we're at the point now where we can be in the top 10 every week,'' said Kevin Manion, Truex's crew chief.</p>
        <p>Thirteen of 26 races that will determine the 12-driver field for the Chase for the Nextel Cup have been run, and the driver who is in 12th place, 48-year-old Mark Martin, is running a part-time schedule and has not disclosed his plans for the rest of the season.</p>
        <p>Truex's victory was also noteworthy because he became the first driver who is not an employee of Hendrick Motorsports to win a race in the new Car of Tomorrow. Hendrick drivers had won the first five Car of Tomorrow races.</p>
        <p>Jimmie Johnson, one of four Hendrick drivers, looked as if he might take a run at Truex late in the race, but the right rear tire on his Chevrolet went flat on Lap 382. He finished 15th.</p>
        <p>Newman was the only driver who had a shot to catch Truex after that. Newman took the lead from him three times earlier with quick pit stops, but Truex took the lead back all three times with a car that was clearly the class of the field.</p>
        <p>''He was smooth and patient at the same time,'' Newman said.</p>
        <p>Truex, who is in his second full season in the Nextel Cup, had to swerve past many obstacles just to reach the major leagues of stock-car racing -- not the least of which is that he is from New Jersey. According to Nascar, only 3 of 108 drivers from New Jersey have won a race in its top series.</p>
        <p>Truex became the first New Jersey native to win a top-series Nascar race since Frankie Schneider, of Lambertville, won at Old Dominion Speedway on April 25, 1958.</p>
        <p>Truex was in eighth place by the second of two so-called competition cautions, which came at Lap 65. Nascar mandated the cautions because heavy rains Sunday had washed away virtually all the tire rubber that had accumulated earlier in the weekend, giving the track less grip.</p>
        <p>Truex passed Newman for second place on the 117th lap and took the lead for the first time by storming past Carl Edwards eight laps later. Truex stayed out of trouble for the rest of the race, which is more than Tony Stewart and Kurt Busch could say.</p>
        <p>With the leaders on Lap 271, Stewart and Busch tangled, with Stewart sending Busch spinning into the wall. Stewart said Busch had not cleared him to make the pass. Ill will had apparently been building between the two all season.</p>
        <p>''He's raced us every lap like it pays a million dollars,'' Stewart said.</p>
        <p>Busch said he criticized Stewart's tactics when he pulled his wrecked car beside Stewart's car on pit road. Nascar officials told Busch to park his car for the day, and he finished 42nd. Stewart completed only 56 additional laps and finished 40th.</p>
        <p>''I have no idea what Tony Stewart had for us today,'' Busch said. ''He finally wrecked me. He got accomplished what he wanted to do.''</p>
        <p>Monday's victory seemed to clarify a lot of things for Truex. He and Manion are convinced their team is headed in the right direction. He promised that he would be celebrating with Dale Jr., his friend and, for now, his teammate.</p>
        <p>''We all love Dale Jr.,'' Manion said, ''but when he made his announcement, we all said we have to carry the torch now.''</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
