<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Padilla Jury Begins to Hear Wiretapped Conversations</title>
    <meta content="05padilla" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/us/05padilla.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852339"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Miami</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Chechnya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wiretapping and Other Eavesdropping Devices and Methods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wiretapping and Other Eavesdropping Devices and Methods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Padilla, Jose</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6D91130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="741" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Padilla Jury Begins to Hear Wiretapped Conversations</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Padilla Jury Begins to Hear Wiretapped Conversations</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GOODNOUGH; Terry Aguayo contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodnough, Abby; Aguayo, Terry</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, June 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prosecutors on Monday began playing the wiretapped telephone conversations at the heart of the terrorism case against Jose Padilla, including several in which a co-defendant discussed sending satellite phones, military tents and other equipment to ''brothers'' in Chechnya in the mid-1990s.</p>
        <p>The federal trial is now three weeks old, and until now prosecutors have spent almost every day seeking to assure the jury that the roughly 120 conversations they plan to introduce as evidence were scrupulously recorded and translated. The defense has tried to suggest that the translators, employees of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, were inept and even biased against Mr. Padilla and his co-defendants, Adham Hassoun and Kifah Jayyousi.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prosecutors on Monday began playing the wiretapped telephone conversations at the heart of the terrorism case against Jose Padilla.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prosecutors on Monday began playing the wiretapped telephone conversations at the heart of the terrorism case against Jose Padilla, including several in which a co-defendant discussed sending satellite phones, military tents and other equipment to ''brothers'' in Chechnya in the mid-1990s.</p>
        <p>The federal trial is now three weeks old, and until now prosecutors have spent almost every day seeking to assure the jury that the roughly 120 conversations they plan to introduce as evidence were scrupulously recorded and translated. The defense has tried to suggest that the translators, employees of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, were inept and even biased against Mr. Padilla and his co-defendants, Adham Hassoun and Kifah Jayyousi.</p>
        <p>Mr. Padilla, an American convert to Islam who was named an enemy combatant after his arrest in 2002, has the highest profile of the three but has not figured prominently in arguments over the calls.</p>
        <p>That is because his voice is heard on only seven of the 300,000 or so calls that the F.B.I. recorded from 1994 to 2001. The government added his case to those of Mr. Hassoun and Mr. Jayyousi only after transferring him to civilian custody last year, as the Supreme Court considered taking up the legality of his military detention.</p>
        <p>The three are charged with conspiring to ''murder, kidnap and maim'' people in other countries. The indictment accuses Mr. Hassoun, a Lebanese-born Palestinian computer programmer, and Mr. Jayyousi, a Jordanian-born engineer, of sending money, goods and recruits abroad to assist ''global jihad.'' It paints Mr. Padilla, a former gang member who met Mr. Hassoun at a mosque in Broward County, Fla., as a recruit.</p>
        <p>Defense lawyers say their clients are passionate and vocal Muslims with no connection to Al Qaeda and no intent to support terrorism. They merely wanted to support persecuted Muslims, the lawyers say.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jayyousi participated in all seven of the telephone conversations that the jury heard Monday. In a particularly tense call from 1996, a representative from Glocom, the company from which Mr. Jayyousi bought two satellite phones, told him the service had been cut off after the Russian government complained that ''armed rebels'' in Chechnya were using one of the phones.</p>
        <p>''This is a very, very, very serious thing,'' the Glocom representative said. ''This is the first time I've ever had this happen.''</p>
        <p>The Glocom representative said she might be able to have the service restored if Mr. Jayyousi would tell her who had the satellite phone and why they were in Chechnya. But Mr. Jayyousi balked, saying only that a nonprofit organization he ran, American Worldwide Relief, had ''relief work going on'' in Chechnya and asking if he could switch to a different carrier or be given his money back.</p>
        <p>Jeremy Collins, a witness who testified that he had helped Mr. Jayyousi run American Worldwide Relief, said the satellite phone service had never been restored. Nor, he said, did Mr. Jayyousi ever tell him who was using the phone in Chechnya.</p>
        <p>Earlier Monday, the jury heard from Herbert Atwell, a former convict who said he attended a mosque in Broward County with Mr. Hassoun and Mr. Padilla in the 1990s. He said Mr. Padilla had been very quiet and carried a Spanish-language Koran, while Mr. Hassoun gave fiery speeches about the importance of ''raising money for mujahedeen fighters all over the world.''</p>
        <p>But, in testimony that could paradoxically help the defense, Mr. Atwell said he had never perceived Mr. Hassoun to support terrorism or ''mujahedeen fighters'' to be terrorists. He said he believed they were ''defending Muslims under attack.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Atwell told the jury that Mr. Hassoun would often weep while speaking at the mosque about abuse of Muslims in Chechnya, and that he would show video clips of ''Muslim sisters in Chechnya and Afghanistan that was being raped and shot in the legs and stuff.''</p>
        <p>At that point in the testimony, Mr. Hassoun appeared to become emotional, wiping his eyes. For most of the trial so far, the three defendants have sat solemnly in suits and ties, occasionally conferring with their lawyers but mostly listening without betraying their thoughts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Collins also testified that he had helped Mr. Jayyousi publish a newsletter in San Diego called The Islam Report and raise money for Islamic causes overseas. They had medicine, tents, sleeping bags, boots, blankets and other supplies sent to Chechnya, he said, adding that he thought they were for humanitarian purposes only.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
