<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nassau Tax Relief System Faces Pressure</title>
    <meta content="05assess" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/nyregion/05assess.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852343"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E4D91130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1297" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nassau Tax Relief System Faces Pressure</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nassau Tax Relief System Faces Pressure</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT</byline>
      <dateline>GARDEN CITY, N.Y., June 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every year, droves of Nassau County homeowners seek tax relief by challenging their property assessments, generating a deluge of cases seen nowhere else in the state.</p>
        <p>The challenges glut the local court. They are decided in a murky legal process by part-time adjudicators holding hearings that average three minutes per case. Collectively, the rulings grant $20 million to $30 million a year in tax reductions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Each year, challenges to property assessments by homeowners seeking tax relief glut the local court in Nassau County.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every year, droves of Nassau County homeowners seek tax relief by challenging their property assessments, generating a deluge of cases seen nowhere else in the state.</p>
        <p>The challenges glut the local court. They are decided in a murky legal process by part-time adjudicators holding hearings that average three minutes per case. Collectively, the rulings grant $20 million to $30 million a year in tax reductions.</p>
        <p>Now, that system is under attack, with critics contending that the reductions are rife with errors and unfairly shift the tax burden to other homeowners.</p>
        <p>''This is not 'Judge Judy,' this is big business,'' said the county's elected assessor, Harvey B. Levinson, who is pushing for a new state law to revamp the system, an arm of the state courts. ''No other agency has the authority to give away over $20 million without any oversight by anyone whatsoever.''</p>
        <p>But defenders say that the real problem is flawed assessments. Taxes approach $10,000 a year for the owner of an average home that sells in the $500,000 range. ''This is the only forum for the poor homeowner to get justice,'' said Fred N. Perry, a lawyer who handles thousands of cases.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levinson acknowledged that ''people are frustrated and angry'' about their tax bills. His agency sets home values but does not control actual taxes, which are levied by local governments and school districts.</p>
        <p>About 128,000 Nassau homeowners, roughly a third, contested their assessments last year, which is not unusual here. Some cases were settled and some were dropped, but 56,000 disputes escalated into court appeals -- 83 percent of the statewide total. Nassau's court cases typically resulted in refunds almost half the time, though often by modest amounts.</p>
        <p>Though millions of tax dollars are at stake, Mr. Levinson said that many of the 150 hearing officers, who are recruited and trained by the state courts, are unqualified. They receive only three hours of training, he said, and are paid $300 for each batch of 20 cases, $15 apiece.</p>
        <p>The challenges here dwarf the number in other areas for several reasons, experts said. Nassau's caseload was stoked for decades by antiquated assessments with extensive overcharges.</p>
        <p>Assessment specialists, who charge contingency fees, recruited thousands of homeowners to file challenges, then won tax refunds that fostered even more challenges. A belated 2003 reassessment hit many owners with increases that resulted in further appeals, and annual assessment updates since then have kept attention focused on the issue.</p>
        <p>Only one other county in New York, Tompkins in the Finger Lakes, has countywide assessment. Elsewhere, assessment is done by cities, towns and villages.</p>
        <p>Here, homeowners first grieve their valuations at Nassau's Assessment Review Commission. Lately it has been granting reductions in about 7 percent of cases. If still dissatisfied, for a $30 filing fee owners can then appeal to court for a Small Claims Assessment Review.</p>
        <p>''There's nothing to lose,'' Mr. Levinson said. The proceedings are closeted in 6-by-12-foot windowless side rooms in State Supreme Court in Garden City. A hearing officer sits at a table with the homeowners' agent and the assessor's representative.</p>
        <p>They shuffle file folders and argue over the ''comps,'' with each side displaying charts that list other properties that they contend are comparable to the disputed home. Location, lot size, architectural style, square footage and sale dates are central factors.</p>
        <p>Thursday was typical, with hearings scattered around the courthouse. In the morning session, 60 of the cases were assigned to three rooms on the third floor, with a 9:30 starting time. An hour later, all those hearings were done.</p>
        <p>There were no transcripts. Within a couple of weeks, hearing officers generally issue a decision of a few sentences in each case. The assessors have no recourse to appeal, one of the things Mr. Levinson wants to change in state legislation. Mr. Levinson helped draft a bill filed by the State Senate's deputy majority leader, Dean G. Skelos, a Nassau Republican, but so far it lacks an Assembly sponsor.</p>
        <p>The bill would put a judge in charge, allow appeals and require hearings to be recorded and hearing officers to be well-trained appraisers. It would also require both sides to exchange evidence in advance, to end what Mr. Levinson calls the present ''trial by ambush.'' A special process would be created for homes valued above $1 million. ''It's obscene for a $6 million home to be revalued in a few minutes,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The popularity of challenges here is rooted in Nassau's history of having had one of the nation's quirkiest assessment systems, which nearly bankrupted the county.</p>
        <p>For decades, Nassau assessed homes based on 1965 land values and 1938 building costs. Those anomalies, along with oddities in commercial assessments, caused widespread errors that fostered thousands of suits. They dragged on for years and won hundreds of millions of refunds. The county borrowed to pay the refunds, incurring a $1 billion debt that helped create a fiscal crisis in the late 1990s. That required a state bailout and the imposition of an oversight board.</p>
        <p>A whole cottage industry of assessment specialists sprang up, with mass mailings promising to contest assessments for a fee of half of any refunds. ''They bombard people, recruiting them even before their assessments are issued,'' Mr. Levinson said.</p>
        <p>Even county legislators encourage residents to contest assessments they think are excessive. Newsday reported on Thursday that 6 of Nassau's 19 legislators had filed challenges on their own homes in recent years, with mixed results. The Nassau County Legislature does not control assessments, and no impropriety was indicated.</p>
        <p>Under court pressure, Nassau finally reassessed all homes in 2003, before Mr. Levinson took office. If those new valuations had been correct, Mr. Perry said, specialists like himself ''would be out of business.'' But new problems cropped up, and the filings kept on coming.</p>
        <p>One client of Mr. Perry's was Stanley Fisher of Great Neck, who said his assessment ''was grossly incorrect.'' He won a 23 percent cut, saving thousands of dollars.</p>
        <p>Another client, Thomas McCracken of East Williston, said he had won reductions four of five years. ''I'm not going to tell anyone what I pay in taxes, but it's ludicrous,'' he said. He added that he was willing to pay his share as long as his tax bill ''is correct.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Levinson contends that most assessments are appropriate now, making most challenges ''frivolous.'' Still, with hearing officers granting reductions nearly half the time, the resulting tax savings encourage more challenges.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levinson cited a 20 percent cut in the $2 million valuation of a home in Garden City, in a neighborhood with prominent residents like the soap opera star Susan Lucci. The reduction was based on a comparison with a house in lower-priced Hempstead.</p>
        <p>Raising ethical issues this year, Mr. Levinson also complained that seven hearing officers hired consultants to file challenges on the officers' homes while presiding over other cases involving the same consultants. A judge intervened to remove cases from those hearing officers.</p>
        <p>Stephen L. Plutzer, a hearing officer not involved in that issue, said, ''I'd like to think that most hearing officers bend over backward to be fair.'' While the hearings seem rapid fire, ''the decision process is much more involved,'' he said. Officers check the filings, hold the hearings, then ''take all the evidence and go back and review it and write up an individual decision,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perry estimated that a third of homes are still overassessed by at least 5 percent, and he objected to Mr. Levinson's proposed changes as an effort to block homeowners from getting a fair shake.</p>
        <p>Matthew Smith, whose Standard Valuation Service company is hired for research to defend the assessments, said that the figures ''are very solid.'' But the challenges continue, he said, ''because we're still paying for past problems.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
