<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shining a Halogen Light On a Senator's Dark Corners</title>
    <meta content="05dallek" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Washington; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/books/review/05dallek.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852277"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gerth, Jeff</person>
        <person class="online_producer">van Natta, Don Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Bill</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2DB1130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1102" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shining a Halogen Light On a Senator's Dark Corners</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shining a Halogen Light on a Senator’s Dark Corners</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT DALLEK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Her Way  The Hopes and Ambitions of Hillary  Rodham Clinton  By Jeff Gerth and Don Van Natta Jr.  Illustrated. 438 pages. Little, Brown. $29.99.</p>
        <p>Two new biographies of Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton, the New York Democrat who is a leading contender for her party's presidential nomination, will put readers in mind of Edward Gibbon's observation that history is essentially the recounting of ''the crimes, follies and misfortunes of mankind.'' Mrs. Clinton's Senate spokesman, Philippe Reines, has complained that these biographies ''are nothing more than cash for rehash,'' containing nothing new and largely focusing on the details of the suspected corruption that never produced indictments, despite the considerable efforts of a special prosecutor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jeff Gerth and Don Van Natta Jr. have written what will become mandatory reading for Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton’s opponents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Her Way  The Hopes and Ambitions of Hillary  Rodham Clinton  By Jeff Gerth and Don Van Natta Jr.  Illustrated. 438 pages. Little, Brown. $29.99.</p>
        <p>Two new biographies of Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton, the New York Democrat who is a leading contender for her party's presidential nomination, will put readers in mind of Edward Gibbon's observation that history is essentially the recounting of ''the crimes, follies and misfortunes of mankind.'' Mrs. Clinton's Senate spokesman, Philippe Reines, has complained that these biographies ''are nothing more than cash for rehash,'' containing nothing new and largely focusing on the details of the suspected corruption that never produced indictments, despite the considerable efforts of a special prosecutor.</p>
        <p>In ''Her Way: The Hopes and Ambitions of Hillary Rodham Clinton,'' Jeff Gerth, a former reporter for The New York Times, and Don Van Natta Jr., an investigative reporter at the paper, have written what will become mandatory reading for Mrs. Clinton's opponents.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gerth and Mr. Van Natta see themselves as relating the unvarnished truth about Senator Clinton. ''Never before has such a high-profile candidate occupied the spotlight for so long without the public's learning the facts about so much that is crucial to finally understanding her,'' they write. Mrs. Clinton; her husband, Bill; and their supporters have told a flattering story about the couple. ''Now it is time for another,'' less laudatory version.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gerth and Mr. Van Natta describe Mrs. Clinton's undeniable flaws. They see her as unable to acknowledge misjudgments on health care reform or her vote in support of President Bush's war in Iraq: she believes that it would ''arm her enemies and undermine her carefully cultivated image as an extremely bright person who yearns only to do good for her fellow citizens.''</p>
        <p>The book is almost uniformly negative and overly focused on what they consider the Clintons' scandalous past and the darker aspects of Mrs. Clinton's personality. Her ambition, for example, is seen as an unattractive compulsion that, at times, has led her into untoward behavior. They assert that the Clintons had a longstanding deal to win the presidency, first for Bill and then for Hillary, a secret pact of ambition.</p>
        <p>The evidence of such a pact -- interviews that have already been challenged in the press -- is less than convincing. Moreover, that the Clintons are ambitious and hunger for the public spotlight is obvious. But does this make them different from anyone else in politics, including two of our most notable presidents, Lincoln and Franklin D. Roosevelt?</p>
        <p>The book's greatest flaw is its flogging of all the Clinton scandals, not simply because they are so familiar and ultimately came to so little, but also because they give us insufficient clues to what sort of president Mrs. Clinton might be. It would have been more instructive to learn something new about why her health reform initiative failed or to explain in some detail why she was overwhelmingly re-elected by New York voters and has been, as even some Republican senators acknowledge, an effective senator.</p>
        <p>The third of the book devoted to Mrs. Clinton's Senate career is no endorsement of her presidential aspirations. They describe her as someone who has operated outside Senate rules and as having been careless in voting for the Iraq war without reading ''the complete intelligence reports.''</p>
        <p>Should Hillary Clinton's personal limitations -- her inclination to shade the truth in the service of her ambition, what former Senator Bill Bradley called her ''arrogance,'' ''disdain,'' and ''hypocrisy'' -- disqualify her for the presidency?</p>
        <p>It is surely preferable to have our most upright citizens sitting in the White House, but history repeatedly shows that presidents with character flaws have not necessarily been less competent leaders, especially in times of crisis, than those with a stronger moral compass: John F. Kennedy's womanizing hardly precluded his effective management of the Cuban missile crisis, and Richard M. Nixon's affinity for cutting political and legal corners did not prevent him from some exceptional foreign policy achievements, most notably the transformation of relations with China.</p>
        <p>Nor has a president's exemplary morals ensured good judgment in response to domestic or international problems. Herbert Hoover's personal integrity was of no demonstrable help in responding to the Great Depression. Harry S. Truman's affinity for plain speaking did not insulate him from misjudgments that led the country into a military stalemate in Korea.</p>
        <p>Carl Bernstein, the veteran journalist of Woodward-and-Bernstein Watergate fame, presents a more balanced and convincing picture of Mrs. Clinton in his competing biography, ''A Woman in Charge: The Life of Hillary Rodham Clinton.'' His book also has its limitations. Like Mr. Gerth and Mr. Van Natta, Mr. Bernstein includes too much recounting of familiar details about the Clintons' past.</p>
        <p>While there is no question about the important role she played in the Clinton administration, Mr. Bernstein is also hyperbolic about Mrs. Clinton's influence and importance. President Bill Clinton survived ''in office due principally to the actions of his wife, just as their tangled relationship,'' he writes, ''was central to his being impeached in the first place.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernstein adds: ''The impeachment of the president was a direct reflection of the choices she had made, the compromises she had accepted, however reluctantly, and the enmity engendered by their grand designs, successes and failures.''</p>
        <p>The best part of Mr. Bernstein's book is about the Clintons' failed efforts to put across major health care reform: an initiative that could have become one of the most important legislative measures of the 20th century, comparable to Social Security, Medicare, civil rights and voting rights. Mrs. Clinton's secretiveness and failure to give sufficient consideration to economic and political realities were central to blocking what the Clintons hoped could be the principal achievement of Mr. Clinton's presidency. Mr. Bernstein's analysis is not only a contribution to understanding the Clinton administration, but also to current and future discussions about how the next administration will try to deal with the country's health care crisis.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernstein also poses the essential concerns voters will need to confront in deciding whether they will support Mrs. Clinton's 2008 candidacy. In the past ''she has misrepresented not just facts but often her essential self,'' Mr. Bernstein writes. Yet in spite of her contradictions, she has almost always ''stood for good things.'' She is ''special,'' and if she consults her better angels, she has the wherewithal ''to change the world, if only a little.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gerth and Mr. Van Natta seem to detect no angels in Mrs. Clinton's nature whatsoever, much less better ones, and the result is a one-sided figure who never quite springs to life or feels truly authentic.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES Robert Dallek is the author, most recently, of ''Nixon and Kissinger: Partners in Power.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Robert Dallek is the author, most recently, of ''Nixon and Kissinger: Partners in Power.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
