<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tribunal System, Newly Righted, Stumbles Again</title>
    <meta content="05combatant" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/washington/05combatant.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852351"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE3D91130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tribunal System, Newly Righted, Stumbles Again</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tribunal System, Newly Righted, Stumbles Again</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM LIPTAK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Liptak, Adam</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush administration's attempt to create an alternative justice system for terrorism suspects, in the works for more than five years, has yet to complete a single trial.</p>
        <p>After an earlier version of the system was rejected by the Supreme Court last year, the administration and Congress went back to the drawing board. The result was the Military Commissions Act, which was meant to settle a host of difficult questions once and for all.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The White House’s attempt to create a justice system for terrorism suspects has yet to complete a single trial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bush administration's attempt to create an alternative justice system for terrorism suspects, in the works for more than five years, has yet to complete a single trial.</p>
        <p>After an earlier version of the system was rejected by the Supreme Court last year, the administration and Congress went back to the drawing board. The result was the Military Commissions Act, which was meant to settle a host of difficult questions once and for all.</p>
        <p>But the system took two more blows yesterday, when, in separate proceedings, military judges dismissed charges against prisoners held at Guantánamo Bay, Cuba, on the ground that the administration had not managed to comply with the new law it pushed through Congress just last fall.</p>
        <p>Eugene R. Fidell, a military law expert in Washington, said the development was but the latest in a long series of missteps.</p>
        <p>''This system, which the administration has had more than ample opportunity to get up and running properly,'' Mr. Fidell said, ''is continuing to bounce down the tracks.''</p>
        <p>No one will go free as a consequence of the decisions, and the administration has a variety of ways, yet again, to try to fix the system. It is likely to appeal the decisions to another new body, the Court of Military Commission Review. Further appeals, to the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit, are also possible.</p>
        <p>Several legal experts said military prosecutors had substantial arguments for reversal. And even if the decisions are sustained, the problems they identified can be remedied by amending Defense Department regulations or the Military Commissions Act.</p>
        <p>David B. Rivkin, a lawyer in the administrations of Ronald Reagan and the first President Bush, said the day's developments brought good and bad news.</p>
        <p>''The good news,'' Mr. Rivkin said, ''is that it shows you that the military commissions are not pliant or tame tools of the states.''</p>
        <p>''One the other hand,'' he added, ''this an aberrant and bad decision.'' (He spoke on Monday afternoon before the second judge's ruling, which seemed to deal the administration an even more decisive rebuke.)</p>
        <p>The question at the heart of the cases is a jurisdictional one arising from the fact that there are two kinds of tribunals at Guantánamo. One, the Combatant Status Review Tribunal, created by Pentagon regulations, makes a threshold determination about whether detainees were properly designated ''enemy combatants'' and are therefore eligible to be held at Guantánamo. That tribunal has not -- and this turns out to be important -- made determinations about whether those same people are ''unlawful'' enemy combatants.</p>
        <p>There have been 558 of those reviews; they are quite cursory.</p>
        <p>The second kind of tribunal is the military commissions. They are intended to hear war crimes cases, and resemble conventional courts. There have been no completed trials before a military commission at Guantánamo. Yesterday's decisions mean there are not likely to be any soon.</p>
        <p>The Military Commissions Act said the commissions could hear only war crimes cases involving violations of the laws of war ''by an alien unlawful enemy combatant.'' It added that the commissions ''shall not have jurisdiction over lawful enemy combatants.''</p>
        <p>The distinction is an important one, said Senator Arlen Specter of Pennsylvania, the ranking Republican on the Senate Judiciary Committee. ''It's not a crime to be an enemy combatant,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Lawful enemy combatants are, broadly speaking, uniformed soldiers fighting for a government. Unlawful enemy combatants, according to the Military Commissions Act, are everyone else who has engaged in or supported hostilities against the United States, including members of Al Qaeda and the Taliban.</p>
        <p>The question in yesterday's decisions was which tribunal has to make the determination concerning ''unlawful enemy combatants.'' Under one reading of the new law, only the combatant status tribunal can make it. Under another, the military commissions themselves can decide whether they have jurisdiction.</p>
        <p>The two decisions yesterday indicated that Congress had contemplated a two-step process, with the status review tribunal making the initial determination and the military commission trying the criminal case. The Military Commissions Act certainly required either the status review tribunal or, in its words, ''another competent tribunal'' to make the determination. Several experts said that other tribunal could be the military commission.</p>
        <p>If the decisions are upheld, either the Defense Department regulations governing the status review tribunals or the Military Commissions Act will have to be amended to allow the trials to go forward.</p>
        <p>That second option would be a welcome development, Mr. Specter said.</p>
        <p>''This may be an avenue for Congress to re-examine the whole procedure,'' he said, ''including habeas corpus.''</p>
        <p>More broadly, critics asked whether a separate justice system was needed at all.</p>
        <p>''This just reinforces the notion that the system is in chaos and that they're making it up on the fly,'' said Steven R. Shapiro, the legal director of the American Civil Liberties Union. ''The time is long overdue for all these cases to be transferred to military courts-martial or civilian courts.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
