<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critic's Choice: New DVD's</title>
    <meta content="05dvds" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/movies/homevideo/05dvds.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852251"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Critics Choice"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Martin, Dean</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lewis, Jerry</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDC1130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1144" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critic's Choice: New DVD's</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New DVDs: Dean Martin and Jerry Lewis</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dave Kehr</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dean Martin and Jerry Lewis Collection  Volume 2</p>
        <p>More than half a century has not proved sufficient to solve the mystery of Dean Martin and Jerry Lewis, nor to diminish their appeal. The mismatched pair -- the smooth crooner and the squeaky kid -- burst out of the smoky nightclub scene of the late 1940s and almost instantly became the dominant entertainers of postwar America. Martin and Lewis conquered movies, radio, the record industry and, not least, the emerging medium of television, the growth of which roughly paralleled their success.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than half a century has not proved sufficient to solve the mystery of Dean Martin and Jerry Lewis, nor to diminish their appeal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dean Martin and Jerry Lewis Collection  Volume 2</p>
        <p>More than half a century has not proved sufficient to solve the mystery of Dean Martin and Jerry Lewis, nor to diminish their appeal. The mismatched pair -- the smooth crooner and the squeaky kid -- burst out of the smoky nightclub scene of the late 1940s and almost instantly became the dominant entertainers of postwar America. Martin and Lewis conquered movies, radio, the record industry and, not least, the emerging medium of television, the growth of which roughly paralleled their success.</p>
        <p>Paramount Home Video has now released the second and presumably final volume of its ''Dean Martin and Jerry Lewis Collection,'' which consists of five films from the last years of their partnership: ''Living It Up'' (directed by Norman Taurog, 1954); ''You're Never Too Young'' (Mr. Taurog, 1955); ''Pardners'' (Mr. Taurog, 1956); and the two films that Martin and Lewis made under the direction of Frank Tashlin, perhaps the most creative comic stylist of the 1950s, ''Artists and Models'' (1955) and ''Hollywood or Bust'' (1956).</p>
        <p>(Missing in action are the team's 3-D movie, George Marshall's 1954 ''Money From Home,'' and Joseph Pevney's 1954 ''3 Ring Circus,'' the first of their films in Paramount's ''Motion Picture Hi-Fidelity'' process, VistaVision.)</p>
        <p>It's a remarkable collection, not least because Paramount has gone the extra mile and remastered ''Artists and Models'' and ''Pardners'' from original eight-perforation VistaVision elements, just as Paramount did with its magnificent reissue of Alfred Hitchcock's ''To Catch a Thief'' a few weeks ago. The images are crystal clear, and the vivid Technicolor almost erupts from the screen. By contrast, the transfer of ''Hollywood or Bust,'' made from normal 35-millimeter elements only three years ago, looks soft and dusty, though still quite watchable.</p>
        <p>The technical stats are important, because they reflect a time when the Hollywood studio predigital technology had achieved its highest level. Prodded by competition from television, the studios joined the great American parade of bigger, better and best, turning out widescreen color films with stereophonic sound that made the fuzzy black-and-white of television look like a Model T parked next to the gleaming, tomato-red Chrysler convertible that co-stars with Martin and Lewis in ''Hollywood or Bust.''</p>
        <p>The huge interior sets constructed for a film like ''Living It Up'' -- a reworking of the 1953 Broadway musical ''Hazel Flagg,'' itself based on the 1937 screwball comedy ''Nothing Sacred'' -- gave Hollywood filmmakers an unusual degree of control over color, lighting and the partitioning of space. Daniel L. Fapp's cinematography, Edith Head's costumes and the art direction credited to Albert Nozaki and Hal Pereira all come together in the service of highlighting the blue of Janet Leigh's eyes -- a shade echoed or complemented by every space she crosses, every dress she wears.</p>
        <p>Paradoxically, it was the greater volume of visual information with the high-definition formats -- VistaVision, CinemaScope, Todd AO -- that eventually forced filmmakers out of the studios and into real-world locations. If location photography meant better-looking backgrounds than the painted flats or rear-projection screens of the studios, it also meant that filmmakers had to curtail their creative urges in the face of unmalleable reality. The next generation of directors -- many of whom came out of television, like John Frankenheimer, Sidney Lumet and Arthur Penn -- quickly learned to capitulate, embracing the new realism that emerged in the '60s and '70s.</p>
        <p>No such barriers faced Frank Tashlin, a former newspaper cartoonist who received his directorial training at the Warner Brothers animation studio. A filmmaker accustomed to directing Bugs Bunny, Daffy Duck and Porky Pig was, of course, right at home with Martin and Lewis, who brought their own cartoon universe with them. Tashlin was happy to provide them with an appropriately stylized world.</p>
        <p>The central section of ''Hollywood or Bust'' finds Martin and Lewis driving that red convertible, the approximate size of a Swift boat, from New York to California, passing through an imaginary Midwest in which the skies are always blue, the road (before superhighways) is empty and inviting, and the haystacks and swimming ponds are overflowing with full-bodied calendar girls, sporting strategically abbreviated overalls. Here in seductive detail is America the Beautiful, the fantasy of ease and plenty and unbridled pleasure that the bounteous '50s made almost possible to believe.</p>
        <p>Tashlin was the most generous of satirists, a man who loved what he lampooned. The America he depicted was gaudy and vulgar, but undeniably fun. As a cartoonist, he was closer to Mr. Lewis's comic persona (''Artists and Models'' has a startling sequence in which a masseuse ties Mr. Lewis's legs in pretzels, just as if he were an animated figure), and he continued to work with Mr. Lewis after the partnership with Martin dissolved. But Martin is more than a straight man in Tashlin's films; he's part of a dialogue between two ideas of the American male.</p>
        <p>The contrast between Martin and Lewis is usually described in sexual terms: the sleek womanizer versus the gawky adolescent -- the original 25- (if not 40-) year-old virgin. But to borrow some terminology from Claude Levi-Strauss (one of the few French intellectuals, it seems, not known to have written about Mr. Lewis), their pairing reflects that cultural division Levi-Strauss hypothesized between the ''raw'' and the ''cooked,'' with Mr. Lewis representing natural man with all his animal instincts and complete lack of self-consciousness, and Martin representing the end product of civilization and socialization, polished and upholstered, distant and cool, self-possessed and vaguely duplicitous.</p>
        <p>If Martin was what America wanted to be -- the young country suddenly pushed to the world stage, matching the Europeans and the Soviets with a manner and cunning of its own, a John F. Kennedy before the fact -- then Mr. Lewis was what '50s America was afraid it was, still a klutzy naïf, an overgrown child playing with dangerous toys. (The threat of nuclear war surfaces both in ''Living It Up'' and ''Artists and Models.'')</p>
        <p>Martin and Lewis's friendship never seems less than genuine in their films, even when, as in the case of ''Hollywood or Bust,'' their last movie together, they were barely speaking on the set. Perhaps it is that warmth, that sense of collaboration and complicity between two fundamentally different characters, that gives these comedies their enduring appeal. These opposites not only attract; they also triumph. (Paramount Home Video, $29.99, not rated.)</p>
        <p>Also Out Today</p>
        <p>SEINFELD: SEASON 8 -- Twenty-two episodes from the eighth season, the first without Larry David, the show's producer, co-creator and frequent scriptwriter. (Sony, $49.95, not rated.)</p>
        <p>RESCUE ME: THE COMPLETE THIRD SEASON -- Denis Leary's emotionally damaged firefighter broods over the death of his son and his separation from his wife in 13 episodes from the 2006 season. (Sony, $49.95, not rated.)</p>
        <p>MISSION: IMPOSSIBLE: THE SECOND TV SEASON -- Peter Graves as Jim Phelps joins the cast for the 1967-68 season. (Paramount, $49.99, not rated.)</p>
        <p>Critics Choice</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
