<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Conrad Black Defense Balks on Trump</title>
    <meta content="05black" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/05/business/media/05black.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852364"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Hollinger Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Black, Conrad M</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Trump, Donald J</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E1D91130F936A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1223" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Conrad Black Defense Balks on Trump</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Conrad Black Defense Balks on Trump</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SIKLOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siklos, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, June 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Canada, at least, the criminal fraud case of Conrad M. Black was billed as ''the trial of the century'' as it began more than two months ago.</p>
        <p>Accusations that Mr. Black and three colleagues had looted more than $60 million from the international newspaper conglomerate that he built promised to put not just Mr. Black's oversize ego and life on display, but also a frothy brew of high finance, high society and high intrigue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A decision not to call as a witness Donald J. Trump underscored that the trial of Conrad M. Black has been mostly a muted affair.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In Canada, at least, the criminal fraud case of Conrad M. Black was billed as ''the trial of the century'' as it began more than two months ago.</p>
        <p>Accusations that Mr. Black and three colleagues had looted more than $60 million from the international newspaper conglomerate that he built promised to put not just Mr. Black's oversize ego and life on display, but also a frothy brew of high finance, high society and high intrigue.</p>
        <p>But a decision over the weekend by Mr. Black's defense lawyers not to call as a witness Donald J. Trump, underscored that Mr. Black's trial has been at times a colorful, but mostly muted and sometimes tedious affair.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Black's defense is expected to wrap up later this week after only a handful of witnesses, none of them the bold-face figures Mr. Black was known for associating with when he built one of the world's largest newspaper companies, Hollinger International.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trump would have been just such a witness. He had been expected to bolster the defense argument that a surprise party that Mr. Black gave for the 60th birthday of his wife, Barbara Amiel, in December 2000 was a business, rather than a social event. Mr. Black charged two-thirds of the $62,000 for the party at La Grenouille in New York to Hollinger International, where he was chairman and chief executive and where Ms. Amiel was a director and its vice president for editorial.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trump was expected to argue that he considered the event a business function because he was in the midst of negotiating a possible joint venture with Mr. Black's company to develop the headquarters of The Chicago Sun-Times, which Hollinger owned, into a residential and hotel tower. Other attendees have testified that they believed the party was a personal, not corporate, function.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trump said yesterday that he had been subpoenaed and planned to travel to Chicago but was told on Saturday that he would not be called to the stand. Mr. Black's lawyer, Edward Greenspan, confirmed that Mr. Trump was no longer on his witness list, but declined to say why.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trump declined to comment on his role in the case or what he would have testified but said he was pleased to be in New York with a clear calendar. ''I've caught up on all sort of stuff,'' he said in a telephone interview. ''I have a free day -- I haven't had one of these days in a long time.''</p>
        <p>Two people close to Mr. Black's defense lawyers said that the decision not to have Mr. Trump testify was based on their perception that the case was going well for them and that the prosecution had failed to deliver a smoking gun through 27 witnesses over 43 days. (This also makes it unlikely that Mr. Black will testify in his defense.)</p>
        <p>Since the trial began on March 14, the jury has been asked to understand complex corporate structures, tax issues and financial practices, which has led to some numbing stretches. But jurors have perked up whenever prosecutors have tried -- as they did yesterday -- to illustrate that Mr. Black was using the company to fund his lavish lifestyle.</p>
        <p>One charge against him is that Mr. Black bought a Park Avenue apartment back from the company on unfair terms. A tax specialist testified that Mr. Black had spent $4.6 million on improvements while occupied it, justifying the $3 million price he paid for the apartment in 2000.</p>
        <p>But an assistant United States attorney, Eric Sussman, then ran through numerous bills for furnishings and improvements, suggesting that at least a portion of the $4.6 million was spent on personal possessions that Mr. Black took when he sold the apartment in 2005 for $10 million.</p>
        <p>The jury paid close attention when Mr. Sussman ran through items like a $17,000 sound system and $9,000 diamond safe, ''Indian white marble reliefs of elephants'' (purchased for $17,710), painted rectangular stools in the Louis XVI style ($9,800), a ''Swedish figured birch 3-drawer commode with fossilized marble top'' ($12,000), $350,000 for three carpets, a $12,500 mahogany shaving stand that was used by Napoleon during his campaign in Russia.</p>
        <p>Defense lawyers have previously argued unsuccessfully for a mistrial on the basis that as a wealthy individual Mr. Black cannot be assured a fair trial. Mr. Sussman repeatedly reminded the jury on Monday that according to securities filings, Mr. Black and the company agreed that the apartment would be kept in an ''appropriately habitable condition for the uses contemplated.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, people with knowledge of the decision not to call Mr. Trump, who asked not to be identified because they were not authorized to speak publicly for the defense, said Mr. Black's lawyers were concerned that a circus atmosphere around Mr. Trump's presence could work against their client.</p>
        <p>After all, Mr. Black invited Mr. Trump to speak at a shareholders' meeting of Hollinger International in the spring of 2003 at a time when investors were agitating about payments to company executives and to Canadian holding companies he and associates controlled.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors two weeks ago introduced a note from Mr. Black to Mr. Trump in which he writes ''Dear Donald, Could I ask a rather esoteric favor?'' Mr. Black goes on to ask Mr. Trump, who was not a shareholder, to ''put in a cameo appearance and say a supportive word'' at the meeting because ''I'm sure it would have an impact on the group and be favorably noted in the press.''</p>
        <p>At that shareholder meeting, Mr. Trump praised Mr. Black and his former partner, F. David Radler, but both were eventually ejected from the company they built after an internal investigation raised questions about the payments that are now the subject of the criminal trial.</p>
        <p>In addition to the prospect of Mr. Trump being cross-examined about the 2003 shareholder meeting, there was concern that Mr. Black would attempt to exchange pleasantries with Mr. Trump in court, as he did last week with Kenneth Whyte, a witness for him who used to work for him as an editor in Canada. Mr. Black's lawyers cut him off.</p>
        <p>A few days earlier, they had promised Judge Amy St. Eve that they would curb Mr. Black from expressing his strong views on the trial outside the courtroom, something he had been doing throughout the trial -- including while granting interviews for a new biography on Richard M. Nixon that he has written. Among other things, Mr. Black had been quoted in various interviews in Canada and Britain saying he was ''at war'' with the United States for its persecution of him, and described the prosecutors in the Northern District of Illinois as ''Nazis'' whose case is ''hanging like a toilet seat around their necks.''</p>
        <p>After the testimony of Mr. Radler, who is the only Hollinger International executive to have pleaded guilty to a single fraud count in exchange for the promise of lenience, Mr. Black told reporters outside the courtroom that ''I don't think any jury in the world would convict anybody on the basis of what he said.''</p>
        <p>Despite his court-imposed restraint, the florid Mr. Black could be overheard during a break in the case on Monday quietly saying in the hallway that most of the prosecution's witnesses had ''left the courtroom in an eye dropper'' after being cross-examined by his lawyers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
