<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Outside Manhattan, Many Oppose Bloomberg's Traffic Plan</title>
    <meta content="09congestion" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/nyregion/09congestion.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853180"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403EFDD163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1323" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Outside Manhattan, Many Oppose Bloomberg's Traffic Plan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Outside Manhattan, Many Oppose Congestion Plan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDY NEWMAN; Ann Farmer, Maureen Seaberg and Ethan Wilensky-Lanford contributed reporting.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Bloomberg's fast-advancing plan to charge drivers $8 to drive in the most congested parts of Manhattan may seem geared mostly toward the suburbanites whom many blame for Manhattan's perpetually snarled weekday traffic.</p>
        <p>But in fact, most of the drivers who would have to pay the toll are the mayor's own constituents: residents of the city itself, who studies show make up more than half the people who drive to jobs in Manhattan below 60th Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Everyone agrees that something needs to be done about Manhattan traffic, but nobody wants to have to pay for it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor Bloomberg's fast-advancing plan to charge drivers $8 to drive in the most congested parts of Manhattan may seem geared mostly toward the suburbanites whom many blame for Manhattan's perpetually snarled weekday traffic.</p>
        <p>But in fact, most of the drivers who would have to pay the toll are the mayor's own constituents: residents of the city itself, who studies show make up more than half the people who drive to jobs in Manhattan below 60th Street.</p>
        <p>And if commuters from New Jersey and Long Island are irked at the prospect of congestion pricing, one can imagine how a Brooklyn resident feels about paying $8 to drive from one part of her hometown to another.</p>
        <p>''I think it's just wrong,'' said Dina Livingston, 36, as she readied to leave her home in Dyker Heights, Brooklyn, yesterday for her job on Wall Street. This neighborhood, like many in the farther reaches of what are impolitely known as ''the outer boroughs,'' is minimally served by subways, and therefore features a relatively high percentage of car owners and daily drivers.</p>
        <p>Bill Leonardi, an electrician in Staten Island who already pays $4 to cross the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge, was slightly more succinct. ''That's insanity,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Interviews yesterday morning with several dozen commuters from those parts of the city found consensus on two points: Everyone agrees that something desperately needs to be done about Manhattan traffic. And nobody wants to have to pay for it.</p>
        <p>Well, almost nobody. A few part-time drivers said $8 was a fair price to pay for less traffic in the busiest parts of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''I think that it's a great idea,'' said Brian Deimling, 37, who lives in Bedford-Stuyvesant, teaches at a private school in Brooklyn Heights and occasionally drives into Manhattan to shop. ''A car really is sort of a luxury in New York City.'' He added: ''I think it would make it more pleasant to be a pedestrian.''</p>
        <p>But most of the people interviewed whose business takes them into Manhattan every day found the notion appalling. Some even said they would sooner switch to mass transit than pay the fee.</p>
        <p>''That could change my commute,'' said Dennis Alicea, a banker getting coffee at an Exxon-Dunkin Donuts complex near his home in Bayside, Queens. ''I would probably have to take the L.I.R.R. and the express bus.''</p>
        <p>That, of course, is exactly what the mayor wants. His congestion pricing plan, which requires approval from state legislators, says it would reduce auto traffic in Manhattan by 6.3 percent, with a resulting increase of 7.2 percent in traffic speeds.</p>
        <p>That may not sound like much -- picture the thrill of racing crosstown at 5.36 miles an hour instead of 5 miles an hour -- but it would be enough to save a good chunk of the $13 billion in lost time, business revenue and gasoline that the mayor says congestion costs the region each year. The mayor says it would also speed traffic outside of Manhattan, on thoroughfares like Flatbush Avenue in Brooklyn, where drivers head for Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The mayor's proposal, a pillar of the long-range sustainability plan for the city that he unveiled in April, made a big step forward on Thursday when Gov. Eliot Spitzer endorsed it and the Bush administration said the city was eligible for hundreds of millions in federal aid if it enacted the plan quickly.</p>
        <p>Under the plan, cars would pay $8 and trucks $21 to enter Manhattan below 86th Street between 6 a.m. and 6 p.m. on weekdays.</p>
        <p>There would be exceptions. Those who paid a bridge or tunnel toll to enter Manhattan would pay only the difference between the toll and the congestion fee, so Mr. Leonardi, the electrician traveling from Staten Island, would pay only $4 more to enter the Manhattan business zone, or nothing if he spent another $4 to take the Brooklyn-Battery Tunnel.</p>
        <p>Also, drivers who stay on Manhattan's waterfront highways would be exempt. Manhattan car drivers moving within the congestion zone would pay $4, or $5.50 for trucks that stay within the zone.</p>
        <p>But it was plainly the very idea of adding yet another expense to the cost of doing business in the city that irritated those who live in New York City, even if they live a considerable distance from Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''Anything that will take away from my profits is no good,'' said Donald Migliorato, 46, who lives in Bayside and runs a messenger service that takes him into Manhattan once or twice a day.</p>
        <p>Small-business owners who do not have the option of moving their goods by subway or during off-peak hours were particularly annoyed. Several threatened to raise prices to cover the increased transportation expense.</p>
        <p>''It's a shame that we're going to have to pass this additional cost on to the consumer,'' said Mark Reyes, an electrical contractor based in Queens who runs three trucks laden with supplies into and out of Manhattan daily. ''Now everyone in New York is going to suffer because of those prices.''</p>
        <p>With gas well over $3 a gallon, many drivers complained that the congestion fees amounted to an assault on the middle class.</p>
        <p>''Probably it's better for the city finances, but it's bad for the working people,'' said John Z. Wang, a postal employee who lives in Dyker Heights, Brooklyn. Mr. Wang said that recent news that the subway fare could reach $3 by 2010 put the average commuter in a bind.</p>
        <p>''That's a good idea, to limit traffic to the city,'' he said. ''But the city should give a good fare to people.''</p>
        <p>The mayor says the money raised by the congestion tolls would go largely toward improving mass transit. Several commuters who work at odd hours said that would be imperative.</p>
        <p>''If they would upgrade the public transportation, I wouldn't mind,'' said Scott Pullman, the manager of McSorley's Old Ale House in the East Village, who drives in from Bayside in part because Long Island Rail Road service after midnight is skeletal. ''They have to make it so that people who work late at night are able to get in and out as easy as the day commuter,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Resistance to congestion tolls was strong in neighborhoods at the edge of the free zone.</p>
        <p>''What about the people who live near 86th Street?'' asked an Upper West Sider who posted to The New York Times Web site yesterday under the name ''meech.'' ''Congestion pricing will bring us nothing but increased local traffic, pollution and more cars searching for free parking spots.''</p>
        <p>In Long Island City, Queens, where many commuters from farther out already park and catch the subway into Manhattan, Joe Walsh, a trucker, predicted that the competition for parking spots would double.</p>
        <p>City Hall is considering creating residential parking permits in areas like Long Island City to discourage their use as parking lots. But Samuel I. Schwartz, a transportation consultant who supports congestion pricing, said that in any case, the parking impact of the tolls would be spread among 20 or so neighborhoods and towns that abut bridges and tunnels into Manhattan and would not cause problems.</p>
        <p>Some of the strongest support for the plan, not surprisingly, came from those who drive to Manhattan the least.</p>
        <p>''I agree with it,'' said Diane L. Giordano, a recreational therapist on Staten Island who lives in Dyker Heights and drives to Manhattan only to go to restaurants or clubs. ''There's too much congestion in the city, too much traffic.''</p>
        <p>But the manager of the Exxon station in Bayside, Litsa Douris, casting a glance at the steady flow of drivers willing to pay $3.29 for a gallon of her regular, said she doubted that congestion pricing would have any effect at all on the traffic.</p>
        <p>''If they'll pay the price of gas, for sure they'll pay that,'' she said. ''I really don't think anyone is going to stop getting into their car. They're hooked in.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
