<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Celebrating the Larger-Than-Life Man Who Coaxed Balanchine to America</title>
    <meta content="09linc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/arts/dance/09linc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853212"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York City Ballet</org>
        <org class="online_producer">School of American Ballet</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kirstein, Lincoln</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Balanchine, George</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kistler, Darci</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Martins, Peter</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03EED61F30F93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Celebrating the Larger-Than-Life Man Who Coaxed Balanchine to America</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Celebrating the Larger-Than-Life Man Who Coaxed Balanchine to America</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lincoln Kirstein came vividly alive in several aspects of his larger-than-life personality on Thursday night at the New York State Theater, when the New York City Ballet presented ''Honoring Lincoln.'' It would not have seemed surprising if an image of Kirstein, co-founder with George Balanchine of the company and its affiliated School of American Ballet, had risen along with the British flag at the end of ''Union Jack,'' the closing ballet in this centennial tribute.</p>
        <p>''Serenade,'' which opened the evening, was the first ballet Balanchine created after leaving Europe for America, coaxed here by a large, raw, manic young American who dreamed of establishing an American ballet and had the money and connections to do it. ''Mmmm, I think we'll start something,'' the choreographer said one day in the studio, in 1934, several months after the school had opened in Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lincoln Kirstein came vividly alive on Thursday when the New York City Ballet presented “Honoring Lincoln.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lincoln Kirstein came vividly alive in several aspects of his larger-than-life personality on Thursday night at the New York State Theater, when the New York City Ballet presented ''Honoring Lincoln.'' It would not have seemed surprising if an image of Kirstein, co-founder with George Balanchine of the company and its affiliated School of American Ballet, had risen along with the British flag at the end of ''Union Jack,'' the closing ballet in this centennial tribute.</p>
        <p>''Serenade,'' which opened the evening, was the first ballet Balanchine created after leaving Europe for America, coaxed here by a large, raw, manic young American who dreamed of establishing an American ballet and had the money and connections to do it. ''Mmmm, I think we'll start something,'' the choreographer said one day in the studio, in 1934, several months after the school had opened in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>That something was a haunting, exquisitely simple portrayal of young dancers and the demanding art that is about to claim them at the start of their careers, though Balanchine scoffed at such interpretations. ''Serenade'' was, he said, a lesson in the relationship between the classroom and the stage. And so the idea of having the opening section performed on Thursday by students from Kirstein's beloved school was especially poignant, and all but a fraught Darci Kistler maintained the atmosphere of luminous mystery.</p>
        <p>It is likely that Kirstein would have been pleased by the performance that followed of Peter Martins's ''Gentilhommes,'' a 1987 celebration of the company's male dancers. The cast was made up of students from the school, who looked much better by all accounts on the spacious State Theater stage than they had in workshop performances at Juilliard a few days before. True, Matthew Renko, the gifted lead dancer, is relatively short, but he and the other eight dancers beautifully combined superb technical skill with boyish gusto.</p>
        <p>Kirstein and Balanchine had a strange relationship. Kirstein was an enabler with some very odd ideas for ballets that Balanchine managed for the most part to ignore. He may have taken on ''Union Jack'' because of an affection for English pantomime and vaudeville. But Kirstein was an Anglophile with a passion for theatrical research, and how better to celebrate the American bicentennial, he apparently reasoned, than to honor the nation it broke away from.</p>
        <p>At its best, which ''Union Jack'' was on Thursday, the ballet is both a spare ritual and a catalog of national attributes and martial history. I will always miss Suzanne Farrell's slyly sexy leadership of the Women's Royal Naval Service battalion, whom Balanchine turned into wartime pinups. But this was otherwise an infectiously giddy, well-danced account of the ballet, particularly by Damian Woetzel, Yvonne Borree and Philip Neal. Nilas Martins's Pearly King was pure silent-movie mime and another high point.</p>
        <p>''Union Jack'' may well be ''visual, aural, metrical versification by an expert,'' as Kirstein wrote. But it is also a colorful spectacle and perhaps even an unaccustomedly affectionate bow by Balanchine to the brilliant, difficult, sometimes charmingly ridiculous notions of the man who made possible Balanchine's creation of an American ballet.</p>
        <p>The New York City Ballet performs through June 24 at the New York State Theater, Lincoln Center; (212) 870-5570 or nycballet.com</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
