<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shock Defeats the Liberty in Battle of Unbeatens</title>
    <meta content="09liberty" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/sports/basketball/09liberty.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853162"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Women's National Basketball Association</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Detroit Shock</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Liberty</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E6DD163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shock Defeats the Liberty in Battle of Unbeatens</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shock Defeats the Liberty in a Battle of Unbeatens</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID PICKER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the schedule for the W.N.B.A. season was announced months ago, there was no reason to expect that last night's game at Madison Square Garden would include two undefeated teams. For starters, the Liberty was coming off its worst season in franchise history. And while the defending champion Detroit Shock was expected to be strong again, unbeaten teams have never met this late in the season.</p>
        <p>But when the game began, the Liberty and the Shock were the only unbeaten teams in the league. Forty minutes later, the Shock had sole possession of bragging rights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Deanna Nolan scored a team-high 17 points as the Shock, off to its best start in franchise history, seized first place in the Eastern Conference.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the schedule for the W.N.B.A. season was announced months ago, there was no reason to expect that last night's game at Madison Square Garden would include two undefeated teams. For starters, the Liberty was coming off its worst season in franchise history. And while the defending champion Detroit Shock was expected to be strong again, unbeaten teams have never met this late in the season.</p>
        <p>But when the game began, the Liberty and the Shock were the only unbeaten teams in the league. Forty minutes later, the Shock had sole possession of bragging rights.</p>
        <p>Deanna Nolan scored a team-high 17 points as the Shock beat the Liberty, 67-57. With the victory, Detroit seized first place in the Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>The Shock (5-0) is off to its best start in franchise history. The Liberty (5-1) had been off to its best start since it went 7-0 in 1997, the league's inaugural season.</p>
        <p>''We weren't our aggressive selves tonight,'' Liberty Coach Pat Coyle said. ''I'm not sure Detroit got our best tonight.''</p>
        <p>Shameka Christon led the Liberty with a game-high 18 points and Cathrine Kraayeveld added 13 points and 7 rebounds. But it was not enough to stop the Shock, which had the tougher inside game and played more intimidating defense.</p>
        <p>The Liberty, at least, took control early. It raced to a 10-5 lead midway through the first quarter as Kraayeveld scored 8 consecutive points. The lead grew to as many as 7 by the end of the quarter, when the Liberty took a 19-12 lead.</p>
        <p>But the Shock went on a 7-0 run midway through the second. After Shannon Johnson made two free throws, the Shock led by 21-20 with 6 minutes 25 seconds left. The Liberty had a terrible second quarter, being outscored by 21-8. It trailed, 33-27, at halftime.</p>
        <p>''Once we started playing a little bit harder defensively and grinding it out and being gritty and being dirty, that's when we started taking over the game,'' Shock Coach Bill Laimbeer said.</p>
        <p>The Shock pulled away after halftime. Cheryl Ford made a turnaround jumper with 7:28 left in the third quarter for the game's first double-digit lead, and Detroit led by as many as 18 in the final minutes.</p>
        <p>''I think it was our experience down the stretch,'' said Swin Cash, who had 14 points for Detroit. ''They're still jelling.''</p>
        <p>Despite the loss, the Liberty is still the surprise team of the season. It traded its marquee player, point guard Becky Hammon, in the off-season and got bigger and younger through the draft with the rookies Jessica Davenport and Tiffany Jackson.</p>
        <p>Laimbeer said he was surprised by the Liberty's fast start. But when asked if he considered the Liberty an elite team, he said, ''The jury's still out.''</p>
        <p>As for the Shock, its start is hardly surprising. It has won two of the past four titles, and five of its players began the day averaging 12 or more points. But it also came into the game leading the league in turnovers with 21 a game.</p>
        <p>The Liberty was hoping to force turnovers and control the tempo.</p>
        <p>''With Detroit, you got to limit the transition,'' Coyle said before the game. ''They just run all over people.''</p>
        <p>The Shock had 14 turnovers last night, leading to 12 points, but only five turnovers came after halftime. And the Shock controlled the tempo, especially on defense, as it forced the Liberty into long possessions.</p>
        <p>The Liberty entered the game leading the league in field-goal percentage (46.8 percent). But it made only 21 of 65 shots (32.3 percent), hardly the way to maintain an undefeated record.</p>
        <p>''We had the shots we wanted,'' Kraayeveld said. ''We got good inside looks; we got good outside looks. We just missed the ones that we would normally make.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
