<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-Champion Is Prepared To Join March</title>
    <meta content="09griffith" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/sports/othersports/09griffith.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853190"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Greenwich Village (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Boxing Hall of Fame</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E6DC163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="893" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-Champion Is Prepared To Join March</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ex-Champion Is Prepared to Join March</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AIMEE BERG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Emile Griffith will ride in the parade of champions at the International Boxing Hall of Fame induction tomorrow in Canastota, N.Y., as he has done almost every year since he was enshrined in 1990.</p>
        <p>But on June 24, Griffith is committed to doing something he has never done: participate in the Gay Pride march down Fifth Avenue. As a guest of the Stonewall Veterans' Association, his car will appear toward the front of the procession.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Former boxing champion Emile Griffith has kept his distance from the gay community  until now. On June 24 he will participate in the Gay Pride march down Fifth Avenue in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Emile Griffith will ride in the parade of champions at the International Boxing Hall of Fame induction tomorrow in Canastota, N.Y., as he has done almost every year since he was enshrined in 1990.</p>
        <p>But on June 24, Griffith is committed to doing something he has never done: participate in the Gay Pride march down Fifth Avenue. As a guest of the Stonewall Veterans' Association, his car will appear toward the front of the procession.</p>
        <p>Although Griffith is the vice president of the association, he has never said unequivocally that he was gay. But he has come close. On those occasions, however, the question was asked directly, putting him in an uncomfortable situation.</p>
        <p>But Sunday at his home in Hempstead on Long Island, the 69-year-old Griffith was in an expansive mood during a two-hour interview. His concentration lapsed occasionally and his memory often failed -- the effect of 112 professional fights over 20 years and a brutal mugging in 1992 -- but he easily remembered the distinction between the boxing and gay subcultures, and how he managed to navigate between them while he was in his prime.</p>
        <p>''My fights came first,'' he said. ''But when I had my free time, sometimes I'd make up my mind to go to gay clubs.''</p>
        <p>Griffith was aware that being seen carried the risk of being outed, and he guarded his privacy the best he could.</p>
        <p>''I was always worried,'' he said. ''I'd never go alone. I'd always go with my friends, so I was always protected. They made sure no one would bother me.''</p>
        <p>Inside, he enjoyed himself. Although he can no longer remember the name of every dance hall, the Stonewall Inn in Greenwich Village was special. ''Couldn't get me out of that place,'' he said. ''I really enjoyed myself there.''</p>
        <p>When Griffith patronized gay establishments during his athletic prime, ''he was really ahead of his time,'' said Williamson Henderson, founding president of the Stonewall Veterans' Association, a group made up of several participants in the 1969 uprising in Greenwich Village that started the modern gay rights movement.</p>
        <p>''Now when an athlete comes out,'' Henderson said, ''they're regarded as being a hero to the community.'' Simply by frequenting the clubs, Henderson said, ''Emile did that a long time ago. When are they going to declare him a hero?''</p>
        <p>Hero of the gay rights movement is one title that was never sought by Griffith, a former welterweight and middleweight champion. In fact, Griffith deliberately kept the two worlds separate because he knew what would happen if his private life collided with his boxing life.</p>
        <p>The most notorious clash came in March 1962, during the weigh-in before his third match against Benny Paret for the welterweight title. Witnesses said that Paret directed a homosexual slur at Griffith, whose trainer, Gil Clancy, instructed him not to react. As usual, Griffith obeyed.</p>
        <p>The bout was televised, and millions watched as Griffith recaptured the title after he sent Paret slithering down the ropes and onto the canvas for a 12th-round technical knockout. Paret died several days later.</p>
        <p>''They could have stopped the fight at any time,'' Henderson said. ''It's not Emile's fault that they allowed it to go on too long. It was a grudge fight and he set a precedent there, about not calling someone, a gay person, a slur word. That should be monumental in gay history.''</p>
        <p>Except that Griffith has kept his distance from the gay community -- until now. It is doubtful, however, that his participation in the march was his own idea. In fact, he doesn't remember whose idea it was. He doesn't remember asking to run for the association's vice presidency. He doesn't even know whether he was at the Stonewall Inn during the six nights of the uprising, a prerequisite for all association officers. He wanted to be in the parade because, he said, ''I'd like to go and see what's going on.''</p>
        <p>''I don't know what they're going to do,'' he said, referring to the public reaction. ''I really don't. I don't think they're going to ask me about my sexuality or anything else. Why worry about it? I just get tired of talking about the same thing over and over. They've got to figure it out themselves.''</p>
        <p>Griffith usually tells people what they want to hear, anyway. And he often does not remember his response. On Sunday, when conversation turned to a biography for which Griffith has been interviewed off-and-on for several years, he recalled telling the writer he was gay.</p>
        <p>His roommate and caretaker for the past 28 years, Luis Rodrigo, interjected, ''Is it coming from you when you're saying, 'Yes, I'm gay'? ''</p>
        <p>''Yes, I'm gay,'' Griffith responded. ''Is there a twin here? I don't see anything wrong with being gay. If that's what I want to do? If that's who I want to be? It's up to me. I give up. I give up trying to explain it.''</p>
        <p>''You surrender?'' Rodrigo said.</p>
        <p>''Leave me alone,'' Griffith replied.</p>
        <p>''O.K., Pilgrim.''</p>
        <p>''Leave me alone.''</p>
        <p>Later, Rodrigo left the room to answer a call. Griffith then said he had been joking when he said he was gay. He said he felt pressured. Even his closest allies dare to prod him, and no matter what he replies, it seems to leave him against the ropes doing what he has always done: fighting.</p>
        <p>BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
