<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spanish Guitars, Fast Footwork, Everything but the Cafe</title>
    <meta content="09noch" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/arts/dance/09noch.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853214"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Flamenco (Dance)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flamenco (Dance)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Noche Flamenca</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Barrio, Soledad</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Perez, Miguel</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEED61F30F93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="522" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spanish Guitars, Fast Footwork, Everything but the Cafe</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spanish Guitars, Fast Footwork, Everything but the Cafe</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROSLYN SULCAS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Flamenco is a soloist's art, an expression of emotion and individuality that is ideally performed in the casual surroundings of cafes and noisy bars. But it's also an ever more popular theatrical form, and flamenco artists have to battle with the conundrum of choreographing spontaneity and reliably evoking the heat and passion that audiences love.</p>
        <p>Noche Flamenca, which returned to Theater 80 in the East Village last week for its summer season, does a pretty good job of all this even if its new program, ''Aldaba,'' is heavily weighted toward the rawly emotional side of flamenco, with mixed results. Choreographed by the artistic director, Martín Santangelo, and the company, it's a smoothly constructed and pleasurable evening of impassioned, keening song; welling guitars; and the intricate tattoos of footwork and sinuous lines fashioned by the dancers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Flamenco artists have to battle with the conundrum of choreographing spontaneity and reliably evoking the heat and passion that audiences love.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Flamenco is a soloist's art, an expression of emotion and individuality that is ideally performed in the casual surroundings of cafes and noisy bars. But it's also an ever more popular theatrical form, and flamenco artists have to battle with the conundrum of choreographing spontaneity and reliably evoking the heat and passion that audiences love.</p>
        <p>Noche Flamenca, which returned to Theater 80 in the East Village last week for its summer season, does a pretty good job of all this even if its new program, ''Aldaba,'' is heavily weighted toward the rawly emotional side of flamenco, with mixed results. Choreographed by the artistic director, Martín Santangelo, and the company, it's a smoothly constructed and pleasurable evening of impassioned, keening song; welling guitars; and the intricate tattoos of footwork and sinuous lines fashioned by the dancers.</p>
        <p>The slightly shabby, low-ceilinged 160-seat theater is about as close to the casual cafe ambience of flamenco as a theater is likely to get. And Mr. Santangelo does well at delicately shaping the performance into different sections without heavily imposing a theatrical structure on a form that must appear uninhibited. (A word also for the uncredited costumes, which, as flamenco outfits go, are models of tasteful restraint.)</p>
        <p>But the emotional quality of flamenco cannot be choreographed; it's an intangible consequence of the dancers' and musicians' intense identification with their art in the moment of performance. And with the exception of the company's star, Soledad Barrio, the dancers (Alejandro Granados, Alfonso Losa, Vanesa Coloma and Elena Martin) on Thursday night too often substituted an intensity of facial expression or gesture for the elusive real thing.</p>
        <p>The program begins with the musicians (Miguel Perez, Chuscales), singers (Manuel Gago and José Anillo) and dancers sitting in a wide semicircle, their singing and clapping punctuated by laughter and friendly banter.</p>
        <p>But the cheerful group soon dissolves, and Mr. Losa plunges into a fiery solo, his feet beating out complex rhythms as the singers surround him on a darkened stage. From here on, the mood remains intense. In ''Se Me Va'' (''She's Leaving Me''), Ms. Coloma darts fiery looks at the audience, sashaying through partly open curtains as Mr. Anillo sings.</p>
        <p>And in ''Siguiriya,'' a dance of grief or mourning that is a flamenco standard, Mr. Granados offered, on Thursday, an impressively slow build from small stamps to stuttering beats, but not much intensity of feeling.</p>
        <p>Ms. Barrio, often rightly lauded for the power and intensity of her performances, lends her creaturelike presence to the second half. In ''Quebrada'' (credited to Mr. Santangelo alone), performed by the entire company, she forms the center of a swirling female trio that offers the most interesting choreographic innovations of the evening through its use of interwoven, circling arms and wrists, and its evocation of sorrow and intimacy.</p>
        <p>And in her final mesmerizing solo, ''Solea,'' Ms. Barrio demonstrates what she does best: display her beautiful, curving back; strong, pounding legs; and mobile hands in proud, tragic response to the passionate, sobbing song that surrounds her.</p>
        <p>Noche Flamenca performs through July 29 at Theater 80, 80 St. Mark's Place, East Village; (212) 352-3101.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
