<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spurs' Victory Illustrates James Is a One-Man Show</title>
    <meta content="09nba" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/sports/basketball/09nba.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853111"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/San Antonio Spurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Cleveland Cavaliers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">San Antonio Spurs</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Basketball Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">James, LeBron</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05EFDF163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spurs' Victory Illustrates James Is a One-Man Show</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spurs’ Victory Illustrates James Is a One-Man Show</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <dateline>SAN ANTONIO, June 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LeBron James completed his public relations duties for the day, and it was time to segue from the hype of the N.B.A. finals to preparing for the N.B.A. finals. But his path down the court was quickly cut off and -- as he often was in Game 1 -- James was quickly surrounded and stifled.</p>
        <p>A phalanx of cameras and boom microphones converged, and James disappeared behind a wall of audio-visual technology. Call it another rookie mistake. A Cleveland Cavaliers official promptly jogged across the court to save James, break up the crowd and let Friday's practice commence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>LeBron James’s supporting cast was helpless without his playmaking and scoring Thursday night. Now the Cavaliers are facing nagging doubt about their chances of defeating the Spurs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LeBron James completed his public relations duties for the day, and it was time to segue from the hype of the N.B.A. finals to preparing for the N.B.A. finals. But his path down the court was quickly cut off and -- as he often was in Game 1 -- James was quickly surrounded and stifled.</p>
        <p>A phalanx of cameras and boom microphones converged, and James disappeared behind a wall of audio-visual technology. Call it another rookie mistake. A Cleveland Cavaliers official promptly jogged across the court to save James, break up the crowd and let Friday's practice commence.</p>
        <p>If James's teammates had been as swift to aid him Thursday night, the Cavaliers might not be facing 72 hours of nagging doubt and pesky questions. The San Antonio Spurs' 85-76 victory reinforced the notion that James was a one-man show, and that the Cavaliers were destined for disappointment.</p>
        <p>Most of James's 14 points came after the game was out of reach, and his six turnovers contributed to a double-digit deficit. When James was flat, so were the Cavaliers. ''I think it's a good job,'' Bruce Bowen said of the Spurs' defense on James. ''But it's not the end.''</p>
        <p>The story of the Cavaliers' rapid rise through the league is packed with similar chapters, so they can afford to put on a brave face. Cleveland lost its opener in the Eastern Conference finals when Detroit held James to 10 points. The Cavaliers fell behind by 2-0 in the series, then won the next four games while James rewrote the record books.</p>
        <p>''We will see a better Game 2 out of him,'' Cavaliers forward Drew Gooden said, looking ahead to Sunday night's rematch.</p>
        <p>James, 22, is playing in only his second playoff run, so every game is another learning experience, another step in his evolution.</p>
        <p>''It was great for him to go through what he went through last night,'' Cavaliers Coach Mike Brown said. ''He struggled a little bit, I think, in the first game against Detroit. It's just a matter of time when you have a player of that magnitude until he can figure out a defense and get himself going.''</p>
        <p>James's supporting cast was helpless without his playmaking and scoring Thursday night. Zydrunas Ilgauskas, Cleveland's most-experienced starter, went 1 for 8 from the field. Larry Hughes, who was signed to a $60 million contract two years ago to be James's running mate, went 1 for 5. Cleveland received another encouraging performance from the rookie Daniel Gibson, who scored a team-high 16 points and made 7 of 9 shots. But Brown resisted suggestions that he start Gibson over the gimpy Hughes.</p>
        <p>The Spurs' defense on James was nothing revolutionary. They sent a big man, often Tim Duncan, to double-team James when he drove, and they sometimes trapped him on the pick and roll. At times they let Bowen, their all-defense first-team forward, handle James by himself.</p>
        <p>Robert Horry said that the defensive approach combined what the Spurs did against the Los Angeles Lakers' Kobe Bryant and the Denver Nuggets' Carmelo Anthony.</p>
        <p>''You switch it up,'' Horry said. ''Sometimes you hang around, sometimes you don't. You just try to keep him guessing.''</p>
        <p>As the Cavaliers will concede, the Spurs' defensive approach is not new -- they just play it better than any other team in the league, Detroit included. The Spurs managed to crowd James and still retreat and rotate to defend his teammates.</p>
        <p>There is also the matter of familiarity. The Cavaliers had played the Pistons 15 times in a one-year stretch, counting the playoffs, before facing them again in the conference finals. They had seen the Spurs, however, only four times before this series and last played them Jan. 2.</p>
        <p>''He's going to look and see how we played it and he's going to adjust his game to that,'' Horry said of James. ''That's why his numbers will always go up, because he's a great basketball player, he has great knowledge of the game, he adjusts to the way a team is playing him.''</p>
        <p>An eager student, James said he watched game film in his hotel room late Thursday night, ''and I'm probably going to watch it again tonight.'' He is said to be a quick study of just about everything.</p>
        <p>''He can listen to one rap CD and he knows the CD by the end of the day,'' Gooden said. James is also quick to master video games, ''and of course, basketball. So I think we have seen him do it in the past.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
