<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Man Agrees To DNA Tests In Deaths Of Prostitutes</title>
    <meta content="09prostitute" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/nyregion/09prostitute.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853152"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey/Atlantic City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">DNA (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DNA (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlantic City (NJ)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02EEDE163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Man Agrees To DNA Tests In Deaths Of Prostitutes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Man Agrees to DNA Tests in Deaths of Prostitutes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATE SCHWEBER</byline>
      <dateline>MAYS LANDING, N.J., June 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A man who stayed at a motel on the outskirts of Atlantic City shortly before four prostitutes were found dead there agreed on Friday to submit to DNA tests.</p>
        <p>The man, Terry Oleson, 35, of Salem County, who has been in jail on an unrelated charge -- invasion of privacy in connection with videotaping a naked 15-year-old girl -- agreed to the testing during a hearing in State Superior Court here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Atlantic County prosecutor has been careful not to describe the Jeffrey S. Blitz, jailed on an unrelated charge, as a suspect.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A man who stayed at a motel on the outskirts of Atlantic City shortly before four prostitutes were found dead there agreed on Friday to submit to DNA tests.</p>
        <p>The man, Terry Oleson, 35, of Salem County, who has been in jail on an unrelated charge -- invasion of privacy in connection with videotaping a naked 15-year-old girl -- agreed to the testing during a hearing in State Superior Court here.</p>
        <p>''We believe the DNA will speak volumes, and he will eventually be exonerated,'' said James J. Leonard, a lawyer for Mr. Oleson.</p>
        <p>The Atlantic County prosecutor, Jeffrey S. Blitz, has been careful not to call Mr. Oleson a suspect. But forensic scientists for the prosecutor have sought a DNA sample as well as head and pubic hair. Mr. Leonard said it could take two to four months to get results.</p>
        <p>The chief Atlantic County assistant prosecutor, Jill Horenberger, said in a motion filed in April that Mr. Oleson's DNA would be compared with biological evidence from the scene and the women's clothes and bodies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Oleson's court appearance was the latest development since the barefoot bodies of four women were discovered in a trash-strewn ditch behind a seedy motel in Egg Harbor Township in November.</p>
        <p>The women were identified as Kim Raffo, 35, Tracy Ann Roberts, 23, Barbara V. Breidor, 42, and Molly Jean Dilts, 20.</p>
        <p>Hugh Auslander, the former husband of Ms. Raffo, who was in the courtroom on Friday, looked at Mr. Oleson and said he ''would like to be quick to judge, but that's too easy.''</p>
        <p>After the hearing, a prostitute from Atlantic City said she recognized Mr. Oleson from a tryst in November in which he confessed to being a murderer.</p>
        <p>The woman, Denise Hill, 44, said that she met Mr. Oleson around the time the victim's bodies were discovered and that he told her he had ''killed some people.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Leonard said that Mr. Oleson had never kept company with prostitutes and called Ms. Hill, who has admitted to smoking crack and appeared in a 2004 HBO documentary about Atlantic City prostitutes, ''the definition of reasonable doubt.''</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Oleson has not been charged with the slayings, the police have questioned him at length about them. He lived for most of November at the Golden Key Motel in the weeks that the four bodies were dumped yards from his room.</p>
        <p>The police questioned Mr. Oleson about the murders in April, and four days later they charged him with invasion of privacy in connection with the taking of nude videos of his female companion's daughter in their Alloway Township home.</p>
        <p>At that time, Judge William Forester set his bail at $100,000 cash without the option of paying 10 percent to be released.</p>
        <p>In a November interview, Ms. Hill said she called the police after spending a night with a man whose name she did not know in an Atlantic City motel in the neighborhood frequented by the women.</p>
        <p>She said that when she saw Mr. Oleson's photograph in a newspaper several months later, she recognized him. And on Friday she found a ride from Atlantic City to see him in person.</p>
        <p>''I watched his nose twitch, his high cheekbones, his eyes, I remember those thin lips,'' she said. ''He's the one I was with. He said he killed some people.''</p>
        <p>Clean-shaven and walking with a limp, Mr. Oleson smiled slightly after his lawyer told Judge Albert Garofolo of Superior Court that he would submit the DNA samples. As he was led from the courtroom, he looked back over his right shoulder in the direction of Mr. Auslander and Ms. Hill.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
