<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Races Going Exactly as Florida State Sprinter Planned</title>
    <meta content="09track" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/sports/othersports/09track.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853191"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TRACK AND FIELD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Florida State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Dix, Walter</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E6DC163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="683" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Races Going Exactly as Florida State Sprinter Planned</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Races Going Exactly as Florida State Sprinter Planned</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY</byline>
      <dateline>SACRAMENTO, June 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a major track and field meet like the N.C.A.A. outdoor championships, it's not how you start, but how you finish.</p>
        <p>For Walter Dix, a Florida State sprinter who seems on the edge of greatness, that holds true in two ways. First, the start of his races are invariably bad, but the finishes are usually excellent. Second, he insists that his unspectacular running Wednesday and Thursday was part of a master plan, saving his fastest running for the finals Friday and Saturday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Walter Dix, a Florida State sprinter, ran the 100 meter dash in 9.93 seconds, the fastest time in the world this year and the second fastest ever by a collegian.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a major track and field meet like the N.C.A.A. outdoor championships, it's not how you start, but how you finish.</p>
        <p>For Walter Dix, a Florida State sprinter who seems on the edge of greatness, that holds true in two ways. First, the start of his races are invariably bad, but the finishes are usually excellent. Second, he insists that his unspectacular running Wednesday and Thursday was part of a master plan, saving his fastest running for the finals Friday and Saturday.</p>
        <p>Dix is a 21-year-old junior from Coral Springs, Fla. Entering this meet, his career bests were 10.05 seconds for 100 meters and 19.69 for 200. His schedule here called for eight races in four days: three rounds of the 100, three rounds of the 200 and two rounds of the 4x100 relay.</p>
        <p>Friday was the day he started living up to his plan. In a 1-hour-45-minute span, he helped Florida State win the 4x100 in 38.60; then he won the 100 in 9.93 -- the fastest time in the world this year and the second fastest ever by a collegian.</p>
        <p>''I thought I could have run faster,'' Dix said. ''I probably should have run through the line instead of celebrating a little early.''</p>
        <p>The 200 final is Saturday, when these four-day championships end. In his 200 semifinal Thursday, Dix seemed to run carefully, as if something were wrong. No, he said, no problems. Then, in an interview, he outlined his plan.</p>
        <p>''I'm running good for a meet like this,'' he said. ''The first two days, I'm basically saving it for the finals. I'm trying to stay even because this has been the longest week of my life. We got here Sunday and I had to run finals Friday and Saturday.</p>
        <p>''Experience is crucial in this meet. You have to know how to run rounds. I know how. Someone can't teach you that.''</p>
        <p>Someone taught him about track when he was young. His mother coached the girls' team at a middle school and his father coached the high school team.</p>
        <p>''They thought I was going to play football,'' Dix said, ''but in my senior year in high school I changed my mind and concentrated on track. I don't want to play football now. I want to run.''</p>
        <p>In 2004, he was the best high school sprinter in the nation. In 2005, as a college freshman, he won the N.C.A.A. outdoor title in the 100. In 2006, he won the N.C.A.A. 200 indoors and outdoors; at last year's N.C.A.A. outdoors, he had a torn groin muscle and strained hamstring.</p>
        <p>Now, at 5 feet 9 inches and 190 pounds, he is strong and sound. Florida State Coach Bob Braman said Dix was like the Dix of old.</p>
        <p>''You look back to his freshman year,'' Braman said, ''when he was fourth in the 200 to Tyson Gay, Wallace Spearmon Jr. and Xavier Carter. They're four of the six fastest ever. He's running like that now.''</p>
        <p>He ran that way two weeks ago, when his 19.69 for the 200 broke a 20-year-old collegiate record. He said his goals were clear.</p>
        <p>''Times, fast times,'' he said. ''When I get those times, the gold medals will take care of themselves.''</p>
        <p>NOTES</p>
        <p>Sally Kipyego, a Kenyan who attends Texas Tech, won the 10,000 meters Thursday but missed a distance double when Michelle Sikes, a Rhodes Scholar from Wake Forest, won the 5,000 Friday night in 15 minutes 16.76 seconds, a meet record.  Other women's winners included Anna Willard of Michigan in the 3,000-meter steeplechase; she set a collegiate record of 9:38.08. Jacquelyn Johnson of Arizona State won her third heptathlon title, with 5,984 points.  In the highly competitive men's high jump, Scott Sellers of Kansas State won at 7 feet 7 1/4 inches, with Andra Manson of Texas and Donald Thomas of Auburn in second and third, each clearing 7-6.  Tommy Skipper of Oregon passed on all pole vault heights until 18- 1/2, then made that on his first attempt and won. The fastest semifinalist in the women's 400 was Natasha Hastings of South Carolina (51.25).</p>
        <p>TRACK AND FIELD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
