<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Palestinian Premier Urges End to Factional Clashes</title>
    <meta content="09mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/world/middleeast/09mideast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853103"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hamas</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fatah</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haniya, Ismail</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Fatah, Al</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Haniya, Ismail</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E2DF163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="477" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Palestinian Premier Urges End to Factional Clashes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Palestinian Premier Urges End to Factional Clashes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Erlanger, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Palestinian prime min Ismail Haniya of Hamas calls for political will to stop another round of intra-Palestinian clashes between his own faction and Fatah, which sit together in unity government (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Palestinian prime minister, Ismail Haniya of Hamas, called Friday for the political will to stop another round of intra-Palestinian clashes between his own faction and Fatah, which sit together in a unity government.</p>
        <p>He spoke before Friday Prayer in Gaza, after fighting on Thursday killed one Palestinian and wounded 17. Such clashes have killed dozens of people in recent weeks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ismail Haniya of Hamas called for the political will to stop another round of intra-Palestinian clashes between his own faction and Fatah.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Palestinian prime minister, Ismail Haniya of Hamas, called Friday for the political will to stop another round of intra-Palestinian clashes between his own faction and Fatah, which sit together in a unity government.</p>
        <p>He spoke before Friday Prayer in Gaza, after fighting on Thursday killed one Palestinian and wounded 17. Such clashes have killed dozens of people in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>''We are not in need of more agreements, but we are in need of the political will to implement the existing agreements,'' Mr. Haniya said. He appeared to blame Fatah, saying, ''There are parties who do not want stability in the internal Palestinian situation.''</p>
        <p>The clashes on Friday were limited, with gunmen firing at Hamas forces deployed east of Gaza City, followed by a Hamas attack on a house where it was thought that Fatah gunmen were staying. A member of Fatah's Presidential Guard was abducted overnight.</p>
        <p>The most recent fighting has been small-scale but personal. In a separate episode on Thursday, Fouad al-Barawi, a physician with ties to Hamas, was kidnapped from a graduation ceremony for his brother, who is a part of Fatah's Presidential Guard.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barawi was then taken to a Fatah base, where he was shot five times in different parts of his body, according to Palestinians who heard his account. The Fatah movement denied involvement on Friday to the Palestinian newspaper Al Ayyam.</p>
        <p>Earlier on Thursday, a Fatah gunman, Waed Wahbi, was shot and killed in a clash with Hamas, which said it was retaliating for an attack on Hamas supporters outside a mosque.</p>
        <p>On Monday, one of Mr. Haniya's bodyguards was captured and beaten, apparently by gunmen of Fatah's elite Force 17, who shaved off his eyebrows and beard and shaved the number 17 into his hair. The bodyguard, Hassan al-Bazam, 20, said he had been beaten with clubs and rifles and had cigarettes extinguished on his back, hot candle wax dripped on him, and gunshots fired between his legs. He was released after seven hours, he said, and asked to reveal the names of local Hamas activists and to curse God and Muhammad. Fatah has denied involvement in that kidnapping as well.</p>
        <p>Fatah is also denying reports that Israel has been asked to approve another shipment of arms, ammunition and armored cars to its security forces in Gaza. That would be the fifth shipment in the past eight months, Israeli officials said. All the shipments have been coordinated by the United States through Egypt and Jordan, but without direct American purchase of arms, the officials said.</p>
        <p>Separately, there were additional Israeli news reports that Israel is interested in exploring peace talks with Syria. Israeli Prime Minister Ehud Olmert reportedly has sent messages to the Syrian leader, Bashar al-Assad, through the Turks and Germans, but has had no response yet, according to the daily newspaper Yediot Aharonot.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
