<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Issues Reprieve on New Passport Rules</title>
    <meta content="09passport" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/us/09passport.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853158"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Passports</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Caribbean Area</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bermuda</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">State Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Homeland Security Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, Ralph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Passports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Passports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Identification Devices</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Homeland Security Department</org>
        <org class="online_producer">State Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E7DD163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="848" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Issues Reprieve on New Passport Rules</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Issues Reprieve on New Passport Rules</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RALPH BLUMENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blumenthal, Ralph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>State Dept and Homeland Security Dept temporarily suspend new passport requirements for traveling to neighboring countries; US citizens flying back from Mexico, Canada, Caribbean and Bermuda who have applied for but not yet received passports can be readmitted with government-issued photo identification and online receipts of their passport application through Sept; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Easing rules that played havoc with the vacation plans of millions of Americans, the State Department and the Department of Homeland Security formally announced yesterday that they were temporarily suspending new passport requirements for travel to neighboring countries.</p>
        <p>Through September, United States citizens flying back from Mexico, Canada, the Caribbean and Bermuda who have applied for but not yet received passports because of huge backlogs can be readmitted with government-issued photo identification and online receipts of their passport application.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The government formally announced on Friday that it was temporarily suspending new passport requirements for travel to neighboring countries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Easing rules that played havoc with the vacation plans of millions of Americans, the State Department and the Department of Homeland Security formally announced yesterday that they were temporarily suspending new passport requirements for travel to neighboring countries.</p>
        <p>Through September, United States citizens flying back from Mexico, Canada, the Caribbean and Bermuda who have applied for but not yet received passports because of huge backlogs can be readmitted with government-issued photo identification and online receipts of their passport application.</p>
        <p>''Finally, somebody had the sense to release the pressure valve,'' said Reg Shiverick of Cleveland who had been waiting for his son's passport requested on March 3 while anxiously watching the clock tick away before the family's flights to Bermuda today. The ''temporary travel flexibility,'' first described Thursday by government officials insisting on anonymity, waives passport requirements that took effect on Jan. 23 for Western Hemisphere flights.</p>
        <p>Members of Congress, furious over a passport breakdown that deluged their offices with constituents' pleas for help, welcomed the accommodation but warned that a new set of passport requirements scheduled to take effect as soon as January could lead to an even bigger crisis. Some said Christmastime travelers should apply for their passports now.</p>
        <p>The Department of Homeland Security warned that those traveling without passports were likely to face increased scrutiny. And officials said that only online receipts from applications electronically trackable would be accepted as proof that a traveler had a passport coming.</p>
        <p>Passport requirements from all other destinations, including Central and South America, remain in place, officials emphasized.</p>
        <p>''I'm pleased the administration agreed that immediate relief was greatly needed,'' said Senator George V. Voinovich, Republican of Ohio, whose staff members spent Thursday night calling panicked constituents -- including Mr. Shiverick -- with news of the change. (As it happened, Mr. Shiverick received his son's passport yesterday.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Voinovich called on the Bush administration to put off from next January until June 2009 a planned extension of the policy that would for the first time require passports of travelers returning from Mexico, Canada, Bermuda and non-United States territories in the Caribbean by road, rail and sea, as well as by air.</p>
        <p>Representative Silvestre Reyes, Democrat of Texas and chairman of the House Select Committee on Intelligence, said he was concerned about the financial burden of obtaining a passport, $97 without expediting fees, for families crossing regularly to Juarez, Mexico.</p>
        <p>Representative Heather Wilson, Republican of New Mexico, was unsparing in her critique of passport officials. ''This is the kind of mess that makes people mad at their government,'' Ms. Wilson said. ''One department says you have to have a passport, and another says we can't get it to you. Dumb as dirt. Homeland Security did the right thing to suspend the requirement so the State Department can get its act together. It's not Middle East peace; it's basic customer service.''</p>
        <p>The easing of the rules this summer was welcomed by leaders of the travel industry.</p>
        <p>''Common sense prevails,'' said Roger J. Dow, president of the Travel Industry Association, which says it represents all components of the $700-billion-a-year travel market. Mr. Dow called the decision ''an all-important timeout that allows the machinery of government to catch up with the new laws.''</p>
        <p>Although it was too soon after the announcement to see any immediate effect, Washington officials said, Jacqueline Harley-Bell, regional director of the Houston Passport Agency, said the number of anxious passport-seekers swarming the office daily was down to about 800 from 1,200 in recent weeks. The State Department said it expected to issue about 17.5 million passports in the fiscal year ending in September, up from just over 12 million last year.</p>
        <p>It attributed the jump to strong tourism and high regard for the identification value of a passport but most of all to the Western Hemisphere Travel Initiative, a security measure that imposed passport requirements for the first time for travel in the nation's backyards.</p>
        <p>Cyberspace, meanwhile, resounded with the blogs and postings of travelers comparing notes, mostly anonymously, of their passport ordeals.</p>
        <p>One person said his experience boded ill for the future of government health care. ''I can just see my dad's pacemaker battery giving out and being told by an 'underpaid, overstressed individual' not to worry, your battery will be expedited,'' he wrote. ''Folks, plan your escape route.''</p>
        <p>But many voiced relief at the breather offered by the rules suspension.</p>
        <p>Jim Finucan, 46, of Westlake, Ohio, had been waiting for five passports that he and his wife, Lindy, and their three children had applied for on March 17. With Sunday's departure date for a trip to Mexico approaching, they were, Mr. Finucan said, ''sweating it out.''</p>
        <p>After three days of calling could not get them through, he said, ''I called every politician I could.''</p>
        <p>On Thursday night, Mr. Voinovich's office called to say they would not need the passports after all -- proof that they had applied would do. But by then, Mr. Finucan said, he had learned that his passports had been sent by FedEx, due to arrive today. ''I'll believe it when I see it,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
