<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Beetle Threatens, 10,000 Staten Island Trees Die by Chain Saw</title>
    <meta content="09trees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/nyregion/09trees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853153"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Staten Island (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Agriculture Department</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEEDE163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1026" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Beetle Threatens, 10,000 Staten Island Trees Die by Chain Saw</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">As Beetle Threatens, 10,000 Staten Island Trees Die by Chain Saw</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDY NEWMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The work crews with their chain saws and grapples and wood chippers fan out across the scrubby forest in northwestern Staten Island in search of trees spray-painted with red bull's-eyes.</p>
        <p>There are thousands.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An unprecedented pre-emptive tree-slaughtering is in the works in New York City, with little public outcry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The work crews with their chain saws and grapples and wood chippers fan out across the scrubby forest in northwestern Staten Island in search of trees spray-painted with red bull's-eyes.</p>
        <p>There are thousands.</p>
        <p>Vrrrrrm! Crash! Grrrrnd. And again, and again.</p>
        <p>If the chipper happens to chew up an Asian longhorned beetle, so much the better.</p>
        <p>In the 11 years since the beetle, public enemy No. 1 of maple and birch, first showed its white-spotted carapace on American soil in Brooklyn, there has never been a pre-emptive tree-slaughtering in the city to compare with this one.</p>
        <p>Ten thousand, eight hundred and seventy-four trees on Staten Island and Prall's Island, an uninhabited sliver of dredge leavings in the Arthur Kill, will be cut down by the end of the month. An additional 13,000 are being injected with pesticide.</p>
        <p>All because of a few dozen beetles, which turned up on Staten Island for the first time in March.</p>
        <p>Inspectors from United States Department of Agriculture found the beetle or its chubby white larva in 41 trees on Prall's Island. Three other infested trees were found on Staten Island, in a desolate square mile of former oil-refinery land where a Nascar track was recently proposed and rejected.</p>
        <p>And under the department's protocol, wherever a beetle is found, every tree within half a mile that could potentially provide a meal for it must be felled.</p>
        <p>''It's really like cancer,'' said Barry C. Emens, the head of the department's Asian longhorned beetle eradication program for New Jersey and Staten Island. ''You take out good cells to get some bad cells, so you take a little bit more. That way you know you get everything.''</p>
        <p>Considering the scope of the arborcide, there has been relatively little public outcry. If you're going to cut down 11,000 trees in New York City, northwestern Staten Island is apparently the place to do it.</p>
        <p>''Despite the number of trees, it's not the same as cutting down a significant forest,'' said Thomas A. Paulo, the borough's parks commissioner. ''I would be much more concerned if it were farther inland.'' Many of the doomed are young birches, which will grow back quickly, he said.</p>
        <p>Glenn Phillips, executive director of New York City Audubon, said that his main concern was that the beetle not spread east to the nearby tract known as Teleport Woods, home to the globally rare Nantucket juneberry, among other precious plants.</p>
        <p>''We need to do what we need to do,'' Mr. Phillips said, to prevent the beetle from spreading any farther.</p>
        <p>The beetle's appearances around the New York region have kept the pest police busy for more than a decade. In 1996, the black bug -- an inch and a half long, with antennas twice as long as its body -- was discovered gnawing through maples and horse-chestnut trees in Greenpoint, Brooklyn, apparently having sneaked in on wooden crates or pallets from China.</p>
        <p>The beetle called at Queens in 1998 and Central Park in 2002. In each place, hundreds or thousands of healthy trees were cut down to keep the beetle from spreading.</p>
        <p>At least three infestations, probably from separate shipments of Chinese wood, turned up in New Jersey: in Jersey City in 2002; in Carteret in 2004; and in Linden in 2006. In all, more than 21,000 trees in New Jersey were sacrificed to keep the beetle at bay.</p>
        <p>The effort was largely successful, Mr. Emens said. But it was not sufficient to prevent some beetles from the Linden infestation from flying across the Arthur Kill to Prall's Island, and from there to the International Speedway Corporation's rejected racetrack site just south of the Staten Island Expressway.</p>
        <p>Mr. Phillips, of the Audubon Society, found this unfortunate. ''I believe that if the A.L.B. infestation in New Jersey had been handled differently, this could have been prevented,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The agriculture department disagrees.</p>
        <p>In any case, the die is cast. Starting in early spring, surveyors combed the woods of Staten and Prall's Islands, marking trees that a longhorned beetle might like to eat. These include maples, box elders, elms, horse chestnuts, willows, birches, poplars, ashes, London planes and mimosas.</p>
        <p>Such trees within half a mile of where beetles were found were marked for death in red. Trees within the next half-mile ring were marked yellow, for pesticide treatment.</p>
        <p>''It's a massive undertaking,'' Mr. Emens said.</p>
        <p>Most of the trees marked for removal are on the rejected speedway site.</p>
        <p>Exactly nine are on residential property, and these will be missed the most.</p>
        <p>The trees belong to the Deckers, an old Staten Island family that owns most of the land in the nearly extinct waterfront neighborhood of Chelsea, west of the West Shore Expressway.</p>
        <p>Helen Decker, a high school English and poetry teacher, immortalized one of them in verse.</p>
        <p>''The willow tree where the giant lives,'' she wrote in 1994, ''her hair was the long green branches, / and when she was thirsty, / she drank the stream she wept the night before.''</p>
        <p>The willow in question, and another one next door, are more than 75 years old, Ms. Decker said. Her sister, Donna Decker, who now lives in Florida, said she could not imagine coming home and not seeing the willow trees.</p>
        <p>''To me they're majestic, and to me they're ageless,'' she said.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, half a mile from the Deckers' ancestral home, a team of federal contractors labored in a 2.7-acre wood owned by the state Department of Environmental Conservation, just behind a strip mall on Victory Boulevard.</p>
        <p>Like much of Staten Island, it was unremarkably beautiful. Maples spread their canopy overhead. Gleaming poison ivy vines embraced in the sun-speckled understory.</p>
        <p>Reggie Wilson, pesticide applicator, knelt in the poison ivy and drilled six holes in the root flares of a red maple. Into each hole he inserted a needle hooked up to an Arborjet trunk injection system. He pulled the plunger; 4 milliliters of Imicide Hp began flowing up the tree's veins.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilson finished the tree. Samantha Roberts, a data recorder, marked it with a blue chalk X, and they moved onto the next.</p>
        <p>''We're going to be here for a while,'' Ms. Roberts said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
