<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Youth Is L.P.G.A. Flavor, But Davies Is Old Reliable</title>
    <meta content="09lpga" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/sports/golf/09lpga.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853141"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ladies Professional Golf Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pak, Se Ri</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Davies, Laura</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E2DE163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="822" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Youth Is L.P.G.A. Flavor, But Davies Is Old Reliable</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Youth Remains L.P.G.A. Flavor, but Davies Is Still Old Reliable</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <dateline>HAVRE DE GRACE, Md., June 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As soon as Se Ri Pak completed her first round Thursday at the L.P.G.A. Championship and her Hall of Fame to-do list was done, the focus shifted to Laura Davies.</p>
        <p>Davies, a 19-year Tour veteran and a two-time champion in this event, is on deck. She needs 2 points to meet the qualifying requirement of 27, and a victory this week in the L.P.G.A. Tour's second major of the year would give her that number.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Laura Davies needs 2 points to meet the qualifying requirement for the L.P.G.A. Championship, and a victory this week in the L.P.G.A. Tour’s second major of the year would give her that number.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As soon as Se Ri Pak completed her first round Thursday at the L.P.G.A. Championship and her Hall of Fame to-do list was done, the focus shifted to Laura Davies.</p>
        <p>Davies, a 19-year Tour veteran and a two-time champion in this event, is on deck. She needs 2 points to meet the qualifying requirement of 27, and a victory this week in the L.P.G.A. Tour's second major of the year would give her that number.</p>
        <p>''I'm the only one that is close enough to do it,'' Davies said. ''So I'm the one on position and basically people are going to talk about it.''</p>
        <p>After starting with a 68 on Thursday at Bulle Rock, Davies slipped to a 75 Friday and is at one-under par, well within striking distance, she said, of the leader, Suzann Pettersen, who shot a 67 in the second round and is at eight under.</p>
        <p>Karrie Webb, who was inducted into the Hall of Fame in 2005, missed only three greens in regulation on her way to a 69 that left her a stroke back in second place. Annika Sorenstam, a three-time champion here, also carded a 69 and was three shots behind.</p>
        <p>Sorenstam, 36, and Webb, 32, are the golden oldies of the leader board. Others close to the lead include 21-year-old Brittany Lincicome (tied for third at six under after a 69); 20-year-old Paula Creamer and 19-year-old Morgan Pressel (tied for fifth at five under); and 18-year-old Angela Park (tied for ninth at four under).</p>
        <p>Seventeen-year-old Michelle Wie, who finished in the top five in two previous appearances here, was not among the leaders. Wie shot a 74 and survived the three-over-par cut without a stroke to spare.</p>
        <p>Wie, who made birdies on two of her last five holes, said: ''I actually felt like I actually played some pretty good golf out there today. I knew I had to make those birdies coming in, and I did, back to back. Those were the kind of holes that show me and other people that I still have it in me.''</p>
        <p>At 43, Davies has laugh lines that are older than Wie. She joined the Tour in 1988, the year before Wie was born, and won four L.P.G.A. titles before Wie drew her first breath.</p>
        <p>Davies, who has won 20 L.P.G.A. events but none since 2001, has been consistent the past year, making the cut at every stroke-play tournament she entered since the United States Open.</p>
        <p>''Something I've always wanted to do is go a full-year period of time without missing a cut,'' she said. ''This is as close as I've been to doing it.''</p>
        <p>When Davies arrived at the par-4 No. 14, she was two strokes off the pace being set by the 25-year-old Pettersen, who was playing three groups ahead of her.</p>
        <p>A bad drive catapulted Davies to a double bogey on the hole. Pettersen, meantime, birdied three of the last four holes, a swing that Davies took lying down.</p>
        <p>During one of the many waits between shots in her five-hour round, Davies lay on her back and used her bag as an armrest, the heat that the sun and Pettersen were bringing to bear proving a little too much.</p>
        <p>''It's so damn hot,'' Davies said afterward, wiping beads of perspiration from her face with the back of her hand. ''The last five, six holes, it was hard to keep concentration, to be honest.''</p>
        <p>Pak, who won this event last year, shot a 70 and was tied with Davies at seven under. Pak became eligible for the Hall of Fame by officially logging her 10th season on the Tour. At 29, Pak will be the youngest member when she is inducted in November.</p>
        <p>If Davies does not qualify for the Hall of Fame by winning two more regular Tour events or one more major, she says she will have a few pangs of regret.</p>
        <p>''I do care about getting in it, because to have had a very long career, as I have, without getting in means I haven't been that good, really,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But the pursuit does not consume her. ''I just want to win tournaments,'' said Davies, who has 65 victories worldwide. ''If it qualifies me for the Hall of Fame, I consider that a bonus.''</p>
        <p>Davies, who has two top-10 finishes in 11 starts this year, seemed optimistic heading into the weekend. ''I think I still have a very good chance to win,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Nobody needs to remind Pettersen of that. At the Kraft Nabisco Championship in April, she surrendered a four-shot lead down the stretch and was passed by Pressel. Last month, Pettersen came from four strokes back to win the Michelob Open in a playoff.</p>
        <p>''You should never say you're in control because then the game will get you the next day,'' she said. ''I hit some good shots. I hit some half-decent shots. There's room for improvement.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
