<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Welterweight Champion Has a New Skill: English</title>
    <meta content="09boxing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/sports/othersports/09boxing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853160"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Judah, Zab</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E7DD163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Welterweight Champion Has a New Skill: English</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Welterweight Champion Has a New Skill: English</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Miguel Cotto, a world champion welterweight boxer, is packing a new punch that he says can help him blow past his opponents in more ways than one. He is speaking English.</p>
        <p>For the first time in his six-year professional career, Cotto, who is from Puerto Rico, has promoted a fight without the aid of an interpreter. In the buildup to tonight's fight against the Brooklyn native Zab Judah at Madison Square Garden, Cotto has mostly spoken in English, a step to achieving the global stardom he desires.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the buildup to Saturday’s fight against Zab Judah, Miguel Cotto, a world champion welterweight boxer, has mostly spoken in English, a step to achieving the global stardom he desires.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Miguel Cotto, a world champion welterweight boxer, is packing a new punch that he says can help him blow past his opponents in more ways than one. He is speaking English.</p>
        <p>For the first time in his six-year professional career, Cotto, who is from Puerto Rico, has promoted a fight without the aid of an interpreter. In the buildup to tonight's fight against the Brooklyn native Zab Judah at Madison Square Garden, Cotto has mostly spoken in English, a step to achieving the global stardom he desires.</p>
        <p>''A few months ago, if I don't have Ricardo beside me, I can't do this,'' Cotto said, referring to his former interpreter, Ricardo Jimenez, during a recent interview with reporters. ''Now, I'm prepared for that. I can do it by myself now.''</p>
        <p>Cotto, the World Boxing Association welterweight champion, has already seen the tangible benefits of his willingness to speak English. He made a television appearance on a sports talk show in New York, and he was a co-host of an episode of ESPN's ''Friday Night Fights'' in April. The opportunities were possible because of Cotto's English skills, said Todd duBoef, the president of Top Rank, the company that promotes Cotto.</p>
        <p>Cotto, 26, is widely adored in Latin America. (He is fighting in New York on the eve of the Puerto Rican Day parade for the third consecutive year.) But he says he hopes that the English language will be the key to tapping into a wider market, as a boxer and an entrepreneur.</p>
        <p>Top Rank has stressed that to him since he turned professional in 2001. Latin American fighters like Julio César Chávez, Roberto Duran and Felix Trinidad failed to realize their full potential as stars, duBoef said, because they could not speak English.</p>
        <p>''It's more real, more tangible for the consumer to be able to hear somebody, even if they struggle with the language,'' duBoef said. ''It allows people, and the writers and other media, to sit down and have a conversation with him and see his reaction.''</p>
        <p>Cotto, who has a record of 29-0, is not yet as popular as Trinidad, one of the most famous Puerto Rican fighters. Of course, a victory against Judah, the toughest opponent he has faced, would do wonders for Cotto's stature.</p>
        <p>Cotto began learning English in earnest about two years ago by going to a tutor in Puerto Rico and taking lessons for three hours every Friday. He still goes to the tutor when he is not training for a fight.</p>
        <p>He has also been working on his language skills with his strength coach, Phil Landman, who is from South Africa and has been living with Cotto for the past eight months.</p>
        <p>''He speaks so well now, he speaks with a lot of confidence,'' said Landman, who knows only a few Spanish phrases. ''He would speak English over Spanish right now in most instances.''</p>
        <p>Cotto sometimes stumbles over his words. But he never seems exasperated or in need of help from Jimenez. ''Ricardo have to find another guy now,'' Cotto joked.</p>
        <p>Cotto already seems at ease talking to reporters. Perhaps channeling his inner Oscar De La Hoya, Cotto wore a chocolate brown suit with a shiny white shirt and a tie at a news conference earlier this week. He was the only fighter on the dais dressed for Wall Street.</p>
        <p>''Besides boxing, we are businessmen,'' Cotto said.</p>
        <p>Responding to a comment by Judah that no one knew who Cotto was, Cotto said, ''He has to know who is Miguel Cotto next Saturday.''</p>
        <p>And responding to past comments by Judah that he was a robot, Cotto said: ''The robot have new software. I will show you next Saturday.''</p>
        <p>BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
