<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TB Patient Says Officials Are Trying to Blame Him to Cover Mistakes</title>
    <meta content="09tb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/us/09tb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853159"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tuberculosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grady, Denise</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Speaker, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Tuberculosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tuberculosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lungs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tuberculosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lungs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Speaker, Andrew</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E7DD163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1188" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TB Patient Says Officials Are Trying to Blame Him to Cover Mistakes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">TB Patient Says Officials Are Trying to Blame Him to Cover Mistakes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENISE GRADY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grady, Denise</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Andrew Speaker has been branded as runaway tuberculosis patient who deliberately evaded health officials and knowingly put other people at risk by traveling on crowded airplanes; Speaker and his family dispute accounts of local and federal health officials who say he had been warned not to fly; he accuses health officials of trying to destroy his credibility in order to cover their own mistakes in handling his case (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By the time Andrew Speaker and his wife returned from Europe late last month, government officials and news reports had already branded him as a runaway tuberculosis patient who had deliberately evaded health officials and knowingly put other people at risk by traveling on crowded airplanes.</p>
        <p>''This is what we're hearing on the news when we land,'' Mr. Speaker said on Thursday from his hospital room in Denver. He called The New York Times in response to repeated requests for an interview. ''My wife and I look at each other, and I said, 'They're going for our throats here.' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Andrew Speaker insisted that officials had never told him that he was infectious and expressed anger, frustration and worry about his reputation and career.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By the time Andrew Speaker and his wife returned from Europe late last month, government officials and news reports had already branded him as a runaway tuberculosis patient who had deliberately evaded health officials and knowingly put other people at risk by traveling on crowded airplanes.</p>
        <p>''This is what we're hearing on the news when we land,'' Mr. Speaker said on Thursday from his hospital room in Denver. He called The New York Times in response to repeated requests for an interview. ''My wife and I look at each other, and I said, 'They're going for our throats here.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker and his family have been fighting back ever since, disputing the accounts of local and federal health officials who say he had been warned not to fly because he posed an infection risk to others.</p>
        <p>''I think when they started all this, they forgot that I spend my whole life defending people who are seriously hurt and need help,'' said Mr. Speaker, 31, a personal injury lawyer. ''I don't think they took that into account when they started coming after me and my family. We're not the kind of people who back down.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker's father, Theodore, also a lawyer, went so far as to record conversations with health officials, and to release selected excerpts from the recordings in which a doctor from the Fulton County Health Department in Georgia can be clearly heard saying, ''you're not contagious'' and also ''as far as we can tell you, you're not a threat to anybody else right now.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker refused to release the complete recordings, saying they included personal medical details that were ''none of anybody's darn business,'' and adding, ''If you want to give me a copy of your next doctor's visit I'll share it with all your friends.''</p>
        <p>In the interview, Mr. Speaker spoke at length, expressing anger, frustration and worry about his reputation and career. He accused health officials of trying to destroy his credibility in order to cover their own mistakes in handling his case. He insisted that officials had never told him that he was infectious. They themselves never wore masks around him, he said, and never told him that he posed any risk to his wife or daughter.</p>
        <p>''If I'm a danger to people in close contact, shouldn't they have told me I was a threat to my wife, sleeping together?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>The convoluted tale began in January, when an X-ray taken for an injury to the left side of his rib cage picked up a shadow in his right lung. TB was immediately suspected, and one test led to another, and the diagnosis. How he contracted the disease is not known, but a trip to Vietnam is a suspected source. It was not until May 10 that doctors realized that Mr. Speaker's TB was resistant to several widely used drugs. They asked him not to travel, but did not discourage him from going to work or tell him to wear a mask, and so he saw no reason not to stick with plans to get married in Greece.</p>
        <p>Not until May 22 did health officials know that the resistance was even worse than they had thought. The bacteria were XDR, for extensively drug resistant, meaning that nearly all the usual TB drugs were useless. By that time, Mr. Speaker was already in Europe.</p>
        <p>TB spreads through the air, but only a small percentage of people who are exposed to the bacteria actually get sick. XDR tuberculosis is not more virulent or more contagious than other types, but it is of great concern because it is so difficult to treat. Patients need multiple drugs for two years or more, and even then only about 30 percent can be cured.</p>
        <p>In Rome, Mr. Speaker was notified by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention that he had XDR TB and should not fly. At first, he said, an official told him that the C.D.C. would help him with travel plans. But a day later, he said, he was told that he would have to pay for a special medical evacuation that would probably cost $140,000, and that his name would be on a no-fly list. The official urged him to turn himself in to Italian health authorities.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Speaker said he believed that his best and perhaps only hope for a cure was to get to the National Jewish Medical and Research Center in Denver, which has expertise treating this kind of TB. Fearing that he might be quarantined indefinitely in Italy, he and his wife, Sarah, avoided the no-fly list by booking a flight to Canada and then driving into the United States, where a border guard ignored an alert triggered by Mr. Speaker's passport.</p>
        <p>Federal officials have offered several explanations for why the disease centers did not dispatch its plane to pick up Mr. Speaker and his wife. Initially, they said it was not clear that they had the legal jurisdiction; later, they said uncertainty about his condition ruled out using the plane, for fear that he might infect the crew. But after subsequent sputum tests that showed a low level of infectiousness, the C.D.C. decided that with the use of masks it could safely fly him on its plane from New York to Atlanta and later to Denver.</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker said he wanted to dispel the news media portrayal of him and his wife as ''the super-rich, globe-trotting couple'' who could easily have afforded to pay $140,000 to fly home in a private plane.</p>
        <p>He said their wedding in Greece cost less than $2,000. The ceremony took place on the balcony of a restaurant, where they had reserved a table for just 12 -- including their parents, daughter and a few other relatives and friends. His wife wore a $250 gown, he said, and after the wedding they planned to travel around Europe, stay in cheap hotels and go sightseeing. He recently left his father's law firm to start one of his own, and sold his house and many of his belongings to finance it.</p>
        <p>''The long and short of it is, we don't have $140,000,'' he said.</p>
        <p>For now, he is focused on beating the TB. His doctors have said they might recommend lung surgery, which is sometimes used in difficult cases if the bacteria are confined to a section of the lung that can be cut out. The operation is not a cure, but removing the bulk of the infection gives the drugs a better chance of working on any bacteria that are left.</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker said he would welcome the surgery if his doctors suggested it.</p>
        <p>Beyond getting well, he said, his main concern is his law career, and that is why he keeps speaking out. ''When I'm done with all this, am I going to have a practice to get back to, with the impression out there now that I'm this selfish, self-absorbed person? It's not how I've lived my life. When I'm done with all this, I want to make sure I still have my life to get back to.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
