<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Triple Crown Races Like Belmont Can Be Tough on a Gal</title>
    <meta content="09racing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/sports/othersports/09racing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853170"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E4DD163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Triple Crown Races Like Belmont Can Be Tough on a Gal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Triple Crown Races Like Belmont Can Be Tough on a Gal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rags to Riches' father, A. P. Indy, won the Belmont Stakes in 1992, and her mother, Better Than Honour, produced last year's winner, Jazil. So why did Michael Tabor, the owner, and Todd Pletcher, the trainer, agonize over whether to run Rags to Riches in the Belmont today?</p>
        <p>Well, Rags to Riches is a filly, an extraordinarily talented one, but historically the girls have not fared well against the boys in Triple Crown races. Since the Belmont began in 1867, only 21 fillies have challenged the colts, with only 2 successes. Ruthless won the first running of the race and Tanya was the victor in 1905.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Historically girls have not fared well against boys in Triple Crown races, as since the Belmont Stakes began in 1867, only 21 fillies have challenged the colts, with only 2 successes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rags to Riches' father, A. P. Indy, won the Belmont Stakes in 1992, and her mother, Better Than Honour, produced last year's winner, Jazil. So why did Michael Tabor, the owner, and Todd Pletcher, the trainer, agonize over whether to run Rags to Riches in the Belmont today?</p>
        <p>Well, Rags to Riches is a filly, an extraordinarily talented one, but historically the girls have not fared well against the boys in Triple Crown races. Since the Belmont began in 1867, only 21 fillies have challenged the colts, with only 2 successes. Ruthless won the first running of the race and Tanya was the victor in 1905.</p>
        <p>No one is quite sure why a filly can match a colt's time on a stopwatch, but somehow consistently fails to beat him in head-to-head competition.</p>
        <p>''Physically, they are totally different,'' said Dr. George Mundy, a veterinarian and general manager of Adena Springs Farm in Kentucky. ''At the top level, especially, colts are usually bigger and stronger. They also have testosterone, which makes them more aggressive. There also is an intimidation factor. There are some fillies and mares out there with he-men characteristics, but they are few and far between.''</p>
        <p>Tabor and Pletcher say they believe Rags to Riches is tough enough to line up against five other colts and a gelding, Imawildandcrazyguy, without blinking. They say she has the heart and talent to overtake the competition in the stretch in what is a grueling mile-and-a-half distance.</p>
        <p>Beyond the impeccable pedigree, Rags to Riches has won four of five of her races, including a dominating four-and-a-quarter-length victory in the Kentucky Oaks. Her victory in the Las Virgenes in February was what convinced Tabor and Pletcher that Rags to Riches had a well of desire to match her chestnut physique. She was bumped early, forced five-wide throughout the mile race, but still found another gear to pass five horses in the final half-mile.</p>
        <p>''She had to overcome a ton to win there,'' said Pletcher, who is 0 for 28 in Triple Crown races. ''She has a lot of want-to-win in here. We know she's going to stay the distance. If I had a colt that I was running against her, I'd be worried about Rags to Riches.''</p>
        <p>Her place in the starting gate has piqued the interest of rival trainers, and the more than 60,000 people expected to spend what has been forecast to be a sunny day in the 70s at the grand old Long Island racetrack in the hopes of witnessing history. Belmont is not the only racetrack that has flummoxed fillies.</p>
        <p>Only 38 of them have started since the Kentucky Derby began in 1875, and only 3 have won: Regret in 1915, Genuine Risk in 1980 and Winning Colors in 1988. In the Preakness, which began in 1873, a total of 52 have tried the boys and 4 came out winners, the last being Nellie Morse in 1924.</p>
        <p>Steve Asmussen, the trainer of Curlin, the Preakness champion and the 6-5 favorite in the morning line, is impressed with Rags to Riches.</p>
        <p>''She adds curiosity,'' he said. ''There's no comparative form as far as common horses as the group has run against. I think everyone's been impressed with her, and I can't say enough about the Las Virgenes; it was just an amazing race. I'm very curious to see how she stacks up to what I believe is a group of excellent 3-year-old colts.''</p>
        <p>As Curlin showed in running down the Kentucky Derby winner Street Sense at the Preakness, he is not only an imposing physical specimen but he also gathers steam like a locomotive in the stretch. Hard Spun also looked the part of an alpha colt when he finish second in the Derby and third in the Preakness.</p>
        <p>Hard Spun's trainer, Larry Jones, started his career in quarter-horse racing, in which it is not unusual for the sexes to meet on the racetrack. He has also thrown some of his fillies in against the boys in 2-year-old races.</p>
        <p>''Just like in people, the girls tend to develop and mature quicker than the boys,'' he said. ''I've had some success with fillies against colts in the baby races. It gets tougher the older they get.''</p>
        <p>It may have been sporting on the part of Tabor and Pletcher to enter Rags to Riches. But is it worth it? Big victories may enhance the value of stud fees for colts, but it does little for potential broodmares.</p>
        <p>Bob Baffert was the last trainer to send a filly to the post in the Belmont. In 1999, Silverbulletday came to New York as a champion filly who had had won 11 of 12 races at 5 different tracks. That included eight in a row, each time as the odds-on favorite.</p>
        <p>In the Belmont, however, she finished a well-beaten seventh.</p>
        <p>''At the time I thought it was a good move because I felt my filly was great and fresh,'' Baffert said. ''We didn't get the soft pace we needed and it was too much for her. I would never do it again. But really you have nothing to lose by running her. If she wins, it was a good move and if she loses, it was because she was a filly. Either way it makes the race more interesting to watch.''</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
