<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nominee for Joint Chiefs Is Called a Pragmatist</title>
    <meta content="09chief" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/washington/09chief.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Joint Chiefs of Staff</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cloud, David S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Robert M (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mullen, Michael G (Adm)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Military Personnel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Personnel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Joint Chiefs of Staff</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Mullen, Michael G</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gates, Robert M</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E3DE163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="937" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nominee for Joint Chiefs Is Called a Pragmatist</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nominee for Joint Chiefs Is Called a Pragmatist</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID S. CLOUD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cloud, David S</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Defense Sec Robert M Gates, by recommending Adm Michael G Mullen to be next chairman of Joint Chiefs of Staff, has chosen low-key pragmatist without well-established stake in Iraq strategy to be country's next senior military adviser; those who know Mullen say that if confirmed as chairman, he has little reason to stick with policy if he decides it is not working (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By recommending Adm. Michael G. Mullen to be the next chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates has chosen a low-key pragmatist without a well-established stake in the Iraq strategy to be the country's next senior military adviser.</p>
        <p>Unlike the two previous chairmen, Admiral Mullen, 60, was not in a top Pentagon post when the Bush administration made the decision to invade Iraq. Those who know him say that if confirmed as chairman, he has little reason to stick with a policy if he decides it is not working.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Adm. Michael G. Mullen is a low-key pragmatist without a well-established stake in the Iraq strategy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By recommending Adm. Michael G. Mullen to be the next chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates has chosen a low-key pragmatist without a well-established stake in the Iraq strategy to be the country's next senior military adviser.</p>
        <p>Unlike the two previous chairmen, Admiral Mullen, 60, was not in a top Pentagon post when the Bush administration made the decision to invade Iraq. Those who know him say that if confirmed as chairman, he has little reason to stick with a policy if he decides it is not working.</p>
        <p>''He will be pragmatic about Iraq,'' said retired Adm. Robert Natter, who described himself as a close friend. ''I know, because I've had long conversations about it with him.''</p>
        <p>Yet Admiral Mullen has seemed at least until now to share the basic assumptions of his predecessors about the way ahead in Iraq.</p>
        <p>Like them, he acknowledges that there is no purely military solution to the conflict and that it is up to Iraqi Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki's government to take political steps in coming months that will lead to political reconciliation among the country's Sunnis, Shiites and Kurds.</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Gates, he appears willing to give the current strategy at least until September to show signs of working.</p>
        <p>''It is a matter of months that this surge is designed to apply,'' he said in a recent interview, noting that the White House had consulted the chiefs before adopting the new strategy. ''If there isn't political progress, if there isn't economic progress, the military isn't going to make this work.''</p>
        <p>His biggest challenge if the strategy shows signs of failure could be convincing Mr. Bush, who until now has resisted efforts by Congress to radically reduce the American military presence in Iraq.</p>
        <p>A Naval Academy graduate from Los Angeles who began his military career at the height of the Vietnam War, Admiral Mullen has long been one of the Navy's stars. He was given his first sea command while still a lieutenant -- a rarity -- and he went on to hold commands at sea and ashore, including deputy chief of naval operations. He also oversaw all NATO naval forces in Europe in 2004 and 2005.</p>
        <p>He earned two master's degrees, one in operations research from the Naval Postgraduate School and another from Harvard Business School. As chief of naval operations, Admiral Mullen has pushed to reverse the decline in the size of the Navy's fleet, which has shrunk to fewer than 280 ships, and to build new types of vessels for the unconventional conflicts the United States may face in coming years.</p>
        <p>Over the years, associates say, Admiral Mullen earned a reputation for mentoring young sailors as well as a fondness for military strategy.</p>
        <p>''He could go between being a sailor and be just as comfortable thinking strategically about where the Navy should go,'' said Rear Adm. William Cobb, retired, who recalled serving with Admiral Mullen on a deployment to the Persian Gulf in the early 1980s, when tensions were running high with Iran over the seizure of hostages at the American embassy in Tehran.</p>
        <p>Although Admiral Mullen was appointed chief of naval operations by former Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld, those who know him say he chafed under Mr. Rumsfeld's management style. In particular, associates say, he felt Mr. Rumsfeld did not rely heavily enough on advice from the joint chiefs and rarely met with them as a group. That has changed under Mr. Gates, who usually meets once a week with the chairman and the service chiefs and with whom Admiral Mullen appears to have forged a close bond.</p>
        <p>''I have become well-acquainted with Admiral Mullen over the past six months and believe he has the vision, strategic insight, experience and integrity to lead America's armed forces,'' Mr. Gates said Friday.</p>
        <p>Admiral Natter said he was not surprised that Mr. Gates had grown to rely on Admiral Mullen. ''They are both quiet professionals and they don't place their egos into any arguments or into any debates,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates seemed impressed by Admiral Mullen's ability to look beyond the interests of his own service. When asked recently by one of Mr. Gates's aides what he was most concerned about, Admiral Mullen replied that he was worried about the Army, which has been badly stretched by the requirement of fighting wars in both Iraq and Afghanistan, Mr. Gates told reporters.</p>
        <p>He added that Admiral Mullen had the ability ''to look to the future in terms of where we need to be 5 years from now or 10 years from now.''</p>
        <p>Those who have worked at senior levels at the Pentagon said Admiral Mullen had shown the independence needed in a chairman during meetings with civilian officials in the Pentagon conference room known as ''the tank,'' where the chiefs convene.</p>
        <p>''I've seen him at several of the tank meetings stand up and say, 'Wait a minute. Is this really the best way to do this?' '' said Gen. Michael Hagee, the former Marine Corps commandant, who said he met Admiral Mullen when they were plebes at the Naval Academy in 1964.</p>
        <p>Admiral Mullen was visiting Annapolis when his selection was announced today.</p>
        <p>The initial reaction to the choice from key lawmakers in the Senate was positive.</p>
        <p>''I think going in that Admiral Mullen is well-qualified,'' said Senator Carl Levin, the Michigan Democrat who is chairman of the Senate Armed Services Committee.</p>
        <p>Admiral Mullen is married and has two sons. Both are Navy officers, and one of them recently returned from a tour as an aviator flying missions over Iraq.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
