<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Philip Morris to Test a Smokeless Tobacco Product in Texas</title>
    <meta content="09smoke" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/business/09smoke.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853140"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Snus</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nicotine</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dallas-Fort Worth (Tex)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philip Morris Usa</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feder, Barnaby J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Dallas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Fort Worth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Texas</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Philip Morris Companies Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E2DE163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Philip Morris to Test a Smokeless Tobacco Product in Texas</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Philip Morris Tries Smokeless Tobacco Product</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARNABY J. FEDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feder, Barnaby J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Philip Morris USA will test-market four flavors of smokeless tobacco product known as snus under Marlboro brand name in Dallas-Fort Worth area, starting in August; snus is moist, spit-free variant of traditional chew and dip tobaccos; it comes in small pouch that users most often place inside upper lip; snus is widely used in Scandinavia, where numerous studies have shown that it offers smokers alternative way to get nicotine and taste of cigarettes with less risk of cancer (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Philip Morris USA, the tobacco company, said late yesterday that it would test-market four flavors of a smokeless tobacco product known as snus under the Marlboro brand name in the Dallas-Fort Worth area, starting in August.</p>
        <p>Snus (rhymes with loose) is a moist, spit-free variant on traditional chew and dip tobaccos. It comes in a small pouch similar to a tea bag that users most often place inside the upper lip. Snus is widely used in Scandinavia, where numerous studies have shown that it offers smokers an alternative way to get the nicotine and taste of cigarettes with less risk of cancer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Philip Morris USA, the tobacco company, will test-market four flavors of a smokeless tobacco product known as snus under the Marlboro brand name.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Philip Morris USA, the tobacco company, said late yesterday that it would test-market four flavors of a smokeless tobacco product known as snus under the Marlboro brand name in the Dallas-Fort Worth area, starting in August.</p>
        <p>Snus (rhymes with loose) is a moist, spit-free variant on traditional chew and dip tobaccos. It comes in a small pouch similar to a tea bag that users most often place inside the upper lip. Snus is widely used in Scandinavia, where numerous studies have shown that it offers smokers an alternative way to get the nicotine and taste of cigarettes with less risk of cancer.</p>
        <p>Opponents of tobacco use have been divided on whether to encourage smokers to switch to snus because they believe that quitting tobacco altogether is the safest course of action.</p>
        <p>Philip Morris said the Marlboro snus line would be made at a factory it reopened recently in York County, Va. That factory was brought online as part of a strategy to expand the company's smokeless products and to develop tobacco-related products, a company spokesman, Brendan McCormick, said. Sales of smokeless products have increased at a 6 percent annual rate over the last five years.</p>
        <p>Philip Morris has been test-marketing two versions of a snus product in Indianapolis under the name Tobaka, with less than stellar results, industry analysts said.</p>
        <p>One analyst, Christopher Growe at A. G. Edwards &amp; Sons, said last month that most retailers he surveyed in Indianapolis had stopped selling Tobaka. But Philip Morris said last night that it was learning from the test and would continue it.</p>
        <p>In moving to attach the name of the company's best-selling cigarette brand to snus, Philip Morris, a division of Altria, is following the lead of R. J. Reynolds Tobacco, which put its Camel brand name on a snus product it is test-marketing in Austin, Tex., and Portland, Ore., and selling over the Internet.</p>
        <p>''This is a very positive signal to current smokers,'' said Brad K. Rodu, a professor of medicine at the University of Louisville who has long been an advocate of smokeless tobacco products as the best way to reduce the health impact of tobacco. Professor Rodu, whose research program is sponsored by smokeless tobacco companies, said studies had shown that snus cut the cancer risks of smoking by as much as 98 percent.</p>
        <p>The most recent research, published in The Lancet, the medical journal published in Britain, reported an elevated risk of pancreatic cancer among Swedish snus users compared with Swedes who used no tobacco. But the combined rate of lung, oral and pancreatic cancer was still far lower than that of Swedish smokers, Professor Rodu said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
