<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Jeter's Night From Start to Finish</title>
    <meta content="09yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/sports/baseball/09yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853194"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Pittsburgh Pirates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Pittsburgh Pirates</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jeter, Derek</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clemens, Roger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E6DC163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Jeter's Night From Start to Finish</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">It’s Jeter’s Night From Start to Finish</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE; Michael S. Schmidt contributed reporting.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last night's 5-4 Yankees victory over Pittsburgh -- won on a bases-loaded infield single by Derek Jeter in the 10th inning -- was not a flawless game, but it was a delight for those who enjoy good pitching, especially from left-handed starters.</p>
        <p>Neither Andy Pettitte of the Yankees nor Tom Gorzelanny of the Pirates got the decision before 54,240 fans at Yankee Stadium. But both starters pitched well enough to win in masterly displays of their art.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was the fourth consecutive victory for the Yankees, their best streak of the season. Roger Clemens is scheduled to start Saturday in his return debut.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last night's 5-4 Yankees victory over Pittsburgh -- won on a bases-loaded infield single by Derek Jeter in the 10th inning -- was not a flawless game, but it was a delight for those who enjoy good pitching, especially from left-handed starters.</p>
        <p>Neither Andy Pettitte of the Yankees nor Tom Gorzelanny of the Pirates got the decision before 54,240 fans at Yankee Stadium. But both starters pitched well enough to win in masterly displays of their art.</p>
        <p>The victory came when Jeter ''didn't have a good swing,'' he said, on a two-seam fastball from Matt Capps (3-3), the fifth Pittsburgh relief pitcher. The ball bounced slowly to second baseman Freddy Sánchez, who could not make a play while Robinson Canó scored.</p>
        <p>''I was lucky,'' Jeter said. ''It's not like you try to hit it right there.'' But, with a smile, Jeter added that it was all right to write that he tried to do just that. It was his night, from start to finish. On their way in, fans were given souvenir dolls of Jeter, who had two hits and two runs batted in while raising his average to .332.</p>
        <p>Hideki Matsui hit a two-run homer in the sixth off Gorzelanny, who is in his first full season and has a 6-3 record. Getting the victory was Mariano Rivera (2-3), who worked the final two innings after Pettitte gave up four runs and nine hits in eight innings.</p>
        <p>''It was a good night and I'm proud of the guys,'' said Pettitte, who did not seem upset that his record remained at 3-4 despite another fine performance. The most damaging hit he gave up was a two-run, inside-the-park homer to Chris Duffy in the seventh to put the Pirates up by 4-2.</p>
        <p>It happened when Melky Cabrera, playing center field, misplayed a line drive by moving sideways, stopping, leaping and falling down as the ball skipped to the wall. ''I read it wrong off the bat,'' Cabrera said through an interpreter, ''and the ball took off.''</p>
        <p>It was the fourth consecutive victory for the Yankees, their best streak of the season, and their seventh in nine games, matching their best stretch. Roger Clemens is scheduled to start today in his return to the Yankees against Paul Maholm of the Pirates.</p>
        <p>''We're excited, obviously, it's a good time for him to come back,'' said Pettitte, a close friend of Clemens who spent the last three years in Houston as his teammate and was with him before that with the Yankees.</p>
        <p>In the 10th, Canó led off with a double off the wall in left-center field off Capps. Cabrera moved Canó to third with a bunt. Miguel Cairo grounded to third for an infield hit when third baseman José Bautista chose not to throw to first.</p>
        <p>After Cairo took second base uncontested , the Pirates walked Johnny Damon intentionally to load the bases. Jeter then bounced the ball to Sánchez. ''It is a tough way to lose it,'' Capps said.</p>
        <p>Had the Yankees not scored, could Rivera -- usually a one-inning closer -- have worked the 11th? ''One more inning?'' he said, eyes wide. Without answering the question, he said he was glad it ended when it did. ''It was a great game,'' Rivera said. ''Both teams gave their best.''</p>
        <p>Pettitte mixed fastballs, cutters, curves and changeups. He said he had no problems with a sore back that bothered him in his previous outing last Sunday in Boston.</p>
        <p>Since a victory May 8, Pettitte has made six starts and has given up only 16 earned runs in them while getting one victory, three defeats and two no-decisions in 42 innings.</p>
        <p>Gorzelanny worked six and a third innings and gave up four runs and six hits while striking out five and hitting one batter, Jeter. Gorzelanny mixed fastballs, changeups, curves and sliders before the Pirates used a parade of relievers.</p>
        <p>The Pirates scored once in the second inning on a home run by Xavier Nady and once again in the fifth on three consecutive singles. The Yankees struck back in the sixth on two consecutive pitches.</p>
        <p>After Posada lined a single through the box that almost hit Gorzelanny, Matsui drilled a fastball down the middle into the lower deck in right field to tie the score, 2-2.</p>
        <p>After Duffy's home run in the seventh, Gorzelanny gave up a leadoff double to Cairo. After retiring Damon on a grounder, he gave up a single to Jeter that cut the lead to 4-3, causing Manager Jim Tracy to pull Gorzelanny after 117 pitches.</p>
        <p>Tracy replaced him with another left-hander, John Grabow, who gave up a single to Bobby Abreu. ''It was unfortunate things happened after I came out of the game,'' Gorzelanny said. Tracy then replaced Grabow with Salomon Torres, who hit Alex Rodriguez on the left arm with his first pitch.</p>
        <p>With the bases loaded, Posada singled to right to tie the score, 4-4, and set the stage for extra innings. Tracy called it ''just a great baseball game'' and Joe Torre, the Yankees' manager, agreed.</p>
        <p>''We have a lot of fight right now,'' Torre said. ''It was a huge game for us, it was very satisfying.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
