<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Surgeon General Nominee Is Assailed for Church Role</title>
    <meta content="09surgeon" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/washington/09surgeon.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853131"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surgeon General (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Public Health Service</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Methodist Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Banerjee, Neela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holsinger, James W Jr (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E4DE163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="848" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Surgeon General Nominee Is Assailed for Church Role</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Surgeon General Nominee Is Assailed for Church Role</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEELA BANERJEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Banerjee, Neela</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush's nomination of Dr James W Holsinger Jr, Kentucky cardiologist, to be surgeon general is drawing criticism from gay rights groups, physicians and lawmakers who say they are troubled by opinions critical of homosexuality that Holsinger has voiced in nearly 20 years as high-ranking layman in United Methodist Church; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush's nomination of Dr. James W. Holsinger Jr., a Kentucky cardiologist, to be surgeon general is drawing criticism from gay rights groups, physicians and lawmakers who say they are troubled by opinions critical of homosexuality that Dr. Holsinger has voiced in nearly 20 years as a high-ranking layman in the United Methodist Church.</p>
        <p>Dr. Holsinger's friends within the United Methodist Church and the medical community, however, are defending him as a professional who does not discriminate against people in his congregation or in his care.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gay rights groups, physicians and lawmakers say they are troubled by opinions critical of homosexuality voiced by Dr. James W. Holsinger Jr.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush's nomination of Dr. James W. Holsinger Jr., a Kentucky cardiologist, to be surgeon general is drawing criticism from gay rights groups, physicians and lawmakers who say they are troubled by opinions critical of homosexuality that Dr. Holsinger has voiced in nearly 20 years as a high-ranking layman in the United Methodist Church.</p>
        <p>Dr. Holsinger's friends within the United Methodist Church and the medical community, however, are defending him as a professional who does not discriminate against people in his congregation or in his care.</p>
        <p>The critics said they were worried that Dr. Holsinger might not serve gay men and lesbians fairly as surgeon general, the nation's chief health educator, largely because of a report he wrote in 1991 for a United Methodist committee that essentially described male homosexuality as unnatural.</p>
        <p>They also point to his service on the board of a Methodist group that in 1998 criticized the ''radical homosexual/lesbian lobby'' for trying to force the church ''to grant approval to the practice of homosexuality.''</p>
        <p>Critics have also cited Dr. Holsinger's leadership of the Judicial Council of the United Methodist Church, the denomination's highest court, which in late 2005 decided to reinstate a pastor who had been suspended for refusing to allow a gay man to join his congregation, a decision the church's bishops later rejected.</p>
        <p>''If he says, 'In my religious tradition, homosexuality is considered sinful, unnatural,' that's his right,'' said Joel Ginsberg, executive director of the Gay and Lesbian Medical Association. Citing opinions by medical associations that homosexuality is not a disorder, Mr. Ginsberg said, ''But if he says it is pathological, he is speaking from a discredited scientific viewpoint.''</p>
        <p>In Dr. Holsinger's defense, Dr. F. Douglas Scutchfield of the College of Public Health at the University of Kentucky noted that Dr. Holsinger took on state politicians who threatened to withhold financing from a women's health conference in 2002 because it had a session on health care for lesbians.</p>
        <p>''Dr. Holsinger's posture was that regardless of people's nature, we need to understand the problems and concerns they have,'' Dr. Scutchfield said.</p>
        <p>President Bush nominated Dr. Holsinger in late May, citing his leadership of the health care system in Kentucky and the medical school at the University of Kentucky. In 1992, he became undersecretary for health in the Department of Veterans Affairs.</p>
        <p>His skill at managing complex health systems has won him wide respect, said Dr. David Dale, president of the American College of Physicians, of which Dr. Holsinger is a distinguished member. Mr. Bush has said that Dr. Holsinger, 68, would focus on educating people about childhood obesity.</p>
        <p>The nomination, which requires the approval of the Senate Committee on Health, Education, Labor and Pensions, has raised questions in the Senate. Senator Edward M. Kennedy, Democrat of Massachusetts who is chairman of the health committee, released a statement saying he was ''disappointed'' that the administration had chosen a doctor ''whose record appears to guarantee a polarizing and divisive nomination process.'' Senator Barack Obama, a committee member and a candidate for the Democratic presidential nomination, said in a statement that he had ''serious reservations'' about the nomination.</p>
        <p>The Human Rights Campaign, a gay rights advocacy group, said Dr. Holsinger's record was ''unworthy'' of the surgeon general post.</p>
        <p>Calls to Dr. Holsinger's office were referred to the Department of Health and Human Services, which said that his ''focus has been to provide compassionate effective care to any and all who need it.''</p>
        <p>Emily Lawrimore, a White House spokeswoman, said, ''On numerous occasions, Dr. Holsinger has taken up the banner for underrepresented populations, and he will continue to be a strong advocate for these groups and all Americans.''</p>
        <p>Gay rights advocates had been alarmed by reports that his congregation, Hope Springs Community United Methodist Church, had a ministry to change the sexual orientation of gay men and lesbians. However, the congregation's pastor, the Rev. David Calhoun, denied that it did.</p>
        <p>The controversy over the nomination has largely been fueled by the 1991 report that Dr. Holsinger prepared for a committee in the United Methodist Church that was reviewing the denomination's stance on homosexuality.</p>
        <p>Dr. Holsinger's supporters contend that the report was based on peer-reviewed medical literature of the time. But the Rev. J. Philip Wogaman, the main writer for the committee, said the report reflected Dr. Holsinger's view on homosexuality. When Dr. Holsinger discerned that the committee was preparing a statement that would ''recognize the moral dignity of gay and lesbian life if practiced without promiscuity,'' Mr. Wogaman said, Dr. Holsinger angrily resigned.</p>
        <p>Maria Kemplin, a former colleague of Dr. Holsinger's who is a lesbian, is familiar with the 1991 report. But in a letter she sent to Senator Mitch McConnell, Republican of Kentucky, she wrote of Dr. Holsinger as a friend who helped without judging her.</p>
        <p>''I am a liberal Democrat and a member of gay and women's rights organizations,'' Ms. Kemplin wrote. ''Still, I strongly support Dr. Jim Holsinger as a leader and administrator who is able to see across divisive issues and relate with integrity to people, no matter their life circumstance.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
