<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chairman of Joint Chiefs Will Not Be Reappointed</title>
    <meta content="09military" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853136"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Joint Chiefs of Staff</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shanker, Thom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pace, Peter (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Robert M (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mullen, Michael G (Adm)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E3DE163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1287" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chairman of Joint Chiefs Will Not Be Reappointed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOM SHANKER; Sheryl Gay Stolberg contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shanker, Thom</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bush administration will not reappoint Gen Peter Pace to second term as chairman of Joint Chiefs of Staff, making him highest-ranking officer to be political casualty of fight over Iraq; Defense Sec Robert M Gates says decision was reached in order to avoid bitter hearings in Democratic-controlled Senate; he will recommend that Pres Bush appoint Adm Michael G Mullen, chief of naval operations, to serve as next chairman; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush administration said Friday that it would not reappoint Gen. Peter Pace to a second term as chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, making him the highest-ranking officer to be a political casualty of the fight over Iraq.</p>
        <p>Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates said the decision was reached in order to avoid bitter hearings in a Democratic-controlled Senate that is already confronting the White House over the wars in Iraq and Afghanistan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bush administration said Friday that it would not reappoint Gen. Peter Pace to a second term as chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, making him the highest-ranking officer to be a political casualty of the fight over Iraq.</p>
        <p>Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates said the decision was reached in order to avoid bitter hearings in a Democratic-controlled Senate that is already confronting the White House over the wars in Iraq and Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>''I have decided that at this moment in our history, the nation, our men and women in uniform, and General Pace himself would not be well-served by a divisive ordeal in selecting the next chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff,'' Mr. Gates said.</p>
        <p>The defense secretary stood alone at a Pentagon podium in making the announcement, and he spoke in somber tones in describing how he fully had intended to recommend General Pace be offered a second two-year term as chairman, only to change his mind over the last few weeks after consulting with senior senators of both parties.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates said he would recommend that President Bush appoint Adm. Michael G. Mullen, the chief of naval operations, to serve as the next chairman. The defense secretary praised Admiral Mullen as a man of ''vision, strategic insight, experience and integrity.''</p>
        <p>General Pace has served for six years at the very highest ranks of the military, for four years as vice chairman of the Joint Chiefs and then two years as the first marine to be chairman. General Pace, who is 61, had made clear that he wanted to be reappointed, and associates said he was deeply disappointed. When he steps down at the end of September, he will become the shortest-serving chairman since Gen. Maxwell D. Taylor in 1964, during the early years of the Vietnam War.</p>
        <p>By law, the chairman is the senior-ranking member of the armed services and is the top military adviser to the president, the defense secretary and the National Security Council. In that capacity, he is not in command of American forces at war, but plays a central role in shaping strategy and policy and in relaying communications from the civilian leadership to commanders in the field.</p>
        <p>But General Pace's reputation has nevertheless become intertwined with the American invasions of Afghanistan and Iraq and the heavy tolls that the subsequent counter-insurgency fights have inflicted on the United States military. He has been criticized by some senior officers who saw him as too deferential to civilian leadership, in particular former Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld, and too inattentive to the impact of prolonged war-fighting on the Army, Marines and their National Guard and Reserve elements.</p>
        <p>President Bush is known for loyalty to members of his senior council, including the generals who have served in Iraq and Afghanistan, and he risked a confirmation battle earlier this year when he successfully nominated Gen. George W. Casey Jr., the top American commander in Iraq, to become Army chief of staff.</p>
        <p>In the case of General Pace, however, Mr. Bush "reluctantly agreed'' not to seek a renomination for the chairman, even though the president ''has the highest regard for General Pace,'' said Dana Perino, the deputy White House press secretary.</p>
        <p>In a written statement, Mr. Bush said, ''I have relied on his unvarnished military judgment, and I value his candor, his integrity and his friendship.''</p>
        <p>A confirmation hearing for the next chairman would have come in September, just as the two top American ground commanders in Iraq are scheduled to issue their first official assessment of Mr. Bush's strategy of escalating the troop presence there.</p>
        <p>In making his announcement, Mr. Gates emphasized that the decision should not be viewed as a rebuke of General Pace's tenure, which he described as one of ''great distinction.'' Mr. Gates likewise said the decision should not be seen as an acknowledgment that the decline in Congressional support for the war was spreading even to Republicans.</p>
        <p>The defense secretary, though, said his conversations with senior lawmakers of both parties had led him to conclude that ''the focus of his confirmation process would have been on the past, rather than the future'' and ''that there was the very real prospect the process would be quite contentious.''</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Gates acknowledged that both Democrats and Republicans had warned of a bruising confirmation hearing for General Pace, the public statements from senior Republicans were effusive. "Peter Pace has served his nation, his beloved Marine Corps, with the greatest of distinction," said Senator John W. Warner of Virginia, the ranking Republican on the Armed Services Committee.</p>
        <p>But Senator Carl Levin, the Michigan Democrat who is chairman of the Armed Services Committee, acknowledged Friday that he had cautioned against offering General Pace a second term as chairman.</p>
        <p>''In response to a request from Secretary Gates, I solicited the views of a broad range of senators,'' Mr. Levin said. ''I found that the views of many senators reflected my own, namely that a confirmation hearing on General Pace's reappointment would have been a backward-looking debate about the last four years.''</p>
        <p>General Pace is a highly decorated combat veteran who led a rifle platoon during some of the most vicious urban combat in American military history, in Vietnam during the 1968 battle of Battle of Hue.</p>
        <p>In the past week, however, speculation swirled that he would not be renominated, rumors coming after General Pace was forced to defend his comments that homosexual conduct was immoral, akin to adultery -- a statement far from the legal underpinnings of the military's ban on openly gay soldiers based on arguments for discipline and unit cohesion.</p>
        <p>General Pace also stirred concern among senior colleagues that he had stepped over a line defining civilian-military relations with a letter urging leniency for I. Lewis Libby Jr., the vice-presidential aide convicted of lying during a Central Intelligence Agency leak investigation.</p>
        <p>Looking to the future, Mr. Gates noted that Admiral Mullen already had a reputation for rising above parochial service interests to focus on how all of the armed forces can best support each other. Mr. Gates said that his senior military assistant had recently been told by Admiral Mullen that his highest priority, even as chief of naval operations, was finding ways to help the Army as it carried the burden of combat in Iraq and Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>Over recent months, Admiral Mullen also called upon his service's brightest minds to write the first new maritime strategy since the end of the cold war to address both traditional challenges and emerging asymmetrical threats.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levin, the armed services committee chairman described Admiral Mullen as '' well-qualified'' for the job of chairman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates also said he would recommend that the new vice chairman of the Joint Chiefs be General James E. Cartwright, the Marine Corps officer in charge of the Strategic Command, responsible for American nuclear forces and computer attack.</p>
        <p>The current vice chairman, Adm. Edmund P. Giambastiani Jr., announced his retirement last week. With the decision to name a Navy officer as chairman, it would not have been possible for Admiral Giambastiani to continue in the No. 2 job, although Mr. Gates said he unsuccessfully had urged the admiral to accept another senior-level position.</p>
        <p>A number of respected officers have seen their career paths damaged or altered by the debate over Iraq.</p>
        <p>Among them are Gen. John P. Abizaid, an advocate of limiting the American presence in Iraq, who retired months early from his command in the Middle East as Mr. Bush was ordering an influx of troops. And Lt. Gen. Ricardo S. Sanchez, the senior ground commander in Iraq after the invasion, never received a fourth star and was quietly pushed toward retirement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
