<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Europeans Fail to Agree on Financing Big Satellite Project</title>
    <meta content="09satellite" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/business/worldbusiness/09satellite.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853105"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Positioning System</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Galileo (Satellite System)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Defense Contracts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Defense Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tiefensee, Wolfgang (Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Castle, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Belgium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Belgium/Brussels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Belgium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Navigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Positioning System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Defense Contracts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Positioning System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Navigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Brussels (Belgium)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">European Union</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E1DF163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Europeans Fail to Agree on Financing Big Satellite Project</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Europeans Fail to Agree on Financing Big Satellite Project</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN CASTLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Castle, Stephen</byline>
      <dateline>BRUSSELS, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>European governments fail to agree on how to salvage their troubled satellite navigation system, Galileo, adding to doubts about their ability to continue to finance 'grand European projects' like European rival to Global Positioning System of US; transport ministers from 27 European Union governments, meeting in Luxembourg, scrap original public-private financing plan for satellite project but postpones decision on how to come up with 2.4 billion euros ($3.2 billion) to keep project afloat; German Transport Min Wolfgang Tiefensee says he supports program in principle but concedes that complete failure of Galileo is possible if financing cannot be found; standing to gain from loss of Galileo could be European Defense Agency, which involves lower-profile effort to help coordinate pan-European military spending and to open military contracts in each European country to companies in other countries (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>European governments failed to agree Friday on how to salvage their troubled satellite navigation system, Galileo, adding to doubts about their ability to continue to finance ''grand European projects'' like the European rival to the Global Positioning System of the United States.</p>
        <p>The transport ministers from the 27 European Union governments, meeting in Luxembourg, scrapped the original public-private financing plan for the satellite project but postponed a decision on how to come up with 2.4 billion euros ($3.2 billion) to keep the project afloat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>European governments failed to agree Friday on how to salvage their troubled satellite navigation system, Galileo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>European governments failed to agree Friday on how to salvage their troubled satellite navigation system, Galileo, adding to doubts about their ability to continue to finance ''grand European projects'' like the European rival to the Global Positioning System of the United States.</p>
        <p>The transport ministers from the 27 European Union governments, meeting in Luxembourg, scrapped the original public-private financing plan for the satellite project but postponed a decision on how to come up with 2.4 billion euros ($3.2 billion) to keep the project afloat.</p>
        <p>Later, the German transport minister, Wolfgang Tiefensee, said he supported the program in principle but conceded that a complete failure of Galileo was possible if financing could not be found.</p>
        <p>Regardless of the outcome, Galileo's difficulties could prompt Europe to think again before embarking on prestige projects that require satisfying disparate government and corporate interests and encourage it to opt instead for smaller programs.</p>
        <p>Standing to gain from a loss of Galileo could be the European Defense Agency, which involves a lower-profile effort to help coordinate pan-European military spending and to open military contracts in each European country to companies in other countries.</p>
        <p>''The E.D.A. is in a very different position,'' its chief executive, Nick Witney, said. ''Given the constraints to defense budgets we have focused on trying to encourage relatively small-scale collaboration between our member states, focusing on key technology and subsystems which will be the building blocks towards improved defense capabilities.''</p>
        <p>By contrast, the future of Galileo looks far from certain. The European Commission will put together a new financing proposal and, though most countries favor a bailout by taxpayers, several are reticent.</p>
        <p>Britain and the Netherlands issued a statement emphasizing the need to keep open the option of a public-private partnership.</p>
        <p>The consortium that has dropped out of the financing mechanism -- and which was to have paid two-thirds of the costs -- included European Aeronautic Defense and Space, Alcatel-Lucent and Thales of France, Finmeccanica of Italy, AENA and Hispasat of Spain, Inmarsat of Britain and TeleOp of Germany.</p>
        <p>The plan was that the consortium would gain long-term concession rights to operate Galileo and have a share in the profit. In recent months, though, the companies began to have doubts because of the risks involved.</p>
        <p>European governments have already spent 1.2 billion euros ($1.6 billion) on the project.</p>
        <p>In fact, the idea of Europeans starting a constellation of 30 navigation satellites was, from the start, difficult to get off the ground. The very concept worried the Pentagon, and Britain initially stalled Galileo, demanding a report by management consultants before it threw its weight behind the project.</p>
        <p>The public-private partnership model adopted for Galileo quickly proved unworkable. In June 2005, the two consortiums bidding for the work were merged when the authority awarding the contract failed to choose between them. The result was one large industrial grouping that was unable to agree on how the contract should operate.</p>
        <p>When a deadline for agreement was missed, the European transport commissioner, Jacques Barrot, stepped in, calling for full public financing. In the meantime, the project fell behind schedule, increasing the risk that the Russians and Chinese will have systems in place before the European Union and that the anticipated financial returns will never be realized.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
