<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Megabytes Triumph Over Muscle</title>
    <meta content="09stew" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/arts/television/09stew.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853074"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Nickelodeon</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Coulier, Dave</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E7DF163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="557" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Megabytes Triumph Over Muscle</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When Megabytes Triumph Over Muscle</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN STEWART</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Shredderman Rules,'' a junior high movie on Nickelodeon tonight, appears at first glance to be a typical revenge-of-the-nerds comedy. It has the usual lineup: a smart, awkward hero; a rich bad guy; clueless adults; and an unattainable love interest. In this formula character generally wins out, and right makes might.</p>
        <p>But in ''Shredderman'' the dice are loaded. The bully is more pathetic than his victims, and the hero has something besides good values going for him: he has computer skills. Ultimately, ''Shredderman'' is a fable about the dominance of technology over muscle. In modern warfare it's the smart weapons that win.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In “Shredderman Rules,” a junior high movie on Nickelodeon, the bully is more pathetic than his victims, and the hero has something besides good values going for him: he has computer skills.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Shredderman Rules,'' a junior high movie on Nickelodeon tonight, appears at first glance to be a typical revenge-of-the-nerds comedy. It has the usual lineup: a smart, awkward hero; a rich bad guy; clueless adults; and an unattainable love interest. In this formula character generally wins out, and right makes might.</p>
        <p>But in ''Shredderman'' the dice are loaded. The bully is more pathetic than his victims, and the hero has something besides good values going for him: he has computer skills. Ultimately, ''Shredderman'' is a fable about the dominance of technology over muscle. In modern warfare it's the smart weapons that win.</p>
        <p>The bully, Bubba Bixby (Andrew Caldwell), is fat, stupid and in dire need of approval from his father, who runs a sewage empire. Bubba's weapons are physical and archaic, running the gamut from ''noogies'' and ''fishhooks'' to ''purple nurples'' and the classic ''atomic wedgie.'' Sometimes he just wanders around the art department, smashing things.</p>
        <p>The hero, Nolan Byrd (Devon Werkheiser), is skinny, bright and adequately raised by his naïve but well-meaning parents (His dad is Dave Coulier, late of ''Full House.'') But he has been insulted one too many times by Bubba.</p>
        <p>''Where did this guy come from?'' Nolan wonders. ''Did he crawl out of the primordial ooze?''</p>
        <p>Well, this is a Nickelodeon production, so there will be ooze somewhere. (In this case it issues from a hose connected to a sewage chemical truck.) In the meantime Nolan uses his camera phone to record the bully doing his misdeeds, then posts his findings on the Internet. Soon the entire school is flocking to the Web to mock Bubba, and Nolan is a legend, albeit an anonymous one.</p>
        <p>Nobody raises the issue of privacy or of the legality of the surveillance, but that's beside the point in a movie about empowerment and heroism. Imagine what Superman could have done if he had used viral marketing.</p>
        <p>There are a few ups and downs before the inevitable denouement. They will give you time to appreciate the quiet talent of Tim Meadows, who, as the teacher, is a still point in this teeming tween world, and to ponder the success of Mr. Werkheiser, who, at 16, has already had his own show (''Ned's Declassified School Survival Guide'') on Nickelodeon for three years. He's cute but not sexy, and he can dance. Perhaps most important, he reacts similarly to skillful and painful dialogue.</p>
        <p>''Shredderman'' has both kinds. Occasionally it's almost clever, as when Miriam, the miserable girl (another stock high school movie character), is pining for the hero.</p>
        <p>''Nolan, you look vulnerable,'' she says in a reedy monotone. ''Do you want me to hold you?''</p>
        <p>Then there's the scene in which Nolan's dad excuses himself: ''I burped an anchovy pizza,'' he explains.</p>
        <p>I hate to sound as archaic as Bubba, but is this necessary? Talk about a gas crisis. If we could harness the energy that goes into cheap flatulence jokes, we could probably end our dependence on foreign oil.</p>
        <p>Shredderman Rules  Nickelodeon, tonight at 8, Eastern and Pacific times; 7, Central time.</p>
        <p>Marjorie Cohn, Joel Rice and Lauren Levine, executive producers; Savage Steve Holland, director; teleplay by Russell Marcus.</p>
        <p>WITH: Tim Meadows (Mr. Green), Andrew Caldwell (Bubba Bixby), Daniel Roebuck (Bixby Sr.), Mindy Sterling (Principal Voss), Dave Coulier (Nolan's dad), Francia Almendarez (Isabel).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
