<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amid the Shirts and Socks, a Concert Can Break Out</title>
    <meta content="09orga" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/arts/music/09orga.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Musical Instruments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Musical Instruments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Macy, R H, &amp; Co Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EED61F30F93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1021" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amid the Shirts and Socks, a Concert Can Break Out</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Amid the Shirts and Socks, a Concert Can Break Out</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG R. WHITNEY</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What do you do if you buy a famous downtown department store and find an organ with 28,482 pipes occupying thousands of square feet of perfectly good retail space?</p>
        <p>If you're Macy's, you let devotees of the instrument put in 61 more pipes and give them thousands more square feet to set up an organ repair shop.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>What do you do if you buy a famous downtown department store and find an organ with 28,482 pipes occupying thousands of square feet of perfectly good retail space?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What do you do if you buy a famous downtown department store and find an organ with 28,482 pipes occupying thousands of square feet of perfectly good retail space?</p>
        <p>If you're Macy's, you let devotees of the instrument put in 61 more pipes and give them thousands more square feet to set up an organ repair shop.</p>
        <p>Diapasons, it would seem, are as much music to Macy's as cash registers, coin counters and customers at its Center City store here, a Philadelphia institution that was originally a Wanamaker's. So the company let the Friends of the Wanamaker Organ, a private group of aficionados who have been helping to maintain the instrument for years, install another stop and set up a repair shop after Macy's took over the store.</p>
        <p>''Every lunchtime, people hear the organ and feel good -- and people are in a mind to shop when they're feeling good,'' explained James Kenny, the store manager. ''It's the ultimate feel-good experience.''</p>
        <p>The organ, the world's largest operating musical instrument, has never sounded better, according to the store's staff organist, Peter Richard Conte, who has been here 20 years and fills the place with warm waves of sound at noon and in the evening, daily except Sunday.</p>
        <p>''In 1995 it was down to about 20 percent of the pipes being playable, maybe,'' and only two keyboards working instead of six, Mr. Conte said. ''Now it sounds loved again.''</p>
        <p>With money from private donors and more than $100,000 from Macy's this year, the staff curator, L. Curt Mangel III, with his assistant, the Friends and numerous organ groupies, now have 95 percent of the organ playing again. Next year they expect to have it all up and running for the first time in decades.</p>
        <p>Today Mr. Conte and the Friends have the run of the store for the annual Wanamaker Organ Day, and Mr. Conte will play something new: his own transcription of Elgar's ''Enigma'' Variations (Op. 36), at 11:30 a.m. Shoppers are welcome.</p>
        <p>He has been working feverishly on the Elgar for weeks, with all-night practice sessions, alone in the store except for a guard. ''It's probably the most difficult piece I've ever done,'' he said before trying out several movements at a Wednesday evening concert, his fingers slinking from keyboard to keyboard and darting restlessly over the 729 stop-control tablets as phrase seamlessly followed phrase and crescendo climaxed and faded into descrescendo.</p>
        <p>The Elgar sounds impressively orchestral on this organ, with its 462 sets of pipes, including stops named for orchestral violins, cellos, flutes, orchestral oboes, clarinets, French horns, tubas and trombones. It has just about everything else imaginable -- chimes and even a kitchen sink (for the curators to wash their hands) -- in a forest of pipes ranging from 32 feet to less than an inch long, spread over both ends and multiple rooms and floors off the store's Grand Court.</p>
        <p>Next year a long, muffled section of 2,000 more pipes, now being cleaned and restored, will rejoin the rest in a more audible spot, and Mr. Conte expects to luxuriate in its liberated sounds, including three more French horn stops made by the Kimball Organ Company of Chicago.</p>
        <p>''I love the sound of French horns and I will probably use them a lot,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The instrument started life at the St. Louis International Exposition of 1904, when the Los Angeles Art Organ Company built it along orchestral lines, rather than according to the baroque organ ideal, as Bach and Buxtehude knew it.</p>
        <p>It was a smash hit at the fair, but bankrupted the company. Then it languished in storage until 1909, when John Wanamaker bought it for the Philadelphia store that he was planning to open two years later.</p>
        <p>His son, Lewis Rodman Wanamaker, saw the vast, 149-foot-high Grand Court center space in the building Daniel Hudson Burnham had designed for them as the ideal place for ''the finest organ in the world,'' and 40,000 people and President William Howard Taft came to the dedication ceremonies on Dec. 30, 1911.</p>
        <p>Until his death in 1928, Lewis Rodman Wanamaker oversaw successive expansions of the organ in the store's own organ shop on the building's roof. The changes were so extensive that the instrument's ''string'' section finally had more pipes than most large organs do altogether.</p>
        <p>Famous organists flocked to play it over the years, and both Marcel Dupré and Virgil Fox developed signature pieces on the organ, but when Lewis Rodman Wanamaker died, the organ's importance faded. Wanamaker's itself was sold to Woodward &amp; Lothrop in 1986; then it became a Hecht's; and in 1997 a Lord &amp; Taylor store. Macy's took it over last year.</p>
        <p>Each of the owners recognized the unique historical value of the organ, and Lord &amp; Taylor hired Mr. Mangel as curator in 2002. The difference now, as Mr. Conte sees things, is that ''Macy's gets it -- it understands how to use this instrument and market it to the public.''</p>
        <p>Martine Reardon, the Macy's national headquarters executive overseeing holiday events, including now the annual Christmas organ and light show in the Philadelphia store, said, ''The Wanamaker Organ's legacy is as legendary as the Thanksgiving Day Parade and the Fourth of July fireworks.''</p>
        <p>Next year, Macy's 150th anniversary, the store hopes to get the Philadelphia Orchestra to come and play Joseph Jongen's ''Symphonie Concertante,'' a work for organ and orchestra commissioned by Wanamaker's in 1928 but never performed at the store.</p>
        <p>And the Friends, with a $150,000 donation from the Phoebe Haas Charitable Trust, have set up a spacious repair and organ-building training center on an unused floor of the store. Early this year the additional 61 new pipes, a rank of singing vox humana stops, joined nine others in a chamber rebuilt especially for them and brought the total to 28,543. To many their vibrato tones call to mind a choir of angels.</p>
        <p>Mr. Conte patted the huge console that controls the pipes and said, nodding at Mr. Mangel, ''Baby hasn't been given such care and tending since John Wanamaker.'' But he still hopes Baby will throw no tantrums at today's performance.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
