<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wife and Son of Police Chief Are Among 50 Killed in Iraq</title>
    <meta content="09iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/world/middleeast/09iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853097"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burns, John F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jorani, Ali al- (Col)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E2DF163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1152" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wife and Son of Police Chief Are Among 50 Killed in Iraq</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Wife and Son of Police Chief Are Among 50 Killed in Iraq</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS; Ali Adeeb contributed reporting from Baghdad, and Iraqi employees of The New York Times from Basra, Baquba and Kirkuk.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burns, John F</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Over 50 people are killed in attacks across Iraq, including 14 who died when gunmen stormed police chief's home northeast of Baghdad and raked occupants with automatic fire; police chief, Col Ali al-Jorani, was staying elsewhere; his wife and son were among dead; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than 50 people were killed in attacks across Iraq on Friday, including 14 who died when gunmen stormed a police chief's home northeast of Baghdad and raked the occupants with automatic fire.</p>
        <p>The police chief, staying elsewhere for the night, survived. His wife and son were among the dead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than 50 people were killed in attacks across Iraq on Friday, including 14 who died when gunmen stormed a police chief’s home northeast of Baghdad.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More than 50 people were killed in attacks across Iraq on Friday, including 14 who died when gunmen stormed a police chief's home northeast of Baghdad and raked the occupants with automatic fire.</p>
        <p>The police chief, staying elsewhere for the night, survived. His wife and son were among the dead.</p>
        <p>At least 34 others were killed in two bombing attacks, one in the northern city of Daquq, about 30 miles south of Kirkuk, and the other in the southern city of Qurna, 60 miles north of Basra. In a familiar pattern, both bombings involved successive explosions set at close quarters in crowded areas, a technique often used to maximize casualties.</p>
        <p>The Daquq bombings struck a Shiite mosque and a nearby police station. The attack began when two suicide bombers detonated explosive vests in the forecourt of a mosque frequented by supporters of the Shiite cleric Moktada al-Sadr, followed by a car bomb close by, according to the local police. They said at least 19 people died, and more than 20 were wounded.</p>
        <p>The Qurna blasts involved two vehicle bombs, one in a minibus in a bus terminal, the other in a car beside a nearby market. The police said at least 15 people were killed and more than 30 wounded.</p>
        <p>Most of the victims in the Daquq and Qurna bombings appeared to have been Shiites, who account for about 60 percent of Iraq's population and have been the principal targets of attacks by Sunni insurgent groups seeking to drive foreign forces out of Iraq and restore Sunni minority rule.</p>
        <p>The attack on the police chief's house, at Kanaan, about 15 miles south of Baquba, the capital of Diyala Province, was the latest in a wave of attacks across the province that have been directed against Iraqi Army and police bases and their commanders, as well as a 5,500-member American force that is seeking to rein in the violence that has made Diyala, after Baghdad, the bloodiest theater of war in Iraq.</p>
        <p>In recent months, the province is thought to have become the main operating base for the insurgent group Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia and its Sunni Islamic allies. Until recently, they were principally based in Anbar, the Sunni-dominated province directly west of the capital. But American success in winning the support of senior Anbar tribal chiefs in fighting Al Qaeda has brought a rush of recruits for the Iraqi Army and the police in the province, and sharp decrease in violence there.</p>
        <p>American commanders say that many of the Sunni insurgent groups appear to have abandoned the harsh desert terrain of Anbar for the relatively lush vegetation of Diyala, whose thick palm groves and orchards provide effective hiding places. American and Iraqi commanders acknowledge that the terrain has helped the insurgents to establish what amount to safe havens in wide areas of Diyala from which the insurgents mount deadly hit-and-run attacks like the one on the police chief's home in Kanaan.</p>
        <p>Police officials said the attack was aimed at Col. Ali al-Jorani, a Sunni officer in Saddam Hussein's army who was recruited into the police last month and appointed the police chief in the Balda district of Baquba.</p>
        <p>He retained his home in Kanaan, a town with a mixed Sunni and Shiite population that police officials said is close to bases used by the Islamic State of Iraq, the umbrella group that includes Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia and that has claimed responsibility for many of the deadliest sectarian attacks in Diyala.</p>
        <p>The police said the gunmen who stormed into Colonel Jorani's home killed 12 bodyguards, mostly members of the colonel's own extended family, and shot dead his wife and one of his sons, also a policeman, before fleeing. The attackers took with them three other residents of the house, but there were conflicting reports on their identities. A police official in Baquba said the kidnap victims were three other bodyguards, two of whom were found dead later. But Western news agency reports quoted Colonel Jorani as saying that those kidnapped included three of his children, two boys and a girl.</p>
        <p>The spate of attacks on police commanders in Diyala continued with another attack later on Friday that killed a district police chief from Bani Sad, a town about 20 miles north of Baghdad on the road to Baquba.</p>
        <p>The police there said the chief, Maj. Saeed al-Amri, and a bodyguard were killed when his car hit a roadside bomb. Two other senior officers in the car were wounded.</p>
        <p>The violence across the country played out against a backdrop of continuing political deadlock in Baghdad. The multiparty, multiethnic government of Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki, a religious Shiite, appears to have reached a point of near exhaustion in the quest for what American officials have called a ''national compact'' among Shiites, Sunnis and Kurds on an array of disputed issues, including future oil revenues and constitutional revisions.</p>
        <p>In the absence of an agreement, or an active drive toward one, there has been increasing fractiousness, characterized by a wave of recriminatory statements by rival leaders. During a meeting with tribal leaders in southern Iraq, Mr. Maliki spoke bitterly of what he described as political ''conspirators'' against his leadership, comparing them to ''a black ant on a black rock on a dark night.'' He added, ''They will definitely pay a price if they insist on weakening Iraq or interfering in its internal affairs.''</p>
        <p>The prime minister mentioned no names. But his anger appeared to be focused on Ayad Allawi, a secular Shiite with a background in the Baath Party of Mr. Hussein. Mr. Allawi was chosen by American officials to head Iraq's first new post-invasion government in 2004.</p>
        <p>Mr. Allawi, from a base in London, has stepped up efforts to form a new political bloc that would bring together secular Shiites, former Baathists and Kurdish splinter groups, and has sought backing in Egypt and Saudi Arabia, among other Sunni-dominated neighbors of Iraq.</p>
        <p>Another target of Mr. Maliki's outburst appeared to be Tariq al-Hashemi, a Sunni political leader who is one of Iraq's two vice presidents and who has accused Mr. Maliki of being an increasingly sectarian figure with little interest in reaching out to Sunnis. Mr. Hashemi's group, the Iraqi Consensus Front, has held talks with Mr. Allawi, arousing fears among religious Shiites that moves to unseat the Maliki government, and Shiite political dominance, may be afoot.</p>
        <p>''They can't be partners in the political process with one hand, and hold a knife in the other,'' Mr. Maliki said of politicians like Mr. Allawi and Mr. Hashemi, whose parties are among those with seats in Parliament. ''We will have to distinguish between those who are true partners in the search for national reconciliation and those who want to maneuver outside the political process.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
