<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beethoven to Brahms to Ives: Tribute to a Tortured Legacy</title>
    <meta content="09quar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/arts/music/09quar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853201"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Emerson String Quartet</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Carnegie Hall</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ives, Charles</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E0D61F30F93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beethoven to Brahms to Ives: Tribute to a Tortured Legacy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Beethoven to Brahms to Ives: Tribute to a Tortured Legacy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES R. OESTREICH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The line from Beethoven through Brahms to Charles Ives is as complex as it is obvious. Brahms adopted gestures, if not actual themes, from Beethoven, and Ives borrowed from both.</p>
        <p>But these influences came freighted with ambivalence. Brahms was tortured by the legacy of Beethoven even as he drew on it. And Ives, misogynistic when he was not outright misanthropic, found them both -- though ''among the strongest and greatest in all art'' -- ''too much'' emasculated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Emerson String Quartet’s concert at Carnegie Hall on Thursday offered much food for thought.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The line from Beethoven through Brahms to Charles Ives is as complex as it is obvious. Brahms adopted gestures, if not actual themes, from Beethoven, and Ives borrowed from both.</p>
        <p>But these influences came freighted with ambivalence. Brahms was tortured by the legacy of Beethoven even as he drew on it. And Ives, misogynistic when he was not outright misanthropic, found them both -- though ''among the strongest and greatest in all art'' -- ''too much'' emasculated.</p>
        <p>So the Emerson String Quartet's concert at Carnegie Hall on Thursday evening, as part of its enhanced Beethoven cycle, ''The Quartets in Context,'' offered much food for thought. Brahms's Quartet No. 1 led up to Ives's Quartet No. 2, leaving Beethoven to bring up the rear with the E minor ''Razumovsky'' Quartet (Op. 59, No. 2).</p>
        <p>In fact, the stimulation began before the Emerson players took the stage, in a prelude concert by the American pianist Jeremy Denk: a performance of Ives's juggernaut Piano Sonata No. 2 (''Concord, Mass., 1840-60'').</p>
        <p>That sonata (1911-20) begins, appropriately enough, with a movement called ''Emerson,'' which makes heavy use of the motto theme of Beethoven's Fifth Symphony. Mr. Denk's brilliant performance made the most of the contrast between Ives's bullying textures and the abrupt transcendent or comic effusions.</p>
        <p>Likewise the Emerson players in the quartet, though the moments of relief are fewer there. Most of the comedy comes in the second movement, ''Arguments,'' with section markings like ''Andante emasculata'' (well, not so comic, that), ''Andante con scratchy (as tuning up)'' and ''Allegro con fistiwatto (as a K.O.).''</p>
        <p>The Second Quartet (1907-13), like the sonata, uses a Beethoven theme, the ''Ode to Joy'' from the Ninth Symphony, but only fleetlingly. More crucial structurally, both works are pulled together in the final moments by ostinatos, the sonata again achieving greater transcendence in its ineffable rising figure than the quartet in its descent.</p>
        <p>It is rare to hear either work so authoritatively performed. It was endlessly fascinating to hear them juxtaposed.</p>
        <p>Brahms was cowed by Beethoven in the quartet medium almost as much as in the symphony. The First Quartet, completed in 1873, with which he finally broke through after many preliminary efforts, bears kinship in its gruff probity to Brahms's First Symphony, completed three years later, and is in the same basic key of C minor.</p>
        <p>After all this gruffness, Beethoven's quartet, the ostensible star of the program, afforded a calming force, not the role you necessarily expect from this composer.</p>
        <p>The Emerson's performances were uniformly compelling and often revealing in their details. But the performance quality was almost secondary to the thoughtfulness of the conception, prelude included.</p>
        <p>''Quartets in Context'' resumes tomorrow, with further concerts on June 12, 14 and 17, at Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
