<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Court Blocks Sri Lanka's Effort to Expel Tamils From Capital</title>
    <meta content="09lanka" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/world/asia/09lanka.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853092"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tamils (Ethnic Group)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sri Lanka</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Colombo (Sri Lanka)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sengupta, Somini</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sri Lanka</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Sri Lanka</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Sri Lanka</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E3DF163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Court Blocks Sri Lanka's Effort to Expel Tamils From Capital</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Court Blocks Sri Lanka’s Effort to Expel Tamils From Capital</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOMINI SENGUPTA; Anthony David contributed reporting from Colombo.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sengupta, Somini</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sri Lankan government's effort to expel ethnic minority Tamils living in Colombo meets with barrage of criticism from home and abroad and is quashed by country's highest court (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Sri Lankan government's efforts to expel ethnic minority Tamils living in Colombo, the capital, met with a barrage of criticism from home and abroad on Friday and was quashed by the country's highest court.</p>
        <p>The government had said it had deported nearly 400 Tamils living in low-cost hotels and boardinghouses in Colombo on suspicion that they were helping ethnic separatist rebels plot bombings in the city, though no criminal charges were filed. Human rights groups said the expulsions were tantamount to ethnic cleansing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Sri Lankan government’s move was met with a barrage of criticism from home and abroad on Friday and was quashed by the country’s highest court.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Sri Lankan government's efforts to expel ethnic minority Tamils living in Colombo, the capital, met with a barrage of criticism from home and abroad on Friday and was quashed by the country's highest court.</p>
        <p>The government had said it had deported nearly 400 Tamils living in low-cost hotels and boardinghouses in Colombo on suspicion that they were helping ethnic separatist rebels plot bombings in the city, though no criminal charges were filed. Human rights groups said the expulsions were tantamount to ethnic cleansing.</p>
        <p>The police, backed by the army, rounded up the men and women on Thursday and placed them in buses bound for a northern district called Vavuniya, near the front line between government and rebel territories. The Defense Ministry said in a statement that only those who could not provide a valid reason for being in the capital were evicted. Opposition politicians denounced the move as a violation of the right to move freely within the country.</p>
        <p>On Friday, a Colombo-based nonpartisan research and advocacy group called the Center for Policy Alternatives successfully lobbied the court to halt the evictions. The police told Reuters that after the court order, those who were expelled the day before would be given the choice to return to Colombo or be sent to their homes in rebel-held areas.</p>
        <p>In the past year, the 2002 cease-fire that halted Sri Lanka's quarter-century-long ethnic conflict has fallen apart. The military, aided by pro-government paramilitary groups, is conducting an intensive campaign against the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam.</p>
        <p>Since July, the government has largely succeeded in flushing the Tamil Tigers out of the east, where the rebels had long held strategic patches of coast, jungle and countryside. The army has tried to push them deeper into the jungle, in and around the rebel headquarters in the north, Kilinochchi, and the air force has regularly bombed what it calls their strategic assets in the area. Meanwhile, the military has also tried to push the rebels away from the western coast around Mannar, where oil exploration is about to start. There are also clashes in and around the Jaffna peninsula, farther north, as well as near the northern front line in northern Vavuniya.</p>
        <p>In April, the Tamil Tigers unveiled their latest weapon in the fight: small airplanes, which they used to bomb an air force base next to the civilian airport just north of Colombo, forcing the closing of the airport at night and prompting a number of international airlines to cancel flights to Sri Lanka. The rebels have refused to return to negotiations until the military offensives cease.</p>
        <p>The United States government, in a statement on Friday, pressed the government to halt the evictions. The United States, a longtime ally of Sri Lanka and one of the first foreign countries to include the Tamil Tigers on its list of banned terrorist organizations, has lately stepped up criticism of the government.</p>
        <p>''The United States understands and supports Sri Lanka's obligation to defend itself against terrorism,'' the statement read. ''But this action can only widen the ethnic divide at a time when important efforts are under way to reach a national consensus to end Sri Lanka's nearly quarter-century-old conflict.'' The United States continues to provide military training assistance to Colombo.</p>
        <p>The court order came Friday as troops defused a roadside bomb in the capital and bombed a rebel airstrip in the north, Reuters reported. Separately, Reuters said, the police found nine unidentified bodies near the capital. Hundreds of people, largely ethnic Tamils, are reported to have been abducted across the country over the last several months. On occasion, their bodies turn up.</p>
        <p>Last week, the bodies of two workers of the Sri Lanka Red Cross Society were found in a suburb of Colombo, a day after they were picked up at a Colombo train station by two men who had identified themselves as police officers. The president, Mahinda Rajapakse, said the killings were an effort to discredit his government. His government has opposed calls to dispatch international human rights monitors.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
