<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rights Group Offers Grim View of C.I.A. Jails</title>
    <meta content="09prisons" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/world/europe/09prisons.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853108"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Poland</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Romania</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Council of Europe</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carvajal, Doreen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marty, Dick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Poland</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Romania</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Council of Europe</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1DF163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="591" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rights Group Offers Grim View of C.I.A. Jails</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rights Group Offers Grim View of C.I.A. Jails</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOREEN CARVAJAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carvajal, Doreen</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Report by Dick Marty, lead investigator for Council of Europe, gives bleak description of secret prisons run by CIA in Poland and Romania from 2003 to 2006; Marty says he relied heavily on information from CIA agents; critics in Poland and Romania attack Marty's use of anonymous sources (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a report on Friday, the lead investigator for the Council of Europe gave a bleak description of secret prisons run by the Central Intelligence Agency in Eastern Europe, with information he said was gleaned from anonymous intelligence agents.</p>
        <p>Prisoners guarded by silent men in black masks and dark visors were held naked in cramped cells and shackled to walls, according to the report, which was prepared by Dick Marty, a Swiss senator investigating C.I.A. operations for the Council of Europe, a 46-nation rights group.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A bleak description of secret prisons run by the Central Intelligence Agency in Eastern Europe emerged from a report on Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a report on Friday, the lead investigator for the Council of Europe gave a bleak description of secret prisons run by the Central Intelligence Agency in Eastern Europe, with information he said was gleaned from anonymous intelligence agents.</p>
        <p>Prisoners guarded by silent men in black masks and dark visors were held naked in cramped cells and shackled to walls, according to the report, which was prepared by Dick Marty, a Swiss senator investigating C.I.A. operations for the Council of Europe, a 46-nation rights group.</p>
        <p>Ventilation holes in the cells released bursts of hot or freezing air, with temperature used as a form of extreme pressure to wear down prisoners, the investigators found. Prisoners were also subjected to water-boarding, a form of simulated drowning, and relentless blasts of music and sound, from rap to cackling laughter and screams, the report says.</p>
        <p>The report, which runs more than 100 pages, says the prisons were operated exclusively by Americans in Poland and Romania from 2003 to 2006. It relies heavily on testimony from C.I.A. agents.</p>
        <p>Critics in Poland and Romania attacked Mr. Marty's use of anonymous sources and issued categorical denials, as they have done repeatedly. Denis MacShane, a British member of Parliament and longtime critic of Mr. Marty, complained that the investigator ''makes grave allegations to two European Union member states, Poland and Romania, without any proof at all.''</p>
        <p>Tomasz Szeratics, a spokesman for the Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs, said: ''We shall not make any comments on Dick Marty's latest report until we receive it officially and analyze the evidence presented. The Polish position remains unchanged and it is very clear: There were no secret C.I.A. detention centers on the territory of the Republic of Poland.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Marty said at a news conference in Paris that anonymous testimony was backed by thousands of flight records showing prisoner transfers, including private planes linked to the C.I.A. that made 10 flights from Afghanistan and Dubai to the Szczytno-Szymany International Airport in Poland between 2002 and 2005.</p>
        <p>That was the closest airport to a Soviet-era military compound where about a dozen high-level terror suspects were jailed, the report charges. The local authorities formed secure buffer zones around the jails, which were operated exclusively by Americans, Mr. Marty reported.</p>
        <p>Lower-level prisoners from Afghanistan and Iraq were held at a military base near the Black Sea in Romania, the report says. The Romanians were restricted to the buffer zone.</p>
        <p>''Our Romanian officers do not know what happened inside those areas because we sealed them off and we had control,'' the report cites a senior military agent as saying.</p>
        <p>The details of prison life were given by retired and current American intelligence agents who had been promised confidentiality, the report says.</p>
        <p>Their motives were varied, Mr. Marty said. ''For 15 years, I have interviewed people as an investigating magistrate and I have always noticed that at a certain point, people with secrets need to talk,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Others justified the grim treatment, the reports said, saying, in one instance: ''Here's my question. Was the guy a terrorist? 'Cause if he's a terrorist, then I figure he got what was coming to him.''</p>
        <p>According to the report, suspects were often held for months with no contact except with masked, silent guards who would push meals of cheese, potatoes and bread through hatches.</p>
        <p>When prisoners resisted, the report says, one investigator considered it a welcome sign. ''You know they are starting to crack,'' he said, ''So you hold out. You push them over the edge.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
