<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mientkiewicz Faces Surgery And Hopes for a July Return</title>
    <meta content="09pins-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853195"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E4DC163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="805" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mientkiewicz Faces Surgery And Hopes for a July Return</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Doug Mientkiewicz, the injured first baseman, showed up in the Yankees' clubhouse yesterday afternoon with a cast on his right wrist and a hopeful sound in his voice. He said he would have surgery in New York on Tuesday to put a pin in his wrist to repair a broken bone.</p>
        <p>He said he wanted to return by late July or, at the latest, Aug. 1. Until then, he said, he will try not to bother his family too much with his anxiety. ''I love playing the game,'' Mientkiewicz said before the Yankees' game with Pittsburgh. ''I hate watching it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Doug Mientkiewicz, the injured first baseman, showed up in the Yankees' clubhouse yesterday afternoon with a cast on his right wrist and a hopeful sound in his voice. He said he would have surgery in New York on Tuesday to put a pin in his wrist to repair a broken bone.</p>
        <p>He said he wanted to return by late July or, at the latest, Aug. 1. Until then, he said, he will try not to bother his family too much with his anxiety. ''I love playing the game,'' Mientkiewicz said before the Yankees' game with Pittsburgh. ''I hate watching it.''</p>
        <p>He said the pin would help him heal more quickly and that he hoped to train soon at the team compound in Tampa, Fla. ''I'll be a homeless single father if I have to wait 12 weeks in a cast,'' Mientkiewicz said.</p>
        <p>He said he and Jason Giambi, another injured Yankee, had been watching recent road games on television and sending each other text messages. ''Two old men in a convalescent home, trying to kill time,'' Mientkiewicz said. ''It's gut wrenching. The game looks a lot easier from your couch.''</p>
        <p>Mientkiewicz was injured last Saturday afternoon in Boston in a collision with Mike Lowell of the Red Sox. When Mientkiewicz leaned back to catch a bouncing throw, Lowell, the batter, ran into him, with Lowell's leg hitting Mientkiewicz's head.</p>
        <p>Along with the broken wrist, Mientkiewicz sustained a concussion, a sprained neck and a sore back.</p>
        <p>''I still have moments when I'm dizzy, when I don't feel so good,'' Mientkiewicz said. ''The neck and the back are the least of my worries. The wrist is a little disconcerting.''</p>
        <p>He said he was not certain, but he thought he might have injured the wrist three innings before the collision, when sliding into second base. But he continued to play.</p>
        <p>After the collision, Mientkiewicz remained on the field for several minutes while trainers treated him. He was then removed from the field on a cart as Boston fans cheered him. He used to play for the Red Sox and said he was thankful for the ovation, although, because his head hurt, the sound was painful.</p>
        <p>That is when he realized that more than his head hurt. ''As the cobwebs started floating away, I realized my wrist really hurt,'' Mientkiewicz said. The first person to call him in Massachusetts General Hospital, Mientkiewicz said, was Lowell.</p>
        <p>They know each other from high school in Florida. ''Mike and I go way back, class guy,'' Mientkiewicz said. ''Class guy. There's no way he could have avoided me. The only thing I could have hoped for is that he'd be a step faster than he was.''</p>
        <p>They work out together in the winter and Mientkiewicz said he had a plan. ''Maybe we'll work out this off-season on getting him a half-step faster,'' Mientkiewicz said. ''That way, he doesn't kill somebody else.'' Turning serious, he added: ''Mike's a good friend of mine. There's no ill feelings.''</p>
        <p>In the clubhouse Friday, Mientkiewicz greeted several teammates, including Andy Pettitte, the starting pitcher. The Yankees were on a three-game winning streak and had won six of their previous eight games, one of their best stretches of a troubled season.</p>
        <p>''I was scared to come in the clubhouse today,'' Mientkiewicz said. ''I didn't want to screw anything up. I don't want to get in anybody's way or disrupt the vibe.''</p>
        <p>UNHAPPY MUSSINA -- Mike Mussina was not happy about being removed from Thursday night's game in Chicago, but Manager Joe Torre said last night that they had not yet discussed the situation. Mussina did not get the decision (Scott Proctor did) in the Yankees' 10-3 victory against the White Sox. Mussina's record remains 2-3.</p>
        <p>''Somebody has to make decisions here,'' Torre said. ''Mike and I have been around a long time together. I'm sure we'll get around to talking about it. You know, I don't think it's necessary. Not that I'm staying away from him.'' Torre added that with Thursday night's travel, ''We really haven't come together yet.''</p>
        <p>Mussina had allowed two hits in six shutout innings before an infield single and another single put runners on first and third with no outs in the seventh. After throwing only 79 pitches, Mussina was replaced by the left-hander Mike Myers, who came in to face the left-handed-batting A. J. Pierzynski, who singled to tie the score, 1-1.</p>
        <p>''Why am I upset?'' Mussina said after Thursday's game. ''Because I threw 80 pitches and I think I could have thrown 110. It was the first mess I had. I just felt like I could have kept going.''</p>
        <p>Torre said: ''Pitch count didn't enter into it. It was more strategy. I was looking more for a strikeout. That's how much I know. A base hit to right field.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
