<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Good Homework Produces A Slam Swing at a Semifinal</title>
    <meta content="09CARD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/arts/09CARD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Bridge"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E7DF163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="552" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Good Homework Produces A Slam Swing at a Semifinal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Good Homework Produces a Slam Swing at a Semifinal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Phillip Alder</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The U.S.A.-2 team for the Venice Cup will be Shawn Quinn, Sue Picus, Hjordis Eythorsdottir and Rozanne Pollack. On Wednesday in Schaumburg, Ill., they defeated Kathleen Sulgrove, Candace Griffey, Cindy Bernstein, Sally Wheeler, Laurie Kranyak and Linda McGarry by 192 international match points to 158.</p>
        <p>In the trial for the Bermuda Bowl, the semifinals were completed yesterday evening. After 90 of the 120 boards, Nick Nickell, Dick Freeman, Bob Hamman, Paul Soloway, Jeff Meckstroth and Eric Rodwell led Seymon Deutsch, Grant Baze, Bart Bramley, Gary Cohler, John Kranyak and Sidney Lazard by 174 imps to 139. And Russ Ekeblad, Ron Rubin, Fred Gitelman, Brad Moss, Chip Martel and Lew Stansby led Richard Schwartz, Michael Becker, David Berkowitz, Larry Cohen, Drew Casen and Jim Krekorian by 237 imps to 147. (The results can be found at usbf.org.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The U.S.A.-2 team for the Venice Cup will be Shawn Quinn, Sue Picus, Hjordis Eythorsdottir and Rozanne Pollack.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The U.S.A.-2 team for the Venice Cup will be Shawn Quinn, Sue Picus, Hjordis Eythorsdottir and Rozanne Pollack. On Wednesday in Schaumburg, Ill., they defeated Kathleen Sulgrove, Candace Griffey, Cindy Bernstein, Sally Wheeler, Laurie Kranyak and Linda McGarry by 192 international match points to 158.</p>
        <p>In the trial for the Bermuda Bowl, the semifinals were completed yesterday evening. After 90 of the 120 boards, Nick Nickell, Dick Freeman, Bob Hamman, Paul Soloway, Jeff Meckstroth and Eric Rodwell led Seymon Deutsch, Grant Baze, Bart Bramley, Gary Cohler, John Kranyak and Sidney Lazard by 174 imps to 139. And Russ Ekeblad, Ron Rubin, Fred Gitelman, Brad Moss, Chip Martel and Lew Stansby led Richard Schwartz, Michael Becker, David Berkowitz, Larry Cohen, Drew Casen and Jim Krekorian by 237 imps to 147. (The results can be found at usbf.org.)</p>
        <p>The winners play a 120-board today and tomorrow to decide the U.S.A.-2 team for the Shanghai world championships, which begin at the end of September.</p>
        <p>The Deutsch team led by 11 imps after Board 73. The diagramed deal was No. 74.</p>
        <p>The auction given was produced by Meckstroth (North) and Rodwell. It gives an insight into the scientific methods they employ when having slam potential. South's opening bid showed 14-16 points. He sensibly added one point for his excellent five-card club suit.</p>
        <p>Two diamonds was a transfer, promising five or more hearts with any point-count, and two no-trump artificially announced four-plus clubs with at least game-forcing values. Three clubs was an inquiry denying three-card heart support. Four no-trump showed 2-5-2-4 distribution with slam-invitational values.</p>
        <p>South, although he had a subminimum in high-card terms, had five great trumps, another ace and a potentially useful heart queen. He had no qualms about jumping to six clubs.</p>
        <p>Rodwell won West's spade-king lead on the board with the ace, unblocked the king and queen of diamonds, played a club to his queen and cashed the diamond ace, discarding dummy's remaining spade. South ruffed a spade on the board, took dummy's heart ace and played a heart to his queen and West's king. At this point declarer claimed. The defense could not stop him from ruffing his last spade in the dummy and drawing trumps.</p>
        <p>At the other table Kranyak (South) opened one club, and Deutsch (North) responded one heart. South rebid one no-trump, showing 12-14 points, and North continued with two diamonds, an artificial inquiry. South bid two no-trump, denying three hearts, and North raised to three no-trump.</p>
        <p>In the other match both South players bid three clubs over two diamonds, which made reaching six clubs much easier. But Deutsch could have continued with three clubs over two no-trump, which would surely also have resulted in the slam's being reached.</p>
        <p>After a spade lead Kranyak took his 10 top tricks.</p>
        <p>Plus 1,370 and minus 630 gave the Nickell team 12 imps and the lead.</p>
        <p>In Thursday's column Jill Meyers opened two hearts with a 1-5-6-1 nine-count. This was incorrectly described as a weak two-bid. It showed at least five hearts, five or more cards in any other suit and some 5-10 high-card points, a Polish two-bit. Jill Levin's two-no-trump response asked for the second suit, and Meyers's four-diamond rebid showed 5-6 and a maximum.</p>
        <p>With a weak two-bid in either major, Meyers would have opened two diamonds.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
