<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Putin Proposes Alternatives for Missile Defense System</title>
    <meta content="09azerbaijan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/world/europe/09azerbaijan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853099"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radar</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Turkey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Azerbaijan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Caucasus (Russia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chivers, C J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Azerbaijan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Azerbaijan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Putin, Vladimir V</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E2DF163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1021" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Putin Proposes Alternatives for Missile Defense System</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Putin Proposes Alternatives on Missile Defense</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. CHIVERS; Sheryl Gay Stolberg contributed reporting from Gdansk, Poland.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chivers, C J</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Vladimir V Putin offers new suggestions for alternatives to missile defense system in Europe, saying Russia would not object to US interceptor missiles in Iraq, Turkey or at sea, and proposing that Russia and West study emerging missile threats jointly; makes his latest proposals after Azerbaijan says it is willing to discuss another Russian proposal to use Soviet-era early warning radar on its territory in Caucasus as part of missile defense system against Iran; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Vladimir V. Putin offered new suggestions on Friday for alternatives to a missile defense system in Europe, saying Russia would not object to American interceptor missiles in Iraq, Turkey or at sea, and proposing that Russia and the West study emerging missile threats jointly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin made his latest proposals hours after Azerbaijan said it was willing to discuss another Russian proposal, made Thursday, to use a Soviet-era early warning radar on its territory in the Caucasus as part of a missile defense system against Iran.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Vladimir V. Putin proposed that Russia and the West study emerging missile threats jointly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Vladimir V. Putin offered new suggestions on Friday for alternatives to a missile defense system in Europe, saying Russia would not object to American interceptor missiles in Iraq, Turkey or at sea, and proposing that Russia and the West study emerging missile threats jointly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin made his latest proposals hours after Azerbaijan said it was willing to discuss another Russian proposal, made Thursday, to use a Soviet-era early warning radar on its territory in the Caucasus as part of a missile defense system against Iran.</p>
        <p>Taken together, the two events suggested that additional new possibilities had emerged for negotiation and engagement on an issue that has been a source of intense anger in the Kremlin and has soured relations between Russia and the West.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin's remarks also appeared to be intended to alleviate doubts about whether his initial suggestion, to link the Russian-operated radar in the Caucasus into a Western system, could serve as a substitute for existing plans for a set of interceptors in Poland and a fire-control radar to guide them in the Czech Republic.</p>
        <p>But Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice, speaking Friday in New York, appeared to cast doubt on the feasibility of the Putin proposal. ''One does not choose sites for missile defense out of the blue,'' she told The Associated Press. ''It's geometry and geography as to how you intercept a missile.''</p>
        <p>She added, ''This is an idea that has not yet been vetted. We have to see whether Azerbaijan makes any sense in the context of missile defense.''</p>
        <p>President Bush himself, at an appearance on Friday with the Polish president, Lech Kaczynski, after the two had dinner at Mr. Kaczynski's presidential retreat on the Baltic Sea, seemed to signal that he was still committed to his original plan. After thanking Mr. Kaczynski for his support of the plan, he once again emphasized that ''the system we have proposed is not directed at Russia.''</p>
        <p>Speaking Friday at a news conference in Germany, the Russian president insisted that his offer of using the existing radar was only part of the Kremlin's alternative plan.</p>
        <p>''My initiative and my proposals to our American partners are much wider than the establishment of a radar station,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He also urged the United States not to proceed with its plans until thoroughly consulting with Russia on its own ideas, and suggested forming a pool of countries, including those in Europe, to evaluate emerging missile threats through 2012.</p>
        <p>The proposal to examine the threats could later prove to be another impasse, however, as Russia has quarreled with the West on the need for a missile defense system, saying Iran possesses no missiles capable of reaching Europe. The United States insists that Iran could develop the technology for such weapons, and that it needs to keep ahead of that possibility.</p>
        <p>There was no immediate reaction from the Bush administration to Mr. Putin's latest remarks.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush had described the previous suggestion as ''interesting,'' and Stephen J. Hadley, the national security adviser, had treated Mr. Putin's shift from criticizing the plans to proposing an alternative as a recognition that missiles from so-called rogue states could become a legitimate threat.</p>
        <p>''He has indicated that since it is a common threat to Russia, Europe and the United States, Russia ought to consider cooperating with us,'' Mr. Hadley said.</p>
        <p>Beyond saying that Russia would ''not rule out'' accepting American interceptor missiles in Iraq, Turkey or at sea, the details of the Kremlin's position were vague and left many issues to be worked out.</p>
        <p>Russia and the United States agreed Thursday to convene meetings of their experts this summer to assess Russia's proposals, and officials said it would be difficult to comment about them until the meetings had begun.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin's new proposals were made shortly after the NATO secretary general, Jaap de Hoop Scheffer, suggested that Azerbaijan was not an ideal location for defensive interceptor missiles, because it was too close to potential launch sites in Iran.</p>
        <p>And while Mr. de Hoop Scheffer made clear that he was giving only an initial assessment and that a fuller judgment should be rendered by experts, diplomats and analysts in Russia, the Caucasus, Europe and the United States also expressed skepticism about whether Mr. Putin's radar proposal was technically feasible.</p>
        <p>The Azeri radar, located in Gabala and operated by Russia under a lease, is used for early detection of launches, and is a different sort of system from the fire-control radar used to guide interceptor missiles against an incoming target.</p>
        <p>''The Gabala radar can only be used as a source of information,'' said Aleksandr A. Khramchikhin, a military analyst and missile expert at the Institute of Military and Political Analysis here. ''It cannot be used for guiding a missile in the direction of a target.''</p>
        <p>''It is incompatible,'' he added. ''So far this is the biggest problem.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Khramchikhin said Russia's proposals were still valuable, because the radar could serve as an excellent complement to an American system, providing a highly accurate early-warning capability that could be used in concert with fire-control radars. ''Principally, this is a rare case when Russia's initiative is sensible,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin made his initial proposal to Mr. Bush on Thursday at a resort on the Baltic Sea, the highlight of a private session between the two presidents during a meeting of the world's wealthy democracies that was hosted by Germany.</p>
        <p>Whatever the outcome of the eventual technical assessments of the proposal, no one disputed that Mr. Putin's suggestion had provided a welcome, if temporary, exit from an intensive diplomatic standoff.</p>
        <p>The Russian president had threatened to aim nuclear weapons at Europe should the current plans for missile defense go forward. The Russian proposal and a subsequent agreement to have experts from the United States and Russia discuss the idea this summer, offered the possibility of a less menacing round of negotiations, diplomats said.</p>
        <p>''The important thing, the good thing, is that the two presidents are engaging in dialogue,'' a NATO official said. ''That can only be welcomed.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
