<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abstract Drones, Delivered With Quiet Conviction</title>
    <meta content="09cali" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/arts/music/09cali.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853200"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Becker, Jim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E0D61F30F93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="484" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abstract Drones, Delivered With Quiet Conviction</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Abstract Drones, Delivered With Quiet Conviction</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATE CHINEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was plenty of time to consider the properties of a drone during Califone's show at the Blender Theater at Gramercy on Thursday night. Again and again, songs migrated back to their root tonalities, nudged along by stark and sober rhythms. The stylistic implication was variously Appalachian, Celtic, aboriginal or electronic, with roughly equal proportions of post-rock minimalism and Delta blues.</p>
        <p>Tim Rutili, the band's lead singer and guitarist, shaped the direction of the music with a quiet sort of conviction. For most of the set he was joined only by his core bandmates: Jim Becker on banjo, guitar and fiddle; Ben Massarella on percussion; and Joe Adamik on drums.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was plenty of time to consider the properties of a drone during Califone’s show at the Blender Theater at Gramercy on Thursday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There was plenty of time to consider the properties of a drone during Califone's show at the Blender Theater at Gramercy on Thursday night. Again and again, songs migrated back to their root tonalities, nudged along by stark and sober rhythms. The stylistic implication was variously Appalachian, Celtic, aboriginal or electronic, with roughly equal proportions of post-rock minimalism and Delta blues.</p>
        <p>Tim Rutili, the band's lead singer and guitarist, shaped the direction of the music with a quiet sort of conviction. For most of the set he was joined only by his core bandmates: Jim Becker on banjo, guitar and fiddle; Ben Massarella on percussion; and Joe Adamik on drums.</p>
        <p>Occasionally they played a song with compact dimensions and clear parameters, like the bluegrass-tinged ''Slow Right Hand.'' More often they started in one place and ended somewhere else, with a lot of fuzzy abstraction in between.</p>
        <p>The standout moments involved material from ''Roots &amp; Crowns'' (Thrill Jockey), Califone's excellent recent album. ''The Eye You Lost in the Crusade'' was one of these, before it melted into a haze. So was ''Pink &amp; Sour,'' a twangy near-samba with a stream of oblique imagery. (''Along your skin lost my language, black lip and red carnation, safe house safe,'' Mr. Rutili sang, making the lines seem almost reasonable.)</p>
        <p>But with the exception of ''Spider's House,'' a polyrhythmic pop song suggestive of the sweeter side of Jim O'Rourke, the songs didn't stand up to their studio versions. Part of what makes ''Roots &amp; Crowns'' so enthralling is a feeling of disciplined restraint: only 2 of the album's 13 tracks exceed five minutes in length, so their fissures and warbles tend to feel tantalizing.</p>
        <p>Uncoiled in performance, those same effects sounded aimless, even when there were guest contributions from the guitarist Curtis Harvey and members of the Bitter Tears. (Both Mr. Harvey and the Bitter Tears played opening sets.)</p>
        <p>At several different points in the show, Mr. Rutili paid tribute to a mentor from his adolescence in Addison, Ill., a wiry choreographer he identified as Tony. (He even invited Tony onstage to sing ''Rose Petal Ear,'' in a shaky but serviceable falsetto.) ''He was really into the fourth wall,'' Mr. Rutili said, recalling his early training as a performer. ''Like, I'm talking to you guys, so the fourth wall is broken down.''</p>
        <p>Actually, the wall had been breached well before Califone took the stage. Mr. Harvey did it the earnest way, with self-conscious banter and a faltering singalong.</p>
        <p>The Bitter Tears went the opposite route, sending their frontman, Alan Scalpone, on a menacing prowl through the crowd. That was merely one tactic in a brazen performance that also involved wedding dresses, prank lyrics and calisthenics. It all had little to do with music, but you couldn't have called it dull.</p>
        <p>Califone and the Bitter Tears perform tonight at the Rock &amp; Roll Hotel in Washington.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
