<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Anticipated Trip Brings Much-Needed Win</title>
    <meta content="09mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/sports/baseball/09mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853193"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Detroit Tigers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Delgado, Carlos</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wright, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E6DC163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="948" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Anticipated Trip Brings Much-Needed Win</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Anticipated Trip Brings Much-Needed Win</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, June 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Damion Easley played three seasons at Comerica Park, long enough to know every nook and cranny of the cavernous stadium, but he was not about to play tour guide Friday. ''Didn't like the gaps too much,'' Easley said.</p>
        <p>His Mets teammates, many here for the first time, thought they would have visited here by now -- say, last Oct. 21, for Game 1 of the World Series -- but they made up for The Game That Should Have Been by turning the Game That Finally Happened into one to remember.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Wright and Carlos Delgado each homered for the second consecutive game, as the Mets snapped their four-game losing streak.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Damion Easley played three seasons at Comerica Park, long enough to know every nook and cranny of the cavernous stadium, but he was not about to play tour guide Friday. ''Didn't like the gaps too much,'' Easley said.</p>
        <p>His Mets teammates, many here for the first time, thought they would have visited here by now -- say, last Oct. 21, for Game 1 of the World Series -- but they made up for The Game That Should Have Been by turning the Game That Finally Happened into one to remember.</p>
        <p>Jorge Sosa tossed eight scoreless innings, and David Wright and Carlos Delgado homered for the second consecutive game as the Mets silenced the Detroit Tigers, 3-0, in a crisp 2 hours 14 minutes to snap a four-game losing streak.</p>
        <p>''We have too good of a team to fall into this long of a slump or a rut,'' said Wright, whose bases-empty home run against Chad Durbin in the fourth opened the scoring.</p>
        <p>Coming into the night, the Mets owned the second-best record in the National League but had sputtered recently, losing five or their past six and being swept at home by the Philadelphia Phillies.</p>
        <p>The danger was what could happen if this little rough patch, as Manager Willie Randolph called it, developed into a full-fledged skid. Their coming schedule is unrelenting, and it started Friday night against the Tigers, a team that scored 81 runs over its recent 10-game trip and had yet to be shut out this season.</p>
        <p>''I feel good going into this series,'' Randolph said before the game. ''We might not be in first place all year, but we are right now, so that's a pretty good place to be. I'm not going to react to such a small window.''</p>
        <p>The Mets' rhythms change from series to series, so there is no use, Randolph said, trying to predict how they would fare in this one. Still, the recent trends held for another game. The offense, batting .143 with runners in scoring position and .239 over all this month, mustered only seven hits against Tigers pitching. The defense, spearheaded by Carlos Gómez and José Reyes, made several sparking plays behind Sosa. The starting pitching, yet again, relieved pressure from the offense.</p>
        <p>According to the Elias Sports Bureau, Mets starters have posted a 1.89 earned run average in June while holding opponents to a .205 batting average. For the 15th consecutive game, a starter allowed three or fewer runs. The last one to allow more was Sosa, on May 22 in Atlanta. But he has recovered nicely to allow only one run in his past 14 2/3 innings and become the first Mets pitcher ever to win six of his first seven starts with the team.</p>
        <p>''I just have to give Willie and the coaching staff credit for having faith in me,'' Sosa said through an interpreter.</p>
        <p>The Mets' diluted lineup, still without Moises Alou and Shawn Green, nonetheless featured six regulars in the starting lineup. Paul Lo Duca served as designated hitter to give Ramon Castro some time at catcher, and Ricky Ledee, recalled Friday from Class AAA New Orleans to replace the demoted David Newhan, started in left field and batted ninth.</p>
        <p>Ledee's playing time may dwindle as soon as Sunday, when Green is scheduled to come off the disabled list. He took batting practice and called himself ready to go. Alou made the trip but is unlikely to be activated any time soon. Randolph mentioned the possibility of Alou returning to Florida for treatment if his strained left quadriceps did not show improvement soon.</p>
        <p>The Tigers' lineup is imposing and intact, and before the game Randolph scanned it and nodded in approval. His eyebrows peaked at the sight of Gary Sheffield, the former Yankee, and they stayed up until he had finished.</p>
        <p>''Inge hits ninth?'' Randolph said, referring to third baseman Brandon Inge. ''That's pretty good.''</p>
        <p>That lineup could not handle the new-and-improved Sosa, who said he threw more off-speed pitches than usual to capitalize on the aggressive hitters. He also seemed to take advantage of a generous strike zone from the home plate umpire, Marty Foster, nibbling at the corners with his fastball and throwing his slider a few inches off the plate in seemingly every direction.</p>
        <p>With Sosa's pitch count up to 103, Randolph left him in to start the eighth, and he retired the first two Tigers without trouble before Plácido Polanco crushed a double to deep center. As Sheffield marched toward the plate, the pitching coach Rick Peterson came out to remind Sosa that Sheffield was an excellent fastball hitter and to throw him only sliders.</p>
        <p>This was precisely the sort of situation that Sheffield, who entered the night with 32 runs batted in in his past 32 games, lives for: down by 2-0, a runner on second, a chance to tie the score with one ferocious swing. Following Peterson's advice, Sosa threw a slider for a strike, then got Sheffield to pound another one into the ground to end the inning. When the throw from Reyes thumped into Delgado's mitt, Sosa pounded his chest and pointed to Castro. His night was done, and so were the Tigers.</p>
        <p>''I'm not surprised,'' Randolph said. ''But you can't predict something like this.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Pedro Martínez threw 40 pitches in a bullpen session in Port St. Lucie, Fla. Martínez, who threw off a mound Tuesday for the first time since having rotator cuff surgery, figures to take two days off between bullpen sessions for the next few weeks.  The Mets selected shortstop Glen Johnson, the son of the first-base coach Howard Johnson, in the 36th round of the draft.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
