<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rancor Level Rises in Rift Over Danone China Venture</title>
    <meta content="09danone" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/09/business/worldbusiness/09danone.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853138"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Groupe Danone</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wahaha</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zong Qinghou</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Faber, Emmanuel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barboza, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Shanghai</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Shanghai (China)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Groupe Danone</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE3DE163FF93AA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="650" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rancor Level Rises in Rift Over Danone China Venture</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rancor Level Rises in Rift Over Danone China Venture</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARBOZA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barboza, David</byline>
      <dateline>SHANGHAI, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dispute between French beverage maker Groupe Danone and its Chinese partner, beverage maker Wahaha, becomes even stranger when Wahaha releases several letters written by employees that denounces Danone for being run by 'rascals' who are committing 'evil deeds'; letters, which are filled with old-fashioned Communist slogans, come one day after Wahaha founder-chairman Zong Qinghou resigned in anger, saying his reputation is being ruined by dispute; resignation appears to be victory for Danone, which is trying to gain control of venture; Emmanuel Faber was named interim chairman of Wahaha; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A dispute between Groupe Danone, the French dairy and beverage maker, and its Chinese partner, the beverage maker Wahaha, became even stranger on Friday when Wahaha released several letters written by employees that denounced Danone for being run by ''rascals'' who were committing ''evil deeds.''</p>
        <p>The letters, which were filled with vitriol and old-fashioned Communist slogans, came a day after the founder and chairman of Wahaha, Zong Qinghou, resigned in anger, saying that his reputation was being ruined by the dispute.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A dispute between Groupe Danone, the French dairy and beverage maker, and its Chinese partner, the beverage maker Wahaha, has become even stranger.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A dispute between Groupe Danone, the French dairy and beverage maker, and its Chinese partner, the beverage maker Wahaha, became even stranger on Friday when Wahaha released several letters written by employees that denounced Danone for being run by ''rascals'' who were committing ''evil deeds.''</p>
        <p>The letters, which were filled with vitriol and old-fashioned Communist slogans, came a day after the founder and chairman of Wahaha, Zong Qinghou, resigned in anger, saying that his reputation was being ruined by the dispute.</p>
        <p>The resignation had appeared to be a victory for Danone, which is trying to gain control of the venture. On Thursday, Danone named Emmanuel Faber, the head of its Asian operations, as the interim chairman of Wahaha.</p>
        <p>But by Friday, there were indications that Wahaha was still being controlled by Mr. Zong or a management team loyal to him.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Danone declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zong, an entrepreneur who has been ranked as one of China's wealthiest individuals, could not be reached for comment on Friday.</p>
        <p>But Danone's dispute with its joint venture partner is turning into an increasingly nasty affair, complicating the company's control over one of its biggest and most lucrative investments in China, a beverage maker with sales of more than $1.4 billion a year.</p>
        <p>The dispute erupted this year after Danone, which owns 51 percent of the Wahaha joint venture that was founded in 1996, accused Mr. Zong of operating mirror companies that independently sold goods in China under the Wahaha brand name and then pocketing huge profits.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Zong has insisted that Danone executives knew about the affiliated companies and even audited them. He said Danone was seeking to acquire most of them but was unwilling to pay a hefty price, setting off the dispute.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, Danone imposed a deadline on its Wahaha partner to stop the companies from selling Wahaha products outside of the joint venture company.</p>
        <p>On Monday, after that deadline had passed, Danone filed a lawsuit in the United States against one of Mr. Zong's Wahaha-affiliated companies, claiming that Danone had been cheated out of at least $100 million.</p>
        <p>The target of the lawsuit was a company controlled or owned by Mr. Zong and his wife and daughter, who are listed as the company's legal representatives and who live in California.</p>
        <p>Angered by the lawsuit, Mr. Zong resigned from Wahaha on Thursday, saying that Danone had used dirty tactics to smear his name and harm his family.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zong also said that Danone executives had him followed and photographed, and that the French company had turned the dispute into a public fiasco.</p>
        <p>''I can no longer bear the abuse and slander of the two directors from your company,'' Mr. Zong wrote in a lengthy letter that offered a detailed assessment of how the joint venture with Danone began to collapse. ''So I have to resign as chairman of the 29 joint ventures between Wahaha and Danone and the 10 subsidiaries.''</p>
        <p>The counterattack against Danone continued late Friday, when Wahaha released letters from workers in various parts of the company.</p>
        <p>In angry tones, the letters defended the former chairman, and the workers vowed never to accept a chairman appointed by Danone.</p>
        <p>In one letter, which claimed to represent the entire sales force of Wahaha, the group called itself ''the army of only Chairman Zong.''</p>
        <p>The letter denounced and made fun of Danone and its directors and insisted that the Chinese people could not be bullied. The workers also said that Danone had engaged in a campaign of slander and intimidation to bring down the former chairman.</p>
        <p>At times, the letters seemed to hark back to the days of Chairman Mao, who was known as the Great Helmsman.</p>
        <p>''How can our respectable helmsman be forced away by Chinese traitors and rascal directors,'' one passage said. ''We only want Chairman Zong and we firmly reject Danone!''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
