<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inspired by Nicklaus, Choi Wins Memorial</title>
    <meta content="04golf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/sports/golf/04golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852157"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Country Clubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Country Clubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">PGA Tour Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Nicklaus, Jack</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Moore, Ryan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E4DE1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inspired by Nicklaus, Choi Wins Memorial</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Inspired by Nicklaus, Choi Wins Memorial</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <dateline>DUBLIN, Ohio, June 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When K. J. Choi was 16 and living in Wando, South Korea, his physical education teacher gave him a copy of an instructional book by Jack Nicklaus.</p>
        <p>It had been translated into Korean and had pictures of everything from the grip to the backswing, all the fundamentals Nicklaus had turned into a career that became legend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>K. J. Choi earn a one-shot victory over Ryan Moore at the Memorial Tournament, firing a seven-under-par 65 in the final round to finish at 17-under-par 271.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When K. J. Choi was 16 and living in Wando, South Korea, his physical education teacher gave him a copy of an instructional book by Jack Nicklaus.</p>
        <p>It had been translated into Korean and had pictures of everything from the grip to the backswing, all the fundamentals Nicklaus had turned into a career that became legend.</p>
        <p>Choi held fast to those long-ago lessons on a muggy Sunday to earn a one-shot victory over Ryan Moore at the Memorial Tournament -- an event for which Nicklaus is the host and the designer of the course.</p>
        <p>Choi, who favors a left-to-right fade in the fashion of Nicklaus, fired a seven-under-par 65 in the final round to finish at 17-under-par 271 at Muirfield Village Golf Club.</p>
        <p>''The fact that it's Jack's tournament just made me feel really comfortable,'' Choi said through an interpreter. ''I think I'm getting used to playing in the bigger tournaments.''</p>
        <p>Choi has five victories on the PGA Tour, and this one came after a frantic final round that featured birdies in bundles. Choi began the round trailing the third-round leader, Rod Pampling, by five shots. He then shot a six-under 30 on the front nine and held his round together with key par saves on the back.</p>
        <p>On the 215-yard, par-3 16th, he got up and down from a bunker by blasting out to 4 feet. On the next hole, a par 4 of 478 yards, Choi knocked his approach shot into the gallery behind the green, but he punched his ball 15 feet past the cup, then made the putt.</p>
        <p>With Nicklaus watching on a hill above the 444-yard, par-4 18th hole, Choi hit out of a greenside bunker to 5 feet and curled in the winning putt.</p>
        <p>''K. J. is a terrific bunker player,'' Nicklaus said.</p>
        <p>Pampling, who shot a 72 on Sunday, and Adam Scott (70) faltered with late bogeys, allowing Choi, 37, to secure the $1.08 million check for first place -- the largest of his career -- and one of the most prestigious titles on the PGA Tour.</p>
        <p>A compact 5 feet 8 inches and 185 pounds, Choi may be best known for wielding one of professional golf's most distinctive-sounding drivers. The square-headed club has been known to cause fellow players to flinch every time Choi brings the club back.</p>
        <p>At impact, the noise is a cross between a car backfiring and an aluminum bat hitting a baseball.</p>
        <p>''The first time he hit it, wow, you could hear it across the whole golf course,'' said Pampling, who finished tied for third with Kenny Perry at 273. ''It's definitely loud. You know when he's teed off.''</p>
        <p>Choi's early athletic endeavors in South Korea included weight lifting. (He could squat more than 300 pounds by age 13.)</p>
        <p>After he read the Nicklaus book and started playing golf, he said, it took him three years to believe he might have a future as a professional. ''All of the things that were written started to make sense to me,'' Choi said.</p>
        <p>He qualified for the PGA Tour in 1999 and 2000, becoming the first Korean to earn a Tour card. He then became the first Korean to win on the Tour, in 2002.</p>
        <p>He lives in Houston now, but his celebrity is unrivaled in South Korea, where simple walks down the street are interrupted by well-wishers.</p>
        <p>Nicklaus, who recently visited South Korea, said, ''I promise you, he's very big in Korea.''</p>
        <p>Nicklaus has tabbed him as an early favorite at the United States Open, which begins June 14 at Oakmont Country Club in Oakmont, Pa. Nicklaus won the Open there in 1962.</p>
        <p>As both men sat in an auditorium near the 18th green, they talked about the wonders of hitting a fade.</p>
        <p>''He'll do very well at Oakmont,'' Nicklaus said. ''K. J. is a high-ball hitter, a left-to-right player, and I think it favors both of those.''</p>
        <p>Choi turned to the golfer who first inspired him, smiled and said, ''Thank you.''</p>
        <p>OCHOA EDGED IN PLAYOFF -- Nicole Castrale chased down the world's No. 1 player, defeating Lorena Ochoa with a par on the first hole of a playoff and earning her first L.P.G.A. Tour victory yesterday at the Ginn Tribute in Mount Pleasant, S.C.</p>
        <p>Castrale closed with a one-under-par 71 to match Ochoa (74) at nine-under 279 on the RiverTowne Country Club course. (AP)</p>
        <p>ROBERTS WINS ON CHAMPIONS TOUR -- Loren Roberts won the Boeing Championship yesterday in Destin, Fla., for his first Champions Tour victory of the year. He closed with a six-under-par 65 for a three-stroke victory over Eduardo Romero of Argentina. Roberts finished with a 16-under 197 total. (AP)</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
