<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bound by Blood, but Separated by a Breach in Sanity</title>
    <meta content="04bran" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/theater/reviews/04bran.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852114"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gurney, A R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simpson, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weaver, Sigourney</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nielsen, Kristine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Esper, Michael</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Crazy Mary (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Gurney, A R</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Weaver, Sigourney</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Nielsen, Kristine</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gurney, A R</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Beatty, John Lee</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Crazy Mary (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E4DF1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="961" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bound by Blood, but Separated by a Breach in Sanity</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bound by Blood, but Separated by a Breach in Sanity</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley reviews A R Gurney play Crazy Mary, directed by Jim Simpson; Sigourney Weaver, Kristine Nielsen and Michael Esper star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sigourney Weaver and Kristine Nielsen serve their specialties with such gusto in ''Crazy Mary,'' the new comedy by A. R. Gurney that opened last night at Playwrights Horizons, that it feels ungallant to point out that their characters are as artificial as hard-plastic dolls.</p>
        <p>A work that never quite succeeds in matching its thoughtful head to its sentimental heart, ''Crazy Mary'' charts a culture clash between a lockjawed, button-down matron and her distant cousin, a longtime sanitarium resident who is, to put it politely, bonkers. Now, to find the natural choices for these parts, you wouldn't even need to consult a casting director, would you?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sigourney Weaver and Kristine Nielsen serve their specialties with such gusto that it feels ungallant to point out that their characters are as artificial as hard-plastic dolls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sigourney Weaver and Kristine Nielsen serve their specialties with such gusto in ''Crazy Mary,'' the new comedy by A. R. Gurney that opened last night at Playwrights Horizons, that it feels ungallant to point out that their characters are as artificial as hard-plastic dolls.</p>
        <p>A work that never quite succeeds in matching its thoughtful head to its sentimental heart, ''Crazy Mary'' charts a culture clash between a lockjawed, button-down matron and her distant cousin, a longtime sanitarium resident who is, to put it politely, bonkers. Now, to find the natural choices for these parts, you wouldn't even need to consult a casting director, would you?</p>
        <p>In recent years Ms. Weaver, who came to fame squashing extraterrestrials on the big screen, has become a peerless anatomist of the classic female WASP (in the title role of Mr. Gurney's ''Mrs. Farnsworth'' and as the society doyenne Babe Paley in the movie ''Infamous''). The spectacularly vibrant Ms. Nielsen has all but cornered the market on madcap madwomen on the New York stage, most memorably in comedies by Christopher Durang.</p>
        <p>These actresses could play their roles in ''Crazy Mary'' in their sleep. That they do not, while also making sure that the audience wants to stay awake, is a testament to their thorough-going professionalism. But they seldom disguise a yawning gap between social symbols and human substance in ''Crazy Mary,'' directed by Jim Simpson, which features a breakout performance by the young actor Michael Esper.</p>
        <p>Aside from the tireless (and seemingly immortal) Horton Foote, no eminent American playwright of the last few decades rivals the staying power and productivity of Mr. Gurney. Though he would seem to be limited by sticking to one area of expertise -- the malaise and mores of the endangered East Coast WASP -- Mr. Gurney's theatrical output is surprisingly varied.</p>
        <p>If his essential subject has largely remained the same, he keeps shifting his focus and perspective in admirably venturesome ways, most recently with his fiercely partisan, Bush-baiting political comedies in collaboration with Mr. Simpson at the Flea Theater in Lower Manhattan.</p>
        <p>As a story of ethnic dinosaurs stranded by history, ''Crazy Mary'' brings to mind vintage Gurney works like ''The Cocktail Hour'' and ''The Middle Ages.'' But though the dialogue in ''Crazy Mary'' can feel canned, its point of view is a fresh one for this dramatist.</p>
        <p>His earlier plays had the passive wistfulness of Henry James portraits of unlived lives; ''Crazy Mary'' has the active morality of E. M. Forster novels, demanding that its characters get off their isolated duffs and connect with the world beyond. The spirit in ''Crazy Mary'' is honorably willing; it's the flesh of organic existence that feels weak.</p>
        <p>The play is set in the library of a genteel Boston mental institution, a converted mansion where the title character (Ms. Nielsen) has been living for some 30 years. Designed with appropriately faded hauteur by John Lee Beatty, the set looks much like the sets of Gurney plays that take place in private clubs or homes.</p>
        <p>Which is the point. Mary and Lydia (Ms. Weaver), her newly designated legal guardian, are relics of a class whose former wealth and dominance has melted away. A house that might once have been a private palace for these women's ancestors has become Mary's prison.</p>
        <p>In her youth Lydia crossed the tracks to marry a jazz musician with a Polish name who has since left her to follow his music. A struggling real estate broker who retains the family sense of entitlement but not its affluence, Lydia springs the play's plot when she and her son Skip (Mr. Esper), an unhappy student at Harvard, visit her nearly forgotten, eternally terrified cousin, whose psychiatric care is financed by a whopping trust fund.</p>
        <p>What follows takes the characters, who also include the stock figures of a plain-spoken nurse (Myra Lucretia Taylor) and ineffectual doctor (Mitchell Greenberg), down some tortuous paths that evoke the distinctly un-Gurney-esque worlds of Tennessee Williams potboilers and the cult movie ''Harold and Maude.''</p>
        <p>In thematic terms it all makes sense. But these devices always feel like devices, and they translate into a swirl of stale melodramatic and perky comic elements that Mr. Simpson's glossy direction can't reconcile.</p>
        <p>So you can't really blame the leading ladies for occasionally coasting on a shticky surface. They have affecting moments. Ms. Weaver is expert in melding airs of arrogance and apology, while Ms. Nielsen touchingly signals the fear in her signature wild-eyed persona. But they never convince you that these disparate souls are sisters under the skin. Since this is what the play is about, that's a serious problem.</p>
        <p>Where ''Crazy Mary'' comes together is in its portrayal of the younger generation, embodied with prickly ambivalence by Mr. Esper's Skip. His character so easily could have been a petulant throwaway cartoon.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Esper, who appeared in the recent revival of Eric Bogosian's ''subUrbia,'' finds a troubled, introspective center to Skip that, by default, becomes our emotional compass in navigating Mr. Gurney's intentions. It is perhaps appropriate for a play about embracing the future that a fresh-faced young actor quietly wrests the spotlight from two daunting veterans.</p>
        <p>Crazy Mary</p>
        <p>By A. R. Gurney; directed by Jim Simpson; sets by John Lee Beatty; costumes by Claudia Brown; lighting by Brian Aldous; sound by Jill B C DuBoff; original music by Michael Holland; production manager, Christopher Boll; production stage manager, Janet Takami. Presented by the Playwrights Horizons, Tim Sanford, artistic director; Leslie Marcus, managing director; William Russo, general manager. At the Playwrights Horizons Mainstage Theater, 416 West 42nd Street, Manhattan; (212) 279-4200. Through June 17. Running time: 2 hours 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Michael Esper (Skip), Mitchell Greenberg (Jerome), Kristine Nielsen (Mary), Myra Lucretia Taylor (Pearl) and Sigourney Weaver (Lydia).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
