<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One Had Stature and One Didn't, But Neither Seemed an Extremist</title>
    <meta content="04suspects" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/nyregion/04suspects.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070613T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852190"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Guyana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Guyana</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E5DD1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1465" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One Had Stature and One Didn't, But Neither Seemed an Extremist</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">One Had Stature and One Didn’t, but Neither Seemed an Extremist</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANNY FERNANDEZ; Reporting was contributed by Daryl Khan, Jennifer 8. Lee, Trymaine Lee and Fernanda Santos.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Abdul Kadir and Russell M. Defreitas met in Georgetown in their native Guyana in late February, according to federal investigators. They walked together with another man to a mall downtown.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kadir said the reason they walked was simple: so they would be seen together. If people had any ideas of harming Mr. Defreitas and the other man, Mr. Kadir said, they would now ''think twice.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Abdul Kadir and Russell M. Defreitas met in Georgetown in their native Guyana in late February, according to federal investigators. They walked together with another man to a mall downtown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Abdul Kadir and Russell M. Defreitas met in Georgetown in their native Guyana in late February, according to federal investigators. They walked together with another man to a mall downtown.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kadir said the reason they walked was simple: so they would be seen together. If people had any ideas of harming Mr. Defreitas and the other man, Mr. Kadir said, they would now ''think twice.''</p>
        <p>It was a boastful gesture from a man of stature -- Mr. Kadir was once a member of Parliament in Guyana and had been mayor of Linden, its second-largest city. But it also illustrated the vast differences between Mr. Kadir and Mr. Defreitas: Back in the United States, Mr. Defreitas was a former cargo worker at Kennedy International Airport, living in a run-down Brooklyn apartment building, estranged from some of his family and friends.</p>
        <p>Both men were converts to Islam. Mr. Kadir, 55, became an imam. Mr. Defreitas, 63, referred to himself as Mohammed, but some of his friends still called him Russell.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kadir had been married for 35 years and had 9 children and 18 grandchildren. Mr. Defreitas was divorced and had apparently lost touch with his children, telling a friend that he was trying to track them down using the Internet. Mr. Kadir held a degree in civil engineering from the University of the West Indies at St. Augustine, in Trinidad and Tobago; Mr. Defreitas had trouble reading, and was homeless for a brief period, sleeping on subway trains.</p>
        <p>What brought the two men together, the federal authorities said, was their Islamic extremism and a plot to blow up Kennedy Airport.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kadir and Mr. Defreitas are accused of conspiring to use explosives to ignite the airport's fuel tanks and underground fuel pipeline network. Both were arrested on Friday, Mr. Kadir in Trinidad and Mr. Defreitas in Brooklyn. Efforts to reach their lawyers were not successful yesterday; at a hearing on Saturday, Mr. Defreitas's lawyer, Drew Carter, said, ''There's a lot more to the story.''</p>
        <p>A third suspect, Kareem Ibrahim, 61, was also arrested in Trinidad, and a fourth, Abdel Nur, 57, remained at large. The United States is seeking the extradition of Mr. Kadir and Mr. Ibrahim.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kadir's arrest shocked his political allies and relatives, many of whom said the man they knew and respected was not capable of such a terrible act.</p>
        <p>''He's a genuine gentle giant of a man,'' Mortimer Yearwood, who has known Mr. Kadir for 20 years and worked with him at a Guyanese charity called the Linden Fund, said by telephone from his home in Linden. In 2003, when he served on the group's board in Guyana, Mr. Kadir helped secure an $85 million donation of recycled medical supplies like beds, sutures and intravenous equipment for a Linden hospital.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Defreitas, however, the foiled plot, as described by the authorities, was another in a lifetime of missteps: It was Mr. Defreitas who had befriended the informant who helped break the case -- the same man who walked with them to the mall in Georgetown, the Guyanese capital.</p>
        <p>One friend, Trevor Watts, knew Mr. Defreitas not as a devout Muslim but as a dreadlocked Rastafarian who used to whistle at the girls strolling past the window of his apartment. He made money shipping air-conditioners and refrigerators to Guyana. He had embraced American culture, becoming a naturalized American citizen, registering to vote and acquiring a taste for jazz. Yet he would later boast to the informant about wanting to eclipse the attack on the World Trade Center.</p>
        <p>He seemed to struggle financially. Mr. Watts, 65, said Mr. Defreitas had collected welfare payments for a time. Years ago, he had his mail forwarded to Mr. Watts's house in Queens, and kept a bed and a trunk of clothes there, because he did not have a place of his own.</p>
        <p>Mr. Defreitas lived alone for several years in an apartment near the airport, and the daughter of his landlord there described him as a polite man who paid his rent on time.</p>
        <p>Recently, Mr. Defreitas had been living in an apartment on Rockaway Avenue in Brooklyn. It is an unlikely place for a man who, the authorities say, tried to tap into an international network of Islamic radicals. The building's door buzzer was broken on Saturday, and the door of one apartment was plastered with an eviction notice. His neighbors said he kept to himself and spent time in the African herbal store on the ground floor.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, Mr. Defreitas made an arrangement with Colin Sam, who runs an import-export business in the city. Mr. Defreitas told Mr. Sam that he would sell some of Mr. Sam's air-conditioners in Guyana and split the profits with him. Mr. Defreitas took the air-conditioners, but told Mr. Sam later that they did not work and that there was no money to be made from them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sam said yesterday that he believed that Mr. Defreitas had sold the air-conditioners and lied to him. ''That's it,'' he said. ''What more do you want me to say?''</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Defreitas's brothers lived in Queens and died of cancer years ago, but Mr. Defreitas did not go to the funeral, said Mr. Watts, who attended the service. Relations between the two brothers were strained, Mr. Watts said, as was Mr. Defreitas's relationship with another brother, who lives in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Mr. Defreitas was arrested at a restaurant in Brooklyn, the Lindenwood Diner, on Friday night. Mr. Watts, an auto mechanic who met Mr. Defreitas when they both lived on Albany Avenue in Brooklyn, said he never suspected his friend of plotting a terrorist attack. On the morning of Sept. 11, 2001, the two men were watching television in Mr. Watts's living room. ''We saw the second plane hit,'' Mr. Watts said. ''We couldn't even talk. He was in shock, just like me, just like everybody else.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kadir was born Michael Seaforch in 1952 in Buxton, a seaside village just east of Georgetown. One of his daughters, Sauda Kadir, said he converted to Islam in 1972 and studied Islamic theology in Iran. He had been living with his family in Linden for at least 20 years, and one of his sons, Sheik Salim Bin Abdul Sadir, is a Shiite Muslim leader there.</p>
        <p>''He is like any other dad: He's strict, and he always told us we should respect others if we wanted to be respected,'' Ms. Kadir, 31, said in a telephone interview from Guyana. ''He taught us to be good people, and he taught us to be good Muslims. He is very serious about his religion.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Kadir said her father was not anti-American. ''The only thing I think my father did wrong was being a Muslim,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kadir worked for a mining company until 2003, when he and many other workers lost their jobs to downsizing, Ms. Kadir said. After he was laid off, he worked as an independent engineering consultant.</p>
        <p>He served as mayor of Linden from 1994 to 1996, and in 2001 he joined the Guyanese Parliament as a member of the opposition People's National Congress, a seat he held until 2006. Judith David-Blair, a member of Parliament from the same party, said she did not believe Mr. Kadir could be involved in planning an attack on the United States. Members of Parliament would often seek his advice in political and personal matters, she said.</p>
        <p>''I never knew him to be that kind of man,'' she said of the charges. ''He was a very kind man, a very caring father; he is a great provider and a very brilliant man, the kind you can always count on.''</p>
        <p>As a board member of the Linden Fund, Mr. Kadir was in charge of receiving and disbursing money and supplies sent to Guyana by the fund's supporters in the United States.</p>
        <p>Last month, in one of the many conversations recorded by the informant, Mr. Defreitas, Mr. Ibrahim and the informant asked Mr. Kadir whether any money for an attack could be kept in Mr. Kadir's foundation in Linden, and Mr. Kadir seemed to agree that it could, though it was unclear if the foundation discussed was the Linden Fund.</p>
        <p>In a 2004 interview with The Stabroek News, a daily newspaper in Georgetown, Mr. Kadir said he joined the Islamic Party of the Caribbean while he was studying in Trinidad, then returned to Guyana to ''foster the teaching of Islam in the hope of bringing about social reform.'' He said he was influenced by Malcolm X and Kwame Nkrumah, the founder and first president of Ghana and one of the most influential Pan-Africanists of the 20th century.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 13, 2007, Wednesday  An article on June 4 about Abdul Kadir and Russell M. Defreitas, two of the four men accused of plotting to blow up Kennedy International Airport, referred imprecisely to Mr. Kadir's role in the Linden Fund, a charity in Guyana, his home country. As a board member and former mayor of Linden, Guyana's second-largest city, he used his contacts to help speed up the distribution of money and supplies sent to Guyana by donors in the United States, but he was not ''in charge'' of receiving and disbursing money and supplies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 13, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article on June 4 about Abdul Kadir and Russell M. Defreitas, two of the four men accused of plotting to blow up Kennedy International Airport, referred imprecisely to Mr. Kadir's role in the Linden Fund, a charity in Guyana, his home country. As a board member and former mayor of Linden, Guyana's second-largest city, he used his contacts to help speed up the distribution of money and supplies sent to Guyana by donors in the United States, but he was not ''in charge'' of receiving and disbursing money and supplies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
