<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>James Gives A New Generation Its Moment</title>
    <meta content="04rhoden" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/sports/basketball/04rhoden.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852173"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Detroit Pistons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio/Cleveland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Cleveland (Ohio)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Cleveland Cavaliers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Detroit Pistons</org>
        <person class="online_producer">James, LeBron</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05EEDE1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="809" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>James Gives A New Generation Its Moment</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">James Leads a New Generation to Its Moment</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <dateline>CLEVELAND</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The morning after the Cleveland Cavaliers defeated the creaking Detroit Pistons in Game 6 of the Eastern Conference finals, Lance Blanks, a Cavaliers assistant general manager, sipped tea and basked in citywide glory.</p>
        <p>I met Blanks in 1989, when he was a star at the University of Texas. He has developed a keen perspective on the business, the culture of basketball. He was a high school icon, a college star, a deflated pro. Now he is a rising front-office administrator.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>LeBron James’s performance in the N.B.A. playoffs marked a rite of passage for his generation - a generation that has been hammered by the previous one for its choice of music and modes of behavior.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The morning after the Cleveland Cavaliers defeated the creaking Detroit Pistons in Game 6 of the Eastern Conference finals, Lance Blanks, a Cavaliers assistant general manager, sipped tea and basked in citywide glory.</p>
        <p>I met Blanks in 1989, when he was a star at the University of Texas. He has developed a keen perspective on the business, the culture of basketball. He was a high school icon, a college star, a deflated pro. Now he is a rising front-office administrator.</p>
        <p>Like everyone else in Cleveland, Blanks was elated -- and a little stunned -- by the city's good fortune: Cleveland is in the N.B.A. finals for the first time in franchise history. A team with a 22-year-old star, LeBron James, had helped Cleveland pull off a stunning upset.</p>
        <p>''Right now, I'm still processing the fact that these 15 guys have managed to come together and take us to a championship,'' Blanks said.</p>
        <p>I'm not one for injecting a great sports moment or sports talent with qualities that have nothing to do with that moment. The ability to hit a baseball has nothing to do with great character; the ability to dunk a basketball has no redeeming social value outside of its entertainment value.</p>
        <p>But there is something to be said for recognizing leadership qualities regardless of where they are demonstrated. James's classic performances in these N.B.A. playoffs can reasonably be seen as the symbol of a rite of passage for his generation -- a generation of 22- to 28-year-olds that has been hammered by the 45-and-over crowd -- for style of dress, manner of speech, choice of music and modes of behavior.</p>
        <p>What we in the news media see more than ever is a generation of wealthy celebrity athlete-entertainers with a sense of entitlement that many find unnerving. Invariably what members of the older generation don't get is that it's not their turn anymore. It's the new generation's turn.</p>
        <p>''There's a new generation and there is a new way of doing things, and the world is moving at a different pace,'' said Blanks, who has two daughters, ages 16 and 13. ''The new vernacular, the gadgets, the way you dress doesn't mean the way you're doing things is wrong.''</p>
        <p>In 2000, Blanks joined the San Antonio Spurs, the Cavaliers' opponents in the finals, as a scout and was promoted to director of scouting two years later. He was with the Spurs for two of their three N.B.A. championships.</p>
        <p>During Cleveland's trip to San Antonio during the 2005-6 season, Danny Ferry, the Cavaliers' general manager, and Blanks were presented with their N.B.A. championship rings. James told Blanks that he wouldn't speak to him for the rest of the trip. And he didn't.</p>
        <p>''He didn't say why,'' Blanks said, ''but I think the gesture from him was, 'That's something I want and it's something I'm going to go get.' ''</p>
        <p>Blanks knows about youth and stardom, and stardom faded. He was a star at Texas, where he and two teammates, Travis Mays and Joey Wright, became known during the 1989-90 season as the B.M.W. Scoring Machine.</p>
        <p>Blanks was selected by Detroit in the 1990 N.B.A. draft. His tenure with the Pistons was brief: two seasons. But something Chuck Daly, the Pistons' coach, used to say became Blanks's code.</p>
        <p>''He said, 'Appreciate every day you're in this league,' '' Blanks said. ''I used to look at it in terms of being a player. Now, being in the front office, I realize he was talking to everybody. He was talking to himself.''</p>
        <p>When Ferry left San Antonio for Cleveland in 2005, he asked Blanks to make a huge leap of faith and pull up his deep Texas roots and help him build the Cavaliers into a winner. Blanks was born in Del Rio; his father, Sid, was a running back for the Houston Oilers and the Boston Patriots.</p>
        <p>San Antonio was an hour from where he went to college, and two hours from Del Rio. It meant that he; his wife, Renee; and their two daughters, one of whom is a promising junior tennis player, would commute between Florida -- where his daughter trains -- and Cleveland.</p>
        <p>San Antonio was Camelot, but Cleveland had King James.</p>
        <p>James is the intriguing young sports figure of our time. Earlier this year, he said that he wanted to be one of the world's wealthiest individuals, like Warren Buffett.</p>
        <p>He also said he wanted to be an icon, like Muhammad Ali, though Ali, as James will discover, is not an icon because of the wealth he accumulated.</p>
        <p>All things in time. For now, let's cherish the moment.</p>
        <p>''If LeBron was a book being written, we'd be just finishing Chapter 1, Chapter 2 at most,'' Blanks said yesterday morning. ''His story is emerging and unfolding in a positive way, but it's still in its infancy.''</p>
        <p>Let the chapter writing resume.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
