<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Palm Is Said To Sell Stake To Equity Firm In Revamping</title>
    <meta content="04deal" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/technology/04deal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852127"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Palm Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Elevation Partners</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rubenstein, Jon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markoff, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wireless Communications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Palm Inc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Elevation Partners</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E2DF1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Palm Is Said To Sell Stake To Equity Firm In Revamping</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Palm Is Said to Sell Stake to Equity Firm in Revamping</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN and JOHN MARKOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross; Markoff, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Palm Inc reaches deal to sell quarter of company to Elevation Partners for $325 million as part of reorganization plan; Jon Rubenstein will become executive chairman as part of transaction; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Palm Inc., the struggling hand-held device company that makes the Treo, reached a deal yesterday to sell a quarter of the company to Elevation Partners, a private equity firm, for about $325 million as part of a plan to reorganize the company, according to people involved in the negotiations.</p>
        <p>Jon Rubinstein, a former Apple executive who ran its iPod division, is also planning to join Palm as its executive chairman as part of the transaction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Palm Inc., the struggling hand-held device company that makes the Treo, has reached a deal to sell a quarter of the company to a private equity firm for about $325 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Palm Inc., the struggling hand-held device company that makes the Treo, reached a deal yesterday to sell a quarter of the company to Elevation Partners, a private equity firm, for about $325 million as part of a plan to reorganize the company, according to people involved in the negotiations.</p>
        <p>Jon Rubinstein, a former Apple executive who ran its iPod division, is also planning to join Palm as its executive chairman as part of the transaction.</p>
        <p>The deal, which is expected to be announced today, includes a plan to pay out about $940 million in dividends to Palm shareholders, worth $9 a share each, these people said.</p>
        <p>The reorganization comes after several months of unsuccessful efforts to find a buyer for Palm, which is facing increasing competition from all directions including Microsoft, which now dominates the smartphone market with its Windows Mobile software.</p>
        <p>Research in Motion, which makes the BlackBerry, is also a direct competitor, and Apple will soon enter the cellular phone market with its highly anticipated iPhone. And Google is said to be readying its own software competitor and is building alliances.</p>
        <p>Palm, which invented the first hand-held organizers in 1992, held preliminary talks with several rivals, including Motorola and Nokia, and private equity firms including Silver Lake Partners and the Texas Pacific Group, but none was willing to buy out the entire company amid such uncertainty over its future, these people said.</p>
        <p>The transaction with Elevation, a relatively new firm that bought a minority interest in Forbes last year, gives Palm an important cash infusion and also some experienced advisers. In addition to Mr. Rubinstein, Fred Anderson, a former chief financial officer at Apple, and Roger McNamee, a co-founder of Silver Lake Partners, both of whom are managing directors at Elevation, will join Palm's board. The deal is Elevation's largest.</p>
        <p>Palm spent the last few months trying to play down the prospect of a buyout. Just last week, Palm's chief executive, Ed Colligan, told CNBC, ''We're not focused on figuring out how to sell the company. We're focused on how to build the company and create long-term shareholder value.''</p>
        <p>At Apple, Mr. Rubinstein, an engineer who developed high-performance computer workstations at Hewlett Packard, oversaw successful products like the consumer-oriented iMac and oversaw the development of the company's iPod music player. He retired from Apple in 2005.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rubinstein will be joining Palm as it tries to break out with new products against its better-financed competitors. Last week Palm introduced a 2.5-pound laptop computer called the Foleo that Palm's co-founder, Jeff Hawkins, said would serve as a large-screen peripheral for the company's Treo smartphone and Windows Mobile devices. The introduction was greeted with skepticism by industry analysts who said that the system would find only niche market acceptance because most smartphone owners already have portable computers.</p>
        <p>Under the terms of the deal, Elevation will purchase $325 million of a new series of convertible preferred stock. The conversion price will be $8.50 a share. Palm will take on about $400 million in debt to pay out the dividend to shareholders. The deal is subject to shareholder approval. If completed, Eric Benhamou and D. Scott Mercer, two current board members, will step down to make room for Mr. Anderson and Mr. McNamee.</p>
        <p>Morgan Stanley is serving as financial adviser to Palm. Houlihan Lokey Howard &amp; Zukin Advisory Services Inc. provided a fairness opinion to Palm, and JPMorgan is acting as financial adviser to Elevation. The Wilson Sonsini Goodrich &amp; Rosati Professional Corporation is serving as outside counsel to Palm, and Simpson Thacher &amp; Bartlett is acting as legal adviser to Elevation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
