<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Mientkiewicz Out, Yankees Fill In Missing Pieces</title>
    <meta content="04pins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/sports/baseball/04pins.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852194"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Mientkiewicz, Doug</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cashman, Brian</person>
        <person class="online_producer">DeSalvo, Matt</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Igawa, Kei</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E5DD1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Mientkiewicz Out, Yankees Fill In Missing Pieces</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Mientkiewicz Out, Yankees Fill in Missing Pieces</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, June 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Doug Mientkiewicz was driven home by his wife on Sunday. He was a wounded passenger, having sustained a concussion, a neck sprain and a fractured bone in his right wrist on Saturday in a collision at Fenway Park. From a baseball standpoint, the wrist injury is the most serious, and it will keep him out a minimum of six weeks.</p>
        <p>''He's a grinder, and he's obviously a major help on the defensive side,'' Yankees General Manager Brian Cashman said. ''We'll miss him.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Doug Mientkiewicz’s placement on the disabled list will allow the Yankees to start Matt DeSalvo on Monday in Chicago, giving Kei Igawa more time in the minors to smooth his mechanics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Doug Mientkiewicz was driven home by his wife on Sunday. He was a wounded passenger, having sustained a concussion, a neck sprain and a fractured bone in his right wrist on Saturday in a collision at Fenway Park. From a baseball standpoint, the wrist injury is the most serious, and it will keep him out a minimum of six weeks.</p>
        <p>''He's a grinder, and he's obviously a major help on the defensive side,'' Yankees General Manager Brian Cashman said. ''We'll miss him.''</p>
        <p>In Mientkiewicz's absence, his teammates poked fun at him. One option to see time at first base is Johnny Damon, but Damon said he was not sure how much help Mientkiewicz could give him.</p>
        <p>''We'll have to make sure that his memory is good,'' Damon said.</p>
        <p>Mientkiewicz's placement on the disabled list will allow the Yankees to start Matt DeSalvo in place of Roger Clemens on Monday in Chicago, giving Kei Igawa more time in the minors to smooth his mechanics. DeSalvo, who was sent back to Class AAA Scranton/Wilkes-Barre on Friday, could not have rejoined the team without a spot opening up as the result of an injury.</p>
        <p>Igawa pitched seven innings for Scranton in Rochester on Sunday, and while he pitched well, allowing two earned runs with nine strikeouts, he told reporters that he needed another start or two in the minors. Cashman said the Yankees were optimistic that Igawa could help, eventually.</p>
        <p>''So far, so good,'' Cashman said. ''He's making the progress we've hoped for.''</p>
        <p>Clemens reported Sunday to the Yankees' complex in Tampa, Fla., where he was examined by the team doctor Andrew Miller. Clemens will undergo a magnetic resonance imaging exam on Monday to see if his groin is simply fatigued, as he told the team, or more seriously damaged.</p>
        <p>For now, the Yankees and Clemens are projecting his first appearance to be Saturday at home against the Pittsburgh Pirates, a team he defeated five times in six decisions over the past three years.</p>
        <p>''Everyone is being optimistic and looking toward the obvious date of next Saturday,'' Clemens's agent, Randy Hendricks, said in an e-mail message. ''I think the results of the M.R.I., plus how Roger feels this week, will determine whether he starts next Saturday.''</p>
        <p>Clemens does not begin collecting his prorated $28 million salary until the Yankees add him to the major league roster. He is currently on a minor league deal.</p>
        <p>''I want to have a healthy Roger Clemens, when he's ready to assist the team, because we still have a shot,'' Cashman said. ''We feel he could have a big impact for us. But were there any guarantees or under-the-table promises made? No.''</p>
        <p>The loss of Mientkiewicz is bad news for the pitching staff. Mientkiewicz was batting only .226, but he had played much better defense than Josh Phelps, who, Manager Joe Torre said, will become the regular first baseman.</p>
        <p>Damon remains the regular designated hitter with Jason Giambi on the disabled list and Melky Cabrera now playing center, but he is taking grounders at first base and has begun learning the position from the bench coach Don Mattingly.</p>
        <p>''There will be a lot of stuff we can do,'' Mattingly said. ''You can't build it in a day. He's not going to eat steak right away; we're going to give him some baby formula first.''</p>
        <p>Damon's weak arm will not be such a liability at first base, and as a left-hander he will have a natural throw to second base, because he will not have to turn his body. He played first base in Little League and once last season. He said his athleticism would help him.</p>
        <p>''I just have to look at it as a positive thing that possibly can help extend my career,'' said Damon, who is 33. ''As a ballplayer you always want to be well-rounded. This gives me an opportunity, gives me a challenge to try to be a better all-around player. I'm actually pretty excited about it.''</p>
        <p>Torre said his first option off the bench to replace Phelps during a game was Miguel Cairo, who has played 34 games there in his career. But Cairo is strictly a bench player, and if Phelps does not start -- perhaps during the Yankees' six remaining games in National League parks, where the D.H. is not used -- Damon could start at first.</p>
        <p>As for outside options, the Yankees appear to have no interest in the massive contract of Todd Helton of the Colorado Rockies. They are more interested in exploring the idea of a trade for Mark Teixeira of the Texas Rangers, but the Rangers want premium pitching prospects and the asking price would seem likely to drop as the July 31 trading deadline approaches.</p>
        <p>The Yankees effectively used that strategy last season to land Bobby Abreu from the Philadelphia Phillies on July 30, without trading a significant prospect.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
