<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In or Out of Eden, One Man's Unicorn May Be Another's Apatosaurus</title>
    <meta content="04conn" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/arts/04conn.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852101"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CONNECTIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Connections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Creationism and Intelligent Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Creationism and Intelligent Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E6DF1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1319" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In or Out of Eden, One Man's Unicorn May Be Another's Apatosaurus</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In or Out of Eden, One Man’s Unicorn May Be Another’s Apatosaurus</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD ROTHSTEIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are some extraordinary fossils at the new Creation Museum, which opened last week in Petersburg, Ky., including one that preserves a perch with a half-eaten herring in its mouth. And there are some extraordinary creatures at the American Museum of Natural History in Manhattan, in a new show that also opened last week, including a life-size unicorn, a gold griffin and not a few dragons.</p>
        <p>What a strange looking-glass world these exhibitions create: real creatures in a museum devoted to religious ideas, and mythological creatures in a museum devoted to scientific ideas. The contrast is particularly haunting at a time when conflicts between reason and faith, science and religion, keep erupting. Old debates about Darwin and biblical truth persist. Presidential candidates are asked about their faith in evolution. And ''Inherit the Wind'' -- a 1955 play about a 1925 trial about the right to teach Darwin's 1859 theory -- is revived on Broadway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Real and mythological creatures mingle in the strange looking-glass world of two new museum exhibitions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are some extraordinary fossils at the new Creation Museum, which opened last week in Petersburg, Ky., including one that preserves a perch with a half-eaten herring in its mouth. And there are some extraordinary creatures at the American Museum of Natural History in Manhattan, in a new show that also opened last week, including a life-size unicorn, a gold griffin and not a few dragons.</p>
        <p>What a strange looking-glass world these exhibitions create: real creatures in a museum devoted to religious ideas, and mythological creatures in a museum devoted to scientific ideas. The contrast is particularly haunting at a time when conflicts between reason and faith, science and religion, keep erupting. Old debates about Darwin and biblical truth persist. Presidential candidates are asked about their faith in evolution. And ''Inherit the Wind'' -- a 1955 play about a 1925 trial about the right to teach Darwin's 1859 theory -- is revived on Broadway.</p>
        <p>Consider these two exhibitions. The Creation Museum, built by a Christian ministry called Answers in Genesis, displays models of dinosaurs, fossils and a few live animals, all put in service to the idea that Genesis is literally true, that the Earth was created in six days, and even the most ''ancient'' fossil would date from the time of Noah's flood, not even 6,000 years ago. Natural objects are used to argue for the truth of what is, for nonbelievers, a mythological vision.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, at the Museum of Natural History's new exhibition of ''Mythic Creatures,'' the reverse is true: Mythological beings are used to demonstrate truths about the natural world. The exhibition suggests that many fantastical creatures were imaginative attempts to make sense of the enormous mastodon and mammoth fossils found by ancient cultures. The giant, the cyclops, the griffin: all were the results of efforts to flesh out the bones and relics of extinct species.</p>
        <p>Even mythological creatures, then, reflect scientific ambitions: How do we make sense of evidence? What are these giant bones, these relics of animals we have never seen? The creators of the griffin -- half eagle, half lion -- were early paleontologists who didn't quite have their genuses straight and put the fossilized bones in the wrong place. In this, a scientist would argue, they resemble creationists: figures who, in trying to make sense of the world, ignore the findings of science to dwell in an imaginary realm where they put everything together according to an alien mold.</p>
        <p>But creationists would say that scientists are making this same error: They may have put the fossil bones together more plausibly but have then forged their own mythic universe in which one species turns into another over millions of years, and human intelligence arises out of haphazard chance. And it is worth recalling that Darwin's theory was once so shocking and so threatening (even for its author) that it might as well have seemed to have been exhaled by one of those dragons now on display in New York.</p>
        <p>These are deeply held convictions, and there must be a way to explore their contrasts with more light and less heat than has been evident so far. But it wouldn't be by simply accepting a symmetrical opposition, saying, perhaps, that one man's griffin is another's Apatosaurus. Neither is it possible simply to dismiss the opposition as if it were something alien and inhumane, as if there were no issues worth exploring: Science, after all, itself evolved out of faith and not always in rebellion to it.</p>
        <p>That ill-tempered ridicule is all too apparent in ''Inherit the Wind,'' which, on revisiting, almost has the air of agitprop (until it tries to backpedal at the very end). The Clarence Darrow-like lawyer, defending an innocent schoolteacher, is making a virtuous stand for independent thought against a town full of ignorant, Bible-thumping yahoos. The play's authors -- Jerome Lawrence and Robert E. Lee -- give their fictional town of Hillsboro a villainous fire-and-brimstone preacher, a kangaroo courtroom and a prosecutor who is a crude version of William Jennings Bryan. The play almost solicits audience jeers.</p>
        <p>Yet the actual 1925 Scopes trial is far more interesting. The full transcript is considered so helpful to the fundamentalist cause that it is sold at the Creation Museum bookshop and is published by a religious college named after Bryan in the town where the trial took place. As for the trial itself, it was partly the result of an advertisement made by the American Civil Liberties Union, seeking a test case to challenge the Butler Act, which prohibited the teaching of evolution in Tennessee. A group of Dayton, Tenn., leaders thought this would be a terrific event to spur local commerce, so they solicited the friendly participation of John Thomas Scopes himself, who was never jailed as the character is in the play.</p>
        <p>Bryan offered to pay Scopes's fine if he was found guilty. And Darrow, far from being met as a pariah by the town like the lawyer in the play, was given a warm public welcome. His challenge to the banner draped outside the court -- ''Read Your Bible'' -- actually succeeded and was not dismissed as in the play. And because his main focus was on an appeal that might declare the Butler Act unconstitutional, he even urged the jury to find his client guilty.</p>
        <p>The play ignores such complications, distorts arguments, associates religious belief with meanness: all of which is unnecessary since the confrontation would be more powerful if more realistically engaged. But the temptation to imitate the spirit of ''Inherit the Wind'' is now embraced by some who have angrily protested the Creation Museum, saying it presents an imminent danger with its seductive displays and views, that it deserves the treatment and scorn the play gave to Dayton, or perhaps that the play's religious believers gave to its science teacher.</p>
        <p>But the museum is forthright about its principles. It also compares its views to evolutionary theory, claiming to agree on facts but disagree on interpretation. The museum seems to keep submitting its assertions of faith to scientific scrutiny, though the impulse is more notable than its success.</p>
        <p>Why these invocations of evidence and plausibility? Partly because if creationist ideas get a scientific imprimatur, they could be taught in schools. But it is also because if you sincerely believe in creation, it really seems as incontrovertible as any science. And there are many scientists who maintain a rigorous approach to understanding scientific processes while asserting that in speculative questions science has nothing to say and Genesis does. I spoke with one cell biologist on the ministry's staff who said he taught in a medical school for more than 30 years without these two perspectives ever clashing.</p>
        <p>But creationism is also radically unlike a scientific theory; it never challenges its own premises. The museum even condemns such attempts, attacking the Enlightenment philosophers who helped establish modern science. The questioning of biblical truth, the museum suggests, leads to social and intellectual dissolution. The entire enterprise is fragile, vulnerable to skeptical pressure. That is because it is a faith, not a science.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately some Darwinian theorists leave a similar impression about their own enterprise when they bristle at dissent or doubt. But the challenge made by faith to science should actually help science be less like faith, more prepared to scrutinize its own assumptions.</p>
        <p>How then can these realms continue to coexist, as the world keeps showing us they will and must? It isn't always easy to tell when bones are being put together properly and when are we forcing them in place to fit our visions of what the world should or could be.</p>
        <p>There are no simple answers, which is why, despite its own simple answers, I liked going to the Creation Museum, if only to try to understand the nature of mythic creatures, even when they still walk the earth.</p>
        <p>Connections, a critic's perspective on arts and ideas, appears every other Monday.</p>
        <p>CONNECTIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
