<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Upper East Side, Two Seek Vacated Assembly Seat</title>
    <meta content="04assembly" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852169"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EFDE1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="610" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Upper East Side, Two Seek Vacated Assembly Seat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Upper East Side was once the reliable foothold of the liberal Republican politician. It was the home of John V. Lindsay and, most recently, State Senator Roy M. Goodman. But in the last decade, the neighborhood has become increasingly Democratic, and Republican officeholders have become fixtures of the past.</p>
        <p>But the Republicans are seeking to change that in a special election tomorrow to fill the Assembly seat vacated by Alexander B. Grannis, commonly known as Pete, a longtime Democratic incumbent who recently became commissioner of the State Department of Environmental Conservation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Upper East Side was once the reliable foothold of the liberal Republican politician. It was the home of John V. Lindsay and, most recently, State Senator Roy M. Goodman. But in the last decade, the neighborhood has become increasingly Democratic, and Republican officeholders have become fixtures of the past.</p>
        <p>But the Republicans are seeking to change that in a special election tomorrow to fill the Assembly seat vacated by Alexander B. Grannis, commonly known as Pete, a longtime Democratic incumbent who recently became commissioner of the State Department of Environmental Conservation.</p>
        <p>In tomorrow's race, the Republicans have selected Gregory Camp, a candidate who they believe can best appeal to the large number of Democrats and independent voters in the 65th Assembly District, which largely includes the area east of Second Avenue between East 60th and East 90th Streets, as well as Roosevelt Island.</p>
        <p>Mr. Camp, 45, is a former Manhattan assistant district attorney who most recently served as deputy director of the State Division of Criminal Justice Services. He is also a decidedly liberal Republican who supports gun control measures, abortion rights and same-sex marriage. In last year's election for governor, he backed Eliot Spitzer, the Democrat.</p>
        <p>The Democratic candidate is Micah Z. Kellner, 28, a former aide to United States Representative Carolyn B. Maloney who currently works as a community liaison for the New York City comptroller, William C. Thompson Jr.</p>
        <p>One striking characteristic of the race is that both candidates have fairly similar views on the major issues in the district. For example, both men have expressed strong reservations about a plan to reactivate a marine waste transfer station on the East River at 91st Street, near the Asphalt Green athletic center. Both say it would create more pollution in an area with many children and elderly residents.</p>
        <p>''Every time you process garbage, particles come up, and they can spread in a radius of 10 blocks,'' Mr. Camp said. ''There are kids there playing in playgrounds within that radius. And a lot of elderly and health-compromised people live in the densely populated area around the transfer station.''</p>
        <p>And both speak passionately about the need to build new schools in the area to accommodate the growth in population. ''We are experiencing a population boom in the district,'' Mr. Kellner said, ''and need schools at all levels, but particularly we need a new grammar school and new middle school.''</p>
        <p>Even their fund-raising totals have been roughly similar. By their own accounts, Mr. Kellner raised more than $90,000 and Mr. Camp about $105,000.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kellner has been endorsed by nearly all Manhattan Democratic officials. (United States Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton is to endorse him today.) And since registered Democrats outnumber Republicans in the district three to one, those officials give the edge to Mr. Kellner.</p>
        <p>Despite so much agreement on issues, each candidate says he has an advantage in experience over his opponent.</p>
        <p>''I have a background of grass-roots community activism,'' Mr. Kellner said. ''I was a housing specialist for Congresswoman Maloney, and I know the importance of affordable housing. I've been involved in community issues. My opponent doesn't really have that much community involvement.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Camp has been endorsed by Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg and is preferred by Citizens Union, the civic group. He said that voters should choose him because he offers ''commitment, experience and independence.''</p>
        <p>He described himself as ''a Republican who believes in a simpler tax structure, but also in certain strong criminal justice initiatives, like expanding the DNA database.''</p>
        <p>''I like being a bit of an iconoclast,'' he said. ''I want to be seen as someone who thinks carefully about issues.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
