<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Walls of Art for Everyone, but Made by Not Just Anyone</title>
    <meta content="04citywide" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/nyregion/04citywide.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852174"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CITYWIDE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Graffiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Graffiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EEDE1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1383" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Walls of Art for Everyone, but Made by Not Just Anyone</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Walls of Art for Everyone, but Made by Not Just Anyone</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID GONZALEZ</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sticky-sweet smell of spray paint hung in the hot air as members of Tats Cru covered a rooftop wall with crazy kinetic letters. They were far from prying eyes, though not because they were doing anything illegal. In fact, the man whose business occupied the football-field-size building was their patron, allowing them and other graffiti artists to use the roof as their own open-air atelier. Here among the drab warehouses of the Hunts Point Cooperative Market, they had the privacy to try out new designs, repainting and refining until they were pleased with the results.</p>
        <p>Privacy might seem like an odd desire for these professional graffiti muralists whose works adorn everything from bodegas and medical vans to playgrounds and public schools. But they have been serious about controlling their work ever since a number of their aerosol tableaus were photographed -- without their permission -- for a book and an exhibit on the murals of New York City.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Aggrieved graffiti artists have joined to seek a settlement from a photographer who included images of their murals in his book without their permission.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The sticky-sweet smell of spray paint hung in the hot air as members of Tats Cru covered a rooftop wall with crazy kinetic letters. They were far from prying eyes, though not because they were doing anything illegal. In fact, the man whose business occupied the football-field-size building was their patron, allowing them and other graffiti artists to use the roof as their own open-air atelier. Here among the drab warehouses of the Hunts Point Cooperative Market, they had the privacy to try out new designs, repainting and refining until they were pleased with the results.</p>
        <p>Privacy might seem like an odd desire for these professional graffiti muralists whose works adorn everything from bodegas and medical vans to playgrounds and public schools. But they have been serious about controlling their work ever since a number of their aerosol tableaus were photographed -- without their permission -- for a book and an exhibit on the murals of New York City.</p>
        <p>Tats Cru and a dozen other similarly aggrieved artists have joined to seek a settlement from Peter Rosenstein, a photographer who spent more than a decade shooting pictures of their work and included the photos in his book, ''Tattooed Walls.'' As a result of the artists' complaints, the University Press of Mississippi, the publisher, removed the book from its catalog a month after its release last year.</p>
        <p>Hector Nazario, a founding member of the group who goes by the name of Nicer, said they are often contacted for releases by film crews when their murals pop up in a background shot. He said ''Law &amp; Order,'' which films all over the city, is a frequent caller.</p>
        <p>''Their production people research the images,'' he said, and they know to seek permission from the artists. ''We're in the business of living off our art. We usually try to get money or a credit, which adds up to money later on.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Rosenstein -- a full-time periodontist -- said he never thought of getting permission to use the photographs. He said he intended only to document murals he liked by artists he thought were underappreciated.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to bond with them and become friends with them,'' he said of the artists. ''I really like these guys.''</p>
        <p>But he said he could not locate many of the artists, even though some of the murals are clearly marked with names and phone numbers -- and a little circled ''c'' indicating copyright protection. In the case of one mural by Tats Cru, it is necessary to walk past the group's brightly painted Bronx studio to photograph the work.</p>
        <p>''A lot of these photographers think they are intrepid explorers discovering these guys in the inner city, making crazy statements like they are going to take them out of the ghetto,'' said Stacey Richman, a lawyer representing Tats Cru and the other muralists. ''But these guys are acclaimed artists in their own right. Just put their names into any search engine. They are world-renowned. They've lectured at M.I.T. and exhibited at the Smithsonian.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Rosenstein said that he did not seek permission from the artists because the murals were in public places, and that publishing the photographs was covered under fair use provisions of copyright law, which allow images to be used to illustrate art criticism and reviews.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for the artists disagree, saying that his book was a thinly researched collection and that his photographic prints, which were exhibited at a gallery show in Chelsea, were not covered by fair use provisions.</p>
        <p>The artists insist that just because their murals, painted on commission or with the landlord's permission, are out for anyone to enjoy, that does not mean others can do whatever they want with them. Obtaining releases, copyright experts said, could help protect authors and photographers from challenges to publication.</p>
        <p>Jane Ginsburg, a professor of intellectual property law at Columbia University, said that creative works are automatically protected regardless of where they are displayed. The extent of protection, she said, varied depending on whether a piece was registered with the federal copyright office at the time of the alleged infringement. If it was registered, current laws allow artists to recover legal fees and statutory damages of up to $30,000, or more if the infringement was willful.</p>
        <p>Without the registration, a person accused of infringing could skirt those penalties, she said. ''The damages in that case would correspond to the sales you lost or the profits the other person made, and that is not always so easy to prove.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Rosenstein said he made no money from his project. And he insisted that he started taking pictures of murals in the 1990s, not for profit, but because he respected the artists.</p>
        <p>Several artists whose work wound up in the book, however, felt decidedly disrespected, since Dr. Rosenstein did not seek them out to talk about the project.</p>
        <p>Sandra Fabara, a graffiti artist known as Lady Pink, first saw a copy of the book last summer and alerted others. She wondered why Dr. Rosenstein took it upon himself to decide which of her works deserved being showcased without regard to her thoughts on the matter. She is also angry that some of the photographs are distorted or have colors that are slightly off.</p>
        <p>''If you are a struggling artist, we feel a kinship with you, and we'll help you out and let you take pictures,'' she said. ''I mean, we are generous and shameless self-promoters.'' But she added: ''We want respect, too. But he could not be bothered. Was it fear or snobbishness?''</p>
        <p>Legalities aside, some artists have objected to the book because they said it contains inaccuracies. They said some murals were misidentified, misinterpreted or misattributed. They are also puzzled that a book that is primarily focused on edgy graffiti would include large-scale community murals -- many with carefully researched political and social themes that were done in close collaboration with local residents.</p>
        <p>''Our work is about social change,'' said Amy Sananman, the executive director of Groundswell, a community mural group. Her work was also included in the book without permission. ''For us, the whole purpose of doing this is to give voice to people and let them express themselves in public. So it is important the way their work is characterized.'' Groundswell recently reached a settlement with Dr. Rosenstein; both parties declined to describe the settlement terms.</p>
        <p>Maria Dominguez was especially riled by the book's reducing some works -- including one of hers -- to ''decorative murals'' done by an anonymous ''local artist.'' She has created many pieces of public art, including a recent stained glass installation at a subway station in Brooklyn. She said it was important for artists to control how their work was displayed. She spoke from bitter experience: In 1987, a mural of dancers she painted with schoolchildren on the Lower East Side appeared without permission in Playboy magazine.</p>
        <p>''Does this make sense that they used this picture of something created by some poor kids from the community?'' she said. ''But nothing happened, since I only had a volunteer lawyer. I think he took the magazine and kept it.''</p>
        <p>For some of the more personal, playful walls done by these urban muralists, especially those who started as graffiti writers, photographs are the only record of their work. Mr. Nazario of Tats Cru said that made it even more important that he and his partners kept control over who photographs their work and how it is used.</p>
        <p>''Graffiti artists do what we do to photograph it,'' he said, taking a break from the wall he and his colleagues were painting for their personal portfolio on the Hunts Point rooftop. ''You're accustomed to feeling this is never going to last forever. So we photograph them for our archives.''</p>
        <p>Behind him, his colleagues laid down intricate lines of rich color, sweating and squinting in the searing heat. They worked in near silence, the only noise coming from the hiss and rattle of spray paint cans and the roar of jets taking off from La Guardia Airport.</p>
        <p>''In public you run into knuckleheads who think you don't have a brain,'' he said. ''But here we can work until we're ready to show it. Yo, we're grown men, and we realize if anyone is going to control our images it has to be us. Full control.''</p>
        <p>CITYWIDE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
