<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Just Aren't Themselves as They Let a Series Slip Away</title>
    <meta content="04mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/sports/baseball/04mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852193"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5DD1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Just Aren't Themselves as They Let a Series Slip Away</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pérez Has a Bad Day and Mets Lose</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was nothing unusual about the message scrawled on the dry-erase board that greeted players walking into the Mets' clubhouse yesterday morning. ''Regular Day, 1:10 p.m.,'' it read, and the team acted accordingly. Oliver Pérez balanced an orange pillow atop his head. Rubén Gotay and José Reyes clamored for autographs from a champion boxer. Ben Johnson downed a fluorescent-green drink that he said tasted like ''lemon-lime Tums.''</p>
        <p>Then their plans for a regular day were ruined when they lost to the Arizona Diamondbacks, 4-1, in decidedly nonregular fashion at Shea Stadium. Suffering from a rare bout of inconsistency, Pérez walked the leadoff hitter in three consecutive innings, allowing two to score, and lost for the first time in four weeks. The Mets committed an error for the first time in 13 games, an errant throw by Reyes in the eighth, missing out on a chance to set the franchise record.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oliver Pérez walked the leadoff hitter in three consecutive innings and allowed two of them to score while Arizona’s Doug Davis shut down the Mets’ lineup.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There was nothing unusual about the message scrawled on the dry-erase board that greeted players walking into the Mets' clubhouse yesterday morning. ''Regular Day, 1:10 p.m.,'' it read, and the team acted accordingly. Oliver Pérez balanced an orange pillow atop his head. Rubén Gotay and José Reyes clamored for autographs from a champion boxer. Ben Johnson downed a fluorescent-green drink that he said tasted like ''lemon-lime Tums.''</p>
        <p>Then their plans for a regular day were ruined when they lost to the Arizona Diamondbacks, 4-1, in decidedly nonregular fashion at Shea Stadium. Suffering from a rare bout of inconsistency, Pérez walked the leadoff hitter in three consecutive innings, allowing two to score, and lost for the first time in four weeks. The Mets committed an error for the first time in 13 games, an errant throw by Reyes in the eighth, missing out on a chance to set the franchise record.</p>
        <p>Their reserves, who have propped up the team during this injury-laden stretch, could not shoulder the load, and the Mets lost a series to an out-of-division team for the first time in nine such series.</p>
        <p>Of all the things that did not go according to plan yesterday, perhaps the least surprising was that the Mets (35-20) are starting to feel the strain of missing their starting outfield -- Moises Alou, Shawn Green and Carlos Beltrán, who are out with injuries. Since Alou strained his left quadriceps May 12, the Mets' run production has dropped by an average of nearly a run a game, to 4.3 from 5.17. In their eight games without Green (broken right foot), they have averaged 3.88 runs.</p>
        <p>''The guys out there have done great, but you're not going to replace a Carlos Beltrán, who does everything exceptionally well,'' said David Wright, who had one of the Mets' six hits against Arizona starter Doug Davis. ''That type of production you're not going to get, no matter how good the bench is playing. To be the team we want to be, we have to have our horses back.''</p>
        <p>Alou and Green could return next weekend in Detroit, and Beltrán, bothered by a bruised right knee he injured Thursday, is aiming to return tomorrow against Philadelphia. Beltrán was available to pinch-hit yesterday, and he said he was sure that today's day off would help him regain strength. But there is also the chance that the switch-hitting Beltrán, who said his knee hurt when he batted right-handed, may sit out with the left-hander Jamie Moyer scheduled to pitch for the Phillies.</p>
        <p>''With Alou out of the lineup and myself, it's a different ball club for sure,'' Beltrán said. ''But that doesn't mean that we're not capable of winning without us.''</p>
        <p>Exhibit A: On Saturday, with five backups in the lineup, the Mets scored seven runs against Arizona and ended the Diamondbacks' eight-game winning streak. Yesterday, two fill-ins, Carlos Gómez and Johnson, combined for three hits (Gómez had two), while the Mets' Nos. 3-4-5 hitters -- Wright, Carlos Delgado and Paul Lo Duca -- went 1 for 10.</p>
        <p>Against Davis, like Pérez a left-hander who superstitiously skips over foul lines, the Mets scored their only run on Delgado's groundout in the sixth, and they truly threatened only once, in the eighth, when they loaded the bases with two outs. Up came Damion Easley, who a month ago hit a three-run homer to fuel a six-run ninth in Arizona.</p>
        <p>Facing Tony Peña, Easley waited out two balls before ripping a sharp grounder down the third-base line that was barely foul. On Peña's next pitch, another two-seam fastball, Easley grounded out to third.</p>
        <p>''I got the count I wanted, I got the pitch I wanted, but I just hit it foul,'' Easley said.</p>
        <p>No one considered blaming Easley for not coming through; he, like so many other of the Mets' lower-profile players, has delivered in clutch situations throughout the season. The frustrating thing, a few players said, was that they felt Pérez minimized damage and pitched well enough to win.</p>
        <p>As it was, Pérez pitched at least seven innings for a career-high fifth consecutive start, and he needed only 42 pitches to retire the minimum number of hitters through four innings.</p>
        <p>In the fifth, he allowed a leadoff walk to Mark Reynolds. The next batter, Scott Hairston, lashed a sharp single to left for Arizona's first hit of the game. A ground-rule double to right-center by Carlos Quentin drove in Reynolds, and Pérez hit Chris Snyder to load the bases with no outs.</p>
        <p>Pérez got Alberto Callaspo to ground into a double play that brought in the Diamondbacks' second run, but he walked Eric Byrnes on five pitches to lead off the sixth. A double by Conor Jackson and a sacrifice fly by Orlando Hudson extended Arizona's lead to 3-0.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes, you're going to walk too many guys, and you just have to try to get out of the inning as fast as you can,'' said Pérez, who walked three over all.</p>
        <p>Finishing the thought, he repeated the theme of the day, saying, ''Sometimes, these things happen.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Pedro Martínez will pitch off a mound tomorrow in Port St. Lucie, Fla., for the first time since having off-season surgery on his right shoulder. The start of the Mets' game July 1 in Philadelphia has been changed to 8:09 p.m. from 1:35 p.m. for ESPN. The Mets released the veteran right-hander Chan Ho Park. Park was 4-4 with a 5.57 earned run average for Class AAA New Orleans. He made one start for the Mets, allowing seven runs in four innings against Florida on April 30.  Miguel Cotto, the World Boxing Association welterweight champion, threw out the ceremonial first pitch to his Puerto Rican countryman Carlos Beltrán. Cotto will fight Zab Judah on Saturday at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
