<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Braves' Cox Is in Shouting Distance Of History</title>
    <meta content="04braves" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/sports/baseball/04braves.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852192"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cox, Bobby</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Piniella, Lou</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McGraw, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E5DD1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1371" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Braves' Cox Is in Shouting Distance Of History</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">All Over but the Shouting</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE; Tyler Kepner contributed reporting from Toronto and Michael S. Schmidt from New York.</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, June 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bobby Cox remained one ejection shy Sunday of tying John McGraw for a dubious distinction and unofficial baseball record. But Lou Piniella showed again Saturday that he has no current equal for flamboyant temper tantrums that often bring banishment by umpires.</p>
        <p>The two veteran managers were at Wrigley Field for a three-game series between Cox's Braves and Piniella's Cubs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bobby Cox remained one ejection shy Sunday of tying John McGraw for a dubious distinction and unofficial baseball record.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bobby Cox remained one ejection shy Sunday of tying John McGraw for a dubious distinction and unofficial baseball record. But Lou Piniella showed again Saturday that he has no current equal for flamboyant temper tantrums that often bring banishment by umpires.</p>
        <p>The two veteran managers were at Wrigley Field for a three-game series between Cox's Braves and Piniella's Cubs.</p>
        <p>The Cubs won, 10-1, on Sunday, hitting three home runs to avoid a sweep and end a six-game losing streak.</p>
        <p>Piniella avoided ejection because he stayed in the clubhouse under indefinite suspension for Saturday's ejection after he shouted, threw his hat, kicked dirt on the third-base umpire, Mark Wegner, and repeatedly made bodily contact with him during a seven-minute rant.</p>
        <p>Cheering fans threw garbage onto the grass from over the ivy-covered brick walls as Piniella argued after the Cubs' Ángel Pagán was called out trying to steal third base. Later, after viewing videotape, Piniella said the umpire was right.</p>
        <p>Piniella was also fined an undisclosed amount by Bob Watson, the vice president for on-field operations for Major League Baseball. ''It was a terrible display of disrespect,'' the umpiring crew chief, Bruce Froemming, told a pool reporter Saturday.</p>
        <p>Alan Trammell, a Cubs coach, filled in Sunday for Piniella, who is to meet Monday with John McHale Jr., Major League Baseball's vice president for administration. It was the 73rd ejection of Piniella's career, tying him with St. Louis Cardinals Manager Tony La Russa for seventh place.</p>
        <p>Cox has 130 ejections, one behind McGraw, who had 131 as a player and a manager. He is best remembered for managing the New York Giants from 1902 to 1932.</p>
        <p>Cox is in his 22nd year managing the Atlanta Braves, and he also managed the Toronto Blue Jays for four seasons, He already holds the record for managerial ejections; McGraw was ousted 14 times as a player. Cox, who played the infield for the Yankees in 1968 and '69, was never ejected as a player.</p>
        <p>Cox' total does not include World Series ejections in 1992 and 1996.</p>
        <p>As with pitching motions and batting stances, every manager his own arguing style. Bob Davidson, a veteran umpire who has ejected Cox five times, more than any other umpire, said he did not mind Cox'.</p>
        <p>He said he liked Cox and enjoyed working his games. ''He's not a real vicious man by any means,'' Davidson said last week at Shea Stadium. ''He's not a Lou Piniella as far as throwing bases and stuff. If I was a ballplayer, I'd want to play for Bobby Cox. He backs his players 150 percent.''</p>
        <p>That seems to be the consensus among umpires as well as players like pitcher Tom Glavine and infielder Julio Franco of the Mets, each of whom played for Cox in Atlanta. They spoke about him last week in interviews at Shea.</p>
        <p>Cox argues about balls and strikes more than some managers, which annoys umpires. ''He's always ready to step up, fight for and defend his guys,'' Glavine said.</p>
        <p>Franco, who hopes to manage in the majors, added: ''I loved playing for him. He knows how to handle people.''</p>
        <p>Ryan Klesko of the Giants, another former Brave, said at Shea that Cox ''is a big strike-zone guy.''</p>
        <p>''Umpires don't like that, especially because you can't see the corners from the dugout,'' Klesko said.</p>
        <p>But Tim Hudson, a Braves pitcher, said Sunday, ''If you have a manager that's passive and sits in the dugout and does nothing, those are the guys players don't like to play for.''</p>
        <p>John Smoltz, the veteran Atlanta pitcher, called Cox' approach toward the ejection record ''much ado about nothing.''</p>
        <p>Cox was unenthused but cooperative when asked recently to discuss the prospect of exceeding McGraw in ejections. ''It's nothing to be proud of,'' Cox said. ''I've managed a long time, and that's what happened.''</p>
        <p>In 26 years, Cox also has 2,203 victories, fourth behind Connie Mack (3,731), McGraw (2,763) and La Russa (2,321).</p>
        <p>Cox, who turned 66 on May 21, was interviewed last month in the dugout at Fenway Park three hours before a game. Rain was falling hard.</p>
        <p>He sat alone on a bench, reading a newspaper, smoking a big cigar, watching the grass grow and wondering why anyone would keep ejection totals. They are not officially listed by Major League Baseball because ejections have not been recorded consistently throughout baseball history.</p>
        <p>They are tabulated by David Vincent of the Society for American Baseball Research. Referring to umpires in general, Cox said: ''I like umpires. I'd do anything for them. They're good guys. But you get caught up in the game. Something goes wrong, you express it. That's all. Simple.''</p>
        <p>Randy Marsh, an umpire who works on a crew with Davidson, said last week at Shea that Cox is ''like a Jekyll and Hyde.''</p>
        <p>''Off the field, they say he's the nicest guy in the world,'' Marsh said. ''On the field, he's always right -- or the thinks he's always right.''</p>
        <p>Marsh and Froemming have each ejected Cox three times. Froemming said that Cox might get thrown out of a game and meet the umpires in the parking lot afterward -- in good spirits.</p>
        <p>''He's walking to his car and he says 'Hey, how ya doing? See ya tomorrow,' '' Froemming said last week in a telephone interview from Milwaukee. ''It's like the clouds blew over. Hard to believe, but true.''</p>
        <p>As for what Cox says during arguments, Froemming chuckled and said, ''He just flips out.''</p>
        <p>Has Cox ever apologized to umpires for things he has said? ''I have, yeah,'' Cox said. '' 'Sorry. I didn't mean it.' Even if they're wrong, you've still got to respect their profession.''</p>
        <p>Has he ever been an umpire himself? Yes, Cox said. In the 1950s, he earned gasoline money as a high school baseball player in Selma, Calif., by umpiring in Little League and the Babe Ruth League for $3 and $5 a game.</p>
        <p>''It's a tough job,'' Cox said. ''It's hard. I know that. That's why I respect them so much. They get 99 percent of the calls right. They can only take so much. They're going to argue back with you. Nothing wrong with that either. I would if I was an umpire.''</p>
        <p>Did he ever eject a coach or manager? ''No, no,'' Cox said. ''We had probably 1,200 people in the entire town, so you knew everybody.''</p>
        <p>Cox also said that he had never intentionally tried to get ejected to motivate his team. Some managers have.</p>
        <p>One of them might have been Piniella on Saturday.</p>
        <p>On Friday, when reporters asked why he had not been ejected this season, Piniella said he had told umpires in the past to prepare to eject him. ''I'm sure I'll get kicked out soon,'' Piniella said Friday. ''It will happen. Believe me.''</p>
        <p>Compared to other recent Cubs' news, Piniella's ejection was not so serious or damaging. On Friday, pitcher Carlos Zambrano and catcher Michael Barrett fought twice, first in the dugout, later in the clubhouse, leaving Barrett with cuts and bruises on his face. After the game, Piniella expressed anger at how the Cubs were performing.</p>
        <p>Speaking of motivation, Yankees Manager Joe Torre recalled last week in Toronto that he knew Froemming from playing in a Class C minor league and once, when managing the Mets, tried to get Froemming to eject him to inspire his slumping team.</p>
        <p>''He said 'I know what you're doing, and I'm not going to throw you out,' '' Torre said. ''I smiled and said, 'Well, I might as well take advantage of this.' I used every ugly word I knew on him, in a kidding way, because I knew I wasn't going to change his mind.''</p>
        <p>When and if Cox breaks McGraw's record, it is not the sort of thing for which games are held up to hold ceremonies. However, it could be brought up in conversation before a game at home plate among managers and umpires when lineup cards are exchanged.</p>
        <p>''I don't know who will get him for the record,'' Davidson said with a smile and a shrug. ''It's baseball, you know? It's not like life or death or war.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
