<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Romney Is Central Target Of McCain Counterattack</title>
    <meta content="04repubs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/us/politics/04repubs.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852160"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Immigration</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Illegal Immigrants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Romney, Mitt</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McCain, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E3DE1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1288" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Romney Is Central Target Of McCain Counterattack</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Romney Is Central Target of McCain Counterattack</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC SANTORA and MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Santora, Marc; Cooper, Michael</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator John McCain, facing increasing anger from fellow Republicans over his support of the immigration bill in Congress, is ramping up his counterattack against a main rival in the presidential campaign, Mitt Romney, by accusing him of ''pandering for votes'' in opposing the measure.</p>
        <p>The attack, in a speech Mr. McCain is to give today, marks a sharp escalation in the war of words between two of the leading Republican presidential contenders. It also represents a risky gambit by Mr. McCain to right the course of a presidential campaign that has been consumed by attacks on his immigration stance, with Mr. Romney among his most vocal critics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator John McCain is accusing Mitt Romney, a main rival in the presidential campaign, of “pandering for votes.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator John McCain, facing increasing anger from fellow Republicans over his support of the immigration bill in Congress, is ramping up his counterattack against a main rival in the presidential campaign, Mitt Romney, by accusing him of ''pandering for votes'' in opposing the measure.</p>
        <p>The attack, in a speech Mr. McCain is to give today, marks a sharp escalation in the war of words between two of the leading Republican presidential contenders. It also represents a risky gambit by Mr. McCain to right the course of a presidential campaign that has been consumed by attacks on his immigration stance, with Mr. Romney among his most vocal critics.</p>
        <p>Excerpts of the speech were provided to The New York Times.</p>
        <p>Mr. Romney, in speeches and in early campaign commercials, has portrayed the proposal as being soft on illegal immigration -- a sensitive red-meat issue for the Republican base -- and condemned it as offering ''amnesty'' to illegal immigrants. Those criticisms have been echoed by other leading Republicans, conservative leaders and radio commentators.</p>
        <p>In fighting back, Mr. McCain is challenging Mr. Romney and other opponents of the Senate's immigration plan to offer counterproposals explaining what they would do with the nation's illegal immigrants, which he estimates could number 12 million. And his campaign has taken to pointing out what it calls Mr. Romney's shifting stances on immigration, and his lack of specificity on any workable alternative.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain's speech is to be delivered today in Florida, where a large number of Cuban-American Republicans have a different perspective on the immigration issue. While he does not mention Mr. Romney by name in the speech, McCain advisers say Mr. Romney is the target of the criticism.</p>
        <p>''I would hope that any candidate for president would not suggest doing nothing,'' Mr. McCain plans to say. ''And I would hope they wouldn't play politics for their own interests if the cost of their ambition was to make this problem even harder to solve. To want the office so badly that you would intentionally make our country's problems worse might prove you can read a poll or take a cheap shot, but it hardly demonstrates presidential leadership.''</p>
        <p>''Pandering for votes on this issue, while offering no solution to the problem, amounts to doing nothing,'' Mr. McCain plans to say. ''And doing nothing is silent amnesty.''</p>
        <p>Kevin Madden, a spokesman for Mr. Romney, said that Mr. McCain's criticism reflected his desperation at holding a position unpopular with Republican primary voters.</p>
        <p>''Opponents who favor this flawed approach are going to offer all sorts of distortions based on the fact that they cannot make a case on the substance for the bill they are advocating,'' Mr. Madden said. ''I think the McCain campaign is lashing out because they are feeling the political pressure and they don't know what to do.''</p>
        <p>The debate over the immigration bill is emerging as one of the most divisive of the campaign. The measure calls for tightening border security, creating a temporary worker program, and giving preference to new immigrants with certain education levels or jobs skills, instead of to those with family ties in the United States.</p>
        <p>And it would provide a path for many illegal immigrants to get legal status by allowing them to apply for temporary ''Z visas'' and to push for more permanent status by paying fines and having the heads of households return to their countries of origin -- the provision Mr. Romney and many other Republicans opposed.</p>
        <p>Rudolph W. Giuliani, the former New York mayor and another Republican presidential candidate, is not supporting the current the legislation either. A strong past supporter of immigration, Mr. Giuliani has developed a nuanced position on the bill, saying that while he favors creating a way for illegal immigrants to become citizens, he cannot support the measure because it does not set as its primary goal registering and tracking the people already here illegally.</p>
        <p>But the McCain campaign has focused its criticism on Mr. Romney, arguing that he has given conflicting accounts of how he would handle immigration and even whether the bill truly offers amnesty.</p>
        <p>With its criticism, the McCain campaign is seeking to build on the perception that Mr. Romney has changed his position on a number of crucial issues -- including going from being a supporter of abortion rights to an opponent -- since he stepped down as governor of Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>The day after the Senate announced its bipartisan compromise plan, Mr. Romney became the first of the leading Republican candidates for president to condemn it as amnesty.</p>
        <p>''One simple rule: no amnesty,'' he said to applause at the South Carolina Republican convention last month. He said the current compromise, despite making illegal immigrants pay hefty fines and wait years for citizenship, was not good enough because workers could apply for visas that would allow them to stay indefinitely.</p>
        <p>''If that is not a form of amnesty, I don't know what is,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But now, Mr. Romney seems to be backing away from that position. While visiting Florida last week, he was asked to clarify his stance, and said he was ''not really trying to define what is technically amnesty.''</p>
        <p>While Mr. Romney has been consistent on two broad principles -- the need for tighter border security and the creation of tamper-proof employee ID cards -- he has not defined what he means when he says there should be no ''special'' pathway to citizenship, or explained exactly what he thinks should be done with the many illegal immigrants who are living and working in the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Romney has said that he objects to the provision in the bill that calls for ''Z visas,'' which illegal immigrants would have to apply for as a first step in becoming a citizen, because he said that the visas could be endlessly renewed and there would be no incentive for people to take the next step toward citizenship.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Romney says it is essential that all the people here illegally be registered, without explaining what kind of system he has in mind that would both encourage people to come forward and penalize them for being here illegally.</p>
        <p>Mr. Romney's tough line is in some ways consistent with the positions he took as governor, where he signed an executive order that gave Massachusetts state troopers the authority to arrest illegal immigrants and also to cut state aid to illegal immigrants attending college.</p>
        <p>But as recently as 2005, Mr. Romney said he could support immigration legislation similar to what is now being proposed. (His aides say that the measure he offered tentative support to then was quite different from the current bill.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Romney confronted Mr. McCain on immigration in the second Republican debate, citing an earlier proposal that Mr. McCain supported with Senator Edward M. Kennedy, Democrat of Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>''My fear is that McCain-Kennedy would do to immigration what McCain-Feingold has done to campaign finance and money in politics,'' he said, naming a pair of Mr. McCain's co-sponsors who are not especially beloved by Republicans.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain has been an outspoken champion of the current proposal, even though his aides say he is well aware that that it is unpopular with some Republican primary voters. But Mr. McCain, who often reminds voters that he represents a border state, Arizona, plans to make it clear on Monday that he was not going to back away from the issue.</p>
        <p>''It is a hard problem, and I understand that. But the choice is between doing something, imperfect but effective and achievable, and doing nothing,'' Mr. McCain plans to say. ''To do nothing now would be an unconscionable abrogation of our responsibilities to defend the security, prosperity and values of our country.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
