<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Stroke Victims Don't Know</title>
    <meta content="l04stroke" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852156"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E4DE1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="890" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Stroke Victims Don't Know</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Lifesaving Opportunities Missed, Before and After Stroke'' (front page, May 28) discusses a number of reasons that stroke patients may not receive tPA as treatment in the emergency department. But there is another reason: the significant controversy in the field of emergency medicine about the use of tissue plasminogen activator, or tPA.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Lifesaving Opportunities Missed, Before and After Stroke'' (front page, May 28) discusses a number of reasons that stroke patients may not receive tPA as treatment in the emergency department. But there is another reason: the significant controversy in the field of emergency medicine about the use of tissue plasminogen activator, or tPA.</p>
        <p>While the benefits of tPA in treating heart attacks have been definitively established, the benefits are not as clear-cut for stroke.</p>
        <p>The studies that established the use of tPA in stroke were less than ''gold standard'' studies. In fact, the efficacy in stroke was determined only through data-mining, as the authors went back in after their original study was completed to salvage some useful information.</p>
        <p>The study, as originally designed, didn't establish any benefit from the use to tPA. The authors then came up with a three-hour window of treatment, which provides some benefit for some patients but poses significant risks for others.</p>
        <p>For this emergency doctor, and for many of my colleagues, the use of tPA to treat stroke is a choice that is reluctantly, if ever, made, and none of the major emergency medicine associations in North America have endorsed it as ''standard of care.''</p>
        <p>Arman Afagh, M.D.  Riverside, Calif., May 30, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your article about stroke treatment highlights an important opportunity for the medical community to close the gap between what should happen and what does happen. For patients, families and society at large, the opportunity is captured in two words: blood pressure.</p>
        <p>Aggressive, sustained treatment of high blood pressure is the best thing patients and their doctors can do to prevent stroke and its complications. It would have more bang for the buck at the societal level than any other intervention.</p>
        <p>Lewis G. Sandy, M.D.  Senior Vice President  Clinical Advancement  UnitedHealth Group  Minnetonka, Minn., May 29, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Lifesaving Opportunities Missed, Before and After Stroke'' says that tPA ''could help half of all stroke patients,'' but that ''only 3 percent to 4 percent'' receive it.</p>
        <p>This is true despite advances in imaging and treatment delivery. The statistic remains a source of frustration for the medical community and should be a point of concern for all of us.</p>
        <p>The first part of the solution lies in federal research money. Though stroke ranks first in causing disability and third in causing death, it ranks 71st out of 215 disease categories for National Institutes of Health financing.</p>
        <p>Also, because of misinterpreted symptoms and denial, patients commonly arrive at the emergency room after the three-hour window when tPA works. Stroke education is imperative for patients, family members and the community that each hospital serves. Such efforts are under way at Columbia University and other academic institutions.</p>
        <p>Without engagement of the public, the promise of better treatment may be deliverable to only a small percentage of those who need it.</p>
        <p>Randolph Marshall, M.D.  Acting Director, Stroke Division  Columbia University Medical Center  New York, May 29, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As a vascular neurologist and chairman of the Stroke Council of the American Heart Association, I am aware of the significant gaps in stroke treatment.</p>
        <p>Because ''time lost is brain lost,'' systems need to be put in place to assure that all patients get appropriate treatment as quickly as possible.</p>
        <p>The federal Stroke Treatment and Ongoing Prevention Act, which has been passed by the House and is pending in the Senate, would help achieve this goal. It calls for educating the public about stroke symptoms and supports coordinated, statewide stroke care systems.</p>
        <p>This bill would help the medical community provide the best available care.</p>
        <p>Larry B. Goldstein, M.D.  Director, Duke Stroke Center  Durham, N.C., May 30, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I am an emergency room doctor, and almost every stroke patient I see has a pre-existing condition -- like high blood pressure, diabetes, tobacco abuse and high cholesterol -- that hasn't been properly addressed.</p>
        <p>While tPA clot-busting treatment and M.R.I. scans are valuable, the emphasis always seems to be on the new and high-tech. That's where the money is, not only for doctors, but also for hospitals and makers of drugs and medical equipment.</p>
        <p>Spending 30 minutes with a patient to work on reducing risk factors is not rewarded, recognized or reimbursed. Our payment system perversely discourages prevention.</p>
        <p>Treating strokes with modern technology and medicines is important, but the real payoff is in fully supporting prevention. We now spend too much too late with too little to show for it.</p>
        <p>Dan Morhaim, M.D.  Owings Mills, Md., May 28, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The reason hospitals do not consider strokes to be ''moneymakers'' is that the real cost comes not in the catastrophic event but in the hours of physical therapy required later.</p>
        <p>Insurers pay for a limited number of these visits because of the conventional medical view that after a year, stroke victims rarely achieve more gains. Yet neurologists and neurophysiologists have recently discovered that stroke patients can continue to make significant recovery even several years after an incident.</p>
        <p>My wife suffered a severe stroke at 53, almost four years ago, and she is still gaining movement on her left side.</p>
        <p>The medical treatment community is lagging behind the science of this disease.</p>
        <p>Doug Garr  New York, May 28, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
