<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Title-Starved Cleveland Pins Hopes on Cavaliers</title>
    <meta content="04cavs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/sports/basketball/04cavs.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852172"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Detroit Pistons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio/Cleveland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Cleveland (Ohio)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Cleveland Cavaliers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Detroit Pistons</org>
        <person class="online_producer">James, LeBron</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEFDE1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1071" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Title-Starved Cleveland Pins Hopes on Cavaliers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Title-Starved Cleveland Pins Hopes on Cavaliers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <dateline>CLEVELAND, June 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LeBron James took the microphone as M.C. of the franchise revival, stepping to center court to cheers of delirium.</p>
        <p>Minutes after guiding the Cleveland Cavaliers to their first Eastern Conference championship with a 98-82 romp against the Detroit Pistons on Saturday in Game 6, James thanked the fans, 20,562 strong, at Quicken Loans Arena.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Cavaliers’ win over Detroit was the ultimate reversal of fortune for a beleaguered sports city accustomed to big-game failure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LeBron James took the microphone as M.C. of the franchise revival, stepping to center court to cheers of delirium.</p>
        <p>Minutes after guiding the Cleveland Cavaliers to their first Eastern Conference championship with a 98-82 romp against the Detroit Pistons on Saturday in Game 6, James thanked the fans, 20,562 strong, at Quicken Loans Arena.</p>
        <p>But when James praised his favorite sidekick, the rookie Daniel Gibson, the fans seemed to boo with all their might.</p>
        <p>But ''BOO-bie! BOO-bie!'' is what they were chanting. They were yelling Gibson's childhood nickname and showering him with gratitude for his 31-point performance.</p>
        <p>On this magical night in Cleveland, the boos that were cheers symbolized the ultimate reversal of fortune for a beleaguered sports city accustomed to big-game failure.</p>
        <p>That Gibson, a 6-foot-2 guard who grew up in Houston, was given his nickname by his mother, Cheryl -- after she saw her small son with scratches and bruises from playing with older boys -- made the moment that much more poetic.</p>
        <p>Together undaunted, the 22-year-old James and Gibson, 21, led the 37-year-old Cleveland franchise to its first N.B.A. finals appearance, dispatching the aging and bickering Pistons as the former power of the East.</p>
        <p>No matter that the Cavaliers must now play the three-time champion San Antonio Spurs, the model of sustained excellence that the Cavaliers were built to emulate. ''It doesn't stop here!'' James shouted into the din.</p>
        <p>James, a native of nearby Akron, Ohio, later marveled at the fans' response. ''After the game, they couldn't even hear what we were saying because they were so loud, so excited about how we grew as a team,'' he said beside his locker.</p>
        <p>James grew before a basketball nation, steadily shaking off criticism from Cleveland's first two losses and peaking in Game 5.</p>
        <p>Single-handedly wresting that double-overtime victory from Detroit on its home court, James emerged from his 48-point performance with an unquestionable killer instinct.</p>
        <p>And because he scored 29 of his team's final 30 points, he was smothered by Pistons defenders in Game 6. James simply displayed his deft touch as a leader, distributing the ball and infusing Gibson with the confidence to take open shots.</p>
        <p>''From Day 1, LeBron has been in my corner,'' Gibson said. ''He told me he was going to make me something special, he was going to do whatever he could to make me better.''</p>
        <p>Gibson starred in this series when Cleveland's starting point guard, Larry Hughes, strained the plantar fascia in his left foot in Game 3. Gibson took advantage of his playing time, especially in Game 6. In the fourth quarter, he made all four of his 3-point attempts, hitting three of them in the opening minutes to help turn a 1-point lead into an untouchable 12-point margin. He scored 19 of his 31 points in the final quarter.</p>
        <p>''I was wowing Daniel like I was on LeBron,'' Cavaliers Coach Mike Brown said, adding that Gibson's game was ''LeBronesque.''</p>
        <p>Gibson took only nine shots from the field, making seven, and he scored the rest of his points from the free-throw line, going 12 for 15. He took advantage of the same aggressive drives he had used in Game 4, when he scored 21 points and made all 12 of his free throws.</p>
        <p>James hit only 3 of 11 field-goal attempts in Game 6 but went 14 for 19 from the line. The entire Pistons team hit 23 of 27 free throws.</p>
        <p>James said that he was convinced of Gibson's talent early in the season. During a down period for the team, Gibson spoke up in a meeting. ''Daniel said, 'Man, if every guy in this locker room just plays as hard as I want to play on this basketball court, we're going to be something special,' '' James said.</p>
        <p>The two had the kind of passion Detroit lacked in this series. Once bound by being hungry castoffs, the Pistons lost their purpose and identity. For the second year in a row, they lost in the conference finals by pointing fingers and letting a star player beat them.</p>
        <p>''They had never been here before,'' Pistons point guard Chauncey Billups said of the Cavaliers. ''They knew what was at stake, and you could see that.''</p>
        <p>Billups had a dismal series, finishing with only 9 points and 1 assist Saturday, in time for his free agency. His teammate Rasheed Wallace played to his reputation, unleashing a profanity-laced tirade at the referee Eddie F. Rush and being ejected in the fourth quarter. Flip Saunders kept to his reputation, too, as a coach who struggles in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>The season before James came in as the No. 1 overall draft pick in 2003, the Cavaliers won only 17 games, to which center Zydrunas Ilgauskas, the lone holdover, can attest. James's teams won 35 and 42 games the next two seasons, missing the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Dan Gilbert, the founder of the online mortgage company Quicken Loans, became the majority owner in March 2005. That June, he hired a defense-minded rookie coach in Brown, and Danny Ferry, a former Cavaliers forward and Spurs executive, to be the general manager.</p>
        <p>James has led the Cavaliers to consecutive 50-victory seasons. This year in the playoffs against Detroit, one round further than Cleveland advanced last season, James led his team to four consecutive victories. Debates from the first two losses, whether he should have passed or shot at the end, disappeared.</p>
        <p>''I have nothing to prove to anybody,'' James said. ''I'm a leader of a group of guys who believe in me and believe in my decisions down the stretch.</p>
        <p>''Everyone has always criticized the way I play the game of basketball because I'm a team-first guy. That's how the game should be played.''</p>
        <p>The Spurs, led by Tim Duncan, and flanked by Tony Parker and Manu Ginóbili, play that way.</p>
        <p>James has had a picture in his locker all season of him dunking over Duncan. As if he needed more inspiration now. At the beginning of the season, and to quizzical looks, James started a chant to end huddles: ''One, two, three -- championship!''</p>
        <p>That turned from a mantra to a possibility Saturday night, as the fans, starved for a title since the Cleveland Browns won the 1964 N.F.L. championship, sensed that James might have altered history.</p>
        <p>''Everybody was a witness, I guess,'' James said with a grin and an irresistible nod to his commercial slogan.</p>
        <p>What will they see next?</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
