<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rodriguez Lifts Weight With Homer in 9th</title>
    <meta content="04yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852213"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3DD1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1021" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rodriguez Lifts Weight With Homer in 9th</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Monday, June 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He was down to his last strike with two outs in the ninth inning of Sunday night's game, at the end of what might be the longest week of his life. Alex Rodriguez -- bad boy of the tabloids, violator of baseball etiquette, object of ridicule and scorn at Fenway Park -- was fighting.</p>
        <p>With the score tied and his teammates seeming to drop all around him with injuries, Rodriguez punished a 95-mile-an-hour fastball from Jonathan Papelbon on a line, into the Boston Red Sox' bullpen, for his 20th home run. With that, Rodriguez led the Yankees to a victory in the game, 6-5, and in the series, two games to one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He was down to his last strike with two outs in the ninth inning of Sunday night's game, at the end of what might be the longest week of his life. Alex Rodriguez -- bad boy of the tabloids, violator of baseball etiquette, object of ridicule and scorn at Fenway Park -- was fighting.</p>
        <p>With the score tied and his teammates seeming to drop all around him with injuries, Rodriguez punished a 95-mile-an-hour fastball from Jonathan Papelbon on a line, into the Boston Red Sox' bullpen, for his 20th home run. With that, Rodriguez led the Yankees to a victory in the game, 6-5, and in the series, two games to one.</p>
        <p>''Just battling for my life at that point,'' said Rodriguez, who homered on an 0-2 pitch. ''Basically I was just trying to hit the ball hard somewhere but not trying to do too much.''</p>
        <p>He had failed two innings earlier, popping up with one out and runners at the corners, when a fly ball would have tied the score. But after Robinson Canó tripled in Hideki Matsui to tie the score in the eighth, Rodriguez sent Papelbon to his first loss of the season with his homer in the ninth.</p>
        <p>The Yankees picked up a game in the American League East standings, but the Red Sox are still far ahead of them, at 12 1/2 games. The Yankees' record improved, at least, to 24-30, and they took a series from Boston for the second time in a row. The teams meet only six times over the Yankees' last 108 games.</p>
        <p>Mariano Rivera set down the Red Sox in the ninth, striking out Mike Lowell to end the game with a runner on first at 12:14 a.m.</p>
        <p>One day after their defense cost them dearly, the Yankees were helped greatly by two plays late in the game. In the sixth, a relay of Matsui to Derek Jeter to Jorge Posada cut down Julio Lugo at the plate to end the inning. And with two outs in the eighth, with runners on first and second, Bobby Abreu made a running backhand catch to preserve a 5-5 tie.</p>
        <p>It was not a total victory for the Yankees, who are making baseball seem a lot more dangerous than it usually is. Andy Pettitte, their steadiest starter, unleashed a strikeout pitch in the fifth inning and shouted in apparent pain. Pettitte lasted three more pitches before leaving with tightness in his lower back. He said he expected to make his next start, Friday at home against Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>Pettitte allowed five runs and seven hits in four and a third innings. His counterpart, Josh Beckett, gave up four runs and eight hits in six and a third.</p>
        <p>Beckett was trying to become the first major leaguer to win nine games this season without a loss. No Red Sox pitcher had won his first nine decisions since Roger Clemens started 14-0 in 1986.</p>
        <p>For all of Beckett's success, though, Pettitte came into the game with a better earned run average. At 2.51, Pettitte's E.R.A. was fourth in the American League. But his record was just 3-4. Six times, he worked at least six innings while allowing no more than three earned runs but did not earn the victory.</p>
        <p>This would not be another, though there was no warning of that at first. Pettitte cruised through four innings, allowing two hits, a walk and no runs.</p>
        <p>The defense sparkled behind him in the third, when Melky Cabrera chased down a Wily Mo Peña drive on the warning track and Canó ranged across second base, abruptly stopped his momentum and whipped a throw to first.</p>
        <p>Posada, naturally, had helped the Yankees take a 4-0 lead by doubling and scoring in the second inning and singling in a run in the fifth. That was after two runs had scored on an infield single by Rodriguez.</p>
        <p>He chopped a ball to Lowell at third base with two outs, and Lowell barehanded the ball and threw it away. Rodriguez got credit for a run batted in, and Lowell for an error. Rodriguez clapped his hands as he crossed first base.</p>
        <p>In the fifth, Lugo came up with the bases loaded, and Pettitte got two quick strikes. He labored from there, with a foul ball and three balls, and a sudden call of time by the plate umpire, Chris Guccione, while Pettitte was in the middle of his delivery.</p>
        <p>Pettitte struck out Lugo on the seventh pitch, letting out a yell as he threw it. The pitching coach Ron Guidry and the trainer Steve Donahue sprang from the dugout and hustled to the mound, with Manager Joe Torre close behind.</p>
        <p>Pettitte stayed in, but he threw only three more pitches. One was a ball. The next, to Dustin Pedroia, was banged off the Green Monster as all three runners scored, Coco Crisp sliding in just a few feet behind the plodding Peña.</p>
        <p>The last, to David Ortiz, was hammered into shallow right field, in front of Abreu. On Saturday, Abreu misplayed a deep drive by Ortiz that landed on the warning track for a double. This time, he charged Ortiz's hit but let it skip past him for a two-base error.</p>
        <p>Pedroia scored, tying the score at 4-4 and giving the Yankees their fifth blown lead of the series. Pettitte's night was over after 83 pitches, and with Ortiz at third after Abreu's error, Kevin Youkilis scored him with a sacrifice fly to put the Red Sox ahead, 5-4.</p>
        <p>With one out in the seventh and Johnny Damon on first, Red Sox Manager Terry Francona removed Beckett for the left-hander Javier López, who gave up a single to Abreu that moved Damon to third. Brendan Donnelly took over to face Rodriguez, who popped out to short.</p>
        <p>That was discouraging for the Yankees, who quietly ended the inning when Hideki Okajima, the lefty the Yankees cannot solve, induced a flyout from Posada to preserve the one-run lead.</p>
        <p>The Yankees finally did solve Okajima in the eighth, when Matsui led off with a single and Canó tripled him home, setting the stage for Rodriguez.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
