<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Red Sox, the Relief Is Almost Beyond Belief</title>
    <meta content="04chass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/sports/baseball/04chass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852198"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Francona, Terry</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Torre, Joe</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4DD1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="845" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Red Sox, the Relief Is Almost Beyond Belief</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Red Sox, the Relief Is Almost Beyond Belief</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This is why they play the games. One of the American League's worst bullpens went up against its best last night, and the Yankees nevertheless beat the Red Sox generally and their bullpen particularly.</p>
        <p>The Yankees tied the score, 5-5, on Robinson Can칩's triple against Hideki Okajima in the eighth inning. They won it, 6-5, on Alex Rodriguez's home run against Jonathan Papelbon in the ninth. Four Yankees relievers, meanwhile, pitched 4 2/3 scoreless innings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Red Sox have put together an outstanding collection of relievers for this season. The Yankees? You have to wonder what they were thinking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This is why they play the games. One of the American League's worst bullpens went up against its best last night, and the Yankees nevertheless beat the Red Sox generally and their bullpen particularly.</p>
        <p>The Yankees tied the score, 5-5, on Robinson Can칩's triple against Hideki Okajima in the eighth inning. They won it, 6-5, on Alex Rodriguez's home run against Jonathan Papelbon in the ninth. Four Yankees relievers, meanwhile, pitched 4 2/3 scoreless innings.</p>
        <p>When a team has a division lead over another team that two months into the season stretches from here to the other side of the Mississippi or the Rockies -- take your pick -- there are most likely several factors at work. In the case of the Red Sox and the Yankees, look at their bullpens.</p>
        <p>The Red Sox, unhappy with a relief corps that was mediocre at best last year, have put together an outstanding collection of relievers for this season. The Yankees? You have to wonder what they were thinking.</p>
        <p>The Red Sox' bullpen is No. 1 in the American League. It entered the game with the lowest earned run average, 3.05, and the best won-lost record, 8-1 for an .889 winning percentage.</p>
        <p>The Yankees have had one of the most ineffective crews. Their relievers had the worst won-lost record, 6-10 (.375), and their 4.57 E.R.A. was 10th out of 14 teams entering yesterday's games.</p>
        <p>Boston Manager Terry Francona has had an array of relievers to use, and he has used them well. Joe Torre, his Yankees counterpart, has a bad habit of not trusting many of his relievers, which results in the overuse of the ones he trusts. Their overuse usually leads to their ineffectiveness, which doesn't help the Yankees solve their problems.</p>
        <p>''I can't come up with another superlative,'' Curt Schilling, dean of the Red Sox starters, said when asked to assess the job the relievers had done.</p>
        <p>''For me, they've been unselfish, dominating and consistent.''</p>
        <p>The best-known member of the relief corps is Papelbon, the second-year closer, but the standout member has been Okajima, who with his unexpected performance has overshadowed his countryman Daisuke Matsuzaka, if that's possible.</p>
        <p>Okajima is one of four new members of the bullpen. The others are Brendan Donnelly, who was obtained in a trade, and Joel Pi침eiro and J. C. Romero, who were signed as free agents.</p>
        <p>Also a free agent, Okajima entered last night's game against the Yankees with a minuscule 1.00 E.R.A. A left-hander, he had held left-handed hitters to a .091 batting average (3 for 33), but right-handers hadn't feasted against him, batting .183. The overall .151 average against him was even lower than Papelbon's .162.</p>
        <p>''He's been incredible,'' Schilling said.</p>
        <p>Why has he been able to be incredible? ''He has no fear,'' Papelbon said.</p>
        <p>The Red Sox acknowledged that they didn't know what they had when they signed Okajima.</p>
        <p>''We left spring training and we didn't know what Okajima's role would be,'' Francona said. ''We didn't quite know him. About 10 days into the season, this kid starts working with a split and looked pretty good.''</p>
        <p>Francona used Okajima as his closer in a game against the Yankees on April 20 when Papelbon wasn't available. Four batters later, Boston's 7-6 lead was a 7-6 victory.</p>
        <p>''He took off,'' Francona said. ''We got a guy who can face lefties and righties any time in the game. He's been real beneficial.''</p>
        <p>Francona credited General Manager Theo Epstein with seeing earlier than anyone how helpful Okajima could be.</p>
        <p>''Theo told me with about 10 days left in spring training,'' Francona said. ''I was sort of lamenting about our pitchers getting hit hard, and he said in about 10 days you're going to be using Okajima in close games. I kind of laughed. He was right. He hit it on the nose.''</p>
        <p>Okajima is one of three left-handers in the Boston bullpen (Romero and Javier L칩pez are the others). That's an unusually high number.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't call it a luxury, but it's nice to have,'' Francona said.</p>
        <p>The Red Sox began spring training without a closer. Papelbon held that role as a rookie last season, but health considerations prompted the Red Sox to plan to use him as a starter this year. Before spring training ended, they reversed their thinking.</p>
        <p>Francona said that the change did not come because they hadn't found a closer, even though they hadn't.</p>
        <p>''It's not that we didn't find anybody,'' he said. ''We needed to have a lot of questions answered. I was maybe a day away from talking to Pap, and he came into my office. It happened a couple days quicker than we thought it would, but we were going that way.''</p>
        <p>Whatever the reason, Papelbon is saving games again. But he has had plenty of help.</p>
        <p>''You could take any one of the guys, put them in a save situation and I'd feel very good about our chances,'' Schilling said. ''There aren't a lot of bullpens you can say that about.''</p>
        <p>For one night, though, the bad bullpen beat the best bullpen.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
