<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Somalia's Prime Minister Survives Suicide Attack; 7 Others Die</title>
    <meta content="04somalia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/world/africa/04somalia.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852140"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Somalia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Somalia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Somalia</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803EEDF1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="398" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Somalia's Prime Minister Survives Suicide Attack; 7 Others Die</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Somalia’s Prime Minister Survives Suicide Attack; 7 Others Die</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFFREY GETTLEMAN; Mohammed Ibrahim and Yuusuf Maxamuud contributed reporting from Mogadishu, Somalia.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gettleman, Jeffrey; Maxamuud, Yuusuf; Ibrahim, Mohammed</byline>
      <dateline>NAIROBI, Kenya, June 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A suicide bomber narrowly missed killing Somalia's transitional prime minister on Sunday afternoon after he rammed a pickup truck packed with explosives into the gates of the prime minister's house in Mogadishu, the capital.</p>
        <p>The prime minister, Ali Mohamed Gedi, who was inside at the time, was unhurt. However, the explosion killed six of his bodyguards, along with a student at a Koranic school across the street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A suicide bomber rammed a pickup truck packed with explosives into the gates of the prime minister’s house.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A suicide bomber narrowly missed killing Somalia's transitional prime minister on Sunday afternoon after he rammed a pickup truck packed with explosives into the gates of the prime minister's house in Mogadishu, the capital.</p>
        <p>The prime minister, Ali Mohamed Gedi, who was inside at the time, was unhurt. However, the explosion killed six of his bodyguards, along with a student at a Koranic school across the street.</p>
        <p>Witnesses said that the pickup sped through a roadblock outside Mr. Gedi's house and that bodyguards opened fire as the truck hurtled onward. It then slammed into a set of gates just feet away from the residence and exploded in a fireball that flattened several buildings and scattered debris for blocks.</p>
        <p>Afterward, Ugandan peacekeepers shuttled Mr. Gedi from his house to an undisclosed location. Speaking on national radio, he blamed Islamist militants for the violence.</p>
        <p>''These cowards, they're trying to sabotage our government,'' he said. ''But we won't stop our mission to stabilize this country and defeat them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gedi said the pickup was able to sail through the checkpoints outside his home because it carried men dressed in government army uniforms.</p>
        <p>''My security guards thought these guys were friends,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The authorities did not say how many attackers died.</p>
        <p>According to Somali security officials, remnants of the Islamist forces that briefly ruled Somalia last year are regrouping and changing their tactics from conventional warfare to terrorist strikes. In December, Ethiopian forces routed the Islamists and helped install Somalia's weak but internationally recognized transitional government in the capital.</p>
        <p>Since then, the Ethiopian troops, thought to number in the thousands, and the government's fledging security forces have struggled to bring the same level of peace and security that the Islamists delivered.</p>
        <p>Many of Mogadishu's neighborhoods are still bullet-pocked no-go zones, and several government officials, including police chiefs, have recently been assassinated. On Saturday, Mogadishu's mayor blamed members of the Hawiye clan, the dominant clan in the city, for the killings. Hawiye elders denied it.</p>
        <p>A contingent of 1,600 Ugandan soldiers, the first part of a larger African Union peacekeeping force, has been beefing up efforts to protect officials.</p>
        <p>It was at least the third time in a year that someone has tried to kill Mr. Gedi, a veterinarian-turned-politician whose support is lukewarm in most parts of the country.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
