<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trial of Black Raises Conflict Issue</title>
    <meta content="04whyte" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/business/media/04whyte.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852106"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Canada</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Chicago (Ill)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Hollinger International Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Black, Conrad M</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE6DF1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="605" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trial of Black Raises Conflict Issue</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trial of Black Raises Conflict Issue</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIA MILLER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Maclean's Magazine, a leading Canadian weekly newsmagazine, has been as eager to cover the trial of Conrad M. Black as any other Canadian news outlet.</p>
        <p>Mr. Black, a Canadian-born businessman who made part of his fortune as chairman of one of the world's biggest newspaper groups, Hollinger International (now called the Sun-Times Media Group), is on trial in Chicago, accused of stealing millions of dollars from Hollinger. Mr. Black stepped down as chairman in January 2004.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Maclean’s Magazine has two important connections with Conrad M. Black that complicate its role as an impartial chronicler of his trial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Maclean's Magazine, a leading Canadian weekly newsmagazine, has been as eager to cover the trial of Conrad M. Black as any other Canadian news outlet.</p>
        <p>Mr. Black, a Canadian-born businessman who made part of his fortune as chairman of one of the world's biggest newspaper groups, Hollinger International (now called the Sun-Times Media Group), is on trial in Chicago, accused of stealing millions of dollars from Hollinger. Mr. Black stepped down as chairman in January 2004.</p>
        <p>Although quite a few journalists in Canada have worked for Mr. Black at some point, Maclean's (which Mr. Black never owned) has two important connections with him that complicate its role as an impartial chronicler of his predicament.</p>
        <p>Mr. Black's wife of 15 years, Barbara Amiel, is a well-known conservative columnist who has worked for Maclean's for 30 years, and Ken Whyte, Maclean's publisher and editor in chief, is a former employee of Mr. Black's who remains a close friend.</p>
        <p>In an e-mail message, Mr. Whyte said that he had discussed the situation with Ms. Amiel and they agreed ''she should avoid comment on the proceedings and the particulars of the case but that she could on occasion write about her own experiences as the wife of a high-profile criminal defendant.''</p>
        <p>Though her columns from Chicago refer to the trial only obliquely, in one of her most recent columns she wrote that a conviction would be a ''miscarriage of justice.''</p>
        <p>A further complication is that several weeks ago Mr. Whyte, who worked for Mr. Black for 10 years, was called as a defense witness. His testimony started Friday and is scheduled to continue today.</p>
        <p>Mark Steyn, a Maclean's columnist who used to work for some of Mr. Black's newspapers, has been commenting on the trial.</p>
        <p>Mr. Whyte said that readers of Maclean's were informed of the potential conflicts. ''When I decided to answer the subpoena I disclosed to our readers that I would appear as a witness in my capacity as a former Black employee,'' Mr. Whyte said. ''Ms. Amiel's relations to the defendant have been abundantly disclosed, as has Mr. Steyn's former employment in the Black empire.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Whyte said that his role in the trial should not affect Maclean's coverage, adding: ''Mr. Steyn has informed me that he plans to prove his journalistic integrity by treating me twice as harshly as other witnesses.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Steyn posted online Friday that his boss ''seemed unprepared'' for the cross-examination.</p>
        <p>Maclean's is owned by Rogers Communications and has a circulation of around 500,000.</p>
        <p>Kelly McBride, a journalism ethics specialist at the Poynter Institute, said that this situation was not unusual in the profession, and often drew criticism from nonjournalists.</p>
        <p>''As an outsider what you see is a sort of incestuous relationship,'' she said. ''People have jobs and relationships with each other, they have financial gains based on these relationships, they are all scratching each other's backs under the guise of journalism.''</p>
        <p>On the other hand, she said, these connections are sometimes unavoidable. ''A lot of journalists marry other journalists, are children of other journalists, and it looks very suspicious to outsiders.''</p>
        <p>She added: ''The best way to judge whether one powerful person is scratching the back of another or whether you have powerful editors hiring journalists into positions that are appropriate for their skills and abilities is to look at the work itself.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Whyte said that Maclean's had not given Mr. Black any special treatment. ''In the pretrial period,'' he said, ''Mr. Black sued me and Maclean's over coverage he considered unfavorable. In fact, he's sued two of my columnists over our coverage of his affairs.''</p>
        <p>LIA MILLER</p>
        <p>MEDIA TALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
