<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mr. Murdoch Comes Round For Tea</title>
    <meta content="04carr" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/business/media/04carr.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852122"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA EQUATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dow Jones &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wall Street Journal</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murdoch, Rupert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bancroft Family</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carr, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Wall Street Journal</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Dow Jones &amp; Co</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Murdoch, Rupert</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bancroft Family</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E3DF1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1076" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mr. Murdoch Comes Round For Tea</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mr. Murdoch Comes Round for Tea</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CARR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carr, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Carr Media Equation column holds that Rupert Murdoch is slowly convincing Dow Jones &amp; Company to accept $5 billion offer for company; at issue is how flagship Wall Street Journal newspaper will be affected by acquisition; Bancroft family will meet with Murdoch to discuss terms (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The meeting later today between Rupert Murdoch and the Bancroft family that could determine the fate of Dow Jones &amp; Company, publisher of The Wall Street Journal, would seem to be a very modern media moment.</p>
        <p>But the specter of it -- all forced smiles and cleared throats, the discovery of common values whether there are any or not -- brings to mind a 19th-century comedy of manners that would be funny, except it is not.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rupert Murdoch, a coarse, self-seeking tabloid king, has become a potential savior who will rescue Dow Jones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The meeting later today between Rupert Murdoch and the Bancroft family that could determine the fate of Dow Jones &amp; Company, publisher of The Wall Street Journal, would seem to be a very modern media moment.</p>
        <p>But the specter of it -- all forced smiles and cleared throats, the discovery of common values whether there are any or not -- brings to mind a 19th-century comedy of manners that would be funny, except it is not.</p>
        <p>The family's first reaction to Mr. Murdoch's $5 billion offer was all pursed lips and tut-tuts. Unthinkable, really, for such a man to be offered custody of the family's most precious asset. He is, after all, a bit of a brute, a man of enormous capital, but very sketchy provenance.</p>
        <p>''The last man in the world whom I could ever be prevailed upon to marry,'' Elizabeth called the well-situated Mr. Darcy in ''Pride and Prejudice.'' But Mr. Darcy wore her down, erasing her doubts and easing her suspicions by gradually revealing his character and suggesting that the stories she had heard about him were just that.</p>
        <p>We are nearing the end of a similar makeover of Mr. Murdoch. A coarse, self-seeking tabloid king has become a potential savior, a man with journalism in his blood and money in his wallet who will rescue Dow Jones from being blown away by forces beyond its control.</p>
        <p>Mr. Murdoch will pass the horns-and-tail test with ease. Anybody who has met him can testify to his easy and substantial personal charm. (Wouldn't you just kill to watch Mr. Murdoch put on the hula skirt and coconuts and dance his way into the hearts of the Bancrofts?)</p>
        <p>Mr. Murdoch will reiterate his love of newspapers, perhaps not mentioning that it ranks a bit behind his lust for power. Trust one of the world's most artful deal makers to evince a wholesale grasp of the newspaper's importance and a retail grasp of individual family concerns. As the head of a diversified media concern, he will speak with a great deal of insight and portentousness about the challenge posed by the Thomson/Reuters merger.</p>
        <p>And most critically, there will be a vow of chastity and fealty to the newspaper's editorial independence, perhaps even dropping retired editor Paul E. Steiger's name as a suitable head of an editorial board that will serve as an in-house Church Lady.</p>
        <p>''Rupert Murdoch, of all people, knows what to do. He is quite worldly,'' said Letitia Baldrige, a longtime arbiter of social and business graces. ''It is a bit of a social ballet, but the outcome is hardly in doubt. The family would not agree to see him unless they were capitulating. Now they just have much face to save in front of family, friends, employees and the public.''</p>
        <p>Manners aside, someone will eventually get around to addressing the elephant in the room. To wit, ''If we take your filthy billions, will we eventually go down in the Book of Life as the people who sold the world's most important arbiter of capitalism to a cad?''</p>
        <p>Put more delicately, will owning The Wall Street Journal change Mr. Murdoch, or will his ownership change the newspaper? Journalism history, let alone Mr. Murdoch's, is a little short on examples of owners who were ennobled by the heralded properties they purchased.</p>
        <p>''Newspapers are transformed by people, not the other way around,'' said David Nasaw, a professor of history at the City University of New York.</p>
        <p>Reporters and editors in The Journal's newsroom are girding themselves for the kind of tectonic change they have covered in almost every other industry. A few pointed out that it was the paper's Web site, WSJ.com, that first published the leaked statement detailing the family's change of heart while some family members were still in a Dow Jones board meeting arguing about its implications.</p>
        <p>''You have to wonder if we put ourselves in play by leaking that,'' one journalist said.</p>
        <p>But their suspicion supposes that the family was willing to walk away, and there isn't much evidence for that. Even Michael Elefante, the influential family trustee and Dow Jones director who had been reflexively opposed to a sale, said it may be time for a realpolitik look at the News Corporation's offer, according to The Wall Street Journal on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Elefante -- in our 19th-century novel, he plays the role of the vicar -- and others were most likely influenced by a presentation from Richard F. Zannino, the current chief executive, which showed revenue bar charts being ground to nothing as an independent enterprise, versus the bird-in-hand bid of Mr. Murdoch, replete with massive golden egg.</p>
        <p>In fact, the Bancrofts' delayed decision to leap into his arms simply reflected a lack of communication common to all families, even ones that don't control big heaving media enterprises. The elders felt that they were speaking for the many, and it turned out that they were speaking only for themselves.</p>
        <p>Younger members who have watched other media companies diversify into a dynamic future while their own company sat on its noble laurels fired up a criss-cross of e-mail messages fomenting dissent. As has happened with the Cowleses (The Star Tribune) and the Chandlers (The Los Angeles Times), subsequent generations began to notice that civic pride of place was not doing much for their net worth.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it matters one little bit what he says in that room,'' said the scion of another endowed media family who did not want to be seen as poking his nose into another family's business. ''Here is someone who believes in The Wall Street Journal, believes in the future of newspapers, who is willing to pay a price no one else will.''</p>
        <p>In this instance, it will go easier because it is not a referendum on any family member's skill as an operator. Unlike The Washington Post and The New York Times, no blood relation actually runs the place, so they won't have to see someone they dispossessed at the next family Christmas party. It will be all nice-to-see-you's, and, hey, isn't that a gorgeous new diamond necklace?</p>
        <p>Mr. Murdoch has already made the Bancrofts much richer, just by declaring his ardor. Today, he will make the sort of cuddly noises that will soothe the remaining skeptics in the family, trading lucre for legitimacy. But it all seems a bit foregone, like a hastily arranged rehearsal dinner for a shotgun wedding.</p>
        <p>He had them at $5 billion.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA EQUATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
