<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Linebacker's Legend Is Growing in Kansas</title>
    <meta content="04brown" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/sports/football/04brown.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852191"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Kansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Kansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Kansas</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E5DD1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="957" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Linebacker's Legend Is Growing in Kansas</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Linebacker’s Legend Is Growing in Kansas</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THAYER EVANS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the midst of the spring period to evaluate high school football players last month, college football's most elite coaches took a detour from the traditional recruiting hotbeds -- California, Florida and Texas -- to an unlikely destination, southern Kansas.</p>
        <p>At Wichita East High School on May 16, 30 coaches converged to watch the 16-year-old middle linebacker Arthur Brown Jr. participate in a 90-minute instructional camp.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Arthur Brown Jr., 16, can run a 40-yard dash in 4.47 seconds and he already has more than 50 scholarship offers. What he doesn’t have is a cellphone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the midst of the spring period to evaluate high school football players last month, college football's most elite coaches took a detour from the traditional recruiting hotbeds -- California, Florida and Texas -- to an unlikely destination, southern Kansas.</p>
        <p>At Wichita East High School on May 16, 30 coaches converged to watch the 16-year-old middle linebacker Arthur Brown Jr. participate in a 90-minute instructional camp.</p>
        <p>Brown, a 6-foot-1, 225-pounder who is nicknamed Fireman and can run a 40-yard dash in 4.47 seconds, is regarded by many college coaches as the top player in the class of 2008 and is rated as such by at least one recruiting service. Last season, he registered 158 tackles, 8 sacks and an interception.</p>
        <p>As the chiseled Brown sprinted in a cone drill, he was flanked on his right by Florida Coach Urban Meyer and Oklahoma Coach Bob Stoops, and Southern California Coach Pete Carroll stood to his left.</p>
        <p>Other coaches in attendance included Kansas' Mark Mangino and Colorado's Dan Hawkins.</p>
        <p>With each team able to call a recruit only once from April 15 to May 31 and not again until Sept. 1, the coaches jostled to be seen by Brown, possibly the best player from Wichita since the Hall of Fame running back Barry Sanders.</p>
        <p>''It's funny to see these coaches falling all over each other,'' Wichita East Coach Brian Byers said. ''It was kind of surreal to see them all standing in one spot. I don't know how often that happens.''</p>
        <p>The first linebacker to be rated by scout.com as the nation's best since Ernie Sims in 2003, Brown already has more than 50 scholarship offers. He plans to whittle that list to 10 universities by the second week of September and make his college choice by Dec. 1, his trainer, Brian Butler said.</p>
        <p>Brown is also considering the possibility of enrolling early at the university he selects so he can be on campus in spring 2008.</p>
        <p>''Pete Carroll said he's the best linebacker that he's seen in seven years,'' Butler said. ''Bob Stoops said he's going to win the Butkus Award two times.''</p>
        <p>Butler began training Brown three years ago after watching video of him devouring a fullback with a body-slam tackle in one of the four varsity games he played as a freshman at Wichita East.</p>
        <p>''I rewinded that play like 30 times,'' Butler said. ''It was pretty monstrous.''</p>
        <p>Although Brown is bigger than Sims, who went to Florida State and was a first-round pick in the 2006 N.F.L. draft by the Detroit Lions, there are ''unbelievable'' similarities between the two players, said Jamie Newberg, a national recruiting analyst for scout.com.</p>
        <p>''Arthur is an athletic freak,'' Newberg said. ''He is physical and quick. He is one of those rare guys. He's a beast.''</p>
        <p>Maize (Kan.) High School Coach Craig Broadbent, whose team faced Brown last year, said: ''It seems like he's in on every tackle. You've got to make sure you've got two people blocking him. He's all over the field. He's always high energy and full go.''</p>
        <p>Unlike most high-profile recruits, Brown does not have a cellphone, which shields him from the constant calls and endless text messaging from college coaches and Internet recruiting sites. He said that he received an average of 15 letters a day from coaches and tried to open at least one from each college.</p>
        <p>''It's overwhelming to me,'' said Brown, whose uncle Lawrence Pete, a former Nebraska nose tackle, played in the N.F.L. for five years.</p>
        <p>Brown's not having a cellphone has not stopped coaches from calling Butler. In each of the past two months, he said he had exceeded his cellphone's monthly allotment of 2,500 minutes, despite having a plan with free nights and weekends.</p>
        <p>''That had never happened before,'' Butler said.</p>
        <p>Brown, a 3.0 student, said that he intended to make unofficial visits to Arkansas, Florida, Florida State, Louisiana State, Mississippi and Oklahoma State this summer. He has made unofficial visits to Kansas State and Oklahoma. He said that the Sooners were recruiting him the most. Many recruiting experts believe Oklahoma is at the top of his list.</p>
        <p>In addition to the Sooners, Brown said that Arkansas, Florida State, Miami, Notre Dame, North Carolina and U.S.C. were recruiting him heavily.</p>
        <p>''I look at the recruits that each school is bringing in,'' Brown said. ''As a great athlete, you also want to be surrounded by other great athletes.''</p>
        <p>Last month's star-studded gathering of college coaches was big news in Wichita. It made the local television news, and a photograph of Carroll, Hawkins, Meyer and Stoops appeared on the front page of The Wichita Eagle's sports section.</p>
        <p>The attention that Brown receives may also help Wichita.</p>
        <p>''People think we're out in the cow pasture way out in the corn,'' said the chief executive of the Greater Wichita Area Sports Commission, Bob Hanson.</p>
        <p>''But we are a progressive city. We do get some athletes out of here, and it does bring a lot of pride to our city and it creates an awareness throughout the country.''</p>
        <p>The spotlight on Wichita is unlikely to subside once Brown departs for college. As talented as he is, many recruiting experts say that his younger brother, Bryce, a class of 2009 running back, is a better prospect. Bryce Brown rushed for 2,039 yards and 26 touchdowns last season as a sophomore.</p>
        <p>The brothers share one of the two bedrooms in their family's 850-square-foot home and are already budding entrepreneurs. They make highlight tapes for other football prospects and send them to as many as five universities for $100, Brown said.</p>
        <p>The venture seems natural for two players whose football prowess is popular on YouTube.</p>
        <p>''They're not short on highlights at all,'' their coach, Byers, said.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
