<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>14 More American Servicemen Are Killed in Iraq, Most of Them by Makeshift Bombs</title>
    <meta content="04iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/world/middleeast/04iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852176"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE REACH OF WAR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E7DD1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1018" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>14 More American Servicemen Are Killed in Iraq, Most of Them by Makeshift Bombs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">14 More American Servicemen Are Killed in Iraq, Most of Them by Makeshift Bombs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD A. OPPEL Jr. and KHALID W. HASSAN; BAGHDAD; Muhanad Seloom contributed reporting from Baghdad, and Iraqi employees of The New York Times from Mosul, Hilla, Diyala and Kut.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hassan, Khalid W; Oppel, Richard A Jr; Seloom, Muhanad</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, June 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The pace of American troop deaths increased this weekend as 14 more servicemen were reported killed in Iraq, all but one from makeshift bombs that insurgents have been employing with greater lethality against American soldiers and armored vehicles. Twenty-one soldiers and an Iraqi interpreter were wounded.</p>
        <p>The makeshift bomb blasts were part of a brazen series of attacks throughout the country by Sunni Arab insurgents, Shiite fighters of the Mahdi Army and other gunmen using rifles, rockets, huge bombs and chlorine canisters. American forces suffered heavy casualties in and around Baghdad and in Sunni insurgent enclaves further north, while Iraqi and American forces took the offensive in Mahdi Army strongholds in Baghdad and southern Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>All but one of the deaths were the result of makeshift bombs, which insurgents have been employing with greater lethality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The pace of American troop deaths increased this weekend as 14 more servicemen were reported killed in Iraq, all but one from makeshift bombs that insurgents have been employing with greater lethality against American soldiers and armored vehicles. Twenty-one soldiers and an Iraqi interpreter were wounded.</p>
        <p>The makeshift bomb blasts were part of a brazen series of attacks throughout the country by Sunni Arab insurgents, Shiite fighters of the Mahdi Army and other gunmen using rifles, rockets, huge bombs and chlorine canisters. American forces suffered heavy casualties in and around Baghdad and in Sunni insurgent enclaves further north, while Iraqi and American forces took the offensive in Mahdi Army strongholds in Baghdad and southern Iraq.</p>
        <p>At least 15 American servicemen were killed in the first three days of June, a pace that exceeds the daily fatality rate in May, when 127 troops were killed. May was the deadliest month since the invasion of Falluja in November 2004.</p>
        <p>In the northern city of Mosul, a Christian priest was gunned down as he left his church after Sunday services. In Baghdad, a director of the Iraqi Central Bank and his brother were shot to death in the dangerous neighborhood of Ameel. Thirty-one bodies were found scattered about the capital, where sectarian murders are once again on the rise.</p>
        <p>Insurgents struck repeatedly in Diyala, the militant-dominated province that borders Baghdad, Iran and Iraqi Kurdistan. A suicide car bomber parked at a crowded marketplace in Balad Ruz killed nine people and wounded 25, including seven children, the Iraqi police said. Insurgents set up a fake checkpoint near Baquba, the provincial capital, and raked a bus with gunfire, killing three. South of Baquba, nine bodies were found handcuffed and shot.</p>
        <p>A vehicle packed with explosives and chemicals detonated near the main American military installation in Diyala, Forward Operating Base Warhorse, just outside Baquba. No soldiers were hurt, but the military said many complained of ''minor respiratory irritations and watery eyes.''</p>
        <p>A Los Angeles Times journalist embedded with troops in Baquba reported that the explosion, 200 yards from the base entrance, released a cloud of chlorine that caused dizziness and nausea and sickened 62 people. An hour before the attack, mortar shells struck the base during lunchtime, wounding two soldiers while sending others rushing from the mess hall into bunkers.</p>
        <p>South of Baghdad in Diwaniya, a Mahdi Army commander led Iraqi police officers on a lengthy chase and eluded his pursuers before fierce fighting broke out that left at least three people dead and wounded 12 more, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>Ten Mahdi Army fighters were arrested in Numaniya, west of Kut, in what an Iraqi security official described as the latest offensive targeting Mahdi fighters. The police in Numaniya also discovered two bodies bearing signs of torture.</p>
        <p>American officials said soldiers killed four men and arrested six more caught setting up rockets to attack the Green Zone, the heavily fortified compound where the American leadership and Iraqi government is headquartered and which has come under increasing attack.</p>
        <p>Apache Longbow helicopters strafed the men setting up the rockets, and soldiers arrested six of them after they sought refuge in Sadr City, the vast Shiite enclave nearby.</p>
        <p>All of the troop deaths reported Sunday by the American military occurred in or around the capital, or in the Sunni Arab areas to the north including Diyala and Nineveh Provinces. The deadliest killed four soldiers on Sunday after their vehicle was struck by a roadside bomb as they took part in an operation to isolate an area northwest of Baghdad.</p>
        <p>The rising American death toll has been largely attributed to an increase in the number of troops and the operations that began three months ago with the plan to pacify Baghdad. But the roots of the worsening casualties go further back.</p>
        <p>Despite optimistic observations by the American government early in 2006, it had become clear by summer that Iraqi forces had proved incapable of curbing rising Shiite militia killings in Baghdad and the resilient Sunni Arab guerrillas who dominate parts of the capital and surrounding regions.</p>
        <p>American commanders ordered combat battalions to increase their presence in many of the areas of the capital where the militias and insurgents were strongest. American fatalities rose as a result.</p>
        <p>Not including the deaths so far in June, American forces have suffered an average of about 90 fatalities per month since they began more aggressively patrolling 10 months ago, according to an analysis of the fatalities tracked by Icasualties.org. That compares with about 65 deaths per month in the previous 10 months.</p>
        <p>The change is far grimmer in the areas where the American presence has increased the most. In Diyala, where large forces of Sunni insurgents have been battling thousands of American troops rushed in to calm raging violence, 78 Americans have been killed this year, compared with 20 in all of last year, according to Icasualties.org.</p>
        <p>American soldiers in Baghdad have been hit the worst: at least 192 Americans were killed in the capital in the first five months of this year, according to the data, compared with 81 in the same period last year.</p>
        <p>The biggest killers are roadside bombs, responsible for four of every five American deaths in combat during the past three months. That trend has continued in the past few days, according to the military.</p>
        <p>In addition to the four soldiers killed Sunday in the one bomb attack, two others were killed by bombs in the Baghdad area.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, two soldiers were killed by separate bombs in western Baghdad. Two soldiers in Nineveh Province died after their patrol was bombed. Two soldiers were killed in separate bombings in Diyala Province. A soldier from Task Force Marne was shot to death on patrol south of Baghdad.</p>
        <p>On Friday, a man killed an American soldier by detonating an explosive device as soldiers on foot patrol tried to question him and another man southwest of Baghdad, the military said.</p>
        <p>THE REACH OF WAR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
