<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Whistling Past The Graveyard As the Wait Goes On</title>
    <meta content="04vecsey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/04/sports/baseball/04vecsey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852214"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Clemens, Roger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3DD1130F937A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Whistling Past The Graveyard As the Wait Goes On</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Whistling Past the Graveyard as the Wait Goes On</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ev'rybody's in despair,</p>
        <p>Ev'ry girl and boy</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Roger Clemens has won some big games for the Yankees even with groin injuries, but at best, acquiring Clemens is a reminder of how bad off the Yankees are.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ev'rybody's in despair,</p>
        <p>Ev'ry girl and boy</p>
        <p>But when Quinn the Eskimo gets here,</p>
        <p>Ev'rybody's gonna jump for joy.</p>
        <p>Quinn the Eskimo (The Mighty Quinn), Bob Dylan</p>
        <p>That song has been on my mind for weeks, ever since Roger Clemens materialized from a balcony in Yankee Stadium, like some specter in ''Field of Dreams.''</p>
        <p>Back in the late '60s -- it seems like only yesterday -- we used to debate who Quinn the Eskimo actually was. Dylan was once quoted as saying the song referred to a role Anthony Quinn played in a movie, but you know Bob, he could have been goofing on us.</p>
        <p>One of my favorite Yippies had a mystical hallucination that Quinn the Eskimo was a reference to Gene McCarthy, coming to stop the war in Vietnam. But, as I said, those were the late '60s.</p>
        <p>Still, it's a great song, the idea of everybody waiting around for the Mighty Quinn to stomp into town in his seven-league boots and make things right again. We all need a Mighty Quinn in our lives.</p>
        <p>The Yankees have been in dire trouble all season, with players dropping on a daily basis, but signing old Roger the Rocket seemed to be the stuff of Yankees dynasties past, like bringing in Johnny Mize or Pedro Ramos just in time to win another pennant.</p>
        <p>Brian Cashman and Joe Torre did not promise any panacea, any cure-all.</p>
        <p>They just wanted five or six credible innings from the old Yankee (old Red Sox, old Blue Jay, old Astro), which would have been a whole lot better than what they were getting from their gaggle of younger pitchers.</p>
        <p>Now Clemens has tweaked his elderly body while rushing his latest comeback. The Yankees made do last night, beating the Red Sox, 6-5, on a ninth-inning home run by Alex Rodriguez at rain-spattered Fenway Park. Instead of pitching tonight in Chicago, Clemens will have a magnetic resonance imaging test today on his injured groin. Torre noted last night that Clemens had won some big games for him even with groin injuries, but at best, getting Clemens was a reminder of how bad off the Yankees are.</p>
        <p>''Everybody was definitely expecting him,'' Johnny Damon said, ''but if he's not right, it's better this way. He's not just showing up for the money. He's doing the right thing.''</p>
        <p>Obviously, the Yankees would have liked to have seen Clemens lumbering into Chicago tonight. They have had three young starting pitchers leave the field with injuries already this season, with Jason Giambi's chemically aided body apparently falling apart, and Doug Mientkiewicz, the first baseman who was making all the infielders look better, now out indefinitely with a fractured wrist, sprained neck and mild concussion sustained in a collision Saturday night. And last night, Andy Pettitte was taken out early because of tightness in his lower back.</p>
        <p>The Yankees need a shot in the arm, something more than having Clemens show up in Manhattan's Bryant Park during the telecast of a Yankees game last week like a Thanksgiving Day parade figure, a living totem pole, a reminder of championships past.</p>
        <p>Was it mostly a gesture to nostalgia that the Yankees made the call to Houston, where Clemens was deeply involved as a father, making peanut butter sandwiches for his kids, serving as class parent and taking out the garbage and cleaning out the gutters and performing other guy chores? The Yankees had to know that Roger needed the challenge, the psychic thrills, more than he needed to go over his kids' homework. The Yankees, whether they acknowledge it or not, needed their own personal Quinn the Eskimo.</p>
        <p>Nobody can get no sleep,</p>
        <p>There's someone on ev'ryone's toes</p>
        <p>But when Quinn the Eskimo gets here,</p>
        <p>Ev'rybody's gonna wanna doze.</p>
        <p>One thing Dylan never answered in his song was the motivation of Quinn the Eskimo. What was in it for him? In Clemens's case, there is the small matter of the prorated $28 million contract, although it does not kick in until he actually joins the Yanks. The motivation for Clemens to still be a force was enough to make him force his almost 45-year-old body to throw 102 pitches in his second minor league tuneup.</p>
        <p>The Yankees cannot be accused of piling too much responsibility on old Roger's broad shoulders. They didn't rush him into Boston to further heat up the normal fever pitch of Yankees-Red Sox meetings (Pedro flips Zim; Varitek encounters A-Rod; Proctor plugs Youkilis).</p>
        <p>Torre said that Clemens might indeed pitch by Saturday, depending on the M.R.I. In the meantime, the Yanks have Matt DeSalvo coming back from the minors if needed to start tonight.</p>
        <p>''We've had a habit of never counting our chickens,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Still, the Yankee fans, with their hard-wired memories of a glorious past, feel they deserve one more season-saving move, just as in the past. It is their due. But I've been thinking it over while the Dylan song was running through my addled mind the past few weeks: No matter how much Dylan praised him, there is no evidence that Quinn the Eskimo ever showed.</p>
        <p>Come all without, come all within,</p>
        <p>You'll not see nothing like the mighty Quinn.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
