<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Night Christopher Wheeldon Met Oscar Wilde</title>
    <meta content="11whee" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/arts/dance/11whee.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York City Ballet</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wheeldon, Christopher</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Whelan, Wendy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sheng, Bright</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mearns, Sara</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Pakledinaz, Martin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EEDF173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="597" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Night Christopher Wheeldon Met Oscar Wilde</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Night Christopher Wheeldon Met Oscar Wilde</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Christopher Wheeldon's new work, ''The Nightingale and the Rose,'' is mysterious, unwieldy and haunting. It is also one of his most beautiful and daringly imaginative works. But be warned: ''Nightingale'' may break your heart.</p>
        <p>This strange little ballet, given its world premiere by New York City Ballet on Friday at the New York State Theater, retells in stylized movement an Oscar Wilde fairy tale in which a nightingale agrees to bring a student a red rose for the spoiled young professor's daughter whom he loves. The bird flies through a nighttime garden, at first finding rose trees bearing only yellow and white blossoms. The trees direct her to a red-rose tree, but one too withered from winter to produce.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Christopher Wheeldon’s new work is one of his most beautiful and daringly imaginative works. But be warned: it may break your heart.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Christopher Wheeldon's new work, ''The Nightingale and the Rose,'' is mysterious, unwieldy and haunting. It is also one of his most beautiful and daringly imaginative works. But be warned: ''Nightingale'' may break your heart.</p>
        <p>This strange little ballet, given its world premiere by New York City Ballet on Friday at the New York State Theater, retells in stylized movement an Oscar Wilde fairy tale in which a nightingale agrees to bring a student a red rose for the spoiled young professor's daughter whom he loves. The bird flies through a nighttime garden, at first finding rose trees bearing only yellow and white blossoms. The trees direct her to a red-rose tree, but one too withered from winter to produce.</p>
        <p>If the nightingale wants a red rose, the tree tells her, she must let her life's blood flow into its veins. Though frightened and sad, the bird agrees, and the tree, limbs now stained red, produces the rose. But the young girl discards it, displeased by its scent, and the rose is tossed to the ground and hardly noticed by the student as he shruggingly steps over the nightingale's body.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wheeldon's nightingale is his muse, Wendy Whelan, and the ballet is a paean to her in all her astringent, peculiar beauty. There is nothing of ballet's exotic firebird or suffering swan queen here. Ms. Whelan is a bird in every preening arch, ground-pricking foot and tangle of jagged limbs, at every moment exuding a quiet modesty and watchful stillness. Mr. Wheeldon creates a complete world for her and the ballet. In this world a bird flies through a dark landscape swept with clouds and whirling roses and a moon looks down at the bird's loving last struggles and blinks back tears.</p>
        <p>The Wilde tale, a thing of complex and nuanced emotions, seems an odd choice for a ballet. And yet Mr. Wheeldon reinvents it in potent dance terms, capturing the deceptively childlike simplicity of the original, though this is a ballet that demands a preperformance reading of program notes. The commissioned score by Bright Sheng, City Ballet's resident composer, sets the atmosphere from its magical first moments, providing aural color and near-melodic climaxes that delicately support the ballet's emotional climaxes. It does not sweep or coax movement along. And Mr. Wheeldon is a choreographer who appears to live to stretch, working his way unassumingly from one to another meditation on the arts of dance and, by reflection, of life.</p>
        <p>''Nightingale'' contains one of Mr. Wheeldon's most tender and mysterious pas de deux, danced by Ms. Whelan, and by Tyler Angle, who plays the student. The duet is filled with trademark but always innovative partnering effects that quietly and respectfully bend and crumple the ballerina's body and stretch it along unexpected planes. The young girl, danced by Sara Mearns, is a device. Mr. Wheeldon is far more interested in getting a mass of gnarled tree limbs to move, in dance that confirms his invigorating choreographic breadth.</p>
        <p>Martin Pakledinaz's costuming for the bird has just the perfect small accent of exoticism. James Buckhouse's animation should at last make a case for animated set effects, so delicately symbiotic here with Mark Stanley's lighting. But in the end this is Mr. Wheeldon's show.</p>
        <p>Will this gnarled little rose of a ballet last? The heartfelt-sounding cheers and extended curtain calls on Friday night and Saturday afternoon suggested, perhaps surprisingly, that it will.</p>
        <p>''The Nightingale and the Rose'' repeats on Saturday night, Sunday afternoon and June 20 at the New York State Theater, Lincoln Center (212) 870-5570 or nycballet.com.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
