<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cotto's Knockout Victory Against Judah Fails to Impress Mayweather Jr.</title>
    <meta content="11boxing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/sports/othersports/11boxing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853824"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Mayweather, Floyd Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E3DD173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cotto's Knockout Victory Against Judah Fails to Impress Mayweather Jr.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cotto’s Knockout Victory Against Judah Fails to Impress Mayweather Jr.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Miguel Cotto's dominating victory against Zab Judah on Saturday night has lifted him to a new level of prominence. But he still lacks the leverage to earn the biggest fight out there: against Floyd Mayweather Jr., considered by many to be the best pound-for-pound boxer in the world.</p>
        <p>''Miguel Cotto ain't even in the same stratosphere as Floyd Mayweather,'' Leonard Ellerbe, an adviser to Mayweather, said yesterday by telephone. ''He's a good little young fighter. He makes a lot of mistakes. In time, as he gets better, he'll become a better fighter.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Floyd Mayweather Jr. has no incentive to fight Miguel Cotto, according to an advisor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Miguel Cotto's dominating victory against Zab Judah on Saturday night has lifted him to a new level of prominence. But he still lacks the leverage to earn the biggest fight out there: against Floyd Mayweather Jr., considered by many to be the best pound-for-pound boxer in the world.</p>
        <p>''Miguel Cotto ain't even in the same stratosphere as Floyd Mayweather,'' Leonard Ellerbe, an adviser to Mayweather, said yesterday by telephone. ''He's a good little young fighter. He makes a lot of mistakes. In time, as he gets better, he'll become a better fighter.''</p>
        <p>Ellerbe said that Cotto was not well known outside Puerto Rico and New York and that there would be no incentive for Mayweather to fight him, even though the bout could be an intriguing matchup.</p>
        <p>The difficulty of making a fight between Mayweather (38-0), a light-middleweight world champion, and Cotto (30-0), a welterweight world champion, underscores the revenue-driven mind-set that prevents many fights from happening.</p>
        <p>''Money makes fights,'' said Todd duBoef, the president of Top Rank, the company that promotes Cotto.</p>
        <p>After Mayweather's fight against Oscar De La Hoya on May 5 drew a record 2.15 million pay-per view purchases, Mayweather contends few opponents can generate the revenue he feels he is worth, Ellerbe said. For now, Mayweather is standing by his decision to retire, Ellerbe said, and is focusing on business ventures outside the sport.</p>
        <p>''We do fights that generate revenue in Las Vegas,'' Ellerbe said. ''Bob Arum can never make Floyd Mayweather an offer with anything.''</p>
        <p>Arum, the chairman of Top Rank, and duBoef may have a different viewpoint about Cotto's future after Saturday's bout.</p>
        <p>Fighting in Madison Square Garden on the eve of the Puerto Rican Day Parade for the third consecutive year, Cotto gave the capacity crowd the excitement it wanted. He went after Judah relentlessly, damaging him with sweeping shots to the body and head from close range.</p>
        <p>Judah (34-5) added to the excitement by withstanding Cotto's power and stunning him on several occasions during the fight. .</p>
        <p>Cotto dropped Judah with low blows in the first and third rounds. Judah said those shots affected him throughout the fight, and the referee, Arthur Mercante Jr., deducted a point from Cotto after the second one.</p>
        <p>But Cotto's legal blows eventually overpowered Judah. In the final four rounds, Cotto landed 90 power punches to Judah's 24. Cotto dropped Judah on his back with a combination of right and left hooks early in the 11th round. Cotto then backed Judah into the ropes and rendered him defenseless with punishing punches, forcing Mercante to stop the fight. Cotto was leading, 97-91, on all three scorecards when the fight was stopped.</p>
        <p>Both fighters were badly bruised. Judah had a severely swollen right eye and was unable to see. Cotto had cuts over his right eye, on his forehead and on his lower lip.</p>
        <p>''That's the toughest fight of my career,'' Cotto said.</p>
        <p>Cotto's face might have taken a beating, duBoef said, but his reputation as a fighter could not be more polished.</p>
        <p>''Everybody that walked away from this event is saying one thing: A star has just arrived,'' duBoef said.</p>
        <p>Persuading Mayweather to believe in Cotto's pay-per-view power could be a challenge. Cotto is not well known to casual sports fans. His popularity lags behind that of his fellow Puerto Rican Félix Trinidad, who Ellerbe said was a big enough star to earn a fight with Mayweather.</p>
        <p>Until Cotto becomes better known, Ellerbe said, he will not be a profitable opponent for Mayweather.</p>
        <p>With or without Mayweather, duBoef said, Cotto is legitimate.</p>
        <p>''I don't chase the money,'' duBoef said. ''I create the money.''</p>
        <p>Judah was asking for a rematch after the fight. But it seems more likely that Cotto will go for someone fresh, probably the World Boxing Organization welterweight champion, Antonio Margarito, if Margarito defeats Paul Williams next month. DuBoef also named Ricky Hatton, Jose Luis Castillo, Kermit Cintron and Shane Mosley as possible opponents.</p>
        <p>''I don't have a choice of anyone,'' Cotto said. ''I'm prepared for everybody in 147 pounds.''</p>
        <p>BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
