<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Few Details of the iPhone Galvanize the Apple Cadre</title>
    <meta content="11iphone" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/technology/11iphone.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853733"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">iPhone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blogs and Blogging (Internet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blogs and Blogging (Internet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Apple Inc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">TBWA/Chiat/Day</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E2DF173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="707" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Few Details of the iPhone Galvanize the Apple Cadre</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Few Details of the iPhone Galvanize the Apple Cadre</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ADAM NEWMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>These days advertisers fret over DVR owners fast-forwarding through their commercials, but that was far from the case with the release by Apple last week of four iPhone commercials, which viewers pored over with Talmudic intensity.</p>
        <p>The product was announced in January, and some teaser ads for it ran during the Academy Awards ceremonies in February. Last week, three new television commercials for the iPhone divulged the product's release date -- June 29 -- and showed off a range of features that led Apple fans to seek more details.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last week viewers pored over four iPhone commercials with Talmudic intensity, trying to determine precisely how the phone will operate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>These days advertisers fret over DVR owners fast-forwarding through their commercials, but that was far from the case with the release by Apple last week of four iPhone commercials, which viewers pored over with Talmudic intensity.</p>
        <p>The product was announced in January, and some teaser ads for it ran during the Academy Awards ceremonies in February. Last week, three new television commercials for the iPhone divulged the product's release date -- June 29 -- and showed off a range of features that led Apple fans to seek more details.</p>
        <p>While the ad campaign, by TBWA/Chiat/Day, highlighted some functions, the individual commercials are being parsed to determine precisely how the phone will operate. In a typical post, Erica Sadun on the Unofficial Apple Weblog (www.tuaw.com) extrapolated how the device's e-mail and map search functions might work, based on the mere seconds that each function was shown in the commercials.</p>
        <p>At Macenstein.com, a ''Dr. Macenstein'' wrote on June 3 that for a moment in one of the ads, the iPhone's screen had 12 icons, each representing a function, where earlier promotional material featured only 11. What was this ''mystery'' application, he wondered, and then said four days later that the 12-icon shot had been edited out of the same commercial featured on apple.com.</p>
        <p>Many bloggers also wrote that fine print initially appearing in ads -- which said that iPhone purchasers would be locked into a "minimum new two-year activation plan" with AT&amp;T  -- was absent from similar ads posted on apple.com, leading, of course, to speculation whether iPhone buyers would have to sign such a contract. An Apple spokesman declined to comment on an AT&amp;T plan or any other aspect of the iPhone or its commercials.</p>
        <p>It is typical for Apple to remain silent, even if speaking up would quash rumors, said Tim Beyers, who wrote about the iPhone ads for the Motley Fool (fool.com). ''When Apple does nothing to stop rumors from circulating, the feeding frenzy gets more and more intense,'' Mr. Beyers said. ''They like to allow the pot to be stirred and not to disturb it, just like a fine sauce simmering. The nature of Apple is that by virtue of the fact that they talk sparingly, they get talked about -- they create this almost audible buzz.''</p>
        <p>After Apple's initial announcement in January, ''Late Night With Conan O'Brien'' broadcast a fake iPhone commercial in which the device was used in myriad ways, including as a bottle opener, electric shaver, blow-dryer and condiment dispenser. In one picture, it helped give a pregnant woman a sonogram.</p>
        <p>Forensics on the real iPhone commercials included sleuthing by Taylor Johnston, who writes about music on his Web site, musicforants.com. Mr. Johnston, who just finished his junior year at Illinois State University, focused on a segment of one ad where the user scrolls quickly through his music library, noting performers like Beck and Lily Allen.</p>
        <p>''If you look closely, though, there's a wealth of other good music that the iPhone is playing,'' said Mr. Johnston, who praised Apple for featuring indie-rock darlings like Feist and Clap Your Hands Say Yeah over mainstream chart-toppers.</p>
        <p>''I'm a huge Apple geek,'' he said in an interview. ''I don't think there's any product out there where people are so attached to the company. You can like Snickers bars, but you're not going to be scouring the Internet for all the information you can get about a Snickers bar.''</p>
        <p>Pacific Catch, a restaurant in San Francisco whose phone number appeared momentarily in one of the iPhone ads, averaged 100 extra calls a day the next week, the general manager, Rob Schechtman, said. Apple's ad agency got the restaurant's permission beforehand.</p>
        <p>Calls came from as far away as Africa and included a collect call from a county jail; the restaurant did not accept the charges.</p>
        <p>''I assume he saw the commercial and maybe wanted to know if we delivered,'' Mr. Schechtman said.</p>
        <p>Most callers are merely curious if it is a real restaurant, while others are more persistent. ''Some people ask about the iPhone -- when it was coming out and how much it would cost,'' Mr. Schechtman said. ''And I say, 'We're a restaurant, not an Apple Store.' '' The restaurant's computer system, he said, is actually PC-based.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
