<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>We Have Always Depended On Strangeness of Families</title>
    <meta content="11heff" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/arts/television/11heff.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853756"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Home Box Office</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Paxton, Bill</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Tripplehorn, Jeanne</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sevigny, Chloe</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EFDF173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>We Have Always Depended On Strangeness of Families</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">We Have Always Depended on Strangeness of Families</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIRGINIA HEFFERNAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three HBO tragedies have comedic set-ups. A middle-class mob boss seeks therapy. A groovy Los Angeles family lives in a mortuary. And, most recently, a Utah entrepreneur has three wives.</p>
        <p>The last series is ''Big Love,'' known in shorthand as the Mormon polygamy show, which returns for its second season tonight. It's ingenious, HBO's latest dark joke, and it investigates the same theme of family separatism that ''The Sopranos'' and ''Six Feet Under'' did. But let's not kid ourselves. The quality of ''Big Love'' doesn't even matter, does it?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Big Love” derives suspense, humor and thrills from HBO’s signature insight: that Americans are profoundly anxious about how their families are different from other families.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three HBO tragedies have comedic set-ups. A middle-class mob boss seeks therapy. A groovy Los Angeles family lives in a mortuary. And, most recently, a Utah entrepreneur has three wives.</p>
        <p>The last series is ''Big Love,'' known in shorthand as the Mormon polygamy show, which returns for its second season tonight. It's ingenious, HBO's latest dark joke, and it investigates the same theme of family separatism that ''The Sopranos'' and ''Six Feet Under'' did. But let's not kid ourselves. The quality of ''Big Love'' doesn't even matter, does it?</p>
        <p>The truth is, we have no choice but to watch, at least during this difficult time. ''Big Love'' is like Nicorette or Methadone. With the lights out on ''The Sopranos,'' and ''Six Feet Under'' a distant memory, we're dope-sick, hard up for the bliss of great serialized fiction. A widespread tremor can already be detected among television viewers, and the street price of even midgrade drama has jumped.</p>
        <p>So unless we rediscover novels or fresh air, we're going to be watching some ''Big Love'' this summer.</p>
        <p>Fortunately it's good. Like the fledgling ''John From Cincinnati'' but with fewer side effects, ''Big Love'' derives suspense, humor and thrills from HBO's signature insight: that Americans are profoundly anxious about how their families are different from other families. The criminal Sopranos, the macabre Fishers, now the polygamous Henricksons: these great inventions of the collective HBO imagination and production schedule live bunkered in their crazy houses (each an architectural masterpiece) simultaneously fearing and hoping that someone with authority greater than theirs will come to smash their doors down and impose order.</p>
        <p>Those houses! What will we do without Tony and Carmela Soprano's bright suburban dream house with its fat open secrets, from which traces of guilt had always just been laboriously expunged? It was so airy and porous. Tony never should have left. And then what of the Fishers' gothic pile, with its retro crypts and secret passages and small scrubbed spaces where odd things (drugs, body parts) were always being stashed?</p>
        <p>So now we have the Henricksons' house. A tripartite wonder (Triune? The question certainly seems theological) that looks like three households from the sidewalk but becomes one when the backyards merge. The casual observer would believe that the real Henricksons, Bill (Bill Paxton) and Barb (Jeanne Tripplehorn), live on the far left, with Nicki (Chloë Sevigny) in the middle, and Margene (Ginnifer Goodwin) to the right. All of the Henricksons -- and there are seven children among them -- keep up the appearance of propriety while begging to be exposed.</p>
        <p>Sound familiar? The Sopranos and Fishers used to invite people into their strange mansions too, and virtually plead with them to capsize the whole fragile order. Our families scare us, it seems; we want rescue. And this insight at HBO is daring: Once, long ago, or so the novels tell us, it was individuals who used to worry about their oddness and perverse longings. Family in those days seemed like the great normalizer.</p>
        <p>But now an individual's love of skinny girls or klezmer can readily be shared on the Internet, and no one these days feels quite so solitary as in the days of existentialism. On the contrary, while individual souls find checks and balances on their idiosyncrasies in cyberspace, the strangeness of families seems to deepen, with a family's creepy, out-of-step food preparations (or décor) or religious practices (or accent) turning almost actionable.</p>
        <p>To judge from the compulsiveness with which people watch and discuss HBO dramas on this topic, then, Americans believe that as families they live at least unconventionally, and possibly immorally or illegally. They're not sure they want to persist this way, but they're also not sure they want to get caught.</p>
        <p>In this season of ''Big Love'' Bill's minor dynasty -- his reputation and his small chain of home-supply stores -- is once again under assault from both the mainstream Mormons in Salt Lake City, who see his polygamy as fundamentalist and thus bad for their image, and the powerful cult called Juniper Creek, led by Roman Grant (the formidable Harry Dean Stanton), one of Bill's fathers-in-law.</p>
        <p>The family is no less fractious. Barb is not sure why she got into this; she seems a figure for any woman who has pursued her love for her husband too far: moved to the wrong place, had too many children or too few, stopped working or never started. In the meantime Ms. Sevigny has turned Nicki into the showpiece character of the series: the Carmela. She is irritable, witchy, phony and supremely capable by turns. She also has a serious debt problem.</p>
        <p>Where Tony Soprano had panic attacks, murderous outbursts and waves of oceanic despair, Bill Henrickson tends to heave sighs and say things like, ''I'm having one of those days.'' But the tension is just as high. And when a snitch is murdered early in the season, it's clear that the Great Salt Lake is not as far from Jersey as it might seem.</p>
        <p>Big Love</p>
        <p>HBO, tonight at 9, Eastern and Pacific times; 8, Central time.</p>
        <p>Created by Mark V. Olsen and Will Scheffer; Tom Hanks, Gary Goetzman, Mark V. Olsen, Will Scheffer and David Knoller, executive producers; Mimi Friedman and Jeanette Collins, supervising producers; Bernadette Caulfield and Doug Jung, producers; Dustin Lance Black and Eileen Myers, executive story editors; Jennifer Schuur and Douglas Stockstill, staff writers; casting by Junie Lowry Johnson and Libby Goldstein. Written by Mark V. Olsen and Will Scheffer; directed by Daniel Minahan. Produced by HBO Entertainment in association with Playtone and Anima Sola Productions.</p>
        <p>WITH: Bill Paxton (Bill), Jeanne Tripplehorn (Barb), Chloë Sevigny (Nicki), Ginnifer Goodwin (Margene) and Harry Dean Stanton (Roman).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
