<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At 295, Glavine Is Suddenly in a Tough Spot</title>
    <meta content="11mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/sports/baseball/11mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853838"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Detroit Tigers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Glavine, Tom</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DD173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="987" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At 295, Glavine Is Suddenly in a Tough Spot</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Path to 300 Wins Gets Rocky for Glavine</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, June 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tom Glavine lay on the Comerica Park grass, his body contorted in a position as uncomfortable as his afternoon. He had just flipped a ball to the backstop, giving Detroit yet another run, and his momentum caused him to tumble forward so that his knees touched his nose. He stayed there for a few seconds, stuck in a moment he could not escape, then rose to one knee and gazed toward the outfield.</p>
        <p>Before allowing nine earned runs in the Mets' 15-7 loss to the Tigers on Sunday, Glavine could have counted on his thumb the number of times in his previous 648 starts that he had given up that many. He also permitted 11 hits in four and a third innings, his shortest outing since last July. Another chance to inch closer to 300 career victories came and went.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Tigers, unnerved by getting shut out Friday for the first time this season, pounded 11 hits and scored nine runs off of starter Tom Glavine in two and two-thirds innings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tom Glavine lay on the Comerica Park grass, his body contorted in a position as uncomfortable as his afternoon. He had just flipped a ball to the backstop, giving Detroit yet another run, and his momentum caused him to tumble forward so that his knees touched his nose. He stayed there for a few seconds, stuck in a moment he could not escape, then rose to one knee and gazed toward the outfield.</p>
        <p>Before allowing nine earned runs in the Mets' 15-7 loss to the Tigers on Sunday, Glavine could have counted on his thumb the number of times in his previous 648 starts that he had given up that many. He also permitted 11 hits in four and a third innings, his shortest outing since last July. Another chance to inch closer to 300 career victories came and went.</p>
        <p>Stuck at 295 since May 24, Glavine (5-4) had pitched well enough to win in each of his previous three starts, but he was done in by poor run support, the Mets having scored two runs during his 20 innings. Staked to a three-run lead Sunday before even throwing a pitch, Glavine gave it back by the third inning and then surrendered five more runs in the fifth.</p>
        <p>Not since May 24, 1999, when Milwaukee scored nine runs against him in two and two-thirds innings, had Glavine endured an outing as miserable statistically as this one. To reach 300 victories by the All-Star Game break, Glavine must win his next five starts, starting with one next weekend against the surging Yankees.</p>
        <p>''I'm getting tired of talking about the whole 300 thing because I get the sense that's all everyone thinks I care about, and I don't,'' Glavine said. ''It's the furthest thing from my mind right now. I go out there to pitch to help us win.</p>
        <p>''It's frustrating regardless of where you are if you're pitching well and your team is not winning games. And it's equally frustrating when I'm standing here as an individual and haven't been a part of winning in a month. That's not fun, regardless of where I am in terms of personal goals.''</p>
        <p>The Mets have lost six of their past seven games and three consecutive series. They are heading into the most challenging portion of their schedule as their pitching is starting to stagger and their offense is stirring.</p>
        <p>For the second consecutive game, the Mets scored seven runs, and it was not enough. Glavine was followed by Aaron Sele and Joe Smith, who combined to allow 6 runs and 10 hits in three and two-thirds innings.</p>
        <p>''I told Joe Smith that Jesus Christ could have been pitching today and they were going to get some hits,'' Mets catcher Paul Lo Duca said.</p>
        <p>After being shut out Friday for the first time this season, the Tigers pounded Mets pitchers for 33 hits and 23 runs over the next two games. This month, they have scored fewer than eight runs only twice, and they played Sunday without the injured slugger Magglio Ordóñez. Another offensive force, Carlos Guillén, left in the third inning with a hamstring injury.</p>
        <p>In their absence, Gary Sheffield went 4 for 5 with a home run and two runs batted in, missing the cycle by a double, while Brandon Inge went 3 for 4 with a homer and five R.B.I.</p>
        <p>''Back there, I couldn't figure it out,'' Lo Duca said of his perspective behind the plate. ''I was putting down the wrong fingers, I guess.''</p>
        <p>David Wright homered for the fourth consecutive game, a three-run blast to right against Detroit starter Andrew Miller that gave the Mets a 3-0 lead in the first inning. But they did not score again until the sixth, when Carlos Gómez hit the first home run of his career, also a three-run shot. In between, the Tigers scored 10 runs.</p>
        <p>With two outs in the first, Glavine allowed a home run to Sheffield, his sixth in 56 at-bats against him. The Tigers added a run in the second on Inge's two-out single. He nearly escaped the third, but after getting ahead, 0-2, on Omar Infante, he walked him. That brought up Iván Rodríguez, who lined a two-run triple to right-center.</p>
        <p>''You always feel it when you walk guys like that,'' Mets Manager Willie Randolph said.</p>
        <p>The Mets' dismal fifth began with a single, continued with a triple and a flyout before Infante pushed what Glavine called a perfect squeeze bunt up the first-base line.</p>
        <p>With no play at first, Glavine tossed underhand to Lo Duca, but the ball flew past him, pushing Sheffield home with the Tigers' sixth run. Rodríguez followed with a double to right and Sean Casey then hit a two-run single.</p>
        <p>Randolph went to the mound. No words were exchanged. Randolph stuck out his hand. Glavine gave him the ball and with steady, purposeful strides headed into the dugout, another loss for him and the Mets on its way.</p>
        <p>''I made some mistakes, and they made me pay for them,'' Glavine said. ''I made some good pitches, and they hit them, too.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Shawn Green (broken bone in right foot) said that he was ready to return Sunday, but Willie Randolph decided to give him another day to regain his timing before activating him Monday in Los Angeles. ''An extra day won't hurt him,'' Randolph said. The news is not nearly as uplifting for Moises Alou, who returned to New York as team doctors attempt to discover why it has taken him so long to recover from a quadriceps strain that was initially expected to sideline him for the minimum 15 days. Alou had been with the team during the nine-game homestand but is expected to return to Port St. Lucie, Fla., to continue receiving treatment.  Damion Easley returned to the lineup at second base after missing four games with a sore right knee.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
