<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Forget Tickling the Keys, It's All About the Power</title>
    <meta content="11fest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/arts/music/11fest.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853759"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Aimard, Pierre-Laurent</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDF173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="582" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Forget Tickling the Keys, It's All About the Power</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Forget Tickling the Keys, It’s All About the Power</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD HOLLAND</byline>
      <dateline>OJAI, Calif., June 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Behind the rise of the all-powerful Romantic movement was the piano and its essential paradox: a percussion instrument (hit it, and it makes noise) that would be tamed and stroked until it sang like the human voice. By the 1920s music had had enough of this romance and returned the instrument to its primary nature: hit it, and it sounds like a drum.</p>
        <p>The French pianist Pierre-Laurent Aimard, who thought up this year's Ojai Festival, has made the piano-as-percussion one of his principal policies. A duo-piano concert with Helena Bugallo and Amy Williams on Thursday night spent half its time doing violence to the instrument's lyrical tradition and the rest acknowledging the closeness of nature in these unnaturally beautiful surroundings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The French pianist Pierre-Laurent Aimard, who thought up this year’s Ojai Festival, has made the piano-as-percussion one of his principal policies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Behind the rise of the all-powerful Romantic movement was the piano and its essential paradox: a percussion instrument (hit it, and it makes noise) that would be tamed and stroked until it sang like the human voice. By the 1920s music had had enough of this romance and returned the instrument to its primary nature: hit it, and it sounds like a drum.</p>
        <p>The French pianist Pierre-Laurent Aimard, who thought up this year's Ojai Festival, has made the piano-as-percussion one of his principal policies. A duo-piano concert with Helena Bugallo and Amy Williams on Thursday night spent half its time doing violence to the instrument's lyrical tradition and the rest acknowledging the closeness of nature in these unnaturally beautiful surroundings.</p>
        <p>The two pianists sat on their hands for Ligeti's ''Poème Symphonique'' in which a reported 100 metronomes (I didn't count them) were set off around the edges of Libbey Bowl's outdoor premises and allowed slowly to tick themselves to death. Those less interested in deep thoughts about the passage of life and its alternative had the coarser pleasures of a passive demolition derby. The surviving handful of swinging mechanical arms at the end made a touching kind of coda.</p>
        <p>Friday night returned listeners to 20th-century music's two great adventures in keyboard banging, the Sonata for Two Pianos and Percussion by Bartok and ''Les Noces'' by Stravinsky: four pianos, more percussion and lots of singing. On both evenings there was music by Peter Eotvos, the Hungarian musician long active in Paris who is this year's featured composer and conductor.</p>
        <p>Ojai performances are used to ad libitum contributions by birds, insects and frogs: some antithetical to the music being played, others strangely congruent with it. Salvatore Sciarrino's Sonata for Two Pianos on Thursday offered a parade of gentle twitters and buzzing passagework; Mr. Eotvos's ''Cricketmusic'' replaced local talent with his own recorded arrangements of natural sounds of the night.</p>
        <p>The piano writing identified Mr. Eotvos as the opera composer he is. Expressive with a tilt toward extravagance, his music throws out big contrasts of color, speed, volume and weight. Every device and gesture tugs at the listener's sleeve for immediate attention. Mr. Eotvos's ''Sonata per Sei'' on Friday confirmed his complex, somewhat verbose and unashamed theatrical style, racing keyboard parts set against a department store of exotic percussions effects: gongs, chimes, cymbals, scraped sheets of metal.</p>
        <p>Perhaps setting Mr. Eotvos's music next to some of Bartok's greatest was unfair. Bartok's Sonata for Two Pianos and Percussion manages monastic dignity and unassailable economies of means even as his music moves from wild to abrasive to tender. (Never forget that Bartok considered himself in the tradition of Liszt.) Mr. Aimard and Tamara Stefanovich were the splendid pianists; Bob Becker's xylophone playing was a delight.</p>
        <p>Thursday's two-piano arrangements of Stravinsky's Septet and ''Dumbarton Oaks'' Concerto are by the composer but miss the site-specific colors of the originals. Both sounded gray next to ''Les Noces,'' Stravinsky's peasant wedding scene that celebrates -- no, explodes with -- life. The vocal lines trip over one another with a wonderful exuberance. Everyone involved seemed to embrace a composer too often thought of in intellectual terms and not as the volcano of life force that he actually was.</p>
        <p>Susan Narucki, Jennifer Roderer, John Aler and Kevin Short sang the solos, and the Los Angeles Master Chorale was master of this Stravinsky's very difficult music. The festival's four pianists were all in harness. Mr. Eotvos is, if nothing else, a first-rate conductor.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
