<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Box Office for Horror Movies Is Weak, Verging on Horrible</title>
    <meta content="11hostel" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/movies/11hostel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070612T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853731"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Box Office</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Roth, Eli</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE3DF173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="533" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Box Office for Horror Movies Is Weak, Verging on Horrible</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Box Office for Horror Movies Is Weak, Verging on Horrible</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL CIEPLY</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, June 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Moviegoers put a nail in the coffin of a dying horror boom this weekend, as ''Hostel: Part II'' opened to just $8.8 million in ticket sales, far behind the crime caper ''Ocean's Thirteen'' in a three-day period of relatively soft box office performance.</p>
        <p>''Ocean's Thirteen,'' with a cast of stars led by George Clooney and Brad Pitt, ranked first with $37.1 million, slightly underperforming its predecessor, ''Ocean's Twelve.'' That film took in about $39.2 million when Warner Brothers released it in December 2004 and went on to collect more than $125.5 million in domestic ticket sales.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Moviegoers put a nail in the coffin of a dying horror boom over the weekend, as “Hostel: Part II” opened far behind the crime caper “Ocean’s Thirteen.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Moviegoers put a nail in the coffin of a dying horror boom this weekend, as ''Hostel: Part II'' opened to just $8.8 million in ticket sales, far behind the crime caper ''Ocean's Thirteen'' in a three-day period of relatively soft box office performance.</p>
        <p>''Ocean's Thirteen,'' with a cast of stars led by George Clooney and Brad Pitt, ranked first with $37.1 million, slightly underperforming its predecessor, ''Ocean's Twelve.'' That film took in about $39.2 million when Warner Brothers released it in December 2004 and went on to collect more than $125.5 million in domestic ticket sales.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile ''Hostel: Part II,'' a torture-theme thriller from the director Eli Roth, placed No. 6 for the weekend and did less than half the opening business of the original ''Hostel.'' That movie made about $19.6 million in its first weekend when Lionsgate released it in January of last year and helped feed a wave of horror releases that have often come up short.</p>
        <p>In the last few months the Weinstein Company's ''Grindhouse'' failed its own hype as a hip event, Fox Atomic's higher-browed zombie film ''28 Weeks Later'' undershot its predecessor, and a long string of less ambitious horror pictures sputtered as the audience for bigger, family-friendly pictures like ''Spider-Man 3,'' ''Pirates of the Caribbean: At World's End'' and ''Shrek the Third'' led a broad surge in ticket sales.</p>
        <p>Lionsgate, although it releases films in a variety of genres, had done especially well with relatively low-budget horror in the recent past. Its ''Saw III,'' for instance, took in about $165 million at the worldwide box office last year, while the original ''Hostel'' had about $81 million in ticket sales around the world.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of like that Mark Twain quote, 'Reports of my death are greatly exaggerated,' '' said Mark Burns, vice chairman of Lionsgate. ''Everything takes a breather.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Burns attributed the weakening performance of horror to a marketplace glut rather than to any growing revulsion to the genre's excesses or a backlash against violence in the wake of the Virginia Tech killings, as some have suggested. He said his studio, which is co-releasing ''Captivity'' with After Dark Films in July and has a fourth ''Saw'' scheduled for October, had already de-emphasized its reliance on the genre because of too much competition.</p>
        <p>Total business for the weekend's Top 12 films was down 9.1 percent from the comparable weekend last year, when Disney's ''Cars'' opened, according to the box-office reporting firm Media by Numbers. Disney's ''Pirates'' fell 52 percent to finish second with $21.3 million for the weekend and a total of $253.6 million; Universal's ''Knocked Up'' was third with $20 million, down 35 percent, and a total of $66.2 million; ''Surf's Up,'' a new release from Sony Pictures, was fourth with $18 million; and ''Shrek the Third,'' from DreamWorks and Paramount, was fifth with $15.8 million, for a total of $281.9 million.</p>
        <p>''We did our share,'' said Dan Fellman, Warner Brothers' president for theatrical distribution, noting that the year-to-date box office remains ''very strong.'' Revenue, thanks in part to higher ticket prices, is up about 5 percent -- a significant amount -- to almost $4 billion so far. Attendance meanwhile is up about 1 percent</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 12, 2007, Tuesday  An article in The Arts yesterday about the leading movies in ticket sales over the weekend misstated the given name of the vice chairman of Lionsgate, who commented on the recent decline in sales for horror films like ''Hostel: Part II,'' which ranked sixth over the weekend. He is Michael Burns, not Mark.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 12, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article in The Arts yesterday about the leading movies in ticket sales over the weekend misstated the given name of the vice chairman of Lionsgate, who commented on the recent decline in sales for horror films like ''Hostel: Part II,'' which ranked sixth over the weekend. He is Michael Burns, not Mark.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
