<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cautious Optimism on Stem Cells</title>
    <meta content="l11stem" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853787"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stem Cells</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E4DE173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="638" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cautious Optimism on Stem Cells</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Biologists Make Skin Cells Work Like Stem Cells'' (front page, June 7):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Biologists Make Skin Cells Work Like Stem Cells'' (front page, June 7):</p>
        <p>If it turns out that the technique developed by Dr. Shinya Yamanaka can be successfully applied in human beings, not just in mice, it will indeed revolutionize the debate over therapeutic cloning.</p>
        <p>Few people would argue in favor of creating embryos to be harvested for their stem cells if this alternative were available. Let's all hope it works out that way.</p>
        <p>Therapeutic cloning has always been ethically and morally troubling, justified only by the absence of an alternative means of obtaining medically useful immature stem cells. But let's not rush to judgment just yet. Plenty of laboratory ''breakthroughs'' turn out not to work outside the highly controlled laboratory setting.</p>
        <p>It will require years of further research first to verify Dr. Yamanaka's findings and then to determine whether his method can actually help treat human patients.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, opponents of therapeutic cloning should not be allowed to use Dr. Yamanaka's work as justification for a ban that would foreclose valuable medical treatments in the mere hope that others less troubling to their moral convictions may someday be available.</p>
        <p>Eric B. Lipps  Staten Island, June 7, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>This is truly groundbreaking research, but it is quite unclear whether such cells will be generally useful for human therapeutics. As noted for Dolly the sheep, the first cloned mammal, significant nuclear reprogramming is possible but so far has been incomplete, as evidenced by Dolly's shortened life span. Nevertheless, availability of more types of cells will promote research.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, the maximal flexibility and developmental potential of embryonic stem cells make them incomparable sources for the most wide range of therapeutic applications.</p>
        <p>Thus, this is a research breakthrough, but it is unlikely to translate directly into therapeutic application of stem cells in patients. Therefore, it is important to continue to be vigilant in overturning President Bush's edict restricting embryonic stem cell research in the United States, so we can catch up with scientists in most of the rest of the world.</p>
        <p>Martin Grumet  Piscataway, N.J., June 7, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is professor and director, W. M. Keck Center for Collaborative Neuroscience at Rutgers University.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Some hail the development of a new method to derive stem cells as an ethical triumph because it averts the killing of embryos. But as embryo research advocates have long observed, conventional in vitro fertilization intrinsically entails the mass destruction of excess embryos and the injection of heart-stopping potassium chloride into the hearts of excess implanted embryos.</p>
        <p>Hence, a new stem cell source solves nothing. The commodification, selection and mass destruction of life in the I.V.F. marts will continue unabated -- using billions of public health insurance dollars -- until the culture sees I.V.F. as the covert, creeping techno-eugenic nightmare it has become.</p>
        <p>Mark Oshinskie  Highland Park, N.J., June 8, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>If the president is truly concerned about forcing taxpayers to support initiatives to which they are morally opposed, he might want to consider the fact that a large number of American taxpayers, very much against their will, are currently compelled to support both state-sponsored death by execution and the pre-emptive invasion of a country that did not directly threaten us.</p>
        <p>Clearly, all taxpayers are not equal in our president's eyes when it comes to moral concerns.</p>
        <p>Geoff Munger  New Canaan, Conn., June 7, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I wonder if those who so ardently oppose the financing of stem cell research -- including President Bush -- would stick to their self-righteous principles and decline a stem cell cure if it was the only hope of saving them from a terminal disease. I strongly doubt it.</p>
        <p>John Blumenthal  Westlake Village, Calif.  June 7, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
