<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yankees Keep Smashing Their Way Toward .500</title>
    <meta content="11yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/sports/baseball/11yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853823"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Pittsburgh Pirates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Pittsburgh Pirates</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Abreu, Bobby</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E3DD173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yankees Keep Smashing Their Way Toward .500</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Yankees Keep Smashing Their Way Toward .500</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The offense was relentless and merciless yesterday, but that has been the case a lot lately. The Yankees are scoring runs in bunches, and they are getting contributions from a player whose season once appeared to be a lost cause. Add pitching that has been effective if not spectacular, and you have a six-game winning streak from a team that no longer resembles the underachieving bunch that stumbled its way through April and May.</p>
        <p>The rampaging Yankees finished off the overmatched Pittsburgh Pirates yesterday, pounding out 14 hits to complete a three-game sweep with a 13-6 victory. They got two home runs from Alex Rodriguez and another big day from the suddenly unstoppable Bobby Abreu. The 13 runs were the most this season by the Yankees, who are averaging 7.4 a game this month in going 8-2.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alex Rodriguez hit two home runs  his 23rd and 24th of the season  and drove in five runs as the Yankees overpowered the Pirates on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The offense was relentless and merciless yesterday, but that has been the case a lot lately. The Yankees are scoring runs in bunches, and they are getting contributions from a player whose season once appeared to be a lost cause. Add pitching that has been effective if not spectacular, and you have a six-game winning streak from a team that no longer resembles the underachieving bunch that stumbled its way through April and May.</p>
        <p>The rampaging Yankees finished off the overmatched Pittsburgh Pirates yesterday, pounding out 14 hits to complete a three-game sweep with a 13-6 victory. They got two home runs from Alex Rodriguez and another big day from the suddenly unstoppable Bobby Abreu. The 13 runs were the most this season by the Yankees, who are averaging 7.4 a game this month in going 8-2.</p>
        <p>''It's just awesome watching something like that,'' said starter Tyler Clippard, who was bailed out by the offense in a shaky outing. ''If a guy like myself struggles, this team is never out of it. We just slugged our way through this one.''</p>
        <p>Rodriguez, who has 24 home runs and 63 runs batted in, has been doing this sort of damage to opposing pitching all season. It is Abreu who has been the pleasant surprise of late.</p>
        <p>He came into June hitting .228 and was among the main reasons the Yankees limped into the month below the .500 mark. He had two hits in a victory against the Red Sox on June 1 and has not stopped since. He went 4 for 4 yesterday with a double, a triple and three R.B.I.</p>
        <p>For the month, he is 19 for 38 and has raised his average to .272.</p>
        <p>''I was struggling for two months, and right now I feel a lot better at the plate,'' Abreu said. ''I'm hitting the baseball all over the place, especially the other way. Before, I was swinging at a lot of bad pitches. Things are back to normal.''</p>
        <p>Yankees Manager Joe Torre said: ''What's happening now isn't as much of a surprise as his dry spell was, when he was swinging and missing and striking out a lot. That was the mystery. He's a good hitter, a .300 hitter. Before, he just wasn't relaxed.''</p>
        <p>That has not been a problem for Rodriguez this season. Yesterday's game was just one more big day at the plate for him. During a three-run first inning, he walked and scored. He walked and scored again in the third, then hit a three-run homer in the fourth and a two-run homer in the sixth. Rodriguez had five R.B.I. and has 16 R.B.I. in his past six games.</p>
        <p>''It's not one particular guy,'' Rodriguez said. ''It's been one through nine. Everybody is contributing for us.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees tacked on three runs in the seventh, the key hit being an Abreu double, which brought in two runs.</p>
        <p>The offense, which did much of its damage against the former Yankee Shawn Chacon, was able to overcome a poor performance by Clippard, who lasted only three and two-thirds innings and gave up six runs, six hits and three walks. The Yankees took a 5-2 lead into the fourth, but the Pirates scored four times to go in front. The big blows were a double by Chris Duffy and a single by José Bautista. After Bautista's single, Clippard was lifted for Sean Henn.</p>
        <p>The Yankees' bullpen did an excellent job; the combination of Henn (2-0), Luis Vizcaíno, Scott Proctor and Mike Myers shut down the Pirates the rest of the way.</p>
        <p>With the winning streak, their longest since last September, the Yankees improved to 30-31, nine and a half games behind Boston in the American League East, and have the type of momentum they have not had throughout much of the season. With Roger Clemens in the rotation, there is reason to expect that the worst is over. With a victory tomorrow against Arizona, the Yankees will have crawled back to .500, a place they have not been since April 21.</p>
        <p>''One to go to .500, and then we can start thinking in terms of starting our season and, basically, seeing how far over .500 we can get,'' Torre said. ''That's going to be the determining factor, the standard by which we make the playoffs or don't make the playoffs. It's all about the record. That's what our goal is. We have to keep paying attention to today.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Coming off a victory in his season debut, Roger Clemens will make his next start Friday against the Mets, Joe Torre said. Clemens, who has been bothered by a minor groin muscle problem, showed no ill effects from Saturday's start, Torre said.  Pirates reliever Masumi Kuwata, 39, appeared in his first major league game, becoming the oldest player to make his major league debut since another Pirates pitcher, 41-year-old Diomedes Olivo, on Sept. 5, 1960. Kuwata allowed two runs in two innings.  The Yankees are a major-league-best 107-73 (.594) against the National League since interleague play began in 1997.  Melky Cabrera made his 11th consecutive start for the Yankees and is batting .390 through that period.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
