<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WHAT'S ON TONIGHT</title>
    <meta content="11tvcol" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/arts/television/11tvcol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853729"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Tonight's TV Listings"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E3DF173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WHAT'S ON TONIGHT</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What’s on Tonight</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHRYN SHATTUCK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>9 P.M. (HBO) BIG LOVE -- The Henricksons, America's favorite polygamists, return for a new season on a new night, with some damage control in the wake of the family's exposure when wife No. 1, Barb, was being considered for mother of the year. (And with seven children scattered among three homes, why not?) Tonight the patriarch Bill (Bill Paxton, above with Jeanne Tripplehorn) scrambles to find out who betrayed him, and Barb (Ms. Tripplehorn) retreats into her own world, leaving wives No. 2, Nicki (Chloë Sevigny), and No. 3, Margene (Ginnifer Goodwin), to pick up the slack. Meanwhile Roman (Harry Dean Stanton) tries to intimidate Joey (Shawn Doyle) after Joey's wife, Wanda (Melora Waters), poisoned Roman's son, Alby (Matt Ross). And back at home, the eldest daughter, Sarah (Amanda Seyfried), catches the eye of Scott (Aaron Paul) at a meeting for ex-Mormons.</p>
        <p>8 P.M. (E!) THE LIFE AND DEATH OF ANNA NICOLE -- The tale of Anna Nicole Smith is presented with fresh details in this three-hour special featuring archival interviews with her and new interviews with more than 25 of her family members and friends. An hour is devoted to speculating about what happened the day she died.</p>
        <p>8 P.M. (Bravo) INSIDE THE ACTORS STUDIO -- The sweetly tart Kyra Sedgwick, right, talks about her Golden Globe-winning role as a deputy chief of police in the TNT series ''The Closer''; life with her husband, Kevin Bacon; the ''Six Degrees of Separation'' game; and maintaining a successful marriage and career in Hollywood.</p>
        <p>8 P.M. (ABC Family) KYLE XY -- Kyle (Matt Dallas), that mysterious teenager found wandering out of a Seattle woods with no memory of the past, no family and no belly button, returns for a new season. Tonight he finally starts getting the answers he has been looking for. But that only means new questions.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (Lifetime) IN GOD'S COUNTRY -- (2007) Kelly Rowan plays Judith, another stressed-out polygamist wife. Judith flees her fundamentalist husband with her five children after her youngest daughter is attacked, but just when she thinks her life will be normal, her oldest daughter runs back home to marry the boy she loves.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (13) KANSAS TO KANDAHAR -- This ''America at a Crossroads'' documentary explores the response of the United States military to the war on terror by following five Army reservists from suburban Kansas City through their one-year deployment to Pakistan and Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>11:35 P.M. (CBS) LATE SHOW WITH DAVID LETTERMAN -- Denis Leary gets riled up about a new season of ''Rescue Me,'' starting Wednesday. Flight of the Conchords performs.</p>
        <p>KATHRYN SHATTUCK</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>9 P.M. (HBO) BIG LOVE The Henricksons, America’s favorite polygamists, return for a new season on a new night, with some damage control in the wake of the family’s exposure when wife No. 1, Barb, was being considered for mother of the year. (And with seven children scattered among three homes, why not?) Tonight the patriarch Bill (Bill Paxton, above with Jeanne Tripplehorn) scrambles to find out who betrayed him, and Barb (Ms. Tripplehorn) retreats into her own world, leaving wives No. 2, Nicki (Chloë Sevigny), and No. 3, Margene (Ginnifer Goodwin), to pick up the slack. Meanwhile Roman (Harry Dean Stanton) tries to intimidate Joey (Shawn Doyle) after Joey’s wife, Wanda (Melora Waters), poisoned Roman’s son, Alby (Matt Ross). And back at home, the eldest daughter, Sarah (Amanda Seyfried), catches the eye of Scott (Aaron Paul) at a meeting for ex-Mormons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>9 P.M. (HBO) BIG LOVE -- The Henricksons, America's favorite polygamists, return for a new season on a new night, with some damage control in the wake of the family's exposure when wife No. 1, Barb, was being considered for mother of the year. (And with seven children scattered among three homes, why not?) Tonight the patriarch Bill (Bill Paxton, above with Jeanne Tripplehorn) scrambles to find out who betrayed him, and Barb (Ms. Tripplehorn) retreats into her own world, leaving wives No. 2, Nicki (Chloë Sevigny), and No. 3, Margene (Ginnifer Goodwin), to pick up the slack. Meanwhile Roman (Harry Dean Stanton) tries to intimidate Joey (Shawn Doyle) after Joey's wife, Wanda (Melora Waters), poisoned Roman's son, Alby (Matt Ross). And back at home, the eldest daughter, Sarah (Amanda Seyfried), catches the eye of Scott (Aaron Paul) at a meeting for ex-Mormons.</p>
        <p>8 P.M. (E!) THE LIFE AND DEATH OF ANNA NICOLE -- The tale of Anna Nicole Smith is presented with fresh details in this three-hour special featuring archival interviews with her and new interviews with more than 25 of her family members and friends. An hour is devoted to speculating about what happened the day she died.</p>
        <p>8 P.M. (Bravo) INSIDE THE ACTORS STUDIO -- The sweetly tart Kyra Sedgwick, right, talks about her Golden Globe-winning role as a deputy chief of police in the TNT series ''The Closer''; life with her husband, Kevin Bacon; the ''Six Degrees of Separation'' game; and maintaining a successful marriage and career in Hollywood.</p>
        <p>8 P.M. (ABC Family) KYLE XY -- Kyle (Matt Dallas), that mysterious teenager found wandering out of a Seattle woods with no memory of the past, no family and no belly button, returns for a new season. Tonight he finally starts getting the answers he has been looking for. But that only means new questions.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (Lifetime) IN GOD'S COUNTRY -- (2007) Kelly Rowan plays Judith, another stressed-out polygamist wife. Judith flees her fundamentalist husband with her five children after her youngest daughter is attacked, but just when she thinks her life will be normal, her oldest daughter runs back home to marry the boy she loves.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (13) KANSAS TO KANDAHAR -- This ''America at a Crossroads'' documentary explores the response of the United States military to the war on terror by following five Army reservists from suburban Kansas City through their one-year deployment to Pakistan and Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>11:35 P.M. (CBS) LATE SHOW WITH DAVID LETTERMAN -- Denis Leary gets riled up about a new season of ''Rescue Me,'' starting Wednesday. Flight of the Conchords performs.</p>
        <p>KATHRYN SHATTUCK  Tonight's TV Listings</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
