<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Colt Versus Filly: What's All the Fuss?</title>
    <meta content="11fillies" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/sports/othersports/11fillies.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853826"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE3DD173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="726" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Colt Versus Filly: What's All the Fuss?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Colt Versus Filly: What’s All the Fuss?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE SCHWARTZ</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>During the stretch run of the Preakness Stakes, American racing fans screamed as Street Sense and Curlin battled to the wire. ''Spectacular,'' ''heart-pounding'' and ''remarkable'' were the adjectives that appeared in the papers the next day.</p>
        <p>Curlin's victory was as exhilarating as Street Sense's come-from-behind victory in the Kentucky Derby two weeks earlier. So the public had not been shortchanged in the first two-thirds of the Triple Crown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Does it make sense to turn horse races into battles of the sexes?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>During the stretch run of the Preakness Stakes, American racing fans screamed as Street Sense and Curlin battled to the wire. ''Spectacular,'' ''heart-pounding'' and ''remarkable'' were the adjectives that appeared in the papers the next day.</p>
        <p>Curlin's victory was as exhilarating as Street Sense's come-from-behind victory in the Kentucky Derby two weeks earlier. So the public had not been shortchanged in the first two-thirds of the Triple Crown.</p>
        <p>But the buildup to the Belmont Stakes was a bit subdued until the filly Rags to Riches joined the field. Marketing went into overdrive. Instead of a small field with no potential for a Triple Crown, the story of the Belmont on Saturday became the battle of the sexes. And because no filly had won the Belmont in 102 years, it was a compelling story line.</p>
        <p>Boy versus girl. It is an elemental point of identification, and the conflict goes all the way back (if you believe Mark Twain's take on the story) to the day Adam started messing up the lean-to and Eve got after him to pick up his fig leaf.</p>
        <p>So the filly and the colt waged a dramatic battle down the stretch, and the filly won, and like so many people, I was thrilled. But I could not help admiring the understated sanity of the Englishman Michael Tabor, one of the owners of Rags to Riches, who said that Americans made too much of a fuss over the difference between colts and fillies. It is less of an issue in European racing.</p>
        <p>It is not that those guys do not get crazy over their sports. (Can you say Manchester United?) And it is not that they do not love their horses. But Europeans in general seem to have gotten beyond our fondness for whipping up each filly-colt contest into a full-blooded battle of the sexes.</p>
        <p>The battle, of course, has no real meaning in the sport. And in terms of symbolic story value for us as humans, isn't it time we just entered the races we were best-suited for and let the chips fall where they may?</p>
        <p>The newly elected Hall of Fame trainer John Veitch suggested a logical reason for the difference in attitudes. Although Veitch is known to the world as the conditioner of the outstanding, gallant-hearted Alydar, who chase Affirmed through the 1978 Triple Crown races, he also had the filly champions Our Mims and Davona Dale running against males in the mid-1970s, winning some and losing some, taking their knocks along with their trophies.</p>
        <p>''Over in Europe, they don't write too many top races just for fillies as they get a little older, so after their 2-year-old season, if you have a good filly, you have to test her against the colts,'' said Veitch, now the head steward in Kentucky.</p>
        <p>Here, he says, there are so many filly races with good purses that owners figure: Why risk going after the colts when they can do O.K. in the more limited pool of competitors?</p>
        <p>And when a filly loses to colts, it is not because she is a filly. After all, when Davona Dale finished second to General Assembly in the Travers in 1979, the other horses in the field were all colts.</p>
        <p>Veitch does not deny that colts, on the whole, are physically bigger and stronger than the average filly. (In the Belmont, fillies are allowed to carry five pounds less than their male counterparts.) But the point is that at each level there are probably more fillies that could compete honestly against colts. It is simply a question of knowing your horse.</p>
        <p>Jacinto Vasquez emphatically agreed, and he should know: he and Gary Stevens are the only jockeys to have won the Kentucky Derby on both a colt and a filly.</p>
        <p>Vasquez scoffs at the idea that competitive fillies were intimidated by colts.</p>
        <p>''A good horse is a good horse,'' he said. ''Filly or colt, don't make no difference.''</p>
        <p>The key is racing fillies against colts at the appropriate level. A truly talented, tough-minded filly can race against anything, and, with ability and heart, there is no limit to what she can achieve.</p>
        <p>Rags to Riches proved it in the Belmont Stakes, displaying the same qualities evident with Street Sense in the Derby and Curlin in the Preakness. We have had a terrific Triple Crown season.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING Jane Schwartz is the author of ''Ruffian: Burning From the Start.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jane Schwartz is the author of ''Ruffian: Burning From the Start.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
