<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Her Own Company, a Former Dancer Reunites Elements of Her Past</title>
    <meta content="11farr" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/arts/dance/11farr.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853806"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Kennedy, John F, Center for the Performing Arts</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Farrell, Suzanne</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E6DD173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="716" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Her Own Company, a Former Dancer Reunites Elements of Her Past</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Her Own Company, a Former Dancer Reunites Elements of Her Past</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA LA ROCCO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It takes seeing the work of George Balanchine and Maurice Béjart side by side to reveal the distance Suzanne Farrell traveled in 1969, when a devastating rupture with Balanchine and his New York City Ballet led her to Europe, and Mr. Béjart's company, for five years. Considering the culture shock it engenders in a viewer, one can only imagine how disorienting it must have been for this great ballerina, steeped in the grand, austere clarity of Balanchine's vision, to sink into Béjart's decadent emotionalism.</p>
        <p>Or perhaps this viewer is projecting. The Suzanne Farrell Ballet has just completed a five-day, two-program engagement at the Kennedy Center in Washington, featuring five Balanchine works and the ''Scène d'amour'' from Mr. Béjart's ''Romeo and Juliet,'' with a score by Hector Berlioz. A second Béjart piece, ''Rite of Spring,'' was dropped because the choreographer was too ill to oversee the production himself; it was replaced by ''Slaughter on Tenth Avenue,'' whose Looney Tunes Richard Rodgers score (from the musical ''On Your Toes,'' reorchestrated by Hershey Kay) and Technicolor sets and emotions suggest Balanchine had at least a little Béjart in him -- maybe just enough for his great muse to make the transition between the two or to believe, 40 years later, that the pairing makes for coherent theater.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Suzanne Farrell Ballet has just completed a five-day, two-program engagement at the Kennedy Center in Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It takes seeing the work of George Balanchine and Maurice Béjart side by side to reveal the distance Suzanne Farrell traveled in 1969, when a devastating rupture with Balanchine and his New York City Ballet led her to Europe, and Mr. Béjart's company, for five years. Considering the culture shock it engenders in a viewer, one can only imagine how disorienting it must have been for this great ballerina, steeped in the grand, austere clarity of Balanchine's vision, to sink into Béjart's decadent emotionalism.</p>
        <p>Or perhaps this viewer is projecting. The Suzanne Farrell Ballet has just completed a five-day, two-program engagement at the Kennedy Center in Washington, featuring five Balanchine works and the ''Scène d'amour'' from Mr. Béjart's ''Romeo and Juliet,'' with a score by Hector Berlioz. A second Béjart piece, ''Rite of Spring,'' was dropped because the choreographer was too ill to oversee the production himself; it was replaced by ''Slaughter on Tenth Avenue,'' whose Looney Tunes Richard Rodgers score (from the musical ''On Your Toes,'' reorchestrated by Hershey Kay) and Technicolor sets and emotions suggest Balanchine had at least a little Béjart in him -- maybe just enough for his great muse to make the transition between the two or to believe, 40 years later, that the pairing makes for coherent theater.</p>
        <p>But to see this ''Scène,'' a company premiere, on the heels of ''Scotch Symphony'' or ''Mozartiana'' is to marvel that Ms. Farrell lasted as long as she did before writing the letter that would lead to her rapprochement with Balanchine: ''As wonderful as it is to see your ballets, it is even more wonderful to dance them. Is this impossible? Love, Suzi.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps the crude gymnastics and overwrought noodling that pass for partnering in ''Scène d'amour'' are wonderful to dance, but they are not wonderful to watch, even when performed with apparent gusto by Ashley Hubbard and her Romeos (Runqiao Du and Matthew Prescott). Everything is given away, on the cheap, from Ms. Hubbard's clambering spread-legged over her partner to a finale featuring the lovers' horizontal bodies pressed together under a giant moon.</p>
        <p>A typical Balanchine ballet, meanwhile, offers its secrets slowly, if ever. Once is never enough; these are works you want to return to, again and again.</p>
        <p>Perhaps for this reason, Ms. Farrell created the Balanchine Preservation Initiative, which aims to resurrect lost works. Last week's programs included company premieres of two reconstructions, 1955's ''Divertimento Brillante,'' set to Glinka, and the adagio from the 1942 ''Concierto de Mozart.''</p>
        <p>As the furor over last year's publication of Elizabeth Bishop's unpublished poems demonstrates, posthumous reconstruction is a thorny issue. This is especially true in dance. The fragility of choreography and the lack of a definitive record to follow make for a hit-or-miss state of affairs.</p>
        <p>When ''Concierto'' had its premiere, the Russian-born Balanchine had been in America for eight years. This reconstruction has the feel of an Edith Wharton novel, full of clashing cultures and roiling desires -- all cloaked in wondrously seductive restraint. Elisabeth Holowchuk and Mr. Prescott beautifully captured this tension, dancing with precision and feeling. Who can say what Balanchine would have thought of this 2007 ''Concierto,'' but it's hard to think he would have been pleased with ''Divertimento'' as danced by Shannon Parsley, whose clunky phrasing and pasted-on smile made nothing of the steps. What to say about this duet? I hardly feel as though I saw it.</p>
        <p>Ms. Parsely's partner, the elegantly supple Momchil Mladenov, faired better when paired with Bonnie Pickard in ''Scotch Symphony.'' Ms. Pickard's steely precision is offset by a winsome fragility; she is a dancer who suggests her own secrets, independent of the work she dances.</p>
        <p>At times, though, her grip on the choreography seemed too tight. The dancers often seemed to be tending to the ballets more than inhabiting them. As a ballerina, Ms. Farrell was known for daredevilry; astonishingly, the heat she generated in flimsy roles like the Strip Tease Girl in ''Slaughter'' comes through even in a recording.</p>
        <p>But her fledgling company lacks this feeling of glorious risk. Perhaps it is unfair to expect that, with the specter of Ms. Farrell hovering; as a muse, after all, she serves as an eternal flame. Her dancers, once removed, must guard this flame, even if it means ignoring their own.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
