<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Former Queen of Buzz Conjures a Golden Heyday</title>
    <meta content="11tina" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/books/11tina.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853753"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Brown, Tina</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Charles, Prince of Wales</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE0DF173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1700" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Former Queen of Buzz Conjures a Golden Heyday</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Former Queen of Buzz Conjures a Golden Heyday</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL KIMMELMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tina Brown, the once highly conspicuous editor of Vanity Fair, The New Yorker and the short-lived Talk, has just written ''The Diana Chronicles,'' about the British princess who, like her, reigned as a golden girl over the transatlantic media world during the 1980s and '90s.</p>
        <p>''I felt the book had to hit a standard or I'd regret it,'' Ms. Brown said over lunch the other day at the Beacon restaurant in Midtown. ''It had to have some endurance, to enable me to make a quantum leap, to take me into a different area.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tina Brown’s “The Diana Chronicles” is about the British princess who, like the author, reigned as a golden girl over the media world during the 1980s and ’90s.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tina Brown, the once highly conspicuous editor of Vanity Fair, The New Yorker and the short-lived Talk, has just written ''The Diana Chronicles,'' about the British princess who, like her, reigned as a golden girl over the transatlantic media world during the 1980s and '90s.</p>
        <p>''I felt the book had to hit a standard or I'd regret it,'' Ms. Brown said over lunch the other day at the Beacon restaurant in Midtown. ''It had to have some endurance, to enable me to make a quantum leap, to take me into a different area.''</p>
        <p>And into the new century, which frankly hasn't been so great for Ms. Brown's career. Talk tanked. ''Topic A With Tina Brown,'' her little-seen show on CNBC, was canceled. For a time she wrote a column for The Washington Post. She contemplated a book about hubris, of all things. Now ''The Diana Chronicles'' (Doubleday), pegged to the 10th anniversary in August of the deadly car crash in Paris, is Ms. Brown's latest attempt to reinvent herself and seize the limelight.</p>
        <p>At lunch she seemed a little nervous about that. She bristled at the idea that the book might be perceived as ''just a gambit for reinvention rather than the passionate literary exercise that it was.'' Life, she said ''is a process of reinvention, of moving on.'' She is returning with pleasure to her ''roots as a writer,'' she added.</p>
        <p>She is, as she knows, an easy target. The culture of celebrity, over which she presided for years, has neither scruples nor sentiment, and a new book by her is an invitation for detractors to gloat over the passing of her time. So far the reviews have been positive.</p>
        <p>Trim, blond, doe-eyed, like her subject, she wore at lunch a smart black T-shirt and skirt, not quite the taffeta ''drop-dead black décolleté number,'' as she describes it in the book, that Diana, formerly the demure virgin, snatched off the rack from a London designer's studio in 1981 and wore on her first public date with Prince Charles. (''Wasn't that a mighty feast to set before a king?'' Lady Diana Cooper said about the ''sudden revelation of cleavage.'')</p>
        <p>Comparing author with subject is inevitable, and not only thanks to the Di-like photo of the attractive 53-year-old Ms. Brown on the book's back cover. She writes about a mix of monarchy, aristocracy and media: ''a revisiting and valedictory of that whole world, which included my own early immersion in the London media,'' she said. Princess Diana brought star power to British royalty, as Ms. Brown would also do within the more circumscribed but likewise clubby sphere of American editing.</p>
        <p>The daughter of a British film producer and of Laurence Olivier's former assistant, Ms. Brown arrived in New York in 1984 from London to save Vanity Fair. She had just resuscitated Tatler, the dowager magazine for the upper classes, whose transformation into something more broadly stylish and socially indispensable was linked with the princess's public ascension.</p>
        <p>''I felt an immediate bond with the Diana story,'' she said. ''Diana emerged blinking into the '80s just when I took over the Tatler. Tatler had started as the 18th-century coffeehouse magazine of Swift, and it got more and more staid, rather as The New Yorker did after Harold Ross,'' its fouding editor.</p>
        <p>''I'd already done a lot of stories about society before I got to Tatler. And I'd grown up in a showbiz background, the bookish daughter in the household. So I got it.''</p>
        <p>By ''it,'' she meant the dawning media and celebrity culture in Britain. She remembers attending ''the definitive end-of-decade social events of the '70s,'' a 40th-birthday costume party for Nicky Haslam, the decorator, who dressed for the occasion in white silk like an Indian rajah, greeting guests like Cecil Beaton, Mick Jagger, Joan Collins and Camilla Parker Bowles's brother, Mark Shand.</p>
        <p>''There was a carnival of influences at that party,'' Ms. Brown recalled, ''and it crystallized the fact that society was no longer homogeneous. It was, I thought, what Tatler magazine should be.''</p>
        <p>Eyeing high society now meant navel gazing too for the media mob that also joined in on the new aristocracy of celebrity. ''The third story I did on Diana was about how she was being covered in the media. We saw something was happening that was as interesting as Di herself.''</p>
        <p>What was happening, thanks to Diana's media-exploiting instincts and looks, was the creation of the mythology of the People's Princess. Years later at The New Yorker, Ms. Brown helped replace that mythology with a new mythology of grief. She recalls being awakened at 5 a.m. that August morning by a phone call from CNN. Within hours she conceived a Diana memorial issue and oversaw its publication three days later. Clive James, Salman Rushdie and Simon Schama wrote for it. On the cover a drawing showed a palace guard shedding a tear.</p>
        <p>She exempts that issue of her New Yorker from the media frenzy, about which she's critical in the book. ''The death became a festival of inclusion,'' Ms. Brown said. ''It was the first great griefathon. Since then it's become common -- the pope, Terri Schiavo. I think a magazine has to mirror its times. The fever of a moment has to be captured. That Diana memorial cover was very effective. I still think it's a very good issue.''</p>
        <p>She added: ''I'm not the sort of person who would have bought a Diana book, but I read all the articles. I'm writing this book for people who read the books but also for people like me.''</p>
        <p>Some people, of course, loved what she did with The New Yorker; others hated it. But the magazine became impossible to ignore. She chafes now at the suggestion that she blew the institution up so that her successor could put it back together after she left. ''We let go 79 people and hired 68,'' she responded. ''It was a total blood transfusion. To me the biggest problem for The New Yorker was how to get people to open something that looks like a safari in print. The idea was always to provide a story that they would read.</p>
        <p>''The sweet and the low, the long and the short, it's somewhat what Harold Ross did. His New Yorker was very topical. I related less to Shawn's New Yorker than to Ross's.'' William Shawn, Ross's successor, ran the magazine from 1952 to 1987.</p>
        <p>When, to the surprise of everyone including S. I. Newhouse Jr., chairman of Condé Nast, owner of The New Yorker, she quit the magazine in 1998 to start Talk, she had become such a public figure and media magnet that her resignation was front-page news in The New York Times. With Talk, and its book and movie divisions, she began a doomed partnership with Miramax, whose co-founder, Harvey Weinstein, also now happens to be in the process of reinventing himself. Talk's christening bash on Liberty Island was the late '90s version of Mr. Haslam's end-of-the-'70s affair.</p>
        <p>Then Talk fizzled. Was she wrong to have left The New Yorker?</p>
        <p>''Oh yes, it was a big mistake,'' said Ms. Brown, who has for years lived on the East Side with her husband, Harold Evans. (They have two children.) Like Diana, she recognizes candor as a form of self-defense. ''I believe we put out a good magazine,'' Ms. Brown continued, ''It was that dot-com moment. I drank the Kool-Aid. I loved my idea of combining Paris Match and The New Yorker. And I loved that glossy paper we used. But it had to be a weekly, not a monthly. And advertisers had to be brought around. The time wasn't there because the money wasn't there.''</p>
        <p>Talk editors soon found new jobs at The Times and elsewhere. Ms. Brown began her stint at CNBC. ''I got much better at it,'' she said about the buzz-based show that exploited her dense Rolodex but never found the magic she showed before. ''I liked everything except being on the air. And CNBC is a business channel. It was put on a Sunday night after a day of infomercials. Then again, I was a television novice.''</p>
        <p>The Washington Post column kept her before the public. Meanwhile her hubris book was going to feature boldface crash-and-burn cases like Gerald Levin and Martha Stewart. ''We're living in an era of hubris,'' Ms. Brown explained. ''In the Bush era it's all about overreach. But in the end I didn't want to write a book on a notional subject. It wasn't engaging me enough.''</p>
        <p>So she turned to writing this book about a celebrity whose iconic glamour harks back to a period that was also Ms. Brown's heyday, not so long ago, but somehow far away. Di, who never shaved her head, went to jail or took off her underpants in public, has been replaced by Britney, Paris and Lindsay. The panache, gloss, savvy and grace that Ms. Brown tried to bring to highbrow celebrity journalism has been marginalized too, by a growing avalanche of more tabloidlike coverage.</p>
        <p>''The temperature has shifted,'' Ms. Brown declared. ''Now everybody's famous and nobody's interesting. Any celebrity will do.'' Tabloids have become ''fabloids,'' she said. And bloggers are watching. With the Web, ''you worry about saying something to somebody in Germany and finding it reverberate around the world. Now you're supposed to love any publicity just because it's great buzz and not mind whether it's fair or true, says the erstwhile queen of buzz,'' said the erstwhile queen herself.</p>
        <p>''Yes,'' she added, answering a question not asked, ''it's nicer to be on the other side.''</p>
        <p>Was it also true, by the way, that she recently expressed her interest in the job of managing editor at Time? The post went to Richard Stengel. ''I think I could have done a good job with that,'' she replied. ''It has great DNA.''</p>
        <p>But it's not a good time to start up new magazines, she said. Editors today ''are a dying breed,'' she added. ''It's all not about the content. In TV it's only about logistics, ratings. It's a very depressing moment in letters.</p>
        <p>''Writing a book is one of the last chances to do what you want.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
