<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="11forsum" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E1DE173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1048" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A2-11</p>
        <p>New Plan to Arm Sunnis Against Qaeda Militants  With the four-month-old buildup of American troops showing only modest success in curbing insurgent attacks, American commanders are turning to another strategy that they acknowledge is fraught with risk: arming Sunni Arab groups that have promised to fight militants linked to Al Qaeda -- in many cases, their former allies.  A1</p>
        <p>Iraq's leading political blocs agreed to remove the speaker of Parliament from his position after accusations that his bodyguards assaulted a Shiite lawmaker as the speaker cursed him. Members of Parliament and a spokesman for the speaker's party confirmed the assault and the plans for removal. A6</p>
        <p>Gaza Infighting and Air Strikes  The Israeli Air Force struck at least two buildings in Gaza City in what appeared to be a response to a raid across the Gaza-Israel border by Palestinian militants. Also, internal violence between the main rival Palestinian organizations, Hamas and Fatah, flared again in the Gaza Strip, with at least four people killed over the weekend.  A9</p>
        <p>Flooding in China Kills 66  Torrential rains in southern China have unleashed surging floodwaters that have swept through small cities and farming villages, claiming at least 66 lives, forcing nearly 600,000 people to be relocated and destroying millions of dollars in property, the state news media reported. A11</p>
        <p>Bush Tour Reaches Albania  President Bush's visit to Albania was the fifth stop on his eight-day, six-country swing through Europe. The first sitting president to visit the country, he told the Albanians that he supported their effort to join NATO and wanted independence soon for Kosovo without making any fresh commitments.  A3</p>
        <p>Sri Lankan Rights Panel Report  An international panel appointed by the government of Sri Lanka has issued a stark indictment of a presidential commission intended to investigate serious human rights violations, saying that its activities so far ''do not satisfy international norms and standards.''  A11</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A12-17</p>
        <p>State Budgets Get Boost From Booming Economy  State lawmakers across the country have found themselves with more money than they planned as they wind down their regular sessions. Burned by several years of shortfalls, states have kept their estimates of total revenues on the conservative side and are now reaping plenty from higher than expected tax collections and booming local economies.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mixed Views of Romney Bid  To many Mormons, Mitt Romney's bid for the presidency is both a proud sign of progress and a cause of real trepidation. Even his many Mormon supporters find the moment fraught with anxiety because his candidacy is bringing intense scrutiny to their church and could worsen longstanding bigotry.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Repatriation of the Dead  The repatriation of remains has become increasingly commonplace as towns across Mexico have sent their children to find work in the United States. As debate rages in Congress over a proposed immigration law, the journey of the dead suggests that for many Mexicans the sojourn in the United States, legal or not, is meant to be temporary.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Immigration Unresolved  Senate Democrats opened the door to reviving the stalled immigration measure, calling on Republicans to resolve their internal divisions and produce an agreement on how to move the legislation forward. Republican critics of the bill have called for more chances to eliminate provisions they describe as amnesty.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Transit Expansion Project  After operating for 32 years, efforts are under way to expand the transit system designed to shuttle between West Virginia University's two campuses, which sit two miles apart. At a cost of up to $40 million a mile, the expansion would extend the system, once derided as a waste of money but now relied on by the city of Morgantown.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION B1-5</p>
        <p>Medical Marijuana Bill Advances in Connecticut  On June 1, the Connecticut State Senate, following the House, passed a bill that allows people with certain medical conditions to grow as many as four marijuana plants for ''palliative use.'' It is unclear whether Gov. M. Jodi Rell will sign the bill, which would make Connecticut the 13th state in the nation to permit marijuana for medical purposes. B1</p>
        <p>Border Rules May Hurt Tourism  Many people in the Niagara Falls tourism industry fear that a set of new rules suggested by the 9/11 Commission requiring Americans traveling by land or sea to Canada, Mexico, Bermuda and the Caribbean to present a passport could discourage millions of visitors from crossing the border and result in billions of dollars a year in lost revenue.  B1</p>
        <p>The Pull of Homelessness  After reading an article about Johnny Five, a homeless man who lived beneath an abandoned train station in the Bronx, a nonprofit group arranged for him to move into an apartment. But for the next several months, Johnny would drift between his old life and his new one.  B1</p>
        <p>ARTS E1-10</p>
        <p>Two Big Winners at Tonys  ''The Coast of Utopia,'' Tom Stoppard's eight-and-a-half-hour epic, was the big winner at the 61st annual Tony Awards, setting the record for the most awards won by any play in Tony history. Meanwhile, the musical ''Spring Awakening,'' won best book, score, direction and choreography and best featured actor. E1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES B7</p>
        <p>Richard Rorty  A scholar whose inventive work on philosophy, politics, literary theory and more made him one the of world's most influential contemporary thinkers, he was 75.  B7</p>
        <p>John P. McGovern  A Houston real-estate investor whose philanthropy helped endow medical facilities at Duke University and other institutions, he was 85. B7</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY C1-8</p>
        <p>Editor Leaves Publisher  Daniel Menaker, the executive editor in chief of the Random House Publishing Group, is leaving the company at the end of June.  C1</p>
        <p>Agency Loses Big Client  Creative Artists Agency has tried expanding its client base from mainstream entertainment companies to a widening ring of customers, but the loss of Hasbro in the month before the release of the movie ''Transformers'' is an example of how cruel the corporate world can be. C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest C2</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: Pakistan's dictator; a test of the Senate; economic life after college; mental health in prisons.</p>
        <p>Columns: Nicholas D. Kristof and Paul Krugman.</p>
        <p>Bridge E6  Crossword E2  Metro Diary B2  TV Listings E9  Weather B8</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A2-11</p>
        <p>New Plan to Arm Sunnis Against Qaeda Militants  With the four-month-old buildup of American troops showing only modest success in curbing insurgent attacks, American commanders are turning to another strategy that they acknowledge is fraught with risk: arming Sunni Arab groups that have promised to fight militants linked to Al Qaeda -- in many cases, their former allies.  A1</p>
        <p>Iraq's leading political blocs agreed to remove the speaker of Parliament from his position after accusations that his bodyguards assaulted a Shiite lawmaker as the speaker cursed him. Members of Parliament and a spokesman for the speaker's party confirmed the assault and the plans for removal. A6</p>
        <p>Gaza Infighting and Air Strikes  The Israeli Air Force struck at least two buildings in Gaza City in what appeared to be a response to a raid across the Gaza-Israel border by Palestinian militants. Also, internal violence between the main rival Palestinian organizations, Hamas and Fatah, flared again in the Gaza Strip, with at least four people killed over the weekend.  A9</p>
        <p>Flooding in China Kills 66  Torrential rains in southern China have unleashed surging floodwaters that have swept through small cities and farming villages, claiming at least 66 lives, forcing nearly 600,000 people to be relocated and destroying millions of dollars in property, the state news media reported. A11</p>
        <p>Bush Tour Reaches Albania  President Bush's visit to Albania was the fifth stop on his eight-day, six-country swing through Europe. The first sitting president to visit the country, he told the Albanians that he supported their effort to join NATO and wanted independence soon for Kosovo without making any fresh commitments.  A3</p>
        <p>Sri Lankan Rights Panel Report  An international panel appointed by the government of Sri Lanka has issued a stark indictment of a presidential commission intended to investigate serious human rights violations, saying that its activities so far ''do not satisfy international norms and standards.''  A11</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A12-17</p>
        <p>State Budgets Get Boost From Booming Economy  State lawmakers across the country have found themselves with more money than they planned as they wind down their regular sessions. Burned by several years of shortfalls, states have kept their estimates of total revenues on the conservative side and are now reaping plenty from higher than expected tax collections and booming local economies.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mixed Views of Romney Bid  To many Mormons, Mitt Romney's bid for the presidency is both a proud sign of progress and a cause of real trepidation. Even his many Mormon supporters find the moment fraught with anxiety because his candidacy is bringing intense scrutiny to their church and could worsen longstanding bigotry.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Repatriation of the Dead  The repatriation of remains has become increasingly commonplace as towns across Mexico have sent their children to find work in the United States. As debate rages in Congress over a proposed immigration law, the journey of the dead suggests that for many Mexicans the sojourn in the United States, legal or not, is meant to be temporary.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Immigration Unresolved  Senate Democrats opened the door to reviving the stalled immigration measure, calling on Republicans to resolve their internal divisions and produce an agreement on how to move the legislation forward. Republican critics of the bill have called for more chances to eliminate provisions they describe as amnesty.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Transit Expansion Project  After operating for 32 years, efforts are under way to expand the transit system designed to shuttle between West Virginia University's two campuses, which sit two miles apart. At a cost of up to $40 million a mile, the expansion would extend the system, once derided as a waste of money but now relied on by the city of Morgantown.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION B1-5</p>
        <p>Medical Marijuana Bill Advances in Connecticut  On June 1, the Connecticut State Senate, following the House, passed a bill that allows people with certain medical conditions to grow as many as four marijuana plants for ''palliative use.'' It is unclear whether Gov. M. Jodi Rell will sign the bill, which would make Connecticut the 13th state in the nation to permit marijuana for medical purposes. B1</p>
        <p>Border Rules May Hurt Tourism  Many people in the Niagara Falls tourism industry fear that a set of new rules suggested by the 9/11 Commission requiring Americans traveling by land or sea to Canada, Mexico, Bermuda and the Caribbean to present a passport could discourage millions of visitors from crossing the border and result in billions of dollars a year in lost revenue.  B1</p>
        <p>The Pull of Homelessness  After reading an article about Johnny Five, a homeless man who lived beneath an abandoned train station in the Bronx, a nonprofit group arranged for him to move into an apartment. But for the next several months, Johnny would drift between his old life and his new one.  B1</p>
        <p>ARTS E1-10</p>
        <p>Two Big Winners at Tonys  ''The Coast of Utopia,'' Tom Stoppard's eight-and-a-half-hour epic, was the big winner at the 61st annual Tony Awards, setting the record for the most awards won by any play in Tony history. Meanwhile, the musical ''Spring Awakening,'' won best book, score, direction and choreography and best featured actor. E1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES B7</p>
        <p>Richard Rorty  A scholar whose inventive work on philosophy, politics, literary theory and more made him one the of world's most influential contemporary thinkers, he was 75.  B7</p>
        <p>John P. McGovern  A Houston real-estate investor whose philanthropy helped endow medical facilities at Duke University and other institutions, he was 85. B7</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY C1-8</p>
        <p>Editor Leaves Publisher  Daniel Menaker, the executive editor in chief of the Random House Publishing Group, is leaving the company at the end of June.  C1</p>
        <p>Agency Loses Big Client  Creative Artists Agency has tried expanding its client base from mainstream entertainment companies to a widening ring of customers, but the loss of Hasbro in the month before the release of the movie ''Transformers'' is an example of how cruel the corporate world can be. C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest C2</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: Pakistan's dictator; a test of the Senate; economic life after college; mental health in prisons.</p>
        <p>Columns: Nicholas D. Kristof and Paul Krugman.</p>
        <p>Bridge E6  Crossword E2  Metro Diary B2  TV Listings E9  Weather B8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
