<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Investing: WebMD's Fever Chart</title>
    <meta content="11web" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Business of Health" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/business/businessspecial3/11web.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853820"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">WebMD Health Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E4DD173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="692" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Investing: WebMD's Fever Chart</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Investing: WebMD’s Fever Chart</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MILT FREUDENHEIM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CAPITALIZING on the national preoccupation with things medical, WebMD Health has built the most-visited and fastest-growing health site on the Internet. Should investors click on its stock?</p>
        <p>Some analysts think so, although they note that the shares are relatively high. But investors should be comfortable with the complexities of the stock and the company, which despite rapidly rising revenue reported only penny-a-share profit in this year's first quarter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>WebMD Health has built the most-visited and fastest-growing health site on the Internet, but should investors click on its stock?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CAPITALIZING on the national preoccupation with things medical, WebMD Health has built the most-visited and fastest-growing health site on the Internet. Should investors click on its stock?</p>
        <p>Some analysts think so, although they note that the shares are relatively high. But investors should be comfortable with the complexities of the stock and the company, which despite rapidly rising revenue reported only penny-a-share profit in this year's first quarter.</p>
        <p>Analysts are expecting better than that -- 8 cents or more -- in the second quarter. And the company predicts full-year earnings of at least 43 cents a share. The forecasts assume that WebMD will benefit from the growth in online spending by drug and other health care companies.</p>
        <p>The flagship WebMD.com site, aimed at consumers, attracts more than 40 million unique visitors a month, which the company says is up 30 percent from a year ago. In April, WebMD.com received 4 percent of the visits to the 6,700 sites in the health and medical category, almost three times as many as MayoClinic.com, its next largest direct competitor, according to Hitwise, an Internet research company.</p>
        <p>Just as important to advertisers as the consumer traffic is the million physicians each month who visit Medscape.com, a separate WebMD Health site. There, doctors can check on news of their specialties -- and even earn educational credits that are required by medical boards in some states. Patients can also get information there.</p>
        <p>''We are at an inflection point,'' said Martin J. Wygod, WebMD Health's chairman. ''A few years ago, we were getting $200,000 to $250,000 from advertisers for each brand,'' he said. ''Now we are getting $8 million to $15 million each from manufacturers.''</p>
        <p>Medscape.com advertisers include Medtronic, a maker of heart devices, and the big pharmaceutical companies Merck and AstraZeneca. Pfizer, which markets Rebif, a treatment for multiple sclerosis, with EMD Serono, has an ad on WebMD's topic page about that disease.</p>
        <p>Because the pharmaceutical industry spends a small fraction of its $13 billion annual marketing budget online, analysts say there is room for companies like WebMD Health to attract more of that money.</p>
        <p>''The growth rate is huge for health and pharmaceutical advertising on the Web, and WebMD is a pretty large receiver of that growth,'' said Peter Gardiner, the chief media officer of Deutsch, a New York agency that works with drug companies.</p>
        <p>So where do the complexities come in? Start with the ownership. The company is controlled by Mr. Wygod, whose holding company, the HLTH Corporation, owns almost all of WebMD's Class B voting shares.</p>
        <p>HLTH, until recently known as Emdeon, traces its ancestry to Healtheon, a fallen star of the dot-com firmament that was founded by the Netscape billionaire Jim Clark but eventually sold to Mr. Wygod.</p>
        <p>The Class A shares that are available to the common investor are nonvoting stock. Big institutional holders of the Class A stock include Fidelity Management, which also has a minority stake in HLTH.</p>
        <p>On Friday, the stock gained 74 cents on Nasdaq to $49.47, below its 52-week high of $58.53 on April 23. That is still almost three times its price two years ago, when it was split from Mr. Wygod's non-Web units.</p>
        <p>WebMD offers employee ''wellness'' programs including special pages for diet and fitness and quitting smoking. But Elizabeth W. Boehm, a health care analyst at Forrester Research, said that WebMD Health could do more on and off the Web. ''To change behavior,'' she said, ''a lot of times you need a series of tactics, a person on the phone, face-to-face persuasion like the Weight Watchers program.''</p>
        <p>Wayne T. Gattinella, WebMD Health's president and chief executive, said the company had begun incorporating health ''coaching'' online and by phone for these plans.</p>
        <p>Other challenges could come from Google and Yahoo, which are increasing their emphasis on health, as well as RevolutionHealth.com, a site by AOL's founder, Steve Case.</p>
        <p>''There will be ups and downs,'' said Larry N. Feinberg, who manages a health care hedge fund that is a big holder of WebMD Health and HLTH stock. But Mr. Feinberg predicts annual revenue will reach $1 billion in five years. ''This thing is taking off,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
