<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Federer Foiled Again; King of Clay Extends Reign</title>
    <meta content="11tennis" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/sports/tennis/11tennis.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Nadal, Rafael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Federer, Roger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE2DD173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="968" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Federer Foiled Again; King of Clay Extends Reign</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nadal Defeats Federer for French Open Title</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIET MACUR</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With clay the color of terra cotta caked on his clothes, Rafael Nadal climbed into the grandstand Sunday at Roland Garros to celebrate his third consecutive French Open victory.</p>
        <p>High above the court, he reached his family and friends, who then smothered him with hugs. But below at courtside, his opponent, Roger Federer, sat alone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rafael Nadal won his third consecutive French Open title on Sunday, topping the top-ranked Roger Federer and extending his unbeaten streak at Roland Garros.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With clay the color of terra cotta caked on his clothes, Rafael Nadal climbed into the grandstand Sunday at Roland Garros to celebrate his third consecutive French Open victory.</p>
        <p>High above the court, he reached his family and friends, who then smothered him with hugs. But below at courtside, his opponent, Roger Federer, sat alone.</p>
        <p>Federer was frozen and expressionless as the reality of the moment sank in. Once again, he had failed to win the French Open. And once again, Nadal had been the man who stopped him.</p>
        <p>In a match anticipated since the start of this tournament, a duel pitting No. 1 versus No. 2, Nadal won, 6-3, 4-6, 6-3, 6-4.</p>
        <p>Federer, the holder of 10 Grand Slam titles, had been hoping to win his first title on the legendary Parisian clay. A victory would have made him the third man to hold all four Grand Slam titles at once. Instead, he had to settle for something he is not used to: second place.</p>
        <p>''Well, you can put it any way you want,'' the 25-year-old Federer said. ''All I know, at the end of the day, is that I'm disappointed today, and I don't care less about the way I've played over the last 10 months or 10 years.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to win this match, and I didn't succeed. So, of course, it's a bit sad.''</p>
        <p>But Nadal, who scowled through nearly every set of the match, showed exactly why the red clay at Roland Garros has recently been his, and his alone. On Sunday, he reveled in it.</p>
        <p>After the final point, a forehand Federer hit long, Nadal threw his racket and collapsed onto the ground that has been so good to him. He remained there for a moment, eyes squeezed shut, letting the clay stain his trademark sleeveless shirt and cropped pants.</p>
        <p>Later, when he addressed the crowd, the 21-year-old Nadal bit his lip, holding back tears.</p>
        <p>''I am very happy,'' he said. ''But I am really sad for Roger. He is a friend, and I know he is a great champion, whether he wins or loses.''</p>
        <p>Nadal is the second man in 93 years to win three consecutive singles titles at the French Open. Bjorn Borg won four in a row from 1978 to 1981.</p>
        <p>Nadal did not preen or boast, even though his performance had solidified his place as one of the best clay-court players ever. Instead, he complimented Federer, who has been No. 1 for 175 weeks. For 98 of those, Nadal has been No. 2. When asked if Federer would ever win at Roland Garros, Nadal defended him.</p>
        <p>''What Federer has done is something almost nobody has done in history, so what are you going to ask of Federer?'' he said. ''What he does is exceptional already.''</p>
        <p>On the Parisian clay, Federer has had spurts of genius but has not been able to capitalize on them. Last year, he lost to Nadal in the final. In 2005, he lost to Nadal in a semifinal.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, Federer pushed Nadal to 10 break points in the first set, only to come up short each time. Nadal, playing some of the best tennis of his career, went on to save 16 of 17 break points in the match.</p>
        <p>Nadal's forehands found the court's white lines as if they were magnets, as he repeatedly hit winners. He dripped with sweat, but seemed to be gaining energy, while Federer looked exhausted.</p>
        <p>Even Federer's formidable forehands were not working. He had 29 unforced errors on that side. In the second set, he came alive, but that did not last long.</p>
        <p>''Roger sometimes plays very, very aggressive, especially with the forehand,'' Nadal said. ''But anyway, for me, he has the best forehand of the tour, no? But, yes, the truth is he had some mistakes today, more than usual.''</p>
        <p>In the end, Federer had 59 unforced errors to Nadal's 27.</p>
        <p>He managed to win one set, though; it was the only set Nadal dropped during the tournament. There is another bright spot. Federer defeated Nadal on clay in Hamburg a week before the French Open. Before that victory, he was 0-5 against Nadal. Now he is 1-6.</p>
        <p>But Federer is not giving up. He expects to see Nadal waiting in the final here once again.</p>
        <p>''If I would have won today, I would have not many other goals to chase in my career,'' Federer said. ''Eventually, if I get it, the sweeter it's going to taste. So hopefully I'll give myself more opportunities, over and over again. I know I can do it now, that's for sure.''</p>
        <p>Federer remains one of the best players without a victory at Roland Garros. He is in good company. Pete Sampras, Jimmy Connors, John McEnroe, Stefan Edberg and Boris Becker never won a singles title at Roland Garros. Still, it hurts.</p>
        <p>Federer received the runner-up's silver platter, the size and shape of a high school cafeteria tray. His mother, Lynette, had that platter tucked under her left arm while she waited for her son in the players' lounge.</p>
        <p>When Federer arrived looking glum, she hugged him as he walked to the locker room, alone.</p>
        <p>''For us Federers,'' his father, Robert, said, ''it was very difficult to see this. But you cannot win them all.</p>
        <p>''It was a game against history, for both of them. Only Rafa was good enough.''</p>
        <p>NOTES</p>
        <p>Individual session tickets for the United States Open tennis tournament go on sale at 9 a.m. today. The Open will run from Aug. 27 to Sept. 9. Tickets for the tournament and Arthur Ashe Kids' Day on Aug. 25 can be purchased at the Billie Jean King National Tennis Center box office, at usopen.org, at all Ticketmaster outlets and by calling Ticketmaster at (866) OPENTIX.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
