<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Pursuing Vick, Government Bares Its Teeth</title>
    <meta content="11rhoden" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/sports/football/11rhoden.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853860"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Atlanta Falcons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Virginia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlanta Falcons</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Vick, Michael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E6DC173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="825" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Pursuing Vick, Government Bares Its Teeth</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Pursuing Vick, Government Bares Its Teeth</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michael Vick may or may not have played a role in an apparent dog fighting ring. But Vick, the Atlanta Falcons' besieged quarterback. has already been indicted in the court of public opinion and by the news media, which increasingly embrace the presumption of guilt as vital to entertainment value.</p>
        <p>This story, like Vick's career, has been puzzling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Would the federal government have gotten involved in a dog-fighting case that didn’t involve a high-profile professional athlete?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Michael Vick may or may not have played a role in an apparent dog fighting ring. But Vick, the Atlanta Falcons' besieged quarterback. has already been indicted in the court of public opinion and by the news media, which increasingly embrace the presumption of guilt as vital to entertainment value.</p>
        <p>This story, like Vick's career, has been puzzling.</p>
        <p>Last Thursday in a surprising development, representatives of the Department of Agriculture's Office of Inspector General showed up at Vick's home in Surry County, Virginia, with a search warrant. Since April, the investigation had been overseen by Gerald G. Poindexter, the commonwealth's attorney. The presence of the Agriculture Department heralded that the Vick dog fighting probe had become a federal matter.</p>
        <p>Poindexter was insulted. Beyond that, he was baffled that the feds had stepped in.</p>
        <p>''What is foreign to me is the federal government getting into a dog-fighting case,'' Poindexter told The Associated Press. ''I know it's been done, but what's driving this? Is it this boy's celebrity? Would they have done this if it wasn't Michael Vick?''</p>
        <p>That, of course, is the million-dollar question. I don't think we would have heard a peep.</p>
        <p>The government' s involvement in pit bull fighting raised my suspicion that celebrity justice was partly at work. Carl W. Tobias, a law professor at the University of Richmond, said he had been intrigued by the story as well. Why was the federal government so interested when Poindexter was moving the case along?</p>
        <p>There are a number of possible answers. The government has more resources to undertake a full investigation in a complex case. The government may also be looking into whether this is related to dog fighting in other states.</p>
        <p>''It could be that there's some pressure on the U.S. attorney here to proceed,'' Tobias said. ''This could be celebrity justice. He's a high-profile person. If you make an example of someone like that, it would really send a message.''</p>
        <p>Make no mistake. A message needs to be sent that dog fighting, cock fighting and their every variation will be prosecuted. I just can't believe that the federal government, with everything else on its massive plate, has an interest in dog fighting that runs so deeply -- or runs that much beyond Vick.</p>
        <p>During the Associated Press interview, Poindexter suggested that more was in play than the government investigation.</p>
        <p>''There's a larger thing here, and it has nothing to do with any breach of protocol,'' he said. ''There's something awful going on here. I don't know if it's racial. I don't know what it is.''</p>
        <p>Poindexter and Vick are African-American.</p>
        <p>What seems at play here is a lust, a clamoring, for a high-profile takedown.</p>
        <p>The approval rating of professional athletes has taken almost as savage a beating as the president's. Indeed, the dog issue has proven to be the president's friend. Vick's home was searched on April 25. On May 3, President Bush signed the Animal Fighting Prohibition Act, a bill that will help law enforcement crack down on animal fighting.</p>
        <p>I don't have a problem with animal-rights groups using a star like Vick to call attention to the barbaric practice of animal fights. I do have a problem with the federal government piling on. More and more, I'm seeing the Vick case as piling on.</p>
        <p>There was a similar case a few years ago in Surry County. A man named Benjamin Butts was suspected of running a dog fighting operation. Dogs and training equipment were found on the property, and Poindexter authorized a search of Butts's property.</p>
        <p>Dave Forster, who is covering the Vick story with Linda McNatt for The Virginian-Pilot, said he asked Poindexter if the federal government had showed any interest in the Butts case. ''He laughed and said, 'Are you kidding me?' '' Forster recalled yesterday in a phone interview.</p>
        <p>The Butts case was dismissed by a judge who said the search had violated his rights.</p>
        <p>One of the larger issues here is Vick, no matter how this case turns out. I'm a fan of Michael Vick as a football player, but his time is running out. With young quarterbacks like Vince Young and JaMarcus Russell in the league, Vick's style could become obsolete.</p>
        <p>Off the field, from Day 1, Vick has seemed intent on proving that he should be able to live with the same right to privacy as noncelebrity citizens.</p>
        <p>This has proved to be a mistake time and again.</p>
        <p>Last week, Vick canceled his youth football camp, scheduled to begin June 30 at Christopher Newport University in Newport News, Va.</p>
        <p>The dilemma for Vick and the other stars and celebrities is that their strike zone expands with wealth and power. The challenge is to avoid striking out.</p>
        <p>What would you tell someone like Vick, who once had the world on a string? Depending on how -- or if -- he comes out of this doghouse, my advice is that he had better go undercover.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
