<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Off the Street and in an Apartment, But Unable to Escape Homelessness</title>
    <meta content="11cave" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/nyregion/11cave.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Caves and Caverns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Nuns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Caves and Caverns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EFDD173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1803" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Off the Street and in an Apartment, But Unable to Escape Homelessness</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Off the Street and in an Apartment, but Unable to Escape Homelessness</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANNY FERNANDEZ; Brent McDonald contributed reporting.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, Johnny Five lived not on the streets but below them, in the dark underworld beneath an abandoned train station in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>He had to crawl in the dirt at the edge of a concrete platform to get in and out. He bathed with rubbing alcohol, but still his skin was covered with insect bites and infections. He said God talked to him there, sometimes through a portable radio, yet he considered his cave a kind of hell: overheated in the summer, frigid in the winter, a sunless place hard on the body but worse on the soul.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, Johnny Five lived in a cave in the Bronx. In December 2006 he was offered an apartment but after four months he chose the streets again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years, Johnny Five lived not on the streets but below them, in the dark underworld beneath an abandoned train station in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>He had to crawl in the dirt at the edge of a concrete platform to get in and out. He bathed with rubbing alcohol, but still his skin was covered with insect bites and infections. He said God talked to him there, sometimes through a portable radio, yet he considered his cave a kind of hell: overheated in the summer, frigid in the winter, a sunless place hard on the body but worse on the soul.</p>
        <p>It was Christmas Eve when he first heard the news: Someone was offering him a way out. After reading an article about Johnny in The New York Times, Peter D. Beitchman, the executive director of the Bridge Inc., a nonprofit group that provides housing and services to mentally ill homeless people and others, immediately arranged for him to move into an apartment.</p>
        <p>Days later, Johnny celebrated with the one person who had looked after him, Sister Lauria Fitzgerald, a Roman Catholic nun who helps the homeless in the Bronx. They ate dinner with another nun at an Italian restaurant in the Arthur Avenue section, three miles from the cave and around the corner from Johnny's new home. He feasted on a plate of eggplant parmigiana and enjoyed his first taste of tiramisù.</p>
        <p>But he didn't want to touch the white linen napkin on the table. It was too clean.</p>
        <p>''I thought I wasn't worthy to use it,'' said Johnny, 45, who said he suffers from schizophrenia and whose real name is John Carbonell. ''I used the one that was in the basket where the bread was.''</p>
        <p>For the next several months, Johnny would drift between his old life underground and his new one above it, struggling the way a man freed from prison must readjust to society. It is easy in a sense to take the city's homeless people off the streets, but it is harder, as Johnny's odyssey illustrates, to take homelessness out of them.</p>
        <p>Even after Johnny moved into the apartment the first week of January, he returned to the wooded area around the cave to feed Meow Meow and the other stray cats he had named. His first several days in the apartment -- a light-drenched one-bedroom unit with hardwood floors and a large kitchen in a five-story building -- he did not bother locking the door. ''There's no doors in the cave,'' he explained.</p>
        <p>He had bold ambitions of starting over: He talked about getting a sewing machine, so he could design clothes, and he refused to move his belongings from the cave to the apartment because he worried about bringing in bugs. He wanted to put up ''No Smoking'' signs, vowing not to indulge his old addictions in his new environment. Johnny, an ex-convict who served time in the early 1990s for a drug-related offense, has been smoking cocaine since he was a teenager.</p>
        <p>One Sunday in January, Johnny slept on the bed, on top of the covers, wearing a leather jacket and muddy boots. He resembled not the sole occupant of Apartment 3B, but a visitor. He said he spent the night in the apartment, then went back to the cave at 6 a.m., then returned later that morning to the apartment. The flashlight he used in the cave still shone inside his jacket pocket.</p>
        <p>He woke up and sat outside on the back fire escape, smoking a cigarette. Behind him, he could hear the water running in the bathtub, his bathtub. On the streets, he used to wash up at an open fire hydrant.</p>
        <p>Johnny survives on a monthly check from the federal Supplemental Security Income program. As part of his arrangement with the Bridge, the nonprofit group that provided the apartment, his rent would be $168 a month, about 30 percent of his government check. Sister Lauria and two case managers, one from the Bridge and one from the Visiting Nurse Service of New York, planned to help him make the transition.</p>
        <p>The bed and the furniture had been supplied by the Bridge. Yet furnishings were not new to Johnny. In the cave, he had created a makeshift home: Sleeping on a quilt-covered mattress atop milk crates, keeping a bottle of cologne near the bed, cooking with cans of Sterno, using a car battery to power a DVD player. He was not awed by 3B, but somewhat suspicious of it.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes the one living in that cardboard box is happier than the one living at the penthouse,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Johnny had been living in the cave off and on since 1986, and for the last nine years or so he had settled in permanently. The abandoned train station sits in a fenced-off area thick with weeds and trash not far from Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>Sister Lauria tried for years to persuade Johnny to get out of the cave, but it was not until last year that he told her he wanted to leave. ''I realized I would have been better off doing 10 years in prison than nine years in that cave, crawling in and out, getting scabs, bugs,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Johnny's homelessness was not about a lack of housing. It was more complicated, a result of a variety of spiritual, psychological and emotional causes. ''Everything just bothering my conscience,'' he said of the reasons he was homeless. ''How can I ask God for forgiveness when I don't forgive myself? So I'll torture myself and go to the cave.''</p>
        <p>Sister Lauria often coaxed him out of the cave with the promise of odd jobs and a good laugh. He became one of her regular assistants, accompanying her on holidays to feed the homeless. Last year, a deliveryman who works in the neighborhood needed a place to stay, so Johnny gave him his room in the cave and moved to the opposite wall.</p>
        <p>''I try to imitate her,'' Johnny said of Sister Lauria, a member of the Sisters of St. Dominic of Blauvelt, N.Y. ''She imitates Christ. I try to imitate her.''</p>
        <p>She was thrilled for Johnny when he moved into the apartment. ''I felt like I was a mother sending my son away to college,'' said Sister Lauria, who helps the homeless as an outreach worker for the Highbridge Community Life Center and as a manager of a thrift shop run by Siena House, a women's shelter.</p>
        <p>But she was worried about how he would cope. She had seen other homeless people struggle to adapt to life indoors.</p>
        <p>Johnny struggled, too. Weeks after moving in, he kept returning to the cave. He missed his cats, whom he called his soldiers. He missed his old neighborhood around Ogden Avenue. He went back out of concern for his former roommate, the deliveryman, and he went back to feed his addictions. He hates and loves his crack cocaine habit, just as he hates and loves his cave. ''When you pick up drugs,'' he said, ''you're saying goodbye to all your dreams, all your goals and all you can be.''</p>
        <p>He figured he stayed in the cave the first three weeks he had the apartment. By March, he had taken the doors off a closet and used them as partitions to create a small darkened hideout, like a room in the cave. By April, Sister Lauria had not seen him for about two weeks, so she paid him a visit. She found he had put up plastic tablecloths and plastic bags all over the apartment, on the walls and on the ceiling. He told her he thought his neighbors were spying on him.</p>
        <p>He took down the plastic, but moved out soon after. He lived there for four months, from early January to late April.</p>
        <p>He said he had become uncomfortable there. ''Even though I had paid the rent, I never really slept there,'' he said. ''There was no life in the apartment. I will compare it to a spring break, with all the utilities and this and that and whatever. But no, it's not for me.''</p>
        <p>The Bridge had offered him another apartment and tried to have him undergo a psychiatric evaluation, but Johnny missed those appointments. ''We hope that Johnny will come back,'' said Mr. Beitchman, the executive director of the Bridge. ''We do hope. Our experience in all these years is that folks are at different points of readiness at different times.''</p>
        <p>Johnny returned to Ogden Avenue and began running errands again for Sister Lauria. She helped get him a job at a substance abuse treatment program. Johnny did janitorial work for several days. Then he quit. He was overpaid by mistake, and he returned the money because he felt it was the right thing to do.</p>
        <p>In the end, he left the apartment for reasons that made sense only to him. Because of his paranoia and schizophrenia, because of crack, because he felt isolated from those who knew him best, because of the cats, because the bathroom was too small, because he didn't want to live there without a spouse.</p>
        <p>Some in his old neighborhood were upset with Johnny, but Sister Lauria told them not to judge him. Whenever Johnny became fed up once again with life on the streets, she was ready to help him find another apartment.</p>
        <p>''Even though housing seemed like a baby step in light of everything else going on in his life, it was too much of a big step,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Johnny said he was now sleeping in a plywood hut he had built near the cave. He was a jumble of emotions, a paradox of hope and despair. He said he worried that he might be infected with H.I.V. He said that he had never been happier and that the best thing God ever made was tomorrow.</p>
        <p>One recent afternoon, Johnny was back in the cave. Candles lighted a back room in a far corner, at the end of a maze of garbage bags and concrete walls. He talked about fixing it up again. He smoked some crack through a thin glass tube the size of a cigarette. Then he crawled out, worried about Sister Lauria.</p>
        <p>His life swayed in this way, between the world above and the one below. On Friday, he said he was ready to work with the Bridge again and to give an apartment another try. He had thrown the tube that he uses as a crack pipe against a wall in the cave. It had been nearly two days since he last got high. ''I had to tell Satan, 'You don't own me,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>He went to a store across the street from the thrift shop. He bought a bottle of nonalcoholic sparkling apple cider, to celebrate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
