<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Missing a Sweep, but Little Else</title>
    <meta content="11racing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/sports/othersports/11racing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853827"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Street Sense (Race Horse)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E2DD173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="907" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Missing a Sweep, but Little Else</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Missing a Sweep, but Little Else</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Todd Pletcher confessed that it had yet to become real to him. How he had led Rags to Riches to the paddock for the Belmont Stakes on Saturday, then met the filly in the winner's circle, where both were toasted for a rare racing feat. She had broken his 0-for-28 streak of futility in Triple Crown races; she had become the third filly to win in the 139 years of the Belmont, known as the Test of the Champion, and the first since Tanya in 1905.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if it's all sunk in yet, the historical significance of it and all,'' Pletcher said yesterday. ''It's a pretty special win.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Short of a horse sweeping all three races, this was as exciting and satisfying a Triple Crown campaign as has been witnessed in many years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Todd Pletcher confessed that it had yet to become real to him. How he had led Rags to Riches to the paddock for the Belmont Stakes on Saturday, then met the filly in the winner's circle, where both were toasted for a rare racing feat. She had broken his 0-for-28 streak of futility in Triple Crown races; she had become the third filly to win in the 139 years of the Belmont, known as the Test of the Champion, and the first since Tanya in 1905.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if it's all sunk in yet, the historical significance of it and all,'' Pletcher said yesterday. ''It's a pretty special win.''</p>
        <p>Rags to Riches walked the shedrow and her muscular chestnut frame was no worse for the wear from outrunning Curlin, the Preakness Stakes champion. The two 3-year-olds ran shoulder to shoulder for the last quarter mile in 23 4/5 seconds, wickedly fast considering that it came in the stretch of the Belmont's marathon mile and a half.</p>
        <p>''She came back well,'' Pletcher said. ''It was a great day and I think a popular victory. It was great for the sport and great for the Belmont, and it made for good TV.''</p>
        <p>Short of a horse winning the Triple Crown by sweeping the Kentucky Derby, the Preakness and the Belmont -- or at least pulling into New York with a shot at the feat, which was last accomplished by Affirmed in 1978 -- this was as exciting and satisfying a Triple Crown campaign as has been witnessed in many years. It had three star-making performances: Street Sense came from 19th place to win the Derby; then he was run down by Curlin in a stirring stretch duel in the Preakness; and the series was capped by Rags to Riches's unforgettable victory.</p>
        <p>Now what?</p>
        <p>With good health and a lot of luck, this threesome of 3-year-olds may meet in August races like the Haskell Invitational at Monmouth Park or the Travers Stakes at Saratoga, or perhaps in October in the $5 million Breeders' Cup Classic.</p>
        <p>The team behind Rags to Riches is game to have its star filly take on the boys again. Her owners, Michael Tabor and Derrick Smith, are from Britain and they race in Europe, where battles between the sexes are more common.</p>
        <p>''I would say it's more than possible,'' Tabor said. ''Obviously, there are some filly races like the Alabama that I suppose we would like to win. Hopefully, we'll take on the boys whenever we think it's appropriate.''</p>
        <p>Even though Rags to Riches is 5 for 6 in her career and has earned more than $1.2 million, Pletcher said he would handle her carefully in the hope of nurturing a long career. He said her next start would probably be the Grade I Coaching Club American Oaks for 3-year-old fillies at Belmont Park on July 21.</p>
        <p>Then he would decide between competing against 3-year-old fillies in the Grade I Alabama Stakes on Aug. 18 at Saratoga, or against 3-year-old colts in the Haskell Invitational on Aug. 5 at Monmouth Park or the Travers Stakes on Aug. 25 at Saratoga.</p>
        <p>''The filly is going to make those decisions,'' Pletcher said. ''My job is to read how the filly is doing and when she's ready to run.''</p>
        <p>Street Sense's trainer, Carl Nafzger, and his owner, Jim Tafel, decided to skip the Belmont in favor of the Grade II Jim Dandy Stakes on July 29 at Saratoga and then the Travers. Street Sense was the 2-year-old male champion and his stallion rights have already been purchased by Darley America, the United States arm of the breeding operation of Sheik Mohammed bin Rashid al-Maktoum, the ruler of Dubai.</p>
        <p>Nafzger and Tafel intend to campaign the colt for the rest of the year with the ultimate goal of capturing the Breeders' Cup Classic on Oct. 26 at Monmouth.</p>
        <p>Curlin and Hard Spun were the only two colts to contest all three legs of the Triple Crown, and they did so determinedly. Hard Spun was second in the Derby, third in the Preakness and fourth at the Belmont.</p>
        <p>''He ate well last night and his legs are good and cold,'' his trainer, Larry Jones, said yesterday. ''We're not going to plan on anything right away. We'll let him recharge his batteries. He won't run again until August.''</p>
        <p>The strapping Curlin has also earned the vacation that his trainer, Steve Asmussen, promised to give him. Curlin's loss by a head to Rags to Riches was only his second defeat in a brilliant, brief and perhaps brutal campaign. The colt has run six times since February.</p>
        <p>Curlin might have been an inexperienced racehorse in the Derby when he overcame a terrible start to finish third, but he became more seasoned with each Triple Crown race. Curlin and Hard Spun have the same races on their dance card as Rags to Riches and Street Sense. ''Curlin is definitely a throwback,'' Asmussen said. ''The races that he's run since March with the pressure that has been on him. I can't say enough about him. The one thing we've learned with Curlin is that he's a competitor. He's got a lot of fight in him.''</p>
        <p>Horse enthusiasts can not only be grateful for the past five weeks of Triple Crown races, but also can keep their fingers crossed that these talented 3-year-olds stay healthy and renew their rivalries in the summer and the fall.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
