<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pettersen's Putts Seal L.P.G.A. Championship</title>
    <meta content="11lpga" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/sports/11lpga.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853825"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ladies Professional Golf Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pettersen, Suzann</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3DD173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pettersen's Putts Seal L.P.G.A. Championship</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pettersen’s Putts Seal L.P.G.A. Championship</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <dateline>HAVRE DE GRACE, Md., June 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>All Suzann Pettersen had to do to win her first major championship Sunday was two-putt from 30 feet. As she stood over her uphill putt on her 72nd hole of the L.P.G.A. Championship, the fans surrounding the 18th green grew quiet.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, Pettersen backed off the putt and a collective gasp rose from outside the ropes at Bulle Rock Golf Course.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Suzann Pettersen’s psyche had been much discussed all week because of how she lost a large lead in the year’s first major, but this time she did not falter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>All Suzann Pettersen had to do to win her first major championship Sunday was two-putt from 30 feet. As she stood over her uphill putt on her 72nd hole of the L.P.G.A. Championship, the fans surrounding the 18th green grew quiet.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, Pettersen backed off the putt and a collective gasp rose from outside the ropes at Bulle Rock Golf Course.</p>
        <p>Pettersen's psyche had been much discussed all week because of how she lost a four-stroke lead in the final holes of the year's first major, the Kraft Nabisco Championship, to hand the tournament to Morgan Pressel.</p>
        <p>As Karrie Webb stood behind the green and Pettersen stood over her putt for a second time, there was reason to wonder if Pettersen's emotions were once again going to be her undoing.</p>
        <p>But this time she did not falter. Using a putter she received from her pro-am partner earlier in the week, she stroked the ball and it rolled to a stop two inches from the cup. She tapped in for a par to post a final round of five-under-par 67 and a four-day total of 14 under par 274. She beat the seven-time major winner Webb, who also shot a 67 Sunday, by one stroke.</p>
        <p>Pettersen, who was in the final twosome of the day, the way she was at the Kraft Nabisco, birdied four of the last nine holes to slay her demons and Webb.</p>
        <p>''I was really calm,'' Pettersen said. ''I felt good. I could feel a bit of tension coming on the back nine and then the last couple of holes. But experience, it does help. I felt good.''</p>
        <p>Pettersen's playing partner, Na On Min, carded a 70 and finished third at 12 under.</p>
        <p>The experience of playing in the final twosome in her first major seemed to overwhelm Min, the third-round leader.</p>
        <p>She made bogeys on Nos. 6, 7 and 8 when she missed par putts that were all inside 9 feet, but rebounded on the back with four consecutive birdies.</p>
        <p>''On the front nine, I just thought too much in my head when I was putting,'' Min said. ''The last nine I just want to forget about it and focus on the hole and my ball.''</p>
        <p>Min took up the game less than six years ago, when she was 12. At the same age, Michelle Wie played in three L.P.G.A. events, playing her way into the field in Monday qualifying in two of them.</p>
        <p>Since then, Wie has gained acclaim for hurdling age and gender barriers, playing in tournaments with women and men, most of whom were considerably older. But since she last broke par in a competitive round, at the Women's British Open last July, other teenagers have stepped to the fore.</p>
        <p>Pressel was 18 years 10 months in April when she won the Kraft Nabisco and became the youngest player to win an L.P.G.A. major. She carded a 73 Sunday to finish 14th. The 18-year-old Angela Park closed with a 71 to place fifth.</p>
        <p>The emergence of Pressel, Park and Min during the four months that Wie was sidelined with wrist injuries has taken some of the blush off Wie's youth. She carries herself with a weariness that was not there at this time last year, when she was contending nearly every week on the L.P.G.A. Tour.</p>
        <p>After posting a 79 Sunday to finish at 21 over par, the highest score by 10 strokes, Wie said seeing other teens grab the spotlight that once was trained solely on her was inspiring.</p>
        <p>''I don't care who wins, it makes me want to be better,'' she said. ''I think that's the real fun part of what we're doing. You play better and then other players play better, so there's always this constant struggle to be at the top.''</p>
        <p>After finishing her roller-coaster round, Min met with members of the Korean news media behind the 18th green. She almost made it through the interview without crying, but at the end she could no longer stem the tears.</p>
        <p>Pettersen could relate to how Min was feeling. Golf is a humbling game, she said. It can exalt you one day and embarrass you the next. ''You want to be under the pressure,'' Pettersen said.</p>
        <p>''It's a good test,'' she added. ''Sometimes you will pass it and sometimes you will fail it. In this game, you will probably fail it more than you will win it. So you just have to appreciate the wins when you finally do get them.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
