<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METROPOLITAN DIARY</title>
    <meta content="11diary" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/nyregion/11diary.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853793"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Metropolitan Diary"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metropolitan Diary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stations and Terminals (Passenger)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stations and Terminals (Passenger)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E3DE173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METROPOLITAN DIARY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dear Diary</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Observed at the corner of 10th Street and Third Avenue in Manhattan:</p>
        <p>A large oil truck stops for a red light. A woman and her dog cross in front of it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A pint-sized straphanger amuses shoppers at Fairway, a dog shows his love for the open road and two strangers finally meet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Observed at the corner of 10th Street and Third Avenue in Manhattan:</p>
        <p>A large oil truck stops for a red light. A woman and her dog cross in front of it.</p>
        <p>Though the dog's leash is unattached and draped around the woman's shoulders, he is heeling obediently.</p>
        <p>But suddenly he whirls and races back toward the truck. The dog gazes rapturously up at the driver, pounding his paws on the asphalt, tail wagging at a furious pace.</p>
        <p>The woman calls his name and the dog returns to her side. But then he does a quick U-turn and returns to the truck, performing a full reprise of his joyous canine dance.</p>
        <p>Finally, the woman clips the leash to the dog's collar and leads him away, calling to the befuddled tanker driver: ''What can I tell you? He likes trucks.'' Sean O'Malley</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>While my family and I were checking out at Fairway recently, another customer walked up to the cashier and asked if her line was the express line. The cashier replied that it was not.</p>
        <p>My 5-year-old son, an experienced straphanger, turned to me and asked, ''Is this the local line?''</p>
        <p>Everyone within earshot had a laugh. Leslie Brown</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>The young parents and their 3-year-old got on the No. 2 train at 14th Street, after asking how to get to the Museum of Natural History. They were clearly visitors to the city. He carried an overstuffed backpack, she a folded stroller.</p>
        <p>Mother found a seat and dad held on to an overhead bar, while their son grabbed the vertical bar with one hand and began to spin around gleefully.</p>
        <p>The woman sitting next to his mother said, ''He can have my seat if you like.''</p>
        <p>His mother replied, ''Thank you, but I want him to have the complete subway experience.''</p>
        <p>Robert M. Feinstein</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>I was walking north on a crowded Avenue of the Americas recently in a slight drizzle. A young couple emerged from the subway steps 20 feet in front of me.</p>
        <p>Just as they hit the sidewalk she began to shout: ''You can't leave me with this baby! And I'm having this baby.'' They shared an umbrella, and were in front of me, and she was still upset. ''You said you loved me!''</p>
        <p>Everyone looked over at them. It was uncomfortable to be that close to that personal a discussion. We all stopped at 57th Street to wait for the light. I was right behind them and I could see that the woman was laughing. The man was smiling and looking away from her.</p>
        <p>I tapped her on the shoulder and said, ''You guys were joking?'' They both burst out laughing and squeezed my arms, leaning in as if trying to hide their faces.</p>
        <p>I said, ''What gives?''</p>
        <p>She said, ''Well, he told me on the subway that he could embarrass me more in public than I could embarrass him.''</p>
        <p>I looked at him and said, ''She wins.''</p>
        <p>He said, ''I know.'' John Hassan</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>My first New York City apartment was a small studio on Sullivan Street where I lived by myself for the first and only time in my life. While I was frequently alone in my apartment, quite often when I'd go outside, I'd coincidentally see the same woman over and over again.</p>
        <p>She was about 10 years older than I was, with dark hair, somewhat scholarly looking. We never spoke or even really made eye contact, yet I saw her so often and in so many locales that it seemed slightly surreal.</p>
        <p>I'd usually see her at the subway station around 8:30 on my way to work, but if I went in earlier or later than normal, there she would be.</p>
        <p>I noticed her at a newsstand around midnight on Saturday buying a paper many blocks from where we lived. I once saw her on the Upper West Side. Whatever time of day or night I'd hit the grocery store, she'd be there, too. Although the woman never acknowledged me, I had to wonder if she realized what a strangely silent part of each other's lives we'd become.</p>
        <p>Early one evening, I went to Bumble and bumble and got my long, straight hair cut into an Anna Wintour-like bob. The next morning, the woman showed up near me on the subway platform and walked right up to me without missing a beat.</p>
        <p>Looking me straight in the eye, she said, ''I liked it better long.''</p>
        <p>Leslie Long</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Diary</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
