<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sri Lanka Human Rights Panel Is Criticized</title>
    <meta content="11lanka" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/world/asia/11lanka.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853764"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sri Lanka</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sengupta, Somini</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rajapakse, Mahinda (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sri Lanka</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Sri Lanka</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Sri Lanka</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EEDF173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="459" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sri Lanka Human Rights Panel Is Criticized</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sri Lanka Human Rights Panel Is Criticized</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOMINI SENGUPTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sengupta, Somini</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, June 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>International panel appointed by government of Sri Lanka issues stark indictment of presidential commission impaneled to investigate serious human rights violations;panel's appointment was seen as effort by Pres Mahinda Rajapakse to stave off moves to deploy international human rights monitors to his country; Sri Lanka's descent into full-fledged civil war has been accompanied by spate of mysterious abductions, extrajudicial killings and other human rights abuses (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An international panel appointed by the government of Sri Lanka has issued a stark indictment of a presidential commission impaneled to investigate serious human rights violations, saying that its activities so far ''do not satisfy international norms and standards.''</p>
        <p>The appointment last fall of the panel, the International Independent Group of Eminent Persons, was widely seen as an effort by President Mahinda Rajapakse to stave off moves to deploy international human rights monitors to his country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An international panel appointed by the government of Sri Lanka has issued a stark indictment of a presidential commission impaneled to investigate human rights violations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An international panel appointed by the government of Sri Lanka has issued a stark indictment of a presidential commission impaneled to investigate serious human rights violations, saying that its activities so far ''do not satisfy international norms and standards.''</p>
        <p>The appointment last fall of the panel, the International Independent Group of Eminent Persons, was widely seen as an effort by President Mahinda Rajapakse to stave off moves to deploy international human rights monitors to his country.</p>
        <p>As Sri Lanka has descended into full-fledged civil war over the past year, there have been a spate of mysterious abductions, extrajudicial killings and other human rights abuses. Security forces and their allied paramilitary groups have been blamed for some of the abuses.</p>
        <p>The 11-member international panel has a limited mandate: to ''observe'' the workings of a commission of inquiry, which the president's office appointed last fall.</p>
        <p>The commission is to carry out independent investigations into 16 high-profile cases in which there have been accusations of human rights abuse, starting with the killings last August of 17 employees of a Paris-based aid group, Action Against Hunger, in the eastern town of Mutur. The killings are also under investigation in a criminal court in the eastern part of the country.</p>
        <p>In its first statement, issued late Sunday, the international group faulted the commission of inquiry, saying that it had dawdled since its inception last November and that its independence had been compromised by interference from the attorney general's office, which acts as the legal counsel to the commission. As the government's top law enforcement authority, the group said, the attorney general's office faces a conflict of interest in investigating crimes in which government officials, including security forces, are suspected.</p>
        <p>''We consider these to be serious conflicts of interest, which lack transparency and compromise national and international standards of independence and impartiality,'' the statement said.</p>
        <p>The panel went further to say that the commission of inquiry ought not to be seen as ''a substitute for robust, effective measures including national and international human rights monitoring.''</p>
        <p>The attorney general's office issued a sharp retort to that last observation, calling it ''inappropriate'' and urging the group to stick to making ''observations and recommendations in terms of its mandate.''</p>
        <p>The commission of inquiry, for its part, disputed that its reliance on the attorney general undermined its independence. It said it expected that the government would soon enact a witness protection law, enabling witnesses to come forward without fear.</p>
        <p>In an interview last month, the chairman of the commission of inquiry, Nissanka Kumara Udalagama, said the commission had not heard from a single witness in the killings of the aid workers, its first case. ''There are witnesses, but they are frightened to come forward,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
