<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Passport Rules Bring Worry Over Tourism at Niagara Falls</title>
    <meta content="11border" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/nyregion/11border.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070613T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853844"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Niagara Falls (New York)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Ontario/Niagara Falls (Canada)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Ontario</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Passports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Passports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Identification Devices</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Niagara Falls (Ontario)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EFDD173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1483" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Passport Rules Bring Worry Over Tourism at Niagara Falls</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Passport Rules Bring Worry Over Tourism at Niagara Falls</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID STABA</byline>
      <dateline>NIAGARA FALLS, N.Y., June 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Standing at Prospect Point in Niagara Falls State Park, Paul Cranley looked through the mist formed by millions of gallons of water dropping more than 160 feet to the gorge below.</p>
        <p>''It's pretty awesome,'' said Mr. Cranley, a retired chemist from Lake Jackson, Tex., who had brought his wife and son more than 1,500 miles to see Niagara Falls for the second time, 21 years after their first visit. ''It's incredible to get up close to all that water. One would hope that people on both sides could see all of it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New rules could discourage millions of visitors and result in billions of dollars a year in lost revenue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Standing at Prospect Point in Niagara Falls State Park, Paul Cranley looked through the mist formed by millions of gallons of water dropping more than 160 feet to the gorge below.</p>
        <p>''It's pretty awesome,'' said Mr. Cranley, a retired chemist from Lake Jackson, Tex., who had brought his wife and son more than 1,500 miles to see Niagara Falls for the second time, 21 years after their first visit. ''It's incredible to get up close to all that water. One would hope that people on both sides could see all of it.''</p>
        <p>But as the vacation season begins in earnest, many people in the tourism industry and other businesses dependent on travel fear the repercussions of changes looming for crossing the border between the United States and Canada. They say the new rules could discourage millions of visitors from coming to one of the nation's most majestic and romantic tourist attractions and result in billions of dollars a year in lost revenue.</p>
        <p>Starting in January, the plan approved in 2004 -- known as the Western Hemisphere Travel Initiative and suggested by the 9/11 Commission -- will for the first time require Americans traveling by land or sea to Canada, Mexico, Bermuda and the Caribbean to present a passport, a less expensive alternative called a passport card or one of several frequent-traveler cards already available. A passport requirement for those flying between the United States and those places went into effect in January but was temporarily lifted last week.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year Congress recommended that the deadline for beginning the land and sea portion of the plan be extended until June 2009, but the Department of Homeland Security has repeatedly said it intends to stick with the original deadline of January 2008. And despite the government's refusal to delay the plan, officials at the State Department and the Department of Homeland Security said in congressional hearings last month that the government had not tested the proposed cards or the machines to process them.</p>
        <p>''It is a security vulnerability as identified by Congress and the 9/11 Commission,'' said Kelly Klundt, a Homeland Security spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>Since January, people flying between the United States and those destinations have been required to present passports. But on Friday the State Department said that because it has been unable to keep up with the surge in new passport applications, it would allow travelers to fly without a passport until the end of September if they could present a State Department receipt showing they had applied for one, as well as a piece of government-issued identification, like a driver's license.</p>
        <p>After the announcement, Homeland Security Secretary Michael Chertoff said the department would begin to phase in the land and sea strictures beginning in January.</p>
        <p>So as the government tightens security between the United States and Canada, the world's longest nonmilitarized border -- 5,526 miles over land and water -- businesses in both countries are growing increasingly wary. A survey conducted by Ontario's Niagara Parks Commission in 2005 showed that 36 percent of Americans and 37 percent of Canadians said they would ''severely curtail'' the number of times they crossed the border if a passport were required.</p>
        <p>Arlene White, executive director of the Binational Tourism Alliance, which has offices in Niagara Falls, Ontario, and Buffalo, said the Niagara Falls region would be hit particularly hard.</p>
        <p>The bill's impact would be felt beyond tourism in industries including trucking and manufacturing, Ms. White said. New York's trade with all of Canada totaled almost $38 billion in 2006, while Ontario did more than $285 billion of business with the United States, according to statistics provided by the Canadian government.</p>
        <p>''If they make everyone have a passport, you'll see people just start to stay away from the border,'' Ms. White said. ''The thought of this actually being allowed to happen is unfathomable to me.''</p>
        <p>About 20 million people travel to Niagara Falls each year, with each side of the border offering a vastly different experience.</p>
        <p>In New York, visitors can walk within yards of the brink of the falls in at least six different places. Ontario's park touches the edge of the cataracts in only one spot, but offers a panoramic and breathtaking view.</p>
        <p>The differences are even more pronounced beyond the parks themselves.</p>
        <p>Niagara Falls, Ontario, offers more flash, with the neon signs for wax museums, restaurants and souvenir shops lighting up Clifton Hill and Lundy's Lane, the area's main drags, and four new high-rise hotels and two observation towers lining the gorge.</p>
        <p>The tourism industry is less developed on the New York side, with smaller, mostly older hotels and scattered attractions operating in the shadow of the 26-story Seneca Niagara Casino Hotel, which is four blocks from the state park.</p>
        <p>Together, public and private investment in infrastructure and attractions on both sides of the border since 2004 has run into the billions, Ms. White said.</p>
        <p>The American and Canadian sides each have wine trails, casinos and historic landmarks dating to the colonial period. And Buffalo's professional football and hockey teams, the Bills and the Sabres, rely on a healthy influx of customers from Ontario, as do ski resorts and shopping centers.</p>
        <p>''We fill each other's gaps,'' Ms. White said. ''We have tourism 12 months of the year -- who else has that? You cross the border into Buffalo and you just sort of shed your Canadian skin. You feel like, 'I'm in another country, I'm on vacation, I can just relax.' ''</p>
        <p>Yet fewer people are experiencing that feeling, perhaps because of the common misconception that a passport is already required to cross the border by car or boat, Ms. White said. A study taken by the Canadian government in January showed that bridge traffic into Canada was the lightest since 1972.</p>
        <p>That trend concerns two members of the local congressional delegation who seldom find themselves on the same side of an issue.</p>
        <p>''Tourism and trade with Canada is one of the only sections of our economy that is growing,'' said Representative Thomas M. Reynolds, a former chairman of the National Republican Congressional Committee. ''Even if the reduction is only 5 percent, that's going to be devastating for western New York.''</p>
        <p>Representative Louise Slaughter, a Democrat who is chairwoman of the House Rules Committee, said: ''The idea of implementing this as soon as this January is a pipe dream. Canada is our biggest trading partner -- it's our life's blood. A large part of the economies of northern states depends on easy access and trade with Canada.''</p>
        <p>Adding to the growing sense of frustration, at Senate hearings in early May, Homeland Security officials questioned by Senator Charles Schumer said the passport cards and the machines to read them had not been tested in the field.</p>
        <p>Miss Klundt, the department spokeswoman, said that a cost analysis was under way and that the National Institute of Standards and Technology had certified the technology for the proposed passport card, which would enable customs inspectors to see a picture of each traveler and verify citizenship at inspection areas at the border.</p>
        <p>''What works quickest?'' Miss Klundt asked. ''Going through wrinkled birth certificates and trying to establish that you are that person, or swiping through a card?''</p>
        <p>So far the Canadian government, which has frowned on the requirements, has no plans for a lower-cost passport alternative. Rather, the premiers of Ontario, Manitoba and New Brunswick visited Washingtonin February, asking the federal government to delay the plan and consider a program with an enhanced driver's license with citizenship verification instead.</p>
        <p>Ms. Slaughter and Mr. Reynolds have also suggested that option, citing a pilot program in Washington State that was approved in March by Homeland Security. That test does not begin until Jan. 1 -- the earliest the passport requirement could start.</p>
        <p>''Why in the world would they set forth on a pilot project and not wait to see the results before putting something else into effect?'' Ms. Slaughter asked.</p>
        <p>She said she planned to introduce a measure next week withholding $100 million of the $202 million budgeted to enact the travel requirements in 2008 and 2009 until the departments complete economic and technological feasibility studies, which would push the deadline back at least a year.</p>
        <p>''They've got to accept that they've got an awful mess that they can't handle,'' Ms. Slaughter said.</p>
        <p>Further complicating the issue, a plan for the two countries to share management of the border stalled this spring after Canadian officials balked at the Department of Homeland Security's desire to fingerprint anyone who turned around at the border rather than provide documentation of citizenship.</p>
        <p>''Canada will not consider any proposal that would diminish the basic individual rights of Canadians,'' that country's public safety minister, Stockwell Day, said after talks broke down.</p>
        <p>Representative Reynolds said of the border negotiations with some exasperation, ''These guys have done more to strain our relationship with Canada than anything since the French and Indian War.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 13, 2007, Wednesday  A map on Monday with an article about fears that tourism in the Niagara Falls area will suffer when tighter border restrictions take effect mislabeled an island in the Niagara River between New York and Ontario. It is Goat Island, not Duck Island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 13, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A map on Monday with an article about fears that tourism in the Niagara Falls area will suffer when tighter border restrictions take effect mislabeled an island in the Niagara River between New York and Ontario. It is Goat Island, not Duck Island.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
