<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Battle for Bermuda Bowl Slot Turns Close With a Late Surge</title>
    <meta content="11card" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/crosswords/bridge/11card.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853751"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Bridge"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cards and Card Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cards and Card Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E0DF173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Battle for Bermuda Bowl Slot Turns Close With a Late Surge</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Battle for Bermuda Bowl Slot Turns Close With a Late Surge</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Phillip Alder</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the final of the trial to select the U.S.A.-2 team for this year's Bermuda Bowl headed toward its conclusion late last night in Shaumburg, Ill., what had seemed a runaway suddenly turned close. The 120-board match pitted Nick Nickell, Dick Freeman, Bob Hamman, Paul Soloway, Jeff Meckstroth and Eric Rodwell against Russ Ekeblad, Ron Rubin, Fred Gitelman, Brad Moss, Chip Martel and Lew Stansby, with Ekeblad surging late. (The final result is at usbf.org.)</p>
        <p>The match started quietly, with the Nickell team ahead 12 international match points to 5 after 10 boards. But Nickell gained three big swings in the last five deals to lead 47 imps to 12 at the end of the first session. The most interesting gain occurred when Rodwell made a fake lead-directing double of a five-diamond control-bid (cue-bid) on three to the jack. This talked Martel and Stansby out of a laydown seven-heart contract, giving Nickell 13 imps.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the final of the trial to select the U.S.A.-2 team for this year’s Bermuda Bowl headed toward its conclusion late last night in Shaumburg, Ill., what had seemed a runaway suddenly turned close.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the final of the trial to select the U.S.A.-2 team for this year's Bermuda Bowl headed toward its conclusion late last night in Shaumburg, Ill., what had seemed a runaway suddenly turned close. The 120-board match pitted Nick Nickell, Dick Freeman, Bob Hamman, Paul Soloway, Jeff Meckstroth and Eric Rodwell against Russ Ekeblad, Ron Rubin, Fred Gitelman, Brad Moss, Chip Martel and Lew Stansby, with Ekeblad surging late. (The final result is at usbf.org.)</p>
        <p>The match started quietly, with the Nickell team ahead 12 international match points to 5 after 10 boards. But Nickell gained three big swings in the last five deals to lead 47 imps to 12 at the end of the first session. The most interesting gain occurred when Rodwell made a fake lead-directing double of a five-diamond control-bid (cue-bid) on three to the jack. This talked Martel and Stansby out of a laydown seven-heart contract, giving Nickell 13 imps.</p>
        <p>There was little scoring in the second set, Nickell staying ahead 67 imps to 34.</p>
        <p>In contrast, the third session was wild, with 70 imps changing hands. But only 18 went to Ekeblad, leaving Nickell in front 119 imps to 52. Ekeblad was plus 3 imps in the last session on Saturday to trail overnight by 153 imps to 89.</p>
        <p>Yesterday morning, Nickell moved another 14 imps in front. But Ekeblad struck back in the sixth set, regaining 50 imps to make the score Nickell 199, Ekeblad 171 with 30 boards to be played.</p>
        <p>The diagramed deal was Board 50. In both rooms, the contract was six diamonds. At the other table, it was played by Meckstroth (North) because Rodwell (South) opened one club, showing 16-plus points, and North responded two diamonds, which described a balanced hand with 8-10 points.</p>
        <p>In this auction, the two-heart response by Martel (North) showed one ace or two kings. His four no-trump was saying that he had some extra values but no control in clubs. So Stansby (South), placing his partner with the heart ace, jumped to six diamonds.</p>
        <p>It is good slam, only slightly worse than one out of two finesses. There are ways to get home if you could look at all the hands, but both declarers started similarly. They won the first trick with South's bare club ace, cashed the diamond ace, then played a heart to North's queen. After winning with his king, what should East have returned?</p>
        <p>Hamman, looking at the North hand as the dummy, led back his heart seven, which defeated the contract. Declarer won with North's ace, played a spade to his ten, cashed one more round of trumps, then tried to take his top spades, but West ruffed the third round to defeat the contract.</p>
        <p>At the other table, Gitelman, looking at the South hand, had a tougher task. He knew declarer (North) had four hearts and not four spades. Probably hoping not to save declarer a heart guess, he shifted to a low spade, but Meckstroth ran it to his eight, drew two rounds of trumps, cashed the spade ace, ran the rest of the trumps and played a heart to his ace, bringing everyone down to two cards. North retained the spade deuce and club queen, South had the king-ten of spades. East was caught in a black-suit showup squeeze. He had to discard either a spade, so his queen would appear, or (his actual choice) the club king.</p>
        <p>Plus 50 and plus 920 gave the Nickell team 14 imps.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
