<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Top Editor Is Leaving Book Post</title>
    <meta content="11random" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/11/business/media/11random.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853744"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Random House Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Menaker, Daniel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Centrello, Gina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bosman, Julie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rich, Motoko</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Random House</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Menaker, Daniel</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E1DF173FF932A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Top Editor Is Leaving Book Post</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Top Editor Is Leaving Book Post</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE BOSMAN and MOTOKO RICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bosman, Julie; Rich, Motoko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daniel Menaker, executive editor of Random House Publishing Group, will leave company at end of June; president and publisher Gina Centrello insists that company will not change its strong emphasis on literary fiction (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Daniel Menaker, the executive editor in chief of the Random House Publishing Group who was hired four years ago for his strong literary credentials, is leaving the company at the end of June.</p>
        <p>His departure will be announced today in a memo to employees, Random House executives said yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Daniel Menaker, the executive editor in chief of the Random House Publishing Group, is leaving the company at the end of June.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Daniel Menaker, the executive editor in chief of the Random House Publishing Group who was hired four years ago for his strong literary credentials, is leaving the company at the end of June.</p>
        <p>His departure will be announced today in a memo to employees, Random House executives said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The move seemed to be an indication that Random House was shrugging off the sophisticated literary fiction that Mr. Menaker had nurtured. But Gina Centrello, the president and publisher of Random House, insisted that the direction of the imprint would not change.</p>
        <p>Mr. Menaker's responsibilities will be divided between Kate Medina, executive editorial director of the group's Random House hardcover imprint, and Jennifer Hershey, editorial director of the Random imprints. Ms. Medina is adding the title of associate publisher and Ms. Hershey will report to her.</p>
        <p>Random House is also expected to announce today that Kurt Andersen, the author and the host of ''Studio 360,'' has been named editor at large, where he will suggest new nonfiction books. Last week, Random House, which published Mr. Anderson's best-selling novel, ''Heyday,'' announced a two-book deal with him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Menaker, 65, said that the decision to leave was ''absolutely mutual'' and that he would continue to edit some of the authors he has worked with at Random House.</p>
        <p>''I cannot emphasize to you how fine I am about this,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Centrello said: ''Dan and I talked about this for a long time, what was right for him and what was right for Random House. Now he can stop with the administrative duties and spend more time on writing.''</p>
        <p>This was Mr. Menaker's second stint at Random House, a unit of Bertelsmann; he first joined the company in 1995. He took his current position in 2003 when he returned after 16 months as an executive editor at HarperCollins. Mr. Menaker also spent 26 years as an editor at The New Yorker.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Menaker was first hired in 2003, Ms. Centrello said it signaled Random House's commitment to literary fiction. Among the writers he edited at Random House were Billy Collins, the former poet laureate; Gary Shteyngart, author of ''Absurdistan''; and Benjamin Kunkel, the author of ''Indecision.''</p>
        <p>But some of his titles failed to flourish financially. Most recently, a first novel by Mr. Kunkel was a critical darling but sold only 15,100 copies in hardcover, according to Nielsen BookScan, which tracks most online and retail sales.</p>
        <p>Ms. Centrello dismissed the suggestion that Mr. Menaker's exit was prompted by a failure to score enough commercial successes. ''I didn't hire Dan to be a commercial editor,'' she said. ''He was hired to acquire literary novels, which he did.''</p>
        <p>When asked if Mr. Menaker's decision was voluntary, Carol Schneider, a Random House spokeswoman, said ''I don't think we will go into the details of it.'' She added that Mr. Menaker and Ms. Centrello, had ''decided together.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Menaker said that both he and Ms. Centrello had ''tried different combinations and permutations for my staying on physically and in the house.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Menaker said he had already discussed with Ms. Centrello the possibility of publishing two books with Random House, including a memoir and another unidentified project. ''I don't want to say anything about it because it is a good idea and I am afraid someone will take it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He said he also wanted to spend time writing a novel and learning to play the fiddle, ''something I always wanted to do.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Menaker is the author of ''The Treatment,'' which was published by Alfred A. Knopf, another unit of Bertelsmann, and two collections of short stories. He is married to Katherine Bouton, an editor at The New York Times Magazine and has written a book of humor with Charles McGrath, the former editor of The New York Times Book Review and now a writer at large at the paper.</p>
        <p>The appointment of Mr. Andersen, a fixture on the New York media circuit since he help found Spy magazine in 1986, could be seen as an effort to restore some of the literary cachet that Random House may lose with Mr. Menaker's departure.</p>
        <p>''I think he's really smart and very well connected,'' Ms. Centrello said. ''What he's going to be doing is coming up with ideas, thinking about what's happening in the world today and trying to connect with the people who can tell us those stories.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Andersen's role at the company will be limited. He will not have an office in the building, for instance, and he will continue as a columnist for New York magazine and the host of ''Studio 360.''</p>
        <p>''It's a consulting arrangement,'' Mr. Andersen said when reached at home yesterday. He added that Ms. Centrello told him, ''If I can find them two or three books that they publish a year, she'll be ecstatic.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
