<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Motivation That Benefits Wrong Team</title>
    <meta content="02vecsey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/sports/baseball/02vecsey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851512"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Torre, Joe</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E5DE1030F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="892" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Motivation That Benefits Wrong Team</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Wrong Team Gets Boost Yanks Needed</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has taken awhile, but Alex Rodriguez has finally managed to unify an entire major league team. Unfortunately for him, it is not the Yankees.</p>
        <p>The last we saw of the Toronto Blue Jays, most of them were sitting in their dugout, glaring at the Yankees right after Wednesday night's game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Of all the Yankees, only Alex Rodriguez has the tools to carry a slumping team, but instead he has been involved in three questionable moments on the field in recent years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has taken awhile, but Alex Rodriguez has finally managed to unify an entire major league team. Unfortunately for him, it is not the Yankees.</p>
        <p>The last we saw of the Toronto Blue Jays, most of them were sitting in their dugout, glaring at the Yankees right after Wednesday night's game.</p>
        <p>The Blue Jays were upset because Rodriguez had shouted something to spook the Blue Jays' rookie third baseman, Howie Clark, causing him to allow a pop fly to fall for a base hit. Last night, Manager Joe Torre openly put the blame on Rodriguez.</p>
        <p>''It's probably something he shouldn't have done,'' Torre said before the Yankees beat the Red Sox by 9-5 last night in a game that became factious toward the end, to cut the Sox lead over them to 12 1/2 games.</p>
        <p>Torre, permanently mellow from decaffeinated green tea, later managed to get himself tossed by the third-base umpire, Jerry Crawford, who had made an atrocious out call on Bobby Abreu. The Yankee manager thus became linked with the great San Antonio basketball player Tim Duncan, who was run from a game this season by Crawford's even crankier brother, Joey, for the high crime of smirking. Joey Crawford was promptly suspended.</p>
        <p>Torre was definitely not smirking, although maybe he smirked in private after the double catharsis of barking at Jerry Crawford after criticizing Rodriguez, his $252 million third baseman for his stunt in Toronto. ''It's not something he's going to do again,'' Torre said emphatically, not flinching when it was pointed out that A-Rod had managed to annoy the Blue Jays, with whom the Yankees still have 14 games left.</p>
        <p>''Aw, that's football stuff,'' Torre said, adding that baseball teams should not play better when upset. ''Whatever happened to self-motivation?'' Torre asked, a fair enough question that can also be applied to the aging, plodding Yankees. Maybe in the old days -- a couple of decades ago -- a Billy Martin or a Dallas Green could bully a team into playing better for a few months, until the novelty wore off, but that is less likely to work in these days of rich and sensitive players. Lou Piniella, considered one of those emotional types who could fire up the Yankees, has his own troubles, what with his battery, Carlos Zambrano and Michael Barrett, staging a nasty fight in the dugout and clubhouse yesterday.</p>
        <p>Rodriguez was hardly the main reason the Yankees were so far behind the Red Sox. Jason Giambi's body seems to be wearing down, much the way Mark McGwire's did late in his career. (Yes, I am making a point about the body-building stuff they may have poured into their systems without exactly knowing how it is all going to end.)</p>
        <p>Last night, Torre said Giambi would be out at least five weeks and that Johnny Damon would replace Giambi as the designated hitter, leaving Melky Cabrera in center field and giving the Yankees a decidedly second-string look.</p>
        <p>Torre, who loves Bernie Williams as a parent figure, said Williams missed his chance to get in shape during spring training, and that it's too late now. Plus, if you stop and think about it, the beloved Williams would probably look even creakier than he did last year.</p>
        <p>Of all the Yankees, only Rodriguez has the tools to carry a slumping team, but instead he has been involved in three questionable moments on the field in recent years -- slapping the ball from Bronson Arroyo of the Sox in 2004, raising an elbow at the end of a slide into Dustin Pedroia of the Sox a few weeks ago, and shouting something at the Jays' rookie infielder Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>The Blue Jays say Rodriguez shouted ''Mine,'' and Rodriguez said he was merely shouting ''Ha,'' which would have been a desperate move even in the sandlots. The ethics of the ball field seem to shift from year to year, or hour by hour. Stealing bases in a one-sided game used to be regarded as overkill, at least until sluggers began developing muscles hitherto unseen in baseball uniforms. Now stealing a base is explained as just a way to offset the next seven-run homer. And there are other modern affronts to ballplayer pride.</p>
        <p>''I've told players not to watch their home runs,'' Torre said, referring to the habit of watching the ball soar, then glancing at the replay on the message board.</p>
        <p>The hapless Rodriguez also called attention to himself by being noticed with a blonde woman entering his hotel in Toronto, the photograph winding up in a New York tabloid. Last night some Boston fans wore masks with bright blonde hair to taunt Rodriguez, who has more important things to worry about.</p>
        <p>The Red Sox management accentuated the positive by introducing a quorum of players from the 1967 Impossible Dream team that won the pennant. On the 40th anniversary of the release of the classic ''Sgt. Pepper'' album, Dr. Charles Steinberg, the impresario of the Sox, produced a video of Red Sox highlights over the decades, with the Beatles in the background. Cute.</p>
        <p>It wasn't so cute in the ninth when the Yanks' Scott Proctor was ejected for hitting Kevin Youkilis after a night of hit batsmen and smoldering annoyance. Torre, somewhere out of sight, wound up using Mariano Rivera in the one-sided game. Hard to blame this one on A-Rod.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
