<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Strange, Faraway Fantasies of Hell and Paradise</title>
    <meta content="02weil" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/arts/music/02weil.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851402"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/South Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/South Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">South Carolina</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Weill, Kurt</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Brecht, Bertolt</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Dusapin, Pascal</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Alden, Christopher</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEED81330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Strange, Faraway Fantasies of Hell and Paradise</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Strange, Faraway Fantasies of Hell and Paradise</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES R. OESTREICH</byline>
      <dateline>CHARLESTON, S.C., June 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two more disparate works could hardly be imagined. And yet they have odd similarities.</p>
        <p>As two of its three operas this year, the Spoleto Festival U.S.A. here is offering Kurt Weill's collaboration with Bertolt Brecht ''Aufstieg und Fall der Stadt Mahagonny'' (''Rise and Fall of the City of Mahagonny'') and Gluck's ''Île de Merlin, ou le Monde Renversé'' (''Merlin's Island, or the World Turned Upside Down''). Both send peculiar creatures to faraway places, and both deal, in contrasting ways, with social issues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At Spoleto U.S.A., two disparate works, “Aufstieg und Fall der Stadt Mahagonny” and “Île de Merlin, ou le Monde Renversé,” have odd similarities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two more disparate works could hardly be imagined. And yet they have odd similarities.</p>
        <p>As two of its three operas this year, the Spoleto Festival U.S.A. here is offering Kurt Weill's collaboration with Bertolt Brecht ''Aufstieg und Fall der Stadt Mahagonny'' (''Rise and Fall of the City of Mahagonny'') and Gluck's ''Île de Merlin, ou le Monde Renversé'' (''Merlin's Island, or the World Turned Upside Down''). Both send peculiar creatures to faraway places, and both deal, in contrasting ways, with social issues.</p>
        <p>(The third opera is Pascal Dusapin's ''Faustus, the Last Night,'' which has its last performance on June 9.)</p>
        <p>In ''Mahagonny'' three fugitives establish a fantastical city in some realm far from civilization, but, as it turns out, within hurricane's distance of Pensacola, Fla. In ''Merlin'' two Parisian wastrels wash up on a remote Arcadian island.</p>
        <p>''Mahagonny,'' a morality play awash in cynicism and pessimism, depicts a hellish world in which there is no such thing as peace and harmony, a world of greed and grasping ambition, a world in which you must do whatever you want before others do unto you what they want. The courts are ''no worse than anywhere else.'' It can only end badly.</p>
        <p>''Merlin,'' a Panglossian comic effusion, offers a paradise in which the rich must marry the poor, artists earn more than businessmen or lawyers, and love is lasting and faithful. The courts know no corruption. It is, in short, the opposite of Paris. And all that is before Merlin appears to fine-tune the outcome.</p>
        <p>For ''Mahagonny,'' in the Sottile Theater, Patrice Caurier and Moshe Leiser, the directors, have devised a colorful and rollicking production set more or less in Weill's time. It offers few subtleties, but those can be effective, as when the chorus is backlighted in the rear of the auditorium to produce an ominous play of shadows onstage.</p>
        <p>Rather than let audience members remain above the fray, as high-minded observers of the sorry scene, Mr. Caurier and Mr. Leiser draw them into the muck. If the proper response to this work is a kind of queasy depression only mildly relieved by the cathartic ending -- and it is hard to see how it could be anything else -- the production succeeds nicely indeed.</p>
        <p>Christopher Alden, the director of ''Merlin'' at the Dock Street Theater, has forgotten the meaning of the word subtle, if he ever knew it. Scapin and Pierrot are depicted as sheer louts in grungy contemporary dress, right down to Superman briefs. They call each other Dude, exchange high fives and deliver lines like, ''You're hotter than Helen of Troy.''</p>
        <p>Despite its excesses, and they are legion, it is hard to dislike this lark of a production. The opera itself is not always subtle and no great masterpiece, and if you're going to revive this sort of thing in the first place, you might as well have harmless fun with it. It is, if nothing else, memorable, in a way that ''Mahagonny'' may not end up being.</p>
        <p>The overall level of performance, too, argues in favor of ''Merlin.'' The fine ensemble cast on Thursday had well-matched baritones, Eugene Brancoveanu as Scapin, and Keith Phares as Pierrot. Monica Yunus and Amanda Squitieri, sopranos, were equally appealing as their amorous partners, Argentine and Diamantine.</p>
        <p>The soprano Constance Hauman made a bawdy and robust doctor, Hippocratine, with her bosom spilling all over the stage. Richard Troxell, a tenor, made appealing work of a series of mostly comic roles, culminating in that of Merlin.</p>
        <p>The pit band, the cumbersomely named Ginn Resorts Spoleto Festival U.S.A. Orchestra, was excellent, as it had been the night before in ''Mahagonny'' (and in a Thursday morning memorial concert in honor of the composer Gian Carlo Menotti, who founded the festival in 1977, acrimoniously left it in 1993 and died in February). The early-music specialist Harry Bicket, conducting with a light hand, achieved just the right effervescence.</p>
        <p>The heavier hand of Emmanuel Villaume, the festival's music director, was equally well judged on Wednesday in ''Mahagonny,'' appropriate to its very different purposes. The vital and engaged performance of the young orchestra, in fact, was the musical highlight of that evening.</p>
        <p>Richard Brunner sang the antihero Jimmy Mahoney with a suitably brash tenor. And the soprano Tammy Hensrud, as the prostitute Jenny Hill, spun out the ''Alabama Song'' for all of its considerable worth. Karen Huffstodt, a soprano, sounded worn at the start as Begbick, but gathered strength as the evening progressed. Inevitably, perhaps, Beauregard Palmer and Timothy Nolen proved more distinctive for their personas as Fatty and Trinity Moses than for their singing.</p>
        <p>As usual, the operas are surrounded by a teeming array of other musical events, dance and theater. And the charms of the city, for once shorn of the oppressive heat and humidity that usually attend the festival, are everywhere.</p>
        <p>''L'Île de Merlin'' will be repeated tonight and on Thursday, and ''Aufstieg und Fall der Stadt Mahagonny'' tomorrow and next Saturday. The Spoleto Festival U.S.A. runs until June 10; spoletousa.org.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
