<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spitzer Pushes a Plan for Paid Leave to Care for Relatives</title>
    <meta content="02leave" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/nyregion/02leave.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851491"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E5DF1030F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1015" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spitzer Pushes a Plan for Paid Leave to Care for Relatives</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spitzer Pushes Paid Leave Plan for Workers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE; Danny Hakim contributed reporting.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer is pushing behind the scenes to win legislative backing for a plan that would give workers several weeks of paid leave to care for newborn children or seriously ill family members.</p>
        <p>Under the plan -- which would make New York one of three states to provide paid family leave -- workers could take up to 12 weeks per year off, with a maximum benefit of $170 a week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer wants to make New York the third state to give workers paid leave to care for newborn children or seriously ill family members.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer is pushing behind the scenes to win legislative backing for a plan that would give workers several weeks of paid leave to care for newborn children or seriously ill family members.</p>
        <p>Under the plan -- which would make New York one of three states to provide paid family leave -- workers could take up to 12 weeks per year off, with a maximum benefit of $170 a week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer's plan would be more expansive than the paid leave in Washington State, which is limited to caring for newborns and newly adopted children, and in California, which covers workers caring for a seriously ill child, parent, spouse or domestic partner. Mr. Spitzer's plan would also cover workers who take off to care for grandchildren, foster parents and parents-in-law.</p>
        <p>To allay employers' concerns about the plan's cost, Mr. Spitzer is proposing that the leave be paid by workers rather than by employers, with 45 cents a week deducted from every worker's paycheck.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Spitzer has been able to line up the support of the Democratic-controlled Assembly, advocates of the plan say he has not yet been able to gain enough support in the Republican-controlled Senate. But supporters say they are optimistic that Mr. Spitzer will prevail. They say the main obstacle is employers who fear that the plan will disrupt their operations by making it easier for workers to leave for 12 weeks.</p>
        <p>Several top aides to the governor said in interviews yesterday that the he was working closely with legislators, businesses and labor leaders in the hope of winning passage of the plan later this year. His aides often use the term ''family care benefit'' instead of paid family leave.</p>
        <p>''For the first time, it will allow working New Yorkers to take the necessary time to care for a sick family member or bond with a newborn child without going broke,'' a top Spitzer aide said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer's plan would be far more generous than the federal Family and Medical Leave Act, which gives covered workers 12 unpaid weeks of leave to care for seriously ill family members or the birth or adoption of a child and guarantees them the right to return to the same jobs.</p>
        <p>The New Jersey State Legislature is considering a plan that would offer 10 weeks of paid leave. Benefits would be two-thirds of weekly pay, up to a maximum of $488.</p>
        <p>Donna Dolan, chairwoman of the New York State Paid Family Leave Coalition, said her group has urged Mr. Spitzer to embrace paid leave because unpaid leave places many workers in a bind.</p>
        <p>''Studies have shown that 78 percent of people who qualify for unpaid family and medical leave can't afford to take it,'' Ms. Dolan said.</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Spitzer's plan, New York would offer longer leaves but lower benefits than other states. California offers six weeks' paid leave with a maximum benefit of $882 a week, while Washington offers five weeks at $250 a week.</p>
        <p>Advocates of paid leave say their main criticism of Mr. Spitzer's plan is that its benefits are low: 50 percent of weekly pay, up to a maximum benefit of $170.</p>
        <p>''My concern is if the rate isn't raised now, it will take several years before we can get it raised,'' Ms. Dolan said.</p>
        <p>Under the governor's plan, the limited number of companies and firms that already provide paid family leave -- some for up to six months -- can be exempted from the program, including the 45-cent weekly deduction, by showing state officials that their programs are at least as good as the state plan.</p>
        <p>The Senate Labor Committee will hold a hearing on Tuesday about paid family leave. The Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, said yesterday that he saw a great deal of merit to the idea.</p>
        <p>''We've always been responsive to the needs of working families and people, so it's something we're going to be taking a close look at,'' Mr. Bruno said.</p>
        <p>Labor unions, women's groups and the Working Families Party have been the primary advocates of paid leave.</p>
        <p>''It's a common-sense reform, and for the governor it looks like a win-win,'' said Daniel Cantor, executive director of the Working Families Party. ''We're still going to have to persuade the Republican Senate on this, but it feels doable because this is a very popular idea.''</p>
        <p>Under state law, New Yorkers can receive six to eight weeks of temporary disability benefits of up to $170 a week after giving birth. Under Mr. Spitzer's plan, women who give birth could obtain 12 additional weeks of paid family care leave.</p>
        <p>State officials say they have worked hard to defuse opposition from business groups. Kenneth Adams, president of the New York State Business Council, the state's main business group, praised Mr. Spitzer for being sensitive to business's needs, especially by agreeing to have employees finance the leaves.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, Mr. Adams said his group opposed the plan. ''At the end of the day,'' he said, ''the proposal is, by design, inherently going to increase absenteeism, and that's going to increase costs and create burdens for employers.''</p>
        <p>Mike Elmendorf, state director of the National Federation of Independent Business, said his group, which represents smaller companies, would oppose the plan because it does not exempt small businesses, as the Family Medical and Leave Act does for workplaces with fewer than 50 employees.</p>
        <p>''Small businesses don't have the excess labor that larger businesses have to help them cover when someone is gone for an extended period,'' Mr. Elmendorf said. ''That could help put a small company out of business.''</p>
        <p>One of the thorniest questions for the governor is whether the plan would cover public-sector workers. Under Mr. Spitzer's proposal, public-sector unions could opt out of the plan. Some unions, most notably the Civil Service Employees Association, want their members to have the right to opt out if the union negotiates provisions on paid family leave. But Dick Ianuzzi, the president of the New York State United Teachers, said that teacher unions would generally be happy to participate in the plan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
