<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From a Long Line of Onlies, a Mother of Two</title>
    <meta content="03essay" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/nyregion/03essay.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851523"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E5D91030F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From a Long Line of Onlies, a Mother of Two</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From a Long Line of Onlies, a Mother of Two</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I get plenty of ribbing from my husband about being an only child. His theory, after spending most of his life with a younger sister, goes something like this: The size of the bite one mooches off a cupcake is inversely proportional to the number of siblings one has. Only children never got pinched by anyone for taking more than their share, so they never learn.</p>
        <p>Apparently, I take too much of the cake.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>I get plenty of ribbing from my husband about being an only child. His theory, after spending most of his life with a younger sister, goes something like this: The size of the bite one mooches off a cupcake is inversely proportional to the number of siblings one has. Only children never got pinched by anyone for taking more than their share, so they never learn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I get plenty of ribbing from my husband about being an only child. His theory, after spending most of his life with a younger sister, goes something like this: The size of the bite one mooches off a cupcake is inversely proportional to the number of siblings one has. Only children never got pinched by anyone for taking more than their share, so they never learn.</p>
        <p>Apparently, I take too much of the cake.</p>
        <p>That aside, I enjoyed growing up as one of the few only children I knew. I didn't buy into the stereotype that we were lonely or obnoxious. I liked my share of solitude, and never felt spoiled with toys or lessons or clothes, just with attention. I did sense the responsibility of being the distillation of the hopes and dreams of an awful lot of people, but I don't recall begging for anyone to share the spotlight with.</p>
        <p>I remember being a little more comfortable with adults than with children. Grownups tended to pass the crackers and inquire politely about one's school experiences. Children, at least in my neighborhood, tended to tie each other up and hog all the good parts of the bus-stop productions of ''The Wizard of Oz.'' I had a feeling that kids who were truly kids' kids knew things I didn't -- like how to roll around on the ground in a scrum, or how to come up with the truly most sticking insult.</p>
        <p>Because both my mother and her mother were only children as well, and my father had one brother who never married, my family could hold a reunion in a Volkswagen Beetle, and we had to scrape for relatives at holidays. My main cousin, also an only child, was my great-great-grandmother's sister's great-great-grandson, which took a while to explain, but didn't detract from the quality of Thanksgiving dinner conversation.</p>
        <p>Being everybody's only child and grandchild had both pluses and minuses. It brought with it more glorious attention, though at times that could resemble sunlight coming through a magnifying glass. But after college, I began to think that if there had been siblings around, my parents could have spent less time worrying about me, especially when I felt I was doing just fine.</p>
        <p>Only as a young adult did I learn that siblings have something really handy that I lacked -- someone to whom you could say ''Hey, what's up with them today?'' about the grown-ups. Living without someone to commiserate with about the occasional parental quirk, I think I was more likely to assume that the adults in the house were pretty infallible. I probably would have been better at questioning authority if I'd had a sibling or two who were a little less reverent.</p>
        <p>Some combination of baby lust, curiosity about the sibling mystique, a morbid desire to have an heir and a spare, and my husband's wishes led me to break the three-generation streak. When my second was born, I got a front-row seat at siblinghood. It nearly sprained my very genes.</p>
        <p>My 3-year-old, who had been perfectly happy being the only daughter of an only daughter of an only daughter of an only daughter, thank you very much, expressed what all those other displaced firstborns feel, though I had until that moment not wanted to believe the rumors I had heard about this.</p>
        <p>''Mama,'' my big-hearted Kate said soon after Drew was born, ''Maybe we can find a poor family who doesn't have a baby, and we can give them Drew.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps I have suffered fewer psychological traumas as an only child than if I'd been born into a family where someone wanted to give me to charity. But I know already that Drew has had a more entertaining babyhood than Kate did, because he has her to laugh at and keep him company in the back seat of the car.</p>
        <p>And they will have each other for comparing notes about their childhoods, finding the perfect nursing home for us, and dividing up the annoying stashes of yarn and fly-fishing gear we are sure to leave them.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, I'll just let one of them cut every cupcake in half, and let the other one choose which part to eat. It will teach them, early on, about life.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
