<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Iraqi Bombers Thwart Efforts To Shield G.I.'s</title>
    <meta content="02military" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/washington/02military.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851450"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shanker, Thom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meigs, Montgomery C (Gen) (Ret)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E5D61330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="997" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Iraqi Bombers Thwart Efforts To Shield G.I.'s</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Iraqi Bombers Thwart Efforts to Shield G.I.’s</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOM SHANKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shanker, Thom</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US commanders express frustration at increasing death toll in Iraq caused by makeshift explosives, which have killed 80 percent of Americans who died in combat over last three months, despite billions of dollars being spent to fight threat; bombs are known as improvised explosive devices, and Pentagon has formed Joint IED Defeat Organization to combat users; retired Army Gen Montgomery C Meigs is director of group; total of US deaths in April and May was highest of any two-month period since war began, and 80 percent ratio caused by makeshift explosives is higher than it has ever been, up from 50 percent in Jan; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>American commanders are expressing frustration at the increasing death toll in Iraq caused by makeshift explosives, which have killed 80 percent of the Americans who died in combat over the last three months, despite the billions of dollars being spent to fight the threat.</p>
        <p>The proportion of American deaths caused by explosives has sharply increased, even as the Pentagon has made a major effort to defend the troops with armored vehicles, to detect or disarm the weapons, and to attack the bomb-making cells and those who finance them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even as the Pentagon works to defend against makeshift explosives, the proportion of American deaths caused by them has sharply risen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>American commanders are expressing frustration at the increasing death toll in Iraq caused by makeshift explosives, which have killed 80 percent of the Americans who died in combat over the last three months, despite the billions of dollars being spent to fight the threat.</p>
        <p>The proportion of American deaths caused by explosives has sharply increased, even as the Pentagon has made a major effort to defend the troops with armored vehicles, to detect or disarm the weapons, and to attack the bomb-making cells and those who finance them.</p>
        <p>The bombs are known as improvised explosive devices, or I.E.D.'s, and the Pentagon has formed a ''Joint I.E.D. Defeat Organization'' to combat the users. But in an interview on Friday, the director of that group said he recognized that the threat could not truly be defeated.</p>
        <p>''It can be mitigated, minimized, made into a nuisance,'' said the director, Gen. Montgomery C. Meigs, a retired Army officer who took over the project in December 2005. ''This is a very tough problem.''</p>
        <p>The total of American deaths in April and May was the highest of any two-month period since the war began, and the 80 percent ratio caused by makeshift explosives is higher than it has ever been, up from 50 percent in January.</p>
        <p>The increase coincided with the more aggressive operations being mounted by American troops in Iraq as part of the stepped-up campaign that President Bush ordered in January.</p>
        <p>Pentagon statistics released Friday showed that May was the third deadliest month of the war in Iraq. The official combat toll stood at 117 late Friday, but some deaths from the final days of the month will not be included until next of kin are notified, officials said.</p>
        <p>From the 50 percent rate for combat deaths in January, which represented a dip in the long-term trend, the share caused by explosives climbed to 59 percent in February and an average of about 80 percent for March, April and May.</p>
        <p>Pentagon officials said they did not compute such monthly statistics before this year, but estimated that improvised explosive devices were responsible for about 70 percent of the overall combat deaths since the devices first appeared on the battlefield of Iraq in 2003.</p>
        <p>The military plans to spend more than $4 billion to combat explosives this year, after spending about $5 billion over the three previous years. The spending has led to the deployment of better-armored vehicles to protect soldiers and new technology to detect and defuse the bombs, but commanders and Pentagon officials say their efforts have produced no more than temporary gains.</p>
        <p>''I do believe that we are instinctively prone to look for technological solutions,'' said one senior Pentagon official. ''That's the way we are wired, and that's the American tradition.</p>
        <p>''But bigger armor, more high-tech detectors and jammers will only take you so far. We never will solve the problem until we can get better intelligence and can break up these I.E.D. cells. And that will require changing the attitudes of the local population toward these explosions and those responsible for them. The Iraqis will have to help us root out the people involved.''</p>
        <p>Across Iraq and Afghanistan, explosives are in ample supply. Improvised bombs can be detonated at a distance by a variety of off-the-shelf systems, some as simple as a wire attached to a doorbell and some controlled by radio or cell phone.</p>
        <p>The United States has accused Iran of assisting Shiite insurgents in Iraq with more advanced designs that are able to penetrate even some armored vehicles.</p>
        <p>And there is a ready supply of unemployed or angry men willing to plant the devices.</p>
        <p>''The problem will not subside even when there is a stable situation of some kind reached in either Iraq or Afghanistan,'' General Meigs said. ''This is going to be around. This is too easy for an insurgent.''</p>
        <p>The anti-I.E.D. organization devoted 78 percent of its budget in the current fiscal year, ending Sept. 30, to defeating the explosives, with 13 percent of the money going to attack bombing networks and 9 percent to training the force.</p>
        <p>In an acknowledgment that the priority should be ''developing the kind of intelligence that is needed to go after these folks,'' General Meigs said, the share of money in the next fiscal year devoted to attacking the network would rise to 31 percent, while 62 percent of the budget would be reserved for detecting and defusing the bombs.</p>
        <p>A far greater number of the bombs are found and cleared today, or prove to be duds, than are effective in attacks. For security reasons, the organization does not release the total number of bomb attacks in Iraq, but General Meigs said bombers had to plant six times as many of the devices for each casualty than when the improvised explosives first appeared.</p>
        <p>''But that is not a satisfactory solution in our view, nor will it be in the view of soldiers and marines, nor will it be in the view of the families that support them,'' he said. ''You are not going to avoid casualties. It is our job to help commanders in the field to minimize them to the absolutely greatest extent possible.''</p>
        <p>Cracking into the bomb-making cells is difficult, and not only because they are far smaller and far more decentralized than traditional military targets of American intelligence.</p>
        <p>''The societal pattern in Oruzgan Province in Afghanistan is very different than in Diyala Province in Iraq,'' General Meigs said. ''So is the social structure. The motivations and ideology are different.''</p>
        <p>In Iraq, those assessing the threat divide their adversaries into three basic camps.</p>
        <p>Those associated with Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia strive for the spectacular bombing, of a mosque, government building or marketplace, in order to generate hostility and headlines.</p>
        <p>Those placed by Shiite forces are increasingly sophisticated, using technology the United States says is from Iran and can puncture armored vehicles. The Sunni-based insurgents plants bombs of a more homemade variety, but still deadly.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
