<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Montana, Under Pressure, to Take Bison Back to Yellowstone</title>
    <meta content="02bison" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/us/02bison.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070607T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851481"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bison</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Montana</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yellowstone National Park</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schweitzer, Brian (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Montana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/National Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Brucellosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Montana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wyoming/Yellowstone National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Brucellosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brucellosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Yellowstone National Park</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Montana</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Schweitzer, Brian</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E7DF1030F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Montana, Under Pressure, to Take Bison Back to Yellowstone</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Montana, Under Pressure, to Take Bison Back to Yellowstone</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>HELENA, Mont., June 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov Brian Schweitzer, facing outcry over plans to slaughter 300 bison that have repeatedly migrated out of Yellowstone National Park, says that Montana will load animals onto trucks if they strayed again and haul them deeper into park (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Facing an outcry over plans to slaughter 300 bison that have repeatedly migrated out of Yellowstone National Park, Gov. Brian Schweitzer said Friday that Montana would load the animals onto trucks if they strayed again and haul them deeper into the park.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't stomach the idea of hauling them to slaughter when you have all of that green grass in the park,'' said Mr. Schweitzer, who helped devise the new approach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Facing an outcry over plans to slaughter 300 bison that repeatedly migrate out of a national park, Gov. Brian Schweitzer has proposed a plan to truck them further in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Facing an outcry over plans to slaughter 300 bison that have repeatedly migrated out of Yellowstone National Park, Gov. Brian Schweitzer said Friday that Montana would load the animals onto trucks if they strayed again and haul them deeper into the park.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't stomach the idea of hauling them to slaughter when you have all of that green grass in the park,'' said Mr. Schweitzer, who helped devise the new approach.</p>
        <p>Bison that do not return to the park are usually killed. Last year, more than 900 bison were shipped to slaughter.</p>
        <p>Bison usually migrate out of Yellowstone in the winter when the snow is deep. The exodus last month was unusual.</p>
        <p>''To have these numbers of bison at this time of year is a situation we've not faced before,'' said Al Nash, a spokesman for the park.</p>
        <p>State officials have herded the animals on horseback and with vehicles back into the park six times this spring. Each time, they left again.</p>
        <p>This week, the Montana Department of Livestock announced plans to capture the 300 bison, including 100 calves, and ship them to a slaughterhouse.</p>
        <p>But the Buffalo Field Campaign, an environmental group that monitored the animals near West Yellowstone, issued an alert that resulted in the outcry and apparently helped stall the plan.</p>
        <p>Nearly 4,000 bison live in Yellowstone, and what to do with those that try to migrate has vexed officials for decades.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schweitzer, a Democrat, recently proposed making room for the bison outside the park by changing rules so that any outbreak of brucellosis on ranches up to 50 miles from the park would not be considered a strike against the state's brucellosis-free status, a federal designation that allows ranchers to ship their cattle without testing for the disease.</p>
        <p>Other state officials are cool to the idea.</p>
        <p>Adding to the controversy, brucellosis was found last month in seven cattle in a herd near Bridger. The animals were not found near the park, but were from a herd north of it. The outbreak has not been traced to Yellowstone bison.</p>
        <p>Ranchers say bison outside the park threaten the state's $1 billion-a-year livestock industry. If another herd tests positive, Montana would lose its brucellosis-free status, and that would require all ranches in the state to undergo expensive testing.</p>
        <p>Cattle ranchers in Idaho and Wyoming lost their brucellosis-free status in recent years, though the outbreaks there were traced to elk in the Yellowstone region.</p>
        <p>The prospect of slaughtering so many bison as the tourist season starts prompted Mr. Schweitzer to become involved. ''We've hazed them back in in six times and they've come out six times,'' he said. ''That's unprecedented.''</p>
        <p>The animals are now being herded. If they return, the Livestock Department will begin to carry them deep into the park.</p>
        <p>It is not a perfect solution, said Michael Mease, co-founder of the Buffalo Field Campaign, which has long been critical of the killing of bison outside the park.</p>
        <p>''It's the lesser of two evils,'' Mr. Mease said. ''They can be injured when they are trucked. The real answer is tolerance for public bison on public land.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schweitzer said that was not likely and that trucking the animals was the best option. ''I am walking a fine line,'' he said. ''We have to protect livestock from brucellosis and allow the bison to live with dignity.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 7, 2007, Thursday  An article on Saturday about a plan to return straying bison to Yellowstone National Park referred incorrectly in some copies to the type of animals from a herd north of the park that were found infected with brucellosis last month. They were cattle, not bison.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 7, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article on Saturday about a plan to return straying bison to Yellowstone National Park referred incorrectly in some copies to the type of animals from a herd north of the park that were found infected with brucellosis last month. They were cattle, not bison.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
