<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where the School Lunch Menu Includes Fire and Swords</title>
    <meta content="02pursuits" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/business/02pursuits.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851408"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="EXECUTIVE PURSUITS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Amusement and Theme Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Swords</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stunts and Stuntmen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Swords</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amusement and Theme Parks</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Hurt, Harry III</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E5D71330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1321" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where the School Lunch Menu Includes Fire and Swords</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Where the School Lunch Menu Includes Fire and Swords</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARRY HURT III</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hurt, Harry 3rd; Hurt, Harry III</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I HOBBLED down the Coney Island boardwalk in the footsteps of all the sideshow freaks who had come and gone before. The sun glinted off the Cyclone roller coaster and the carousels. Flags flapped in the wind. Mothers pushed baby carriages. Couples strolled arm in arm past hot-dog stands, piña colada huts and potholes strewn with broken glass.</p>
        <p>The crowd hardly noticed as I clutched my crutches and sidled down the 12th Street ramp. My only visible deformity was a heavily bandaged foot that resembled a reptile claw, thanks to a protruding metal pin surgically inserted to repair my hammer toe. Nothing suggested I was on an executive pursuit that would transform me into a fire-eating human blockhead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Coney Island school teaches the arts of carnival sideshows, like sword-swallowing and lying on a bed of nails.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I HOBBLED down the Coney Island boardwalk in the footsteps of all the sideshow freaks who had come and gone before. The sun glinted off the Cyclone roller coaster and the carousels. Flags flapped in the wind. Mothers pushed baby carriages. Couples strolled arm in arm past hot-dog stands, piña colada huts and potholes strewn with broken glass.</p>
        <p>The crowd hardly noticed as I clutched my crutches and sidled down the 12th Street ramp. My only visible deformity was a heavily bandaged foot that resembled a reptile claw, thanks to a protruding metal pin surgically inserted to repair my hammer toe. Nothing suggested I was on an executive pursuit that would transform me into a fire-eating human blockhead.</p>
        <p>I ducked through a steel door near the corner of Surf Avenue and entered a 1917 vintage auditorium that houses the sideshow school in Coney Island. It featured some wooden bleachers occupied by a dozen fellow students, black walls covered with murals depicting sword swallowers and snake charmers and a stage equipped with a faux electric chair.</p>
        <p>Todd Robbins, 43, dean of the school, bounded onto the stage. Six feet four inches tall with blond hair, a black vest and a mischievous grin, he was wielding a 100-year-old Moroccan sword. ''Most people think sword swallowing is fake, but it's the most dangerous act in the sideshow,'' he declared. ''People have died trying to do this. I myself once ended up in the emergency room in Wichita, Kan., at 3 a.m.''</p>
        <p>Todd tilted his head back, hoisted the sword over his mouth and then lowered the tip. The blade was 18 inches long and made of forged steel, but it seemed to slide down his throat as easily as a melting icicle. When the blade disappeared, he bowed forward from the waist to show the hilt protruding from his lips. Then he straightened up again and extracted the sword from his mouth. My fellow students and I applauded in wonder.</p>
        <p>''All the acts you're going to learn this evening are real,'' Todd assured us as he wiped the sword with a cloth. ''They're based on principles of physics and anatomy. But since most people slept through physics and anatomy in high school, the secrets have been safe until now.''</p>
        <p>I felt my own throat tighten in nervous anticipation as Todd outlined the curriculum. Founded in 2002, the sideshow school offers courses in spring and fall consisting of five classes lasting from 6-10 p.m. on weekdays. Subjects ranged from sword swallowing, in which you trained your throat to overcome its natural gag reflex, to lying on a bed of nails.</p>
        <p>Todd's recounting of bizarre sideshow history was worth the $600 tuition. He noted that sideshows were a major form of entertainment in Coney Island and in much of America through the first half of the 20th century. They were called ''10 in ones'' because they presented 10 acts in one venue, typically a small tent or catwalk adjacent to the main carnival arena. Except for notorious frauds perpetrated by the likes of P. T. Barnum, many of the acts demanded actual feats of derring-do and/or people who were unabashed in displaying their so-called oddities.</p>
        <p>Indeed, sideshows were among the nation's original countercultures, self-contained worlds with their own protocols and a three-rung hierarchy of performers. The royalty were the highly paid ''true freaks,'' people who were born with some kind of physical deformity. Two famous examples were Emmitt Bejano, the Alligator Man with scaly skin caused by ichthyosis, and his wife, Percilla the Monkey Girl, who had abnormally profuse hair growth. Married for 50 years, Alligator Man and Monkey Girl ended up owning their own traveling sideshow.</p>
        <p>The second rung of the hierarchy was occupied by ''self-made freaks,'' people born looking pretty much like everyone else who did something to make themselves different. They ran the gamut from performers with full-body tattoos and piercings to those who created artificial deformities like elongated lips and necks.</p>
        <p>The third rung consisted of ''working acts,'' otherwise normal people who learned the dark secrets of things like sword swallowing and fire eating, many of them dating back thousands of years to the fakirs of India.</p>
        <p>Todd himself was a working act. Born in Southern California, he had earned a theater degree and performed Shakespeare with the American Conservatory Theater in San Francisco. But at age 12, he had become enamored of the magic of the sideshow. ''I grew up in a safe, clean, unexciting suburb,'' he recalled. ''I wanted to experience something extravagant, especially those acts that were real and did not involve some form of deception.''</p>
        <p>Realizing that the sideshow counterculture was dying out, Todd persuaded several old masters like Ward Hall to share their secrets. In 1991, Todd started performing in Coney Island. He has since become chairman of Coney Island USA, which operates a museum as well as the sideshow school. He has performed on television, at Carnegie Hall and for major corporations like Fujifilm, Salomon Smith Barney and General Electric. Among his stunts is eating G.E. light bulbs, which he describes as ''very risky because you're playing Russian roulette with your intestinal tract for the next two days -- if the broken glass doesn't pass through, it can penetrate the lining and cause you to bleed to death.''</p>
        <p>I commenced my study of sideshow acts by becoming a human blockhead, a stunt that called for me to jam a nail up my nose. Todd wisely started me off with a Q-tip and a reassuring explanation of the secret involved. Contrary to popular misconception, he noted, the human nasal cavity goes straight back rather than straight up. He showed me how to locate the proper passage by keeping the Q-tip parallel to the floor. Sparing the gory details, suffice it to say that I made the Q-tip disappear, and I later managed to cover half of a 6-inch nail.</p>
        <p>Presently, we turned to fire-eating, a decidedly more dangerous stunt. ''Kids, don't try this at home -- wait until you get to school,'' Todd joked. Then he added in a cautionary tone: ''This is not for everyone. Occasionally, it throws people off, but if it does, we'll find a way to get you through it.''</p>
        <p>The tools required in fire-eating were a torch consisting of a metal stick with a wad of cotton fabric on the tip, a jar of camper-stove fluid and a lighter. The obvious hazards included singeing your lungs by inhaling the flame and blistering your lips on the torch. But by now I was willing to put my trust in Todd and his prescribed step-by-step approach.</p>
        <p>First, I dipped the cotton end of the torch into the camper-stove fluid and shook off the excess. I tilted my head back and licked my lips. Then I opened my mouth, took a deep breath and held it. Todd ignited my torch with his lighter. ''Now put the torch in your mouth, close your lips and keep them closed until I say O.K.,'' he instructed. ''That will put the fire out by depriving it of oxygen.''</p>
        <p>Next thing I knew, I devoured the first torch, then a second and a third. The only unpleasant aftereffects were a slight stinging in the back of my throat caused by the heat of the flames and what my long-suffering wife later described as ''horribly bad breath'' caused by the camper-stove fluid. I'd found my sideshow métier -- and something else I hadn't expected.</p>
        <p>''I've challenged you to expand your perceptions and how far you can stretch the boundaries of what is doable in your own life, '' Todd said. ''The desire to find out what is possible is what makes people go out and do great things.''</p>
        <p>Afew minutes later, I hobbled back out onto the Coney Island boardwalk and hoisted my crutches in jubilation, a solitary fire-eating human blockhead waving his freak flags at the starry sky.</p>
        <p>EXECUTIVE PURSUITS E-mail: pursuits@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: pursuits@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
