<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some on Journal Staff Voice Wish That Different Bidder Would Emerge</title>
    <meta content="02react" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/business/media/02react.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851445"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Dow Jones &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="online_producer">News Corporation Limited</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Wall Street Journal</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Murdoch, Rupert</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E6D61330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="642" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some on Journal Staff Voice Wish That Different Bidder Would Emerge</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Some on Journal Staff Voice Wish That Different Bidder Would Emerge</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDUARDO PORTER and LOUISE STORY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They only work there. But still, a small group of reporters and editors at The Wall Street Journal raised an outcry yesterday against Rupert Murdoch's plan to buy Dow Jones &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Less than a day after the family that controls Dow Jones, the Bancrofts, said in a statement that it would consider selling the company, a group of about 15 Wall Street Journal reporters and editors met in a conference room at the paper's headquarters and said they hoped to find another bidder they could endorse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A small group of reporters and editors at The Wall Street Journal raised an outcry against Rupert Murdoch’s plan to buy Dow Jones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They only work there. But still, a small group of reporters and editors at The Wall Street Journal raised an outcry yesterday against Rupert Murdoch's plan to buy Dow Jones &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Less than a day after the family that controls Dow Jones, the Bancrofts, said in a statement that it would consider selling the company, a group of about 15 Wall Street Journal reporters and editors met in a conference room at the paper's headquarters and said they hoped to find another bidder they could endorse.</p>
        <p>That may be wishful thinking. But the journalists hope that the Bancroft family will place significant weight on a newsroom recommendation.</p>
        <p>''That's the sort of comfort that could let the family take perhaps a less remunerative offer, knowing that folks that work every day in the newsroom feel O.K. with it,'' said a Journal staff member who attended the meeting and spoke only on condition of anonymity. ''We have a role to play in some way.''</p>
        <p>Steve Yount, the president of the Independent Association of Publishers' Employees, the union that represents Journal reporters, said: ''I do not believe that a News Corporation takeover is a done deal. I think there are people who are yet to be heard from.''</p>
        <p>None of them have come out of the woodwork yet.</p>
        <p>And even if they did, noted a Journal reporter, who also spoke only on condition of anonymity, it could raise other problems for the paper's editorial independence. ''Who would you get?'' he asked. ''Say it's Microsoft. How do you cover the computer industry if you are owned by Microsoft?''</p>
        <p>Several Journal reporters said that, in their view, the best outcome would be one in which The Wall Street Journal remained an independent entity.</p>
        <p>E. S. Browning, a financial reporter at The Journal, said he opposed any large company's purchasing of Dow Jones. ''When great newspapers get acquired by big conglomerates, they subsequently cease to be great newspapers,'' Mr. Browning said. ''I don't think that big conglomerates or big diversified media empires would have the same dedication to the paper that the Bancrofts have had.''</p>
        <p>Many in the Journal newsroom have not hidden their discomfort with Mr. Murdoch's bid. Dozens of reporters and editors wrote to members of the Bancroft family asking them to reject the News Corporation offer. The letter writers included James Bandler and Charles Forelle, reporters in Boston who just won Pulitzer Prizes for their articles on the backdating of stock options, and seven members of the China bureau who won the Pulitzer this year for international reporting. Many people who signed the letters were not active union members, a Journal reporter said.</p>
        <p>''We are well aware of the pressures facing our industry; they impact our careers and families as much as anyone else concerned, and many of us are shareholders as well as employees,'' read one letter, signed by two dozen staff members in the Washington bureau. ''But it's no secret that we in the newsroom believe the end of an independent Dow Jones would be an irreplaceable loss to our profession, and to our country.''</p>
        <p>Another Journal reporter said that Christopher Bancroft, a member of the family who has made some skeptical statements about the News Corporation bid, responded directly to many of the letters, assuring reporters that he would do what he could to ensure they could continue producing the same quality of journalism that they do today.</p>
        <p>Some in the newsroom doubted that a group of reporters and editors could sway the Bancrofts at this stage. ''The arguments are out there,'' one reporter said. ''The family knows them.''</p>
        <p>One indication of the depth of the skepticism in the newsroom is that several reporters have already started to look for other jobs.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people are contemplating their Plan B's in life,'' one said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
