<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beethoven And Friends, Together Once Again</title>
    <meta content="02emer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/arts/music/02emer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851405"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Emerson String Quartet</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Carnegie Hall</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Guzelimian, Ara</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Morris, Edmund</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E7D71330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beethoven And Friends, Together Once Again</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Beethoven and Friends, Together Once Again</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On paper a program of three string quartets by Haydn, Mozart and Beethoven may look terribly conventional. But the Emerson String Quartet, which began its performances in the Perspectives series at Carnegie Hall on Thursday night with such a program, had a larger purpose in mind.</p>
        <p>The Emerson has titled its series ''The Complete Beethoven Cycle: The Quartets in Context.'' The idea is to survey Beethoven's 16 quartets, starting tomorrow, placing the works in context with quartets by the composer's immediate predecessors and contemporaneous colleagues. Eventually it will expand to include Baroque works, seminal 20th-century quartets and pieces by living composers, everything from Bach to Kaija Saariaho.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On paper a program of three string quartets by Haydn, Mozart and Beethoven may look terribly conventional. But the Emerson String Quartet, which performed on Thursday night, had a larger purpose in mind.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On paper a program of three string quartets by Haydn, Mozart and Beethoven may look terribly conventional. But the Emerson String Quartet, which began its performances in the Perspectives series at Carnegie Hall on Thursday night with such a program, had a larger purpose in mind.</p>
        <p>The Emerson has titled its series ''The Complete Beethoven Cycle: The Quartets in Context.'' The idea is to survey Beethoven's 16 quartets, starting tomorrow, placing the works in context with quartets by the composer's immediate predecessors and contemporaneous colleagues. Eventually it will expand to include Baroque works, seminal 20th-century quartets and pieces by living composers, everything from Bach to Kaija Saariaho.</p>
        <p>So what better way to commence the series than by establishing Beethoven in the context of his times? Hence these three quartets, all in C major, by Haydn, Mozart and Beethoven, the Holy Trinity of the high classical style.</p>
        <p>That the Emerson Quartet played these pieces so compellingly here was no surprise. Concertgoers have come to count on these superb musicians, who are celebrating their 30th anniversary with this series and who continue to play with technical command, musical insight, vivid imagination and tireless enthusiasm.</p>
        <p>For me, the one disappointment of this program and the series is its location. Carnegie Hall's 2,800-seat Stern Auditorium is far from an ideal place to hear a string quartet. The acoustics are splendid, of course. And the playing came through with plush sound and clarity. But the performances inevitably seemed a little distant.</p>
        <p>There is no substitute for hearing chamber music in a chamber-size hall, where the sound of a string quartet has a physical presence and the spatial relationship between players and audience achieves the intended immediacy. These works were conceived for salons and music rooms that would have seated at best a couple of hundred people. It's notable that all three pieces received their Carnegie Hall premieres in the ideally intimate 268-seat space known today as Weill Recital Hall: Haydn's Op. 33, No. 3 in 1973; Mozart's K. 465 in 1898; and Beethoven's Op. 59, No. 3 in 1891.</p>
        <p>The Emerson has a large and deserved following, and there was an impressive turnout for this concert in the big hall. Still, though box-office revenue would have taken a hit and tickets would have been scarcer, it's unfortunate that the players did not conceive even one or two of their concerts in this series for Zankel Hall downstairs. Given this, today's ''Discovery Day'' program at Weill Recital Hall stands out: an all-day event starting at 11 a.m. with an introduction by Ara Guzelimian and keynote address by Edmund Morris, followed by discussions and demonstrations on topics related to the Beethoven works with the Emerson Quartet and some guest artists.</p>
        <p>Other than for its location, Thursday's concert was rewarding. The players gave a buoyant and elegant account of Haydn's ingenious 1781 Quartet, known as ''The Bird,'' from his miraculous and influential series of Opus 33 quartets. They brought rich shadings to the Mozart work, written in 1785 in tribute to Haydn, dubbed the ''Dissonance'' Quartet for the tonally unmoored, dissonance-saturated slow introduction to its first movement. The players made the clashing dissonances ever more shocking by executing them with such focused and piercing tone.</p>
        <p>They won a huge ovation for their dynamic account of the 1806 Beethoven work, the last of the three ''Razumovsky'' Quartets, which ends with a hyper-virtuosic finale, a whirlwind of rapid-fire counterpoint. After 30 years, these master musicians are still playing this music with youthful abandon and white-hot brilliance. If only we could have heard the performance up-close.</p>
        <p>The eight-concert series, running through June 17, continues tomorrow at Carnegie Hall; (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
