<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 American Pilots Are Indicted in Brazilian Airliner Crash</title>
    <meta content="02pilot" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/world/americas/02pilot.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070604T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851434"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Traffic Control</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brazil</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Amazon Jungle</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gol Linhas Aereas Inteligentes</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lepore, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Paladino, Jan Paul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pilots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Traffic Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pilots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brazil</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Honeywell International Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401EED71330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="506" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 American Pilots Are Indicted in Brazilian Airliner Crash</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">2 American Pilots Are Indicted in Brazilian Airliner Crash</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD; Andrew Downie contributed reporting from Rio de Janeiro.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brazilian judge indicts Joseph Lepore and Jan Paul Paladino, American pilots of corporate jet that collided with airliner over Amazon on Sept 29, 2006; four Brazilian air traffic controllers are also indicted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Brazilian judge on Friday indicted the two American pilots of a corporate jet that collided with an airliner over the Amazon on Sept. 29, along with four Brazilian air traffic controllers.</p>
        <p>After the crash, which killed all 154 people on the airliner, the Americans, Joseph Lepore, 42, of Bay Shore, N.Y., and Jan Paul Paladino, 35, of Westhampton, N.Y., were held in Brazil until December, then allowed to return to the United States and their Long Island homes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Brazilian Federal Police said that the two Americans had not knowingly caused the crash, but that their negligence had contributed to Brazil’s worst air disaster.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Brazilian judge on Friday indicted the two American pilots of a corporate jet that collided with an airliner over the Amazon on Sept. 29, along with four Brazilian air traffic controllers.</p>
        <p>After the crash, which killed all 154 people on the airliner, the Americans, Joseph Lepore, 42, of Bay Shore, N.Y., and Jan Paul Paladino, 35, of Westhampton, N.Y., were held in Brazil until December, then allowed to return to the United States and their Long Island homes.</p>
        <p>They were flying for ExcelAire Service Inc. of Ronkonkoma, N.Y. They had picked up a new Embraer Legacy from a Brazilian factory and were flying it back to the United States. The airliner that went down was a Boeing 737 operated by Gol Linhas Aéreas Inteligentes.</p>
        <p>A Brazilian federal judge in Sinop, a small Amazon town, agreed with the results of a Brazilian Federal Police inquiry and ruled that Mr. Lepore and Mr. Paladino were guilty of ''exposing an aircraft to danger.''</p>
        <p>The judge ordered the Americans to appear before him on Aug. 27 for questioning. Four Brazilian air traffic controllers were also charged.</p>
        <p>''I came to this conclusion because it was the only conclusion available to me,'' Judge Murilo Mendes said in a brief telephone interview. He said the two would not be permitted to give evidence in the United States.</p>
        <p>But the pilots' lawyer, Joel R. Weiss, said that endangering an aircraft was not one of the crimes listed in the extradition treaty between the United States and Brazil.</p>
        <p>He said he had not seen the judge's charge and could not say what the next step would be until he had read it. The Federal Police said that the two Americans and three of the four Brazilians had not knowingly caused the crash, but that their negligence had contributed to Brazil's worst air disaster.</p>
        <p>If found guilty of the charge against them, which is akin to involuntary manslaughter, they could face between two and five years in jail, a court official, Fábio Paz, said.</p>
        <p>The fourth air traffic controller faces a stiffer charge because he had been aware that the two planes were flying at the same altitude in the same area but did not take the necessary steps to warn them of the impending collision, the police said.</p>
        <p>The United States National Transportation Safety Board last month attributed the crash partly to the cockpit systems' failure to alert the American crew that the jet's anticollision equipment had failed.</p>
        <p>The equipment also helps ground-based radar to recognize the airplane; those signals were received only intermittently by the Brazilian system.</p>
        <p>Honeywell, which built the system on the corporate jet, said that it did alert the pilots if it failed, and that it met all American requirements. Families of victims have filed suit in New York and Miami against the charter company, ExcelAire, and Honeywell. Lockheed-Martin and Raytheon, which provided the air traffic control system, and Embraer, which built the airplane, are also being sued.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 4, 2007, Monday  An article on Saturday about charges being brought in Brazil against two American pilots, whose corporate jet was involved in a mid-air collision last year over the Amazon with a Brazilian airliner that went down with 154 people aboard, misstated a Brazilian judge's position on the case. He said in a statement issued in Portuguese on Friday that the two pilots, Joseph Lepore and Jan Paul Paladino, should be charged with exposing an aircraft to danger; he did not say they were guilty of having done so.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 4, 2007, Monday</p>
        <p>An article on Saturday about charges being brought in Brazil against two American pilots, whose corporate jet was involved in a mid-air collision last year over the Amazon with a Brazilian airliner that went down with 154 people aboard, misstated a Brazilian judge's position on the case. He said in a statement issued in Portuguese on Friday that the two pilots, Joseph Lepore and Jan Paul Paladino, should be charged with exposing an aircraft to danger; he did not say they were guilty of having done so.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
