<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yanks Show Some Fire in Victory at Fenway</title>
    <meta content="02yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/sports/baseball/02yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851513"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <org class="online_producer">American League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E5DE1030F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1006" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yanks Show Some Fire in Victory at Fenway</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Yanks Show Some Fire in Victory at Fenway</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, June 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They are far apart in the standings. One team threatening to run away with the American League East, the other still well under .500. But passion is the lifeblood of the rivalry between the Yankees and the Boston Red Sox, and that blood was still boiling Friday.</p>
        <p>Five players were hit by pitches in the Yankees' 9-5 victory at Fenway Park, which ended with Mariano Rivera on the mound and Joe Torre and Scott Proctor in the clubhouse, both having been ejected in separate incidents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees kicked off the month of June with an outburst of offense to put them 12½ games behind Boston in the division race.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They are far apart in the standings. One team threatening to run away with the American League East, the other still well under .500. But passion is the lifeblood of the rivalry between the Yankees and the Boston Red Sox, and that blood was still boiling Friday.</p>
        <p>Five players were hit by pitches in the Yankees' 9-5 victory at Fenway Park, which ended with Mariano Rivera on the mound and Joe Torre and Scott Proctor in the clubhouse, both having been ejected in separate incidents.</p>
        <p>''We need to be a little more fiery,'' Torre said. ''I'm not saying that's going to be my new personality. But I think we showed fight tonight. We really need to assert ourselves.''</p>
        <p>Proctor asserted himself in the ninth inning, with one out and the bases empty, against Kevin Youkilis. The teams had traded hit batsmen early in the game, when Chien-Ming Wang knocked Mike Lowell from the game with a contusion of the left hand in the third inning and Kyle Snyder hit Alex Rodriguez in the fourth.</p>
        <p>''You don't assume intent,'' Snyder said. ''It's our responsibility on this team, as pitchers, to protect hitters.''</p>
        <p>In the ninth, Proctor was pitching after Javier López plunked Robinson Canó in the top of the inning. Proctor's 2-2 fastball knocked Youkilis to the ground and hit him on the left jersey sleeve.</p>
        <p>Proctor was immediately ejected, and although Youkilis tossed the bat to the ground and took a step toward the mound, he did not charge. Torre said he believed the plate umpire, Brian O'Nora, was reacting to Youkilis more than the pitch itself.</p>
        <p>''But with the two teams involved,'' Torre conceded, ''I'm not surprised.''</p>
        <p>Proctor, who had been suspended four games for throwing behind Seattle's Yuniesky Betancourt on May 6, may face another suspension. But he said he was not trying to hit Youkilis.</p>
        <p>''If I'm going to do it, I'm going to do it first pitch,'' Proctor said. ''I'm not going to do it on a 2-2 count. I'm not going to waste four pitches. That's stupid. That's bad baseball.''</p>
        <p>The Red Sox, who had fallen behind early thanks to Tim Wakefield's worst start in years, stirred after Youkilis was hit. Ron Villone replaced Proctor and allowed a single to David Ortiz, prompting Rivera to start warming up.</p>
        <p>Villone threw one ball to Manny Ramírez before Don Mattingly, the bench coach acting as manager, called for Rivera. Ramírez singled off the Green Monster to score a run, and a grounder by Wily Mo Peña brought in another. Another groundout ended the game, but the Red Sox had been riled, which Proctor insisted he did not want to do.</p>
        <p>''You're not trying to wake a sleeping dog,'' he said. ''You're just trying to get outs and get out of there with a win.''</p>
        <p>The victory nudged the Yankees' record to 23-29; they trail Boston by 12 1/2 games in the division.</p>
        <p>As usual, the fans made for a charged atmosphere, hooting at the embattled Alex Rodriguez when he camped under a pop-up -- as Howie Clark did in Toronto on Wednesday -- with the bases loaded in the Boston second. Rodriguez caught the ball, tossed it into the stands  and a fan flipped it back.</p>
        <p>Torre gave the park an added jolt when the umpire Jerry Crawford ejected him in the fifth inning. Torre argued twice with Crawford for calling Bobby Abreu out at third base on a stolen base attempt, and he was unusually animated, wagging his finger at Crawford, pointing repeatedly and screaming as the two went face to face.</p>
        <p>Torre said he left the bench a second time to argue, during a pitching change, because Crawford made a gesture with his hand, apparently intimating that the Yankees' bench needed to quiet down.</p>
        <p>''It got into one of those agitation things and got out of hand,'' Torre said. ''I'm sorry the whole thing happened.''</p>
        <p>In Wakefield, the Yankees were facing a pitcher they once feared so much they would import Joe Ausanio, a former Yankee who throws a knuckleball, to throw batting practice before his starts. But Wakefield's mastery of the Yankees has waned.</p>
        <p>In three starts against the Yankees this season, Wakefield is 0-3 with a 10.93 earned run average. In eight starts against other teams, he is 5-2 with a 2.50 E.R.A.</p>
        <p>Wakefield's command of his knuckleball disappeared after he retired the side in the first inning. He gave up eight earned runs for the first time in 72 starts, since Sept. 4, 2004, and matched a season high with six walks.</p>
        <p>The first was to Rodriguez, who was booed all night and jeered by fans holding Halloween masks of a woman with blond hair, a reference to his off-field troubles this week. The fan reaction hardly seemed to bother Rodriguez, who reached base three times.</p>
        <p>After Rodriguez's walk, Canó ripped a home run to right for the first two runs of the game. Canó is batting .385 (15 for 39) over his last 10 games.</p>
        <p>The slumping Bobby Abreu, back in the lineup after resting Wednesday, smacked a double off the Green Monster, and three walks followed. The last, by Johnny Damon, drove in Abreu to make the score 3-0.</p>
        <p>After the Red Sox left eight runners on base in the first three innings against Wang, the Yankees broke through with six runs in the fourth, three coming on a double by Jorge Posada.</p>
        <p>''It's definitely a great way to start June,'' Damon said. ''Here we go. This month is so important for us. We need to make up ground, and not just a game or two. We need to make up five or six games this month and try to get on a roll. I think we did all right.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The Yankees recalled reliever Chris Britton to stay with the team until Roger Clemens arrives Monday in Chicago. To make room for Britton, they sent the right-hander Matt DeSalvo to Class AAA Scranton/Wilkes-Barre, a move that keeps Tyler Clippard in the rotation.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
