<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Salary May Be Low, But How About Those Hours?</title>
    <meta content="02about" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/nyregion/02about.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ABOUT NEW YORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/About New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/About New York/About New York - Dwyer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fringe Benefits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fringe Benefits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1D71330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="732" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Salary May Be Low, But How About Those Hours?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Salary May Be Low, but How About Those Hours?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM DWYER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At a retirement party last fall, the master of ceremonies noted that the guest of honor, a police chief, had served the city for four decades.</p>
        <p>''Forty years,'' said Steve Davis, the master of ceremonies. ''Forty years is a long time. How long is 40 years?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Police officers in New York City work an average of less than 41 weeks per year, meaning that they have nearly three months of time off.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At a retirement party last fall, the master of ceremonies noted that the guest of honor, a police chief, had served the city for four decades.</p>
        <p>''Forty years,'' said Steve Davis, the master of ceremonies. ''Forty years is a long time. How long is 40 years?''</p>
        <p>Punch line alert:</p>
        <p>''Back when he joined the Police Department 40 years ago, the starting salary for cops was just $25,000.''</p>
        <p>Now for the annotation.</p>
        <p>Police recruits today -- not 40 years ago -- are paid at the rate of $25,100 for the six months they are in the academy, and move up to $32,700 for the six months after they graduate. That comes to about $29,000 for the first year. It compares miserably to the starting wages paid in Nassau County -- about $34,000 -- or in Suffolk County, at $57,000. The suburban departments also pay much higher wages than the city after five or six years.</p>
        <p>No one tries to defend this. After all, the city can't recruit enough people to replace those who leave. Other employers are willing to pay more for the skills and judgment that make a good police officer.</p>
        <p>Police officers have to do society's dirty work 365 days a year.</p>
        <p>But that needs some annotation, too.</p>
        <p>Police officers in New York City put in an average of 202 ''appearances'' a year, meaning they work less than 41 weeks per year, according to the Citizens Budget Commission, a business-backed research organization. That's nearly three months of time off. How did that happen?</p>
        <p>For many years, mayors made deals to pay city workers with time off instead of money. Police officers, for example, are credited with about 20 minutes a day for washing up, and those minutes go into a bank for time off, known as ''chart days.'' After five years, an officer who works a shift that is 8 hours and 35 minutes long is credited with 18 ''chart days'' of time off -- not counting a month or more of vacation.</p>
        <p>During the 1990s, as Rudolph W. Giuliani poured money into the Police Department, its budget grew at 18 to 20 times the rate of other city agencies. Crime went down. So did any notion of efficiency.</p>
        <p>The chart day arrangement was basically unchanged throughout Mr. Giuliani's two terms as mayor.</p>
        <p>When Michael R. Bloomberg succeeded him, he brought in a new commissioner, Raymond W. Kelly, and they drastically slowed the growth of the police budget. Crime has continued to drop, but the police payroll has decreased by about 10 percent, or 4,000 officers and civilians, according to the city's Independent Budget Office.</p>
        <p>DURING contract negotiations that have dragged out for years, Mr. Bloomberg said that salaries for all police officers -- rookies and veterans -- could be increased if the officers agreed to surrender some of the chart days, which require the city to hire more police officers. The Patrolmen's Benevolent Association refused, saying its members were already doing more work with fewer people, and noted that other police departments in the region paid more and required fewer shifts.</p>
        <p>The dispute went to an arbitrator, who decided to increase wages for veterans by 10.5 percent, and to pay for it by cutting the starting salary to $25,100 from $34,800. No additional shifts would be required, though in a separate deal, police lieutenants did surrender some chart days for more pay.</p>
        <p>New York City is not alone in granting plenty of time off. On Long Island, the police work year is even shorter than in New York City. In Suffolk County, young police officers are scheduled to work 232 days -- but that is reduced by 26 vacation and personal days, according to Jeffrey Tempera, the county's director of labor relations. There are also 13 paid holidays.</p>
        <p>And in Nassau County, many police officers work 12-hour shifts -- and with vacation time calculated, they report to work an average of 130 days a year, according to Maria Doulis of the Citizens Budget Commission.</p>
        <p>Steve Davis, who was the master of ceremonies at that police retirement party last fall, was himself a police captain. Like many senior officers, he did not earn overtime, but accumulated days off -- ''comp time'' -- when he had worked long hours.</p>
        <p>''I retired in 1991, so a lot of you may not know me,'' he told the crowd. ''I just got a letter that my comp time is running out next Tuesday.''</p>
        <p>ABOUT NEW YORK E-mail: dwyer@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: dwyer@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
