<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reconsidering, Torre Admonishes Rodriguez</title>
    <meta content="02pins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/sports/baseball/02pins.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851498"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Toronto Blue Jays</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Torre, Joe</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DF1030F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="985" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reconsidering, Torre Admonishes Rodriguez</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Reconsidering, Torre Admonishes Rodriguez</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, June 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Politically, it would have been easy for Yankees Manager Joe Torre to defend Alex Rodriguez for distracting a Toronto fielder by shouting as he ran past him on the bases Wednesday night. But with two days to think about it, Torre admonished Rodriguez on Friday.</p>
        <p>''It's probably something he shouldn't have done,'' Torre said before the Yankees played the Boston Red Sox. ''But it's over with. I don't sense he's going to do it again. Just the reaction probably told him that. He may have been excited about the fact that we were leading the ballgame. It was probably inappropriate to do it at the time he did it. But you can't change it, unfortunately.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yankees Manager Joe Torre said it was inappropriate for Alex Rodriguez to have distracted a Toronto fielder by shouting as he ran past him on the bases Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Politically, it would have been easy for Yankees Manager Joe Torre to defend Alex Rodriguez for distracting a Toronto fielder by shouting as he ran past him on the bases Wednesday night. But with two days to think about it, Torre admonished Rodriguez on Friday.</p>
        <p>''It's probably something he shouldn't have done,'' Torre said before the Yankees played the Boston Red Sox. ''But it's over with. I don't sense he's going to do it again. Just the reaction probably told him that. He may have been excited about the fact that we were leading the ballgame. It was probably inappropriate to do it at the time he did it. But you can't change it, unfortunately.''</p>
        <p>Blue Jays Manager John Gibbons told Rodriguez on the field that he had made a bush league play, something more appropriate for a Little Leaguer, and repeated those assertions to reporters after the game. Several other Blue Jays were furious at Rodriguez.</p>
        <p>''They were angry, no question,'' Torre said. ''I can't say I blame them.''</p>
        <p>Torre, who gave a lukewarm defense of Rodriguez immediately after Wednesday's game, said he spoke with Rodriguez that night about the play.</p>
        <p>''I sensed from our conversation it won't happen again,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Rodriguez did not make himself available to reporters after Torre's comments, but the Hall of Famer Reggie Jackson defended him. Jackson, a special adviser who has spent considerable time around the clubhouse as the Yankees have struggled, said that Rodriguez was within his rights to distract Blue Jays third baseman Howie Clark from catching a pop-up.</p>
        <p>''If it's not Alex Rodriguez, it's not a story,'' Jackson said.</p>
        <p>Jackson broke up a potential double play in the 1978 World Series when he froze on the basepaths and turned his hip into a throw. He said he did it so the ball would not hit him in a more sensitive spot, but he also said that, like Rodriguez, he was denounced instead of praised for a play that helped his team.</p>
        <p>''No over ever gave me credit for making a smart play, because I wasn't in favor,'' Jackson said. ''They said it was a cheap shot. Now, A-Rod's not in favor. People won't appreciate him until he's done. Love him or hate him, you can't ignore him. He comes to play every day.''</p>
        <p>'BLESSING IN DISGUISE' -- Jason Giambi's torn left plantar fascia will probably keep him sidelined six to eight weeks, based on the size of the tear and the typical recovery time. Giambi has a rather large tear -- 75 percent -- but that may actually allow him to return more quickly.</p>
        <p>''With a 75 percent tear, if you're going to immobilize him for three weeks, you're looking at six weeks and possibly up to eight weeks -- a month and a half to two months at most,'' said Dr. Dominic Catanese, the director of podiatric medicine and surgery at Montefiore Medical Center in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>''The tear may actually resolve the pain. Going in there to fix it is worse than just leaving it alone and letting it heal.''</p>
        <p>Giambi, who is not traveling with the team, has the foot immobilized in a boot he will wear for three weeks. He will then be re-evaluated, and Joe Torre said that he did not expect Giambi back for at least five weeks. The Yankees said they did not think Giambi would need surgery.</p>
        <p>''My guess is that he's going to be back,'' Catanese said. ''I wouldn't expect him to be out for the season. I'm sure he will rest and then obviously, they'll be aggressive with therapy. If they can get the inflammation to come down, he'll be back.''</p>
        <p>Torre called the injury a ''blessing in disguise,'' because Giambi had been struggling, Johnny Damon can now rest his legs as the designated hitter and Melky Cabrera can play every day.</p>
        <p>Using Cabrera in center field will improve the Yankees' defense because Damon's arm has become a liability and his ability to track down balls has been hindered by occasional calf cramps.</p>
        <p>''Seeing him throw the ball, that's one of the truly great things about watching baseball, to see a kid with a cannon like that,'' Damon said of Cabrera. ''Every time he thinks you might have a chance to throw someone out, he's going to show off his arm.''</p>
        <p>NIEVES WILL CATCH MUSSINA -- Wil Nieves will catch for the Yankees on Saturday, with Jorge Posada starting at designated hitter, because Joe Torre wanted Nieves to work with Mike Mussina. If Mussina pitches well, Torre said he would keep the arrangement.</p>
        <p>''The pitching is important for us,'' he said. ''Moose is important for us. We need to have Moose be a part of our starting rotation, and hopefully he can add something.''</p>
        <p>Mussina generally calls his own game, with minimal input from the catcher, and Torre said that Mussina did not make the request. But in three starts with Nieves as the starting catcher, Mussina is 2-0 with a 2.08 earned run average. In four starts with Posada, he is 0-3 with a 9.00 E.R.A.</p>
        <p>NO YANKEE COMEBACK FOR WILLIAMS -- Joe Torre called Bernie Williams on Thursday, but it was not to ask him to make a comeback. Torre wanted to invite Williams to lunch and remind him that he was being honored at Torre's Safe At Home dinner Nov. 9. The Yankees promoted Kevin Thompson from Class AAA Scranton/Wilkes-Barre to take Jason Giambi's roster spot. Williams is not a possibility.</p>
        <p>''He had an opportunity,'' Torre said. ''I'm sorry to say that he didn't take advantage of the opportunity he had in spring training when I tried to talk him into coming. But to think someone almost 40 years old without any spring training or practice can just come onto the scene here -- I guess Joe Hardy did it in 'Damn Yankees' -- you just can't do it.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
