<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Underscoring the Romance Of a Romantic Composer</title>
    <meta content="02phil" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/arts/music/02phil.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851397"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Philharmonic</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Maazel, Lorin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502EFD81330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="450" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Underscoring the Romance Of a Romantic Composer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Underscoring the Romance of a Romantic Composer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN KOZINN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York Philharmonic's Brahms the Romantic festival, scattered in chunks throughout the season, offers the perfect measure of how bereft of fresh ideas this orchestra's artistic management is. Here is the degree to which the works on the two concluding programs would have been neglected if Lorin Maazel hadn't offered this festival overview of the Brahms orchestral canon: the Third and Fourth Symphonies, heard on Thursday evening at Avery Fisher Hall, were last played by the Philharmonic in 2003 and 2005. The Haydn Variations and the German Requiem, to be performed tonight and on Tuesday, were on the orchestra's programs in 2006 and 2001.</p>
        <p>Is it possible that Mr. Maazel and his team can't find music that is heard less frequently yet deserves the attention a festival could bring it? And if it has to be Brahms -- it's great stuff, commonplace as it is -- isn't Brahms the Romantic a bit redundant? Does anyone not think of Brahms as a Romantic?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York Philharmonic’s Brahms the Romantic festival offers the perfect measure of how bereft of fresh ideas this orchestra’s artistic management is.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York Philharmonic's Brahms the Romantic festival, scattered in chunks throughout the season, offers the perfect measure of how bereft of fresh ideas this orchestra's artistic management is. Here is the degree to which the works on the two concluding programs would have been neglected if Lorin Maazel hadn't offered this festival overview of the Brahms orchestral canon: the Third and Fourth Symphonies, heard on Thursday evening at Avery Fisher Hall, were last played by the Philharmonic in 2003 and 2005. The Haydn Variations and the German Requiem, to be performed tonight and on Tuesday, were on the orchestra's programs in 2006 and 2001.</p>
        <p>Is it possible that Mr. Maazel and his team can't find music that is heard less frequently yet deserves the attention a festival could bring it? And if it has to be Brahms -- it's great stuff, commonplace as it is -- isn't Brahms the Romantic a bit redundant? Does anyone not think of Brahms as a Romantic?</p>
        <p>Brahms the Classicist would have been more thought-provoking, and a case can be made that a Classical sensibility can be found in Brahms, although Mr. Maazel, whose performances of Classical works are Romantic as well, is probably not the one to make that argument.</p>
        <p>What Mr. Maazel seems to mean by Brahms the Romantic is that Brahms is even more Romantic than anyone thought, assuming your definition of Romantic is bloated, full of tempo-stretching phrase manipulation, magnified dynamics and vulgar overstatement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maazel's Brahms, in other words, is very much like his Tchaikovsky, replete with chiseled articulation and dramatic chordal blasts, but coldly unemotional. A listener wanted to believe that all that fussiness and noise meant something -- that some form of spirit or feeling animated these performances. But the harder you searched, the emptier these interpretations seemed.</p>
        <p>The Philharmonic players were complicit to the extent that they gave Mr. Maazel what he asked for. But on purely technical grounds, their contribution was generally admirable, tarnished only by a few braying horn notes in the Third Symphony and fleeting ensemble imprecision in the first movement of the Fourth.</p>
        <p>Still, if Mr. Maazel took a dawdling tempo in the Third Symphony's Poco Allegretto, the string and brass playing made it seem worth lingering over. And the woodwinds offered a lovely rendering of that work's concluding bars.</p>
        <p>In its best moments the Philharmonic performed like a precision music-making machine. But for anyone who thinks of Brahms as passionate, not just hulking, those were the worst moments as well.</p>
        <p>Lorin Maazel conducts the New York Philharmonic, with Celena Shafer, soprano; Matthias Goerne, baritone; and the New York Choral Artists, tonight and Tuesday at Avery Fisher Hall; (212) 721-6500.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
