<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush's Longest-Serving Aide Announces His Departure</title>
    <meta content="02bartlett" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/washington/02bartlett.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bartlett, Dan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (DC)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bartlett, Dan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E4D61330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush's Longest-Serving Aide Announces His Departure</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush’s Longest-Serving Aide Plans to Depart</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dan Bartlett, counselor to Pres Bush, will leave administration in summer; he is one of Bush's longest-serving aides and closest confidents; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dan Bartlett, one of President Bush's longest-serving aides and closest confidants, said Friday that he would leave the administration in the summer. Mr. Bartlett's is the latest and most significant departure in what has been a shrinking of Mr. Bush's inner circle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bartlett, who turned 36 on Friday, has spent more than a third of his life working for Mr. Bush, starting as a junior policy aide when Mr. Bush ran for governor of Texas and becoming a crucial member of his presidential inner circle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The decision by Dan Bartlett, one of President Bush’s longest-serving aides, to leave is the most significant departure in a shrinking of Mr. Bush’s inner circle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dan Bartlett, one of President Bush's longest-serving aides and closest confidants, said Friday that he would leave the administration in the summer. Mr. Bartlett's is the latest and most significant departure in what has been a shrinking of Mr. Bush's inner circle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bartlett, who turned 36 on Friday, has spent more than a third of his life working for Mr. Bush, starting as a junior policy aide when Mr. Bush ran for governor of Texas and becoming a crucial member of his presidential inner circle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bartlett, counselor to the president, said he was leaving to spend more time with his family and pursue new career options.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Bush's inner circle shrank through his second term, Mr. Bartlett's stature -- initially questioned by some outside advisers who viewed him as too inexperienced to work at a high level -- increased. Colleagues said he frequently was an effective balance to more combative and aggressive instincts of other advisers like Karl Rove.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bartlett was known by colleagues inside and outside the White House to be worn out from years of service that have seen a rare presidential recount, two wars, the largest foreign attack on domestic soil since Pearl Harbor and regularly intense partisan battles. Through all of that, Mr. Bartlett had come to appear far older than his years.</p>
        <p>The birth of Mr. Bartlett's third child, a boy, four months ago -- he has 3-year-old twin sons -- put him over the limit of what he could still do, he told reporters on Friday.</p>
        <p>The departure will be a year after the president's chief of staff, Joshua B. Bolten, asked all of Mr. Bush's top aides to commit to serving out the rest of his term or submit their resignations then.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bartlett's is the latest departure from the White House by longtime aides, many dating from Mr. Bush's Texas days. Harriet E. Miers, general counsel, left a few months ago. Scott McClellan, press secretary, left last spring, not long after Mr. Bush's first chief of staff, Andrew H. Card Jr., announced his resignation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bartlett was among a special class of advisers, and he was occasionally described as having a father-son relationship with Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Nicolle Wallace, former White House communications director, disputed that description, saying the two bonded in other ways, including as the fathers of twins.</p>
        <p>''The nature of the advice he gave the president,'' Ms. Wallace said, ''was that it stayed between himself and the president. And the very source of his power and influence was the fact that he had a kind of a constituency of really just the president.''</p>
        <p>In a White House not known as exceptionally friendly or very accessible to the news media, presumably based on the president's preference, Ms. Wallace said, ''what has been possible has been Dan's doing.''</p>
        <p>At the White House, Mr. Bartlett has not received the same public notice as Mr. Rove. But he has been on hand for almost every major decision Mr. Bush has made, including the planning for the Afghan and Iraqi campaigns and the recent decision to increase troops in Iraq.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bartlett was also among a handful of deputies who helped the president seek a successor for Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld when most of the staff did not know that he was being forced out.</p>
        <p>Speaking with reporters on Friday, Mr. Bartlett said he had been part of the decision to embed reporters with military units in Iraq, a development that led to live and up-close coverage of the initial invasion. Critics said embedding co-opted the news coverage.</p>
        <p>Asked Friday whether he had regrets about the administration's communications about the war, Mr. Bartlett said: ''There will be plenty of time to pick over some of the decisions I helped make and determine whether they were done right or wrong. I'm sure there are plenty that are right, and plenty that are wrong.''</p>
        <p>He demurred when asked about the counterbalancing role he was said to have among Mr. Bush's advisers.</p>
        <p>''It's not a matter of counterbalancing as it is complements,'' he said. ''We complement each other well. We have a diverse set of advisers who bring different perspectives to the table. And obviously, when we announce a replacement, that person will be able to provide that type of complement, as well.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bartlett said Mr. Bush had indicated that he wanted him to stay but understood that Mr. Bartlett could not continue beyond six years amid the exhausting and demanding pace of the White House.</p>
        <p>Speaking of the day a couple of weeks ago when he told the president that he was on his way out, Mr. Bartlett said, ''He knew I wouldn't have walked in that day and had that conversation with him if the gig wasn't really up.''</p>
        <p>Dana Perino, a White House deputy press secretary, said that a search was under way but that she did not expect a successor to be named until after Mr. Bush had returned from his trip to Europe for the Group of Eight summit meeting.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
