<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Field Is Paved, the Gloves Are Borrowed, the Spirit Is Real</title>
    <meta content="02summer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/nyregion/02summer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Summer Rituals: Asphalt Dreams" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851508"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Summer Rituals | Asphalt Dreams"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Trymaine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Harlem (NYC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDF1030F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1354" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Field Is Paved, the Gloves Are Borrowed, the Spirit Is Real</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Field Is Paved, Gloves Are Borrowed, Spirit Is Real</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRYMAINE LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Trymaine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article in Summer Rituals series focuses on Intermediate School 286 baseball team, which practices on asphalt patch at Manhattanville housing project in West Harlem; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a tattered patch of asphalt in the heart of a West Harlem housing project. It is caged in and a world apart, in the shadows of the burnt-orange high-rises. The bases are whatever the players can find: worn-out gloves, T-shirts, their imaginations. The outfield is a basketball court; baseballs take funny bounces on this hard surface.</p>
        <p>But each day after school, a social studies teacher leads a crew of middle school boys to this hardened field of play with baseballs, bats and borrowed gloves. They are a brand new team in a new middle school baseball league that is as much a social experiment as it is boys at play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A patch of West Harlem asphalt is home to a baseball team that is as much a social experiment as it is boys at play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a tattered patch of asphalt in the heart of a West Harlem housing project. It is caged in and a world apart, in the shadows of the burnt-orange high-rises. The bases are whatever the players can find: worn-out gloves, T-shirts, their imaginations. The outfield is a basketball court; baseballs take funny bounces on this hard surface.</p>
        <p>But each day after school, a social studies teacher leads a crew of middle school boys to this hardened field of play with baseballs, bats and borrowed gloves. They are a brand new team in a new middle school baseball league that is as much a social experiment as it is boys at play.</p>
        <p>For many of the players on this team from Intermediate School 286, the Renaissance Military and Leadership Academy, baseball is a respite from the pressures, social and emotional, that they battle daily. The school does not have a band or a debate team or much beyond its studies. But here, they can be all-stars, they can be somebodies.</p>
        <p>And this fenced-in patch of asphalt in the Manhattanville housing projects, caged in and a world apart, becomes a baseball diamond. It is transformed just as countless other cracked lots and hot forlorn expanses of concrete around New York City are transformed each summer -- into fields for competition, for sports, for sweating and playing and sometimes even winning on the longest days of the year.</p>
        <p>Off the field, some of the players from I.S. 286 struggle with behavioral issues, school attendance and unstable home lives. They do what they can to avoid the gangs, and shrug off being robbed and jumped. They want to be ballplayers.</p>
        <p>''I always wanted to play, but my father said I wasn't any good,'' said Jefry Puntiel, 14, who is shorter than most of the other players, more bookish than brawny. ''So this is my first year. And it's been a lot of fun.''</p>
        <p>The team does not cut players based on talent, only on the basis of behavior and grades. The team does not have heavy financing, and for some, cash at home is scarce, so not every player can afford the $30 uniform. Instead, slacks and T-shirts or sweat pants replace the white-bodied, blue-sleeved shirts and gray baseball pants worn by the rest of the team.</p>
        <p>They also have other obstacles to overcome.</p>
        <p>For example, the I.S. 286 social studies teacher and team's coach, Andrew Jarboe, 24, said his entire outfield was arrested not long ago, and released shortly afterward, after getting caught up in an after-school brawl just off school grounds.</p>
        <p>Some players have missed nearly as many days of school as they were present, like the team's best pitcher, who was absent for weeks at a time. And more recently, an undercover police officer posing as a cabdriver called for backup when two teammates kicked dirt and threw rocks aimlessly, with no targets in range, after a heartbreaking loss on an opponent's game-ending grand slam.</p>
        <p>''There is no real official public middle school league in the city,'' Mr. Jarboe said. ''They just don't have much of anything else. So this means a lot to them.''</p>
        <p>He continued: ''As a teacher, discipline is maybe two-thirds of the job. It's different from school to school, but 286, it's a tough school. It's kind of, it's not officially a dumping ground, but it's a dumping ground. These are the kids nobody else wants. And yes, that runs over onto the baseball field, too. But the nice thing about that is that they really want to play, so I can hold that over their heads, so the behavior is less of a problem on the field than it is in the school.''</p>
        <p>The team was formed last year as something to do after school, with Mr. Jarboe and a few students tossing the ball around after class. Then, this year, a friend who teaches at a nearby school mentioned that a new league had been formed by a group of teachers from other schools.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jarboe signed his team up and began scheduled practices in the asphalt yard. Players included Little League veterans and children who had never picked up a glove. This year the team has ventured away from its hardtop practice haven, to fields of dirt and grass. The first game, in early May, took the players to Columbus Park in Chinatown.</p>
        <p>Melvin Ruiz, 14, a catcher and the team captain, paced along the third-base line, more focused than usual -- no smile, no horsing around, no trash talk with his teammates. His signature smirk had faded. He mustered a game face.</p>
        <p>''I'm ready,'' Melvin said, pounding on the marker-applied ''C,'' for captain, scrawled on the white T-shirt, before he put his catcher's gear on over it. ''I feel like Derek Jeter.''</p>
        <p>Upon hearing that, Mr. Jarboe replied, ''Just pass your exams.''</p>
        <p>Melvin smiled, tightened the last strap on his shin guards, then headed to home plate.</p>
        <p>The pitcher, Edward Perez, 15, took the mound. Mr. Jarboe, who is also an umpire when his team is in the field, put a book bag over his chest and crouched a bit, tugging at his umpire's mask.</p>
        <p>I.S. 286 eventually defeated East Side Community Middle School, 5-4. In the six-inning game, Edward struck out 15 batters.</p>
        <p>A few weeks later, he stopped coming to school.</p>
        <p>''I know where he hangs out,'' Melvin said, lowering his head, jamming a baseball in his glove. ''But I didn't go looking for him.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jarboe said he cut Edward some slack for the absenteeism because ''if I have another chance to try to rope them in, or bring them under my wing, I'll take it.''</p>
        <p>Last week, the team suffered a tough loss against Junior High School 104. The difference in the two sets of players, and how they were dressed, was stark -- and noted.</p>
        <p>''The other team doesn't even have uniforms,'' said Niles Lang, an assistant coach for J.H.S. 104, pointing to I.S. 286. ''They are grossly underfunded. They have to borrow catcher's equipment.''</p>
        <p>After the loss to J.H.S. 104, tensions flared as the two teams lined up for a game-ending handshake. There was a slight pause on the line, as Melvin and a player for the J.H.S. 104 team locked eyes and exchanged looks.</p>
        <p>Melvin said the other boy had said ''that's why y'all mothers smoke crack'' -- although if any words were exchanged they could not be heard from more than a few feet away. Still, Melvin's teammates had to pull him away. ''I just lose my temper sometimes,'' Melvin said. ''Nothing really changes with that. When people mess with me I get mad.''</p>
        <p>Byron Tummings, the dean of discipline at I.S. 286, said he has been impressed with the turnaround in some students on the team.</p>
        <p>''Some of the kids that I wouldn't think would be at all interested in participating are out there gung-ho,'' Mr. Tummings said from his office, where he was dealing with a dripping-wet girl who had been pelted by a water balloon and a student involved in a fistfight that day.</p>
        <p>With about six games under their belts, some players are now talking like seasoned veterans.</p>
        <p>''I just try to do what I can,'' said Adam Diane, 13, a pitcher and an outfielder. ''And it doesn't matter if we don't have this or that, no jerseys or whatever, baseball ain't no fashion show. If we play good, it's not going to be because of the jersey. It's about the experience.''</p>
        <p>Back at the asphalt practice field in West Harlem last week, Mr. Jarboe led the team in pregame stretching. A few girls lined up outside the field's mesh metal fencing, cooing at some of the players in uniform.</p>
        <p>Edward Perez had returned. Just before warming up with Melvin Ruiz, he explained his absence simply, saying, ''I was at home.''</p>
        <p>Edward turned and gunned the ball to Melvin. ''Time to play,'' the pitcher said.</p>
        <p>Summer Rituals</p>
        <p>This is one in a weekly series, running on Saturdays through Labor Day weekend, on what makes summer summer for people in and around New York.</p>
        <p>Summer Rituals | Asphalt Dreams</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
