<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Troupe Known for Daredevil Choreography Copes With a Casualty</title>
    <meta content="02stre" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/arts/dance/02stre.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Streb, Elizabeth</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEED81330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1103" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Troupe Known for Daredevil Choreography Copes With a Casualty</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Troupe Known for Daredevil Choreography Copes With a Casualty</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL J. WAKIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Performers in the dance company Streb Extreme Action fling themselves against plexiglass or sail off a trampoline and land facedown on a mat. They yank themselves around on ropes and dodge swinging cinder blocks. Some shows are subtitled ''Slam,'' and a company motto is ''Dance, Danger, Action!''</p>
        <p>Such high-octane movement risks serious injury, and two weeks ago it happened. The Streb dancer deeAnn Nelson, 28, landed hard on her back during a performance of a work called ''Surface'' and crushed a vertebra. She underwent surgery and now has a metal rod permanently embedded in her back, ending her career with the company but not, she hopes, in dance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The dancer deeAnn Nelson landed hard on her back during a performance, ending her career with the company Streb Extreme Action but not, she hopes, in dance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Performers in the dance company Streb Extreme Action fling themselves against plexiglass or sail off a trampoline and land facedown on a mat. They yank themselves around on ropes and dodge swinging cinder blocks. Some shows are subtitled ''Slam,'' and a company motto is ''Dance, Danger, Action!''</p>
        <p>Such high-octane movement risks serious injury, and two weeks ago it happened. The Streb dancer deeAnn Nelson, 28, landed hard on her back during a performance of a work called ''Surface'' and crushed a vertebra. She underwent surgery and now has a metal rod permanently embedded in her back, ending her career with the company but not, she hopes, in dance.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nelson, as it happened, did not hurt herself with a particularly daring move. She was running up a 4-by-8-foot plywood board held at an angle by a fellow dancer and was to jump off about six feet above the ground. But she slipped, caught her ankle on the top and pitched forward in a half-tuck. The dancer left the stage under her own steam as the performance, held at the company's studio in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, was halted, and she was taken by ambulance to Bellevue Hospital.</p>
        <p>''It was a freak accident,'' said the company's founder, Elizabeth Streb. ''It was one of our more benign pieces, if there is such a thing. She just was in a sense too close to the ground to save the manner she was falling.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Streb said she would not make any immediate changes to the rehearsal routine or performances, which continue this weekend, but would think about developing techniques for dancers who have to react in the split second when something goes wrong.</p>
        <p>''We're basically in the business of not getting hurt,'' Ms. Streb said. ''I'm extremely sad about it. The last thing I, as director of this company, want is for one of my dancers to get hurt.''</p>
        <p>The injury to Ms. Nelson, which Ms. Streb said was the most serious among her dancers since she founded the company in the late 1970s, cast a spotlight on its daredevil form of movement, the lengths her dancers go to train themselves to absorb hard landings, and the toll on them.</p>
        <p>''I was riddled with injuries for my entire tenure with Streb, but nothing so serious that I couldn't dance,'' said Nikita Maxwell, who danced with the company for four and a half years and said she was hurt more than most.</p>
        <p>''There was a certain point where I got tired of being injured, and it became a deterrent to trying the daredevil moves,'' said Ms. Maxwell, who emphasized that she was a big supporter of Ms. Streb and plans to enroll her young son in the company's school. ''It's amazing there have been no injuries like that up to this point.''</p>
        <p>Current and past dancers in the company said they were fully aware of the risks and were drawn to the thrill of the Streb style. ''You develop an appetite for impact,'' Ms. Maxwell said. ''It feels really good after a while.''</p>
        <p>They also said Ms. Streb was deeply focused on safety, built slowly toward the execution of risky moves and always allowed dancers to opt out with no consequences.</p>
        <p>Christine Chen, a member since January 2004, said the first thing Streb dancers learned was how to land, partly by developing and engaging their musculature. ''The technique protects you from injury,'' she said. And part of the violence is illusion. ''We are taking impacts,'' she said, ''but we are also a theater company, so we are 'theatricalizing' things too,'' through grimaces and surfaces equipped with microphones to amplify the thuds.</p>
        <p>Ms. Streb has codified her choreography into what she calls ''pop action.'' The Streb Web site, www.strebusa.org, calls it a combination of ''dance, athletics, extreme sports and Hollywood stunt work into a bristling muscle and motion vocabulary that combines daring and strict precision.'' The site emphasizes the risky and boundary-pushing nature of her work, and the ''energy of near-misses and imminent crashes.''</p>
        <p>The company, which is based in Williamsburg and also tours internationally, has been widely praised by critics, and Ms. Streb won a MacArthur ''genius'' grant in 1997. The members come from different backgrounds. Many are trained dancers, but there have also been gymnasts, acrobats and divers.</p>
        <p>''Oftentimes, dance is emotive and gestural, and therefore definitely safer than what Elizabeth is creating,'' said Brian Brooks, a former Streb member who has formed his own company. ''Her stuff is always in the extreme physical place. You are always in a place of instability. That's what the work is about. There is definitely a heightened risk.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Streb and some of the dancers interviewed asserted that her company was no more subject to injury than more traditional modern troupes and ballet companies. Rather than muscle and ligament pulls and knee injuries, they said, Streb dancers tend to suffer twisted ankles, bruises, broken fingers and toes, wrist injuries and even broken noses.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, since the accident on May 20, the company -- and many in the dance world -- have rallied around Ms. Nelson.</p>
        <p>Terry Dean Bartlett, the associate artistic director, immediately sent out an e-mail appeal for contributors to a fund-raising performance -- itself the source of some conflict. ''We're a little upset about that,'' said Ms. Streb, adding that Ms. Nelson should have been consulted first. ''It wasn't really something the company had organized.''</p>
        <p>But she said the members had come together to support their fellow dancer. ''When a tribe of people have a wounded member, of course they are all gathering to the scene and taking care of our wounded member,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nelson, who grew up in Idaho Falls and attended the University of Nevada at Las Vegas and the Tisch School of the Arts at New York University, said she was moved by the outpouring of support, which included checks from strangers. She welcomed the benefit as a message that performers can help others. ''That's something I've always hoped art could do in general,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nelson said she did not expect to be able to build her body back up to the level of doing Streb work, but did expect to return to dancing some day. She said she looked upon the accident as an opportunity to explore other things, like rock climbing, and had no regrets about being part of the company.</p>
        <p>''I knew I was always testing myself when I was doing Streb,'' she said. ''That's the beauty of the work. I was dancing since I was 8 years old, and here I was 20 years later, still challenged.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
