<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Runner Who Is Taking Each Hurdle as It Comes</title>
    <meta content="02track" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/sports/othersports/02track.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851461"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TRACK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Beijing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Beijing (China)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E1D61330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="948" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Runner Who Is Taking Each Hurdle as It Comes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Runner Taking Each Hurdle as It Comes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Liu Xiang approaches life the same way he does the hurdles. He says he takes each day as it comes, instead of letting his focus drift to what lies ahead.</p>
        <p>His philosophy has put him at odds with millions of his Chinese compatriots, who have been projecting Liu's star turn at next year's Beijing Olympics since his gold-medal performance in the 110-meter hurdles at the 2004 Games in Athens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hurdler Liu Xiang says he takes each day as it comes, a philosophy that has put him at odds with millions of his Chinese compatriots, who have been projecting Liu’s star turn at next year’s Beijing Olympics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Liu Xiang approaches life the same way he does the hurdles. He says he takes each day as it comes, instead of letting his focus drift to what lies ahead.</p>
        <p>His philosophy has put him at odds with millions of his Chinese compatriots, who have been projecting Liu's star turn at next year's Beijing Olympics since his gold-medal performance in the 110-meter hurdles at the 2004 Games in Athens.</p>
        <p>''Everybody is hoping for me to win the gold medal in Beijing, and I completely understand that,'' Liu said through an interpreter Thursday during an interview at a hotel in Midtown Manhattan. ''But for myself, I don't want to think about that. I want to focus on what's happening now and make my life right now worthwhile.''</p>
        <p>Liu, who is scheduled to race today in the Reebok Grand Prix at Randalls Island, looked as relaxed as the fit of the blue jeans he was wearing. They were a gift from his sponsor, Nike, with a Michael Jordan label on the left pant leg.</p>
        <p>But that is not why Liu likes them so much.</p>
        <p>''I like them because I didn't have to pay for them,'' he said, laughing.</p>
        <p>Liu, who will be 24 next month, has the kind of outsize personality that tears down language barriers. His face is a flip book of emotions, his expression changing from one sentence to the next. He can communicate a wide range of feelings -- surprise, embarrassment, joy -- without saying a word.</p>
        <p>Ask him any question, no matter how prosaic, and his answer is liable to go on longer than one of his races. Asked how many times he had watched the videotape of his Olympic triumph, Liu held up five fingers. He had not watched it recently because, he said as his face broke into a wide smile as he said this, it made him too excited.</p>
        <p>Liu tied the world record of 12.91 seconds in the Olympic final, and he eclipsed it last July, when he was timed in 12.88. He was the first Chinese man to win an Olympic gold medal in track, and his victory in Athens was hailed in his homeland as a cultural leap forward because it ran counter to the stereotypes of what makes a great sprinter.</p>
        <p>''My victory has proved that athletes with yellow skin can run as fast as those with black and white skin,'' Liu said at the time.</p>
        <p>Overnight, he became China's most cuddly commodity this side of pandas. He signed multiple endorsement deals that paid him more than $7 million last year, according to Forbes magazine.</p>
        <p>He was approached about recording an album, and he collaborated on a music video that featured other Chinese athletes and a few professional singers. Unlike when he is on the track, Liu said he did not become nervous while laying down a track.</p>
        <p>''It's in the studio, so you can do it over and over if it's not perfect,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A bronze statue of Liu was erected in his hometown, Shanghai. ''I don't like a fake statue of myself,'' he said. Laughing, he added, ''I think it's scary.''</p>
        <p>To avoid being mobbed by fans, Liu has had to use decoy cars to go to his training sessions. Gone are the days when he could celebrate after a meet by singing at a karaoke bar. ''Aside from being home and going to the training center, I basically don't go anywhere else,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Drug testers have had no trouble finding Liu; he said he had submitted to five tests by the World Anti-Doping Agency and the Chinese Athletic Association this year. Race winners are automatically tested, which is why Liu says: ''I feel honored to be checked so many times, because they would only do that to famous athletes. If I was just somebody ordinary, they wouldn't make so many drug exams.''</p>
        <p>Liu insists that success has not changed him. ''It's just everything around me has changed,'' he said. Sounding more like Confucius than Carl Lewis, he added, ''The most important thing is to face life yourself, and then to accept what life throws at you.''</p>
        <p>His coach, Sun Haiping, has expressed concern that Liu's fame will become the one hurdle that causes him to stumble. Sun has appealed to the Chinese public and to the news media to stop making Liu into a legend, to no outward effect.</p>
        <p>Edwin Moses, a two-time Olympic gold medalist in the 400 hurdles, has seen the ballyhoo for Liu up close during visits to China, most recently last month, in his capacity as chairman of the Laureus World Sports Academy.</p>
        <p>''I think Liu represents a whole different generation in China,'' Moses said in a telephone interview from Atlanta.</p>
        <p>Moses noted that Liu's hurdling technique was outstanding, but suggested that perhaps his business instincts were even sharper. ''I think he's an entrepreneur at heart,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Where is the piece of gold at the heart of Liu's success? He did not answer immediately. Liu was silent for one second, two seconds, three. He shook his head and laughed. How could he forget where he put his Olympic gold medal?</p>
        <p>Then he remembered. It is locked in a safe at his parents' house.</p>
        <p>New York is the ideal hiding place for Liu, as he was reminded the other day. He and Feng Shuyong, a Chinese sports administrator and former national track team coach, slipped into a Chinese restaurant near their hotel for lunch. The man who took their order looked at Liu and said: ''I know you. You are chess player.''</p>
        <p>No, Liu told him, he is just an ordinary person. Millions in China may beg to differ.</p>
        <p>TRACK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
