<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>General Says Bosses Knew Of '05 Killings In Iraqi Town</title>
    <meta content="02haditha" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/world/02haditha.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851447"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teleconferencing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Haditha (Iraq)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Camp Pendleton (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Von Zielbauer, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Huck, Richard A (Maj Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Casey, George W Jr (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chessani, Jeffrey R (Lt Col)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Military Personnel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Personnel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Haditha (Iraq)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E5D61330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="569" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>General Says Bosses Knew Of '05 Killings In Iraqi Town</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">General Says Bosses Knew of ’05 Killings in Iraqi Town</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL VON ZIELBAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Von Zielbauer, Paul</byline>
      <dateline>CAMP PENDLETON, Calif., June 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maj Gen Richard A Huck, who was in charge of Marine division in Iraq when infantrymen killed 24 civilians in Haditha in Nov 2005, says that all his superiors, including Gen George W Casey Jr, top commander in Iraq, knew of event in hours; testifies, via video link from Pentagon on third day of hearing at Camp Pendleton, Calif, for Lt Col Jeffrey R Chessani, one of four Marine officers charged with dereliction of duty in case (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The general who was in charge of the Marine division in Iraq when infantrymen in the division killed 24 civilians in Haditha in late 2005, said Friday that all his superiors, including Gen. George W. Casey Jr., the top commander in Iraq, knew of the event within hours.</p>
        <p>The commander of the Second Marine Division, Maj. Gen. Richard A. Huck, also said in sworn testimony on Friday that he knew the civilians had been killed in their homes, but that he did not investigate because subordinates in the field, upon whom he relied to suggest such an inquiry, did not do so.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>General Huck testified that all his superiors, including the top commander in Iraq, knew of the killings in Haditha within hours.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The general who was in charge of the Marine division in Iraq when infantrymen in the division killed 24 civilians in Haditha in late 2005, said Friday that all his superiors, including Gen. George W. Casey Jr., the top commander in Iraq, knew of the event within hours.</p>
        <p>The commander of the Second Marine Division, Maj. Gen. Richard A. Huck, also said in sworn testimony on Friday that he knew the civilians had been killed in their homes, but that he did not investigate because subordinates in the field, upon whom he relied to suggest such an inquiry, did not do so.</p>
        <p>Testifying for the second time in three weeks in a military hearing here about the killings in Haditha, which included several women and children, General Huck repeated assertions from his previous testimony: that his superiors knew about the killings at the same time he learned of them.</p>
        <p>But on Friday, under questioning from lawyers for a former battalion commander charged with failing to properly investigate and report the deaths, General Huck took pains to show that the generals above him were also well aware of the episode but, like him, did nothing to immediately look into it.</p>
        <p>''Everyone above Two M.E.F. (Forward)'' knew of it, he said, referring to the Marine Expeditionary Force he commanded in Iraq. General Huck said he sent reports of the killings to Maj. Gen. Steve Johnson, the top Marine commander in Iraq, who sent it up the chain of command.</p>
        <p>''Major General Johnson forwarded this up to Corps,'' General Huck said, referring to Lt. Gen. John R. Vines, the Corps commander who then led ground operations in Iraq, ''and Corps forwarded it to Force.'' Force refers to Multinational Force-Iraq.</p>
        <p>General Huck, speaking via a video link from the Pentagon, where he is now an assistant deputy commandant for plans, policies and operations, testified on the third day of a hearing for Lt. Col. Jeffrey R. Chessani, one of four Marine officers charged with dereliction of duty in the Haditha case. Three enlisted men have been charged with murder.</p>
        <p>General Huck said his view that the civilian deaths required no follow-up was based on a Marine dictum, ''trust tactics,'' which requires commanders to rely on subordinates to report events accurately and completely so that they may make sound decisions. But early reports about the killings from Colonel Chessani's battalion staff, based on radio reports from platoon-level marines, were inaccurate.</p>
        <p>They erroneously stated, for instance, that only 15 noncombatants died, most from a roadside bomb followed by insurgent gunfire; the reports characterized the marines' fire only as ''further adding to'' the number of civilian deaths, a military prosecutor said Friday.</p>
        <p>Under cross-examination by a government lawyer, General Huck said that Colonel Chessani had not told him about several facts that might have induced the general to look into the Haditha killings.</p>
        <p>For example, General Huck said he was not told that marines had killed five unarmed men they had ordered out of a car minutes after the roadside bomb blast killed one marine and wounded two others. ''It sounds like a law-of-armed-conflict violation,'' he said. ''That should have been reported.''</p>
        <p>He said he also had no idea that, five days after the Haditha episode, which took place on Nov. 19, 2005, town council members gave Colonel Chessani a letter in English demanding that the killings of ''24 civilians'' be investigated.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
