<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Breathing In Coney Island, At Just $178 A Bottle</title>
    <meta content="02coney" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/nyregion/02coney.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851423"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Perfumes and Fragrances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Perfumes and Fragrances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0D71330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="648" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Breathing In Coney Island, At Just $178 A Bottle</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Breathing in Coney Island, at Just $178 a Bottle</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some have left their heart there. Others love it in the springtime. Not a few -- maybe most -- hold its eating contests, roller coaster and skeeball in high regard.</p>
        <p>But what Coney Island has not been celebrated for, perhaps wrongly, is its smell -- what an out-of-towner might call its parfum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A perfume attempts to capture Coney Island’s essence, and decides it smells like a saltless margarita with a touch of caramel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some have left their heart there. Others love it in the springtime. Not a few -- maybe most -- hold its eating contests, roller coaster and skeeball in high regard.</p>
        <p>But what Coney Island has not been celebrated for, perhaps wrongly, is its smell -- what an out-of-towner might call its parfum.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, a Manhattan perfume house introduced ''Coney Island,'' the fragrance, priced at $178 for 3.4 ounces (or $1,675 a gallon for those who buy in bulk).</p>
        <p>Laurice Rahme, founder and president of the company, Bond No. 9, which specializes in mostly Manhattan-themed fragrances, said the marketplace prompted the creation of the new scent.</p>
        <p>''People are coming in here,'' said Ms. Rahme, a former Lancôme executive, gesturing around her flagship boutique on Bond Street, in NoHo. ''They are saying, 'When are you going to do Brooklyn, Brooklyn, Brooklyn?' ''</p>
        <p>She pondered the neighborhoods of Brooklyn Heights and Williamsburg, and its hotspots like the River Cafe and the Brooklyn Academy of Music, but settled on Coney Island as her first olfactory excursion into the borough.</p>
        <p>And why not? If Michael Jordan, Elizabeth Taylor and Britney Spears can have premium perfumes, selling for as much as $200 a bottle, why not Coney Island, the neighborhood made famous by Woody Guthrie, Isaac Bashevis Singer and P. T. Barnum?</p>
        <p>Still, it is understood that those celebrity fragrances do not directly suggest the basketball court, movie lot, or recording studio.</p>
        <p>Surely something called Coney Island must capture a particle of ballyhoo, sea air, Boardwalk and Coppertone. Might there be a piquant X-factor, like fresh brioche in Paris or pine needles in the Rocky Mountains, that will forever summon up Mermaid Avenue?</p>
        <p>Maybe, maybe not.</p>
        <p>For reasons that sound clearer when delivered in Ms. Rahme's French accent, Coney Island, the fragrance, is based, at first sniff, on margaritas.</p>
        <p>''New York is not a straight-faced city,'' said Ms. Rahme, 56. ''You have to do things with humor. Of course, they make fun of me about the snacks and the cotton candy, whatever. The Boardwalk, the wheels, so let me start with fun.''</p>
        <p>She remembered Richard Herpin, a perfume maker -- or, in industry-speak, a ''nose'' -- who had moved to Manhattan a few years earlier. Also French, he once gave out as a party favor a fragrance that smelled like margarita mix.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rahme approached Mr. Herpin about a Coney Island perfume. It turns out he had visited Coney Island for an afternoon, rode the Cyclone twice, but tweaked his back.</p>
        <p>''The roller coaster was a little bit too old,'' said Mr. Herpin, who is helping Liz Claiborne with a new fragrance for Usher, the singer. ''It has bitten my back.''</p>
        <p>Over the course of a year of development, the perfume took on a life of its own, a Mexican life. Its up to 200 ingredients had more to do with tequila than Astroland. Coney Island, the fragrance, took on melon, guava and other scents suggested by margaritas.</p>
        <p>''We were not completely sure where it was going to be reached,'' Mr. Herpin said. ''But it was fun.''</p>
        <p>True, Ms. Rahme and Mr. Herpin added caramel to suggest an amusement park, but other things are missing.</p>
        <p>''There is no salt for the margarita,'' Ms. Rahme affirmed, giving a Gallic shrug. The Coney Island bottle, in Bond No. 9's signature shape, is colored turquoise to suggest the ocean, but its neck is colored gold to suggest its premium nature.</p>
        <p>''This is perfume, not hot dog,'' Ms. Rahme said sternly.</p>
        <p>At any rate, Ms. Rahme's expectations for ''Coney Island'' are modest, perhaps 10,000 bottles sold in the first year. Her best seller is ''Scent of Peace,'' which has about $2 million in wholesale revenue a year in various sizes, followed by ''Chinatown,'' and ''Wall Street.'' (There are 29 New York fragrances in all.)</p>
        <p>What perfume is next? ''Brooklyn,'' Ms. Rahme exclaimed. ''We cannot miss because everyone is moving there!''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
