<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Questions Spain's Leaders on Cuba Policy</title>
    <meta content="02spain" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/world/europe/02spain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851438"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Spain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burnett, Victoria</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rice, Condoleezza (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moratinos, Miguel Angel (Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Castro, Fidel (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Spain</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Cuba</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Rice, Condoleezza</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEED71330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="610" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Questions Spain's Leaders on Cuba Policy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Questions Spain’s Leaders on Cuba Policy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VICTORIA BURNETT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burnett, Victoria</byline>
      <dateline>MADRID, June 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sec of State Condoleezza Rice meets with Foreign Min Miguel Angel Moratinos in Madrid, and prods Spanish government to do more to support dissidents in Cuba as it prepares for what she calls 'major transition'--reference to health of Fidel Castro; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice bluntly criticized Spain's increasingly close contacts with Cuba on Friday and prodded the Spanish government to do more to support dissidents in Cuba as it prepares for what she called a ''major transition'' -- a reference to the health of Fidel Castro.</p>
        <p>''I made very clear before I came and in my meetings that I have real doubts about the value of engagement with a regime that is antidemocratic,'' Ms. Rice told reporters after a meeting with Miguel Ángel Moratinos, the Spanish foreign minister.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the highest-level visit to Spain by an American official since 2004, Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice criticized the country’s increasingly close contacts with Cuba.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice bluntly criticized Spain's increasingly close contacts with Cuba on Friday and prodded the Spanish government to do more to support dissidents in Cuba as it prepares for what she called a ''major transition'' -- a reference to the health of Fidel Castro.</p>
        <p>''I made very clear before I came and in my meetings that I have real doubts about the value of engagement with a regime that is antidemocratic,'' Ms. Rice told reporters after a meeting with Miguel Ángel Moratinos, the Spanish foreign minister.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rice's six-hour trip to Spain, where she also met with Prime Minister José Luis Rodríguez Zapatero and King Juan Carlos, was the highest-level visit by a United States official since Mr. Zapatero made good on an election promise and pulled Spanish troops out of Iraq in 2004. That decision sharply cooled the relationship cultivated by Mr. Zapatero's predecessor, José María Aznar, who had been a strong ally in the Iraq invasion and pushed Europe to take a tough stance on Cuba.</p>
        <p>Appearing at a news conference with Ms. Rice on Friday, Mr. Moratinos said her trip signaled that relations were back to normal. Still, the brief visit appeared to have been dominated by differences over how to promote a transition to democratic rule in Havana once Mr. Castro is incapacitated or dead.</p>
        <p>''I'm particularly concerned that the dissidents in Cuba get the right message,'' Ms. Rice said, referring to a decision by Mr. Moratinos not to meet with Mr. Castro's opponents during a visit to Havana in April. ''People who are struggling for a democratic future need to know that they are supported by those of us who are lucky enough to be free.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Moratinos defended Spain's approach, saying it had as much, if not more, contact than any other country with Cuban dissidents. In an interview before Ms. Rice's visit, he said he hoped that the United States would respect Spain's position.</p>
        <p>''What Spain is not prepared to do is be absent from Cuba,'' he said. ''And what the U.S. has to understand is that, given they have no relations with Cuba, they should trust in a faithful, solid ally like Spain.''</p>
        <p>Appearing relaxed despite their differences over Cuba, Ms. Rice and Mr. Moratinos stressed strong cooperation in fighting drug trafficking and terrorism, as well as their joint role in stabilizing Afghanistan, where Spain has about 750 troops deployed under NATO.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rice said they had spent a ''great deal of time'' discussing Latin America, where leaders in the United States and Spain have been alarmed by what they called the increasingly undemocratic style of Hugo Chávez, the Venezuelan president. She called for Mr. Chávez to reopen Radio Caracas Televisión, an independent broadcaster, which was taken off the air on Sunday.</p>
        <p>While the two countries remain far apart on policy toward Cuba, their differences have narrowed over how to handle Mr. Chávez and his Bolivian counterpart, Evo Morales, political analysts said this week. Mr. Zapatero's initial friendliness toward both leaders has chilled in the past year, as Mr. Chávez became increasingly autocratic and Bolivia and Spain clashed over Mr. Morales's decision to nationalize the natural gas industry, where Repsol YPF, a Spanish energy company, has significant interests.</p>
        <p>However, analysts said they did not expect Ms. Rice's visit to augur a sudden transformation of the relationship between President Bush and Mr. Zapatero, one of the few current European leaders not to have visited the White House. Mr. Aznar, in contrast, visited Washington several times during his eight years in office and became the first Spanish prime minister to address a joint session of Congress, in February 2004.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
