<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hat-Wearing Bank Robber Strikes Again, in Montclair</title>
    <meta content="02bank" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/nyregion/02bank.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851421"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E0D71330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="634" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hat-Wearing Bank Robber Strikes Again, in Montclair</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hat-Wearing Bank Robber Strikes Again, in Montclair</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD G. JONES</byline>
      <dateline>MONTCLAIR, N.J., June 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He usually wears baseball caps. But on occasion, there have been a hunting cap and a fisherman's hat. And this time, there might be a big red splotch.</p>
        <p>That is because a serial bank robber known as the Mad Hatter because of the distinctive headgear he wears during thefts struck again on Friday in what the authorities said was his 17th robbery in three northern New Jersey counties over the last nine months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A serial bank robber known as the Mad Hatter because of his distinctive headgear struck again on Friday, his 17th heist over the last nine months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He usually wears baseball caps. But on occasion, there have been a hunting cap and a fisherman's hat. And this time, there might be a big red splotch.</p>
        <p>That is because a serial bank robber known as the Mad Hatter because of the distinctive headgear he wears during thefts struck again on Friday in what the authorities said was his 17th robbery in three northern New Jersey counties over the last nine months.</p>
        <p>But in this case, the authorities said, the robber left with more than just cash -- they did not say how much. A package of red dye that had been hidden in the stack of money he was given exploded as he fled.</p>
        <p>The authorities said the robbery occurred around midmorning, when a man wearing a white and blue plaid shirt and sunglasses -- and a dark baseball cap -- entered a Commerce Bank on Bloomfield Avenue near Elm and Grove Streets and handed a note to a teller demanding money.</p>
        <p>The suspect, who witnesses told the police was a man in his 40s or 50s, fit the description of the robber who is believed to be responsible for the string of bank robberies in Essex, Union and Morris Counties. More than two-thirds of them occurred in Commerce Banks.</p>
        <p>''We do believe he is possibly the Mad Hatter,'' said Sean Quinn, a spokesman in the Newark office of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, which has been involved in the hunt.</p>
        <p>Although bank surveillance cameras captured the image of the dye pack exploding, it was not clear how much, if any, of the dye rubbed off on the robber. The authorities said the man threw at least some of the money into a storm drain as he made his escape.</p>
        <p>The presence of police helicopters, federal agents and local police shattered the peace of the languid spring day as an extensive manhunt ensued in this affluent suburb about 12 miles west of Manhattan. Yet the search yielded little.</p>
        <p>By midday, the bank had resumed normal operations, and customers began trickling through its doors shortly after the last federal agents left with brown paper bags bearing the word ''Evidence.''</p>
        <p>The authorities interviewed scores of people who live in a nearby condominium complex and others who work in a shopping center adjacent to the bank.</p>
        <p>Dennis Perry, 52, a telecommunications analyst who lives at the Montclair Mews condominiums, said federal agents asked if he had seen a car parked next to a gray, four-door sedan in the complex's parking lot. Mr. Perry said he had not, but he said the agent told him that that car could have been the vehicle the robber used to escape.</p>
        <p>The condominium parking lot is about 100 yards from the bank and is separated from the bank parking lot by a chain-link fence with a gate near where the car was parked. The Mad Hatter has confounded the authorities by what they say is his ability to hide in plain sight.</p>
        <p>Because the robber uses notes -- but no weapon -- during his thefts and says few words to the tellers involved, the transactions are so low-key that many of the customers and workers in the banks that have been struck and businesses nearby were not aware of the robberies until after the suspect had left.</p>
        <p>That was the case on Friday when Brendan O'Boyle, a salesman at a Firestone shop across the street from the Commerce Bank, was tending to his duties and noticed teams of officers scouring the streets and heard the whupping of a helicopter overhead. Soon, he said, there were more officers in squad cars, and on motorcycles and bicycles.</p>
        <p>It was only then, Mr. O'Boyle said, that he realized what had happened.</p>
        <p>''I didn't notice the commotion until I saw the police,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
