<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seeking Trade to Bridge a Political North-South Divide</title>
    <meta content="02tajikistan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/world/asia/02tajikistan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070606T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851428"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tajikistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kazakhstan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Army Corps of Engineers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chivers, C J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kazakhstan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Tajikistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Kazakhstan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Tajikistan</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EFD71330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1195" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seeking Trade to Bridge a Political North-South Divide</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Seeking Trade to Bridge a Political North-South Divide</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C.J. CHIVERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chivers, C J</byline>
      <dateline>NIZHNY PANJ, Tajikistan</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US-backed bridge linking Tajikistan with Afghanistan is nearing completion; bridge, underwritten by Washington and designed by US Army Corps of Engineers, is at center of plans to establish trade route from Kazakhstan to Pakistan; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The nearly completed bridge over the Panj River makes an incongruous sight. More than 700 yards long, it is the sort of modern and imposing concrete structure that might carry a rush of traffic over a gorge in the West.</p>
        <p>Instead it reaches from one nearly deserted bank of the Panj to the other, spanning the silence above a line that for decades has been one of the world's least traveled boundaries -- the border between Afghanistan and Tajikistan, where the former Soviet Union met a land with which the Kremlin was at war.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The nearly completed bridge over the Panj River is at the center of plans to connect trade and energy markets in South and Central Asia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The nearly completed bridge over the Panj River makes an incongruous sight. More than 700 yards long, it is the sort of modern and imposing concrete structure that might carry a rush of traffic over a gorge in the West.</p>
        <p>Instead it reaches from one nearly deserted bank of the Panj to the other, spanning the silence above a line that for decades has been one of the world's least traveled boundaries -- the border between Afghanistan and Tajikistan, where the former Soviet Union met a land with which the Kremlin was at war.</p>
        <p>By mid-August, if work here is completed on schedule, this isolated stretch of river will become a leg in an ambitious plan to connect trade and energy markets in South and Central Asia. These regions, adjacent to each other and sharing linguistic, religious and ethnic ties, have been separated for generations -- first by ideology, then by instability and a dearth of safe and easy routes.</p>
        <p>The bridge, underwritten by Washington and designed by the United States Army Corps of Engineers, is at the center of plans to establish a trade route from Kazakhstan to Pakistan. The corridor has been under construction for several years; Western and Central Asian diplomats say it will soon take shape.</p>
        <p>''The bridge is the symbol, the concrete symbol, of larger regional integration,'' Tracey Ann Jacobson, the United States ambassador to Tajikistan, said as she toured the structure in late May with foreign diplomats.</p>
        <p>Under plans in progress along the route, foreign developers have been extending Central Asia's and Afghanistan's limited network of roads, tunnels and bridges.</p>
        <p>The improvements have been under way in Kyrgyz mountain passes and the arid canyons between Kabul and Jalalabad in Afghanistan, the route that leads to the Khyber Pass. They have been paid for by China, Iran, the United States and other nations, many of them competing for influence in the region.</p>
        <p>Now many projects are nearing completion. Together they might not merely improve access, but undo the trends of history.</p>
        <p>During Soviet times, Central Asia faced north and west toward the Kremlin, moving goods to and from Moscow and Soviet cities along the line. Afghanistan faced toward Pakistan or Iran, feeling more affinity to Islamic traders than to the Slavic-led Communists to the north.</p>
        <p>The border where the two worlds met served as an obstacle, both physical and intellectual, to robust trade. ''It was a wall for a long time,'' Hamrokhon Zarifi, Tajikistan's foreign minister, said in an interview.</p>
        <p>After the Soviet Union's collapse, the murky Panj, mined in places on its banks and watched over from bunkers and guard towers, was crossed mostly by smugglers, armed groups and those with the means or connections to navigate the complications it posed.</p>
        <p>Several ferries and barges have been working the river in recent years, and a few small bridges, some of them footbridges, have been built in the headwaters as well.</p>
        <p>In place of these limited and sometimes illegal border crossings, Tajikistan and other countries seek a two-stage development. First, beginning this year, they hope that fleets of trucks will regularly be driven across the border, generating trade in both directions.</p>
        <p>Proponents point out that goods to Tajikistan now travel overland roughly 4,300 miles from ports on the Baltic Sea, on the far side of Russia. Ports in Pakistan or Iran, which will be accessible once the bridge opens, are less than half that distance away.</p>
        <p>Later, developers hope to construct power lines along the route, carrying electricity from Tajik hydropower stations, most of them not yet built, to Afghanistan, Pakistan and Iran.</p>
        <p>Questions remain about how many such dreams will be realized, in part because experience in neighboring Uzbekistan has shown that access alone does not guarantee trade.</p>
        <p>In the 1980s, the Soviet Union built a bridge to Afghanistan, downstream from here on the Amu Darya, which begins where the Panj meets the Vakhsh River and forms the Uzbek-Afghan border.</p>
        <p>Built as a thoroughfare for Red Army armor and supplies during the war in Afghanistan, it was named straight from party doublespeak: the Friendship Bridge. Uzbekistan inherited the span when the Soviet Union collapsed, then closed it in the 1990s as the Taliban spread.</p>
        <p>Beginning late in 2001, after the Taliban lost its hold in northern Afghanistan, the Uzbek government allowed the United Nations to move food and other aid across the bridge. But otherwise it has largely been padlocked. Uzbekistan, security-minded and suspicious of outsiders, allows little traffic across it.</p>
        <p>Tajik and American officials insist that the bridge over the Panj will be run differently. ''It will be a very busy bridge,'' said Mr. Zarifi, the foreign minister.</p>
        <p>He noted that Tajikistan had already shown that its attitude toward foreigners differed from that in Uzbekistan: Last year it eased visa rules for visitors from 68 countries. Many visitors, including those from the United States, can purchase visas on demand at the airport in Dushanbe, the capital. Mr. Zarifi said he expected visas would also be available at the bridge.</p>
        <p>But other potential complications remain. Security is still a concern along many legs of the corridor, especially in Afghanistan, where the Kabul-to-Kandahar route is prowled by criminals and insurgents, and is especially dangerous to outsiders.</p>
        <p>Even in the north, where the Taliban is much less strong, terrorists have detonated several bombs this year in Kunduz, a short drive from the bridge.</p>
        <p>A range of other problems could also undermine prospects for growth and investment. These include endemic corruption with border agents and the traffic police, whose conduct will to a large extent give the roads and borders their character.</p>
        <p>A shortage of banking transparency and independent judges also undermine a mature business climate. ''There is a reason that there is not a lot of investment here,'' said Elizabeth K. Horst, chief of the political and economics section at the American Embassy in Dushanbe. ''It's not ready for it.''</p>
        <p>About the trade corridor, she added, ''It is a really good idea, but making it happen on the ground is going to be harder than people realize.''</p>
        <p>For now, the bridge, being built by Rizzani de Eccher of Italy, is almost finished after 16 months' work. Administration zones on either side -- including passport-control areas, barracks, parking lots and reception centers -- are beginning to rise.</p>
        <p>The span stands almost 50 feet above the Panj's typical high water, which means the channel below will be navigable for ferries and other small craft.</p>
        <p>It was also designed to withstand a severe earthquake and to handle military traffic, said Brian Walls, an engineer from the Army Corps of Engineers who is supervising the construction. ''We don't build bridges any stronger than the standards for this,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In all, the project will cost more than $52 million. American officials described the investment as a long-term bet, not just to help stabilize northern Afghanistan, but to promote larger ideas of regional cooperation and business collaboration.</p>
        <p>''I think it is going to be an organic thing that is finally going to come together,'' Ms. Horst said. ''It is not going to come with a boom, but one day these countries will be used to trading together.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 6, 2007, Wednesday  A map of Central Asia with an article on Saturday about the construction of a bridge linking Tajikistan and Afghanistan misidentified the country shown in the lower left. It is Iran, not Azerbaijan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 6, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A map of Central Asia with an article on Saturday about the construction of a bridge linking Tajikistan and Afghanistan misidentified the country shown in the lower left. It is Iran, not Azerbaijan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
