<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playing Games at CNBC</title>
    <meta content="02online" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/technology/02online.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851407"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S ONLINE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light Bulbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light Bulbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blogs and Blogging (Internet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lighting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">CNBC</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cramer, James J</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jobs, Steven P</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E5D71330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playing Games at CNBC</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Playing Games at CNBC</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Dan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN his 5,000-word apologia in New York magazine this week, the TV stock-picker James Cramer wrote that in the 1990s ''people learned the stock market was a game that could make them rich, and they loved it because the pursuit of wealth is our true national pastime.''</p>
        <p>In all, he referred nine times to investing as a ''game'' (nymag.com).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The TV stock-picker James Cramer certainly draws plenty of criticism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN his 5,000-word apologia in New York magazine this week, the TV stock-picker James Cramer wrote that in the 1990s ''people learned the stock market was a game that could make them rich, and they loved it because the pursuit of wealth is our true national pastime.''</p>
        <p>In all, he referred nine times to investing as a ''game'' (nymag.com).</p>
        <p>The article was meant to address the question ''Why does everybody hate me?'' Quite clearly, not everybody does, or his show wouldn't be so popular. But Mr. Cramer -- who yells, sweats, throws things, wears diapers and flings himself into piles of lettuce while giving stock advice on his CNBC show ''Mad Money'' -- certainly draws plenty of criticism. He ascribes it to two things: inaccurate assessments of his stock-picking abilities (which he says are pretty good) and his on-air persona.</p>
        <p>He tries to dispense with the latter issue by saying that the people who do not like his presentation ''are not the people I'm trying to reach.''</p>
        <p>''The guys who think that my shtick is obnoxious and impossible to watch are already well served by the conventional outlets for information and entertainment.''</p>
        <p>But some of the criticism goes beyond simply not liking his presentation. Mr. Cramer's ''buffoonery'' is the most obvious reason some people do not like him, wrote Mark Lacter of LA Observed. ''But let's put all that off to one side, and get to the more serious matter of hosting a TV money show in which investing is treated as a game -- a silly game at that'' (laobserved.com).</p>
        <p>The games at CNBC aren't limited to Mr. Cramer's show. It is also the network that produces ''Fast Money,'' which resembles an N.F.L. pregame show. It consists of five alpha-males who argue about stocks amid blaring sound effects and garish graphics (cnbc.com).</p>
        <p>And this week, the network said that it was investigating some of the players in its stock-trading contest, the Million Dollar Portfolio Challenge, which has contestants building virtual portfolios on its Web site. The top trader will win $1 million. CNBC said there was ''unusual trading in violation of contest rules'' by one or more of the 20 finalists.</p>
        <p>The network needs to get to the bottom of the situation quickly, wrote Jonathan Berr at A.O.L's bloggingstocks. ''Otherwise, the network may lose credibility with viewers and advertisers'' (bloggingstocks.com). ''For CNBC,'' Mr. Berr added, ''this isn't just a game.''</p>
        <p>BRIGHT IDEA -- Switching from incandescent to compact fluorescent light bulbs sounds like one of those small things people do mostly just to make themselves feel better.</p>
        <p>But consider this: according to the Earth Policy Institute, if the whole world were to make the switch, 270 500-megawatt coal-burning power plants could be closed. If the United States were to switch, it could close 80 plants (earth-policy.org).</p>
        <p>Australia plans to phase out incandescents in favor of compact fluorescents by 2010; Canada by 2012. Environmental groups, along with Philips Lighting, are trying to get the United States to make the switch by 2016.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes an idea seems almost too good to be true,'' the institute's president, Lester R. Brown, wrote at TreeHugger. ''But this one is not'' (treehugger.com).</p>
        <p>WHO'S FAKE STEVE? -- Nick Denton of the technology-gossip blog Valleywag (valleywag.com) is 0 for 2 in trying to guess the identity of Fake Steve Jobs, who keeps a blog, The Secret Diary of Steve Jobs, where he refers to Bill Gates as Beastmaster and to his namesake as Real Steve Jobs, or just ''RSJ'' (fakesteve.blogspot.com).</p>
        <p>First, Mr. Denton guessed that Fake Steve was an Apple-watcher, Leander Kahney, who writes about Apple for Wired.com. Wrong. This week, his guess was John Paczkowski of All Things Digital, a property of The Wall Street Journal (allthingsd.com). Wrong again.</p>
        <p>In response, Fake Steve wrote of Mr. Denton's labored (but fake) efforts to prove that Princess Diana is alive and well and living in Qatar with Dodi Fayed.</p>
        <p>During their rare joint appearance during a technology conference this week, the Beastmaster assured RSJ, ''I want to clarify I'm not Fake Steve Jobs.''</p>
        <p>DAN MITCHELL</p>
        <p>WHAT'S ONLINE E-mail: whatsonline@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: whatsonline@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
