<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Principal Goodell Is Setting a New Tone</title>
    <meta content="02rhoden" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/sports/football/02rhoden.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851451"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Goodell, Roger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jones, Pacman</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Portis, Clinton</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Vick, Michael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5D61330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Principal Goodell Is Setting a New Tone</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Principal Goodell Sets a New Tone for the N.F.L.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I've watched with great curiosity during the past few months as Roger Goodell, the new National Football League commissioner, has made his moves. What I've been unable to determine is whether he wants to be a commissioner of the people, or whether he will be the law and order commissioner. Early returns point to law and order, although after speaking with Goodell yesterday, he also seems to see himself as a conductor who uses his pitch pipe to set the proper tone. Indeed, the N.F.L., for all its soaring profits, is out of tune.</p>
        <p>Without reciting chapter and verse of all the recent arrests and brushes with the law, suffice it to say that Goodell has had to face a growing perception that the league is being overtaken by lawlessness. He has flexed his muscles in a way that has grabbed everyone's attention.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Roger Goodell, the new National Football League commissioner, has had to face a growing perception that the league is being overtaken by lawlessness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I've watched with great curiosity during the past few months as Roger Goodell, the new National Football League commissioner, has made his moves. What I've been unable to determine is whether he wants to be a commissioner of the people, or whether he will be the law and order commissioner. Early returns point to law and order, although after speaking with Goodell yesterday, he also seems to see himself as a conductor who uses his pitch pipe to set the proper tone. Indeed, the N.F.L., for all its soaring profits, is out of tune.</p>
        <p>Without reciting chapter and verse of all the recent arrests and brushes with the law, suffice it to say that Goodell has had to face a growing perception that the league is being overtaken by lawlessness. He has flexed his muscles in a way that has grabbed everyone's attention.</p>
        <p>''My job is the National Football League,'' Goodell said during a telephone interview, ''but I think there's an erosion of what's acceptable behavior in society in general.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''Don't make this about me and 'This is Goodell the tough guy.' I don't look at it that way. I'm doing what I think is in the best interest of the N.F.L., that's what this is about.''</p>
        <p>In April, Goodell introduced something he called a Code of Conduct, and in the intervening months he has laid down the gauntlet, introducing law and order, and not in a silent way. He has taken two highly visible disciplinary actions, suspending the Tennessee Titans' Pacman Jones for the entire season and the Cincinnati Bengals' Chris Henry for eight games. The steps were tough, but they were necessary.</p>
        <p>Last week, Goodell was harsh in his criticism of Clinton Portis, the Washington Redskins running back, for remarks Portis made about the investigation into Michael Vick's possible involvement in dog fighting.</p>
        <p>A day later, Portis issued a statement apologizing for remarks that may have made him seem sympathetic to the brutality of dog fighting. I despise censorship, but sometimes some people need to be edited. It's one thing for Portis to say that what Vick does with dogs in his home is his business -- but at least know that dog fighting is a felony in your state.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, in something of a surprise, Goodell announced that N.F.L. clubs may no longer serve alcohol at team functions or on buses or flights. The rule pertains not only to players but also to owners, coaches and guests.</p>
        <p>Certain clubs had an alcohol policy, but there was no uniformity. ''There were variations from club to club and that was another aspect here, to try to standardize this,'' Goodell said.</p>
        <p>In another matter, perhaps in an effort to score points with the news media, Goodell fired a shot at the head coaches who for years have created as wide a gap as possible between members of the news media, players and coaches.</p>
        <p>Goodell began his N.F.L. career in 1982 as an administrative intern in the league office. A year later he joined the Jets in media relations, then returned to the league office in 1984 as an assistant in the public relations department. Whether it was because of his sojourn in media relations or the pragmatic realization that appeasing the news media is better than antagonizing it, Goodell ordered head coaches to remove the moats and drawbridges. Coaches have to make themselves, their players and their assistant coaches available to the news media.</p>
        <p>''I think that's a very good example of an erosion of a policy that became the lowest common denominator,'' he said. ''We're all going to be held to the same standard, you're all going to do the same amount to cooperate with the media. I didn't allow a lot of debate on that.''</p>
        <p>That is well and good, but Goodell's early term will be decided by his relationship with -- and to -- Vick, the Atlanta Falcons' quarterback and the onetime face of the N.F.L.</p>
        <p>Vick is being investigated over suspicions he was involved in dog fighting. That investigation, coupled with his style of play and his off-field entanglements, have made Vick the most scrutinized player in the N.F.L. A wrong outcome here could be devastating for the league.</p>
        <p>Goodell was noncommittal on the specifics regarding Vick.</p>
        <p>''All of us should allow the facts to become clear,'' Goodell said. ''Right now there is a rush to judgment.</p>
        <p>''I think he's making the changes in his life. We talked an awful lot about the choices that are being made, the intense focus that's on him and he's got to make better choices. He knows the difference between right and wrong and he needs to start making the right choices and I think he's going to do that.''</p>
        <p>Which raises this question: What is Goodell trying to get across to the players and coaches in his league?</p>
        <p>''That if you're involved with the N.F.L. you represent the N.F.L., you are held to a higher standard and you need to be accountable, and there is a certain standard of behavior that you're going to have to live up to, from the commissioner on down,'' Goodell said. ''This is a personal conduct policy, not a player conduct policy.''</p>
        <p>I haven't figured out yet whether Goodell is the sheriff or the conductor. But this much is certain: He is the caretaker of a multibillion-dollar industry with highly visible warts.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
