<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Russian Panel Delays Vote on Revoking BP Gas Field License</title>
    <meta content="02oil" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/business/worldbusiness/02oil.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851453"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
        <org class="online_producer">BP Plc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E4D61330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="514" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Russian Panel Delays Vote on Revoking BP Gas Field License</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Russian Panel Delays Vote on Revoking BP Gas Field License</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW E. KRAMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kramer, Andrew E</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, June 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Russian committee delayed a decision on Friday on whether to revoke the license for a major natural gas field held by a BP joint venture, though draft minutes for the meeting are said to have included a recommendation to cancel the license.</p>
        <p>That does not bode well for BP, which bet heavily on Russia four years ago when it set up the joint venture, TNK-BP, in what was the largest foreign investment in the country at the time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The draft minutes for the meeting are said to have included a recommendation to cancel the license.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Russian committee delayed a decision on Friday on whether to revoke the license for a major natural gas field held by a BP joint venture, though draft minutes for the meeting are said to have included a recommendation to cancel the license.</p>
        <p>That does not bode well for BP, which bet heavily on Russia four years ago when it set up the joint venture, TNK-BP, in what was the largest foreign investment in the country at the time.</p>
        <p>Since then, Russian authorities have shifted tack. Their new policy favors government control over major reserves and threatens TNK-BP's investment at the giant Kovykta natural gas field near China.</p>
        <p>The decision on TNK-BP's Kovykta license will be delayed two weeks, according to the Interfax news agency. A spokesman for the committee declined to comment as the proceedings were not public.</p>
        <p>The delay will push any action against the British-based BP until after two important events in Russia's economic calendar this spring. While giving BP breathing room in its negotiations, it will also avoid a potentially embarrassing mixed message for the Kremlin.</p>
        <p>Russia is playing host to an economic forum next weekend intended to highlight the investment potential in the country as an emerging market -- a theme that could be undermined by stripping the big BP license. The Kovykta field is estimated to hold enough natural gas to meet world demand for one year.</p>
        <p>Also, the Russian president, Vladimir V. Putin, is scheduled to attend a Group of 8 meeting of the leaders of industrialized nations in Germany next week, where Russia's openness to investment will probably be discussed.</p>
        <p>Still, draft minutes for the closed meeting of the committee, called Rosnedra, had recommended stripping the license, according to a report by Interfax that cited a copy of the meeting's minutes.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for TNK-BP said the company was not informed of the proceedings, though the committee's decision will affect a development where BP and its partners have invested hundreds of millions of dollars.</p>
        <p>''We don't know even the status,'' Marina Dracheva, the spokeswoman, said. ''We have zero information at this stage.''</p>
        <p>Tony Hayward, BP's chief executive, visited Moscow on Thursday for talks and left without publicly commenting on their outcome.</p>
        <p>Critics of Russia's economic tactics say the license is being stripped on a pretext; Russian officials say they are merely sticking to the letter of the contract.</p>
        <p>Authorities accuse TNK-BP of failing to meet a license requirement to produce nine billion cubic meters of natural gas for the local market in eastern Siberia by 2006.</p>
        <p>TNK-BP does not dispute that it failed to meet that provision, but counters that demand for natural gas is now far below this level in eastern Siberia, meaning it is impossible to meet the requirement.</p>
        <p>The licensing troubles in Russia come as the latest setback for BP, after the company came under scrutiny in the United States for a refinery explosion in Texas and a pipeline spill in Alaska. BP pumps a quarter of its worldwide oil output from Russia, through its 50 percent share in TNK-BP.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
