<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Five Starters Out of Lineup, Mets' Offense Has Little in Reserve</title>
    <meta content="02mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/sports/baseball/02mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Arizona Diamondbacks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Beltran, Carlos</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wright, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Maine, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E7DE1030F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Five Starters Out of Lineup, Mets' Offense Has Little in Reserve</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Five Starters Out of Lineup, Mets’ Offense Has Little in Reserve</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID PICKER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets received some good news and some bad news before their game against the Arizona Diamondbacks yesterday. A magnetic resonance imaging test on Carlos Beltrán's right knee was negative.</p>
        <p>That was the good news. The bad news was that David Wright awoke with back spasms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets managed four singles  only one of them out of the infield  and were baffled by the Diamondbacks’ starter, Brandon Webb.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Mets received some good news and some bad news before their game against the Arizona Diamondbacks yesterday. A magnetic resonance imaging test on Carlos Beltrán's right knee was negative.</p>
        <p>That was the good news. The bad news was that David Wright awoke with back spasms.</p>
        <p>Neither player was healthy enough to start for the Mets, who were already missing three starters. So they began their game at Shea Stadium with five reserves behind starter John Maine.</p>
        <p>That was when the really bad news arrived. Brandon Webb, the Diamondbacks' sensational right-hander, threw a sinkerball that baffled the Mets, reserves and regulars alike.</p>
        <p>The Mets (34-19) managed four singles -- only one of them out of the infield -- in a 5-1 loss that probably would have felt more disheartening had it come with their more robust lineup.</p>
        <p>''He was painting his sinker all night,'' catcher Paul Lo Duca said. ''He was tough to hit. We knew we were in trouble.''</p>
        <p>With such a makeshift lineup, and with Webb in such a groove, there was little margin for error by Maine. He was nearly flawless early in the game, allowing a leadoff single to Eric Byrnes in the first inning and then retiring the next nine batters, five of them on strikeouts.</p>
        <p>But Maine made two costly mistakes in the fifth inning. He allowed a one-out double to Carlos Quentin. The next batter, Chris Snyder, clobbered a 91-mile-an-hour fastball that was supposed to be inside but stayed in the middle, sending the ball cruising over the left-field wall to give the Diamondbacks (33-23) a 2-0 lead.</p>
        <p>''You never want to give up runs when another pitcher's doing well,'' Maine said. ''It just makes it tough.''</p>
        <p>The Mets' depleted lineup, which had Damion Easley batting third, appeared puzzled by Webb, who won the National League's Cy Young award last season. Webb surrendered two hits through the first six innings, an infield single in the third and a bunt single in the sixth, both by José Reyes.</p>
        <p>Easley, who has been filling in at second base for the injured José Valentín and usually bats much lower in the order, went 0 for 4. With the fourth and fifth batters, Carlos Delgado and Lo Duca, also hitless, Manager Willie Randolph tried to generate some offense in the sixth inning by lifting Maine, who had thrown 103 pitches, for a pinch-hitter. The move failed when Webb struck out Carlos Gómez.</p>
        <p>Maine allowed two runs and five hits in six innings while striking out seven batters and walking none.</p>
        <p>''He threw the ball well,'' Randolph said. ''Webb was even better.''</p>
        <p>On a normal night, Maine's performance might have been good enough.</p>
        <p>But this night was anything but normal. With Beltrán out, the outfield was made up of backups.</p>
        <p>''I hope they don't run into each other,'' Randolph said before the game.</p>
        <p>Beltrán, who would have been in center field, injured his knee during the first inning of Thursday's game against the San Francisco Giants. He was listed as day to day.</p>
        <p>''I feel better than yesterday for sure,'' said Beltrán, who sustained the injury while colliding with first baseman Rich Aurilia. ''But my leg's still weak. I just want to take the field when I feel like I can play the game the way I want to play the game. Maybe not 100 percent, because that's impossible. But at least 80, 85 percent.''</p>
        <p>Endy Chávez replaced Beltrán and was joined in the outfield by David Newhan, who started in left, and Ben Johnson, recently called up from Class AAA New Orleans.</p>
        <p>The Mets were already missing left fielder Moises Alou (strained left quadriceps) and right fielder Shawn Green (broken bone in his right foot), both of whom are on the disabled list.</p>
        <p>Wright wanted to play and even requested to pinch hit during the game, but was persuaded to sit. The 48-year-old Julio Franco started at third base.</p>
        <p>''More than anything, it's precautionary,'' said Wright, who had back problems last season and usually sees a chiropractor once every week or two.</p>
        <p>''I talked to Willie and planned on playing the whole day. I sat down with him and our trainer, and they thought it was best just to give us a day. But I plan on being there tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>Had Wright played, he might have had success against Webb. But it is hard to imagine how. Webb allowed four hits and one unearned run over eight innings. He retired the side in order four times and allowed only four runners to reach scoring position.</p>
        <p>The Diamondbacks increased their lead to 5-0 when Stephen Drew hit a three-run homer in the eighth against Guillermo Mota, who relieved Maine.</p>
        <p>''I think I made a good pitch,'' Mota said. ''He hit it on a good part of the bat.''</p>
        <p>The Mets finally scored in the eighth, when Newhan reached on an infield single and advanced to second on a wild throw from third baseman Mark Reynolds. He scored when pinch-hitter Rubén Gotay's grounder squirted past a diving Conor Jackson at first base and rolled into right field for the only Mets hit that left the infield.</p>
        <p>''As a player, obviously you want to be on the field,'' Newhan said, speaking for himself and for his fellow reserves. ''It's fun to run out there and play. But you got to come away with a win.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
