<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Young Siblings From Iowa Learn to Shine</title>
    <meta content="02sibl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/arts/dance/02sibl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851395"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York City Ballet</org>
        <org class="online_producer">School of American Ballet</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Soto, Jock</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Martins, Peter</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E0D81330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Young Siblings From Iowa Learn to Shine</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Young Siblings From Iowa Learn to Shine</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GIA KOURLAS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is a universal truth that whenever a child appears in a production by the New York City Ballet, audiences, even those immune to the easy charms of a mop-headed boy or a frisky, budding ballerina, melt like butter.</p>
        <p>And every so often one does appear, as Austin Bachman did in his 2005 debut as the Nutcracker Prince, offering not only youthful charm but also a captivating hint of the future. Just 13, he stars as the lone boy in Sean Lavery's ''Twinkliana'' this afternoon and on Monday night at the School of American Ballet Workshop Performances.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is a universal truth that whenever a child appears in a production by the New York City Ballet, audiences, even those immune to the easy charms of a mop-headed boy or a frisky, budding ballerina, melt like butter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is a universal truth that whenever a child appears in a production by the New York City Ballet, audiences, even those immune to the easy charms of a mop-headed boy or a frisky, budding ballerina, melt like butter.</p>
        <p>And every so often one does appear, as Austin Bachman did in his 2005 debut as the Nutcracker Prince, offering not only youthful charm but also a captivating hint of the future. Just 13, he stars as the lone boy in Sean Lavery's ''Twinkliana'' this afternoon and on Monday night at the School of American Ballet Workshop Performances.</p>
        <p>''He's naturally talented, that's for sure,'' said the dancer Jock Soto, one of his teachers. ''You know that he's going to have long, gorgeous legs when he gets older, and his feet are beautiful. But the way he presents himself is also very special. He's got the whole package.''</p>
        <p>And to think: Austin, a serious contender for the lead in Stephen Daldry's musical version of ''Billy Elliot'' -- until he grew too tall and his voice changed -- wasn't even the main prize, just a hefty bonus. The first member of the family to attract attention was his older sister, Callie, the inspiration for Peter Martins's ''Romeo + Juliet,'' who at 12 auditioned for the school before Kay Mazzo, its co-chairwoman of the faculty, in Chicago. After an injury forced Callie to give up the part of Juliet during City Ballet's recent run of the production, she will perform the balcony pas de deux opposite Russell Janzen at the Workshop Performances.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'Oh my gosh, we have to have this little one!' '' Ms. Mazzo recalled of Callie at that audition. ''Everything was right: the proportions were good, and nothing was forced. People have trouble understanding why, out of 80 people, you get possibly one wonderful dancer. It's a combination of what God gave you as a body, and then how intelligent you are to work with what you have, and perseverance. She had a lot of attributes at the beginning. And when we got her to the school, all was good. Our little hothouse flowers!''</p>
        <p>The flowers in question bloomed in seemingly nonballet terrain, Des Moines, where Callie's parents enrolled their daughter, now 16, in a ballet class when she was 4. Her brother began training at 6.</p>
        <p>''I was doing gymnastics at the time, and my dad, when he was young, was a gymnast and he took ballet to improve his gymnastics,'' Austin said in an interview. ''Since Callie did ballet I thought I'd do it too. We used to dance together. I used to copy whatever she did.''</p>
        <p>Callie added: ''At home, we have videotapes. They're pretty funny.''</p>
        <p>When Callie was invited to remain at the school the year after a summer course, the Bachman family faced a difficult decision: at 12, she was too young to live in the dormitories. So they decided to move to New York as a family. Her mother, Sue Bachman, formerly a nurse, is now Ms. Mazzo's assistant, and her father, Dan Bachman, a financial planner in Iowa, divides his time, in two-week increments, between New York and Des Moines.</p>
        <p>''When we first moved here, we thought, it's an adventure, and the worst thing is that we get to live in New York and have this great experience,'' Sue Bachman said. ''We always tried to be careful with the kids, not to make them feel pressured. Sometimes I still say, 'Are you sure this is what you want?' ''</p>
        <p>But both siblings remain enthusiastic about their career choices, especially Callie, whose recent injury left her knee swollen but with no torn ligaments. ''I decided that I didn't want to go out there feeling nervous,'' she said. ''It was really hard. I looked forward to it so much.'' Her blue eyes welled with tears. ''Peter knew how devastating it was,'' she said, referring to Mr. Martins. ''He said, 'If you're ready, this would be a really good chance for you to show everyone why this was made on you.' I'm so happy that I get this chance.''</p>
        <p>Austin is also pleased that she has an opportunity to prove herself as Juliet. ''It's really nice to see your sister doing so well, and it makes me think that if she can do it, then maybe I can,'' he said. Blinking his eyes briskly -- it is one of his most charming traits -- he added, a bit guiltily, ''It's nice for me too, because she opens the door a little bit more for me.'' Callie, blond curls framing her angelic face, shook with laughter.</p>
        <p>The School of American Ballet Workshop Performances are today and Monday at the Peter Jay Sharp Theater, 155 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center; (212) 769-6600.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
