<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cars Outsell Light Trucks For First Time Since 2002</title>
    <meta content="02auto" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/business/02auto.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E7D61330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cars Outsell Light Trucks For First Time Since 2002</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cars Outsell Light Trucks for First Time Since 2002</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICK BUNKLEY; Micheline Maynard contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bunkley, Nick</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, June 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The car is officially back.</p>
        <p>More cars than light trucks were sold in the United States last month, reports from the automobile companies showed Friday, as gasoline prices nationwide soared to more than $3 a gallon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>More cars than light trucks were sold in the U.S. last month, as gasoline prices nationwide soared to more than $3 a gallon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The car is officially back.</p>
        <p>More cars than light trucks were sold in the United States last month, reports from the automobile companies showed Friday, as gasoline prices nationwide soared to more than $3 a gallon.</p>
        <p>Toyota, Nissan, General Motors and the Chrysler Group all said their sales rose in May compared with 2006, primarily because of stronger car sales. Toyota, which has benefited most among the major companies from the rise in gas prices, said its May sales set a monthly record, up 9.7 percent from a year ago.</p>
        <p>The Ford Motor Company was the only major player to be left out: its sales fell 11.7 percent from 2006.</p>
        <p>Of the 1.56 million vehicles sold in May, 778,651 were cars and 777,296 were light trucks, including pickups, according Ward's AutoInfoBank, which tracks industry statistics.</p>
        <p>The last time cars outsold light trucks was in May 2002, according to Autodata, another statistics firm. But light trucks have routinely been outselling cars each month since 1997, when consumers' tastes for big vehicles tipped the scales in their favor.</p>
        <p>Among the most popular cars, sales of the Honda Civic rose 32.6 percent in May to set a new record, while sales of the Chevrolet Impala rose 44.7 percent.</p>
        <p>Sales of the hybrid-electric Toyota Prius rose 184.9 percent, according to Autodata. Dealers in parts of the country are again reporting waiting lists for the fuel-efficient model, even though Toyota has doubled production from last year.</p>
        <p>But this latest shift does not mean Detroit auto companies are rushing to build more cars. Ford, for example, said it would build twice as many light trucks as cars during July, August and September.</p>
        <p>One reason, analysts said, is that trucks are far more profitable than cars, with the typical midsize S.U.V. still generating about $4,000 a vehicle in gross profits, versus about $400 for a subcompact car.</p>
        <p>''That's where they make their money,'' said Jesse Toprak, director of industry analysis for Edmunds.com, a Web site that provides car-buying advice.</p>
        <p>But with S.U.V.'s falling out of favor, Detroit companies are heavily promoting crossover vehicles, which are sport utilities built on the underpinnings of cars, not pickups. Ford, in fact, has said its turnaround plan rests on the success of the Edge, a crossover introduced in December. It expects to sell about 120,000 this year.</p>
        <p>''This transition to midcrossovers has been even more rapid than people assumed,'' said G.M.'s chief sales analyst, Paul Ballew.</p>
        <p>Not all trucks are selling poorly. Sales of the Chevrolet Silverado rose 10.9 percent in May compared with 2006, outselling its biggest rival, the Ford F-series, whose sales fell 15.1 percent last year.</p>
        <p>The Silverado was redesigned last fall, while the F-series, long the top-selling vehicle in the United States, is several years older and not scheduled to be revamped until next year.</p>
        <p>Over all, vehicle sales were up 0.7 percent from May 2006, according to Ward's. Car sales were up 2.2 percent, while truck sales slipped 0.7 percent.</p>
        <p>G.M. held 23.9 percent of the American market in May, while Toyota held 17.3 percent. Ford's market share was 16.1 percent, while DaimlerChrysler, including Mercedes-Benz, took 14.2 percent of the market.</p>
        <p>DaimlerChrysler said last month that it would sell the Chrysler Group to Cerberus Capital Management, in a transaction expected to be final this fall. The deal could be the end of monthly sales reports by Chrysler, which will become a privately held company.</p>
        <p>Detroit auto companies have been cutting supplies of unsold vehicles on dealer lots in an effort to reduce rebates and other incentive plans. But both Chrysler and G.M. spent more on incentives in May than in 2006, according to data from Edmunds.</p>
        <p>Japanese automakers also have been discounting their vehicles more, however. Honda, whose sales were down 1.4 percent for the month, offered incentives worth an average of $1,399 per vehicle in May, a record for the company, Edmunds reported. One reason is that it is discontinuing the current version of its midsize sedan, the Accord, and clearing out supplies ahead of the new version, due this summer.</p>
        <p>Toyota's discounts rose to $1,140 last month, from $886 a year ago. Toyota has been offering deals on its new Tundra pickup, which was introduced in February, but company officials say the company must do so because Detroit companies offer discounts on their trucks. Sales of the Tundra rose 113.8 percent in May compared with 2006, according to Autodata.</p>
        <p>Despite a sales decline at Ford, the company is adapting to the buyers' changing tastes, said its sales analyst, George Pipas. Three years ago, cars accounted for only 30 percent of its sales in the United States, but now are close to half.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
