<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jankovic Rolls Along Merrily and Tops Venus Williams</title>
    <meta content="02tennis" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/sports/tennis/02tennis.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851484"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Paris (France)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Williams, Venus</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jankovic, Jelena</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E6DF1030F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jankovic Rolls Along Merrily and Tops Venus Williams</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Venus’s Exit Means Serena Williams Stands Alone</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIET MACUR</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>During a changeover in the middle of her third-round match, Venus Williams whipped out a notebook and flipped through its pages, desperately looking at strategy and inspirational sayings she had compiled for times just like this.</p>
        <p>In her first Grand Slam event since Wimbledon last year, Williams struggled at the French Open on Friday. One glimpse at her opponent during that changeover showed how badly things were going.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After Venus Williams, the five-time Grand Slam champion, lost to Jelena Jankovic, her sister Serena became the last American woman left in the singles competition at the French Open.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>During a changeover in the middle of her third-round match, Venus Williams whipped out a notebook and flipped through its pages, desperately looking at strategy and inspirational sayings she had compiled for times just like this.</p>
        <p>In her first Grand Slam event since Wimbledon last year, Williams struggled at the French Open on Friday. One glimpse at her opponent during that changeover showed how badly things were going.</p>
        <p>Jelena Jankovic, seeded fourth, sat in her chair at courtside, giggling. She stole glances at the box in the stands where a crowd of boisterous friends and family from Serbia cheered and sang. She needed to bury her face in a towel to repress her laughter.</p>
        <p>Jankovic had plenty to be happy about in her 6-4, 4-6, 6-1 victory that knocked Williams, a five-time Grand Slam singles champion, out of the tournament.</p>
        <p>Going into the fourth round at Roland Garros, the only American remaining is the eighth-seeded Serena Williams, Venus's sister, who beat Michaella Krajicek, 6-3, 6-4, on Friday night.</p>
        <p>''I have really positive people in my player box, so it really helps me to play, and it releases the tension on the court,'' said Jankovic, who referred to herself and her entourage as clowns, because they are so giddy when they are together.</p>
        <p>Later, Jankovic wondered why so many players looked solemn during their matches. ''Why go to the court like you are going to a cemetery?'' she said, grinning wide. ''It doesn't make any sense to me.''</p>
        <p>For Williams, there was not much reason to smile. With her wrists taped, she remained stoic throughout the match, although she shrieked several times when her shots flew wide or long.</p>
        <p>Her stinging first serve, which reached a Grand Slam-record 128 miles an hour earlier this week, did not rattle Jankovic. Neither did her powerful shots that landed in nearly every spot on the court.</p>
        <p>With grace and ease, Jankovic returned those shots, skillfully -- and joyfully -- hitting on the lines or into the corners. Without much resistance from Williams, Jankovic won the first set. Williams recovered, taking a 3-0 lead in the second set before winning it, 6-4.</p>
        <p>The third set flew by for Williams, who was worn down by long rallies and Jankovic's ability to stay peppy on the clay. Jankovic broke her serve three times. Williams double-faulted twice. Her shots, particularly her forehands, often floated long. She hit a backhand into the net to end the match.</p>
        <p>''I'm disappointed that I lost, but I feel like I'm playing well,'' Williams said. ''I think I just got a little bit tired at the end, too. It's tough on clay.''</p>
        <p>Williams, who turns 27 this month, had played the 22-year-old Jankovic four times before. Jankovic now has a 3-2 edge, having won their past three matches.</p>
        <p>In April, Jankovic beat Williams in the semifinals of the clay-court event in Charleston, S.C. Jankovic also eliminated Williams in the third round at Wimbledon last year, preventing Williams from successfully defending her title.</p>
        <p>Williams said that those previous losses did not affect the way she played Friday.</p>
        <p>Considering how much tennis she has missed in the past year because of wrist problems, Williams said that she was happy with how she played at Roland Garros. Her father, Richard Williams, said he thought she looked intimidated.</p>
        <p>''Venus played with fear because she lost to that girl a couple of times now,'' he said, shaking his head. ''I've never ever seen her play like that before. She has never been that scared of hitting the ball.</p>
        <p>''If I was her and I kept playing like that, I would just quit. I'd just retire.''</p>
        <p>Zina Garrison, Venus Williams's coach on the United States Fed Cup team, said she thought Williams looked strong, but that she lacked the energy to keep up with Jankovic. Williams lost a few pounds recently, Garrison said, and that may have weakened her.</p>
        <p>Garrison seemed impressed with every part of Jankovic's game, saying, ''It's been a long time since I've seen anyone who moves as easily as her.''</p>
        <p>It has also been a long time since there has been a player as bubbly as Jankovic, whose upbeat attitude seems irrepressible. Her mother, Snezana, takes credit for that.</p>
        <p>Snezana Jankovic, an economist in Belgrade, Serbia's capital, said she made a point of reminding Jelena to stay happy.</p>
        <p>She added: ''I tell her, 'Don't ever cry about tennis because I don't want to see your tears. When you cry, it hurts me, too. If you lose, just stay happy and forget it. If you are good enough, the results will come.' ''</p>
        <p>NOTES</p>
        <p>Both No. 1 seeds won matches Friday to reach the fourth round. Roger Federer, the world's No. 1, beat Potito Starace without breaking a sweat, 6-2, 6-3, 6-0. Justine Henin, the two-time defending French Open champion, only looked as if she had broken a sweat because it rained during her match. On her 25th birthday, Henin defeated Mara Santangelo, 6-2, 6-3, while fighting through stomach cramps. ''No, it was nothing to do with my being 25, although I'm aging, that's true,'' she said. She said that the cramps were probably a result of stress as she waited for her match to begin.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
