<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dazzling Display Takes Everything Out of James</title>
    <meta content="02cavs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/sports/basketball/02cavs.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851514"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Detroit Pistons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Cleveland Cavaliers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Detroit Pistons</org>
        <person class="online_producer">James, LeBron</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E5DE1030F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dazzling Display Takes Everything Out of James</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dazzling Display Takes Everything Out of James</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <dateline>CLEVELAND, June 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The electric night faded into a new day and a new month, and LeBron James looked like he had been snapped out of a dream. He was as dazed as the next person inside the Palace of Auburn Hills.</p>
        <p>In the final quarter and two overtimes of Game 5 of the Eastern Conference finals Thursday night, James defied the Detroit Pistons, the laws of probability and, at times, gravity as well. James scored 25 consecutive points and 29 of his team's last 30, using his entire arsenal -- driving, twisting layups, fadeaway jumpers, off-balance 3-pointers, free throws and dunks -- that gave the Cavaliers a 109-107 victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the moments after his winning layup carved through the heart of Detroit’s defense, LeBron James said he felt emotionally and physically depleted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The electric night faded into a new day and a new month, and LeBron James looked like he had been snapped out of a dream. He was as dazed as the next person inside the Palace of Auburn Hills.</p>
        <p>In the final quarter and two overtimes of Game 5 of the Eastern Conference finals Thursday night, James defied the Detroit Pistons, the laws of probability and, at times, gravity as well. James scored 25 consecutive points and 29 of his team's last 30, using his entire arsenal -- driving, twisting layups, fadeaway jumpers, off-balance 3-pointers, free throws and dunks -- that gave the Cavaliers a 109-107 victory.</p>
        <p>With a victory in Game 6 here on Saturday, the Cavaliers could advance to the N.B.A. finals for the first time in franchise history.</p>
        <p>James scored a career-playoff-high 48 points -- the most of any player in this postseason -- but the 50 minutes and 18 seconds he played took their toll. James needed intravenous fluids on the charter back to Cleveland, his coach, Mike Brown, said Friday, as a precaution to prevent dehydration and cramping.</p>
        <p>In the moments after his winning layup carved through the heart of the matador Pistons defense, James described just how emotionally and physically depleted he was.</p>
        <p>''During the course of the game, you're all the way here,'' James said, raising his arm above his 6-foot-8 frame in a quiet moment in a hallway of the Palace.</p>
        <p>''It seems like when the buzzer ends, you ever see the Demon Drop? The roller coaster? You're all the way up here during the game, as soon as the buzzer sounds, it's just woooh,'' he said, dropping his arm to his waist and shaking his head. ''Nothing left.''</p>
        <p>The Demon Drop, a ride at Cedar Point amusement park in Sandusky, Ohio, takes riders up 10 stories and drops them in a simulated free fall.</p>
        <p>Will the 22-year-old James be able to recover in time for Saturday?</p>
        <p>''With him being as young as he is, as strong as he is, physically and mentally, he should be ready to go tomorrow night,'' Brown said on a teleconference with reporters Friday. He had given the team the day off and said he had not talked with James.</p>
        <p>Brown's mind, however, was racing. ''I'm still in awe of James's performance last night,'' he said.</p>
        <p>James said after the game that he planned to send his 2 1/2-year-old son, LeBron Jr., to a grandmother's house, so James could decompress and prepare for the next biggest game of his life.</p>
        <p>Since Game 3 (''the biggest game of my life''), James has led the Cavaliers to three consecutive victories. ''This is definitely one of the biggest wins in Cavaliers' franchise history, for me and my teammates,'' James said Thursday. ''But we have a goal. We can't dwell on this when we have another game on Saturday.''</p>
        <p>The Pistons, however, share that goal. The mood in their locker room was surprisingly upbeat. Rasheed Wallace's music was blasting from the speakers, and Chauncey Billups spoke quietly, smiling, and seemed strangely confident.</p>
        <p>''We've seen this before -- 12 months ago,'' Billups said.</p>
        <p>The Cavaliers had also beaten the Pistons three consecutive games in last season's conference semifinals and had a chance to close out the series on their home court. The Pistons won the next two.</p>
        <p>Having made the conference finals the past five seasons, the Pistons are not ready to abdicate the throne to James. ''The series just got harder for us, but we've been in these waters before,'' Billups said. ''We can handle ourselves in these situations.''</p>
        <p>And yet this situation may seem more familiar for another group of Pistons -- those of Joe Dumars and Isiah Thomas.</p>
        <p>It took Michael Jordan four playoff series against the two-time champion Pistons before he could vanquish his rivals in 1991 and advance to win his first of six titles with the Bulls. Jordan was 28 then.</p>
        <p>For as complimentary as James is of his teammates, he simply does not yet have the same complementary players as Jordan had.</p>
        <p>''We don't expect him to have to carry us like that all the time,'' Brown said Friday. ''We have other guys who are capable of making plays. When nobody else can, that's when he comes to the rescue. It's not something we're going to carry into the next game hoping he continues to save us throughout the playoff run.''</p>
        <p>At one point during James's personal run, which began with 6:05 left in regulation, Brown said he asked James if he wanted a play run for Zydrunas Ilgauskas to lighten his load.</p>
        <p>James shot Brown a look, one that Brown said he interpreted as confidence, and told Brown he wanted the basketball. Drew Gooden was the only other Cavalier to score during that run, on a free throw with 2:49 left in regulation.</p>
        <p>Gooden fouled out early in the first overtime and said it felt as if he were watching James take over a video game. ''I guess that is why he has a new nickname and that would be Video Game James,'' Gooden said.</p>
        <p>Brown says he expects the Pistons to make changes, to double- and triple-team James, swarming him from the moment he catches the ball. That will put even more pressure on Cleveland's role players.</p>
        <p>Eric Snow, the veteran guard, came off the bench cold at the end of the fourth quarter and had two crucial steals for Cleveland. Anderson Varejao drove hard to the basket in the first quarter before Antonio McDyess raked him across his shoulders, earning a flagrant foul and an immediate ejection.</p>
        <p>The Pistons lost their most consistent reserve and physical inside presence. At the end of the game, when James was gallivanting through the lane for easy layups, the absence of McDyess cost the Pistons most.</p>
        <p>The league did not suspend McDyess after reviewing the flagrant foul Friday, so he will return the Pistons to full strength.</p>
        <p>Will James be that way, too?</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
