<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ready To Fly Again</title>
    <meta content="02interview" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/business/02interview.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851442"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SATURDAY INTERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Northwest Airlines</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Steenland, Douglas M</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E7D61330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="742" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ready To Fly Again</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ready to Fly Again</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF BAILEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bailey, Jeff</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Douglas M. Steenland, chief executive of Northwest Airlines, steered his carrier out of bankruptcy protection this week after nearly 20 months of haggling with creditors and workers to reduce annual costs by about $2.4 billion.</p>
        <p>Northwest became the last of the big airlines -- following US Airways, United Airlines and Delta Air Lines -- to finish off its post-Sept. 11 court-supervised restructuring. The industry is vastly changed: smaller in number of airplanes; far less generous in paying its workers and retirees; and operating on a new hurry-up basis with fewer employees and less time between flights for planes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Douglas M. Steenland, chief executive of Northwest Airlines, took a quick detour by Federal Bankruptcy Court for one last look and then answered some questions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Douglas M. Steenland, chief executive of Northwest Airlines, steered his carrier out of bankruptcy protection this week after nearly 20 months of haggling with creditors and workers to reduce annual costs by about $2.4 billion.</p>
        <p>Northwest became the last of the big airlines -- following US Airways, United Airlines and Delta Air Lines -- to finish off its post-Sept. 11 court-supervised restructuring. The industry is vastly changed: smaller in number of airplanes; far less generous in paying its workers and retirees; and operating on a new hurry-up basis with fewer employees and less time between flights for planes.</p>
        <p>All of that, and a stock package for Mr. Steenland valued at more than $25 million, has made many Northwest workers angry. Flight attendants passed a contract by a mere 51 percent to 49 percent last week, even though failing to do so would have cost most of them a payout of $14,500 each related to the bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Steenland, 55, rang the opening bell on the New York Stock Exchange on Thursday morning to celebrate the beginning of trading in new Northwest shares, took a quick detour by Federal Bankruptcy Court in downtown Manhattan for one last look and then answered some questions. Following are excerpts:</p>
        <p>Q. Given how angry workers across the airline industry are about chief executive pay packages, why did you take such a big one?</p>
        <p>A. The compensation process is not one I play a role in. The decisions were made by the Northwest board of directors, acting completely independently of management.</p>
        <p>Q. But you could have insisted on less, just as you took reduced pay during the bankruptcy, right?</p>
        <p>A. If you look at things on a relative basis, in 2006 compared to the other network C.E.O.'s, I was fifth out of six. Among Fortune 500 C.E.O.'s, I'm in the lower 50 percent.</p>
        <p>Q. Workers are maddest, of course, about their own reduced paychecks. Should their compensation be more tied to stock price, as yours is?</p>
        <p>A. A fair subject for discussion is the structure of how airline employees get compensated and how much should be variable. Unions have shied away from variable compensation: equity ownership or profit sharing. They have preferred the less-risky approach.</p>
        <p>Given the volatility this industry has always had, when downturns come the focus becomes the overall costs. And the more compensation that is fixed, the more it becomes a focus.</p>
        <p>Q. Given the pain and hard feelings from bankruptcy, would airlines be better off with new management after one of these?</p>
        <p>A. Every board has the choice to do that. I don't think there's any general rule one way or another. The Northwest team did a good job. Northwest is secure. It's going to be profitable for a long time. People don't have to go home and worry, ''Is my job safe? Am I going to lose my pension?''</p>
        <p>Q. What about a possible merger?</p>
        <p>A. There has been airline consolidation discussion for the last 10 years. There are in fact economic benefits. But the difficulty of combining two airlines and preserving the value -- there's a lot of stories out there about combinations that didn't go well.</p>
        <p>Q. Are you in merger talks now?</p>
        <p>A. No.</p>
        <p>Q. Planes are crowded and Northwest's are among the most crowded in the industry. Is there any relief in sight for cramped economy-section passengers?</p>
        <p>A. Internationally, our A-330s come with full video in economy. Boeing 787s will come with full video in economy. For the rest of economy, there's the core product of be-on-time, be-courteous. But a lot of these decisions are price-based. One of the success stories is how affordable air travel has become.</p>
        <p>Q. How about a little extra legroom?</p>
        <p>A. That experiment was run by American Airlines. They completely reconfigured their airplanes. At the end of the day, the assessment was by and large the traveling public was not willing to pay extra for that.</p>
        <p>Q. How vulnerable is Northwest to the next economic downturn?</p>
        <p>A. We built the business plan to withstand any challenge we can think of. We got $4.5 billion of debt off the balance sheet. We're going to emerge with over $3 billion of cash. Among network airlines we're the lowest-cost provider. We also built our plan around realistic fuel prices. We think we're in a great position.</p>
        <p>SATURDAY INTERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
