<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Team New Zealand Takes An Early Lead and Protects It</title>
    <meta content="02sailing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/02/sports/othersports/02sailing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851452"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SAILING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">America's Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sailboats and Sailing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sailboats and Sailing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">America's Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Oracle Corp</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Vuitton, Louis</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E5D61330F931A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Team New Zealand Takes An Early Lead and Protects It</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Team New Zealand Takes an Early Lead and Protects It</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <dateline>VALENCIA, Spain, June 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was the first day of the Louis Vuitton Cup finals between Emirates Team New Zealand and Luna Rossa Challenge, and it must have been close to what America's Cup officials had in their collective mind's eye when they decided to take Valencia's millions and word and bring sailing's premier regatta here.</p>
        <p>Floating just off shore in the sunshine, with the long stretch of beach (and the ever-present construction cranes) in view, was a sizable spectator fleet. Blowing at them was the double-digit sea breeze that was one of Valencia's selling points but was sorely missed in the early stages of this competition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Kiwis clung pugnaciously and cleverly to the favored right side of the course and the slight lead they earned on the opening leg of the Louis Vuitton Cup finals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was the first day of the Louis Vuitton Cup finals between Emirates Team New Zealand and Luna Rossa Challenge, and it must have been close to what America's Cup officials had in their collective mind's eye when they decided to take Valencia's millions and word and bring sailing's premier regatta here.</p>
        <p>Floating just off shore in the sunshine, with the long stretch of beach (and the ever-present construction cranes) in view, was a sizable spectator fleet. Blowing at them was the double-digit sea breeze that was one of Valencia's selling points but was sorely missed in the early stages of this competition.</p>
        <p>Most reassuring, there were two yachts jousting at spitting range from prestart to finish, providing the sort of close-quarter sailing that was the goal when the Cup organizers decided to narrow the design window and develop a series of lead-up races for this mature class of yachts.</p>
        <p>All that was missing Friday was the passing, but that was more a tribute to Team New Zealand than a criticism of the rules of engagement. There does not appear to be much between the two finalists in terms of boat speed or broad-brush issues. But the Kiwis got the finer points and the weather calls quite right, and they clung pugnaciously and cleverly to the favored right side of the course and the slight lead they earned on the opening leg.</p>
        <p>Their victory came by less than a boat length and it earned them a rumble of applause from the decks of the spectator boats and a 1-0 lead in this best-of-nine series that will determine which boat will face the defending champion, Alinghi, for the America's Cup.</p>
        <p>''I think we sailed a good regatta today, but they sailed a better one,'' said Luna Rossa's tactician, Torben Grael, looking glum.</p>
        <p>After last month's semifinals, it seemed strange to see Luna Rossa in a trailing position. In their upset of the American challenger BMW Oracle Racing, the Italians rounded every mark first, often gambling by splitting far from the opposition and getting the benefit.</p>
        <p>But this time, Grael and Luna Rossa played it more conservatively in the shifty conditions and trailed at every stage, if only by small margins. In a prestart that was lacking in fireworks but not in significance, Luna Rossa's young Australian helmsman, James Spithill, maneuvered well, seemingly content to let the Kiwis and their skipper, Dean Barker, take the right side of the course. But that was just the briar patch the New Zealanders said they wanted for the upwind leg, which is known as the beat.</p>
        <p>''It was one of those races where every meter counted,'' said Grant Dalton, the head of Team New Zealand.</p>
        <p>''We got the bow in front early on the first beat, and in the end, there were no passing lanes.''</p>
        <p>The wind ended up favoring the right slightly more than the Kiwis expected, and with most of the first leg exceedingly tight, they rounded the top mark with a 12-second advantage, which turned out to be their biggest lead of the afternoon.</p>
        <p>The gap was 9 seconds at the gate; 11 seconds after a tack-filled second upwind leg; and, ultimately, only 8 seconds as the Kiwis held on during an edgy final downwind leg in which their spinnaker often appeared to be at less than full stretch.</p>
        <p>''It was pretty dangerous most of the way around,'' said Ray Davies, Team New Zealand's strategist.</p>
        <p>''I don't think there was any point we felt comfortable. We had to defend pretty hard.''</p>
        <p>Not that they were doing cartwheels when the race ended. Team New Zealand is a restrained lot, full of the gravitas that goes with having a mission, not just a goal.</p>
        <p>In this case the team's goal grew from a 5-0 thumping by Alinghi in the last America's Cup, in 2003 in front of their home fans in Auckland.</p>
        <p>The mission is to win the Auld Mug back, and while Alinghi and most of the challengers are cosmopolitan teams with a thick mix of nationalities on board, Team New Zealand has remained truer to its origins. Its 17-man crew on Friday was composed of 15 New Zealanders and two Americans: the tactician Terry Hutchinson and the navigator Kevin Hall.</p>
        <p>''That's a fundamental key or point about our whole team, that we are quite nationalistic in the way we think and certainly in the way we go about our business,'' said Dalton, who sets the tone by doing unglamorous work in the hold on the racing team. ''And if we weren't nationalistic, we never would have managed to gather the support from all our suppliers that adds up to many, many millions.''</p>
        <p>Having many, many millions of dollars remains vital to any credible bid for the America's Cup, but the biggest budget does not guarantee the prize or even a spot in the challenger final, as BMW Oracle proved by faltering against Luna Rossa. One notable absence from the spectator fleet Friday was Rising Sun, the massive white yacht of the Oracle syndicate head Larry Ellison, which no longer looms over the coastline and proceedings.</p>
        <p>It is up to Team New Zealand and Luna Rossa to carry the event forward now, and Friday was a fine, upbeat start, if only a start.</p>
        <p>''What we learned,'' Dalton said, ''is that we will have another tough day tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>SAILING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
