<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Haitian Teammates Turn Up After a Detour</title>
    <meta content="15haiti" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/nyregion/15haiti.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854645"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Haiti</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE2DC153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="687" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Haitian Teammates Turn Up After a Detour</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Haitian Teammates Turn Up After a Detour</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DALTON WALKER and LAURA RIVERA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two days after 13 members of the Haitian national junior soccer team disappeared during a stopover at Kennedy International Airport, all but one had returned voluntarily, a Haitian diplomat said last night. The last boy was being held by the police and was waiting to be picked up, the diplomat said, but did not disclose the location.</p>
        <p>The diplomat, Felix Augustin, the Haitian consul general in New York, spoke at a hotel near the airport, alongside members of the team and their coaches.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two days after 13 members of the Haitian national junior soccer team disappeared during a stopover in New York, all but one had returned voluntarily.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two days after 13 members of the Haitian national junior soccer team disappeared during a stopover at Kennedy International Airport, all but one had returned voluntarily, a Haitian diplomat said last night. The last boy was being held by the police and was waiting to be picked up, the diplomat said, but did not disclose the location.</p>
        <p>The diplomat, Felix Augustin, the Haitian consul general in New York, spoke at a hotel near the airport, alongside members of the team and their coaches.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the day, Mr. Augustin blamed ''outsiders'' for the boys' disappearance, and suggested that the players' friends and relatives in the United States had been involved.</p>
        <p>Officials had said two of the players had gone to Boston, and the rest were in New York City.</p>
        <p>Mr. Augustin said it was unclear why the players, all under 17, had walked off, and rejected suggestions that they would abandon their team for a new life in the United States.</p>
        <p>''They are all well-to-do youngsters, but when they listened to the news reports, they found out they were misguided and they called their families and then they got back safely,'' he said last night.</p>
        <p>One player, Aian Atiye, said team members were excited about continuing their trip and competing in South Korea. ''We are happy to be here, and we are looking forward to playing,'' he said, before leaving with his team for the airport.</p>
        <p>A growing number of Haitians have been trying this year to flee their country, the poorest in the Western Hemisphere, to come to the United States.</p>
        <p>The 13 boys, part of a team of 18, disappeared on Tuesday evening during a trip to an airport McDonald's with their teammates and coaches, slipping outside and into a waiting van, Mr. Augustin said. He said he did not know who had provided the van, but suggested that family members had orchestrated a plan to whisk the boys away, and had manipulated them into participating.</p>
        <p>Pasquale DiFulco, a spokesman for Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, which operates the airport, said it was investigating the incident, but had no indication that any laws had been violated.</p>
        <p>Jean Robert Vilbrun, a family friend of a player who had not fled with the others, said two of the boys had told their coaches that they had gotten lost in the airport. Mr. Vilbrun said one player had told him that the two had encouraged others to leave.</p>
        <p>The disappearance of the boys was ''a shock for everyone,'' said Mr. Vilbrun, 49, a limousine driver from Queens, adding: ''They are a wealthy group. They have no reason to leave Haiti; they travel all the time.''</p>
        <p>The team had been at Kennedy awaiting a flight to South Korea on Wednesday to prepare for the FIFA Under-17 World Cup this summer. The invitation to compete in the tournament this year was the first for Haiti's national youth soccer team.</p>
        <p>Ricot Dupuy, the station manager of Radio Soleil, a Haitian radio station in Brooklyn, said the boys' disappearance was ''the talk of the town'' in the borough's Haitian enclaves.</p>
        <p>''This is one of the worst things that could have happened,'' Mr. Dupuy said. ''We Haitians live for soccer. It's one of the only things that we are proud of.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''The general feeling is that parents may be involved somehow. The parents may not have fully appreciated the ramifications of defecting to the U.S.''</p>
        <p>At the Impeccable barbershop on Nostrand Avenue in Flatbush, where many Haitian immigrants live, Joseph Deorna, 51, criticized the runaway players as he clipped hair.</p>
        <p>''It's not right for the country; it's not right for the team,'' he said. ''The players have promised to return Haiti to its former glory from the 1970s. What they did yesterday, they broke that promise.''</p>
        <p>His customer, Ozias Antoine, echoed Mr. Deorna.</p>
        <p>''It's disappointing,'' said Mr. Antoine, 48. ''They're representing our flag, our country. Whoever tried to get them to do it, it's illegal and it's not right.'' The team was scheduled to fly to South Korea at 11:45 last night.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
