<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES: June 15 - June 21; 'IT'S A BEE, HONEY'</title>
    <meta content="15bkids" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854508"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E2D6143FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="401" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES: June 15 - June 21; 'IT'S A BEE, HONEY'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAUREL GRAEBER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Their lives are filled with drama: a ruthless hierarchy, slavish devotion to one boss, brutality and intense competition, even murder. Yet they're also a devoted family. And their secrets will be revealed on Sunday on television screens.</p>
        <p>No, ''The Sopranos'' hasn't been extended. These characters are bees, the TV screens are empty frames, and the show is for children. Titled ''It's a Bee, Honey,'' it will unfold in the sculpture garden of the Abrons Arts Center, with puppets portraying the insects.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Their lives are filled with drama: a ruthless hierarchy, slavish devotion to one boss, brutality and intense competition, even murder. Yet they're also a devoted family. And their secrets will be revealed on Sunday on television screens.</p>
        <p>No, ''The Sopranos'' hasn't been extended. These characters are bees, the TV screens are empty frames, and the show is for children. Titled ''It's a Bee, Honey,'' it will unfold in the sculpture garden of the Abrons Arts Center, with puppets portraying the insects.</p>
        <p>''The kids' puppets are about the size of a Nerf ball,'' said Erin Orr, who will hold a puppet-making workshop tomorrow at the center for 5- to 10-year-olds who would like to star as the show's worker bees. ''The drones are larger -- about a foot long -- and the queen is about two feet long and has a tail made out of a Chinese lantern.''</p>
        <p>Although the workshop is limited to 30, the garden has plenty of space for the play, which will call on parents to hold giant flower puppets. (They're made of Chinese umbrellas.) Ms. Orr, the puppets' designer, collaborated on the script with the performer known as Baby Dee, who conceived the show and composed its music. Silvi Wool, Ms. Orr's sister, also takes part, along with Rima Fand, who plays the violin while Baby Dee plays accordion and harp.</p>
        <p>The show proceeds as a combination nature documentary and sports event. Consider the drones' race to mate with the queen: The ''athletes'' are interviewed by sportscasters. Then Baby Dee, dressed in a bee costume and carrying the queen (above), sets out on a giant tricycle, with the drones, held aloft by Ms. Orr and Ms. Wool, in hot pursuit. Of course the winner also loses; the mating drone dies.</p>
        <p>''We don't go into the gory details,'' Ms. Orr said. ''But we do lay him down. We're going to give him a tie, and maybe sing a song, since it will be Father's Day.''</p>
        <p>The show also presents other quirks of bee life, like the figure-eight dance (it communicates the location of flowers) and the bees' form of air-conditioning (beating their wings to cool the hive). ''They're amazing,'' Ms. Orr said. ''Totally amazing.'' (Workshop, tomorrow from 10 a.m. to 2 p.m., and performance, Sunday at 3 p.m., rain or shine, at 466 Grand Street, at Pitt Street, Lower East Side. Free. Reservations requested: abronsartscenter.org.)</p>
        <p>LAUREL GRAEBER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
