<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MySpace Mini-Episodes, Courtesy of Honda</title>
    <meta content="15adco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/business/media/15adco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sony Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Honda Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Myspace.com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">MySpace.com</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Honda Motor Company Limited</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE1DE153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="880" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MySpace Mini-Episodes, Courtesy of Honda</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">MySpace Mini-Episodes, Courtesy of Honda</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART ELLIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Honda Motor will be sole sponsor of what Sony Pictures Television is calling Minisode Network, which is scheduled to begin next week; visitors to MySpace Web site will be able to watch episodes of 15 vintage Sony series, edited from their original lengths of 30 or 60 minutes each to Internet-friendly 4 to 6 minutes; Honda and its agency RPA have agreed to run only eight seconds of commercials with each episode; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YEARS after Volkswagen challenged drivers to ''Think small,'' another automaker, Honda, plans to run smaller commercials for a smaller car in smaller versions of television series.</p>
        <p>Honda will be the sole sponsor of what Sony Pictures Television is calling the Minisode Network, which is scheduled to begin next week. Visitors to the MySpace Web site (myspace.com) will be able to watch episodes of 15 vintage Sony series like ''Charlie's Angels,'' ''The Facts of Life,'' ''Fantasy Island'' and ''Who's the Boss,'' edited from their original lengths of 30 or 60 minutes each to an Internet-friendly 4 to 6 minutes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Honda plans to run smaller commercials for a smaller car in smaller versions of television series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YEARS after Volkswagen challenged drivers to ''Think small,'' another automaker, Honda, plans to run smaller commercials for a smaller car in smaller versions of television series.</p>
        <p>Honda will be the sole sponsor of what Sony Pictures Television is calling the Minisode Network, which is scheduled to begin next week. Visitors to the MySpace Web site (myspace.com) will be able to watch episodes of 15 vintage Sony series like ''Charlie's Angels,'' ''The Facts of Life,'' ''Fantasy Island'' and ''Who's the Boss,'' edited from their original lengths of 30 or 60 minutes each to an Internet-friendly 4 to 6 minutes.</p>
        <p>To mirror the pared-down programming, Honda and its longtime agency, RPA, have agreed to run only eight seconds of commercials with each episode, appearing before the shortened show starts.</p>
        <p>First, there will be an onscreen billboard lasting three seconds, declaring, ''The Minisode Network, brought to you by Honda.'' The billboard will be followed by a five-second commercial for the Honda Fit, the minicar that American Honda introduced last year, and its Web site (fit.honda.com).</p>
        <p>''Minisodes are right up the Fit's alley, so to speak,'' said Tom Peyton, senior manager for advertising at the American Honda Motor Company in Torrance, Calif., which is part of Honda Motor of Japan.</p>
        <p>The sponsorship, estimated in six figures, is indicative of the intensifying interest in online video among marketers. As broadband penetration increases, making it easier to watch video clips online, online video is becoming a significant advertising medium.</p>
        <p>''As the Net becomes its own media channel, we continue to look for the right opportunities to access consumers and the right media formats,'' Mr. Peyton said.</p>
        <p>Shortening TV series to lengths more appropriate for watching on a PC ''is a very innovative use of existing content,'' he added, ''and it's another way to leverage MySpace,'' the social networking Web site owned by the News Corporation.</p>
        <p>The minisodes will appear exclusively on MySpace through the end of August. Initially, there will be three episodes of each series, with new episodes to be added each week. Sony Pictures Television announced the idea in April, describing it as a way to repurpose for the new media programming that was originally produced for the traditional media.</p>
        <p>Other series that will be boiled down for minisodes include ''Diff'rent Strokes,'' ''The Partridge Family,'' ''Police Woman,'' ''Silver Spoons'' and ''What's Happening!!''</p>
        <p>The minisodes are not intended as pastiches or excerpts; they are edited carefully so the plots can be followed from beginning to end. (It helps that many of the series are formulaic sitcoms or police dramas.)</p>
        <p>The concept is comparable to the Condensed Books once sold by Reader's Digest, which promised to provide readers with the essence of the original, longer versions.</p>
        <p>''The new forms of media make lots of things possible,'' said Amy Carney, president for advertiser sales at Sony Pictures Television in New York, part of the Sony Corporation of America division of the Sony Corporation of Japan.</p>
        <p>For those who watched the full-length episodes of the series, ''you'll feel like your life is flashing before your eyes,'' she added, laughing.</p>
        <p>After the exclusivity with MySpace ends, Ms. Carney said, the goal is for the minisodes to come to other Web sites while remaining on myspace.com. Sony Pictures Television is looking at sites like aol.com, yahoo.com and youtube.com, she added, as well as posting them on a microsite, a special site of their own.</p>
        <p>Plans call for the contents of the Minisode Network to eventually be available on mobile devices like cellphones, Ms. Carney said.</p>
        <p>''As we roll out the minisodes to other distribution platforms,'' she added, Honda ''has the right of first refusal'' on sponsorship.</p>
        <p>Lauren Mehl, associate media director at RPA in Santa Monica, Calif., said the agency would evaluate the subsequent sponsorship opportunities based on how the commercials perform their run onMySpace.</p>
        <p>The five-second Fit commercials that will appear before each episode are among several produced last year by RPA to herald the car's arrival in the United States. Fit is a member of a class of smaller imports that also includes the Nissan Versa and the Toyota Yaris.</p>
        <p>Honda said it sold 27,934 Fits from its introduction in spring 2006 through the end of the year. Through the first five months of 2007, sales totaled 18,156.</p>
        <p>''We're working on additional supply and expanding the car in the U.S.,'' Mr. Peyton said.</p>
        <p>Fit and minisodes are among examples of a trend that is gaining favor on Madison Avenue to reprise ''Think small,'' which was created almost five decades ago for Volkswagen by the old Doyle Dane Bernbach agency.</p>
        <p>For example, the CW network, owned by CBS and Time Warner, plans to sell five-second commercials during the 2007-8 season that starts in September. Unilever makes a concentrated version of its All detergent, named All Small and Mighty, which comes in a smaller bottle.</p>
        <p>And the July issue of Cosmopolitan, published by the Hearst Magazines division of the Hearst Corporation, carries a tiny brochure for the O. B. line of feminine hygiene products sold by the McNeil-P.P.C. unit of Johnson &amp; Johnson.</p>
        <p>The minibooklet, ''The Book of Mighty Small,'' urges women to ''discover how little can be big'' and promotes a Web site, mightysmall.com.</p>
        <p>That would have made a nice Web address for the Minisode Network.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
