<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Winners Of Big Three May Meet In Travers</title>
    <meta content="15racing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/sports/15racing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854590"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Street Sense (Race Horse)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DD153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="646" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Winners Of Big Three May Meet In Travers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Winners of Series May Meet in Travers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a thrilling Triple Crown series, the Kentucky Derby winner Street Sense, the Preakness winner Curlin and the Belmont heroine Rags to Riches will soon begin to gear up for summer campaigns that could, for all three, include a stop in Saratoga for the Travers Stakes on Aug. 25.</p>
        <p>There are no certainties that the race just about everyone wants to see -- a meeting of the three winners of this year's Triple Crown races -- will occur in the Travers, but the trainers of the three horses listed the race as a possible goal for their horses yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a thrilling Triple Crown series, the winners of the Kentucky Derby, the Preakness and the Belmont may race in Saratoga on August 25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a thrilling Triple Crown series, the Kentucky Derby winner Street Sense, the Preakness winner Curlin and the Belmont heroine Rags to Riches will soon begin to gear up for summer campaigns that could, for all three, include a stop in Saratoga for the Travers Stakes on Aug. 25.</p>
        <p>There are no certainties that the race just about everyone wants to see -- a meeting of the three winners of this year's Triple Crown races -- will occur in the Travers, but the trainers of the three horses listed the race as a possible goal for their horses yesterday.</p>
        <p>All three horses are scheduled to have one race before the Travers, and there is a strong possibility that Curlin and Street Sense, who finished a head apart in the Preakness, will renew their rivalry in the Haskell at Monmouth Park in New Jersey on Aug. 5.</p>
        <p>Steve Asmussen, Curlin's trainer, confirmed yesterday that his horse would make his next start in the $1 million Haskell.</p>
        <p>With the Breeders' Cup set to be run in October at Monmouth, Asmussen is one of many horsemen eager to have his top horses race on the track beforehand.</p>
        <p>''The Haskell is our target,'' Asmussen said. ''With the Breeders' Cup Classic being run there this year, this gives us a race against straight 3-year-olds to get an idea of how things might go when we go back there. Curlin went back to the track Wednesday morning and did amazingly well. He's a true throwback.''</p>
        <p>Asmussen would not commit to a race beyond the Haskell, but most horses that do well in the Haskell return in the Travers.</p>
        <p>Carl Nafzger, the trainer of Street Sense, said that the Travers is the primary goal this summer for Street Sense and that his colt would prep for that race in either the Haskell or the Jim Dandy at Saratoga on July 29. Nafzger also said the fact that the Breeders' Cup will be run at Monmouth would factor into his decision.</p>
        <p>Monmouth Park's general manager, Bob Kulina, said this week: ''We've been talking to Carl and think we have an excellent chance of getting Street Sense for the Haskell. The race-over-the-track angle is definitely working in our favor.''</p>
        <p>Todd Pletcher, the trainer of Rags to Riches, confirmed yesterday that his filly would not run in the Haskell. She is scheduled to race next on July 21 in the Coaching Club American Oaks at Belmont, a race for fillies. Pletcher said Rags to Riches' next race after the Oaks would either be in the Travers or against fillies on Aug. 18 in the Alabama at Saratoga.</p>
        <p>''Right now, it's 50-50 between the Alabama and the Travers,'' Pletcher said. ''We'll try to get a sense of how she is doing and we'll see how tough the Travers comes up. Obviously, there are some very good colts out there.</p>
        <p>''The equalizing factor in the Belmont was the mile-and-a-half, which was an advantage for us. The Travers is only a mile-and-a-quarter, so the pendulum will swing back in favor of the colts.''</p>
        <p>The plans for Hard Spun, who was second in the Derby, third in the Preakness and fourth in the Belmont, also remain up in the air. Hard Spun's owner, Rick Porter, said the colt's options include the Haskell and the King's Bishop, a seven-furlong race at Saratoga.</p>
        <p>Trained by Larry Jones, Hard Spun may also be reunited with jockey Mario Pino, who was fired after the Preakness and replaced by Garrett Gomez.</p>
        <p>Gomez, who chose to wrangle the speedy Hard Spun off the pace in the Belmont, has been widely criticized for that ride.</p>
        <p>''I'll leave the jockey decision up to Larry, but from what he's been saying, I think there's a strong chance he'll elect to go back to Mario,'' Porter said. Reached yesterday at Delaware Park, Jones declined to address the jockey issue.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
