<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Forensic Experts Testify That 4 Iraqis Killed by Marines Were Shot From a Few Feet Away</title>
    <meta content="15haditha" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/world/middleeast/15haditha.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854691"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Camp Pendleton (Calif)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts-Martial</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Haditha (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Von Zielbauer, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharratt, Justin L (Lance Cpl)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wuterich, Frank (Staff Sgt)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Military Personnel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts-Martial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Personnel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Haditha (Iraq)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E4DB153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="698" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Forensic Experts Testify That 4 Iraqis Killed by Marines Were Shot From a Few Feet Away</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Forensic Experts Testify That 4 Iraqis Killed by Marines Were Shot From a Few Feet Away</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL von ZIELBAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Von Zielbauer, Paul</byline>
      <dateline>CAMP PENDLETON, Calif., June 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Government forensic experts testify at military hearing at Camp Pendleton that four Iraqi men killed by marines in Haditha in 2005 apparently were shot in head from at least few feet away; this undercuts prosecutors' argument that men were 'executed' by two Marine infantrymen; but one expert who claimed evidence contradicts one marine's account of shooting later concedes that evidence could support marines' account of acting in self defense; hearing is being conducted to determine whether there is enough evidence to refer charges to court-martial for one of marines, Lance Cpl Justin L Sharratt, who is accused of killing three of men; similar hearing for Staff Sgt Frank Wuterich will begin this summer (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Government forensic experts testified at a military hearing here Thursday that four Iraqi men killed by marines in Haditha in 2005 appeared to have been shot in the head from at least a few feet away, undercutting prosecutors' argument that the men had been ''executed'' by two Marine infantrymen.</p>
        <p>But, in a sign of how forensic evidence can be open to differing interpretations, one expert conceded that the evidence could support the marines' account of acting in self-defense just minutes after he had asserted that it contradicted one marine's account of the shootings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The testimony undercuts prosecutors’ argument that the men had been “executed” by two marine infantrymen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Government forensic experts testified at a military hearing here Thursday that four Iraqi men killed by marines in Haditha in 2005 appeared to have been shot in the head from at least a few feet away, undercutting prosecutors' argument that the men had been ''executed'' by two Marine infantrymen.</p>
        <p>But, in a sign of how forensic evidence can be open to differing interpretations, one expert conceded that the evidence could support the marines' account of acting in self-defense just minutes after he had asserted that it contradicted one marine's account of the shootings.</p>
        <p>The hearing is being conducted to determine whether there is enough evidence to refer charges to a court-martial for one of the marines, Lance Cpl. Justin L. Sharratt, who is accused of killing three of the men. A similar hearing for the other infantryman, Staff Sgt. Frank Wuterich, who has attended Corporal Sharratt's hearing with his lawyer, will begin this summer.</p>
        <p>Thursday's testimony, based on an analysis of photographs of the four bodies, came from Lt. Col. Elizabeth A. Rouse, an Air Force pathologist who described the victims' fatal injuries, and from Special Agent Michael S. Maloney, a forensic consultant from the Naval Criminal Investigative Service who analyzed the room of the Haditha home where the men were killed.</p>
        <p>In sworn statements provided to The New York Times though they have not yet been made public, Corporal Sharratt said that he and Sergeant Wuterich pursued the men into the house after observing them ''turkey peeking'' at their squad's convoy from behind a wall nearby.</p>
        <p>Inside the home, Corporal Sharratt said in the statements, he saw one man near a bedroom doorway point an AK-47 at him, and shot the man in the face with his 9-millimeter pistol. As he entered the bedroom, he said, he shot a second man holding another AK-47 at waist level, from about two feet away. He then shot a third man whom he perceived as moving toward him, and a fourth man in the room, he said.</p>
        <p>''I could not tell while I was shooting if they were armed or not,'' Corporal Sharratt said in a sworn statement, dated March 19, 2006, ''but I felt threatened because the first two individuals had rifles and I assumed they had some sort of weapon.''</p>
        <p>''I believe I did not get shot by the first Iraqi because I think he had a malfunction of either his weapon or round,'' the statement continued. ''While clearing the weapons, they all had a round in their chambers and were ready to fire with what appear to be full magazines.''</p>
        <p>Corporal Sharratt said that he had fired all the bullets in his handgun and that Sergeant Wuterich, who had been behind him, had entered the room and shot five to seven rounds into the ''bodies on the ground to make sure that none were capable of grabbing a weapon and firing back at us.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Rouse said that none of the bullet wounds to the four bodies, which had all been shot in the head, appeared to come from shots fired closer than two feet away. Her testimony supported defense arguments that Corporal Sharratt had shot the men in a cramped, darkened bedroom in self-defense and not execution style.</p>
        <p>But Special Agent Maloney, in a forensic report last year, concluded from blood spatter and bullet trajectories that two Iraqi men were shot ''while crouched or sitting'' -- one against a wall, the other inside a closed closet.</p>
        <p>In his testimony here Thursday, he reasserted those conclusions under questioning by a military prosecutor. But minutes later, pressed by a lawyer for Corporal Sharratt, Special Agent Maloney conceded that it was just as possible that at least one of the men had been moving in Corporal Sharratt's general direction, or diving toward a closet that may have contained a gun, when he was fatally shot in the head.</p>
        <p>But whether the men were armed when they were shot remains an open question. The two AK-47s, which Iraqi witnesses said they saw marines carry out of the home after the shootings, were not kept in a secure locker at the nearby Marine base, and cannot be found.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
