<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Curious Time Travel Through Art History</title>
    <meta content="15rauc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/arts/design/15rauc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854525"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Metropolitan Museum of Art</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rauch, Neo</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E7DF153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1194" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Curious Time Travel Through Art History</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Curious Time Travel Through Art History</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA SMITH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Metropolitan Museum of Art is not doing the German painter Neo Rauch any favors. It has invited him to mount a show, but in such an infelicitous, low-ceilinged gallery that he has had to abandon his usual proscenium proportions and walk-in scale. In the canvas called ''Para,'' one of his characteristically large, heavy-limbed men wears a red riding jacket and holds a hunting horn; he is bent over, bumping his head against the top edge of the painting.</p>
        <p>But the real problem with this show may be the Met as a setting. In a museum whose permanent galleries house one of the world's best surveys of the history of Western painting, Mr. Rauch's lugubrious canvases feel dutiful and full of echoes. They fit too easily into this historical continuum and feed off of it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Neo Rauch’s lugubrious canvases, filled with theatrical, inchoate scenes and clunky figures, feel dutiful and full of echoes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Metropolitan Museum of Art is not doing the German painter Neo Rauch any favors. It has invited him to mount a show, but in such an infelicitous, low-ceilinged gallery that he has had to abandon his usual proscenium proportions and walk-in scale. In the canvas called ''Para,'' one of his characteristically large, heavy-limbed men wears a red riding jacket and holds a hunting horn; he is bent over, bumping his head against the top edge of the painting.</p>
        <p>But the real problem with this show may be the Met as a setting. In a museum whose permanent galleries house one of the world's best surveys of the history of Western painting, Mr. Rauch's lugubrious canvases feel dutiful and full of echoes. They fit too easily into this historical continuum and feed off of it.</p>
        <p>Full of theatrical, inchoate scenes and clunky figures, they offer skillful pastiches of familiar styles. As is repeatedly (and accurately) noted, the canvases evoke everything from the Baroque to Neo-Expressionism, Pop, Surrealism and Social Realism.</p>
        <p>The show has been organized by Gary Tinterow, curator in charge of the department of 19th-century, Modern and contemporary art. He writes defensively in the catalog, making light of the comparisons to previous styles and artists, and dismissing the portrayal of Mr. Rauch as ''a savvy interpreter of the contemporary scene,'' succeeding by associating his work ''with figures of the near and distant past.'' (Translation: He is not a pasticheur.)</p>
        <p>Saying that Mr. Rauch is ''self-described as a 'conservative' and sometimes 'romantic' artist,'' Mr. Tinterow makes the improbable assertion that Mr. Rauch's art ''is uniquely his own because it springs from his dreams.'' I'll leave the debate about the uniqueness of dreams to others. Mr. Rauch's may be unlike any dreamed before, but they have not enabled him, as yet, to develop an individual style.</p>
        <p>In his work at the Met, he seems almost deliberately to set back the clock, not only in terms of history, but also in terms of his development. While some of these paintings feature the beefy, Communist-bloc citizens of his previous works, several are populated by men with high white collars and jackets that scream 1825. In ''Father'' a small adult man is cradled by a portrait of the artist as a 14-year-old whose clouded face, tied collar and ample hair brings to mind portraits of early-19th-century Romantics -- Robert Schumann, for example.</p>
        <p>Some works seem intended as deliberate, possibly ironic, tributes. ''At Forest's Edge,'' which shows a man with a crossbow-tipped rifle and a woman with a guitar or cello case, could have been deemed a failure and discarded by Balthus or Max Beckmann, who are both finely represented in galleries downstairs from this show.</p>
        <p>Color is always a crucial element in Mr. Rauch's work, but here his palette is loaded with gravy-browns that add to the backward-looking aura. Only two paintings have color that really sings and draws you toward them.</p>
        <p>One is the enormous ''Waiting for the Barbarians,'' with its intense blue sky and flailing figures in red, yellow and blue. It includes a reclining woman holding an orange ball while being menaced by a red-faced penguinlike creature (a barbarian?) holding a stick. Gazing somberly at us, she looks like a version of Eve or the Madonna who has toppled out of Renaissance painting without dropping her main prop.</p>
        <p>The other is ''The Next Move,'' in which two 19th-century rakes or artists ponder, and two women, one nude, lounge on a bed in the background. (Manet, anyone?) But the main event is tension between the smoked-salmon pink of the wall, the white of the men's coats and the inky darkness in the right corner.</p>
        <p>The tendency of Mr. Rauch's paintings to remain an assembly of more or less -- or a lot less -- interesting parts rather than resolving into convincing wholes is especially overt in these works. Mr. Rauch's subject may be the discombobulation of modern life, but his convoluted scenes need to make more sense or emit more heat, whether formal or emotional.</p>
        <p>This may explain why they are so frequently called Surrealist, but great Surrealism makes sense (at least as visual pun, as in Magritte) or gives off heat (as in Dalí). The painting that makes the most sense is ''Waiting for the Barbarians,'' in which a Minotaur, or a man dressed as one, is taken to a small stage, like Christ before the people, while another burns at the stake.</p>
        <p>Mainly, these paintings feel unassembled and formulaic. You look at bits and pieces: a flash of color here, a reference to graffiti or cartooning there, a passage of paint elsewhere. The roughly worked surfaces have a modern, if stilted, physicality and are peppered with apparent riffs on Gerhard Richter. There is a hint of Mr. Richter's steely shading in ''Para'' and of his ironic color-sample geometries in ''Paranoia.''</p>
        <p>Throughout are the rough, scabby pulls of one color over another. ''Para,'' the subtitle of this show, appears in several canvases, including these, and also suggests parasite, paranormal and paramilitary, among other words.</p>
        <p>At the same time, although Mr. Rauch insists that his paintings are made without ''any preconception,'' and are composed directly on canvas without preparatory drawings, his figurative style has become as predictable as a coloring book's. He seems to have settled prematurely into a groove, and a middlebrow one at that.</p>
        <p>To call an artwork middlebrow is probably not the put-down it was back in the day, about 1950, when the critic Clement Greenberg wielded it like a cudgel. After all, since then we've had Pop and post-Pop; appropriation has metastasized; and every point of the spectrum between high and low art seems to have been visited, glorified and revisited.</p>
        <p>Yet middlebrow remains a useful term, and an expanding category in today's art world, a handy handle for art that is nonthreatening, accessible and earnest and that deals with time-honored humanistic themes.</p>
        <p>The phrase connotes an absence of, say, highbrow rigor and difficulty, or, equally, lowbrow flash and perversity. Jeff Koons is an example (not rare these days) of an artist who has had it both ways -- he's highbrow and lowbrow with such success that by now he probably can't avoid being a bit middlebrow too. But there are also artists whose work is middlebrow to begin with. Bill Viola and Tim Hawkinson, for example.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rauch's middlebrow doesn't feel inevitable. His art exudes a tremendous ambition, and he has done some wonderful paintings. He concluded his second New York show in 2002 at the David Zwirner Gallery, then in SoHo, with a painting that is unlike anything else he has shown in New York. A large landscape devoid of people or architecture, ''Field'' depicts a plunging expanse of deep red earth, first broken into chunks and then tilled, this difference marked by four barren shrubs.</p>
        <p>The image was built of four strong colors laid on thick and without fuss. For me this painting hangs over Mr. Rauch's career like a beacon. He still has time to heed it.</p>
        <p>''Neo Rauch at the Met: Para'' is on view through Oct. 14 at the Metropolitan Museum of Art; (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
