<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Jersey, Trying to Save in '02, Drove Up Pension Costs Instead</title>
    <meta content="15pension" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Washington; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/nyregion/15pension.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcginty, Jo Craven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, David W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Mcgreevey, James E</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E3DB153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Jersey, Trying to Save in '02, Drove Up Pension Costs Instead</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trying to Save, New Jersey Drove Up Pension Costs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JO CRAVEN McGINTY and DAVID W. CHEN; Mary Williams Walsh contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcginty, Jo Craven; Chen, David W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey's ability to meet its pension obligations have been undermined by generous early retirement packages and years of skipping payments into system; over past two decades, state has offered thousands of state employees pension enhancements to avoid layoffs; experts say that in each case, plan cost state more than it saved; study of 2002 early retirement plan finds more than 5,500 workers--twice what state projected--received early retirement packages, that more than 2,000 retirees were in federally financed jobs for which state did not realize any savings in salaries, and that pledge was not kept to to keep half of vacated jobs open for three years; also, normal review process for early retirement legislation did not occur because special panel that analyzes all pension-related bills did not meet that entire year; Gov Jon Corzine has warned that state faces $25 billion shortfall in $80 billion pension system; some experts say gap is much larger; graphs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In 2002, struggling to close a huge budget gap, the New Jersey Legislature hurriedly passed a bill offering thousands of state employees generous early retirement packages. Unions applauded because layoffs had been averted. Gov. James E. McGreevey claimed the state would save millions by cutting its payroll.</p>
        <p>But those savings have proved negligible compared with the long-term cost of the plan. By its own accounting, the state would have to set aside $617 million today to finance those sweetened pensions, double the amount it says it will have saved by trimming the work force and reducing salaries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Generous early retirement benefits have undermined the state’s ability to meet its pension obligations, experts say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In 2002, struggling to close a huge budget gap, the New Jersey Legislature hurriedly passed a bill offering thousands of state employees generous early retirement packages. Unions applauded because layoffs had been averted. Gov. James E. McGreevey claimed the state would save millions by cutting its payroll.</p>
        <p>But those savings have proved negligible compared with the long-term cost of the plan. By its own accounting, the state would have to set aside $617 million today to finance those sweetened pensions, double the amount it says it will have saved by trimming the work force and reducing salaries.</p>
        <p>In the past two decades, New Jersey has on at least four other occasions granted generous early retirement benefits, and in each case, experts say, the plans cost the state more than it saved.</p>
        <p>These and other pension enhancements, combined with years of skipping payments into the system, have undermined the state's ability to meet its pension obligations without raising taxes, borrowing money or shifting money from other state programs, experts and lawmakers warn.</p>
        <p>''Collectively as a Legislature we really never learn,'' said Senator Shirley K. Turner, a Democrat from Mercer County, who was a prime sponsor of the 2002 early retirement bill but now regrets its passage. ''We want to please people, we want to make them happy. But it has to be paid for. That's how we've mortgaged the future.''</p>
        <p>At least 14 other states, including Illinois and Texas, have made similar attempts to cut the work force in recent years and found the costs much greater than expected. Even Illinois, which did manage to shrink its staff over all, failed to pay for the pension enhancements on time, leading to higher costs.</p>
        <p>A review by The New York Times of New Jersey pension records and government and legislative reports relating to its 2002 early retirement plan reveals the following problems:</p>
        <p>More than 5,500 workers -- better than twice what the state had originally projected -- received early retirement packages, which added thousands of dollars to many workers' annual pensions. The larger number of retirements has meant higher than projected long-term costs to the pension and retiree health care systems.</p>
        <p>Though the McGreevey administration pledged to keep half of the vacated jobs open for three years, only 210 state-financed vacancies remained by the end of the next fiscal year. The total amount spent on state salaries did not decline.</p>
        <p>The normal review process for the early retirement legislation did not occur because a special panel that analyzes all pension-related bills did not meet that entire year.</p>
        <p>More than 2,000 of the retirees were in federally financed jobs for which the state did not realize any saving in salaries. Yet the state will still have to cover their retirement costs.</p>
        <p>In his budget address this year, Gov. Jon S. Corzine warned that New Jersey faced a $25 billion shortfall in the $80 billion pension system. Some experts say the gap is much larger.</p>
        <p>Mr. McGreevey did not respond to requests for interviews on the 2002 plan, but state officials who worked under him have said the plan helped keep down state spending and helped the administration close a $5.3 billion budget gap without undue pain.</p>
        <p>Those officials also acknowledge that they knew savings from the early retirement program would not last long.</p>
        <p>''We never thought it would be a real long-term savings,'' said John E. McCormac, who was Mr. McGreevey's treasurer and an architect of the 2002 plan. ''There were a lot of promises made, but at the end of the day, those commitments weren't honored, because the departments said, 'I can't do with less.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. McGreevey came into office in January 2002 facing a daunting $5.3 billion gap that had resulted from declining tax revenues caused by the post-9/11 economic downturn. Within a week of taking office, he fired several hundred nonunion state employees and threatened layoffs.</p>
        <p>During his election campaign, Mr. McGreevey, a Democrat, had forged a close alliance with the state's powerful public employee unions, so he was hesitant to lay off workers. He had also pledged not to raise taxes. So he turned to other measures to close the gap.</p>
        <p>''It's a textbook solution for every state or county with a deficit,'' Mr. McCormac said.</p>
        <p>To encourage people to leave government service, the plan offered employees one of three pension sweeteners based on their age and length of service: extra years of service credit, free health benefits, or $500 a month for 24 months.</p>
        <p>For most employees, the enhancements meant thousands of dollars more each year in pension payments. A doctor at Hunterdon Developmental Center, for example, retired with three extra years of service credit and an annual maximum pension of $81,470.83. Without the additional credit, his pension would have been $74,007.85, a difference of $7,462.98. New Jersey also adds a cost-of-living adjustment each year.</p>
        <p>In 2002, the McGreevey administration projected that the early retirement plan would save about $50 million in the first year and $261 million in salaries, benefits and taxes over five years. But for those savings to occur, the state said some things had to happen:</p>
        <p>First, 2,481 employees would have to take advantage of the incentives. Second, the state would have to hold open half those vacated positions until 2005. Then, it could fill only 10 percent of the openings each year.</p>
        <p>None of that happened.</p>
        <p>Perhaps because of the generous terms, more than 5,500 employees retired with the incentives. Half of those retirees worked in jobs at universities, colleges or agencies in which the federal government provided money for their positions. Their departures did not reduce state salaries; but with some exceptions, the state still had to pay for their pensions.</p>
        <p>The administration did identify 2,573 full-time employees in state-paid jobs whose retirements produced salary savings. But instead of holding most of their jobs open for several years, the state filled nearly all of them quickly; only 210 remained vacant at the end of the 2003 fiscal year.</p>
        <p>Because the state filled so many positions so quickly, it appears that the early retirement plan had minimal effect on the state's payroll. Indeed, a review of state records shows that the state's salary costs rose at an even pace before and after the 2002 plan was enacted.</p>
        <p>The state, however, says salary costs would have risen even higher had the plan not been enacted. And it asserts that savings from the plan have grown to $314 million, though the accuracy of that number is difficult to determine because the state has never performed a job-to-job analysis of the savings. Instead it relied on averages to estimate savings.</p>
        <p>By the state's own calculations, it also turns out that the cost of the early retirement package to the pension system is now more than double what the state projected in 2002: $616.8 million in today's dollars, instead of $278.1 million. The cost appears to have grown because more employees than predicted took advantage of the plan and the state needed to pay for pensions for the replacement workers.</p>
        <p>Experts say that New Jersey's experience with the 2002 plan is quite typical of early retirement programs. Alan R. Kooney, a former legislative budget and finance director whose office reviewed the 2002 plan, said such packages were used during crises because they provide immediate savings without painful layoffs or service cuts. But those savings, he said, are almost always dubious propositions in the long run.</p>
        <p>Still, New Jersey has tried them again and again: in 1991, 1993, 1997 and 1999 -- all years when it faced budget shortfalls. At present, more than 20,000 retirees, or about one in 10, benefit from some sort of early retirement incentive.</p>
        <p>Thomas Bryan, who was director of the Division of Pensions and Benefits in 2002, said those earlier programs did not seem to have saved as much of the money as had been anticipated. And a task force appointed by Acting Gov. Richard J. Codey to scrutinize employee benefits urged the state in 2005 to declare a permanent moratorium on early retirement plans because of their large, long-term liability.</p>
        <p>The current state treasurer, Bradley I. Abelow, said he was ''highly skeptical'' of early retirement incentives but did not rule them out as a way to encourage local governments to consolidate services.</p>
        <p>Despite that poor track record for early retirement plans, the 2002 bill passed quickly: just 18 days from its introduction to its final approval. (The only debate was over whether to expand the plan to include thousands of teachers and municipal employees. After Mr. McGreevey objected, that idea was shelved until the following year when the Legislature enacted it.)</p>
        <p>The 2002 package was also approved without being reviewed by a 10-member state panel appointed by the governor and legislative leaders that customarily examines pension-related bills. That panel, the Pension and Health Benefits Review Commission, has opposed early retirement plans because of the costs they impose on the system.</p>
        <p>But in 2002, the panel did not meet once, records show, because the administration had not filled vacancies and then failed to convene the group.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCormac acknowledged that the early retirement measure had contributed to the pension system's current fiscal trouble. He asserted, however, that its impact was small compared with other measures, including a benefit enhancement in 2001 that increased all state pensions by 9 percent, and stock market losses between 2000 and 2002.</p>
        <p>But even some prominent lawmakers who supported the 2002 measure now say it was a mistake.</p>
        <p>''All too often in state government we look toward short-term immediate solutions to problems without looking at the long-term consequences,'' said John Bennett, a Republican and former Senate president who voted for the measure but now says it was a mistake.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
