<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Gallery of Characters, a Galaxy of Possible Outcomes</title>
    <meta content="15brit" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/theater/reviews/15brit.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brits Off Broadway Festival</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Isherwood, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ayckbourn, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Champion, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elmhirst, Claudia</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Intimate Exchanges (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">59E59 Theaters</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ayckbourn, Alan</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Intimate Exchanges (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E4DF153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1487" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Gallery of Characters, a Galaxy of Possible Outcomes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Gallery of Characters, a Galaxy of Possible Outcomes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES ISHERWOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Isherwood, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Isherwood reviews Intimate Exchanges, series of related plays directed by Alan Ayckbourn and starring Bill Champion and Claudia Elmhirst; is part of Brits Off Broadway Festival; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Who wants to eat just one potato chip? Nobody, I trust. Similarly, dedicated theater lovers will not be content to sample just one of the eight plays that constitute ''Intimate Exchanges,'' the abundant buffet of domestic comedy by Alan Ayckbourn that opened last night at the 59E59 Theaters. To see a single play in this cycle, all about disappointing marriages and promising love affairs in a sleepy London suburb, is to be left with wistful, tantalizing thoughts about other possible fates that might befall its characters.</p>
        <p>Might Celia Teasdale, the harried wife of a drunken headmaster, escape her life of humiliation and submission? Why, yes, she might.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alan Ayckbourn’s abundant buffet of domestic comedy is receiving a spiffy production at the Brits Off Broadway festival.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Who wants to eat just one potato chip? Nobody, I trust. Similarly, dedicated theater lovers will not be content to sample just one of the eight plays that constitute ''Intimate Exchanges,'' the abundant buffet of domestic comedy by Alan Ayckbourn that opened last night at the 59E59 Theaters. To see a single play in this cycle, all about disappointing marriages and promising love affairs in a sleepy London suburb, is to be left with wistful, tantalizing thoughts about other possible fates that might befall its characters.</p>
        <p>Might Celia Teasdale, the harried wife of a drunken headmaster, escape her life of humiliation and submission? Why, yes, she might.</p>
        <p>Could it be that Sylvie Bell, Celia's part-time housemaid, possesses more ambition and human potential than a brief acquaintance with her might suggest? Could be.</p>
        <p>Will poor cuckolded Miles Coombes muster the courage to stand up to his reckless floozy of a wife? Perhaps he will.</p>
        <p>Only by returning more than once to the Brits Off Broadway festival, which is presenting the whole series in a spiffy production directed by Mr. Ayckbourn and Tim Luscombe, will you be able to witness the variously fulfilling or frustrating fates Mr. Ayckbourn has imagined for his half-dozen love-struck or love-starved characters. Although each play begins with the same minor incident -- Celia steps into her backyard and eyes a pack of cigarettes longingly -- each takes a different dramatic path at one of several turning points, ultimately leading to a fresh conclusion.</p>
        <p>Of course, just as you don't want to eat just one potato chip, you probably don't want to eat a whole jumbo-size bag either. Since each play in ''Intimate Exchanges'' has two alternate endings, you'd need to set aside a full two weeks for nonstop theatergoing to take in all 16 possible variations.</p>
        <p>Even those who have proudly punched their theater-marathon cards at ''The Coast of Utopia'' and last summer's cycle of plays by J. M. Synge may quail at that prospect, particularly because there is a fair amount of direct overlap between some of the plays. (More advice on that later.) Attending the whole series would probably appeal only to Ayckbourn completists, should there be any such lunatics roaming the city. (Mr. Ayckbourn's staggering output runs to more than 70 plays.)</p>
        <p>I had time to see five of the plays in ''Intimate Exchanges'' and am happy to leave it at that. For if I may draw on the potato-chip analogy one last time, it must be admitted that individually the plays do not offer much in the way of serious nutrition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ayckbourn specializes in light comedy tinged with rue, and in ''Intimate Exchanges'' he does not strive to strike any deeper chords. Seen as a whole, the cycle becomes an expansive comic meditation on the role choice, character and moment-by-moment circumstance can play in the workings of human destiny. But individually the plays generally resemble elongated sitcom episodes, some running well past two hours. The romantic shenanigans Mr. Ayckbourn concerns himself with here, against a rural English backdrop of tea and cricket and garden parties, are not touched with any grandeur or profound feeling.</p>
        <p>They are, however, delineated with a warm spirit and impressive comic flair by the two versatile actors who play all the characters in all the plays, Bill Champion and Claudia Elmhirst. For Mr. Ayckbourn, whose comedies are often derived from structural or theoretical challenges he sets for himself, was not satisfied merely to compose eight different plays beginning at the same point and juggling the fates of the same characters. He also limited himself to using just two actors. (That constraint was actually imposed by necessity. In 1982, when the project was undertaken, only two actors were available from the company at the Stephen Joseph Theater in Scarborough, England, where Mr. Ayckbourn is artistic director, and where this new production originated.)</p>
        <p>Ms. Elmhirst plays the stalwart Celia, wife of Toby Teasdale, the tippling headmaster of a private school. When the plays begin, Celia's deep resources of common sense, goodheartedness and loyalty have been depleted by her husband's abrasiveness and neglect, and she is on the verge of leaving him. She also plays the sweet but sullen Sylvie, whose yearning for more attention from her strutting doofus of a boyfriend, Lionel Hepplewick, may or may not go unheeded. And she portrays Rowena Coombes, the free-spirited cynosure of local gossip, who is cheating on her husband with virtually the whole of his squash team.</p>
        <p>Mr. Champion is the cranky Toby, tired of his wife and of the headmaster's life, who may either drink himself to death, irascible to the end, or mend his ways and come to see the folly of his cruelty to Celia. In ''A Pageant,'' probably the funniest of the plays I saw, Mr. Champion's Lionel becomes a working-class Henry Higgins to Sylvie's Eliza Doolittle, but finds his role as mentor cruelly usurped by the more refined Toby.</p>
        <p>In ''Events on a Hotel Terrace,'' on the other hand, Lionel's casual flirtation with Celia blossoms into an obsession, as Toby looks on bewildered and resentful. In ''A One Man Protest,'' another of the better plays, Mr. Champion's miserable Miles moves into the Teasdales' garden shed to lick his wounds and punish his errant wife.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Champion and Ms. Elmhirst are expert at defining these distinct characters with sharply contrasted voices or changes in physical bearing. Mr. Champion in particular looks wholly different in his three roles: sour, scrunched and exhausted as Toby; anxious and mousy as Miles; a walking leer as the self-satisfied Lionel. Ms. Elmhirst's Celia, the warm center of the cycle, is the most deeply explored character, her gentle determination to make the best of things truly touching. If you see a few of the plays, your admiration grows exponentially for the actors' ability to move smoothly from mild caricature to more thoughtful portraiture as their characters' roles in the plays expand or contract.</p>
        <p>Some of the fun is in the mischievous devices Mr. Ayckbourn concocts to allow the actors to shuffle between roles. At one point in ''A Pageant'' Mr. Champion crawls beneath a grandstand to perform a contretemps between Lionel and Toby. The contrivance is deeply silly but also irresistible, as is the farcical offstage catfight between Celia and Sylvie in the same play, which finds Ms. Elmhirst poking her head through a curtain at quick intervals as each character in turn. In the plays' most inspired passages Mr. Ayckbourn uses theatrical limitations as a springboard for fresh comic invention.</p>
        <p>If you're interested in seeing a few of the plays, you'd be wise to choose with care rather than randomly. The pathways of the plot sometimes do not diverge until the last minutes of the first act, so if you pick two plays from the same strand of the cycle, you will see the same hour or so of material twice. Fortunately, on the theater's Web site, 59e59.org, the most closely aligned plays are paired together in odd and even numbers. ''Affairs in a Tent,'' labeled A2, overlaps most closely with ''Events on a Hotel Terrace,'' which is A3, for example. If you want the greatest diversity, and are up for four, pick all the odd or all the even numbers.</p>
        <p>Choose to do that, and you may watch potential romances blossom between virtually all the men and women in the plays, who discover unexpected possibilities when they find themselves at a crossroads, face to face with a friend or acquaintance who suddenly looks like a possible savior. Life, dreary and routine, may yet turn out to be full of unexpected adventure.</p>
        <p>Or it may not. In some plays a leap of faith is taken, a daring opportunity is embraced; in others a safe return to habit, with a feeble hope that things might get better, is chosen. Either way, the plays tend to end on a note of melancholy. Like many humorists Mr. Ayckbourn believes that many an adventure is likely to end in misadventure. The potential for change in life may be a constant, but happiness -- that prize forever beckoning us on to seek choice and change -- remains maddeningly elusive.</p>
        <p>Intimate Exchanges</p>
        <p>A sequence of eight related plays, ''Events on a Hotel Terrace,'' ''Affairs in a Tent,'' ''A One Man Protest,'' ''Love in the Mist,'' ''A Cricket Match,'' ''A Game of Golf,'' ''A Pageant'' and ''A Garden Fete'' by Alan Ayckbourn; directed by Mr. Ayckbourn and Tim Luscombe; designed by Michael Holt; lighting by Ben Vickers; assistant director, Joe Douglas; company stage manager, Emily Vickers; production stage manager, Misha Siegel-Rivers; production manager, Adrian Sweeney. Presented as part of Brits Off Broadway by the Stephen Joseph Theater, Scarborough, England. At the 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, Manhattan, (212) 279-4200. Each play runs through July 1. Running times: 2 hours 15 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Bill Champion (Toby and others) and Claudia Elmhirst (Celia and others).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
