<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Now Americana, Pac-Man and Its Ilk May Gobble Auction Bids</title>
    <meta content="15auct" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/arts/15auct.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854539"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Video Games"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Archives and Records</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archives and Records</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Sotheby's Holdings Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Atari</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E3DF153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="922" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Now Americana, Pac-Man and Its Ilk May Gobble Auction Bids</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Now Americana, Pac-Man and Its Ilk May Gobble Auction Bids</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH SCHIESEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the near future video games may attain the exalted levels of cultural respect now reserved for pop jingles and situation comedies. When that happens, consumers and collectors alike may discover a reverence for artifacts from gaming's misty past (also known as the 1970s and '80s).</p>
        <p>Sotheby's New York believes that moment is now. In its auction next Thursday, Fine Books and Manuscripts Including Americana, Lot 151 will be an archive of roughly 2,200 drawings, schematics, diagrams and other documents generated in the early 1980s by Atari, arguably America's most important video game pioneer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sotheby’s Fine Books and Manuscripts sale next Thursday will feature valuable artifacts from gaming’s misty past: Atari’s archive of drawings and documents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the near future video games may attain the exalted levels of cultural respect now reserved for pop jingles and situation comedies. When that happens, consumers and collectors alike may discover a reverence for artifacts from gaming's misty past (also known as the 1970s and '80s).</p>
        <p>Sotheby's New York believes that moment is now. In its auction next Thursday, Fine Books and Manuscripts Including Americana, Lot 151 will be an archive of roughly 2,200 drawings, schematics, diagrams and other documents generated in the early 1980s by Atari, arguably America's most important video game pioneer.</p>
        <p>Estimated sale price: $150,000 to $250,000. That doesn't make the Atari archive the star of the show; a draft of ''Alcoholics Anonymous,'' that organizations's ''Big Book,'' could fetch more than $1 million. But that does mean that the Atari collection is expected to sell for more than a first edition of ''Ulysses'' ($50,000 median estimate), a letter from George Washington about the management of Mount Vernon ($30,000) and a pen-and-ink drawing by James Thurber titled ''(Parties) Four O'Clock in the Morning'' (a mere $4,000).</p>
        <p>''This is an important archive, and it's a lot of fun as well,'' said Selby Kiffer, a senior vice president in Sotheby's books and manuscripts department. ''It has a lot of cultural resonance, not only nostalgia, but things that carry over to the current day. My children and I might not have music or authors we both enjoy, but we always have Mario and Pac-Man in common.''</p>
        <p>Facing stacks of large folders with titles like 2600 Rubiks Manual, Asteroids PAL Manual and Carton Mech. Berzerk 5200, Mr. Kiffer said he bought his older brother an Atari home Pong console around 1977. He added, though, that he had been frustrated until recently in his search for Nintendo's new Wii console.</p>
        <p>At that moment C. Hugh Hildesley, a white-haired Sotheby's executive vice president, poked his head into the vault where the precious material was being stored and begged a moment of Mr. Kiffer's time for his opinion on the value of a 19th-century Philadelphia telephone directory ($15,000 to $20,000, Mr. Kiffer said).</p>
        <p>Perusing the Atari material, which goes on public view today, is like taking a time machine back to the basement rec rooms of the early '80s, a time when the carpet was shag, and game consoles like Atari's seminal 2600 came lined in faux-wood trim.</p>
        <p>In one folder are drafts for a manual for the game Robotron 2084. ''At first it was a technological breakthrough,'' reads the typewritten manuscript. ''Mankind created the Robotrons -- a species of robots so advanced they no longer needed their human creators to think and act. But the Robotrons have turned on their creators! They're now determined to destroy humanity -- or reprogram the survivors into destructive mutants!''</p>
        <p>In the margin you can see the handwritten addition of a careful copy editor, inserting a comma and the words ''turning them'' between ''survivors'' and ''into.''</p>
        <p>The most visually engaging pieces demonstrate how limited a palette early game designers had to work with. In a colorful acetate of images from the classic game Dig Dug, you can see that the artists had only a few dozen pixels at their disposal to create recognizable images of a walking alligator, a turnip and Mr. Dug himself. (''How many Veggies can a Dig Dug Dig?'' asks a mockup of the game's retail box.)</p>
        <p>On their own, the most valuable items would probably be artwork and design documents for Atari versions of Nintendo's famous Mario and Donkey Kong franchises. In later years Nintendo became notoriously protective of its signature brands. Looking at the Sotheby's material, you can see why: the box art for one of the Atari games features a drawing of Mario that looks nothing like the character now familiar around the world.</p>
        <p>So who has been holding onto these 161 folders all this time? That would be Cort Allen, a semiconductor design consultant in Pleasanton, Calif. As the original Atari was going belly up in the mid-'80s down the road in Sunnyvale, Mr. Allen stopped by a fire sale of Atari office equipment.</p>
        <p>''I saw this guy going by with a bin of documents and saw all this original artwork, and they said they were just emptying out a bunch of cabinets so they could sell the cabinets,'' he recalled in a telephone interview. ''It was 44 cabinets, and they had already cleaned out 4 of them, and I said, 'I want to buy those cabinets,' and the guy said, 'How many?' and I said, 'All of them.' ''</p>
        <p>The price: $2 each, or $80 total, which means that Mr. Allen stands to make a return of about 250,000 percent on his investment.</p>
        <p>Since he bought the Atari archive, it has migrated though various closets and shelves in Mr. Allen's house and garage. His wife nagged him about it, he said, but he held tight until the family's recent move to a new, smaller house finally forced the issue.</p>
        <p>''My wife didn't see the value of it,'' he said, ''and I was hoping to maybe get $4,000 or $5,000 for it. When I got a letter with the numbers and saw the estimate, I just about fell off the chair. My wife said, 'Is this real?' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Allen said he couldn't really keep up with modern video games but added that if the sale went as expected, the old ones would treat him just fine.</p>
        <p>''I just got two kids through college,'' he said. ''I've got a lot to pay off.''</p>
        <p>Video Games</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
