<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rodriguez And Pettitte Turn Success Into Victory</title>
    <meta content="15yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854696"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E3DB153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="954" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rodriguez And Pettitte Turn Success Into Victory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Yankees played in Chicago last week, Manager Joe Torre considered giving Alex Rodriguez a day off. Torre guessed that Rodriguez might be worn down mentally by the swirl of stories about his private life, and worn down physically by playing every game this season.</p>
        <p>But Rodriguez seems to be rejuvenated, Torre said, and the best rest he could give him was a start at designated hitter yesterday against the Arizona Diamondbacks. The Yankees, as always, were happy to have him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Yankees played in Chicago last week, Manager Joe Torre considered giving Alex Rodriguez a day off. Torre guessed that Rodriguez might be worn down mentally by the swirl of stories about his private life, and worn down physically by playing every game this season.</p>
        <p>But Rodriguez seems to be rejuvenated, Torre said, and the best rest he could give him was a start at designated hitter yesterday against the Arizona Diamondbacks. The Yankees, as always, were happy to have him.</p>
        <p>Rodriguez had three hits and figured in all three scoring rallies in Andy Pettitte's 7-1 victory at Yankee Stadium. It extended the Yankees' winning streak to nine games on the eve of this weekend's series with the Mets at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>The nine-game winning streak is the longest by any team in the majors this season, and Rodriguez's torrid play has more meaning than it did in April, when the Yankees won nine games all month.</p>
        <p>''It feels better, just because we're winning games,'' Rodriguez said. ''It feels like you're in the flow of things a little bit better.''</p>
        <p>Rodriguez has driven in 21 runs during the winning streak, and he is batting .391 in June. He has a major league-best 68 runs batted in this season, a total he did not reach last year until July 16, and he leads the major leagues with 25 homers.</p>
        <p>''I think he's relaxed,'' Torre said. ''That's the best part of Alex right now, because if you're relaxed, all of a sudden you're going to just allow your ability to do what it does, and he's got special ability. That's the best thing I see about Alex right now, that he's having some fun.''</p>
        <p>How could he not? Rodriguez is hitting behind Bobby Abreu, who has hit safely in all 13 games in June, with a .440 average and 12 walks. Abreu was relatively quiet yesterday, but Hideki Matsui was not.</p>
        <p>Matsui drove in three runs and went 3 for 4, improving his career average in interleague play to .362, the highest of anyone with 200 at-bats in interleague games. The reason, he said, is not National League pitching but the fact that most of the games come in June, when he feels most comfortable at the plate.</p>
        <p>But Matsui laughed and said, through his interpreter: ''We've still got nine games left. So that's good.''</p>
        <p>The way they are playing now, it is hard to imagine the Yankees losing many of those nine against the Mets, the Colorado Rockies and the San Francisco Giants. The Diamondbacks are one of the better teams in the National League, at 37-30, and they looked severely overmatched.</p>
        <p>The Yankees outscored the Diamondbacks by 18-4 and trailed for only one half-inning in the series. They drew 12 walks in 16 innings off Arizona starters, and capitalized on five Diamondback errors, including three yesterday.</p>
        <p>After opening with three singles off Doug Davis in the first inning, the Yankees scored on a walk by Rodriguez. When Abreu walked to lead off the third, Rodriguez scored him with a double to left that Scott Hairston misplayed for an error. Matsui scored Rodriguez with a hard double to right to make it 4-1.</p>
        <p>Singles by Rodriguez, Jorge Posada and Matsui touched off a three-run seventh inning that included another error, on an overthrow by center fielder Chris Young. The Yankees actually left 10 runners on base yesterday, but they had enough chances to make their offense seem robust.</p>
        <p>''You look at our lineup and you feel like you can score from any part of the lineup, regardless of where it starts,'' Matsui said. ''It's got good balance and a good flow right now.''</p>
        <p>It was the kind of run support that had been lacking for Pettitte, who lost three games in May in which he worked at least seven innings and allowed three runs or fewer. His record is just 4-4, but his earned-run average, 2.93, is the best among left-handers in the American League.</p>
        <p>The Diamondbacks had just four hits and a run in eight innings off Pettitte, who struck out four. Against an inexperienced lineup, he went with his vintage game plan: burying his cutter inside to righties and spotting his curveballs and four-seam fastballs. One hundred and one pitches rarely seemed so effortless.</p>
        <p>Pettitte, like Rodriguez, is finally seeing personal success translating to team victories.</p>
        <p>''When you're playing like this, you just want to keep it going,'' Pettitte said. ''Really, that's all there is to it. We're throwing the ball well, swinging the bats well. It's fun right now to come to the ballpark and do this.''</p>
        <p>Even at the Yankees' lowest point -- on May 29, when Aaron Hill stole home off Pettitte in Toronto to help push the Yankees to 21-29, 14 1/2 games behind the Red Sox -- Pettitte could draw on personal history.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, Pettitte and Roger Clemens helped anchor a Houston team that started 15 games under .500 but wound up in the World Series. The Yankees, he said, could make a similar turnaround.</p>
        <p>''We were 15-30 and we made the run,'' Pettitte said. ''So this team just has too much talent not to win. That's what I just continued to tell myself and tried to tell everybody in here: 'Just stay positive, and this thing's going to turn around.'</p>
        <p>''It wasn't happening for a couple of months, but we expected to win, and we expected to be playing like we are right now.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The pitching matchups this weekend: Roger Clemens (1-0, 4.50) vs. Oliver PÉrez (6-5, 3.21) tonight, Tyler Clippard (3-1, 5.32) vs. Tom Glavine (5-4, 4.15) tomorrow, and Chien-Ming Wang (6-4, 3.49) vs. Orlando HernÁndez (3-2, 2.38) Sunday night.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
