<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LIVING HERE | Houses in Theater Towns; The Play's the Thing</title>
    <meta content="15live" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854640"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Berkshire Theater Festival</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Stockbridge (Mass)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jassy, Margery</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jassy, Everett</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyttle, Bethany</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Living Here</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E3DC153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="893" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LIVING HERE | Houses in Theater Towns; The Play's the Thing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">As told to Bethany Lyttle</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyttle, Bethany</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Margery and Everett Jassy comment on their second home in Stockbridge, Mass, within walking distance of Berkshire Theater Festival; photos and brief descriptions of other properties in theater towns (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHO -- Margery Jassy, 68, a part-time student, and her husband, Everett, 70, a retired lawyer, from Manhattan  WHAT -- 5-bedroom house  WHERE -- Stockbridge, Mass.</p>
        <p>Margery: As you walk through the gate and up the wooden steps of the Main Stage at the Berkshire Theater Festival, something wonderful happens. Summer memories combine with anticipation of the season's coming productions. Year after year, they're outstanding. We like to say we bought this house because we fell in love in with Kate Maguire, the festival's executive director.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHO -- Margery Jassy, 68, a part-time student, and her husband, Everett, 70, a retired lawyer, from Manhattan  WHAT -- 5-bedroom house  WHERE -- Stockbridge, Mass.</p>
        <p>Margery: As you walk through the gate and up the wooden steps of the Main Stage at the Berkshire Theater Festival, something wonderful happens. Summer memories combine with anticipation of the season's coming productions. Year after year, they're outstanding. We like to say we bought this house because we fell in love in with Kate Maguire, the festival's executive director.</p>
        <p>Everett: The Berkshire Theater Festival is 78 years old. Among others, Katharine Hepburn and Richard Chamberlain have played here. There are two theaters, the Main Stage and the Unicorn, and their plays run concurrently. Next week, Terrence McNally's ''Love! Valour! Compassion!'' will open on the Main Stage. ''The Glass Menagerie'' will continue at the Unicorn.</p>
        <p>Margery: When I was a girl, I used to go to camp in Maine, and in the summer evenings they would take the girls -- not the boys -- to local theater. I still remember that clapboard building and the way it felt to watch a play in such a beautiful and rural setting. A part of me experiences those feelings here.</p>
        <p>Everett: Our house is just up the hill. We can walk here to see a play. We've made a lot of friends here. Among second-home owners, it's easy to do in the Berkshires, in part because of the area's rich cultural life.</p>
        <p>Margery: After a play, if we have guests with us from the city, we'll all walk slowly back to the house. And then if the mosquitoes aren't too bad, we'll go out on the deck and talk about the play over dessert before parting sweetly until morning.</p>
        <p>As told to Bethany Lyttle</p>
        <p>Information on properties was supplied by the owners or the listing companies.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Sebastapol, Calif.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $1.32 million</p>
        <p>This 2,752-square-foot house, which is about 15 minutes from the North Bay Theater Group in Santa Rosa, is on a private paved lane and has more than seven acres of property. The house has vaulted ceilings with exposed beams, walls of windows and a separate office/studio. There are two and a half bathrooms. A solarium and decks on two sides of the house look out onto grounds that include woods, a meadow, a pond and a creek. Agent: Cary Fargo, Prudential California Realty, (707) 824-4507; www.westofthelaguna.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Arundel, Me.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house with guesthouse  HOW MUCH -- $525,000</p>
        <p>Built in 1840, this house is less than two miles from the Arundel Barn Playhouse, which offers live musical theater. The house, on four acres, has pine floors, original wood moldings and three fireplaces. There is also a guesthouse with two bedrooms and two bathrooms. The house is about three miles from Kennebunkport. Broker: Sam Downing, Downing Real Estate Agency, (207) 985-3328; www.downingagency.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- West Stockbridge, Mass.  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $895,000</p>
        <p>This 2,990-square-foot house is about a 10-minute drive to the Berkshire Theater Festival and the Mahaiwe Theater in Great Barrington. The house, which was built in 1981, is on 5.8 acres and has three bathrooms, a sun room with a woodstove, a large eat-in kitchen and two marble fireplaces. A separate barn has about 500 feet of finished living space and one bathroom. Perennial gardens and organic orchards are on the property. Agent: Dan Howard, Stone House Properties, (413) 232-4253; www.stonehouseproperties.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Woodstock, N.Y.  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $699,000</p>
        <p>Less than 10 minutes from the Woodstock Playhouse, this 3,249-square-foot house is on just over nine acres of wooded property. A large sun room opens onto a swimming pool and gardens. The house, which was built in 1974, has a family room with a fireplace, a large formal dining room and a music room. There are three and a half bathrooms, vaulted ceilings and French doors. Woodstock is about 100 miles from New York City. Agent: Rusty Marks, Westwood Metes &amp; Bounds Realty, (845) 679-0006; www.westwoodrealty.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Ashland, Ore.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $749,000</p>
        <p>Built in 1983, this 2,144-square-foot house has mountain views and is only a few minutes from the Oregon Shakespeare Festival. The house, on about a third of an acre, has bamboo floors, new windows and French doors, a gas fireplace and new countertops. Outside a curved deck runs the length of the house. There are two and a half bathrooms, and a master suite on the second level. Ashland is about 280 miles south of Portland. Broker: Carlene Hester, Ashland Homes Real Estate Inc., (541) 482-0044; www.ashland-homes.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Stratford, Ontario  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $555,460</p>
        <p>This brick house was built in 1875 and almost all of its original interior and exterior detail has been restored. The house is within 15 minutes of three active theaters and the Stratford Festival, which is known for its Shakespeare theater productions. The house has an elegant main staircase, stained-glass windows and a kitchen with an attached screened porch. There are four bathrooms. The asking price is 599,900 Canadian dollars. Broker: Barb Hiller Thibeault, Royal LePage Hiller Realty, (519) 273-1650; www.realestatebarb.ca.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
