<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Assisting the Good Life; Resorts Add Jobs, But They Also Tap Into a Reservoir Of Subsidies</title>
    <meta content="15subsidy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/business/15subsidy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854651"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Credits, Deductions and Exemptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lotteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reservoirs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Eminent Domain</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bandon (Ore)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bandon Dunes Golf Resort (Ore)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, David Cay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Oregon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oregon/Bandon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oregon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lotteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Eminent Domain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waterways and Other Bodies of Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bandon (Ore)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E0DC153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1420" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Assisting the Good Life; Resorts Add Jobs, But They Also Tap Into a Reservoir Of Subsidies</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Assisting the Good Life</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CAY JOHNSTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, David Cay</byline>
      <dateline>BANDON, Ore.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mike Keiser's Bandon Dunes Golf Resort in Bandon, Ore, has created 325 full-time jobs, plus hundreds more part-time jobs in town that saw timber and fishing industries collapse quarter-century ago; largely hidden subsidies from airline passengers, state-lottery players, taxpayers and company shareholders support benefits that owner, workers and visitors at Bandon Dunes enjoy; airline passengers and lottery players are paying for $31 million airport expansion to serve 5,000 business jets that arrive each year, filled almost entirely with golfers; little attention has focused on many kinds of indirect favors that are showered on places like Bandon Dunes through government policies that influence flow of money from public to private interests and often serve to reinforce benefits for those who are already successful; after resort was built without government aid, first subsidy was put in place only after Keiser's lawyers succeeded in eliminating for three years larger property-tax bill that would normally accompany new construction--tax break worth $99,000 this year; city of Bandon also allowed Keiser to buy into proposed reservoir project, which would produce water for town and for another gold course he may build; project requires condemnation of land, which can be done only by government agency; other subsidies discussed; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike Keiser, who made a fortune selling greeting cards on recycled paper, turned this remote spot on the southern Oregon coast into a golfing mecca that attracts wealthy people in private jets from around the world.</p>
        <p>To many in this hard-luck town of 3,000, Mr. Keiser is an economic hero. Work became scarce after the timber and fishing industries collapsed a quarter-century ago, and his Bandon Dunes Golf Resort, a few miles north of town, has created 325 full-time jobs, plus hundreds more part-time jobs. Mr. Keiser earns millions of dollars in profits each year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A golf resort in Oregon benefits from a variety of hidden subsidies, the kind of indirect favors that influence the flow of money from public to private interests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mike Keiser, who made a fortune selling greeting cards on recycled paper, turned this remote spot on the southern Oregon coast into a golfing mecca that attracts wealthy people in private jets from around the world.</p>
        <p>To many in this hard-luck town of 3,000, Mr. Keiser is an economic hero. Work became scarce after the timber and fishing industries collapsed a quarter-century ago, and his Bandon Dunes Golf Resort, a few miles north of town, has created 325 full-time jobs, plus hundreds more part-time jobs. Mr. Keiser earns millions of dollars in profits each year.</p>
        <p>But beneath this model of enterprise, largely hidden subsidies from airline passengers, state-lottery players, taxpayers and company shareholders support the benefits that the owner, workers and visitors at Bandon Dunes enjoy.</p>
        <p>Airline passengers and lottery players are paying for a $31 million airport expansion to serve the 5,000 business jets that arrive each year, filled almost entirely with golfers. Many of them are executives of publicly traded companies flying at a small fraction of the real cost of their trips; taxpayers and shareholders bear nearly all of these costs.</p>
        <p>Much controversy swirls around the subsidies and tax exemptions state and local governments offer expressly to attract businesses to a community. But far less attention has been focused on the many kinds of indirect favors that are showered on places like Bandon Dunes through government policies that influence the flow of money from the public to private interests and often serve to reinforce benefits for those who are already successful.</p>
        <p>''In every situation, governments need to ask what the necessary public role is,'' said Irene S. Rubin, a public finance expert at Northern Illinois University. ''Why is the government even involved in this activity? What is the public good?''</p>
        <p>No official tally of business subsidies exists, but in separate studies Peter S. Fisher of the University of Iowa and Kenneth F. Thomas of the University of Missouri estimated that state and local subsidies aimed at creating jobs total about $50 billion annually. More subtle subsidies like those that benefit Bandon Dunes are not counted in those figures and may be even larger.</p>
        <p>Such government subsidies have been challenged as inefficient by a broad spectrum of critics, from the libertarian Cato Institute and the conservative Heritage Foundation to liberal groups like Good Jobs First.</p>
        <p>To be sure, said Martin S. Feldstein, a Harvard University economics professor and a former chief economic adviser to President Ronald Reagan, some government subsidies can be beneficial for society.</p>
        <p>''A subsidy for flu vaccines is good,'' he said, ''because if you are vaccinated I am less likely to get flu by contagion.'' But job subsidies are a drag on the economy, he added, ''unless the local gain exceeds the loss in the rest of the nation.''</p>
        <p>In the beginning, there were no subsidies at Bandon Dunes. That stands in contrast to many projects where state and local agencies compete to attract investments in factories, corporate headquarters and other developments that claim to create or retain jobs.</p>
        <p>''I am the sole owner -- no one else would have invested,'' said Mr. Keiser, who paid $2.4 million, half the asking price, for his first parcel of scrub land in 1990. The country may seem overrun with golf courses, but Mr. Keiser had something else in mind. He calls it ''dream golf,'' modeled after the age-old seaside links in Scotland where the game was invented.</p>
        <p>Tens of thousands of golfers now come each year, many in corporate jets, to play on three courses, all considered among the best in the world. They lie on the sandy bluffs above the Pacific Ocean, with no power poles, no traffic and no whine from electric golf carts, because players must walk, carrying their own bags or relying on caddies to help them navigate the course. Stiff winds carry balls unpredictably; wet weather is common.</p>
        <p>Bandon Dunes has become extraordinarily popular. This year about 120,000 rounds of golf will be played, at a typical cost in season of more than $200 a person. Lodging and meals add hundreds more to the expense. Among the visitors have been Bill Gates, Michael Jordan and Don Johnson.</p>
        <p>After the resort was built without government aid, the first subsidy was put in place only after Mr. Keiser's lawyers succeeded in eliminating for three years the larger property-tax bill that would normally accompany new construction -- a tax break worth $99,000 this year.</p>
        <p>John Griffith, the Coos County commission chairman, complained that the tax cut had been sought after the decision was made to invest. ''It is supposed to be an incentive to attract new investment, not a reward for an investment you have already decided to make,'' said Mr. Griffith, who was almost alone among public officials in opposing the subsidy. The incentive was supported by the others as a means of rewarding Mr. Keiser for his investment in the area.</p>
        <p>The city of Bandon also allowed Mr. Keiser to buy into a proposed reservoir project, which would produce water for the town and for another golf course he may build south of here. The project requires condemnation of land, which can be done only by a government agency.</p>
        <p>But those two relatively modest government subsidies pale in comparison to the support for private jets that has made the resort far more accessible. About 20 miles north of Bandon Dunes lies an airport, which handles only three commercial flights a day. The airport was originally created to serve planes guarding the coast during World War II.</p>
        <p>Before the first golf course opened in 1999, perhaps three private jets a year landed here, said Gary W. LeTellier, the airport director. Last year 5,000 private jets came; the number should grow to as many as 7,500 once the expansion is completed, Mr. LeTellier said.</p>
        <p>The airport expansion is being financed by a tax paid on all commercial airline tickets and state bonds backed by revenue from the Oregon lottery, which is heavily used by the state's poor.</p>
        <p>Even if the planned growth of the resort leads to a doubling of the full-time payroll to 650, the airport expansion alone represents a one-time cost to taxpayers of almost $48,000 a job. The average pay for a full-time Bandon Dunes worker, including benefits and tips, is about $36,000.</p>
        <p>The biggest subsidy is even more hidden, a consequence of the rules under which executives make personal use of company jets. Most executives do not pay directly; instead the value of the flights is supposed to be counted as income.</p>
        <p>In most cases, the executive's only expense is higher income taxes. Some companies reimburse executives for these taxes and even pay the taxes on the reimbursement.</p>
        <p>Moreover, under current government rules, the income attributed to personal use of such jets is only a fraction of the real cost. Take a trip that costs a company $100,000. Of that, $35,000 is borne by the federal government because such expenses are tax deductible. The other $65,000 is borne by shareholders in the form of lower profits.</p>
        <p>Yet the executive owes no more than a few thousand dollars in taxes. That's because to calculate income taxes on personal flights, the government counts only a portion of costs, excluding, among other things, flights to position a plane or fly it home empty.</p>
        <p>Based on the number of corporate jets flying here, an average four-hour flight time and total costs of $4,000 per hour, the subsidy from taxpayers works out to about $12 million, with shareholders effectively paying about twice that. For the 325 existing jobs, that adds up to an annual total of $37,000 a job.</p>
        <p>Michael Greenstone, a professor of economics at Massachusetts Institute of Technology, said that the subsidy is a significant boon to Mr. Keiser and his customers, sharply reducing the expense of reaching such a remote location.</p>
        <p>As the owner of a private business, Mr. Keiser personally bears the full cost of the leased Gulfstream 200 that brings him from his home in Chicago to Bandon Dunes roughly every six weeks. The resort never asked for the tax subsidy for executives, he said. And if taken away, he added, ''I think that it would have negligible impact on us.''</p>
        <p>''Certainly from the recipient point of view,'' Mr. Keiser said, ''I'm pleased that there is a subsidy and know very well that it is a subsidy that can be changed at any point in time. That is why we have a Congress, to look at things like that.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
