<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HAVENS | Tucson Foothills; Cleared to Tee Off or Take Off</title>
    <meta content="15havens" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/realestate/greathomes/15havens.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854524"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Havens| Tucson Foothills"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tucson (Ariz)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arizona</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">smalera, paul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Great Homes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions/Western States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Vacation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona/Tucson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Tucson (Ariz)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Arizona</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E7DF153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1538" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HAVENS | Tucson Foothills; Cleared to Tee Off or Take Off</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cleared to Tee Off or Take Off</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL SMALERA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">smalera, paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on foothills of Tucson, Ariz, as place to live or visit; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Hohokams were probably the first to turn the foothills of North Tucson into a second home. Two millenniums ago, they spent their summers gathering cactus pears and mesquite beans, anthropologists say, just north of the basin where the city of Tucson was founded in 1775.</p>
        <p>In more recent years, the foothills and the areas adjacent to the north have been rediscovered, you might say, by second-home owners who are finding that the Hohokams were onto something. Depending on the neighborhood, real estate agents estimate that 10 to 40 percent of the residents in North Tucson are second-home owners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Golf, high-end shops and a popular airpark draw second-home buyers to the foothills of North Tucson, Ariz.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Hohokams were probably the first to turn the foothills of North Tucson into a second home. Two millenniums ago, they spent their summers gathering cactus pears and mesquite beans, anthropologists say, just north of the basin where the city of Tucson was founded in 1775.</p>
        <p>In more recent years, the foothills and the areas adjacent to the north have been rediscovered, you might say, by second-home owners who are finding that the Hohokams were onto something. Depending on the neighborhood, real estate agents estimate that 10 to 40 percent of the residents in North Tucson are second-home owners.</p>
        <p>If, like Buck Clippard, you fly but have trouble finding airplane parking, you might consider requesting permission to land at La Cholla Airpark, a community 20 miles north of downtown Tucson. The Clippards have a second home there -- and a two-plane hangar on a taxiway (or, as the earthbound might call it, a road), right off the airpark's main drag, a 4,500-foot landing strip.</p>
        <p>''About every six months or year, we sponsor a fly-in pancake breakfast where about 300 pilots fly their little airplanes in, park on the street, and we play Dixieland jazz,'' Mr. Clippard said. When Mr. Clippard, a former airline pilot who retired from Pan American in 1991, and his wife, Carol, settled in Fort Lauderdale, Fla., they often flew their vintage Beechcraft to visit Mr. Clippard's father, who lived in Green Valley, Ariz. But because the local public airstrip was in an inconvenient location, the Clippards decided to build on land they'd bought in La Cholla.</p>
        <p>The Clippards completed their self-designed home in 1999. Their aircraft-size version of a detached garage also houses a workshop and a second-floor guest suite.</p>
        <p>If your concept of flying doesn't involve starting your own engine, though, you may find it convenient that the developments around the Santa Catalina foothills are 20 minutes closer to downtown than La Cholla is, and often feature more amenities like golf courses and tennis courts.</p>
        <p>Paul and Marianne Pellegrino, however, found they preferred living in a foothills development without golf -- Pima Canyon. Their previous house in Tucson was right on a fairway. ''When the lawnmowers are going off at 5 o'clock in the morning, getting the course ready, you don't like it,'' Mr. Pellegrino said. ''And when a golf ball comes crashing through your window, you don't like it.''</p>
        <p>Many part-time residents do enjoy living right off the courses, however, according to John Schneider, a real estate agent who specializes in the foothills. He estimated that up to half the houses in newer developments like La Paloma and Ventana Canyon are bought as second homes.</p>
        <p>Tucson has long been known as a snowbird destination, where Midwesterners like the Pellegrinos, from Chicago, come to escape the winters.</p>
        <p>The Scene</p>
        <p>The Santa Catalina and Tortolita Mountains, natural boundaries to the north that are full of prickly cactuses and wild desert creatures, have halted the sprawl that affects the east and west sides of Tucson, creating a natural enclave where part-time residents say they feel at home.</p>
        <p>North Tucson is also becoming the home of the city's high-end shopping. A once dusty intersection of North Campbell Avenue and East Skyline Drive has become a town square for those who live in the foothills.</p>
        <p>La Encantada shopping center opened on one corner of the intersection in 2003, to some skepticism. Mr. Schneider said he initially wondered who would shop at La Encantada, which is anchored by AJ's Fine Foods and a Tiffany store. Mr. Pellegrino, who is semiretired from the food distribution business, said he had noticed that people treated food displays as if they were exhibitions at the Field Museum in Chicago.</p>
        <p>Less than four years later, the other three lots have spawned their own shopping centers, and Campbell Avenue's commercial district has grown northward. The Foothills Mall, on Oracle Road, has played a similar role near the airpark.</p>
        <p>The Nederlander Producing Company of America is in the third season of the ''Broadway in Tucson'' series, bringing musicals like ''Rent'' and ''Evita'' to downtown.</p>
        <p>Although national chain restaurants have made inroads in the new shopping plazas, so have local favorites like Mosaic Cafe Dos, which is run by the daughter of the owners of Teresa's Mosaic Cafe, one of Tucson's best-known Tex-Mex restaurants.</p>
        <p>Some residents of North Tucson are skeptical about whether other desert communities offer the same lifestyle as theirs. ''Phoenix is becoming mini-L.A., with all the freeways,'' Mr. Pellegrino said.</p>
        <p>About 15 percent of residents in La Cholla join the Clippards in making it a second home, said Peggy A. Fuenning, a real estate agent who lives in La Cholla. The Clippards are certain that there are few places in Arizona that could give them their current arrangement. Since they keep their planes at a public airstrip while in Fort Lauderdale, they often put their planes, and themselves, in Tucson during hurricane season.</p>
        <p>Pros</p>
        <p>Infrastructure, services and shopping are the key to the foothills' attractiveness. Since there are few large lots left, congestion is not likely to develop along River Road and Skyline Drive, the region's main east-west roads, real estate agents say, though crossing into downtown can be an ordeal.</p>
        <p>Near the airpark, there are still undeveloped spaces that once defined the entire north side of town.</p>
        <p>Cons</p>
        <p>Without a comprehensive freeway system, it's tough to get to other areas of Tucson, creating an enclave effect that some residents love but others hate.</p>
        <p>Residents also worry that subdivisions of 10-acre lots in the old foothills area immediately south of River Road and the smaller lots at newer developments will disfigure the views that attracted so many of them in the first place. As Mr. Schneider put it, ''What's rare these days is not a hillside with a beautiful mansion built into it, but a hillside with no mansion at all.''</p>
        <p>As in just about every rapidly growing desert community in Arizona, there are issues involving land and water use.</p>
        <p>The Real Estate Market</p>
        <p>Condos as investment properties are out. Mr. Schneider said that more than 800 have become available in the North Tucson area in the last year and a half, flooding what was once a speculative market. That makes buying for the long term more affordable, with new two-bedroom units available for less than $200,000.</p>
        <p>Single-family home sales in the foothills slowed in mid-2006, Mr. Schneider said, but he added that there has since been a rebound. He also said that asking prices had dipped recently, but sellers had adjusted to the market and homes were now selling for 96 percent of listing prices.</p>
        <p>Single-family houses under $500,000 are rare but do exist. Expect to pay a premium to be near a golf course or an airstrip. Million-dollar houses in Tucson, once unthinkable, have become common, and houses costing well over $2 million are abundant at newer developments like Pima Canyon.</p>
        <p>LAY OF THE LAND</p>
        <p>POPULATION -- About 60,000 people live in the foothills and another 45,000 live around La Cholla Airpark.</p>
        <p>SIZE -- About 42 square miles in the foothills and 50 square miles around nearby La Cholla.</p>
        <p>WHO'S BUYING -- Baby boomers from cities like Chicago, Minneapolis and Los Angeles who are planning for a retirement that allows them to enjoy the culture and sophistication of life near an urban core.</p>
        <p>GETTING THERE -- Many flights from the East Coast connect to Tucson International Airport through Chicago, Dallas or elsewhere. There are some nonstop flights from New York, and most service from the West Coast is direct. Tucson is a stop on Amtrak's Sunset Limited route.</p>
        <p>WHILE YOU'RE LOOKING -- The Westin La Paloma Resort &amp; Spa (3800 East Sunrise Drive, 520-742-6000; www.westinlapalomaresort.com) is nestled in the Tucson foothills, and rooms typically start at $299 a night. There is also a Holiday Inn Express (10150 North Oracle Road, 520-202-4000; www.hiexpress.com) in Oro Valley, near La Cholla, where rooms start at $129 a night.</p>
        <p>THREE FOR SALE</p>
        <p>Where Tucson Is Spreading Out in a Whole New Direction</p>
        <p>Information on properties was supplied by the listing companies.</p>
        <p>WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $649,000</p>
        <p>This 2,442-square-foot house is on 0.6 acre on a ridge at the base of the Santa Catalina foothills. It has two and a half bathrooms and a new roof. Agent: Michelle Craig, Tierra Antigua Realty; (520) 331-0806; www.tierraantiguarealty.com.</p>
        <p>WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $1.91 million</p>
        <p>This 4,051-square-foot house in the Skyline Country Club, a gated community, is in the Santa Catalina foothills and has views of Tucson. It is on nearly an acre and has four bathrooms, an attached three-car garage, three fireplaces and 16-foot vaulted and beamed ceilings. Agent: John Schneider, Long Realty; (520) 271-4164; www.thefoothillstoday.com.</p>
        <p>WHAT -- 3-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $2.18 million</p>
        <p>This 4,015-square-foot house is on 7.76 acres in the La Cholla Airpark. There are four bathrooms, a wine cellar and an outdoor kitchen. An aquarium separates the great room and the master bedroom. It is zoned for a detached hangar. Agent: Peggy A. Fuenning, Realty Executives Southern Arizona; (800) 298-8285; www.tucsonairparks.com.</p>
        <p>Havens| Tucson Foothills</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
