<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mitchell-Giambi Meeting Under Discussion as Deadline Nears</title>
    <meta content="15giambi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/sports/baseball/15giambi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854644"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">USA TODAY</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Giambi, Jason</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mitchell, George J</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Tellem, Arn</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E2DC153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="562" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mitchell-Giambi Meeting Under Discussion as Deadline Nears</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mitchell-Giambi Meeting Under Discussion as Deadline Nears</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With five days left before the Yankees' Jason Giambi must decide if he will meet with investigators about steroid use in baseball, lawyers from the players union and Arn Tellem, Giambi's agent, are in deep discussions with lawyers from Major League Baseball.</p>
        <p>A person who has been briefed on the discussions said the two sides were negotiating the parameters for Giambi to meet with George J. Mitchell, the former United States senator who is heading the investigation. Giambi, who tacitly admitted to using steroids in an article in USA Today last month, faces a deadline of Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jason Giambi has until Wednesday to decide if he will meet with the Mitchell investigators about steroid use in baseball.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With five days left before the Yankees' Jason Giambi must decide if he will meet with investigators about steroid use in baseball, lawyers from the players union and Arn Tellem, Giambi's agent, are in deep discussions with lawyers from Major League Baseball.</p>
        <p>A person who has been briefed on the discussions said the two sides were negotiating the parameters for Giambi to meet with George J. Mitchell, the former United States senator who is heading the investigation. Giambi, who tacitly admitted to using steroids in an article in USA Today last month, faces a deadline of Wednesday.</p>
        <p>If Giambi had already determined that he was not going to talk to Mitchell and was simply going to await discipline from Commissioner Bud Selig, the lawyers for the union and for baseball would have abandoned negotiations.</p>
        <p>Giambi's lawyers are undoubtedly trying to limit the kind of questions Mitchell can ask Giambi, the Yankees' designated hitter. Selig, who owned the Milwaukee Brewers when Paul Molitor admitted to using cocaine in the 1980s, knows that Giambi would become a clubhouse pariah if he disclosed the habits of other players. So it is probable that Mitchell would mostly ask Giambi about himself.</p>
        <p>When Selig requested on June 6 that Giambi cooperate with the Mitchell investigation, his statement needed little interpretation. If Giambi did not agree to cooperate within two weeks, Selig strongly implied that he would punish him, presumably with a fine and a suspension.</p>
        <p>Once Selig asked Giambi to cooperate and suggested that Giambi's potential discipline would be influenced by whether he spoke with Mitchell, the commissioner was indicating that he would take some action if Giambi refused to cooperate.</p>
        <p>''Discipline for wrongdoing is important, but it is also important to create an environment so players can feel free to honestly and completely cooperate with this important investigation,'' Selig said at the time.</p>
        <p>While Selig is prepared for the possibility that Giambi will not meet with Mitchell, baseball's lawyers have discussed internally what type of penalty would be appropriate.</p>
        <p>Although baseball's current policy calls for a 50-game suspension for a first offense, Giambi's statement to USA Today referred to a time before baseball had a steroid policy. Selig could invoke the best-interests-of-baseball clause to suspend Giambi. Baseball lawyers are considering how many games they could suspend Giambi and still prevail in the likelihood that Giambi initiated a grievance hearing. Union lawyers are confident that Giambi would win such a hearing.</p>
        <p>The Mitchell investigators have been rebuffed in their attempts to speak to current players. The San Francisco Chronicle reported in 2004 that Giambi's testimony to a federal grand jury investigating the Balco steroid-distribution ring included his admitting to using performance-enhancing drugs.</p>
        <p>Giambi reportedly testified that he had used steroids and human growth hormone before signing a seven-year, $120 million deal with the Yankees in late 2001, and that he also used performance-enhancing substances while with the Yankees in 2002 and 2003. Baseball's testing policy began in 2003, but players were not penalized for a first offense until 2005.</p>
        <p>If Giambi merely repeated what he said during the Balco inquiry, Mitchell would consider it beneficial because it would put that information on the public record. It is possible that Giambi may agree to repeat his testimony. After the Chronicle's article, Giambi apologized for his actions, even though he never specified why he was apologizing.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
