<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Feisty Philanthropist at 100, With a Five-Year Plan</title>
    <meta content="15lives" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/nyregion/15lives.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854618"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Kathryn W. Davis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Scenic Hudson</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Davis, Shelby Cullom Sr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFDD153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Feisty Philanthropist at 100, With a Five-Year Plan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Feisty Philanthropist at 100, With a Five-Year Plan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN FINN</byline>
      <dateline>Tarrytown</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PRECEDED by the authoritative tap of her stylish blue-and-white cane, and trailed by an animated Maltese typecast as doggie-in-waiting to a spry centenarian, Kathryn W. Davis, pacifist and adventurer, methodically descends the imposing staircase of Broad Oak, her bluff-top colonial overlooking her beloved Hudson River. How beloved? She is celebrating her centenary this year by giving it ''a little gift'' of $20 million. The trip from the second floor, where she keeps an easel at the foot of her bed and paints water-dominated landscapes -- she's a Pisces -- in two-hour bursts, is silent, except for an encouraging yip or two.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Davis, the widow of Shelby Cullom Davis, the innovative Wall Street financier (he transformed a $100,000 investment in 1947 into $848 million in capital by 1993), economics adviser to Thomas E. Dewey's 1940 and 1944 presidential campaigns, and United States ambassador to Switzerland during the Nixon administration, apologizes for going slowly on the stairs. And for using a cane. Its constant presence is a consequence of breaking a hip on the tennis court back in her 90s.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Centenarian Kathryn W. Davis is donating $20 million to the effort to preserve of the Hudson River.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PRECEDED by the authoritative tap of her stylish blue-and-white cane, and trailed by an animated Maltese typecast as doggie-in-waiting to a spry centenarian, Kathryn W. Davis, pacifist and adventurer, methodically descends the imposing staircase of Broad Oak, her bluff-top colonial overlooking her beloved Hudson River. How beloved? She is celebrating her centenary this year by giving it ''a little gift'' of $20 million. The trip from the second floor, where she keeps an easel at the foot of her bed and paints water-dominated landscapes -- she's a Pisces -- in two-hour bursts, is silent, except for an encouraging yip or two.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Davis, the widow of Shelby Cullom Davis, the innovative Wall Street financier (he transformed a $100,000 investment in 1947 into $848 million in capital by 1993), economics adviser to Thomas E. Dewey's 1940 and 1944 presidential campaigns, and United States ambassador to Switzerland during the Nixon administration, apologizes for going slowly on the stairs. And for using a cane. Its constant presence is a consequence of breaking a hip on the tennis court back in her 90s.</p>
        <p>''I have a cane for every costume, all of them gifts,'' she says cockily, holding her complementary cane against her blue-and-white embroidered tunic. ''I started out doing it just for fashion, but now it's a necessity for keeping my balance. If you live to be a hundred, you'll understand.'' One can only hope.</p>
        <p>She arrives at the bottom intact and barely winded. Evidently the rumors about her prowess paddling a kayak in Cold Spring and peddling a bicycle at her winter home on Jupiter Island in Florida aren't hyperbole. She is a headstrong great-grandmother with ''two children, eight grands and seven great-grands.'' She candidly adds, ''I had a third child, Priscilla, but they gave me too much ether in the delivery room and it went from me into her and killed her.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Davis, who like her husband received a Ph.D from the University of Geneva in 1934, says, ''I was delighted to get married and have children; it was the best kind of job.''</p>
        <p>As for making the grand gesture -- by age 4 she was waving flags at suffragist parades, and after graduating from Wellesley College in 1928 she hopped a rickety flight (her first) from Finland to Leningrad for an anthropologic jaunt into the rugged Caucasus Mountains -- she's still at it.</p>
        <p>HER only concession to turning 100 in February was to compile a five-year-plan, ''because 105 is how long I think I should live, and everybody told me that when I got to be 100, I should do whatever I want. One thing I want to do is save the Hudson River, see it accessible and swimmable and green along the banks: parks are the lungs for people living in the city or anywhere.'' The Shelby Cullom Davis Foundation is her conduit.</p>
        <p>Hence her $20 million gift to Scenic Hudson Inc., an environmental organization dedicated, as she is, to the proposition that the Hudson River Valley is a natural treasure to be preserved forever, not paved over for profit. The gift, being announced today at a ceremony accompanied by a speech from Mrs. Davis (she delivered her last public oration in 2006 while accepting the Woodrow Wilson Award for Public Service in Washington) will enable Scenic Hudson to extend its necklace of 40 riverfront parks and renovate the historic bathhouse at Kingsland Point Park in Sleepy Hollow. Scenic Hudson, whose board includes her grandson Chris, estimates that $1 billion is required to preserve 100,000 acres of threatened land along the Hudson from Westchester County to Albany.</p>
        <p>''They say money is the root of all evil, but it can be the root of good things, too, and I hope that's what mine will do,'' she says. Her other plans for her personal centenary: ''100 Projects for Peace,'' which awards $10,000 each to student projects formulated to promote peace; and a foreign-language program, administered by Middlebury College, that gives $10,000 scholarships to students who master Arabic, Chinese, Russian or other languages outside the traditional curriculum of Romance languages and German.</p>
        <p>She subscribes to the theory that war should be outlawed as a means of settling disputes. ''I had to keep quiet and hope Nixon was right, but I felt he was wrong,'' she says of her husband's tenure as an ambassador during the Vietnam War.</p>
        <p>''I'm a little surprised to be giving away $20 million,'' she adds, sipping minted iced tea, ''but I trust Scenic Hudson will be careful and won't throw it around, won't let it fall into wrack and ruin, into the hands of the Trumps of the world.''</p>
        <p>Along with a thistledown of pastel hair -- ''It's a rinse; plain white hair is too stark at this age,'' she says of its apricot hue -- held back by pearl barrettes, she still has plenty of pep, much of it verbal. When Mrs. Davis bumped into Donald Trump at a civic function, she informed him that delighted as she was to meet him, she did not ever wish him to become her neighbor lest he build a skyscraper and block her river vistas. Mr. Trump gallantly replied that he would do no such thing. Sure you would, she replied tartly.</p>
        <p>She grew up in Philadelphia, where her father ran Art Loom, a carpet manufacturer. The family traveled extensively in Europe and Asia, and besides cultivating an appreciation for fine art and textiles, her itinerary cultivated her political conscience. When she made the first of her 25 trips to Russia, her father was afraid she would return a Communist. Not exactly. ''I voted for Norman Thomas when I got back; he was the Socialist candidate.'' Her father was furious. Her mother applauded.</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
