<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES: June 15 - June 21; For Children</title>
    <meta content="15kids" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/arts/15kids.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854510"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E2D6143FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1732" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES: June 15 - June 21; For Children</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spare Times: For Children</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAUREL GRAEBER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'ADVENTURES NYC' (Tomorrow) Pitching a tent in the backyard isn't an option for most Manhattan children. But tomorrow the Parks and Recreation Department will try to make at least part of the borough seem more like Yellowstone than like the land of the yellow cab. The occasion is the third annual ''Adventures NYC,'' which will turn a wide swath of Central Park into a huge campground. (Other city parks will also sponsor events.) Base camp is the Bandshell, and activities will include kayaking, rock climbing and hiking. From noon to 4 p.m., midpark at 70th Street; free. Information: 311; nyc.gov/parks.</p>
        <p>'AN AFRICAN VILLAGE: POSTCARDS FROM POTOU' (Tomorrow and Sunday) These postcards will be written with the feet, as 200 children who are advanced team dancers for National Dance Institute display choreography that celebrates the young of Potou, a town in Senegal. The performances include hip-hop and jazz as well as African-inspired dance. Tomorrow at 3 and 6 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., La Guardia High School Concert Hall, 100 Amsterdam Avenue, at 65th Street, (212) 352-3101, nationaldance.org; $10 in advance, $15 at the door.</p>
        <p>ALL STARS HIP-HOP CABARET (Tonight and tomorrow) This evening by and for teenagers and young adults -- with song, dance and rap about growing up in the city's poorer neighborhoods -- also offers work by seasoned artists, including an excerpt from ''Sally &amp; Tom (the American Way),'' a musical by Fred Newman about Thomas Jefferson and his slave Sally Hemings. At 7, the All Stars Project, 543 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 941-1234; $25; $10 for students.</p>
        <p>CIRCUS SUNDAYS IN JUNE (Sunday) Brooklyn not only has a floating concert hall (Bargemusic), it also has a floating circus. This attraction, on board the Waterfront Museum and Showboat Barge, presents different entertainers every Sunday of the month. This Sunday's roster includes the Mermaidens, sisters who perform on trapeze; Nathalie Enterline, a dancer; Gordoon, a clown; and Carlo Pellegrini, a jack of all trades. At 1 and 4 p.m., Conover Street and the waterfront, Red Hook, (877) 238-5596, waterfrontmuseum.org. Tickets: in advance, $12; $6 for under 12. At the door, $15 and $8.</p>
        <p>'DEAR OLD DAD' (Tomorrow) Father's Day was invented for two-legged dads, but the furry, four-legged kind (and some feathered ones too) will all receive their due at this event at the Staten Island Zoo. In addition to viewing animal fathers, children will create crafts for their human ones. From 1:30 to 3:30 p.m., 614 Broadway, West Brighton, (718) 442-3174, statenislandzoo.org. Free with admission: $7; $5 for 60+; $4 for 3 through 14; free for under 3.</p>
        <p>FATHER'S DAY WEEKEND AT THE BRONX ZOO (Tomorrow and Sunday) Speaking of nonhuman fathers, the Bronx Zoo will highlight two who are people's close cousins: Fubo and Zuri, silverback gorillas. Families can also see other animal parents (and offspring) and enjoy theme activities: making a Father's Day tie, playing ring toss, running three-legged races and hearing music by John Farrell. On Sunday only, Asheba, an artist from Trinidad, will also offer a concert in conjunction with the Putumayo Kids ''Animal Playground'' tour (see below). From 11 a.m. to 4:30 p.m., Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road, Fordham, (718) 367-1010, bronxzoo.com. Free with admission: $14; $12 for 65+; $10 for 3 to 12; free for under 3. Parking, $10.</p>
        <p>'FEELIN' GOOD' (Tomorrow) There will be plenty of reasons to feel good at this concert: It's free, it's fun, and it represents a wonderful project: the satellite schools program of the Young People's Chorus, in which teaching artists from the chorus train public school students in vocal technique and reading and writing music. Two divisions of the chorus will also participate with the schoolchildren in the event; selections range from Cole Porter to folk songs. At 4 p.m., the 92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, ypc.org.</p>
        <p>FLOWER TOWER (Tomorrow) Towers will definitely flower, although not necessarily from blossoms, in this workshop for children 7 to 12 at the Skyscraper Museum. Participants will first learn about the exhibition ''World's Tallest Building: Burj Dubai,'' which centers on the massive project under construction in the United Arab Emirates. With everyday objects as inspiration, they will then design their own towers. From 10:30 to 11:30 a.m., 39 Battery Place, Lower Manhattan, (212) 945-6324, skyscraper.org/family; free, but registration is required.</p>
        <p>'THE GAZILLION BUBBLE SHOW' (Tonight through Sunday, and Wednesday and Thursday) Children love bubbles, and Fan Yang, in his interactive show, promises not just a gazillion, but also some of the largest ever blown (he holds the world record), along with light effects and lasers. (Through Sept 2.) Tonight at 7; tomorrow at 11 a.m. and 2 and 7 p.m.; Sunday at noon and 3 p.m.; Wednesday at 2 and 7 p.m.; Thursday at 7 p.m. New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200, gazillionbubbleshow.com; $40, $50 and $60.</p>
        <p>'THE JUNGLE BOOK' (Tomorrow and Sunday) This Mowgli shouldn't have any trouble swinging through the jungle; he's on strings anyway. Puppetworks has adapted Rudyard Kipling's tales into a marionette production featuring traditional Indian motifs. (Through Aug. 19.) At 12:30 and 2:30 p.m., 338 Sixth Avenue, at Fourth Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-3391, puppetworks.org; $8; $7 for 15 and under.</p>
        <p>'LOVE'S LABOUR'S LOST' AND FREE SHAKESPEARE WORKSHOPS (Tomorrow and Sunday) Where else can you find a Shakespearean theater that welcomes infants, children and dogs? This one is Central Park, where New York Classical Theater presents outdoor productions at which the actors change location with each scene. This weekend and next the company is also offering preshow Shakespeare workshops for 8- to 10-year-olds, in which the children will do theatrical warm-up exercises, play games and even perform a scene with actors. Take a picnic, and sneakers. Workshops at 5 p.m. (children must be accompanied by an adult), performances at 7 p.m., in the park at West 103rd Street and Central Park West, (212) 252-4531; free. (The play alone is also being performed tonight at 7.)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK FAMILY ARTS FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday) Unity in diversity is certainly possible, and it is being celebrated at this monthlong event, which focuses on the multicultural arts of the city. Tonight at 7 the Forces of Nature Dance Theater Company will perform, and tomorrow from noon to 7 p.m., the festival's Trinidad and Tobago Cultural Village will feature workshops in carnival arts, Afro-Caribbean dance, stilt-walking and percussion. On Sunday at 2 p.m., Dr. Glory's Youth Theater will perform ''Year of NOW,'' a puppet play in which good battles evil. At the Riverside Theater, Riverside Avenue at 122nd Street, Morningside Heights. Free, but reservations requested: (212) 870-6784.</p>
        <p>'PINKALICIOUS' (Tomorrow) Sometimes being in the pink can be too much of a good thing, as the pink-obsessed title character finds out in this new musical from Vital Children's Theater, which Elizabeth and Victoria Kann adapted from their children's book. (Extended through June 30.) At noon, SoHo Playhouse, 15 Van Dam Street, near Varick Street, South Village, (212) 691-1555, sohoplayhouse.com; $25 (reservations advised).</p>
        <p>PUTUMAYO KIDS PRESENTS: THE 'ANIMAL PLAYGROUND' TOUR (Today through Sunday) Animals are also global citizens, and this tour from the family division of Putumayo World Music celebrates the release of ''Animal Playground,'' a CD featuring multilingual tunes about creatures. Asheba, a performer from Trinidad, will sing songs from the album today at 11:30 a.m. at the Children's Museum of Manhattan (212-721-1223, cmom.org); tomorrow at 11 a.m. at Bank Street Books (212-678-1654, bankstreet.edu) and at 3 p.m. at the American Museum of Natural History (212-769-5200, amnh.org); and on Sunday at 1 p.m. at the Bronx Zoo (718-367-1010, bronxzoo.com). Free with the site's admission, except at Bank Street: $8; $5 for 12 and under.</p>
        <p>SAMBA AND SEA LIONS (Tomorrow) Samba is so catchy that everyone seems to want to move to it, and that includes Stella, Alexis and Beebe, the sea lions at the Prospect Park Zoo. A Brazilian samba drum ensemble will provide the music, and actors from the zoo's Wildlife Theater will join the samba line, but don't be surprised if they're upstaged by the sea lions. From noon to 3 p.m., 450 Flatbush Avenue, Prospect Park, Brooklyn, (718) 399-7339, prospectparkzoo.com. Free with zoo admission: $6; $2.25 for 65+; $1 for 3 to 12; free for under 3.</p>
        <p>'SHERLOCK HOLMES TAKES THE CASE' (Tonight) Holmes won't be the only one following clues in this production from the Traveling Lantern Theater Company; children in the audience will help him solve the mystery. The case should be elementary -- but still a bit of a challenge -- for sleuths who are at least 4. At 6:30 p.m., the New York Public Library, Roosevelt Island Branch, 524 Main Street, Manhattan, (212) 308-6243; free.</p>
        <p>STATEN ISLAND CHILDREN'S MUSEUM FAMILY FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) You can expect both health information and a few not-so-healthy pleasures (cotton candy and snow cones) at this annual event, sponsored by Health Plus, a managed-care organization. In addition to games and crafts, the fair will include the New York Bloodmobile, information from health organizations and demonstrations by the Police and Fire Departments. From noon to 4 p.m., the museum's East Meadow, 1000 Richmond Terrace, Livingston, (718) 273-2060, statenislandkids.org; free.</p>
        <p>'A TALE OF TWO CITIES' (Tomorrow and Sunday) Mme. Defarge knits, the tumbrels roll, and love and death are evoked again in Dwayne Hartford's adaptation of Dickens's novel. The production is part of New Plays for Young Audiences, a series of staged readings sponsored by the Program in Educational Theater at the Steinhardt School of Culture, Education and Human Development at New York University. Tomorrow at 3 and 7:30 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., the Provincetown Playhouse, 133 Macdougal Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 998-5867; $5; free for high school students and children.</p>
        <p>TARGET CHILDREN'S DAY AND FIREWORKS (Tomorrow and Sunday) This family festival returns for its 14th incarnation. Roscoe Orman (Gordon from ''Sesame Street'') will be the host, and the many acts tomorrow (the day of the main festival) include AudraRox, the rock band; Lisa Brescia from ''Wicked''; and John Lithgow in his children's singer persona. Tomorrow night at 8 the Brooklyn Philharmonic will perform Handel's ''Music for the Royal Fireworks'' (accompanied by real fireworks), and Sunday at 6 the band the Jonas Brothers will perform. Tomorrow from noon to 5 p.m., Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan, (212) 732-7678, childrensdaynyc.com; free.</p>
        <p>LAUREL GRAEBER</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR CHILDREN.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'ADVENTURES NYC' (Tomorrow) Pitching a tent in the backyard isn't an option for most Manhattan children. But tomorrow the Parks and Recreation Department will try to make at least part of the borough seem more like Yellowstone than like the land of the yellow cab. The occasion is the third annual ''Adventures NYC,'' which will turn a wide swath of Central Park into a huge campground. (Other city parks will also sponsor events.) Base camp is the Bandshell, and activities will include kayaking, rock climbing and hiking. From noon to 4 p.m., midpark at 70th Street; free. Information: 311; nyc.gov/parks.</p>
        <p>'AN AFRICAN VILLAGE: POSTCARDS FROM POTOU' (Tomorrow and Sunday) These postcards will be written with the feet, as 200 children who are advanced team dancers for National Dance Institute display choreography that celebrates the young of Potou, a town in Senegal. The performances include hip-hop and jazz as well as African-inspired dance. Tomorrow at 3 and 6 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., La Guardia High School Concert Hall, 100 Amsterdam Avenue, at 65th Street, (212) 352-3101, nationaldance.org; $10 in advance, $15 at the door.</p>
        <p>ALL STARS HIP-HOP CABARET (Tonight and tomorrow) This evening by and for teenagers and young adults -- with song, dance and rap about growing up in the city's poorer neighborhoods -- also offers work by seasoned artists, including an excerpt from ''Sally &amp; Tom (the American Way),'' a musical by Fred Newman about Thomas Jefferson and his slave Sally Hemings. At 7, the All Stars Project, 543 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 941-1234; $25; $10 for students.</p>
        <p>CIRCUS SUNDAYS IN JUNE (Sunday) Brooklyn not only has a floating concert hall (Bargemusic), it also has a floating circus. This attraction, on board the Waterfront Museum and Showboat Barge, presents different entertainers every Sunday of the month. This Sunday's roster includes the Mermaidens, sisters who perform on trapeze; Nathalie Enterline, a dancer; Gordoon, a clown; and Carlo Pellegrini, a jack of all trades. At 1 and 4 p.m., Conover Street and the waterfront, Red Hook, (877) 238-5596, waterfrontmuseum.org. Tickets: in advance, $12; $6 for under 12. At the door, $15 and $8.</p>
        <p>'DEAR OLD DAD' (Tomorrow) Father's Day was invented for two-legged dads, but the furry, four-legged kind (and some feathered ones too) will all receive their due at this event at the Staten Island Zoo. In addition to viewing animal fathers, children will create crafts for their human ones. From 1:30 to 3:30 p.m., 614 Broadway, West Brighton, (718) 442-3174, statenislandzoo.org. Free with admission: $7; $5 for 60+; $4 for 3 through 14; free for under 3.</p>
        <p>FATHER'S DAY WEEKEND AT THE BRONX ZOO (Tomorrow and Sunday) Speaking of nonhuman fathers, the Bronx Zoo will highlight two who are people's close cousins: Fubo and Zuri, silverback gorillas. Families can also see other animal parents (and offspring) and enjoy theme activities: making a Father's Day tie, playing ring toss, running three-legged races and hearing music by John Farrell. On Sunday only, Asheba, an artist from Trinidad, will also offer a concert in conjunction with the Putumayo Kids ''Animal Playground'' tour (see below). From 11 a.m. to 4:30 p.m., Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road, Fordham, (718) 367-1010, bronxzoo.com. Free with admission: $14; $12 for 65+; $10 for 3 to 12; free for under 3. Parking, $10.</p>
        <p>'FEELIN' GOOD' (Tomorrow) There will be plenty of reasons to feel good at this concert: It's free, it's fun, and it represents a wonderful project: the satellite schools program of the Young People's Chorus, in which teaching artists from the chorus train public school students in vocal technique and reading and writing music. Two divisions of the chorus will also participate with the schoolchildren in the event; selections range from Cole Porter to folk songs. At 4 p.m., the 92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, ypc.org.</p>
        <p>FLOWER TOWER (Tomorrow) Towers will definitely flower, although not necessarily from blossoms, in this workshop for children 7 to 12 at the Skyscraper Museum. Participants will first learn about the exhibition ''World's Tallest Building: Burj Dubai,'' which centers on the massive project under construction in the United Arab Emirates. With everyday objects as inspiration, they will then design their own towers. From 10:30 to 11:30 a.m., 39 Battery Place, Lower Manhattan, (212) 945-6324, skyscraper.org/family; free, but registration is required.</p>
        <p>'THE GAZILLION BUBBLE SHOW' (Tonight through Sunday, and Wednesday and Thursday) Children love bubbles, and Fan Yang, in his interactive show, promises not just a gazillion, but also some of the largest ever blown (he holds the world record), along with light effects and lasers. (Through Sept 2.) Tonight at 7; tomorrow at 11 a.m. and 2 and 7 p.m.; Sunday at noon and 3 p.m.; Wednesday at 2 and 7 p.m.; Thursday at 7 p.m. New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200, gazillionbubbleshow.com; $40, $50 and $60.</p>
        <p>'THE JUNGLE BOOK' (Tomorrow and Sunday) This Mowgli shouldn't have any trouble swinging through the jungle; he's on strings anyway. Puppetworks has adapted Rudyard Kipling's tales into a marionette production featuring traditional Indian motifs. (Through Aug. 19.) At 12:30 and 2:30 p.m., 338 Sixth Avenue, at Fourth Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-3391, puppetworks.org; $8; $7 for 15 and under.</p>
        <p>'LOVE'S LABOUR'S LOST' AND FREE SHAKESPEARE WORKSHOPS (Tomorrow and Sunday) Where else can you find a Shakespearean theater that welcomes infants, children and dogs? This one is Central Park, where New York Classical Theater presents outdoor productions at which the actors change location with each scene. This weekend and next the company is also offering preshow Shakespeare workshops for 8- to 10-year-olds, in which the children will do theatrical warm-up exercises, play games and even perform a scene with actors. Take a picnic, and sneakers. Workshops at 5 p.m. (children must be accompanied by an adult), performances at 7 p.m., in the park at West 103rd Street and Central Park West, (212) 252-4531; free. (The play alone is also being performed tonight at 7.)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK FAMILY ARTS FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday) Unity in diversity is certainly possible, and it is being celebrated at this monthlong event, which focuses on the multicultural arts of the city. Tonight at 7 the Forces of Nature Dance Theater Company will perform, and tomorrow from noon to 7 p.m., the festival's Trinidad and Tobago Cultural Village will feature workshops in carnival arts, Afro-Caribbean dance, stilt-walking and percussion. On Sunday at 2 p.m., Dr. Glory's Youth Theater will perform ''Year of NOW,'' a puppet play in which good battles evil. At the Riverside Theater, Riverside Avenue at 122nd Street, Morningside Heights. Free, but reservations requested: (212) 870-6784.</p>
        <p>'PINKALICIOUS' (Tomorrow) Sometimes being in the pink can be too much of a good thing, as the pink-obsessed title character finds out in this new musical from Vital Children's Theater, which Elizabeth and Victoria Kann adapted from their children's book. (Extended through June 30.) At noon, SoHo Playhouse, 15 Van Dam Street, near Varick Street, South Village, (212) 691-1555, sohoplayhouse.com; $25 (reservations advised).</p>
        <p>PUTUMAYO KIDS PRESENTS: THE 'ANIMAL PLAYGROUND' TOUR (Today through Sunday) Animals are also global citizens, and this tour from the family division of Putumayo World Music celebrates the release of ''Animal Playground,'' a CD featuring multilingual tunes about creatures. Asheba, a performer from Trinidad, will sing songs from the album today at 11:30 a.m. at the Children's Museum of Manhattan (212-721-1223, cmom.org); tomorrow at 11 a.m. at Bank Street Books (212-678-1654, bankstreet.edu) and at 3 p.m. at the American Museum of Natural History (212-769-5200, amnh.org); and on Sunday at 1 p.m. at the Bronx Zoo (718-367-1010, bronxzoo.com). Free with the site's admission, except at Bank Street: $8; $5 for 12 and under.</p>
        <p>SAMBA AND SEA LIONS (Tomorrow) Samba is so catchy that everyone seems to want to move to it, and that includes Stella, Alexis and Beebe, the sea lions at the Prospect Park Zoo. A Brazilian samba drum ensemble will provide the music, and actors from the zoo's Wildlife Theater will join the samba line, but don't be surprised if they're upstaged by the sea lions. From noon to 3 p.m., 450 Flatbush Avenue, Prospect Park, Brooklyn, (718) 399-7339, prospectparkzoo.com. Free with zoo admission: $6; $2.25 for 65+; $1 for 3 to 12; free for under 3.</p>
        <p>'SHERLOCK HOLMES TAKES THE CASE' (Tonight) Holmes won't be the only one following clues in this production from the Traveling Lantern Theater Company; children in the audience will help him solve the mystery. The case should be elementary -- but still a bit of a challenge -- for sleuths who are at least 4. At 6:30 p.m., the New York Public Library, Roosevelt Island Branch, 524 Main Street, Manhattan, (212) 308-6243; free.</p>
        <p>STATEN ISLAND CHILDREN'S MUSEUM FAMILY FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) You can expect both health information and a few not-so-healthy pleasures (cotton candy and snow cones) at this annual event, sponsored by Health Plus, a managed-care organization. In addition to games and crafts, the fair will include the New York Bloodmobile, information from health organizations and demonstrations by the Police and Fire Departments. From noon to 4 p.m., the museum's East Meadow, 1000 Richmond Terrace, Livingston, (718) 273-2060, statenislandkids.org; free.</p>
        <p>'A TALE OF TWO CITIES' (Tomorrow and Sunday) Mme. Defarge knits, the tumbrels roll, and love and death are evoked again in Dwayne Hartford's adaptation of Dickens's novel. The production is part of New Plays for Young Audiences, a series of staged readings sponsored by the Program in Educational Theater at the Steinhardt School of Culture, Education and Human Development at New York University. Tomorrow at 3 and 7:30 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., the Provincetown Playhouse, 133 Macdougal Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 998-5867; $5; free for high school students and children.</p>
        <p>TARGET CHILDREN'S DAY AND FIREWORKS (Tomorrow and Sunday) This family festival returns for its 14th incarnation. Roscoe Orman (Gordon from ''Sesame Street'') will be the host, and the many acts tomorrow (the day of the main festival) include AudraRox, the rock band; Lisa Brescia from ''Wicked''; and John Lithgow in his children's singer persona. Tomorrow night at 8 the Brooklyn Philharmonic will perform Handel's ''Music for the Royal Fireworks'' (accompanied by real fireworks), and Sunday at 6 the band the Jonas Brothers will perform. Tomorrow from noon to 5 p.m., Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan, (212) 732-7678, childrensdaynyc.com; free.</p>
        <p>LAUREL GRAEBER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
