<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senate Leader Criticizes Performance of Joint Chiefs Leader</title>
    <meta content="15reid" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854576"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zeleny, Jeff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reid, Harry (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pace, Peter (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Petraeus, David H (Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E7DD153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="510" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senate Leader Criticizes Performance of Joint Chiefs Leader</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF ZELENY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zeleny, Jeff</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen Harry Reid, majority leader, demands that Congress be given 'fair, honest and frank' report about conditions in Iraq and says Gen Peter Pace, outgoing chairman of Joint Chiefs of Staff, was never 'candid' about conduct and progress of war; White House, which just announced that Pace would not be reappointed to second term, rejects Reid's comments, and Republicans in Congress say Reid crossed line by openly questioning whether Gen David H Petraeus, top American commander in Iraq, would deliver honest report to Congress; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Harry Reid, the majority leader, delivered a critical assessment on Thursday of Gen. Peter Pace's performance as chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff and demanded that Congress be given a ''fair, honest and frank'' report about conditions in Iraq when it receives a progress report in September.</p>
        <p>''General Peter Pace is a distinguished military veteran and public servant,'' Mr. Reid said. ''Unfortunately, in my opinion, he was never as candid as he should have been about the conduct and progress of this war.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator Harry Reid, the majority leader, delivered a critical assessment on Thursday of Gen. Peter Pace's performance as chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff and demanded that Congress be given a ''fair, honest and frank'' report about conditions in Iraq when it receives a progress report in September.</p>
        <p>''General Peter Pace is a distinguished military veteran and public servant,'' Mr. Reid said. ''Unfortunately, in my opinion, he was never as candid as he should have been about the conduct and progress of this war.''</p>
        <p>The White House, which announced last week that General Pace would not be reappointed to a second term, forcefully rejected the comments by Mr. Reid, a Nevada Democrat. Republicans in Congress joined in the criticism, saying Mr. Reid had also crossed a line by openly questioning whether Gen. David H. Petraeus, the top American commander in Iraq, would deliver an honest report to Congress.</p>
        <p>''In a time of war, for a leader of a party that says it supports the military, it seems outrageous to be issuing slanders toward the chairman of the Joint Chiefs and also the man that is responsible for the bulk of military operations in Iraq,'' said Tony Snow, the White House spokesman.</p>
        <p>Congressional Democrats, facing increasing pressure to respond to the antiwar sentiment in their party, have told Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates that they intended to challenge General Pace if he was nominated to serve a second term as chairman. He is the highest-ranking officer to become a political casualty of the Iraq war.</p>
        <p>Hoping to avoid a confirmation fight, Mr. Gates announced last week that Adm. Michael G. Mullen, the chief of naval operations, would be nominated as the next Joint Chiefs chairman. In his statement on Thursday, Mr. Reid singled out Admiral Mullen, too, calling on him to ''speak up and pull no punches'' if he is confirmed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reid's comments came after he drew unusually harsh criticism from the White House after a report by The Politico, a Washington newspaper, that he had suggested that General Pace was ''incompetent.'' Aides to Mr. Reid would neither confirm nor deny whether he had used that characterization of General Pace during a telephone conference call earlier this week with liberal bloggers.</p>
        <p>Senator John McCain, an Arizona Republican who is seeking his party's presidential nomination, called on Mr. Reid to ''clarify his criticisms, which can only be described as highly inappropriate and regrettable.''</p>
        <p>As the back-and-forth intensified, Mr. Reid and other Democrats made plans to open a new Congressional debate on Iraq as early as next week. Among the plans being considered, aides said, is to debate legislation to revoke the president's original war authorization.</p>
        <p>''It is incumbent upon the president, the Pentagon and our commanders in the field to give us the information that we need to hear, not what we want to hear,'' Mr. Reid said. ''It is the only way we in Congress will be able to make the right decisions as we work to change course in Iraq and responsibly end this war.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
