<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Climbing to the Upper Decks (Before They're Torn Down)</title>
    <meta content="15chea" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/arts/15chea.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854613"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CHEAP SEATS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFDD153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1297" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Climbing to the Upper Decks (Before They're Torn Down)</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Climbing to the Upper Decks (Before They’re Torn Down)</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SISARIO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>UP in the distant, thin-air seats of Shea Stadium, where the sky-splitting peal of airplanes taking off from La Guardia seems even more terrifying than on the field level below, I had a clear view across the park to the forest of cranes in the neighboring lot. The Mets' $600 million new stadium has been under construction since last summer, and though it is still only a concrete skeleton, I couldn't help but think as I clutched my $9 nosebleed ticket: It looks awfully expensive out there.</p>
        <p>As the Mets and the Yankees begin their three-game Subway Series tonight in the Bronx, both teams are building big-money homes. The Yankees are expecting to spend $800 million on a new stadium, also right next to their current one. The ballparks are to open two seasons from now, with plans to reduce overall capacity while maximizing high-roller sky boxes and club seats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a frugal baseball fan smitten with the romance of the old parks, it’s an ideal time to make a sweep through the fields.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>UP in the distant, thin-air seats of Shea Stadium, where the sky-splitting peal of airplanes taking off from La Guardia seems even more terrifying than on the field level below, I had a clear view across the park to the forest of cranes in the neighboring lot. The Mets' $600 million new stadium has been under construction since last summer, and though it is still only a concrete skeleton, I couldn't help but think as I clutched my $9 nosebleed ticket: It looks awfully expensive out there.</p>
        <p>As the Mets and the Yankees begin their three-game Subway Series tonight in the Bronx, both teams are building big-money homes. The Yankees are expecting to spend $800 million on a new stadium, also right next to their current one. The ballparks are to open two seasons from now, with plans to reduce overall capacity while maximizing high-roller sky boxes and club seats.</p>
        <p>Both teams have said they will retain plenty of inexpensive seating. But for a frugal baseball fan smitten with the romance of the old parks -- and also curious about the going rates for bleacher seats, popcorn and Cracker Jack -- it's an ideal time to make a sweep through the fields. (For especially parsimonious followers, the local minor league season begins Tuesday with another series doable by mass transit, if not the subway: The Staten Island Yankees head to KeySpan Park in Coney Island to play the Brooklyn Cyclones. Bleacher tickets there cost half what they do in Yankee Stadium.)</p>
        <p>Baseball allegiances are handed down by blood, like religious affiliation. In my case I am a Yankees fan. Growing up I watched as Phil Rizzuto called the games on Channel 11, and one of my most cherished memories is a trip with my father, brother and uncle to see a Red Sox game at Yankee Stadium on July 4, 1983. We had field-level, first-base-side seats as Dave Righetti pitched the Yankees' first no-hitter in 27 years. I vividly recall the ecstatic thunder of the crowd when Righetti doffed his hat at the end of the game.</p>
        <p>I got a taste of Mets fans' cries of triumph (and groans of defeat) on June 7 against the Phillies. The pricing scheme at Shea is divided into five ''game categories''; this game was in the ''bronze,'' or second-cheapest group, with the top price set at $62 and the lowest, for the upper decks and the back rows of the loge and mezzanine levels, at $9. (Shea has a small bleachers section in left field, but it's only for large groups.)</p>
        <p>I was in Section 2, Row M, of the upper deck, behind home plate and about halfway up the slope. The view was decent if a little remote, but not long after the first batter (pop-up to left field), I had to get out of there. Within the first eight minutes of the game seven shouting vendors passed before me -- ''Peanuts!'' ''Hot dogs!'' ''Soda!'' ''Cotton candy!'' -- and I found myself stuck between loud packs of Mets and Phillies fans engaged in a crude but highly focused debate over which team was worse.</p>
        <p>Seeking quiet, and to avoid giving into temptation for a $7.25 beer, I made my way to the upper rim, where my only company was the salty old guys scoring the game; they didn't say a word. Up there I caught the full view of the stadium and beyond, with the new ballpark -- Citi Field, thanks to a $20 million-a-year sponsorship from Citigroup -- looming just past the scoreboard. But as picturesque a vista as the rooftops of Flushing may be, by the bottom of the fourth I couldn't resist trying to steal a base of my own, and made it with ease into a seat on the third-base side of the loge worth $36.</p>
        <p>The otherwise uneventful evening had a feverish, three-homer outburst in the bottom of the sixth. A drive by the Mets' third baseman David Wright hit a sign above the fence in left-center field, and after it was ruled a home run, Phillies Manager Charlie Manuel promptly stormed out and protested right in the face of the first-base umpire, Jerry Layne. When Layne threw him out with an angry stabbing gesture, a deafening, bloodthirsty roar erupted all around the stadium, as if Caesar himself had given the thumbs-down to a particularly hated gladiator. The din quieted to a grumble in the 10th inning as the Phillies took the game 6-3.</p>
        <p>Yankee Stadium has one of the great budget traditions in baseball, the ring of 5,450 bleacher seats stretching across the outfield, time-honored home of the rowdy and the penny-pinching. Long sold only on game day, bleacher tickets can now be bought in advance, and go for $12, 50 percent more than they cost in 2000, when beer sales were banned to curb drunken fights.</p>
        <p>Bleacher tickets can sell out quickly, and when I checked a few weeks before last weekend's games against Pittsburgh, none were available. But it took only a few days of persistence on the Yankees' Web site to nab them: a pleasant surprise, since Saturday afternoon's game featured one of the most anticipated events of the season, the return of Roger Clemens.</p>
        <p>As I entered the bleacher section on River Avenue beneath the elevated tracks for the No. 4 subway -- the section is segregated from the rest of the stadium -- the guards made it clear that I and my fellow $12 ticketholders were no V.I.P.'s. It was free-hat day, and as one man unceremoniously handed out blue caps from a cardboard box another looked straight ahead and barked as if we were prisoners getting our daily gruel: ''Get your hat and move on.''</p>
        <p>But inside the park the experience is more like being part of a mass church. Yankee Stadium is the temple of a warrior cult with a century of mostly good fortune, and proud reminders of triumph and tradition are everywhere: banners proclaiming the 26 World Series victories, the regal white frieze above the bleacher billboards, Monument Park with its shrine of 16 retired numbers. There is even a deity. Bob Sheppard, who has been announcing Yankee games since 1951 with calm authority, was called the ''voice of God'' by Reggie Jackson.</p>
        <p>The atmosphere in the peanut gallery can't be called calm however. Last weekend's games began, as all do, with the right-field ''bleacher creatures'' chanting their roll call of the Yankees' opening lineup. (They also offered some off-color chants to the box seats.) And on Sunday a man halfway back in Section 43 led relentless heckling of the Pirates' center fielder Chris Duffy. After three innings he went too far and was ejected by the police. As he walked off to approving applause, I could see the dozen or so 10-to-12-year-old boys sitting near me alight with inspiration. Before they were silenced by their chaperones, they were able to get in some good practice at the rude ballpark holler.</p>
        <p>The gods of baseball smiled on the Yankees last weekend, as they won all three games against Pittsburgh. Clemens threw 108 pitches over six innings on Saturday, 69 for strikes, and on Sunday Alex Rodriguez belted two homers. As I left after the game on Sunday afternoon and walked down 161st Street to look at the new stadium taking shape like the unfinished Death Star, I could hear another Yankee tradition that goes back as far as I can remember. Frank Sinatra sang, in words that might apply to the team itself as it prepares to leave the stadium it has occupied since 1923, ''Start spreading the news/I'm leaving today.''</p>
        <p>I hope that in the new stadium the bleacher creatures get all the space they want. And get it cheap.</p>
        <p>CHEAP SEATS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
