<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Reversal of Fortunes for the Yankees and the Mets</title>
    <meta content="15chass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854643"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E2DC153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="939" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Reversal of Fortunes for the Yankees and the Mets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reggie Jackson was in the first class of free agents and began playing for the Yankees in 1977. That was 20 years before the onset of interleague play, so Reggie missed that revolutionary development in Major League Baseball.</p>
        <p>''I don't like interleague play,'' Jackson, a Yankees consultant, said yesterday, but, he quickly added, he would like to have been a part of it, especially when the Yankees played the Mets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Reggie Jackson was in the first class of free agents and began playing for the Yankees in 1977. That was 20 years before the onset of interleague play, so Reggie missed that revolutionary development in Major League Baseball.</p>
        <p>''I don't like interleague play,'' Jackson, a Yankees consultant, said yesterday, but, he quickly added, he would like to have been a part of it, especially when the Yankees played the Mets.</p>
        <p>''Oh, sure, I'd have looked forward to it,'' Jackson said, ticking off the reasons -- ''the inner city, the rivalry, the fan intensity, the importance of it, the excitement of it. Just being a part of it is a privilege. Playing those games is important.''</p>
        <p>When the Yankees and the Mets began their first 2007 interleague series four weeks ago at Shea Stadium, the Mets were in first place in their division by a game and a half and the Yankees were in second place, a distant 9 1/2 games behind Boston in their division.</p>
        <p>As they prepare to play their second and last series of the season beginning tonight at Yankee Stadium, the Mets are still in first place and the Yankees are still in second. Those facts, however, obscure underlying factors that could have an impact on this series.</p>
        <p>The Yankees, who tumbled 14 1/2 games behind Boston in the middle of this four-week interim, go into the series with a 9-game winning streak that had slashed the Red Sox lead over them to 7 1/2 games, after Boston's 7-1 loss to Colorado last night.</p>
        <p>Concurrent with the Yankees' strongest stretch of the season, the Mets have experienced their worst, losing 9 of their last 10 games before mercifully getting a day off yesterday while the Yankees were winning yet another game, a 7-1 decision over Arizona.</p>
        <p>The Mets have maintained their lead over the similarly struggling Atlanta Braves, but they have allowed another challenger, Philadelphia, to join the race.</p>
        <p>Last month, the Mets were the better team going into the series and won the first two games before the Yankees salvaged the third. Could the recent play of the teams have an impact on this series?</p>
        <p>''Yeah, it could,'' said Joe Torre, the Yankees' manager. ''Going in the way things are sitting now, we're probably a more confident team than they are, and we're playing at home. It's sort of the reverse of what it was then. They were a more confident team, they were playing at home and they beat us two out of three.''</p>
        <p>Last season, the Mets had a half-game better record than the Yankees at the start of the first series and won two of three, then lost two of three in the second series even though their record was two games better than the Yankees' record.</p>
        <p>''What Willie's going through now is pretty much what we were going through when we were over there,'' Torre said of Willie Randolph, the Mets' manager and one of his former coaches. ''Obviously, we feel a lot better about ourselves than we did going into the first series.''</p>
        <p>Tony Clark, an Arizona first baseman, played for the Mets against the Yankees in 2003 and played for the Yankees against the Mets in 2004.</p>
        <p>''With the Yankees moreso than with the Mets, those games were important,'' said Clark, who hit two home runs in a game the Yankees lost. ''The series with Tampa Bay and the Red Sox and the Subway Series were very important. Any time I was fortunate enough to make a contribution in any of those series, I was happy.''</p>
        <p>The Diamondbacks, who have one of the best records in the National League, were not thrilled with the three-game sweep by the Yankees.</p>
        <p>''They carried themselves the way championship teams carry themselves, with the expectation on any given night to come out and win a ballgame,'' Clark said. ''We weren't here early on when things weren't going as well as they would have liked, but being here now and watching the way they're playing, I wouldn't have expected them to be 14 1/2 out two weeks ago.''</p>
        <p>Asked if current streaks will matter in the weekend series, Clark said: ''To a certain extent. You'd like to be playing well coming into any series against any team, but over the course of 162 games there's going to be stretches where things aren't going your way.''</p>
        <p>Jackson dismissed the Mets' recent misfortunes as foreshadowing a possible outcome of the weekend series.</p>
        <p>''They're not playing as well as they've been playing,'' he said of the Mets, ''but it doesn't matter. Tomorrow night what you've been doing and how you've been playing, you start with an even slate. They're not going to play bad forever. Everybody thought we were going to play bad forever and they wrote the obits. But that's baseball.''</p>
        <p>Derek Jeter echoed Jackson's view, citing the length of the season and all that can and usually does occur in that six-month marathon.</p>
        <p>''Everybody's going to struggle,'' Jeter said. ''I don't care how good the team is. Everybody's going to have a time when they don't play well. It's not an end-of-the-world situation. It just comes with playing 162 games. We've had bad stretches, too. It's part of the season. You look at the whole season; you don't look at a couple weeks. They played pretty well before that, didn't they?''</p>
        <p>And they will again, the Mets believe.</p>
        <p>''We are planning on showing up,'' said Omar Minaya, the Mets' general manager. ''We know we're going to play a hot team and we haven't been playing good baseball. We'll show up, and we have to play better baseball.''</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
