<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Antiques</title>
    <meta content="15anti" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/arts/design/15anti.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Antiques"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Antiques</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E2D6143FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1026" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Antiques</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Toy Building Sets Are Up for Auction</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Wendy Moonan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Toy Building Sets Are Up for Auction</p>
        <p>''It's architecture in miniature,'' said Paul Neuman, explaining his attraction to antique building toys. ''It's about construction, assembly and materials. These toys are nothing until you build them. They require imagination and dexterity. And, unlike models, they can be taken apart and put back together.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Neuman, who owns the Neuman's catering firm in Manhattan, has consigned 218 of his architectural toy sets to Noel Barrett, a toy expert in New Hope, Pa., who will auction them tomorrow and Sunday. The toys can be previewed today and tomorrow morning in New Hope; online viewing and bidding are available at liveauctioneers.com and eBayliveauctions.com.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A treasure trove of antique building toys, which include German military forts, European castles, Chinese pagodas and landmarks, will be auctioned this weekend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Toy Building Sets Are Up for Auction</p>
        <p>''It's architecture in miniature,'' said Paul Neuman, explaining his attraction to antique building toys. ''It's about construction, assembly and materials. These toys are nothing until you build them. They require imagination and dexterity. And, unlike models, they can be taken apart and put back together.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Neuman, who owns the Neuman's catering firm in Manhattan, has consigned 218 of his architectural toy sets to Noel Barrett, a toy expert in New Hope, Pa., who will auction them tomorrow and Sunday. The toys can be previewed today and tomorrow morning in New Hope; online viewing and bidding are available at liveauctioneers.com and eBayliveauctions.com.</p>
        <p>The sets include German military forts, European castles, Chinese pagodas and landmarks like the Eiffel Tower and the Chrysler Building.</p>
        <p>''Paul Neuman has the most significant collection of architectural toys made between 1850 and 1920 in private hands,'' said Tom Gray, a founder of the Old Salem Toy Museum in Winston-Salem, N.C. ''It's the combination of rarity and condition that makes it so important.''</p>
        <p>Most were made between 1817 and 1950,'' Mr. Gray said. ''They are from the golden age of toys.''</p>
        <p>Such toys usually have stone, plain wood or cardboard components, but the most valuable sets have hand-colored, chromolithographed wood blocks. Mr. Neuman's favorite 19th-century German set, the Magnificent Palace in Peking, has tiers of blocks with upturned red-tile roofs, black and gold columns and green and red geometric wall decorations. It is estimated to sell for $2,000 to $2,500.</p>
        <p>A German set from the 1930s portrays Palestine and the Holy Land; its stenciled and stained wood blocks depict ancient walls, domed temples, a street in Jerusalem and palm trees.</p>
        <p>The sets come in every architectural style: Gothic, Renaissance, Baroque, Rococo, Neo-Classical and Modern. There is even a Frank Lloyd Wright Prairie Style model of the 1910 Robie House in Chicago.</p>
        <p>''Until the age of plastics, the toys were usually made of the materials they represented and often dealt with real architectural issues of the time: form, style, detail and material,'' James Biber, an architect with Pentagram Design, wrote in a 1995 booklet about the Neuman collection that his company published. ''They transcend their historical and cultural descriptions. They move us because they combine, in deceptive simplicity and harmony, all the disciplines, the vision and the talents a designer may hope for. They are at once graphics and architecture, product and package, model and reality.''</p>
        <p>Such toys appeal to architects, graphic artists, designers and curators at museums like the Canadian Center for Architecture in Montreal, which bought the collection of the New York architect Norman Brosterman, Mr. Neuman's mentor in the field.</p>
        <p>Mr. Neuman, 53, said he had been an ''obsessive'' collector from the start. ''I studied architecture for a year in college and loved seeing the world in miniature,'' he said. ''On June 2, 1985, the day I bought my first Richter blocks, I realized I had found something new. There were no books on the toys; it was an open universe. Pieces were often undocumented. Most toy dealers hated the toys because they were heavy and bulky. No one knew how rare anything was.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Neuman scoured the Stella antique shows on the piers in New York and the flea markets in London and Paris. He took out ads in foreign newspapers. ''Dealers got to know me and sent me stuff from Australia, Holland, France and England,'' he said. ''At some point, nothing new was coming up.''</p>
        <p>Will he miss his sets after the sale?</p>
        <p>''Not all of them,'' he said. ''Taking proper care of them was a huge responsibility. I want them to go to a museum or collectors who can preserve them for the next 100 years.''</p>
        <p>The sale has elicited interest from Europe. ''A German museum curator is coming,'' Mr. Barrett, the auctioneer, said. ''He told me he had never seen so many architectural toys at one time in one sale.'' The collection is expected to bring $100,000 to $150,000.</p>
        <p>Grosvenor House Fair</p>
        <p>A rare 19th-century Anglo-Indian ivory and penwork davenport desk that Ronald Phillips Ltd. is showing at the Grosvenor House Art &amp; Antique Fair is as architectural and graphic as Mr. Neuman's toys. The fair opened yesterday and continues through Wednesday at the Grosvenor House hotel in London. (With 90 major international dealers, Grosvenor is considered one of the top antiques fairs in the world.)</p>
        <p>The desk, signed by the owner of a workshop in the port of Vizagapatam on the Coromandel Coast of eastern India, is lavishly engraved on four sides with garlands, swags and geometric motifs. The ivory gallery above the slanted velvet writing surface is pierced with extravagant foliage. The borders and feet are festooned with carved pearls. Side doors open to reveal a series of fragrant sandalwood drawers.</p>
        <p>''This is off the beaten track for me, but the quality is unbelievable,'' said Simon Phillips, the second-generation owner of the gallery. ''The detail is unreal.''</p>
        <p>Ambitious pieces like this might have been made for maharajas but they were also taken to London to celebrate India's skilled artisans. In 1875 the Prince of Wales, later Edward VII, toured Madras and subsequently patronized exhibitions at home promoting India, the jewel in the crown of the British Empire.</p>
        <p>Only a handful of similarly fine Anglo-Indian ivory desks are known, which accounts for its breathtaking price: $720,000.</p>
        <p>Ceramics Fair</p>
        <p>London is also the host of the International Ceramics Fair and Seminar, which opened yesterday and runs through Sunday at the Park Lane Hotel. It features more than a dozen specialized dealers showing British and Continental pottery, porcelain and glass, made from the 15th century to today. The fair displays Renaissance maiolica; 18th-century Vincennes, Sèvres and Meissen porcelain; Wedgwood wares; and English Worcester, Derby and Chelsea.</p>
        <p>During the fair experts from all over the world are scheduled to lecture on topics that include the idiosyncrasies of Bow porcelain; dining wares in the Dresden court; salt-glazed German and English stoneware unearthed at colonial Williamsburg in Virginia; Wedgwood; and a series of porcelain diplomatic gifts exchanged between the French and Saxon-Polish courts, starting in the late 1740s.</p>
        <p>Antiques</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
