<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Socialist-Style Realism Depicts Socialist-Style Reality</title>
    <meta content="15stri" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/movies/15stri.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854501"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Schlondorff, Volker</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Strike (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5D6143FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Socialist-Style Realism Depicts Socialist-Style Reality</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Socialist-Style Realism Depicts Socialist-Style Reality</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A.O. SCOTT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Volker Schlöndorff's new film, ''Strike,'' shares its title with Sergei Eisenstein's 1924 film and also with a rabble-rousing novel from the 1930s by Mary Heaton Vorse about textile workers in North Carolina. More broadly the movie belongs to a tradition of heroic labor-union melodramas that stretches, in America, from ''Waiting for Lefty'' through ''Norma Rae.''</p>
        <p>Like ''Norma Rae,'' ''Strike'' tells the story of a tough, resilient working woman who refuses to back down from her fight with the bosses. The difference is that in this case the bosses are not greedy capitalists but Communist bureaucrats, committed, in theory, to defending the interests of the workers. There is a delicious poetic justice in the way Mr. Schlöndorff, in telling part of the story of Poland's Solidarity movement, has used some of the crude, effective techniques of Socialist realism to depict the collapse of socialism. He calls the film ''a ballad inspired by true events,'' and its occasional bouts of clumsiness and sentimentality are inseparable from its power.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Strike” tells the story of a tough, resilient working woman who refuses to back down from her fight with the bosses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Volker Schlöndorff's new film, ''Strike,'' shares its title with Sergei Eisenstein's 1924 film and also with a rabble-rousing novel from the 1930s by Mary Heaton Vorse about textile workers in North Carolina. More broadly the movie belongs to a tradition of heroic labor-union melodramas that stretches, in America, from ''Waiting for Lefty'' through ''Norma Rae.''</p>
        <p>Like ''Norma Rae,'' ''Strike'' tells the story of a tough, resilient working woman who refuses to back down from her fight with the bosses. The difference is that in this case the bosses are not greedy capitalists but Communist bureaucrats, committed, in theory, to defending the interests of the workers. There is a delicious poetic justice in the way Mr. Schlöndorff, in telling part of the story of Poland's Solidarity movement, has used some of the crude, effective techniques of Socialist realism to depict the collapse of socialism. He calls the film ''a ballad inspired by true events,'' and its occasional bouts of clumsiness and sentimentality are inseparable from its power.</p>
        <p>The central figure is Agnieszka, a character based on Anna Walentynowicz, who worked in the Gdansk shipyards for many years and was a catalyst of the strike in August 1980 that foretold the end of Communism. Agnieszka is played by Katharina Thalbach, a German actress whose dialogue is dubbed into Polish. At first this is distracting, since most of the rest of the cast is already speaking Polish, but Ms. Thalbach is such a lively and forceful screen presence that after a while you stop noticing. In the early 1960s Agnieszka is the single mother of a young son and a much-praised, much-envied ''heroine of socialist labor,'' exceeding all production quotas and going home from the annual union banquet with a prize television set.</p>
        <p>In spite of her gender, her short stature and her near-illiteracy, she becomes a crane operator. She also falls in love with a sweet-tempered trumpet player (Dominique Horwitz) and for a time seems more or less content with her lot. But her work ethic is accompanied by a strong, innate sense of fairness, and when this is violated by the party hacks and union flunkies who run the shipyard, she cannot countenance the betrayal.</p>
        <p>Her defiance of shipyard management -- and thus of the Polish government and its Soviet sponsors -- has its costs. Her son's educational prospects suffer, as does her relationship with him. But she is buoyed by the respect and fellowship of her fellow workers (including a Lech Walesa figure wryly played by Andrzej Chyra) and by the mixture of patriotism, religious devotion and class consciousness she sees embodied in Pope John Paul II. The key to the film, though, is Agnieszka's own stubbornness, a quality that makes her both ordinary and heroic.</p>
        <p>In his recent projects -- ''Legend of Rita,'' about a left-wing terrorist in the 1970s, and ''The Ninth Day,'' about a priest imprisoned by the Nazis -- Mr. Schlöndorff has concentrated on dramas of individual conscience in times of political crisis. ''Strike'' tells a less ambiguous tale, but it shows a similar interest in exploring the way historical events entwine with, and emerge from, the pressures and difficulties of everyday life.</p>
        <p>This movie, much of which was filmed in and around the Gdansk shipyards where the real events took place, is rough-hewn and modest, stirring but rarely grandiose. This seems fitting, since part of what made Solidarity so inspiring was its gritty, determined refusal of ideological grandstanding or political melodrama.</p>
        <p>Strike  Opens today in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Directed by Volker Schlöndorff; written (in Polish and German, with English subtitles) by Andreas Pflüger and Sylke Rene Meyer; director of photography, Andreas Höfer; edited by Peter Przygodda and Wanda Zeman; music by Jean Michel Jarre; production designer, Robert Czesak; produced by Jürgen Haase; released by Red Envelope Entertainment/Laemmle/Zeller Films. At the Lincoln Plaza, Broadway at 62nd Street. Running time: 104 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: Katharina Thalbach (Agnieszka), Andrzej Chyra (Lech), Dominique Horwitz (Kazimierz), Andrzej Grabowski (Sobecki), Dariusz Kowalski (Bochnak), Ewa Telega (Mirka) and Wojciech Pszoniak (Kaminski).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
