<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giants' Jacobs Hopes Barber's Shoes Are a Comfortable Fit</title>
    <meta content="15giants" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/sports/football/15giants.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854577"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jacobs, Brandon</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Barber, Tiki</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Droughns, Reuben</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7DD153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giants' Jacobs Hopes Barber's Shoes Are a Comfortable Fit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Giants’ Jacobs Hopes Barber’s Shoes Are a Comfortable Fit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N. J., June 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Brandon Jacobs is eager to fill the large void left by Tiki Barber's retirement.</p>
        <p>During two seasons with the Giants, running primarily in short-yardage and goal-line situations, Jacobs became a fan favorite because of his powerful running style. Listed at 6-foot-4, 264 pounds, Jacobs is built more like a linebacker than a running back, and defenders attempting to tackle him have often found themselves overpowered. Giants defensive end Osi Umenyiora admitted that he has avoided tackling Jacobs during practice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In this post Tiki Barber era, Brandon Jacobs is determined to be the starter, a role he intends to earn during minicamp and training camp.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Brandon Jacobs is eager to fill the large void left by Tiki Barber's retirement.</p>
        <p>During two seasons with the Giants, running primarily in short-yardage and goal-line situations, Jacobs became a fan favorite because of his powerful running style. Listed at 6-foot-4, 264 pounds, Jacobs is built more like a linebacker than a running back, and defenders attempting to tackle him have often found themselves overpowered. Giants defensive end Osi Umenyiora admitted that he has avoided tackling Jacobs during practice.</p>
        <p>''Jacobs is bigger than I am, I don't want to tackle that guy,'' Umenyiora said Thursday, the second day of a three-day Giants minicamp. ''I guess you try to take his legs up from under him. But a lot of teams are going to be in a lot of trouble when that guy starts coming downhill.''</p>
        <p>With Barber gone, the top two running backs on the depth chart are Jacobs and Reuben Droughns, a veteran acquired by the Giants in a trade with the Cleveland Browns. Jacobs is determined to be the starter, a role he intends to earn during minicamp and training camp.</p>
        <p>''I've worked hard in previous years to get here,'' said Jacobs, who rushed for 423 yards and 9 touchdowns last season in 96 carries. ''I want it so much more than everybody else. Reuben is great. We've got a good group, and it won't be easy to maintain, but I will.''</p>
        <p>Barber, who ran for 1,662 yards last season, was both effective and durable, never missing a game the last five seasons of his career. Becoming a regular will be an adjustment for Jacobs, who never worried about pacing himself as Barber's backup. Jacobs would often spike the ball or yell with emotion after one of his effective runs last season, but in the future he is likely to show a little less emotion.</p>
        <p>''All that extra stuff that, when you're taking 20 25 carries, a game, you have to keep yourself down to keep yourself in it,'' Jacobs said. ''But I feel confident. I feel I've got everything under control and I'm ready to go.''</p>
        <p>Jeremy Shockey, the Giants' extroverted tight end, enjoys watching Jacobs, and believes he is ready to assume the starting job.</p>
        <p>''Brandon's got size, speed, and he's a good person,'' Shockey said. ''I'm really looking forward to watching him run this year. He's going to show everybody what he can do.''</p>
        <p>With no tackling during minicamp, Jacobs has been unable to display his power. But while the Giants expect to miss Barber, they say they believe that Jacobs gives them a capable replacement.</p>
        <p>''Tiki Barber was, in my opinion, the best running back in football the past three years,'' Umenyiora said. ''But we've seen what Brandon can do. We have confidence in him.''</p>
        <p>Jacobs also has confidence, and after two years as an understudy, he feels ready to become a starter.</p>
        <p>''This is just something we've got to get used to,'' Jacobs said. ''We're going with some new people, and that new person is me.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Jeremy Shockey was hobbled by an ankle injury late last season, and he has missed at least one game every year in his five seasons with the Giants. Shockey reported to camp with more muscle mass, and avoiding injury has become a top priority. ''I'd like to stay healthy all year, something I haven't been able to do,'' Shockey said. ''That's a goal for the season.'' Jim Finn's season-ending shoulder operation has given Robert Douglas a chance to become the starting fullback. ''I've been impressed with what Robert Douglas has been able to do,'' Coach Tom Coughlin said. ''But of course, we don't have any pads on yet, either.'' Douglas, a second-year player from Memphis, said: ''It's a big opportunity, but the main thing is to focus. Don't get the big head and think that it's all mine. It's really not, It's wide open.''  A head injury forced cornerback Aaron Ross, the Giants' first-round draft pick, to miss Thursday's workouts. ''He fell down yesterday and banged his head,'' Coughlin said. ''So it is precautionary. They pulled him out of second half of practice yesterday. Today it was just a precautionary measure. But he seemed to feel a little bit better.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
