<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commuters Get a Chance to Take Their Complaints to the Top</title>
    <meta content="15QandA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/nyregion/15QandA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854615"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York City Transit</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Roberts, Howard H Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EFDD153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commuters Get a Chance to Take Their Complaints to the Top</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Commuters Get a Chance to Take Their Complaints to the Top</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ivette Davila, who had an hour to kill yesterday on her way from the cable television network where she works during the day to the store where she works at night, could have done many things in the sprawling Atlantic Avenue subway station in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>She could have tried to become a sailor: the Navy had a recruiting table set up. Or she could have tried to become a police officer: the Police Department had its own recruiters and its own table. Or she could have rushed through the station the way she usually does.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The president of New York City Transit fielded questions from the public at “Transit Talk” in the Atlantic Avenue subway station.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ivette Davila, who had an hour to kill yesterday on her way from the cable television network where she works during the day to the store where she works at night, could have done many things in the sprawling Atlantic Avenue subway station in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>She could have tried to become a sailor: the Navy had a recruiting table set up. Or she could have tried to become a police officer: the Police Department had its own recruiters and its own table. Or she could have rushed through the station the way she usually does.</p>
        <p>But she stopped to ask something of someone who does not visit the Atlantic Avenue subway station nearly as often as she does: Howard H. Roberts Jr., the president of New York City Transit. He had chosen that hour to face the public, taking questions from commuters, and Ms. Davila had a question.</p>
        <p>''Why is it they want to increase the fare when they said a year or two ago they had a surplus?'' she asked. ''They're making it a hardship for people like me who have to work two jobs.''</p>
        <p>It was hard to hear in the noisy corridor. Mr. Roberts was standing behind a wooden lectern. Ms. Davila was standing in front of the lectern. He said something about revenue from subsidies and revenue from ''the fare box'' -- in other words, from fares paid by commuters like Ms. Davila.</p>
        <p>''In this business, expenses keep going up, and we're trying to make up for it,'' he said, ''so we're trying to get more subsidies, but we may, may, have to get more from the fare box.</p>
        <p>''We'll do the best we can not to raise fares,'' he continued, ''and if we have to, we'll do our best to raise them as little as possible.''</p>
        <p>They shook hands and Ms. Davila walked away. He had not wowed her.</p>
        <p>''I swear, I wanted to tell him, 'Speak in English now,' '' she said. ''His answer reminded me of when I was in college and taking economics. That didn't tell me why there was a surplus a year and a half ago.''</p>
        <p>So it went at what turned out to be a cross between open-mike night at a comedy club, minus the microphone and the comedy, and ''Face the Nation'' or ''Meet the Press,'' minus the lights, the cameras, the studio and the practiced questioners.</p>
        <p>Would Bob Schieffer or Tim Russert ever ask a question like the one Robert Martinez asked about what he called ''the deplorable conditions'' in the Jamaica Center Parsons/Archer station at the end of the E, J and Z lines? Would they mention ''one inch of urine on the floors if you go into the bathrooms,'' as he did?</p>
        <p>He said there had been no one to complain to -- until Mr. Roberts. ''He's working on it,'' Mr. Martinez said after their chat. ''It's a baby step, but it's a step.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Roberts, who was appointed in April and who was the vice president and chief operating officer for surface transit in the 1980s, had arrived shortly after 5 p.m., a few minutes late for what large posters in the station billed as ''Transit Talk.'' An assistant explained that the No. 4 train he rode to the station was delayed because a train in front of it had to be taken out of service.</p>
        <p>Waiting near the lectern were more than 40 transit executives, most of whom were wearing dark suits with plastic name tags pinned on. As ''Transit Talk'' went on, Mr. Roberts turned to them for details he did not know. At times, he cupped his hand to his right ear -- he had some hearing loss, he explained later.</p>
        <p>''Artillery and helicopters'' in Vietnam, he said.</p>
        <p>But he listened as more than 30 commuters stepped up, one by one. Sometimes he stepped out from behind the lectern. He had to when it was 7-year-old Naddie Marques's turn: she was not tall enough to see over the lectern.</p>
        <p>She forgot her question. But she showed Mr. Roberts the certificate she had received from the Brooklyn Music School and told him that she had enjoyed her dance lessons.</p>
        <p>''Am I going to see you at the New York City Ballet some day?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>She laughed. Her mother, Barbara Sampson, said Naddie had wanted to ask why the subway so often made her late for her lessons.</p>
        <p>A number of questioners were people in wheelchairs for whom accessibility is a personal issue and who said they looked forward to meeting with other high-level transit officials.</p>
        <p>Edith M. Prentiss, who uses a wheelchair and said she had a debilitating connective-tissue disease, said she had asked Mr. Roberts how many elevators she had to take to get to see him.</p>
        <p>She said his reply was, ''I have no idea.''</p>
        <p>She said the answer was three subway trains and five elevators.</p>
        <p>She said he had promised to spend time following her through the subway and observing exactly what it took for her to get around. ''We'll make an appointment,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
