<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Are You Tough Enough? An Adventurer's Guide To Surviving the Wilds</title>
    <meta content="15wild" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/arts/television/15wild.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854532"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Discovery Channel</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E5DF153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1130" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Are You Tough Enough? An Adventurer's Guide To Surviving the Wilds</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Are You Tough Enough? An Adventurer’s Guide to Surviving the Wilds</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA COHEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The plain metal rowboats at the Central Park Boathouse are surprisingly similar to the skiff that Bear Grylls commandeered in Alaska during an episode of ''Man vs. Wild,'' his hit series on the Discovery Channel. Except that his leaked, lacked oars and eventually sank among a pack of ice floes, forcing him to strip down to a T-shirt and swim to shore. The water was so frigid that he started hyperventilating as his pulse raced to the heart-attack zone.</p>
        <p>But then what kind of survival show would it be without a near brush with death? Tonight at 9 is the new season's premiere, and Mr. Grylls has to find food, water and a way out of the Florida Everglades with only a flint, a water bottle and a knife. There is razor grass and mud holes that could inhale a jeep in a single breath. Without giving too much away, let's just say that those with a soft spot for Kermit the Frog might want to avert their eyes during lunch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bear Grylls survived Everest, the British Special Air Services and a broken back before he became known for “Man vs. Wild,” a hit series on the Discovery Channel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The plain metal rowboats at the Central Park Boathouse are surprisingly similar to the skiff that Bear Grylls commandeered in Alaska during an episode of ''Man vs. Wild,'' his hit series on the Discovery Channel. Except that his leaked, lacked oars and eventually sank among a pack of ice floes, forcing him to strip down to a T-shirt and swim to shore. The water was so frigid that he started hyperventilating as his pulse raced to the heart-attack zone.</p>
        <p>But then what kind of survival show would it be without a near brush with death? Tonight at 9 is the new season's premiere, and Mr. Grylls has to find food, water and a way out of the Florida Everglades with only a flint, a water bottle and a knife. There is razor grass and mud holes that could inhale a jeep in a single breath. Without giving too much away, let's just say that those with a soft spot for Kermit the Frog might want to avert their eyes during lunch.</p>
        <p>There are also bears, panthers, skunks, bobcats and a million alligators that could snap up a man in a couple of bites.</p>
        <p>This morning, though, the only ones snapping are camera-toting tourists, and Mr. Grylls looks relaxed. Aimlessly rowing around the park's lake, Mr. Grylls talks about shows that have taken him from the African savanna to the Sierra Nevada.</p>
        <p>''I get really scared regularly,'' he says. He turned 33 last week, and his flab-free physique, lapis-colored eyes and British accent are naturals for television. But what makes Mr. Grylls a particularly winning character is his lack of pretension. He doesn't seem to mind looking silly or embarrassed or just scared stiff -- as when a 16-foot tiger shark began circling the bamboo raft he had constructed to escape a deserted South Pacific island last season.</p>
        <p>And that wasn't even the worst. The closest he has come to calling for emergency help was in his own backyard. (The episode will be shown on July 20.) He was high in the Cairngorm Mountains of Scotland when a storm rolled in. The temperature dropped to 30 degrees below zero, visibility was less than 50 feet, and the wind was so powerful that he could not stand up.</p>
        <p>''I was on the edge of calling in help,'' Mr. Grylls said. Then he found a dead deer, which he skinned, wrapping himself in the bloody coat to get through the night.</p>
        <p>''If I'm honest, I'm quite on the edge here,'' he says. ''I'm really exposed.'' Mr. Grylls was filming in the Amazon last September when he heard that Steve Irwin had died while filming his show ''The Crocodile Hunter.'' ''It was a real shock to me,'' he said. ''You can get it right 1,000 times and wrong only once.''</p>
        <p>Still, he added, ''I'm working within my own limits. I trained for this all my life.''</p>
        <p>It seems so. Mr. Grylls, whose name Edward morphed to Teddy and then Bear, grew up on the Isle of Wight. His father, a member of the Royal Marines and of Parliament, started teaching him to rock climb when he was 4.</p>
        <p>''He instilled in me two things: follow your dreams and look after your friends,'' Mr. Grylls said. When he was 8, his dad showed him a picture of Mount Everest, and they decided that one day they would climb it together. With two such daredevils in the family, his mother ended up with ''a life of quiet turmoil,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He joined the British Special Air Services when he turned 18. Jumping out of a plane over southern Africa, he was about 16,000 feet up when his parachute's canopy ripped, and he hurtled toward the desert floor. His back was broken in three places. It took him 18 months to recover. His Christian faith helped. ''I've never met anyone who is an atheist in a lifeboat,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''When I got better, Everest became the whole focus of my recovery,'' Mr. Grylls said. At 23, he joined an expedition and after 3 1/2 months, he reached the top, although four others in his group died.</p>
        <p>''It was kind of a hollow victory,'' he says now. Still, he was gratified that his father managed to see him get to the top before his death. Mr. Grylls wrote a book about the adventure, ''The Kid Who Climbed Everest'' (Lyons Press, 2001).</p>
        <p>A few years later he met his wife, Shara, while he was skinny-dipping on a New Year's Day in Scotland. They have two boys, Jesse, 4, and Marmaduke, 1, with whom he is planning to spend a quiet summer, baking cakes, hiking and changing diapers.</p>
        <p>Does he worry that his riskier-than-average job might deprive his sons of their father? ''Yes, it is something I struggle with,'' he later writes in an e-mail message. ''I have to just trust my instincts always out there and make good decisions -- but it is my job and where I come alive.''</p>
        <p>His record-breaking stunts eventually captured the attention of British television producers, who signed him up to do a show about what it was really like to join the French Foreign Legion. (''Brutal and unpleasant,'' he says.)</p>
        <p>And then came the offer to be the host of ''Man vs. Wild.'' For the past year, he has spent about three weeks of every month going to the most remote, perilous spots he and his producers could think up.</p>
        <p>''Anytime I say something is too dangerous to go, the next thing I know we're off there,'' he said. He initially turned down the Australian outback. ''It gets 145 degrees,'' he said. ''There are stories of seawater crocodiles taking people off yachts; mosquitoes as big as your thumb.''</p>
        <p>He ended up having to drink his own urine to survive. (That episode will be shown on July 6.)</p>
        <p>In a nearby rowboat a mother and her son float by. ''My son loves you,'' she calls out. ''He stayed in the Boy Scouts because of you.'' Mr. Grylls beams.</p>
        <p>The boy, Joseph Taylor, 13, is waiting by the boathouse to take a picture with his hero. Another fan comes up, talking enthusiastically about Mr. Grylls's bug eating. ''Wait till you see Ecuador,'' Mr. Grylls says. ''I eat a maggot this big,'' he explains, holding up his fingers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grylls said that next season he would like to go to a city. ''I could show people how to get out of a burning building,'' he says, or get out of a trapped elevator or defend themselves against a mugging.</p>
        <p>So what if he had to forage for food in Central Park? A piece of cake -- so to speak. ''There are more rats in New York than any other city,'' he says. ''You've got plenty to eat.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
