<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Rakish Sabbatini Yuks It Up</title>
    <meta content="15roberts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/sports/golf/15roberts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854695"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Selena Roberts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DB153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="892" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Rakish Sabbatini Yuks It Up</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Rakish Sabbatini Yuks It Up</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What do you make of a player who tees off wearing a diamond-encrusted tarantula as a belt buckle that looks more like a first prize for the Orkin man of the year?</p>
        <p>It is difficult to square the outrageous Rory Sabbatini with the PGA Tour's conservative khakiklatsch of players with III's after their names -- as in Davis Love III or Charles Howell III.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is difficult to square the outrageous Rory Sabbatini with the PGA Tour’s conservative khakiklatsch of players with III’s after their names.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What do you make of a player who tees off wearing a diamond-encrusted tarantula as a belt buckle that looks more like a first prize for the Orkin man of the year?</p>
        <p>It is difficult to square the outrageous Rory Sabbatini with the PGA Tour's conservative khakiklatsch of players with III's after their names -- as in Davis Love III or Charles Howell III.</p>
        <p>Sabbatini is, in fact, a little naughty, which actually has nothing to do with his wife's famous affection for go-go boots and sassy T-shirts.</p>
        <p>He is, to a degree, public in his excess, but this is not about Sabbatini posed at the pump to top off a motor coach he often steers down the highway and over a few curbs as he crisscrosses the Tour.</p>
        <p>What is a gallery at the United States Open to make of an attention-needy mischief-maker from South Africa who dares challenge the myth of Tiger Woods?</p>
        <p>''I think they're scared of me,'' Sabbatini said with a sly grin after posting a respectable first-round score of three-over-par 73 on an impossible Oakmont course he called Oak Monster yesterday. ''They fear what they don't know.''</p>
        <p>Clairvoyance is spooky stuff. In essence, Sabbatini's candor about the future fade of Woods's game has created a stir for one obvious reason: He is the lone peer willing to challenge golf's Zeus. But there is also the absurd possibility that Sabbatini just may be right about Woods's state of decline.</p>
        <p>In a summation of his brazen critiques in recent weeks, Sabbatini basically described Tiger as less dominant and more beatable, less focused and more distracted.</p>
        <p>''I like the new Tiger,'' Sabbatini said at the Players Championship last month.</p>
        <p>An amused Woods said, ''I like the new Tiger as well,'' and rattled off his nine Tour victories in a dozen starts at the time.</p>
        <p>Sabbatini attempted to make peace -- or have fun -- with Tiger at Oakmont when he signed up for an early practice round Wednesday in hopes of pairing with Woods. But did Woods pull a no-show? When a reporter from The Daily Telegraph of Australia asked Sabbatini why he had been stood up, he reportedly crossed the practice green to seek out Woods.</p>
        <p>Sabbatini found him. And as Woods lined up a putt, Sabbatini dared to interrupt his trance. (Why not just grab the elbow of Picasso in mid-brushstroke?) Woods gave Sabbatini a bizarre stare but spoke to him. Upon Sabbatini's return, he informed reporters, ''Tiger said he never plays Wednesday before a major.''</p>
        <p>It would be simple to dismiss Sabbatini as the wacky uncle of the Tour if not for his No. 6 ranking, if not for his five top-10 finishes in 15 events this year, if not for the truth in his message.</p>
        <p>Sabbatini is right. Woods's attention has been splintered in his consuming effort to globally expand his brand. There are no pedestrian ventures for Woods, an adrenaline seeker who digs bungee-cord jumping and black diamond ski runs. So where else but Dubai -- an exotic desert paradise of gilded whimsy -- would Woods take the plunge in designing his first golf course? Woods doesn't skip workouts while Dubai hopping, but he has lost some sleep.</p>
        <p>Diaper detail could occupy even more zzz's. Woods and his wife, Elin, will be parents soon, with a baby on the way in weeks. Woods honestly has no idea what he is in for.</p>
        <p>''I don't really know how my game is going to be affected by it because I've never gone through it before,'' said Woods, who shot a 71 yesterday. ''All I know is that Elin and I are excited, and that this is far more important than any game of golf.''</p>
        <p>Priorities rightly shift. Dominance may slide. Maybe this is all Sabbatini is saying: What makes Woods vulnerable is his growth as a person.</p>
        <p>Sabbatini just explains it more colorfully. He is an authentic among players who maintain a plastic veneer. Yesterday was merely another afternoon at the Improv for Sabbatini, who chatted away outside the Oakmont Country Club doors until he saw someone straining to hear him.</p>
        <p>''You want me up here so you can see me?'' Sabbatini said as he stepped on a carpeted podium.</p>
        <p>Only 5 feet 10 inches in golf spikes, and including the curl in his hair, he remains hard to miss. Beyond wearing a spidery belt buckle that could induce an arachnophobia cold sweat, he distinguishes himself with the galleries by making cartoonish faces and body motions.</p>
        <p>After his approach on the ninth hole, he looked at someone in the crowd and raised his arms, making circles in the air with his hands as if acting out the childhood song that begins, ''The wheels on the bus go round and round.''</p>
        <p>Had the Oakmont goblins snatched his mind?</p>
        <p>''I was motioning to my wife to get the umbrella,'' Sabbatini said. ''I was doing sign language for, 'Get me the umbrella, please. It's in the car.' ''</p>
        <p>Amy Sabbatini easily decoded her husband. She is a character herself. A year ago, when Rory Sabbatini, famously intolerant of leisurely players, was paired with the easygoing Nick Faldo, she showed up in a black T-shirt with the words Keep Up ironed on it.</p>
        <p>What do you make of the Sabbatinis? They use irreverence as a strategy. Why not? Cowering has never beaten Woods.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
