<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AMERICAN JOURNEYS | Franconia Notch, N.H.; Mountains, Woods and Noisy Waters That Dig Deep</title>
    <meta content="15American" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/travel/escapes/15American.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854520"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="American Journeys | Franconia Notch, N.H."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Franconia Notch (NH)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Hampshire</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Franconia Notch State Park (Nh)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Samuels, Sam Hooper</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Hampshire/White Mountains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">White Mountains (NH)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New Hampshire</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00EED6143FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AMERICAN JOURNEYS | Franconia Notch, N.H.; Mountains, Woods and Noisy Waters That Dig Deep</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mountains, Woods and Noisy Waters That Dig Deep</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOOPER SAMUELS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Samuels, Sam Hooper</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on visit to Franconia Notch, NH, including Franconia Notch State Park; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN June 1808, so the story goes, a 93-year-old woman known to history as Aunt Jess Guernsey set out on foot from her family's log house at the base of Mount Pemigewasset in New Hampshire to look for a new place to fish. Led by the sound of water, she wandered into a gorge that, although she'd lived close to it for years, she'd never seen before. She found herself at the bottom of a chasm of lush natural beauty, a roaring stream at its base, carved deep into the granite of the rugged White Mountains, yet so narrow as to be easily missed from the top.</p>
        <p>Aunt Jess had discovered the Flume, and it seems to have thrilled her much as it does everyone who visits it today, and probably thrilled Indian discoverers long before her. Eight hundred feet long and about 20 feet from side to side at its widest, with granite walls 90 feet high, the Flume feels otherworldly -- a descent into a tranquil haven, secluded and cool. It lives up to its billing as one of the major tourist attractions at Franconia Notch, a winding mountain pass that cuts through the White Mountains and connects the more densely populated southern part of the state with its wilder side, known to Granite Staters as ''North of the Notches.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eight hundred feet long and about 20 feet from side to side at its widest, with granite walls 90 feet high, the Flume feels otherworldly  a descent into a tranquil haven, secluded and cool.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN June 1808, so the story goes, a 93-year-old woman known to history as Aunt Jess Guernsey set out on foot from her family's log house at the base of Mount Pemigewasset in New Hampshire to look for a new place to fish. Led by the sound of water, she wandered into a gorge that, although she'd lived close to it for years, she'd never seen before. She found herself at the bottom of a chasm of lush natural beauty, a roaring stream at its base, carved deep into the granite of the rugged White Mountains, yet so narrow as to be easily missed from the top.</p>
        <p>Aunt Jess had discovered the Flume, and it seems to have thrilled her much as it does everyone who visits it today, and probably thrilled Indian discoverers long before her. Eight hundred feet long and about 20 feet from side to side at its widest, with granite walls 90 feet high, the Flume feels otherworldly -- a descent into a tranquil haven, secluded and cool. It lives up to its billing as one of the major tourist attractions at Franconia Notch, a winding mountain pass that cuts through the White Mountains and connects the more densely populated southern part of the state with its wilder side, known to Granite Staters as ''North of the Notches.''</p>
        <p>This part of the Whites is the home of the Old Man in the Mountain, the famous natural rock formation looking like a stern face in profile that was a magnet for tourists from the early 1800s until the night in May 2003 when it slid off the side of Cannon Mountain. Images of his craggy visage live on, plastered on state highway signs and license plates. If any of the quarters you plug into the coin-operated binoculars at the viewpoint atop Cannon Mountain are New Hampshire state quarters, the Old Man is pictured there too. You just won't see him in person anymore.</p>
        <p>The Old Man is mourned, but the valley he surveyed remains a magnet for hikers, campers, fly fishers and anyone thirsty to drink in the majestic scenery of the Whites. Wooded trails beckon both hikers and mountain bikers. Crystal-clear lakes invite visitors to cast a lure, dip a kayak paddle or, in the warmer months, just dive in. The nearby town of Lincoln caters to the tourist trade, with many small, informal eating places, purveyors of crafts and antiques and a pleasant 80-minute ride along the Pemigewasset River on the Hobo Railroad, an excursion train. At the southern end of the Notch, and for many visitors its heart and soul, lies the Flume.</p>
        <p>You enter through the Flume Gorge Visitor Center, a large, welcoming building with a gift shop, cafeteria and information on the gorge itself and the Notch area. In the high-ceilinged atrium, the historically minded can examine the Concord Coach, an ornately filigreed stagecoach built in 1874 that once carried proper Bostonians from the train station in nearby Plymouth to the Flume -- a major 19th-century tourist attraction.</p>
        <p>The trail to the Flume and back, a two-mile loop, begins at a small cabin with glass cases containing examples of the local flora and fauna and a display of amusing historical postcards of the Flume, and for much of its distance follows Flume Brook. The oohing and aahing begin in earnest at Table Rock, where the stream bed widens into a broad expanse of flat granite, with the water passing over it in a gleaming, paper-thin sheet. A few hundred feet more of walking leads to the mouth of the gorge, and the world transforms.</p>
        <p>Inside the Flume, the senses themselves seem somehow changed. The light that filters down into the rocks from the opening of the chasm high above is soft and pale. Even on a blisteringly hot day, the air inside is soothing, perhaps 20 degrees cooler than at Table Rock. There's a pleasing dampness to the air. The rock walls themselves ooze and trickle cool, clean water.</p>
        <p>They also drip with life. From cracks and fissures, birch trees impossibly grow, twisting and thrusting upward to catch a glimpse of sun. Cliffs are coated with thick blankets of soft, dense moss and lichen, a curtain of mottled green.</p>
        <p>Once inside, the path changes from dirt to a wooden catwalk hugging the rock wall. The water beneath rambles over boulders, through cracks and around bends. A hundred years ago, a huge oval rock lay across the top, spanning the gorge far overhead. Then in the late 19th century, a torrential spring downpour set off a landslide that sent the boulder crashing. That flood also rearranged the stream at the head of the Flume, forming Avalanche Falls, the climax to the walk. The falls kick up clouds of mist, and as the path crosses in front of them I heard many a child (and more than one adult) let out a scream in the spray and go back for another round.</p>
        <p>JUST a few miles away is the Cannon Mountain Aerial Tramway, a gondola-style ski lift that takes summer visitors up the mountain through a vertiginous landscape of awe-inspiring views. As many as 80 passengers can crowd in to enjoy the ride (70 in winter, when they're loaded with skis and poles). The eight-minute ride lifts you nearly half a mile and inspires, depending on your temperament and proximity to a window, rapture or stark terror.</p>
        <p>At the top are a ski lodge, which serves pizza and sandwiches, and an observation tower with a panoramic view of famous nearby peaks in the Whites, like Mounts Washington and Lincoln, and distant features in Maine, Vermont, New York and Canada.</p>
        <p>At the bottom of Cannon Mountain, the tramway leaves you a short drive from the Old Man of the Mountain Historic Site. Though the Old Man is no more, the site is still well worth a visit to see relics of its past, learn about the geologic forces that brought about its demise and have an ice cream. Immediately after the famed visage fell, there was talk of a granite face-lift to restore him to his approximate former state. That hasn't come to pass, but last February the Old Man of the Mountain Legacy Fund announced a plan for a series of large granite sculptures at the base of the mountain as a memorial.</p>
        <p>At the tiny one-room museum, you can see a place setting of 19th-century Wedgwood china featuring the Old Man and learn about efforts dating back as early as 1915 to prevent its inevitable downfall, using metal turnbuckles. There's a short walk from the museum to the edge of Profile Lake, the aptly named spot that afforded prime viewing of the Old Man.</p>
        <p>In the lake itself, fly fishers wade. The quiet swish of their fishing lines whipping through the air makes a poignant accompaniment to the sight of the familiar, majestic mountain now literally defaced by the very forces that formed it.</p>
        <p>You can't swim in Profile Lake, but just a short hop up the road is Echo Lake. This 28-acre body of water, open summers only for a small fee, affords swimmers the rare combination of a sandy beach and a spectacular mountain view. There's a small snack bar, as well as hourly rentals of canoes and kayaks.</p>
        <p>Most of these sites are easily accessible by car from the various turnoffs along Interstate 93 that form the Franconia Notch State Park. To cover the territory without looking through a windshield, the Franconia Notch Bike Path provides an eight-mile ride through the Notch with views all along the way. A bike shop near the base of the Cannon Mountain Tramway offers rentals and repairs.</p>
        <p>For the more adventurous, the whole region is networked with hiking trails that stray far farther from the highway. Some are kid-friendly loops that start and end right off the highway, while some are ambitious mountain hikes, including a segment of the Appalachian Trail.</p>
        <p>Lodging in the Notch ranges from campgrounds to modest motels, quaint B&amp;B's to full-fledged resorts. One popular and long-standing choice is the Indian Head Resort. (Yes, the Old Man may be gone, but a lesser-known rock outcropping resembling the profile of an Indian remains.) For 80 years, this 180-acre spot has lured families with the mountain and water views from its rooms.</p>
        <p>CARVING THE GRANITE</p>
        <p>A Park as Eight Miles of Exits</p>
        <p>The Flume, Cannon Mountain and the Old Man of the Mountain Historic Site are all part of Franconia Notch State Park (www.franconianotchstatepark.com) in New Hampshire. The park is laid out as a series of exits along eight miles of Interstate Route 93, which follows a winding mountain pass through the White Mountains. It's about a two-and-a-half-hour drive from Boston, or three hours from Hartford.</p>
        <p>Admission at the Flume is $10, and a round-trip ride on the Cannon Mountain Aerial Tramway is $11. Other attractions in the park include the Basin, a natural bowl carved into rock by rushing water; Boise Rock, a protected overhang where an early settler sought shelter from the elements; Lafayette Campground, a center for hiking and camping; and Echo Lake, which has a sandy beach for swimming. The nearby town of Lincoln, N.H., offers a variety of restaurants and hotels as well as the scenic Hobo Railroad and a handy visitor information center.</p>
        <p>American Journeys | Franconia Notch, N.H.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
