<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Proposed Ban on Taco Trucks Stirs Animosity in a California Town</title>
    <meta content="15taco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/us/15taco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854611"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E0DD153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Proposed Ban on Taco Trucks Stirs Animosity in a California Town</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Proposed Ban on Taco Trucks Stirs Animosity in a California Town</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLYN MARSHALL</byline>
      <dateline>SALINAS, Calif.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jose Martínez left Mexico around 1988 and toiled for years in a patchwork of fields here, harvesting berries and lettuce and barely making ends meet.</p>
        <p>In 2002, Mr. Martínez took advantage of a city law created to help novice entrepreneurs start businesses related to the city's largely Hispanic cultural heritage. He bought a taco truck, one of 31 licensed mobile catering vehicles in Salinas, and built it into a modestly profitable operation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A proposed ordinance to ban catering vehicles in Salinas, Calif., has placed Mexican immigrants at odds with longtime residents whose families emigrated years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jose Martínez left Mexico around 1988 and toiled for years in a patchwork of fields here, harvesting berries and lettuce and barely making ends meet.</p>
        <p>In 2002, Mr. Martínez took advantage of a city law created to help novice entrepreneurs start businesses related to the city's largely Hispanic cultural heritage. He bought a taco truck, one of 31 licensed mobile catering vehicles in Salinas, and built it into a modestly profitable operation.</p>
        <p>But the City Council, responding to a business group and its most vocal members -- the owners of Mexican restaurants -- is poised to vote next month on a draft ordinance to ban taco trucks and other catering vehicles from Salinas, a farm town about 120 miles south of San Francisco.</p>
        <p>The proposed ordinance, which is still subject to revision, is the latest round in a two-year debate that some say has created a rift in this community, placing poorer Mexicans who are looking to better themselves at odds with longtime residents whose families emigrated years ago.</p>
        <p>Salinas is not alone. Taco trucks, cultural icons and social magnets in Mexico, have become a flashpoint in at least a dozen cities in California -- including Santa Rosa, 55 miles north of San Francisco, and Gardena, 15 miles south of Los Angeles -- and in other states, like Arizona, Oregon and Tennessee.</p>
        <p>Restrictions are being debated in the Central Valley towns of Lathrop, Escalon and Lodi. In most cases, brick-and-mortar businesses resent the competition. Many observers say the taco truck issue illuminates far more complex dynamics, from the perils of rapid urban development to hidden resentments toward, and among, Hispanics.</p>
        <p>''It's rarely if ever discussed, but there are obvious racial undertones,'' said David LeBeouf, a lawyer for about 100 food vendors here and in several Central Valley cities.</p>
        <p>The ordinance would phase out mobile and stationary catering vehicles, most of which are taco trucks, by 2011, and would restrict how, when and where 240 pushcart vendors could sell cold prepared foods.</p>
        <p>''Of course I'm worried,'' said Mr. Martínez, who at 36 is saving to buy a home. ''It's my job, my livelihood.''</p>
        <p>Salinas officials say the proposed ordinance was not intended to shut down the vendors. ''We don't want to put these people out of business,'' said the senior deputy city attorney, Chris Callihan. ''We want to move them off the street and put them into brick and mortar establishments.''</p>
        <p>Concern about mobile vendors escalated in 2005 when a trade group, the Salinas United Business Association complained about a proliferation of taco trucks, some run illegally, in east Salinas, a hardscrabble area that is slated for modest improvements, including new landscaping and a promenade.</p>
        <p>The harshest complaints came from restaurateurs, who said that the trucks had an unfair competitive advantage, fostered urban blight, blocked traffic and were sometimes unsanitary.</p>
        <p>''We all love Mexico, but once you jump on a plane you leave Mexico behind,'' said Antonio Campos, the owner of a Mexican restaurant here. ''Once you are in America, you have rules, regulations and standards.''</p>
        <p>Taco trucks ''should go to the fields and feed the agriculture guys,'' said Mr. Campos, 29, a Salinas native of Mexican descent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Campos and others want taco trucks off east Salinas streets. ''If they are mobile vendors, keep them mobile. We have way more overhead and the competition is not on a level playing field,'' Mr. Campos said.</p>
        <p>Vendors pay $25,000 to $50,000 for trucks and about $1,000 for permits.</p>
        <p>The vendors say critics are trying to undo the reputation of their businesses as clean, safe and respectable, known to provide a vital service to cash-strapped farm workers and to a growing legion of out-of-town food fanatics. The vendors have protested, circulated petitions and, as of May 31, hired Mr. LeBeouf.</p>
        <p>Vendors ''are very angry, very upset,'' Teresa Hernandez, a volunteer spokeswoman, said. ''That group's whole argument is that the vendors are in the way of revitalization.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Callihan said the city's main concern has always been on public health and safety, especially since an E. coli scare last fall when tainted spinach was traced to farms in this region.</p>
        <p>''There is a huge concern around here because of E. coli,'' Mr. Callihan said. ''It happened after the vendor issue came up. But it fed into it and our need to make sure food is safe.''</p>
        <p>City officials, though, note that no Salinas vendor has been linked to a health scare, prompting some taco truck advocates to call the rationale for the ordinance ''a smoke screen.''</p>
        <p>''It really comes down to competition,'' said Melanie Wong, a Salinas native and a frequent blogger on Chowhound.com. ''Why should one class of merchant roll over for another class of merchant?''</p>
        <p>Mr. LeBeouf said the ordinance's rules on how far vendors must be from restaurants and that set hours of operation from 3 p.m. to 6 a.m., were unrelated to health and safety.</p>
        <p>''It's a restraint of trade and you cannot do it,'' Mr. LeBeouf said. ''The city may be banking on the fact that the vendors don't have the money or motivation to challenge it. That's not the way you make good law.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
