<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crew Chief's Strategy Gives Gordon an Edge</title>
    <meta content="15nascar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/sports/othersports/15nascar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854607"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gordon, Jeff</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE1DD153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crew Chief's Strategy Gives Gordon an Edge</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Crew Chief’s Strategy Gives Gordon an Edge</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Steve Letarte is Jeff Gordon's crew chief, which means that Letarte spends race days perched on a portable cart next to Gordon's pit stall. Letarte pulls on a headset and, like an offensive coordinator in football, becomes a tactician.</p>
        <p>The 28-year-old Letarte, who has been working for Gordon since he was hired as a junior in high school to sweep the garage floors, says that calling a race is his favorite part of the job. In his second full year as a crew chief, Letarte has proven to be good at it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Steve Letarte is Jeff Gordon’s crew chief, and one of the reasons Gordon has a a 242-point lead over Matt Kenseth in the Nascar Nextel Cup standings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Steve Letarte is Jeff Gordon's crew chief, which means that Letarte spends race days perched on a portable cart next to Gordon's pit stall. Letarte pulls on a headset and, like an offensive coordinator in football, becomes a tactician.</p>
        <p>The 28-year-old Letarte, who has been working for Gordon since he was hired as a junior in high school to sweep the garage floors, says that calling a race is his favorite part of the job. In his second full year as a crew chief, Letarte has proven to be good at it.</p>
        <p>''I guess I'm not the best car guy, the best engine guy, the best chassis guy,'' Letarte said Wednesday from Gordon's shop in Charlotte, N.C., ''but I pride myself on being a strategist, a manager.''</p>
        <p>Gordon, the four-time series champion, has a 242-point lead over Matt Kenseth in the Nascar Nextel Cup standings heading into the Citizens Bank 400 on Sunday at Michigan International Speedway. Gordon has surged to the top because he has had fast cars. But he has also had Letarte.</p>
        <p>Horsepower and handling are vital to winning a stock-car race, but, as Letarte proved last Sunday at the Pocono 500, shrewd pit-road strategy can push a slower car to the front. Gordon had a top-10 car, but not a sure winner.</p>
        <p>Because of poor weather, Letarte made one critical decision that led to Gordon's fourth victory of the season. Should Gordon be among the top 12 drivers after the Sept. 8 race in Richmond, Va., he will take 40 bonus points into the 10-race Chase for the Nextel Cup.</p>
        <p>''We want to take every chance we can to win races,'' Letarte said.</p>
        <p>Gordon leads the 12th-place driver, Mark Martin, by 663 points going into the race at Michigan. That margin is more important to Letarte than Gordon's lead over Kenseth. Drivers who do not make the Chase cannot use the bonus points.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to get too caught up in the Chase before we make it,'' Letarte said.</p>
        <p>Things can turn bad in a hurry. Jimmie Johnson, Gordon's teammate, cut a left front tire late at Pocono and slipped to 42nd place, or next to last. Johnson, the defending Nextel Cup champion, fell two places to fourth in the standings.</p>
        <p>''The 48 had a fabulous car, but one cut tire and he finishes 42nd -- it's that easy,'' Letarte said, referring to Johnson by his car number. ''When you're up front, you don't want to take any chances -- any chances at all.''</p>
        <p>Gordon's car did not appear to be capable of running up front last Sunday, but Letarte used two resources -- one in his pit box, the other atop the long grandstands at Pocono -- to put him there.</p>
        <p>Two waves of rain showers had swept over the track, pushing the start of the race back nearly three hours, to 5 p.m. Pocono is not lighted, and 500-mile races there take nearly four hours to complete, meaning that the race would probably end at dusk.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Pocono is nestled in the mountains of eastern Pennsylvania, and weather conditions are unpredictable. So Letarte and his race engineer, Kane Replogle, kept an eye on a television monitor on the pit box that carried information from weather radar.</p>
        <p>Most teams have access to such information. They also have spotters standing on the press box high above the track to provide drivers and the teams with details about traffic and developments they may not see on the track.</p>
        <p>Letarte told his spotter, Shannon McGlamery, to not only look down at the track, but to glimpse at the clouds. About an hour into the race, McGlamery radioed Letarte to tell him of a sizable rain cloud rolling toward the racetrack.</p>
        <p>Now the race, to Letarte, appeared sure to end well before dark, and it would become an official race after 101 of 200 laps. So he changed his strategy, basing his pit-road decisions on the race ending slightly after the halfway point. When the race leader, Ryan Newman, made a pit stop after 64 laps, Letarte had Gordon stay on the track, a move that gave Gordon the lead. It was a gamble that was dicey enough for TNT commentators to second-guess -- Sunday-night quarterbacking, perhaps.</p>
        <p>''I think it became apparent to everyone there that we were racing until the rain got there,'' Letarte said. ''I was amazed that the cars running behind us didn't use the same strategy.''</p>
        <p>Gordon gave up the lead when he pitted 17 laps later, but he had enough gas and tires with just enough grip to make it to the halfway point.</p>
        <p>Newman had to pit again after the 90th lap, and Gordon took the lead again when Carl Edwards, running low on gas, pitted after 98 laps. The race was stopped after 106 laps, or right after Gordon held off a last-ditch charge by Newman before rain fell again as the sun was setting.</p>
        <p>''I would have been happy with a third or a fourth or a second,'' Letarte said. ''We've been blessed this season. At the same time, we've brought cars to the racetrack that have been good enough to win. And when you have good-enough cars, the good breaks tend to outnumber the bad breaks.''</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
