<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Father Figures, Though Not As Much</title>
    <meta content="15nyc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/nyregion/15nyc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854697"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Koplewicz, Harold S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E3DB153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="773" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Father Figures, Though Not As Much</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Father Figures, Though Not as Much</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This is about as scientifically rigorous as alchemy. But the sense here, as we head toward another Father's Day, is that married men and women could not be more different when it comes to displaying family photographs at work. It says something about relationships.</p>
        <p>Men usually put up photos of their wives and children. Women tend to post pictures of just the kids, almost as if the tykes had made it into this world through parthenogenesis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fathers tend to put up photos of their wives and children in their offices; mothers just display pictures of their kids.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This is about as scientifically rigorous as alchemy. But the sense here, as we head toward another Father's Day, is that married men and women could not be more different when it comes to displaying family photographs at work. It says something about relationships.</p>
        <p>Men usually put up photos of their wives and children. Women tend to post pictures of just the kids, almost as if the tykes had made it into this world through parthenogenesis.</p>
        <p>Naturally, this is a generalization with many exceptions, so please hold those protest messages. But we've observed the phenomenon long enough that a line from an old folk song rattles across the brain: Where have all the young men gone?</p>
        <p>Where? That's easy, Dr. Catherine Birndorf said: ''The guy has served his purpose.''</p>
        <p>Is that it? The men did their duty, and are now dispensable?</p>
        <p>Well, if you distill the answer to its essence, yeah.</p>
        <p>''The core issue is that for women, once they have kids, the man becomes, not second rate or second fiddle, but they're the primary caretaker for these kids,'' said Dr. Birndorf, a psychiatrist who is director of the Payne Whitney Women's Program at NewYork-Presbyterian/Weill Cornell hospital. ''Even with a really participatory father, Mom is still the mom.''</p>
        <p>With those photos, she said, the mother is saying, ''These are my kids, this is my life -- you may think I'm here at work, but I have a second shift, and here it is, represented.''</p>
        <p>It may sound ''so horrible,'' Dr. Birndorf said, but ''the husband becomes a little ancillary.''</p>
        <p>And oh Dad, poor Dad? Why is the schnook still putting up photos of the whole family?</p>
        <p>Fathers are ''a little more traditional,'' she said. ''They think it's a symbol, as one of my colleagues said, that they've made it. It's a status. The family's intact.''</p>
        <p>As for herself, being a psychiatrist, ''I, of course, have no pictures up in my office.'' Too personal. ''But my husband, who's a surgeon, has a picture of me and my kids up in his office,'' she said. (We were tempted to point out that she said ''my kids'' and not ''our kids,'' but decided that this was a road best not traveled.)</p>
        <p>Similar thoughts were offered by Dr. Harold S. Koplewicz, director of the New York University Child Study Center, who says that, yes, he has pictures of his wife and three children in his office.</p>
        <p>Women, whether they stay at home or go to an office, are more likely to make the children a priority, he said. Men today may do more around the house than in the past. But traditional roles -- Pop as chief breadwinner, Mom as nurturer -- have hardly disappeared.</p>
        <p>With the photos, Dr. Koplewicz said, ''men are taking tremendous pride in the fact of, 'This is my family. These are the people benefiting from my work.' It's very different from the mind-set of a woman who's saying, 'These children are my primary responsibility.' ''</p>
        <p>Even at home, the father is often missing from family photos. A technology company in New York called SharedBook, which turns digital data into book form, did a survey two years ago of Americans' picture-taking habits. It found that the person who appeared most frequently in family shots was the mother, followed by the daughter and then the son.</p>
        <p>Who brought up the rear? Dad, of course. Even the dog showed up more than he did.</p>
        <p>One reason may be that ''the father tends to take most of the pictures,'' said Caroline Vanderlip, SharedBook's chief executive. That said, ''it's more often the mother who puts them in a photo album or on a mug or makes a photo book.''</p>
        <p>''Women tend more to be the harvester of memories,'' Ms. Vanderlip said.</p>
        <p>The father may be missing for a reason beyond the probability that he's snapping the pictures. He is absent from photos because he is often absent, period. While fathers today are more involved in their kids' lives, Dr. Koplewicz said, they are still far less likely than mothers to be on hand for Kodak moments: the kindergarten graduation, the school play, the midweek soccer game.</p>
        <p>But there are, as we said, exceptions.</p>
        <p>We are familiar with a father who has been photographed many times, from various angles. He has attended his daughter's high school performances and taken her on college tours. He has cheered on his son at football. For sure, he has had rocky times with them and with his wife. Still, when last seen, they were all gathering for dinner. He seemed content with them, and they with him.</p>
        <p>But enough about Tony Soprano.</p>
        <p>NYC E-mail: haberman@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: haberman@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
