<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boom Times For Banks In Venezuela</title>
    <meta content="15venezbank" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/business/worldbusiness/15venezbank.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854657"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit and Money Cards</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gross Domestic Product</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Venezuela</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Citigroup Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Santander Central Hispano</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bbva Sa</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chavez, Hugo (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Guerra, Betzaida</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gould, Jens Erik</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Guerra, Betzaida</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit and Money Cards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gross Domestic Product</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leading Economic Indicators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Venezuela</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Chavez, Hugo</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E0DC153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1261" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boom Times For Banks In Venezuela</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Boom Times for Banks in Venezuela</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENS ERIK GOULD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gould, Jens Erik</byline>
      <dateline>CARACAS, Venezuela</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Venezuelan Pres Hugo Chavez, who repeatedly vows to do away with capitalism in Venezuela, is finding his economic policies have been generating boom for those most capitalist institutions--Venezuela's banks; record public spending, fueled by high oil prices, is flooding economy with cash; government currency controls are trapping much of that money in country; extra cash is increasing consumer spending; banks are taking advantage of that by handing out scores of loans; bank profits grew 32 percent in 2006, led by increases of more than 100 percent in credit card loans and 143 percent in automobile credit; banking and insurance industries' contribution to gross domestic product rose 37 percent in 2006; banks may be thriving too much for government's liking; Chavez warned in May that state could take over industry if it did not offer low-cost financing to Venezuelan businesses; among institutions that would be affected by such move are Citigroup and Spanish banks Santander and BBVA, customers are taking advantage of expansion in credit; Betzaida Guerra secured credit for nearly $5,000 surgery to enlarge her breasts; photo of Guerra (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In marathon speeches peppered with quotes from Marx and accolades to Che Guevara, President Hugo Chávez repeatedly vows to do away with capitalism in Venezuela. But it turns out that Mr. Chávez's economic policies have been generating a boom for those most capitalist of institutions -- Venezuela's banks.</p>
        <p>Record public spending, fueled by high oil prices, is flooding this flourishing economy with cash. Government currency controls are trapping much of that money in the country. The extra cash, in turn, is increasing consumer spending. The banks are taking advantage of that by handing out scores of loans, advertising on flashy billboards across Caracas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Hugo Chávez’s economic policies have been generating a boom for those most capitalist of institutions  Venezuela’s banks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In marathon speeches peppered with quotes from Marx and accolades to Che Guevara, President Hugo Chávez repeatedly vows to do away with capitalism in Venezuela. But it turns out that Mr. Chávez's economic policies have been generating a boom for those most capitalist of institutions -- Venezuela's banks.</p>
        <p>Record public spending, fueled by high oil prices, is flooding this flourishing economy with cash. Government currency controls are trapping much of that money in the country. The extra cash, in turn, is increasing consumer spending. The banks are taking advantage of that by handing out scores of loans, advertising on flashy billboards across Caracas.</p>
        <p>And with interest rates lower than the rate of inflation, ''you would be stupid not to take out a loan right now,'' said Richard Francis, a director of sovereign ratings at Standard &amp; Poor's.</p>
        <p>As a result, bank profits grew 33 percent last year, led by increases of more than 100 percent in credit card loans and 143 percent in automobile credit, according to Softline Consulting, a financial analysis firm here. The banking and insurance industries' contribution to the gross domestic product rose 37 percent in 2006, the central bank said.</p>
        <p>The market looked attractive enough two years ago that the Stanford Financial Group of Houston put political risk on the back burner to open a dozen branches here. Now, remodeling its office tower in the Caracas business district of El Rosal, the bank has seen its revenue in Venezuela grow fourfold, and its credit portfolio nearly tripled last year.</p>
        <p>Still, the banks may be thriving too much for the government's liking. Mr. Chávez warned last month that the state could take over the industry if it did not offer low-cost financing to Venezuelan businesses. Among the institutions that would be affected by such a move are Citigroup and the Spanish banks Santander and BBVA, which control lucrative outlets here.</p>
        <p>Venezuelan private industry is well aware that the president is not afraid of nationalizing. He made similar threats before the government bought out American companies' stakes in the largest private electric and telephone utilities this year. Venezuela also took over operation of multibillion-dollar oil projects in May.</p>
        <p>Bankers do not dismiss the possibility of an eventual takeover in their business, but they do not expect such a move in the short or medium term. ''The government needs private investment in banking,'' said Dirán Sarkissián, president of the Stanford Bank in Venezuela. ''Ask them if they have the personnel to manage 50 financial institutions.''</p>
        <p>Oscar García Mendoza, president of the locally owned Venezolano de Crédito and one of the few bankers openly critical of the Chávez government, said that the threat could be seriously intended but that ''it would be a disaster that would affect millions of Venezuelans who trust the banking system for their savings.''</p>
        <p>In the meantime, customers have been taking advantage of the expansion in credit. Betzaida Guerra, 43, for example, said she discovered in a newspaper ad last year that a bank could finance an operation she had long wanted but could not afford. Within weeks, she secured credit for the nearly $5,000 surgery to enlarge her breasts.</p>
        <p>''I was excited,'' said Ms. Guerra, an accountant from a Caracas suburb, who has nearly finished paying off her 12-month loan. ''I saw the advertisement and thought, 'The way out has arrived.' ''</p>
        <p>The expanded use of credit is apparent in upper-middle-class Caracas neighborhoods like Altamira, where Gabriel Jiménez was getting ready to drive his new black Mercedes-Benz C200 sedan off the lot. Mr. Jiménez had bought the same model without financing in 2000, but this time he chose a 48-month loan to pay off most of the cost at 19 percent interest. The Venezuelan-owned Banesco approved his loan in only 72 hours.</p>
        <p>''The process is really easy,'' said Mr. Jiménez, a divorce lawyer, before hopping into the driver's seat, smelling the new car's scent and playing with its gadgets. ''Before, interest rates were so high that it wasn't worth it.''</p>
        <p>The Altamira Mercedes dealership, which opened last year because of rising demand for luxury cars, has sold 9 of every 10 automobiles on credit this year since it began advertising the financing option in local newspapers, the director of operations, Vicente Amengual, said. Last year, only one of 10 was bought with a loan.</p>
        <p>Government officials point to the booming banks as an indicator of a healthy economy, which grew more than 10 percent last year and nearly 9 percent in the first quarter of 2007.</p>
        <p>They say that the surge in the use of credit reflects growing consumer power and access to banking services for the country's poor, many of whom do not have bank accounts.</p>
        <p>A burgeoning number of state-financed development banks have increased access to microcredit loans for low-income Venezuelans. Yolanda Vera, from the lower-class area of Propatria in western Caracas, said one such institution, a women's development bank called Banmujer, has given her a series of loans totaling $2,500 over the last three years for a start-up business that produces table linen.</p>
        <p>''It has been a great push,'' said Ms. Vera, 50, who left her job at a cloth factory to open the business. ''I always wanted to have my own company.''</p>
        <p>Banks have profited as well from Argentine bonds they bought from the Venezuelan government in 2005 and 2006 at the official exchange rate. Then they sold the bonds for dollars and profited by buying bolívars at a higher black market rate. ''They were very attractive earnings,'' said Miguel Octavio of BBO Financieros of Caracas.</p>
        <p>This year, banks earned commissions as intermediaries for $7.5 billion in bonds issued by the state oil company Petróleos de Venezuela, the largest corporate bond sale in the country's history.</p>
        <p>But bank directors say these advantages and current revenue are more than offset by government regulations that are making the sector more vulnerable. Banks are required to commit 32 percent of their loans to specific areas of the economy, including agriculture, housing and microcredit. Coming changes in the country's banking law may increase that percentage, said Ricardo Sanguino, president of the National Assembly's Finance Commission.</p>
        <p>''Here, the norms change,'' Mr. Sarkissián said. ''Every day they give us more news, a new regulation. That is constant.''</p>
        <p>The central bank, which has lost most of its autonomy from the government, announced in April that it would force private banks to double the amount of cash they deposit in their reserves, to 30 percent, in an effort to curb inflation. In the same week, Mr. Chávez ordered Fogade, the country's bank deposit protection fund, to transfer all its assets to the government, which would then distribute the cash to the poor.</p>
        <p>Critics also say that Venezuela's inflation rate of more than 19 percent, the highest in Latin America, could force the government to raise interest rates. That, in turn, could make it more difficult for borrowers to pay back their loans.</p>
        <p>Still, even with the ground shifting beneath them, banks expect to keep prospering, at least in the short term, as long as high oil prices continue to energize consumption.</p>
        <p>After all, these days Venezuelans can get financing to buy silicone for plastic surgery at their local pharmacy. At a Locatel drug store in eastern Caracas, eight people a day request loans administered through a Banesco credit card for implants.</p>
        <p>''Lots of people come, especially during Christmas, Easter and graduation season,'' a saleswoman, Solsyret Delgado, saidas customers lined up at her register to inquire about the credit card offer. ''We've given them to almost everyone.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
