<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Anglican Demand for Change Is Rebuffed by Episcopalians</title>
    <meta content="15episcopal" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/us/15episcopal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854580"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Episcopal Church</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Anglican Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anglican Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Episcopal Church</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DD153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="454" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Anglican Demand for Change Is Rebuffed by Episcopalians</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Anglican Demand for Change Is Rebuffed by Episcopalians</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE GOODSTEIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The executive council of the Episcopal Church announced yesterday that it would not comply with demands from leaders of the global Anglican Communion to retract the church's liberal position on homosexuality and create alternative supervision for disaffected conservative Episcopalians.</p>
        <p>The announcement came a day after the Anglican archbishop of Kenya said he would consecrate an American bishop in Texas to minister to alienated Episcopalians in the United States. In May, the archbishop of Nigeria installed a bishop in Virginia, a step considered by many to be outside the bounds of Anglicanism's traditional lines of authority.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The executive council of the Episcopal Church announced that it would not comply with demands from Anglican leaders to retract the church’s liberal position on homosexuality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The executive council of the Episcopal Church announced yesterday that it would not comply with demands from leaders of the global Anglican Communion to retract the church's liberal position on homosexuality and create alternative supervision for disaffected conservative Episcopalians.</p>
        <p>The announcement came a day after the Anglican archbishop of Kenya said he would consecrate an American bishop in Texas to minister to alienated Episcopalians in the United States. In May, the archbishop of Nigeria installed a bishop in Virginia, a step considered by many to be outside the bounds of Anglicanism's traditional lines of authority.</p>
        <p>The churches in the Anglican Communion, which trace their heritage to the Church of England, have been brought to the brink of schism over the issue of homosexuality. The executive council's action makes clear that the Episcopal Church, Anglicanism's American branch, does not intend to back down.</p>
        <p>Leaders of the Anglican Communion's geographical provinces, known as primates, issued an ultimatum to the Episcopal Church in February demanding that it stop blessing same-sex unions and agree not to consecrate another openly gay bishop. The primates gave the Episcopal Church until Sept. 30 to comply.</p>
        <p>The executive council, after a four-day meeting in Parsippany, N.J., followed the footsteps of the church's House of Bishops and issued a statement yesterday, saying, ''We question the authority of the primates to impose deadlines and demands upon any of the churches of the Anglican Communion.''</p>
        <p>The council said the primates' demands could ''only properly be dealt with by our General Convention,'' the large triennial meeting of Episcopal bishops, priests and laity, next scheduled for 2009.</p>
        <p>The council said, ''We strongly affirm this church's desire to be in the fullest possible relationship with our Anglican sisters and brothers, but in truth the only thing we really have to offer in that relationship is who we are.''</p>
        <p>The council said that the Episcopal Church had always ''struggled to embrace people who have historically been marginalized'' -- and that this applied to gay men and lesbians.</p>
        <p>Bonnie Anderson, president of the church's House of Deputies, composed of clergy and lay representatives, said: ''The Episcopal Church has spoken quite clearly as to where we are on this.''</p>
        <p>The new bishop to be consecrated by the archbishop of Kenya, Benjamin Nzimbi, is the Rev. Canon Bill Atwood, who runs the Ekklesia Society, an aid organization based in Dallas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Atwood said he would minister to about 30 congregations, 20 predominantly American and 10 Kenyan, throughout the United States. He said his churches were cooperating with other conservative networks in the United States established by the archbishops of Nigeria and Rwanda.</p>
        <p>''There is a desperate need for care,'' Mr. Atwood said, ''and the Episcopal Church has been utterly unresponsive.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
