<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AHEAD | Independence Day Celebrations; Where It All Started</title>
    <meta content="15ahead" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854519"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Independence Day (US) (July 4)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Considine, Austin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Independence Day (US) (July 4)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EED6143FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AHEAD | Independence Day Celebrations; Where It All Started</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AUSTIN CONSIDINE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Considine, Austin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Independence Day celebrations scheduled around country; list; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INDEPENDENCE DAY means fireworks and parades all over the United States, but in cities that played roles in the American Revolution, the commemorations go to another level. Some of the best Fourth of July parties this year will be in Boston; Philadelphia; Charleston, S.C.; Bennington, Vt.; and Yorktown, Va.</p>
        <p>Philadelphia, where the Declaration of Independence was signed, the Continental Congress met and the British camped as occupiers in 1777 and 1778, will be busy with activities from June 28 to July 4. The weeklong Welcome America Philadelphia festival includes two evenings of fireworks on the waterfront, with performances by acts like Chaka Khan and Hall and Oates; an all-day salsa fest on the Ben Franklin Parkway; and the Taste of Philadelphia. Cara Schneider, director of media relations for the Greater Philadelphia Tourism Marketing Corporation, said at least a million people were expected to participate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INDEPENDENCE DAY means fireworks and parades all over the United States, but in cities that played roles in the American Revolution, the commemorations go to another level. Some of the best Fourth of July parties this year will be in Boston; Philadelphia; Charleston, S.C.; Bennington, Vt.; and Yorktown, Va.</p>
        <p>Philadelphia, where the Declaration of Independence was signed, the Continental Congress met and the British camped as occupiers in 1777 and 1778, will be busy with activities from June 28 to July 4. The weeklong Welcome America Philadelphia festival includes two evenings of fireworks on the waterfront, with performances by acts like Chaka Khan and Hall and Oates; an all-day salsa fest on the Ben Franklin Parkway; and the Taste of Philadelphia. Cara Schneider, director of media relations for the Greater Philadelphia Tourism Marketing Corporation, said at least a million people were expected to participate.</p>
        <p>Away from the revelry, visitors in town for the Fourth can pay a quiet visit to the National Constitution Center where, starting July 4, a rare early printing of the Magna Carta can be viewed alongside equally rare early copies of the Constitution and the Emancipation Proclamation.</p>
        <p>One block away, public readings of the Declaration of Independence will be held at the Independence Visitor Center each day from June 28 through July 4 at noon.</p>
        <p>Boston, famous in revolutionary history for such events as the Boston Tea Party in 1773, also goes all-out for the Fourth. The Boston Harborfest, held downtown from June 28 to July 4, encompasses music ranging from Motown cover bands to the Middlesex Country Volunteer Fifes and Drums; Tea Party re-enactments; history tours; sailing trips aboard the Liberty Clipper schooner; storytelling sessions; and a clam chowder competition.</p>
        <p>Then comes the Boston Pops Fireworks Spectacular, this year featuring the late-night talk-show host Craig Ferguson and John Mellencamp. The show, which also includes a patriotic singalong and the ''1812 Overture'' performed with real cannons, draws hundreds of thousands of people each year, organizers said.</p>
        <p>When it comes to fireworks shows, though, New York boasts the country's largest, most notably above the East River and in front of the Statue of Liberty. It's a yearly nose-thumbing at British victories in early Revolutionary War battles fought in New York, including those at Brooklyn Heights and Fort Washington.</p>
        <p>Local tradition often means private rooftop parties along the waterfront. But there are also public viewpoints in places like Roosevelt Island, South Street Seaport, the Brooklyn Heights Promenade, Empire-Fulton Ferry State Park in Brooklyn and Liberty State Park in Jersey City. Battery Park is a good viewing spot for the Statue of Liberty fireworks show and concert, which will feature performances this year by the indie rock bands Midlake and the New Pornographers.</p>
        <p>Charleston, S.C., was the location of a crippling siege laid by British forces that ended in the city's surrender in 1780. On the Fourth, Charleston's festivities include a fireworks display launched from the flight deck of the U.S.S. Yorktown, a World War II-era aircraft carrier that saw action in the battles of the Philippine Sea and Iwo Jima and that is now part of the Patriots Point Naval and Maritime Museum.</p>
        <p>The fireworks and other festivities draw between 20,000 and 30,000 people to Patriots Point, on the Mount Pleasant side of Charleston Harbor, said Jim McElroy, director of communications there. This year visitors can also check out the newly opened Congressional Medal of Honor Museum inside the carrier.</p>
        <p>Smaller towns also remember their Revolutionary moments on the Fourth. Festivities in Bennington, Vt. -- site of the Battle of Bennington, in which American troops trounced a force of Hessian mercenaries -- include a reading of the Declaration of Independence in front of the town's battle monument, colonial-era games for children and a fireworks show.</p>
        <p>And Yorktown, Va., a small village of just over 200 people, celebrates its big name in history as the site of Gen. George Cornwallis's surrender to American forces in 1781, effectively ending the war. Yorktown's Fourth of July celebrations have drawn as many as 35,000 people, organizers said, for fireworks, live music, a five-kilometer ''Freedom Run'' and a parade.</p>
        <p>DETAILS</p>
        <p>PHILADELPHIA</p>
        <p>What: Welcome America Philadelphia festival, (215) 683-2200, www.americasbirthday.com When: June 28 to July 4.</p>
        <p>BOSTON</p>
        <p>What: Boston Harborfest, (617) 227-1528, www.bostonharborfest.com; Boston Pops Fireworks Spectacular, www.july4thorg.</p>
        <p>When: June 28 to July 4.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>What: Fireworks, concerts, www.rivertorivernyc.com.</p>
        <p>When: July 4.</p>
        <p>CHARLESTON, S.C. Patriots Point Naval and Maritime Museum</p>
        <p>What: Fireworks, festival, (866) 831-1720; www.patriotspoint.org.</p>
        <p>When: July 4.</p>
        <p>BENNINGTON, VT.</p>
        <p>What: Battle monument ceremony, fireworks, www.bennington.com.</p>
        <p>When: July 4.</p>
        <p>YORKTOWN, VA.</p>
        <p>What: Parade, fireworks, music, 5-kilometer run, (757) 890-3500; www.yorkcounty.gov/fourth.</p>
        <p>When: July 4.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
