<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giuliani Cites Reagan, Not Bush, As Model for Strong Leadership</title>
    <meta content="15giuliani" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854624"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2008 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7DC153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="341" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giuliani Cites Reagan, Not Bush, As Model for Strong Leadership</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC SANTORA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rudolph W. Giuliani, who has largely steered clear of criticizing President Bush as he campaigns for the Republican presidential nomination, took an indirect swipe at the president on Thursday, suggesting that Mr. Bush was failing to provide strong leadership.</p>
        <p>''What we're lacking is strong, aggressive, bold leadership like we had with Ronald Reagan,'' Mr. Giuliani told supporters at a Flag Day rally in Wilmington, Del.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rudolph W. Giuliani, who has largely steered clear of criticizing President Bush as he campaigns for the Republican presidential nomination, took an indirect swipe at the president on Thursday, suggesting that Mr. Bush was failing to provide strong leadership.</p>
        <p>''What we're lacking is strong, aggressive, bold leadership like we had with Ronald Reagan,'' Mr. Giuliani told supporters at a Flag Day rally in Wilmington, Del.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Bush's job-approval rating at a record low, Mr. Giuliani is wrestling with how to not seem disloyal to the president while making it clear that he would bring change to Washington.</p>
        <p>Unlike Senator John McCain of Arizona, who has been a frequent and vocal critic of the administration as he campaigns for the 2008 Republican nomination, Mr. Giuliani has largely avoided directly challenging the actions of the White House.</p>
        <p>After his address in Delaware, Mr. Giuliani was quick to try to explain his remarks and praise Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>''I have tremendous admiration for President Bush,'' he said, according to a transcript provided by his campaign. ''I guess in the first debate when some of my Republican colleagues were trying to distance themselves I went ahead and I said, you know, we Republicans should be talking about the things President Bush has done right.''</p>
        <p>In the past, Mr. Giuliani has been critical of what he referred to as the administration's failure to explain the importance of the war in Iraq, but not the decision to go to war.</p>
        <p>''I think President Bush made the single biggest decision of his presidency correctly,'' he said. ''He put us on offense against terrorism. I will always admire him for that.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Giuliani said he viewed Reagan as his model.</p>
        <p>''As far as the things that developed my ideas and thinking, which developed as a much younger man, it was Ronald Reagan,'' he said.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Bush was running for president, he also often chose to invoke the memory of Reagan, even, at times, at the expense of the earlier President George Bush, his father.</p>
        <p>THE 2008 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
