<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Street Scene; India's Economic Boom Transforms Stock Trading Into a National Pastime</title>
    <meta content="15indiastox" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/business/worldbusiness/15indiastox.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854550"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Timmons, Heather</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">India</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E4DE153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1064" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Street Scene; India's Economic Boom Transforms Stock Trading Into a National Pastime</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">India’s Economic Boom Transforms Stock Trading Into a National Pastime</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HEATHER TIMMONS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Timmons, Heather</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, June 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>India's stock markets are on roll, surpassing even rosiest forecasts, in part because of young, wealthy, expanding middle class that is banking on India's aggressive corporate growth; Indian indexes have hit new highs, drawing in foreign investors and Wall Street banks; market bulls say fundamental shift is under way as consumers tie their personal wealth more closely to India Inc, paving way for more prosperous middle class; bears have begun to talk about bubble fed by naive optimism and day trading; critics say Indian investors have forgotten heavy losses they suffered after fraud depressed markets in early 1990s and technology burst few years ago; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Devender Singh invested in India's volatile stock markets for the first time last year after watching a friend make a mint. The markets promptly fell 30 percent.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Singh, who runs a travel company that leads tours to New York, did not panic. He waited, and a few months later, his investments were up 10 percent. ''You've got to have patience,'' he said. Of course, he also stopped taking all of his friend's advice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>India’s markets are on a roll, as an expanding middle class banks on corporate growth. But bears have begun talk of a bubble.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Devender Singh invested in India's volatile stock markets for the first time last year after watching a friend make a mint. The markets promptly fell 30 percent.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Singh, who runs a travel company that leads tours to New York, did not panic. He waited, and a few months later, his investments were up 10 percent. ''You've got to have patience,'' he said. Of course, he also stopped taking all of his friend's advice.</p>
        <p>For now, India's markets are on a roll, surpassing even the rosiest forecasts, in part because of a young, wealthy, expanding middle class that is banking on India's aggressive corporate growth. While Alan Greenspan, the former chairman of the Federal Reserve, has offered warnings about China's market, Indian indexes have hit new highs, drawing in foreign investors and Wall Street banks.</p>
        <p>Many Indian companies are looking to take advantage of the fervor. This week, the country's largest public offering came to the market, the $2.4 billion float of the real estate company DLF. Despite a history strewn with lawsuits, fears of a property bubble and a prospectus that lists 76 risks, DLF was oversubscribed.</p>
        <p>This month, India's ICICI Bank plans to tap markets in India and the United States for $5 billion. Stock offerings in 2007 will shortly reach $10 billion, in part because of a new issue from Tata Steel, which is raising money to finance the acquisition of a rival, the Corus Group.</p>
        <p>The frothy share prices and large initial offerings are intensifying a debate in India.</p>
        <p>Market bulls say a fundamental shift is under way as consumers tie their personal wealth more closely to India Inc., paving the way for a more prosperous middle class.</p>
        <p>''There has been a sea change in the way people are approaching savings and investments,'' said Sanjay Prakash, head of HSBC's mutual fund business in India. In the last five years, he said, a lot of people became very rich.</p>
        <p>But bears have begun to talk about a bubble fed by naïve optimism and day trading. Indian investors have forgotten, critics say, the heavy losses they suffered after fraud depressed the markets in the early 1990s and the technology bubble burst a few years ago.</p>
        <p>''It's a bubble to the extent that we lack depth and breadth in the market,'' said Prithvi Haldea, a founder and managing director of New Delhi's Prime Database, which tracks issues and trends in the markets. About three-quarters of the daily volume comes from day trading, he said. ''It's more of a casino,'' he said. If you ask those traders what they know about a stock, ''they can't answer you,'' Mr. Haldea said.</p>
        <p>While the argument intensifies, the recent growth and volatility are undeniable. In 2004, the Bombay Stock Exchange's Sensex Index passed what was seen as the psychologically crucial 4,000 mark. It closed Thursday at 14,203.73, and many traders expect it to hit 15,000 this year. In the 12 months ended June 8, India's market indexes have risen 45.6 percent, HSBC said. In addition, the amount of household savings invested in the equities and mutual funds has risen to about 5 percent from about 1 percent four years ago.</p>
        <p>In May, the market cap of companies on the Bombay Stock Exchange crossed $1 trillion, putting India second only to China among emerging markets. But in recent weeks, the Sensex Index has yo-yo'ed, dropping as much as 1 percent in a day.</p>
        <p>Stock watching has become an obsession in India, one that rivals cricket and Bollywood. India has three national business television news channels and another in the planning, four national daily business newspapers and dozens of business magazines. In The Hindustan Times, a daily newspaper that claims 14 million readers, the ''World News'' is tucked behind the business section.</p>
        <p>Believing in India's stock markets means believing in India itself -- and the country's ability to transform its combination of young population, dilapidated infrastructure, chaotic streets and unbridled optimism into a corporate superpower.</p>
        <p>The market is ''fundamentally going to rise,'' said D. K. Malhotra, a 46-year-old bank manager whose household has about 50 percent of its savings in the markets. Sureha, his wife, a 41-year-old homemaker, does the trading, he said, and makes her own decisions. The Malhotras have put all their investments in blue chips, companies like Reliance Industries and Maruti.</p>
        <p>''This is not a fad,'' Mr. Malhotra said. ''We sleep quiet at night, no problem.''</p>
        <p>Even Bollywood has joined in. ''Guru,'' a 2007 film about an Indian villager turned business tycoon, neatly sums up the ethos of the time. At a pivotal point, a taxi driver tells the chief executive and hero, ''I got my three daughters married'' thanks to your stock shares. At the close of the film, the hero promises to make India's largest company a global powerhouse, yelling to a stadium of gleeful shareholders, ''Tell the world we are coming.''</p>
        <p>In the Delhi headquarters of Angel Broking, across the hall from the Uzbekistan national airline, young male traders pack into computer-lined rooms that are frostily chilled against the heat outdoors. The brokerage house, which has 76 branches, has 220,000 clients and is growing 30 percent a year.</p>
        <p>''The risk appetite here is greater than in developed countries,'' said Dinesh Thakkar, founder of the brokerage firm, which is soliciting bids for a foreign partner. ''If you've already got wealth, you don't want to take risks,'' he said, ''but if you're aspiring to be wealthy, you're willing to do so.''</p>
        <p>Younger investors, he said, are more willing to take risks than previous generations, and they understand the products. Investors, in general, he said, are financially savvy because many of them have run or have grown up around small businesses.</p>
        <p>Even mutual funds, which have had a difficult time attracting assets in India, are growing.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Haldea has expressed concern about day traders, he acknowledges that his son is active in those very markets. ''He's earning tons of money and is willing to put it into the capital markets,'' Mr. Haldea said. ''With a growing population, there are new suckers every year.''</p>
        <p>Most Indian investors, though, are expressing nothing but optimism. Indian corporations are ''buying companies bigger than themselves, and have confidence,'' said Raman Verma, a trader who started with family money and now trades for several clients. ''In two or three years, the market may be saturated, but not now.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
