<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Austrians Cast Doubt on Russian Arrests in Murder Case</title>
    <meta content="15moscow" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/world/europe/15moscow.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854552"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Money Laundering</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Austria</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kramer, Andrew E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kozlov, Andrei</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frenkel, Aleksei Y</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Austria</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E2DE153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Austrians Cast Doubt on Russian Arrests in Murder Case</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Austrians Cast Doubt on Russian Arrests in Murder Case</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW E. KRAMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kramer, Andrew E</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, June 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Austrian authorities cast doubt on arrest made in Russia in shooting death last year of Andrei A Kozlov, deputy chairman of Russian Central Bank; suggest that Kozlov's death is linked to multimillion-dollar money-laundering scheme that made use of bank in Vienna; Austrian police say they passed important lead to their Russian colleagues, but it was disregarded; Kozlov was among highest-ranking officials to be killed in six-year administration of Pres Vladimir V Putin; Austrian disclosure suggests motive for killing at odds with what Moscow prosecutors pursued; Russian authorities say they solved case when they charged midlevel banker Aleksei Y Frenkel, whose business was unrelated to money-laundering investigation; Austrian authorities say police could not rule out 'official corruption' in Russia as motive for Kozlov's murder (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was among the more shocking contract murders in recent years in Moscow, a city that has seen more than its share of such crimes.</p>
        <p>Men wielding pistols walked up to the first deputy chairman of the Russian Central Bank in a parking lot of a soccer stadium and shot him in the head. Andrei A. Kozlov, 41, died early the next morning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Austrian authorities have cast doubt on the quality of Russian sleuthing, possibly linking a recent murder to a multi-million-dollar money-laundering scheme.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was among the more shocking contract murders in recent years in Moscow, a city that has seen more than its share of such crimes.</p>
        <p>Men wielding pistols walked up to the first deputy chairman of the Russian Central Bank in a parking lot of a soccer stadium and shot him in the head. Andrei A. Kozlov, 41, died early the next morning.</p>
        <p>Even more shocking, perhaps, as contract murders here are rarely solved, was the prosecutorial diligence that followed. Within three months, the police had arrested seven suspects and called the case closed.</p>
        <p>Now, however, authorities in Austria have cast doubt on the quality of the Russian sleuthing, possibly linking Mr. Kozlov's murder to a multi-million-dollar money-laundering scheme that made use of a bank in Vienna. ''We stated there could be a link and it should be investigated,'' Gerald Hersztera, a spokesman for the Austrian Interior Ministry, said in a telephone interview. So far, however, there has been no follow-up by Russian investigators.</p>
        <p>The Austrian police say that as the investigation into the shooting of Mr. Kozlov on Sept. 13, 2006, unfolded in Moscow, they passed an important lead to their Russian colleagues, but it was disregarded -- though Mr. Kozlov was among the highest-ranking officials to be killed in the six-year administration of President Vladimir V. Putin.</p>
        <p>Two weeks before his murder, Mr. Kozlov had been cooperating closely with Austrian authorities on the money-laundering case, a detail the Austrians made public in April. They said the Austrian police could not rule out ''official corruption'' in Russia as a motive for murder.</p>
        <p>''We didn't get any information about how the investigation is going in Russia,'' Mr. Hersztera said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kozlov's responsibilities involved, in part, shutting smaller banks that were used as intermediaries in schemes to launder money. These usually entail shifting profits from illegal enterprises, like drug deals or bribe taking, between banks and companies to disguise the origin of the money. In Russia, the initial, or precursor, crime is most often official corruption.</p>
        <p>The New Times, an independent magazine in Moscow that first reported the story, suggested that Mr. Kozlov was killed as he tried to halt a money-laundering operation run for officials in the Russian government.</p>
        <p>In August, Mr. Kozlov had informed an Austrian bank of suspicious transfers from a bank in Russia, according to Mr. Hersztera.</p>
        <p>As the authorities in both countries were rolling up the suspected money-laundering channel, Mr. Kozlov on Sept. 1 revoked the license of Diskont Bank, an obscure ''pocket bank'' of the sort that operate discreetly and without visible customers. The Austrian police have not identified the Viennese bank that received wire transfers from Diskont Bank. But Raiffeisen Zentralbank, one of Central Europe's largest, conceded in a statement that it had done so. The New Times, citing anonymous Russian Interior Ministry officers, said that $60 million was transferred in the final days of last August.</p>
        <p>Raiffeisen has confirmed that it froze money transferred from Diskont Bank based on a tip from Russia. Raiffeisen, in a statement, said its employees immediately notified the Austrian authorities and the Belgium-based Swift system for clearing international bank transfers.</p>
        <p>''We have instantly and actively cooperated with the authorities both in Austria and Russia because the avoidance of suspicious transactions is of paramount importance for us,'' Raiffeisen said in the statement.</p>
        <p>After the killing of Mr. Kozlov, the Austrian state attorney forwarded evidence -- including the information Mr. Kozlov had provided about money laundering -- to the Russian prosecutor general. The Austrian state attorney did not receive information from the Russian authorities, either on the initial money-laundering investigation begun by Mr. Kozlov or on the possible link to his killing, Mr. Hersztera said.</p>
        <p>Written questions submitted recently to the prosecutor general's office were not answered.</p>
        <p>But other Russian officials have acknowledged that Diskont Bank was involved in more than small-time fraud. On Sept. 16, just three days after the Kozlov shooting, Russia's finance minister, Aleksei L. Kudrin, speaking at a meeting of the Group of 8 finance ministers in Singapore, named Diskont Bank as suspicious when asked whether Mr. Kozlov's campaign against money-laundering was a motive for the killing.</p>
        <p>In March, a department head in the Russian Interior Ministry, Fyodor Putintsev, said the police suspected that a total of 41 billion rubles, or about $1.6 billion, was laundered through Diskont Bank.</p>
        <p>The Austrian disclosure suggests a motive for the killing that is at odds with what prosecutors pursued in Moscow last fall. Authorities here said they had solved the case when they charged a midlevel banker, Aleksei Y. Frenkel, whose business was unrelated to the Diskont Bank money-laundering investigation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frenkel was a board member of a little-known Russian bank, VIP Holding, which had earlier been sanctioned by Mr. Kozlov but had no relation to Diskont Bank.</p>
        <p>''The Russian police believe he was killed by another suspect, who had nothing to do with these banks'' in the money-laundering scheme, Mr. Hersztera said. Russian prosecutors say Mr. Frenkel paid a female acquaintance to arrange the killing of Mr. Kozlov. They say the woman and two other intermediaries paid three Ukrainian taxi drivers to shoot Mr. Kozlov as he walked toward his car.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frenkel maintains his innocence. His lawyer, Igor Trunov, said in a telephone interview that his client refused to confess even after being placed in a pretrial detention cell with inmates who were given incorrect information that Mr. Frenkel was homosexual, opening him to violence. The evidence from Austria, Mr. Trunov added, has not been made available to defense lawyers.</p>
        <p>In letters from jail published in Russian newspapers, Mr. Frenkel has further muddied the waters. He alleged that Central Bank officials, including Mr. Kozlov, were engaged in blackmailing bankers accused of money laundering by demanding bribes in exchange for destroying evidence of illegal transfers. The Central Bank has denied wrongdoing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
