<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Protesters of Shark Hunt Have New Strategy: They Get a Bigger Group</title>
    <meta content="15shark" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/nyregion/15shark.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sharks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Humane Society of the United States</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0DE153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1011" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Protesters of Shark Hunt Have New Strategy: They Get a Bigger Group</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Protesters of Shark Hunt Have New Strategy: They Get a Bigger Group</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIA C. MEAD</byline>
      <dateline>MONTAUK, N.Y., June 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When about 250 fishing boats sail out of Montauk Harbor on Friday in the hope of reeling in an enormous shark, and a share of $700,000 in prize money, they will be leaving trouble in their wake.</p>
        <p>For the past several years, the Star Island Yacht Club shark tournament, now in its 21st year, has faced only meager opposition from animal welfare advocates, who contend that such contests glorify the killing of declining species. But this time, the small band of demonstrators who plan to protest at the club's entrance have the backing of a powerful animal rights group, the Humane Society of the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Montauk shark fishing tournament is accused of glorifying the killing of endangered species.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When about 250 fishing boats sail out of Montauk Harbor on Friday in the hope of reeling in an enormous shark, and a share of $700,000 in prize money, they will be leaving trouble in their wake.</p>
        <p>For the past several years, the Star Island Yacht Club shark tournament, now in its 21st year, has faced only meager opposition from animal welfare advocates, who contend that such contests glorify the killing of declining species. But this time, the small band of demonstrators who plan to protest at the club's entrance have the backing of a powerful animal rights group, the Humane Society of the United States.</p>
        <p>''We know that sport fishing is considered a central part of Montauk's economy and we are up against some strong financial interests, but there's also a macho element to it,'' said William Crain, a professor of psychology at City College of New York. He noted that in the first year of the protests, only he and his wife picketed.</p>
        <p>The Humane Society, which has seven million members nationwide, has already shut down a small tournament in Destin, Fla., where it ran advertisements in newspapers, campaigned for a moratorium, organized protests and told officials about scientists' findings of declining shark populations. The society is using similar techniques on Long Island for the Star Island competition, and it is also campaigning against events this weekend in Ocean City, Md., and in July on Martha's Vineyard.</p>
        <p>''These tournaments inflict incredible suffering and cruelty on the sharks, and they are particularly unconscionable given the disastrous state of the shark populations,'' said John W. Grandy, the society's senior vice president for wildlife and habitat protection.</p>
        <p>Scientists have warned for decades that populations of the more popular game sharks -- mako, blue, thresher, tiger, hammerhead and great white among them -- have plunged, many in the North Atlantic by at least half. They say the decline is caused largely by commercial harvesting, in which sharks are often a throwaway ''bycatch.''</p>
        <p>In February, after scientists at a conference of the World Conservation Union reported that humans kill more than 70 million sharks each year, the union downgraded the status of threshers, prized for their scythelike tails, and short-fin makos -- both favored by recreational and commercial fishermen -- from ''near threatened'' to ''vulnerable to extinction.'' They found that the North Atlantic population of blue sharks, the most heavily fished of the fast-swimming pelagic species, had fallen by half in recent years.</p>
        <p>Many in Montauk, part of the town of East Hampton, remain passionate about its image as a historic fishing port, and its fleet of about a hundred charter and commercial boats depends heavily on the shark season for revenue.</p>
        <p>Tournament organizers and officials here and in other Long Island communities contend that the competitions are good for the economy, expose people to animals they may otherwise never see up close and operate under government limits that are intended to discourage wholesale slaughter.</p>
        <p>In addition, they say that the carcasses help researchers, and that some catches, like the Star Island tournament's, help feed the poor. Thirty-five potential prize-winning sharks were landed last year, including a 399-pound thresher, enabling Star Island to give 1,750 pounds of shark meat to food pantries and group homes.</p>
        <p>Jay Schneiderman, a Suffolk County legislator whose family owns a motel in Montauk, said landing a big fish has always touched off excitement here. ''All the restaurants have big fish mounted on their walls,'' Mr. Schneiderman said. ''There's always been pride about that.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Grandy of the Humane Society acknowledged that greater threats are posed by commercial harvesting and by ''finning'' -- slicing off a shark's fins and dumping it back into the water to die -- a practice that is illegal in the United States and Mexico.</p>
        <p>The crowds at Star Island cheer as each huge beast is hung by its tail and weighed. After a carcass is dumped on the dock, children poke at it, exclaim over its rows of fearsome teeth, and pose for family pictures as the animal is gutted, decapitated and sliced into steaks.</p>
        <p>''It's like a petting zoo,'' said Richard Janis, Star Island's general manager. ''When else can a kid get close enough to a shark to touch it?''</p>
        <p>Sharks are highly migratory and rarely surface, making them difficult to survey. Only in recent years have scientists begun to study closely the effects of exploitation, said Enric Cortés, a research biologist with the National Marine Fisheries Service. One result has been general agreement among scientists that pelagic species have declined since the 1960s, when their meat increased in value, and the 1970s, when the movie ''Jaws'' touched off an international sport-fishing fury.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cortés said that many species like threshers are slow to reproduce, making them more vulnerable to overfishing.</p>
        <p>''The people in Destin looked at the science and the conduct of their tournaments and decided they could no longer justify it,'' Dr. Grandy said. ''I am hopeful that people of good will and integrity will take that position up and down the East Coast.''</p>
        <p>But Dr. Timothy Holcomb, president of the Destin History and Fishing Museum, which sponsored the event in Florida, had a different recollection. ''They shut us down this year by threatening to scare off our donors,'' Dr. Holcomb said. ''The society said it had donors who would put up several million dollars for an advertising campaign to drive us out of business. We wanted to put the tournament on, but the museum just couldn't afford the fight.''</p>
        <p>The society may have met far more determined and deep-pocketed opposition in Montauk.</p>
        <p>Tournament competitors come to Star Island from all over the world, having made substantial investments in luxury boats, crews, travel costs and an $800 entry fee.</p>
        <p>And there is Sam Gershowitz, the owner of the Star Island Yacht Club as well as a large scrap-metal processing company, who has a reputation for not scaring easily. Mr. Gershowitz issued a statement saying, ''Fishing has been an important part of Long Island's heritage and economy, and we are honored to continue the tradition.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
