<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Energy Measure Blocked By Republicans in Senate</title>
    <meta content="15energy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/washington/15energy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854588"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (DC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E4DD153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Energy Measure Blocked By Republicans in Senate</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Energy Measure Blocked by Republicans in Senate</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senate Democrats, facing their first significant battle over a wide-ranging bill intended to reduce oil consumption, found themselves blocked by Republicans on Thursday and postponed all significant votes until next week.</p>
        <p>Republicans vowed to filibuster over a Democratic proposal that would force electric utility companies to generate a big share of their power from renewable fuels, and Democrats failed to muster the 60 votes needed to close off debate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Republicans vowed to filibuster over a Democratic proposal that would force electric utility companies to generate a big share of their power from renewable fuels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senate Democrats, facing their first significant battle over a wide-ranging bill intended to reduce oil consumption, found themselves blocked by Republicans on Thursday and postponed all significant votes until next week.</p>
        <p>Republicans vowed to filibuster over a Democratic proposal that would force electric utility companies to generate a big share of their power from renewable fuels, and Democrats failed to muster the 60 votes needed to close off debate.</p>
        <p>The impasse forced Democrats to begin negotiating a possible compromise with Republicans and the power industry, which have argued that companies in many parts of the country simply cannot generate enough power from wind or solar energy to meet the requirements.</p>
        <p>''We're trying to work something out,'' said Senator Harry Reid of Nevada, the Senate Democratic leader. But by early evening, the principle negotiators had failed to reach a deal and Democrats decided to postpone further voting until next Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The Democrats' unexpected difficulty meant they made virtually no progress on the energy bill after about a week of floor debate. Though the Senate's intricate rules make such logjams common, the delay was a bad omen for what lawmakers already knew would be a long and grueling fight on one of the signature issues of energy conservation and renewable fuels.</p>
        <p>At issue on Thursday was a provision called the ''Renewable Portfolio Standard,'' which would require electric utilities to obtain 15 percent of their electricity from wind, solar or biomass energy by 2020.</p>
        <p>But the energy bill would make profound changes in other areas as well. It would require car companies to increase the average fuel economy of cars and light trucks to 35 miles a gallon by 2020. It would also require a huge increase in the production of renewable fuels for cars and trucks and require the federal government to set tougher efficiency standards for electric appliances. The measure would also give the government more power to prosecute ''price gouging'' by oil companies.</p>
        <p>Senate Democrats are also drafting a tax package that is expected to provide as much as $25 billion in incentives for renewable fuels and conservation -- much of which would be paid for by tax increases on the nation's oil companies. Those provisions face intense opposition from the affected industries, and President Bush has threatened to veto any bill that contains the price-gouging measure.</p>
        <p>At the moment, renewable fuels produce less than 1 percent of the nation's electricity, and wind power is by far the biggest alternative source for that electricity. Supporters of the measure say other sources, such as methane from landfills, could eventually play a major role.</p>
        <p>''The benefits are clear,'' said Senator Jeff Bingaman, Democrat of New Mexico and the energy bill's primary author. ''This portfolio standard would reduce our dependence on traditional polluting sources of electricity. It would reduce our dependence on foreign energy sources. It would reduce the growing pressure on natural gas as a fuel for the generation of electricity.''</p>
        <p>But Republicans said the goals were unrealistic because many parts of the country -- especially in the southeast -- do not get enough wind to meet the bill's goals.</p>
        <p>A substitute proposed by Senator Pete V. Domenici of New Mexico, the ranking Republican on the Energy Committee, would have allowed utilities to meet their goal with nuclear energy and would have allowed states to ''opt out'' of the federal requirement.</p>
        <p>''We cannot ignore the reality that some regions of the country cannot meet the R.P.S.,'' Mr. Domenici said. ''Since they cannot produce it, they'll have to pay a fine, a pretty whopping penalty.''</p>
        <p>Democrats defeated Mr. Domenici's proposal, 56 to 39, but Mr. Domenici vowed to block further voting through a filibuster and Democrats were one vote short of the 60 they needed to stop debate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reid, the majority leader, said he was confident of reaching an agreement. But while Mr. Bingaman and Mr. Domenici have collaborated on many issues in the past, they have sharply disagreed about imposing mandates on the use of renewable fuels.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
