<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. to Keep Europe as Site For Deterrent To Missiles</title>
    <meta content="15gates" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070619T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854556"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Poland</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Czech Republic</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Azerbaijan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shanker, Thom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Robert M (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Azerbaijan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Czech Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Czech Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Azerbaijan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE2DE153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. to Keep Europe as Site For Deterrent To Missiles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOM SHANKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shanker, Thom</byline>
      <dateline>BRUSSELS, June 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Defense Sec Robert M Gates, meeting with European defense ministers in Brussels, secures NATO's endorsement for American plan to deploy parts of missile defense system in Poland and Czech Republic, and says plan will not be altered despite unexpected proposal by Pres Vladimir V Putin of Russia to use radar base in Azerbaijan instead; Gates says radar in Azerbaijan offered by Putin could complement sites proposed for Central Europe, but not replace them; NATO support is described by its officials as significant step forward for American proposals (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates made clear Thursday that the United States would not alter plans to deploy parts of a missile defense system in Poland and the Czech Republic, despite an unexpected proposal by President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia to use a radar base in Azerbaijan instead.</p>
        <p>During a session of defense ministers here, Mr. Gates also effectively secured NATO's endorsement for an American plan to build the missile defense bases in Central Europe, overcoming the concerns of some alliance members that the effort could rupture relations with Russia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates made clear Thursday that the United States would not alter plans to deploy parts of a missile defense system in Poland and the Czech Republic, despite an unexpected proposal by President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia to use a radar base in Azerbaijan instead.</p>
        <p>During a session of defense ministers here, Mr. Gates also effectively secured NATO's endorsement for an American plan to build the missile defense bases in Central Europe, overcoming the concerns of some alliance members that the effort could rupture relations with Russia.</p>
        <p>The radar in Azerbaijan offered by Mr. Putin at the recent Group of 8 session with President Bush in Germany could complement the sites proposed for Central Europe, Mr. Gates said, but not replace them.</p>
        <p>''I was very explicit in the meeting that we saw the Azeri radar as an additional capability, that we intended to proceed with the radar, the X-band radar, in the Czech Republic,'' Mr. Gates said at an evening news conference after meeting with his Russian counterpart, Anatoly E. Serdyukov. American military officers have said that the X-band radar proposed for the Czech Republic is designed to spot specific objects in space and to assist interceptors in locking on and destroying an adversary's missile in the middle of its flight. The system in Azerbaijan is an early warning radar, with a wider range but also less specific tracking ability.</p>
        <p>NATO support, described by its officials as a significant step forward for the American proposals, came in the somewhat coded language typical of the Atlantic alliance.</p>
        <p>NATO did not issue a specific endorsement of placing the elements of the system in former Soviet states in Central Europe. But it announced an effort that in essence was an agreement that the system would be deployed: a study of how proposed shorter-range NATO missile defense systems would be incorporated in the long-range American antimissile program. That American system will include 10 missile interceptors in Poland and a network of radar defenses in the Czech Republic.</p>
        <p>''There were no criticisms by any of the NATO allies of our missile defense proposals or of our moving forward,'' Mr. Gates said. ''There obviously is interest in trying to encourage the Russians to participate with us, to make the system complementary to NATO shorter-range missile defenses, and for transparency.''</p>
        <p>These systems would be ''bolted on'' to the American system, which is designed to counter long-range missiles, in particular a potential threat from Iran, alliance officials said.</p>
        <p>''The NATO road map on missile defense is now clear,'' said Jaap de Hoop Scheffer, the NATO secretary general. ''It's practical, and it's agreed by all.''</p>
        <p>A senior American official, who described the closed-door debate under standard diplomatic rules of anonymity, was even more explicit than Mr. Gates in summarizing NATO's support. ''What you see here is allies agreeing to adapt NATO's work to the reality that there will be a long-range system, as well,'' the official said.</p>
        <p>NATO was already studying a theaterwide missile defense system, and the decision made Thursday alleviates the alliance of the financial and political costs of creating long-range missile defenses.</p>
        <p>The NATO study is to be completed by February. Its military experts will work on blueprints for short- and medium-range missile defense systems to shield allies not under the cover of the system proposed for Central Europe, including Bulgaria, Greece, Romania and Turkey.</p>
        <p>In an unexpected development sure to be scrutinized by the Kremlin, Mr. Gates indicated an interest in pushing cooperation on missile defenses even further into the former Soviet hemisphere of Eastern Europe by raising the prospect of future discussions with Ukraine.</p>
        <p>Ukraine is not a NATO member, but is part of an alliance dialogue, the NATO-Ukraine Commission. Mr. Gates said that on Thursday he ''indicated a willingness to share information, data with Ukraine'' on the missile defense efforts in Poland and the Czech Republic.</p>
        <p>Russian officials have complained that the proposed system is a Trojan horse designed to counter Moscow's strategic rocket forces, although Mr. Putin shifted the debate with a proposal last week to link the American system to a radar in the former Soviet republic of Azerbaijan.</p>
        <p>At the session of the NATO-Russia Council on Thursday, Mr. Serdyukov, the Russian defense minister, ''made no threats'' about the American plans, said senior American officials who had attended, speaking anonymously under diplomatic rules.</p>
        <p>While the United States, Poland and the Czech Republic are all alliance members, the negotiations on missile defense bases are being carried out in bilateral talks outside the NATO framework.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 19, 2007, Tuesday  Because of an editing error, an article on Friday about comments by Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates that the United States would not alter its plans to deploy a missile defense system in Poland and the Czech Republic, despite a proposal by Russia that the United States instead use a radar base in Azerbaijan, referred incorrectly to the former status of Poland and the Czech Republic. They were Soviet satellite states, not Soviet states.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 19, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article on Friday about comments by Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates that the United States would not alter its plans to deploy a missile defense system in Poland and the Czech Republic, despite a proposal by Russia that the United States instead use a radar base in Azerbaijan, referred incorrectly to the former status of Poland and the Czech Republic. They were Soviet satellite states, not Soviet states.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
