<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inside Art</title>
    <meta content="15voge" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/arts/design/15voge.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070629T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854514"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Inside Art"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0D6143FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="961" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inside Art</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Japanese Show Seeks a Berth in Basel</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
      <dateline>BASEL, Switzerland, June 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Japanese Show Seeks a Berth in Basel</p>
        <p>Takashi Murakami, the Japanese artist and curator, arrived here on Tuesday, not just to peruse the thousands of artworks on view at Art Basel, the annual contemporary art fair, but also to scout possible sites for his Gesai show, which Mr. Murakami has been running twice a year in the Big Sight Exhibition Center in Tokyo since 2002.</p>
        <p>''I had applied to Art Unlimited,'' Mr. Murakami said of a large space next to Art Basel's main hall where outsize artworks are on view. ''But they didn't have room.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Takashi Murakami attended Art Basel to scout possible sites for his Geisai show, which gives young Japanese artists the opportunity to show their work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Japanese Show Seeks a Berth in Basel</p>
        <p>Takashi Murakami, the Japanese artist and curator, arrived here on Tuesday, not just to peruse the thousands of artworks on view at Art Basel, the annual contemporary art fair, but also to scout possible sites for his Gesai show, which Mr. Murakami has been running twice a year in the Big Sight Exhibition Center in Tokyo since 2002.</p>
        <p>''I had applied to Art Unlimited,'' Mr. Murakami said of a large space next to Art Basel's main hall where outsize artworks are on view. ''But they didn't have room.''</p>
        <p>The purpose of Gesai, which lasts only one day and takes its name from the Japanese word for art festival, is to give young Japanese artists the opportunity to show their work and be noticed by an international panel of judges who are art professionals. Each artist pays Kaikai Kiki, Mr. Murakami's company, about $200 for a space to show at Gesai, and at each event the panel selects several artists to show their work. (Kaikai Kiki also takes a 10 percent agent's fee for any works that are sold.)</p>
        <p>''We are planning to do a smaller version of Gesai at Pulse in Miami,'' Mr. Murakami said, referring to a fair timed to coincide with Art Basel Miami Beach every December. ''But the Gesai in Miami won't just be for Japanese artists. Local artists will be able to show there too.''</p>
        <p>Art Basel's Director Leaves</p>
        <p>Sam Keller, director of Art Basel and Art Basel Miami Beach for seven years, is stepping down to become director of the Beyeler Foundation in Basel.</p>
        <p>Art Basel organizers announced on Tuesday that he was being replaced by three people. Marc Spiegler, a journalist based in Zurich, will be responsible for strategy and development. Cay Sophie Rabinowitz, the United States editor of the Swiss magazine Parkett and a teacher at Parsons the New School for Design in New York, will become artistic director of the fairs. Annette Schönholzer, manager of the fairs since 2005, will be in charge of organization and finances. They begin their jobs in September.</p>
        <p>The National's New Ivory</p>
        <p>The National Gallery of Art in Washington has bought a rare Baroque ivory sculpture attributed to the Belgian François Duquesnoy, one of the leading artists who worked in 17th-century Italy. ''Christ Bound,'' from the 1620s, depicts Jesus' body twisting to one side with his head gently pivoting onto his shoulder.</p>
        <p>The sculpture is quite large for an ivory -- more than 13 inches tall -- and extraordinarily detailed. ''Although the hands are close to the body, they are completely formed, which is very hard to do, and you can see the veins on his arms,'' said Nicholas Penny, the gallery's sculpture curator. ''The drapery that forms Christ's loincloth is paper thin.''</p>
        <p>The gallery bought the work from Daniel Katz, a London dealer, for an undisclosed sum. Mr. Katz had purchased it last year at the European Fine Art Fair in Maastricht, the Netherlands.</p>
        <p>''This sculpture was a complete surprise,'' Mr. Penny said. ''No one knew of its existence. Although Duquesnoy is known for his marble sculptures and bronze statuettes, he first made his reputation as a great virtuoso ivory carver. But we've all forgotten that because almost none of the works survived.''</p>
        <p>The work goes on view Friday in a West Building sculpture gallery.</p>
        <p>A Major Gift to the Clark</p>
        <p>The Sterling and Francine Clark Art Institute in Williamstown, Mass., has received a gift worth an estimated $80 million to $90 million from the Manton Foundation, created by Edwin A. G. Manton, a businessman and arts patron who died in 2005 at 96. It is one of the largest donations ever made to the Clark.</p>
        <p>It includes a group of British artworks, among them 3 paintings and 17 watercolors by J. M. W. Turner; 6 paintings, 17 oil studies, 8 watercolors and 19 drawings by John Constable; and 3 oil paintings and 15 drawings by Thomas Gainsborough. Among the highlights are ''Cloud Study,'' a romantic painting by Constable of an ominous sky from 1821-22, and ''Off Ramsgate,'' a Turner seascape circa 1840.</p>
        <p>In addition to art the foundation has contributed $50 million to endow the Clark's research and academic program.</p>
        <p>Mr. Manton, who was born in England but spent most of his life in the United States, and who made his fortune with the insurance company the American International Group (AIG), put together a world-class collection of paintings, drawings and watercolors by British masters. He gave most of them to the Tate in London, becoming its largest benefactor after its founder, Henry Tate.</p>
        <p>''The family knew the Clark,'' said Michael Conforti, its director. ''They had one daughter, Diana Morton, who was raised in America and who heads the foundation. She realized the gift would make a significant addition to what was a very thin area of our collection.''</p>
        <p>In recognition of the gift the Clark will name the building housing its research and academic program the Sir Edwin and Lady Manton Research Center. It will have a gallery dedicated to British art that will show both the Manton gift and other works from the Clark's collection.</p>
        <p>The gift goes on view Friday.</p>
        <p>Modern's Late Thursdays</p>
        <p>From July 5 through Aug. 30 the Museum of Modern Art will stay open until 9 on Thursdays, rather than closing at 5:30, to give visitors another opportunity to see the Richard Serra retrospective, said Glenn D. Lowry, its director. (The Modern stays open until 8 p.m. on Fridays.)</p>
        <p>Since the June 3 opening 7,000 to 8,000 people a day have visited the show, where 40 years of work by Mr. Serra are on view in the museum and around its sculpture garden.</p>
        <p>Inside Art</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 29, 2007, Friday  A report in the Inside Art column in Weekend on June 15, about the Japanese artist and curator Takashi Murakami, misspelled the name of the art show he runs. It is Geisai, not Gesai. It also misstated the policy of his company, Kaikai Kiki, on taking a 10 percent agent's fee for works sold at the show. It does not always take a fee, and in Miami in December it plans to waive it for young artists.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 29, 2007, Friday  A report in the Inside Art column in Weekend on June 15, about the Japanese artist and curator Takashi Murakami, misspelled the name of the art show he runs. It is Geisai, not Gesai. It also misstated the policy of his company, Kaikai Kiki, on taking a 10 percent agent's fee for works sold at the show. It does not always take a fee, and in Miami in December it plans to waive it for young artists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 29, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>A report in the Inside Art column in Weekend on June 15, about the Japanese artist and curator Takashi Murakami, misspelled the name of the art show he runs. It is Geisai, not Gesai. It also misstated the policy of his company, Kaikai Kiki, on taking a 10 percent agent's fee for works sold at the show. It does not always take a fee, and in Miami in December it plans to waive it for young artists.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
