<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TODAY IN BUSINESS</title>
    <meta content="15biztoday" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854628"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E5DC153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="884" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TODAY IN BUSINESS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HIGHER YIELDS TO HIT HOMEOWNERS The fallout from the increasing yields on the 10-year Treasury note -- a benchmark that influences many long-term interest rates, including home mortgages -- is likely to be widespread, and felt most immediately by homeowners and people looking to purchase a house. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>MORTGAGE PROBLEMS PERSIST Delinquencies and foreclosures among homeowners with weak credit moved higher in the first quarter, but an industry report suggested that the problems have not extended into the larger pool of borrowers with stronger credit. [C1.]</p>
        <p>A TOLL ON WALL STREET The meltdown in the subprime housing market may be taking a toll on Wall Street firms. Goldman Sachs reported that profits were flat from a year ago, due to a weak mortgage market. And Bear Stearns reported a 10 percent drop in net income, excluding a one-time charge, also largely a result of the tepid mortgage market. [C7.]</p>
        <p>HANDOUTS FOR THE SUCCESSFUL A golf resort on the windy coast of Oregon benefits from a variety of state and local subsidies, the kind of indirect favors that influence the flow of money from the public to private interests and often serve to reinforce benefits for those who are already successful. [C1.]</p>
        <p>TAXES ON PUBLIC HEDGE FUNDS Two senators introduced legislation that could significantly increase taxes on publicly traded private equity firms and hedge funds, a move that could dampen interest as the Blackstone Group, the giant private equity firm, continues marketing its initial public offering to potential investors. [C1.]</p>
        <p>BOOM FOR VENEZUELAN BANKS President Hugo Ch치vez repeatedly vows to do away with capitalism in Venezuela. But it turns out that Mr. Ch치vez's economic policies have been generating a boom for those most capitalist of institutions -- Venezuela's banks. [C1.]</p>
        <p>THOMAS THE TANK ENGINE RECALL The toy maker RC2 Corporation pulled a number of its Thomas &amp; Friends trains and accessory parts off the shelves after learning the red and yellow paint used to decorate more than 1.5 million of the toys contained lead. [C3.]</p>
        <p>PRICE INCREASES ARE MODERATED A double-digit jump in gasoline prices pushed up inflation at the wholesale level in May, but tame increases for most other goods suggested that price increases were largely contained and businesses would not react by raising prices. [C2.]</p>
        <p>DEMOCRATS PUT OFF ENERGY BILL Senate Democrats, facing their first significant battle over a wide-ranging bill aimed at reducing oil consumption, found themselves blocked by a Republican threat of a filibuster, and postponed all significant votes until next week. [A23.]</p>
        <p>LENDERS' TIES TO UNIVERSITIES Gifts and payoffs to universities and their officials by student lenders were far more pervasive than has been disclosed, and in some cases were demanded by university officials themselves in exchange for promoting lenders to students, according to a Senate report on the student loan industry. [A21.]</p>
        <p>CHINESE AUTOMAKER IN MEXICO A small Chinese automaker and its New Jersey partner are negotiating with Mexican officials to import Chinese-made pickup trucks and sport utility vehicles, the first step toward building an assembly plant in Tijuana that could export vehicles to the United States. [C9.]</p>
        <p>TALKS TO BUY INDIAN AIRLINE An Indian tycoon, Vijay Mallya, is in talks to acquire a stake in SpiceJet, a publicly traded Indian airline backed by a Dubai investment fund and a group of investment banks. Mr. Mallya, left, is chairman of the UB Group, an airline and liquor conglomerate, and he also owns Kingfisher Airlines. Acquisition of SpiceJet would likely speed up consolidation in the money-losing Indian airline business. [C9.]</p>
        <p>HOT STOCK MARKETS IN INDIA India's stock markets are on a roll, surpassing even the rosiest forecasts, in part because of a young, wealthy, expanding middle class banking on India's aggressive corporate growth. [C4.]</p>
        <p>ROBOT CAR'S LATEST MODEL The team of Stanford University engineers that won $2 million in a Pentagon-sponsored robot car contest in 2005 unveiled its next-generation vehicle, which will maneuver in traffic without a human driver. [C3.]</p>
        <p>S.E.C. CHARGES LAWYERS The Securities and Exchange Commission filed a civil suit against two lawyers, one a former enforcement lawyer for the commission, charging that they had played important roles in a penny stock fraud that cost investors at least $160,000 in 2005. [C5.]</p>
        <p>CONDENSED ADS Honda will be the sole sponsor of what Sony Pictures Television is calling the Minisode Network on MySpace, which will show vintage television series edited down to 4 to 6 minutes. To mirror the pared-down programming, Honda will run only eight seconds of commercials with each episode. Advertising: Stuart Elliott. [C5.]</p>
        <p>PENSION PROMISES COME DUE IN N.J. New Jersey's history of granting state workers generous retirement benefits, combined with years of skipping payments into the system, have undermined the state's ability to meet its pension obligations. [A1.]</p>
        <p>HIRING FROM A BIGGER POOL The Center for Venture Education in Palo Alto, Calif., is trying to improve the record of technology investors in integrating African-Americans, Hispanics and particularly minority women into their ranks. V.C. Nation. [C4.]</p>
        <p>DRUG MAKER'S PROBATION ENDS A two-year probation for Bristol-Myers Squibb ends today, freeing the company from federal supervision after a major accounting scandal and other misconduct. [C7.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HIGHER YIELDS TO HIT HOMEOWNERS The fallout from the increasing yields on the 10-year Treasury note -- a benchmark that influences many long-term interest rates, including home mortgages -- is likely to be widespread, and felt most immediately by homeowners and people looking to purchase a house. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>MORTGAGE PROBLEMS PERSIST Delinquencies and foreclosures among homeowners with weak credit moved higher in the first quarter, but an industry report suggested that the problems have not extended into the larger pool of borrowers with stronger credit. [C1.]</p>
        <p>A TOLL ON WALL STREET The meltdown in the subprime housing market may be taking a toll on Wall Street firms. Goldman Sachs reported that profits were flat from a year ago, due to a weak mortgage market. And Bear Stearns reported a 10 percent drop in net income, excluding a one-time charge, also largely a result of the tepid mortgage market. [C7.]</p>
        <p>HANDOUTS FOR THE SUCCESSFUL A golf resort on the windy coast of Oregon benefits from a variety of state and local subsidies, the kind of indirect favors that influence the flow of money from the public to private interests and often serve to reinforce benefits for those who are already successful. [C1.]</p>
        <p>TAXES ON PUBLIC HEDGE FUNDS Two senators introduced legislation that could significantly increase taxes on publicly traded private equity firms and hedge funds, a move that could dampen interest as the Blackstone Group, the giant private equity firm, continues marketing its initial public offering to potential investors. [C1.]</p>
        <p>BOOM FOR VENEZUELAN BANKS President Hugo Ch치vez repeatedly vows to do away with capitalism in Venezuela. But it turns out that Mr. Ch치vez's economic policies have been generating a boom for those most capitalist of institutions -- Venezuela's banks. [C1.]</p>
        <p>THOMAS THE TANK ENGINE RECALL The toy maker RC2 Corporation pulled a number of its Thomas &amp; Friends trains and accessory parts off the shelves after learning the red and yellow paint used to decorate more than 1.5 million of the toys contained lead. [C3.]</p>
        <p>PRICE INCREASES ARE MODERATED A double-digit jump in gasoline prices pushed up inflation at the wholesale level in May, but tame increases for most other goods suggested that price increases were largely contained and businesses would not react by raising prices. [C2.]</p>
        <p>DEMOCRATS PUT OFF ENERGY BILL Senate Democrats, facing their first significant battle over a wide-ranging bill aimed at reducing oil consumption, found themselves blocked by a Republican threat of a filibuster, and postponed all significant votes until next week. [A23.]</p>
        <p>LENDERS' TIES TO UNIVERSITIES Gifts and payoffs to universities and their officials by student lenders were far more pervasive than has been disclosed, and in some cases were demanded by university officials themselves in exchange for promoting lenders to students, according to a Senate report on the student loan industry. [A21.]</p>
        <p>CHINESE AUTOMAKER IN MEXICO A small Chinese automaker and its New Jersey partner are negotiating with Mexican officials to import Chinese-made pickup trucks and sport utility vehicles, the first step toward building an assembly plant in Tijuana that could export vehicles to the United States. [C9.]</p>
        <p>TALKS TO BUY INDIAN AIRLINE An Indian tycoon, Vijay Mallya, is in talks to acquire a stake in SpiceJet, a publicly traded Indian airline backed by a Dubai investment fund and a group of investment banks. Mr. Mallya, left, is chairman of the UB Group, an airline and liquor conglomerate, and he also owns Kingfisher Airlines. Acquisition of SpiceJet would likely speed up consolidation in the money-losing Indian airline business. [C9.]</p>
        <p>HOT STOCK MARKETS IN INDIA India's stock markets are on a roll, surpassing even the rosiest forecasts, in part because of a young, wealthy, expanding middle class banking on India's aggressive corporate growth. [C4.]</p>
        <p>ROBOT CAR'S LATEST MODEL The team of Stanford University engineers that won $2 million in a Pentagon-sponsored robot car contest in 2005 unveiled its next-generation vehicle, which will maneuver in traffic without a human driver. [C3.]</p>
        <p>S.E.C. CHARGES LAWYERS The Securities and Exchange Commission filed a civil suit against two lawyers, one a former enforcement lawyer for the commission, charging that they had played important roles in a penny stock fraud that cost investors at least $160,000 in 2005. [C5.]</p>
        <p>CONDENSED ADS Honda will be the sole sponsor of what Sony Pictures Television is calling the Minisode Network on MySpace, which will show vintage television series edited down to 4 to 6 minutes. To mirror the pared-down programming, Honda will run only eight seconds of commercials with each episode. Advertising: Stuart Elliott. [C5.]</p>
        <p>PENSION PROMISES COME DUE IN N.J. New Jersey's history of granting state workers generous retirement benefits, combined with years of skipping payments into the system, have undermined the state's ability to meet its pension obligations. [A1.]</p>
        <p>HIRING FROM A BIGGER POOL The Center for Venture Education in Palo Alto, Calif., is trying to improve the record of technology investors in integrating African-Americans, Hispanics and particularly minority women into their ranks. V.C. Nation. [C4.]</p>
        <p>DRUG MAKER'S PROBATION ENDS A two-year probation for Bristol-Myers Squibb ends today, freeing the company from federal supervision after a major accounting scandal and other misconduct. [C7.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
