<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Dismay of Some in Florida, Legislators Cut Property Taxes</title>
    <meta content="15florida" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/us/15florida.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854581"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Florida</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E6DD153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="728" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Dismay of Some in Florida, Legislators Cut Property Taxes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">To Dismay of Some in Florida, Legislators Cut Property Taxes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GOODNOUGH and CHRISTINE JORDAN SEXTON; Abby Goodnough reported from Miami, and Christine Jordan Sexton from Tallahassee.</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, June 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Addressing rising anger about the cost of owning a home in Florida -- and the recent troubles of the state's real estate industry -- the Legislature on Thursday approved a plan for a property tax cut it said would be the largest in state history.</p>
        <p>The plan was championed by Gov. Charlie Crist, a Republican who has vowed to make taxes ''drop like a rock,'' and Marco Rubio, the Republican speaker of the House of Representatives, who has made property-tax relief the main goal of his first year in power.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Addressing rising anger about the cost of owning a home in Florida, the Legislature approved a plan for a property tax cut it said would be the largest in state history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Addressing rising anger about the cost of owning a home in Florida -- and the recent troubles of the state's real estate industry -- the Legislature on Thursday approved a plan for a property tax cut it said would be the largest in state history.</p>
        <p>The plan was championed by Gov. Charlie Crist, a Republican who has vowed to make taxes ''drop like a rock,'' and Marco Rubio, the Republican speaker of the House of Representatives, who has made property-tax relief the main goal of his first year in power.</p>
        <p>The cost of the package was initially estimated to be $31.6 billion over five years, but a last-minute change pushed by Republicans in the Senate may have blunted the savings by as much as $7 billion.</p>
        <p>Even so, many local governments that levy property taxes said it would ravage their budgets, potentially forcing layoffs of police officers and firefighters and deep cuts to public schools. Some counties and cities have raised the possibility of a legal challenge.</p>
        <p>Florida does not have an income tax, and lawmakers did mention imposing one to make up for lost property tax revenue. Republican leaders had hoped to substantially decrease or even eliminate property taxes in exchange for a sharp sales tax increase. But that idea proved too controversial.</p>
        <p>The tax reduction is a two-part plan. The first piece would require cities and counties to roll back rates this fall and impose a cap on future spending that local government bodies could override only with a supermajority.</p>
        <p>The second, more contentious piece of the plan is a proposed constitutional amendment for a ''supersized'' homestead exemption. It would shield from taxes 75 percent of the first $200,000 in assessed property value, and 15 percent of the next $300,000.</p>
        <p>Should the amendment pass, homeowners could choose instead to keep their current exemption of $25,000 a year and a cap that prevents assessments from rising more than 3 percent a year for a primary residence. Those measures, in place since 1995, have kept property taxes low for longtime homeowners but not for part-time residents whose primary homes are elsewhere, or for business owners or recent home buyers. They are the ones who have clamored for change.</p>
        <p>The plan would save property taxpayers an average of $174 this year, and, if voters approve the constitutional amendment, $948 in 2008, lawmakers said.</p>
        <p>''I am so impressed,'' Mr. Crist said in a news conference after the vote, indicating he would approve the first piece. Because the second piece requires a public referendum, it does not need Mr. Crist's approval -- perhaps providing him political cover if it proves unpopular down the road.</p>
        <p>The vote on the property tax amendment is scheduled for Jan. 29, the same day as Florida's presidential primaries. If approved, it would take effect in November, the start of the next budget year for local governments.</p>
        <p>But counties, cities, teachers unions and Democrats who oppose the plan say they will strive to persuade voters to reject the proposed amendment. It would reduce public school spending by as much as a $7.2 billion.</p>
        <p>''I think we could really devastate education,'' said Representative Shelley Vana, a Democrat from Lantana and former teacher. ''I think we are going off the deep end.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Rubio and other architects of the plan said that somehow -- they would not provide details -- the Legislature would bridge the difference.</p>
        <p>Mr. Crist has repeatedly said property-tax cuts would not force layoffs, but local government and union officials insist otherwise.</p>
        <p>''They are huge cuts, the largest we've ever seen,'' said Andy Ford, president of the Florida Education Association, predicting that the cuts would block school districts from hiring new employees, from teachers to bus drivers to cafeteria workers. ''It will affect absolutely everybody.''</p>
        <p>The real estate and building industries, which are suffering from the housing slump, lobbied relentlessly for the cuts. The revenue that Florida collects from real estate transactions dipped 25 percent over the last year, causing overall tax revenue to fall for the first time since the 1970s. This year the Legislature approved a series of measures to reduce home insurance rates, which have soared as major hurricanes have struck in recent years. But many homeowners are finding the savings to be much smaller than they had hoped.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
