<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oakmont Is Rough, and Mickelson Feels Pain</title>
    <meta content="15golf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/sports/golf/15golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854693"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Pennsylvania</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Winged Foot Golf Club</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Olazabal, Jose Maria</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Watson, Bubba</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ogilvy, Geoff</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mickelson, Phil</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Furyk, Jim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E4DB153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oakmont Is Rough, and Mickelson Feels Pain</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Oakmont Is Rough, and Mickelson Feels Pain</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa., June 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a century-old golf course carved among rusted bridges and a roaring turnpike, Phil Mickelson stood atop one of the highest points at Oakmont Country Club and prepared for his first swing in the 107th United States Open. He tugged at the black sleeve covering his balky left wrist, and all eyes seemed trained on him. He balanced his golf ball on a white, wooden tee, and a gallery waited for impact.</p>
        <p>At last, he sent a shot with a hybrid club into the distance, embarked on a five-hour walk through ankle-deep rough and vanilla-colored bunkers, and told himself that he still had reason to believe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The course at Oakmont, the site of the 107th U.S. Open, got the better of the hampered Phil Mickelson who was six shots off the leader, Nick Dougherty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a century-old golf course carved among rusted bridges and a roaring turnpike, Phil Mickelson stood atop one of the highest points at Oakmont Country Club and prepared for his first swing in the 107th United States Open. He tugged at the black sleeve covering his balky left wrist, and all eyes seemed trained on him. He balanced his golf ball on a white, wooden tee, and a gallery waited for impact.</p>
        <p>At last, he sent a shot with a hybrid club into the distance, embarked on a five-hour walk through ankle-deep rough and vanilla-colored bunkers, and told himself that he still had reason to believe.</p>
        <p>''I believe I'll be better as the week goes on,'' Mickelson said Thursday after opening the championship with a four-over-par 74, which placed him six shots behind the leader, Nick Dougherty. ''I need one good round to get me into the weekend.''</p>
        <p>On a breezy and difficult day at Oakmont, Dougherty (68) and Ángel Cabrera (69) were the only golfers to break par on the 7,230-yard layout. José María Olazábal and Bubba Watson trailed Dougherty by two shots. Tiger Woods survived several trips to Oakmont's 210 bunkers to headline a group of golfers three shots back.</p>
        <p>Mickelson, a four-time runner-up in the championship, quickly vaulted himself into the role of protagonist simply by arriving at the 10th tee.</p>
        <p>While he had announced every intention to play, his preparation for Oakmont had been scattershot after he injured his wrist while practicing at Oakmont last month. He withdrew from the Memorial Tournament two weeks ago, pulled out of the St. Jude Championship last week, and received a cortisone shot after visiting two doctors. He spent his practice rounds this week taking light swings from the fairway.</p>
        <p>Mickelson received lusty applause when he arrived for his opening tee shot and was trailed by a phalanx of cameras throughout the round.</p>
        <p>''When he went to fix his wrist on 10, I heard about 50 clicks of cameras,'' said Jim Furyk, Mickelson's playing partner, who shot a 71. ''It was a little bit of a circus out there.''</p>
        <p>After making a par on his opening hole, Mickelson drove into the deep rough to the left of the 11th fairway. He took a large cut at his golf ball, but he let go of the club with his left hand after impact and let it dangle by his hip pocket. After a bad chip shot on the green, he made a bogey.</p>
        <p>Instead of feeling as if his wrist was improving during the round, Mickelson said that he felt the pain growing. He constantly fidgeted with his wrist between shots, loosening the wrap, tightening it at times, or just flexing his wrist in a search for comfort.</p>
        <p>After hitting putts with the wrap on to start the round, he putted without it during his back nine, revealing a small white bandage beneath it.</p>
        <p>He hit some loose shots and found only 5 of 14 fairways, but said he discovered that he could play through the aches.</p>
        <p>''It's aggravating,'' said Mickelson, who used a hybrid club more often than usual to protect his wrist. ''I wouldn't say it's painful like Memorial, not at all, but it's annoying. That's probably a better word.''</p>
        <p>Even the healthy and whole at Oakmont found trouble. Woods began the championship by hitting his driver into a fairway bunker to the left and opened the chase for his 13th major victory with a bogey. He spent the rest of his round weaving in and out of problems and holding his round together with his putter.</p>
        <p>Woods seemed destined to drop shots at No. 13 and No. 16, but he drilled two curling par putts from 8 feet away. After knocking home a 5-foot birdie putt on No. 17, Woods nestled a short pitch from the greenside rough to 3 feet and rolled it in for par to finish his round.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to make birdies out there and it's easy to makes bogeys and doubles,'' said Woods, who missed the cut at last year's championship at Winged Foot Golf Club. ''It was conservative today -- that's how you normally play U.S. Opens. You don't play aggressively.''</p>
        <p>The 25-year-old Dougherty, who is from Liverpool, England, had the gumption to call Oakmont easy on Thursday. Suddenly aware, though, that the United States Golf Association could toughen the course at any time, he quickly changed his mind and called the course ''barbaric.''</p>
        <p>Despite playing in only his third United States Open, no one played Oakmont better than Dougherty on Thursday.</p>
        <p>''It's the first major I've come to in good form,'' he said. ''Usually, I'm struggling or my confidence is struggling a bit, so I'm very pleased.''</p>
        <p>Mickelson, despite surviving 18 holes, did not call his round a victory. He bemoaned a few mistakes, but he was still a factor in the championship.</p>
        <p>After piecemeal practices and ice and massage treatments, he had completed 18 holes on one of the toughest courses in the world.</p>
        <p>''We've got a long ways to go,'' Mickelson said. ''I fought the last eight holes to keep me in it, and if I do well tomorrow, that's all I care about.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
