<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Trans-Atlantic Deal For Plays From London</title>
    <meta content="15boye" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/theater/15boye.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070623T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">London (England)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Menier Chocolate Factory</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boyett Ostar Productions</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E3DF153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="522" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Trans-Atlantic Deal For Plays From London</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Trans-Atlantic Deal for Plays From London</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAMPBELL ROBERTSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Another piece of the London theater market has just been claimed by the same producer whose partnership already has a deal with the National Theater in Britain that gives it the first option to transfer shows to Broadway.</p>
        <p>The Menier Chocolate Factory, a plucky 3 1/2-year-old theater company that has become the critic's darling of the Off West End scene in London, has signed a three-year deal with the producer, Bob Boyett, giving him first rights to transfer shows to Broadway. But Mr. Boyett and David Babani, artistic director of the Menier Chocolate Factory, said the deal was only the official part of a larger creative partnership.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Menier Chocolate Factory has signed a three-year deal with the producer Bob Boyett, giving him first rights to transfer shows to Broadway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Another piece of the London theater market has just been claimed by the same producer whose partnership already has a deal with the National Theater in Britain that gives it the first option to transfer shows to Broadway.</p>
        <p>The Menier Chocolate Factory, a plucky 3 1/2-year-old theater company that has become the critic's darling of the Off West End scene in London, has signed a three-year deal with the producer, Bob Boyett, giving him first rights to transfer shows to Broadway. But Mr. Boyett and David Babani, artistic director of the Menier Chocolate Factory, said the deal was only the official part of a larger creative partnership.</p>
        <p>''We really discuss everything on a project-by-project basis,'' Mr. Boyett said yesterday in a phone interview.</p>
        <p>Unlike the National, the Menier Chocolate Factory is not subsidized by public money, giving Mr. Boyett the freedom to become involved in developing shows and suggesting projects. He has already been working with the factory on ''Take Flight,'' a new musical with lyrics by David Shire, score by Richard Maltby Jr. and book by John Weidman, that is having its premiere there in July.</p>
        <p>The partnership could be more lucrative than some of Mr. Boyett's other enhancement deals, in which he contributes money to productions at nonprofit theaters. The Chocolate Factory, after all, is a commercial theater and intends to make money. ''I'm working very hard to create opportunities where the initial money sunk in can be made back,'' Mr. Babani said.</p>
        <p>The Menier Chocolate Factory has been celebrated for its digs as much as for the productions that play there. Housed in a 19th-century former, uh, chocolate factory in South London, the space includes an art gallery, rehearsal space, bar and restaurant in addition to the theater, which seats up to 180.</p>
        <p>The theater, interestingly, has gained most attention for its productions of American shows, like a revival of ''Little Shop of Horrors'' that transferred to the West End (with Mr. Boyett's help).</p>
        <p>The big breakout was a critically acclaimed revival of ''Sunday in the Park With George,'' a sold-out hit that transferred to the West End and won five Olivier Awards. The production is being brought to Broadway this winter by Mr. Boyett's producing partnership, Boyett Ostar Productions.</p>
        <p>While the ''Sunday'' transfer and the National deal, which has been renewed through summer 2008, involved Ostar Productions, run by Bill Haber, this one is Mr. Boyett's alone.</p>
        <p>That's the other bit of news here: Mr. Boyett said that he and Mr. Haber would be working primarily apart after three years of Boyett Ostar, which was responsible for the London-to-New York transfers of ''The Pillowman,'' ''The History Boys'' ''Journey's End'' and ''Coram Boy.''</p>
        <p>That partnership will still exist for projects already in the works and productions that may transfer from the National, he said.</p>
        <p>''I think our tastes are not always totally in sync,'' Mr. Boyett said. ''It just seems like the right thing to do. There's no acrimony involved.''</p>
        <p>In an e-mail message, Mr. Haber wrote that he and Mr. Boyett ''will continue to produce Broadway theater projects separately and together as we have always done.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 23, 2007, Saturday  An article in Weekend on June 15 about a deal between the Menier Chocolate Factory theater company in London and the producer Bob Boyett that gives Mr. Boyett first rights to transfer the company's shows to Broadway referred incompletely to the transfer of the company's revival of ''Sunday in the Park With George'' next winter. The Broadway revival will be a Roundabout Theater Company production. Boyett Ostar Productions, Mr. Boyett's producing partnership, will be an associate producer; it is not bringing over the revival by itself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 23, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article in Weekend on June 15 about a deal between the Menier Chocolate Factory theater company in London and the producer Bob Boyett that gives Mr. Boyett first rights to transfer the company's shows to Broadway referred incompletely to the transfer of the company's revival of ''Sunday in the Park With George'' next winter. The Broadway revival will be a Roundabout Theater Company production. Boyett Ostar Productions, Mr. Boyett's producing partnership, will be an associate producer; it is not bringing over the revival by itself.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
