<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Experts Advise on Combating Radicalization</title>
    <meta content="15radical" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/washington/15radical.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854573"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <org class="online_producer">House of Representatives</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Al Qaeda</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EEDE153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="560" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Experts Advise on Combating Radicalization</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Experts Advise on Combating Radicalization</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL MacFARQUHAR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While the United States has expended enormous effort in fighting terrorists in Iraq and Afghanistan, it has neglected the fight for the hearts and minds of young radicals in Internet chat rooms and other places where they cluster, experts on radicalization told a House panel yesterday.</p>
        <p>''Unless we can impede radicalization and recruitment, then we are condemned to a strategy of stepping on cockroaches one at a time,'' Brian M. Jenkins, a terrorism expert from the Rand Corporation, told the House Subcommittee on Intelligence, Information Sharing and Terrorism Risk Assessment</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Experts on radicalization told a House panel that the United States has neglected the fight for the hearts and minds of young radicals in Internet chat rooms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While the United States has expended enormous effort in fighting terrorists in Iraq and Afghanistan, it has neglected the fight for the hearts and minds of young radicals in Internet chat rooms and other places where they cluster, experts on radicalization told a House panel yesterday.</p>
        <p>''Unless we can impede radicalization and recruitment, then we are condemned to a strategy of stepping on cockroaches one at a time,'' Brian M. Jenkins, a terrorism expert from the Rand Corporation, told the House Subcommittee on Intelligence, Information Sharing and Terrorism Risk Assessment</p>
        <p>The subcommittee and the Senate Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee have held recent hearings on the possible threat from ''homegrown'' radicals. The general conclusion has been that although such a threat exists, it is small, especially when compared with Europe, because assimilation works so much better here.</p>
        <p>Individual sessions have covered the possibility of terror cells forming in prisons, considered a ripe environment with little concrete activity, and countering the vision of extremists who use Islam to convince the young that suicide bombings are the righteous path to a better world.</p>
        <p>''We have to stop attacking only the structure and start attacking their strategy,'' the director of the Homeland Security Policy Institute at George Washington University, Frank J. Cilluffo, said.</p>
        <p>Terrorist organizations, for example, use the Web to glorify the people who carry out attacks as serving God. But, Mr. Cilluffo noted, there is no effort to use video from gruesome attacks like the slaughter of Russian schoolchildren or the bombing of a wedding at a Jordanian hotel to underscore that terrorists are cold-blooded murderers</p>
        <p>The United States has had scattered arrests of bumblers who may have intended to carry out terrorist attacks, but none have had the capability to undertake the deadly violence seen on 9/11 or in London and Madrid, witnesses said. The treason indictment last year of Adam Yahiye Gadahn, a Californian who is a Qaeda spokesman, is a rarity. The United States has had about 30 treason cases.</p>
        <p>But the Internet age can make moving from intent to capability rapid. So the goal is to block the path and undermine the desire.</p>
        <p>''There is nothing wrong with people being recruited to become Muslims,'' Representative Jane Harman, the California Democrat who is chairwoman of the subcommittees, said in an interview yesterday. ''What is wrong is when people who are becoming Muslims are manipulated by radical fanatics into a death cult.</p>
        <p>''That small passage that very few of these people take is where we have to interfere. We have to understand how it happens and when it happens.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Harman and a Republican colleague, Representative Dave Reichert of Washington, are drafting a measure that would direct Congress to form a commission to develop a strategy for preventing such radicalization. She said she hoped that a similar bill would emerge from the Senate.</p>
        <p>Among the major recommendations of the experts at the hearing yesterday were greater involvement of Muslim-Americans in the antiradicalization effort; more aid for community policing, which is deemed most effective at nipping radicalization in the bud; and a smarter focus on countering what Al Qaeda and other groups do to win recruits.</p>
        <p>''We need to isolate the extremists as opposed to isolating the mainstream community'' of American Muslims, Salam al-Marayati, executive director of the Muslim Public Affairs Council, said in an interview.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
