<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Mt. Shasta, Winter's Wrath Knows No Calendar</title>
    <meta content="15Shasta" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/travel/escapes/15Shasta.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854516"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mountain Climbing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cascade Mountains</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mount Shasta (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Regenold, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mountain Climbing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EFD6143FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1680" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Mt. Shasta, Winter's Wrath Knows No Calendar</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On Mt. Shasta, Winter’s Wrath Knows No Calendar</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN REGENOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Regenold, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on attempt to climb Mount Shasta in California's Cascade Mountains, which ended when high winds prevented further advancement; photos; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ABOVE the timberline on Mount Shasta, somewhere near 10,500 feet, my tent decided to take flight. ''Grab that corner, grab an ice ax!'' I yelled over wind roaring down in gusts like waves. ''Don't let go!''</p>
        <p>My climbing partner, the photographer T. C. Worley, held a flapping frame of nylon, a box kite crumpled, whipping in the wind. On the slope above, silhouetted on a dark sky, a wall of white descended toward our perch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Things don’t always go as planned, especially in mountaineering, where weather can play the ultimate trump card on any trip.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ABOVE the timberline on Mount Shasta, somewhere near 10,500 feet, my tent decided to take flight. ''Grab that corner, grab an ice ax!'' I yelled over wind roaring down in gusts like waves. ''Don't let go!''</p>
        <p>My climbing partner, the photographer T. C. Worley, held a flapping frame of nylon, a box kite crumpled, whipping in the wind. On the slope above, silhouetted on a dark sky, a wall of white descended toward our perch.</p>
        <p>''Don't let go,'' I repeated.</p>
        <p>Mount Shasta, a 14,162-foot stratovolcano in Northern California, is the second-highest peak in the Cascade Range, measuring a couple hundred feet short of Mount Rainier in Washington. But Shasta is more voluminous, a stone and snow mass of more than 80 cubic miles with slopes that plunge over 10,000 vertical feet to rivers and piney forests below.</p>
        <p>For experienced mountaineers, most routes up Shasta are only moderately difficult, with bowls, faces and snowfields flanking the peak, never tipping steeper than an expert ski run. Its high altitude poses dangers of exposure, oxygen deprivation and fatigue. But climbs on Shasta are straightforward, and its long snaking glaciers are easy to avoid.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the mountain's first recorded climb was in 1854, and today thousands of people attempt the peak each year. In 2006, about 6,400 climbers bought summit pass permits to head up with guides or on their own, according to records kept by the United States Forest Service. About half made it to the top.</p>
        <p>Guide companies like Sierra Wilderness Seminars and Shasta Mountain Guides, both based in the town of Mount Shasta below the mountain's slope, lead hundreds of trips a year, many in June and July, the peak's prime climbing season.</p>
        <p>''Shasta can be the perfect mountain for first-time mountaineers,'' said Chris Carr, a co-director of Shasta Mountain Guides. ''But it's a high peak that shouldn't be underestimated, and there are rescues every year up there.''</p>
        <p>On our trip to Shasta in early May, Mr. Worley and I started the climb on a Friday afternoon from the Bunny Flat trailhead at about 6,900 feet on the south side of the mountain. The summit loomed more than a vertical mile above, though clouds obscured its upper reaches in a murky stew.</p>
        <p>Our plan was to snowshoe up the initial slopes to 9,000 feet by early evening, continuing uphill on snowfields to camp at 10,400 feet near Helen Lake, a frozen tarn under the snow. We'd don headlamps for a 4 o'clock start the next morning, trading snowshoes for crampons on our boots to kick the remaining 3,700 feet to the top, summiting just after sunrise.</p>
        <p>But things don't always go as planned, especially in mountaineering, where weather can play the ultimate trump card on any trip.</p>
        <p>Sun burned the slope for the first 2,000 feet of our climb. We plodded uphill on a glinting base of springtime snow, bare hands gripping trekking poles in weather warm enough for shorts.</p>
        <p>''Nice day,'' a skier commented, striding uphill adjacent to our trail in the trees.</p>
        <p>It was around 3 p.m. on Friday, and a group of local skiers was heading uphill for an after-work schuss. Mr. Worley and I were among a dozen or so climbers from various parties snowshoeing toward Avalanche Gulch, a glacial valley that closes in past 9,000 feet.</p>
        <p>''Let's stop at this shade and de-layer some clothing,'' Mr. Worley said near the tree line, where stunted pines poke out from the snow. The route above, a rolling slope between two spiked ridgelines, blazed in the alpine sun, though the mountaintop was obscured still in a thick cap of cloud.</p>
        <p>The easiest route to the top of Mount Shasta is via Avalanche Gulch, which is essentially a steep hike, though crampons and ice axes are employed for the final few thousand feet. We planned to climb Avalanche Gulch and camp at 10,400 feet, detouring the next morning to a route called Casaval Ridge, which follows a direct rocky ridgeline to the final slope below the summit.</p>
        <p>At 9,500 feet, the weather began to change. Gray-green clouds, sailing level with us past the mountain a few miles away at an adjacent altitude, dropped virga in dark little tendrils. A plume of white shot upward from the middle of Casaval Ridge, signaling high winds above.</p>
        <p>''We should climb quick to get above this storm,'' I yelled back to Mr. Worley as a draft stirred the snow at his feet.</p>
        <p>I put my gloves back on.</p>
        <p>We climbed for another hour, following the tracks of a climbing party ahead of us, which were quickly disappearing under blowing snow. Gusts were intermittent, but immense, one time nearly knocking us over on the top of a rise.</p>
        <p>At Helen Lake things were worse, with waves of crystal snow whipping up and shooting into the sky.</p>
        <p>''Welcome,'' a climber yelled out from near his tent, hunkering down. ''You guys doing O.K.?''</p>
        <p>John Broadbooks and Ed Simmons had come from Colorado for a weekend attempt on the peak. Experienced climbers, they'd built a snow wall around their camp and were cooking dinner in the squall. ''It's Mountain House Beef Stew,'' Mr. Broadbooks yelled over a gust, referring to the brand of soup in his steaming pot. ''I have a weakness for this stuff.''</p>
        <p>MR. WORLEY and I dropped our packs and stepped out of our snowshoes. The gulch above -- an amphitheater of steep white walls and dark volcanic stone -- swirled with snow and clouds thick and descending.</p>
        <p>''We should get this tent up quick,'' Mr. Worley said, his hood cinched in on a red face.</p>
        <p>For the next hour we fought to set up camp, stamping a platform in the snow, shoveling walls and building anchors to tie the tent down.</p>
        <p>Then, the tent decided to try and fly away. In wind that was now unrelenting, we wrestled the nylon beast, an invisible hand tugging and bullwhipping our shelter in the wind.</p>
        <p>Upslope, a wall of white -- a huge tornado of ice -- spun like an exclamation point in the tempest.</p>
        <p>''Wow, it's getting real,'' Mr. Broadbooks yelled through the roar.</p>
        <p>The next 10 hours -- most of which were spent inside a tent -- were the most harrowing of the weekend. As we later learned, the jet stream had dipped to scour Mount Shasta during the night of our stay, pushing wind speeds to more than 100 miles an hour on the summit.</p>
        <p>At Helen Lake, I huddled sleepless for hours in the fetal position, wrapped in a sleeping bag, wearing every stitch of clothing I'd brought up. Our tent was a madhouse of warping walls, bending poles and fine flying crystals of snow seeping in through seams.</p>
        <p>An avalanche slid during the night, scarring a streak of debris on the slope a quarter-mile from camp. The wind was as loud as thunder.</p>
        <p>At sunrise, a pole snapped on Mr. Simmons's tent, partially collapsing the shelter. ''We're heading down,'' I heard him yell.</p>
        <p>Mr. Worley and I suited up at 7 a.m. and crawled out into the torrent. A half-dozen climbers stood gazing uphill, leaning into gusts.</p>
        <p>Despite a blue sky, no one was climbing higher. Guided parties weren't even approaching Helen Lake. The exposed upper slopes were a war zone of white, giant plumes and explosions of snow. ''This is insane,'' a climber yelled during a lull.</p>
        <p>The winds kept up like that for four days straight, driving an unrelenting, impassable north wind into Shasta's bulk. Mr. Worley and I retreated from Helen Lake at 9 a.m. along with all the other climbing parties.</p>
        <p>We never got above 11,000 feet the entire weekend, a disappointment, but an accepted reality given the tempest. Indeed, no one made Shasta's summit for the better part of a week, according to local guides.</p>
        <p>Later in the week I phoned John Broadbooks to go over the climb, to compare notes and commiserate on the failed attempt. But he wasn't having it, staying upbeat on the line, laughing about the drifting tornadoes of snow and sandblasting ice crystals that stung like birdshot on exposed skin.</p>
        <p>''I have no regrets -- nothing you can do with that kind of wind,'' he said. ''Sometimes the mountain gods just pause and say, 'Not today.' ''</p>
        <p>CASCADE CHALLENGE</p>
        <p>Here's a Mountain for the Must-Climb List</p>
        <p>AT 14,162 feet, Mount Shasta towers miles above the surrounding green forests and babbling brooks. For climbers, it's an obvious target, and dozens of routes to the top have been established, ranging from beginner climbs that involve little more than steep hiking with an ice ax to advanced lines that require ropes, route choices and glacier-climbing skills.</p>
        <p>The high altitude -- and the resulting lower quantity of oxygen in the air -- poses risks of fatigue, disorientation and other altitude-induced maladies. Usually, snow flanks the upper reaches year-round, and the mountain has several glaciers. Ice axes and crampons are always used on summit attempts. In the summer, the snow line creeps up the mountain, and by July or August much of the climb involves hiking on rocky trails to 10,000 feet or higher. Though Shasta is a volcano, it is dormant. The last major eruption was more than 200 years ago.</p>
        <p>Guide companies like Sierra Wilderness Seminars (888-797-6867, www.swsmtns.com) and Shasta Mountain Guides (530-926-3117, www.shastaguides.com), both based in Mount Shasta, Calif., organize dozens of trips a year. May, June, July and August are the most popular months. Beginners in good physical condition are welcome for these two- or three-day attempts at the summit, which include instruction, camping on the mountain and a chance to reach the peak for prices starting at $425.</p>
        <p>Do-it-yourself mountaineers take guidebooks like ''The Mt. Shasta Book'' by Andy Selters and Michael Zanger (Wilderness Press, $18). A detailed topographical map of the mountain with popular climbing routes is available from the Fifth Season outdoors store (530-926-3606, www.thefifthseason.com), also in Mount Shasta.</p>
        <p>Climbers use the National Weather Service's Web site to check conditions at the Mount Shasta Recreational Area (www.noaa.gov). The administrative offices of the Shasta-Trinity National Forest are in Redding, Calif. (530-226-2500, www.fs.fed.us/r5/shastatrinity or www.shastaavalanche.org).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
