<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Often Accused, Never Charged, Newark's Ex-Mayor Faces U.S.</title>
    <meta content="15sharpe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/nyregion/15sharpe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854648"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICAL MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">James, Sharpe</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mattison, Jackie R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E1DC153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1079" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Often Accused, Never Charged, Newark's Ex-Mayor Faces U.S.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Often Accused, Never Charged, Newark’s Ex-Mayor Faces U.S.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When federal prosecutors found in 1995 that Sharpe James, then the mayor of Newark, could not account for hundreds of thousands of dollars in donations from political patrons, his only penalty was a $44,000 fine from the state election commission.</p>
        <p>Two years later, Mr. James's chief of staff was imprisoned for accepting bribes from city contractors. The mayor praised him as ''a loyal public servant'' and escaped from that investigation unscathed, soon winning a second public office as state senator.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal prosecutors have told Sharpe James that he is likely to face indictment on charges that abused his position as mayor for personal gain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When federal prosecutors found in 1995 that Sharpe James, then the mayor of Newark, could not account for hundreds of thousands of dollars in donations from political patrons, his only penalty was a $44,000 fine from the state election commission.</p>
        <p>Two years later, Mr. James's chief of staff was imprisoned for accepting bribes from city contractors. The mayor praised him as ''a loyal public servant'' and escaped from that investigation unscathed, soon winning a second public office as state senator.</p>
        <p>And throughout his five terms at the helm of New Jersey's largest city, Mr. James lived a lifestyle so lavish -- complete with a beach house, 54-foot yacht and Rolls-Royce -- that he was frequently the focus of accusations and insinuations, but he never faced a criminal charge.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. James, who left office last summer after 20 years at Newark City Hall, has been told by federal prosecutors that he is likely to face indictment on charges that he misused his city credit card to pay for personal expenses and allowed his friends and campaign contributors to buy tens of millions of dollars in municipal property at deeply discounted prices.</p>
        <p>Despite Mr. James's record of avoiding legal sanctions, this case poses a formidable threat. Thousands of pages of financial documents, credit card receipts and other city records have been subpoenaed by the United States attorney. Federal agents have also been investigating aides and associates of the former mayor who profited from the land deals, some of whom might cooperate now that Mr. James is out of office.</p>
        <p>''He's flaunted so much wealth for so long, and skirted so close to the line that it's no surprise he's under investigation,'' said Joseph R. Marbach, a political science professor at Seton Hall University. ''But he's been so savvy in how he's handled himself, and portrayed himself politically, that a lot of people wonder if the U.S. attorney will be able to meet the high standard necessary for criminal charges.''</p>
        <p>The United States attorney for New Jersey, Christopher J. Christie Jr., has declined to speak about the investigation, as have Mr. James and his lawyer, Raymond M. Brown. But Mr. James's son John said in an interview this week that he was confident that his father had done nothing improper.</p>
        <p>''In the end, I think people will see that everything he did, he did to help the city,'' John James said. ''When he left office, the real estate market was finally starting to percolate. There were $500,000 houses going up on vacant lots that had been sitting there growing weeds since the riots 40 years ago. Without him, none of this redevelopment would have happened. And when this is all over, history will show he was an excellent mayor who helped rebuild this city.''</p>
        <p>A Newark native who worked as a track coach and physical education teacher before entering politics, Mr. James was elected mayor in 1986 and quickly established a reputation as an energetic cheerleader for a struggling city. Using salesmanship and political savvy, Mr. James helped assemble the public financing and private support that led to construction of the New Jersey Performing Arts Center, the downtown stadium and the hockey arena, three shiny landmarks in a downtown that was once little more than a case study in blight.</p>
        <p>He also built a political machine that was on display each February at his lavish birthday parties. In exchange for Champagne and cake, city employees, vendors and political supporters were expected to make donations to the Sharpe James Civic Association, which massed some $3 million over eight years.</p>
        <p>That money was the focus of the federal investigation that ended in 1995. When he was cleared, Mr. James, who is African-American, charged that the inquiry was racially motivated and attributed his personal wealth to wise investments.</p>
        <p>In the years that followed, critics say, Mr. James seemed emboldened as he enjoyed the perks of his office, expanded his real estate portfolio and orchestrated land deals that were a boon to his friends and allies.</p>
        <p>During his final year in office, for instance, Mr. James used a city credit card to charge $80,000 in expenses on everything from dinners at Hooter's restaurants to trips to Florida, Arizona, Puerto Rico, the Dominican Republic and Brazil. Last year, Mr. James and his lawyer told reporters those charges were legitimate business expenses incurred while trying to attract more development.</p>
        <p>But at least three city police officers who provided security for Mr. James have been questioned by federal investigators about whether those trips were for business or pleasure, according to Anthony Fusco, a lawyer who represented them.</p>
        <p>Mr. James's administration also sold hundreds of parcels of vacant city land to dozens of friends and supporters during his last three years in office for as little as $1 a square foot, when similar property had been appraised at $20 per square foot or more, according to city records and court documents.</p>
        <p>Among the buyers was Jackie R. Mattison, the former chief of staff who served a prison term for accepting bribes. Mr. Mattison's company bought more than 30 city lots for millions of dollars below their appraised value.</p>
        <p>Tamika Rile, a woman who accompanied Mr. James on several trips, also bought cut-rate city properties, paying a total of $46,000 and selling them within two years for more than $700,000, according to city and county land records. Nothing in the publicly available documents indicates that Mr. James was directly involved in, or received a personal benefit from, the discounted land sales, which were approved by the City Council.</p>
        <p>But he did collect campaign contributions from the developers who profited from the deals shortly before or afterward. When the city's new mayor-elect, Cory A. Booker, sued in May 2006 to halt the sales, a state judge blocked 70 deals that were in progress, noting that the timing of those donations was troubling.</p>
        <p>Mr. James and his family have also received mortgages at below-market interest rates from a bank whose officers were allowed to buy millions of dollars of cut-rate city property.</p>
        <p>In recent years, Mr. Christie and other prosecutors have pressed political corruption charges by using a statute known as mail fraud/honest services, which is violated whenever elected officials use their positions to benefit a concealed financial interest rather than the public.</p>
        <p>''Sharpe James has been cheating the taxpayers for years,'' said Candace Straight, a Republican fund-raiser. ''If this case leads to charges and a sentence, it'll be long overdue.''</p>
        <p>POLITICAL MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
