<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playing the Palace</title>
    <meta content="15book" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/books/15book.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854528"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DF153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playing the Palace</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On Royalty</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Royalty  A Very Polite Inquiry Into Some Strangely Related Families  By Jeremy Paxman  370 pages. PublicAffairs. $26.95.</p>
        <p>Reflecting on his own loss of power, the English-educated King Farouk of Egypt once predicted that by the end of the 20th century there would be only five monarchies left in the world: the kings of hearts, diamonds, clubs and spades, and the king of England.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The British journalist Jeremy Paxman leads the reader on an entertaining tour through Europe’s royalty, without being terribly new or revealing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Royalty  A Very Polite Inquiry Into Some Strangely Related Families  By Jeremy Paxman  370 pages. PublicAffairs. $26.95.</p>
        <p>Reflecting on his own loss of power, the English-educated King Farouk of Egypt once predicted that by the end of the 20th century there would be only five monarchies left in the world: the kings of hearts, diamonds, clubs and spades, and the king of England.</p>
        <p>And yet, as the British journalist Jeremy Paxman notes in his witty new book, monarchies endure in Europe in the new millennium: Denmark, Norway and Sweden, he writes, ''show no sign of becoming disenchanted with their royal families,'' and the Netherlands persists ''with a characteristically Dutch arrangement which is half republican and half royalist'' (in which ''monarchs treat their role as just another job, from which they can retire when they get tired''). In Spain, he says, ''there is no head of steam to replace'' the newly restored monarch with something more modern, and in Belgium, ''the monarchy is one of the very few institutions which hold an intrinsically incoherent state together.''</p>
        <p>Then of course there is Britain, where the monarchy chugs along under the stolid stewardship of Queen Elizabeth, having survived the crises of Charles and Diana's marital soap opera, a furor in the early '90s over the queen's exemption from the tax code and outcries that Buckingham Palace failed to accord Diana the proper respect after her death in a car accident in Paris a decade ago.</p>
        <p>Among the reasons the monarchy has endured in Britain, Mr. Paxman says, are: sentimentality, habit, a sense that the monarchy is a link to England's past and a key somehow to its identity, and perhaps most important, the understanding that the British monarchy is a very modest one, its power trimmed and trimmed again to the point that it has become difficult for ''republicans to demonstrate that anything much would be gained by getting rid of it.''</p>
        <p>With the accepted political roles of a constitutional monarch reduced to consultation, encouragement and warning, he argues, the sovereign had been deprived of those ''historic male functions of god and governor and general'' and been left essentially with the traditionally feminine roles of ''giving comfort and nurturing good causes.'' In short, the king has become a nanny.</p>
        <p>''On Royalty: A Very Polite Inquiry into Some Strangely Related Families'' is also modest -- and polite -- in its ambitions. Very little of what Mr. Paxman -- a British journalist, best known for his interviews on the BBC's ''Newsnight'' -- says is terribly new or revealing, but he writes with a wry sense of humor and a keen sense of history, and he leads the reader on an entertaining tour through the House of Windsor, with some excursions abroad to visit the king of the Albanians and the queen of Denmark.</p>
        <p>Mr. Paxman enlivens the familiar stories of Henry VIII (and his efforts to sire an heir) and Edward VIII (whose determination to marry his divorced American mistress precipitated an abdication crisis) with his anthropological take on the customs and folkways of the royals. And he provides a gripping -- and very chilling -- account of the execution of King Charles I in 1649, embroidered with some meditations on why republicanism never took hold for long in Britain, as opposed to France, where a procession of philosophers boasted that the beheading of Louis XVI ''marked the end of an age of magical, divine authority and the birth of an age of reason.''</p>
        <p>Like the award-winning Stephen Frears movie ''The Queen,'' this book works hard to create sympathy for members of the royal family, even as it conjures up the absurdities of their daily existence in a plush but faintly dowdy bubble manned by phalanxes of courtiers and valets. Mr. Paxman not only points out the burdens of being a national symbol but also notes the endless ceremonies that must be attended, the outfits and uniforms that must be worn, the rituals that must be followed.</p>
        <p>He observes that more than a half-dozen male witnesses (including the archbishop of Canterbury, the chancellor of the Exchequer and the secretary for war) attested to the birth of the future Queen Victoria, and that this custom of having witnesses attend the birth of a royal heir survived in Britain well into the 20th century. He also observes that a good royal education is built around ''a perverse priority,'' seeking ''not to develop exceptional talent so much as to turn a uniquely privileged individual into the expression of the common man or woman.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Paxman has nothing particularly illuminating to volunteer on the already-talked-to-death subject of Charles and Diana, though his chapters on Charles give the reader an appreciation of the difficulties this man-who-would-be-king has faced throughout his life. He's had to grapple with a distant, withholding mother (who was often so busy ''queening,'' as one earlier biographer observed, that she had little time for her sensitive, lonely son); humiliating experiences in boarding school (where he was relentlessly bullied by oafs who liked to boast: ''We did him over. We just punched the future king of England''); and years of heckling from the tabloid press, which used his genuine interest in environmentalism and historic preservation to turn him into a caricature of a fuddy-duddy, tree-hugging twit.</p>
        <p>Most of Mr. Paxman's descriptions of royal life serve to reinforce the playwright Alan Bennett's observation that ''to be heir to the throne is not a position; it is a predicament.''</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
