<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kendall Reports but Is Not a Happy Camper</title>
    <meta content="15jets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/sports/football/15jets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854578"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Free Agents (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Free Agents (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kendall, Pete</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mangini, Eric</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E7DD153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="680" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kendall Reports but Is Not a Happy Camper</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kendall Reports but Is Not a Happy Camper</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., June 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pete Kendall vented his bitterness at how the Jets' management had handled his request for a new contract, capping the first practice at the mandatory minicamp Thursday by saying he had asked to be traded or released and would not rule out holding out of training camp.</p>
        <p>After skipping voluntary workouts in the off-season, Kendall, a guard, reported for minicamp but did not wait long to air his feelings about how the Jets were treating him. Kendall, one of the offensive captains and a 12-year veteran who has been instrumental in tutoring the young linemen, said he restructured his deal last year at the team's request and expected the Jets to return the favor after he had a successful season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the first practice at the mandatory minicamp, Jets guard Pete Kendall said he had asked to be traded or released and would not rule out holding out of training camp.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pete Kendall vented his bitterness at how the Jets' management had handled his request for a new contract, capping the first practice at the mandatory minicamp Thursday by saying he had asked to be traded or released and would not rule out holding out of training camp.</p>
        <p>After skipping voluntary workouts in the off-season, Kendall, a guard, reported for minicamp but did not wait long to air his feelings about how the Jets were treating him. Kendall, one of the offensive captains and a 12-year veteran who has been instrumental in tutoring the young linemen, said he restructured his deal last year at the team's request and expected the Jets to return the favor after he had a successful season.</p>
        <p>''I just felt like I'd make a reasonable request in a professional manner at the right time and something would get worked out,'' Kendall said. ''I didn't think I'd get the stonewall.''</p>
        <p>Kendall said that although he had a positive meeting with Coach Eric Mangini in March, Mangini had stopped returning his phone calls. He said he had talked with General Manager Mike Tannenbaum until recently but believed the Jets had closed the door on renegotiating.</p>
        <p>With the Jets prepared to cut or trade him last season, Kendall signed a four-year contract. It paid him $3.3 million for last season, a $300,000 raise, but dropped his salary to $1.7 million this season. He had the option of signing a one-year deal instead of this one, but he said he understood that if he played well, the team would revisit the contract. He said he was asking for $2.7 million a year.</p>
        <p>Neither Tannenbaum nor Mangini would specifically address Kendall's criticism.</p>
        <p>''First of all, we won't comment publicly about any negotiations we have, but what I will say about Pete is, I have all the respect in the world for him,'' Tannenbaum said. ''Last year, he signed a contract that I know he felt comfortable signing at the time that was in everyone's best interest.''</p>
        <p>Mangini said contract disputes were common and not something he would focus on as long as Kendall was reporting to camp. He disputed Kendall's contention that he had stopped talking to him.</p>
        <p>''Pete and I did sit down after the season,'' Mangini said. ''I've talked to his agent several times. Mike's talked to his agent several times. If there's any level of miscommunication, that's certainly not something that you're looking for. But there has been contact several times either directly or through the agent.''</p>
        <p>Kendall said he and his agent, Neil Schwartz, began working toward a new deal shortly after last season. He said Tannenbaum told him he did not want to set a precedent by renegotiating with three years left on a contract. Tannenbaum would neither confirm nor deny that.</p>
        <p>''I think all parties went into last year with the understanding it was a one-year deal,'' Kendall said. ''Eric had serious reservations about keeping me on the team, but we were able to come to an agreement. I think my play and my performance and my contribution warranted reconsideration.''</p>
        <p>Kendall, 33, who has played for the Jets since the Cardinals released him during training camp in 2004, said his request had nothing to do with the large deals signed by several free-agent linemen this off-season.</p>
        <p>He said he believed Mangini had come to accept his outspokenness last season and that their meeting in March had gone well. But Kendall said their only conversation since was a brief, unfriendly one Wednesday night when he arrived.</p>
        <p>At the first set of practices, Kendall spent much of his time with the second-team line despite having been a starter for his previous three seasons here. He stood apart from his teammates for some drills.</p>
        <p>''It's awkward,'' Kendall said. ''I'm not happy to be here. I suspect there are people in the organization who aren't happy that I'm here.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>The only player missing from the first day of mandatory minicamp Thursday was safety Kerry Rhodes, who was excused for personal reasons, the Jets said.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
