<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Woods, It's Not Only How, But How Many Other Players</title>
    <meta content="15anderson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/sports/golf/15anderson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854642"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E2DC153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="879" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Woods, It's Not Only How, But How Many Other Players</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Woods, It’s Not Only How, but How Many Other Players</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Through 15 holes at Oakmont Country Club yesterday, Tiger Woods was two over par. If he missed an eight-foot par putt on No. 16, he would be three over, going the wrong way in the first round of the 107th United States Open. But he made the putt. When he made a birdie on No. 17 with a three-foot putt and saved par on No. 18 with a pitch to about 3 feet after driving into the rough, he salvaged a one-over-par 71 that had him smiling.</p>
        <p>''On this golf course, it's fine,'' he said a few minutes later. ''It's right there.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Tiger Woods is to win at Oakmont, he will have to do what he has never done in the U.S. Open: come from behind after the first round.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Through 15 holes at Oakmont Country Club yesterday, Tiger Woods was two over par. If he missed an eight-foot par putt on No. 16, he would be three over, going the wrong way in the first round of the 107th United States Open. But he made the putt. When he made a birdie on No. 17 with a three-foot putt and saved par on No. 18 with a pitch to about 3 feet after driving into the rough, he salvaged a one-over-par 71 that had him smiling.</p>
        <p>''On this golf course, it's fine,'' he said a few minutes later. ''It's right there.''</p>
        <p>Over the years, ''right there'' has been one of Woods's favorite phrases, especially in a major. Right there is where he wants to be after the first of four rounds. Right there is reasonably close to the leaders, only three strokes behind Nick Dougherty of England and only three other golfers ahead of him going into the second round today.</p>
        <p>But in his 10 previous United States Opens as a pro, merely being right there after the first round has never been good enough for him to go on and win.</p>
        <p>In his relentless march on Jack Nicklaus's record 18 majors, Woods has won 12, but only 2 were United States Opens -- in 2000 at Pebble Beach and 2002 at Bethpage Black. In each, he was the first-round leader, with a 65 at Pebble Beach when he won by a record 15 strokes and with a 67 at Bethpage Black when he won by 3.</p>
        <p>In two other Opens, he was right there after the first round with a 68 behind only four golfers in 1999 at Pinehurst No. 2, and a 70 behind only nine golfers in 2005, also at Pinehurst No. 2, but he didn't win. He tied for third in 1999, two strokes behind Payne Stewart; he was second in 2005, two strokes behind Michael Campbell.</p>
        <p>So if Woods is to win at Oakmont in the hills above the Allegheny River, he will have to do what he has never done in the Open: come from behind after the first round. And he's going to have to do it on what is being described as golf's most difficult course.</p>
        <p>''If you play most tournaments, even a major like in Augusta,'' he said, referring to the Masters, ''even other difficult majors that we play, you probably are going to have one or two shots where it's not that hard of a shot. You can close your eyes and probably hit it either in the fairway or on the green; it's an easy shot. On this course, there are none. And no easy birdies.''</p>
        <p>In assessing Oakmont at his news conference Tuesday, Woods was asked if there was any particular hole that he looked forward to. ''Yeah, the 19th is great, man,'' he said with a laugh.</p>
        <p>When Woods was asked what hole was the hardest to make par on, he replied, ''It might be the first hole right out of the gate.'' And right out of the gate yesterday, he made a bogey on the first hole after his tee shot soared left into a deep fairway bunker.</p>
        <p>''I think that's one of the more difficult holes I've ever seen as your opening hole,'' he said. ''I know that we thought No. 1 at Muirfield in 2002 was pretty hard,'' he added, referring to the site of that year's British Open, ''but I think this one's a lot harder.''</p>
        <p>And after that first hole out of the gate, there are 17 more treacherous holes that are difficult enough at the members' leisure, much less when they're set up for the Open.</p>
        <p>''The greens were a touch softer,'' Woods said. ''If we had wedges in our hand into the wind, you had to worry about spinning the ball back if you had a full one; in most U.S. Opens, that's not the case, but over all I think the U.S.G.A. did a fantastic job setting up the course. The holes were probably in the easiest section in that section of the green. But still, look at the scores.''</p>
        <p>In golf, it's not always how many strokes you're behind the leader, it's how many golfers you're behind, because some of those golfers are going to play well.</p>
        <p>In six Opens, Woods dug a hole with a shaky first round and couldn't escape. In addition to last year's 76 at Winged Foot that he repeated in the second round to miss the 36-hole cut for the only time in a major as a pro, he opened with three 74s that trailed 63, 52 and 43 golfers -- too many to leapfrog over the next three days.</p>
        <p>When he opened with a 72 at Shinnecock Hills in 2004, he trailed 35 golfers and finished in a tie for 17th. Even when he opened with a par 70 at Olympia Fields in 2003, he was behind 27 golfers and finished tied for 20th.</p>
        <p>After a 71, Tiger Woods may be right there, but if he is to win an Open coming from behind, he can't stay right there. He has to climb closer to the lead, and he also has to lower the number of golfers he's behind.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
