<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Do a Guy and a Gal Do in a Truck? They Sing</title>
    <meta content="15mill" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/theater/reviews/15mill.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854541"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bunin, Keith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Griffin, Patty</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mayer, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morrison, Matthew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Molly, Irene</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">10 Million Miles (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlantic Theater Co</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Griffin, Patty</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bunin, Keith</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mayer, Michael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Winningham, Mare</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">10 Million Miles (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E3DF153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1107" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Do a Guy and a Gal Do in a Truck? They Sing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What Do a Guy and a Gal Do in a Truck? They Sing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley reviews Keith Bunin and Patty Griffin musical 10 Million Miles, directed by Michael Mayer; Matthew Morrison and Irene Molly star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every major road trip, at least from my experience, is a mixture of tedium and serendipity: long stretches of empty, eye-glazing highway interrupted by the awakening punctuation of the unexpected oddity or beauty spot.</p>
        <p>In this sense ''10 Million Miles,'' the musical chronicle of such an expedition that opened last night at the Atlantic Theater Company, steadfastly reflects its subject. You can identify when one of the main characters, driving from Florida to New England, nods off at the wheel. But then suddenly you glimpse a ray of beauty that, however fleeting, makes you glad you came along for the ride.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are rays of beauty in this stiff musical, courtesy of the songs of Patty Griffin, the immensely talented, country-hybrid cult composer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every major road trip, at least from my experience, is a mixture of tedium and serendipity: long stretches of empty, eye-glazing highway interrupted by the awakening punctuation of the unexpected oddity or beauty spot.</p>
        <p>In this sense ''10 Million Miles,'' the musical chronicle of such an expedition that opened last night at the Atlantic Theater Company, steadfastly reflects its subject. You can identify when one of the main characters, driving from Florida to New England, nods off at the wheel. But then suddenly you glimpse a ray of beauty that, however fleeting, makes you glad you came along for the ride.</p>
        <p>Most of those moments come courtesy of Patty Griffin, the immensely talented, country-hybrid, cult composer and performer who has lent 15 of her songs to this show, which features a book by the playwright Keith Bunin. Ms. Griffin, whose work has found its largest audience through recordings by higher-profile acts like the Dixie Chicks, writes cameo-carved songs that create complete emotional portraits of specific people.</p>
        <p>For those of us with a soft spot for the confessional heartbreak ballads on country radio stations, it was a sign of hope that Ms. Griffin had ventured into the fields of musical theater, which could certainly use a new fertilizer. Even more auspiciously, she was collaborating with the Atlantic and Michael Mayer, the company and director responsible for ''Spring Awakening,'' a show that demonstrated that pop-rock of a nonsynthetic stripe can flourish on Broadway (and just won a passel of Tonys to prove it).</p>
        <p>''10 Million Miles'' is not, sad to say, a down-home answer to ''Spring Awakening.'' In form, this sentimental story about a young couple who slip in and out of love all over the Eastern Seaboard has the arthritic, connect-the-dots stiffness that plagues most jukebox musicals, a genre known for crippling itself by trying to weave credible plots out of existing songs.</p>
        <p>That said, ''10 Million Miles'' still sparkles with signs of hope, not for this show's future prospects, but for the use of country-inflected music in narrative theater. When the four cast members sing, you often feel as if you're looking right inside them, to the point of violating their characters' privacy. This is never truer than when the singer is Mare Winningham, a film and television actress who emerges here as a musical performer to reckon with.</p>
        <p>At the center of the stage (and story) is a red pickup truck, a vehicle transformed into a diner, motel or gas station when the occasion demands. (The set is by the ever-flexible Derek McLane.) The truck carries Duane (Matthew Morrison), its enthusiastic driver, and Molly (Irene Molloy), its reluctant passenger, over many miles of road and many more psychic miles on what spiritual self-help books like to call the Journey.</p>
        <p>Molly is a recovering alcoholic and former wild girl; Duane is a former soldier and full-time fantasist. Only (and barely) friends when their trip begins, they set out together to pursue different avenues of escape from their unsatisfying lives in Florida. Will they discover each other along the way? More important, will they discover their true inner selves?</p>
        <p>The answers, which come with the assistance of various men and women they meet along the way (all played by Ms. Winningham and Skipp Sudduth), are as unsurprising as the questions. Mr. Bunin, the author of stylish and ambitious plays like ''The Credeaux Canvas'' and ''The Busy World Is Hushed,'' is in a more primitive mode here. His principal objective appears to be to create dialogue that jibes with the internal stories of Ms. Griffin's songs, and the strain and a certain perfunctoriness are evident. Whenever it's not singing ''10 Million Miles'' feels like it's merely marking time.</p>
        <p>But the music, soulfully performed by a six-member onstage band, has a fluid life of its own. You can feel the cast members settling into it as if it were a custom-contoured chair that lets them stretch and relax into character. Ms. Molloy has a passing physical and vocal resemblance to Ms. Griffin, effectively applied in infectious, pain-edged ballads like ''Be Careful'' and ''Mary.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Morrison has already proved himself on Broadway as a matinee-idol hunk of disarming musical sensitivity (in ''The Light in the Piazza'') and comic flair (in ''A Naked Girl on the Appian Way''). And he combines those virtues in his sharp-witted portrayal of Duane as a sexy, show-off narcissist with a conscience that keeps getting louder. He and the affable, pleasant-voiced Mr. Sudduth are both at their best in a duet called ''Mad Mission,'' a funny slice of boyish machismo.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Winningham is the show's revelation. First known as the good girl (read: the boring one) among the so-called Hollywood Brat Pack that populated the 1985 film ''St. Elmo's Fire,'' she has since become one of those earnest figures who regularly show up on women's television as someone with a soap-opera affliction or a daughter in jeopardy.</p>
        <p>But this actress, who played a country singer in the film ''Georgia,'' is also a musical performer of depth, style and versatility. Playing a drunken divorcée at an Atlantic City wedding chapel and an elderly factory worker in upstate New York, Ms. Winningham shifts with sublime seamlessness from feisty flash (leading a rousing version of the blissful ''Love Throw a Line'') to humble resignation (in a rendering of Ms. Griffin's ''Making Pies'' that is a heartbreaking study in quiet resignation).</p>
        <p>Both characters, like Ms. Griffin's songs, have independent lives that continue in your head when the music ends. How often does that happen when you see a new musical these days? ''10 Million Miles'' may not, in itself, go the distance. But unlike the sputtering ''Ring of Fire'' (the ill-fated Johnny Cash show on Broadway), this production suggests encouragingly that for creators of American musicals, country back roads are well worth pursuing.</p>
        <p>10 Million Miles</p>
        <p>Book by Keith Bunin; music and lyrics by Patty Griffin; directed by Michael Mayer; music direction, arrangements and orchestrations by Tim Weil; sets by Derek McLane; costumes by Michael Krass; lighting by Jules Fisher and Peggy Eisenhauer; sound by Brian Ronan; music coordinator, Michael Keller; production stage manager, James Harker; production manager, Lester Grant; general manager, Melinda Berk; associate artistic director, Christian Parker. Presented by the Atlantic Theater Company, Neil Pepe, artistic director; Andrew D. Hamingson, managing director; in association with Ira Pittelman and Tom Hulce. At the Atlantic Theater Company, the Linda Gross Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea; (212) 279-4200. Through July 15. Running time: 1 hour 40 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Irene Molloy (Molly), Matthew Morrison (Duane), Skipp Sudduth (the Men) and Mare Winningham (the Women).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
