<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Striving for Perfection, García Forgets to Practice</title>
    <meta content="15sidebar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/sports/golf/15sidebar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854641"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Garcia, Sergio</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bjorn, Thomas</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Leonard, Justin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DC153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Striving for Perfection, García Forgets to Practice</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Striving for Perfection, García Forgets to Practice</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa., June 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Maybe Sergio García should have genuflected at Oakmont Country Club's Church Pews instead of joking about them.</p>
        <p>During a practice round for the United States Open, García hit his golf ball into the 26,000-square-foot bunker tucked between the third and fourth holes, the one with the 12 fingers of grass rising like welts across its face.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sergio García’s round at the United States Open went downhill after he found Oakmont Country Club’s Church Pews on hole No. 3.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Maybe Sergio García should have genuflected at Oakmont Country Club's Church Pews instead of joking about them.</p>
        <p>During a practice round for the United States Open, García hit his golf ball into the 26,000-square-foot bunker tucked between the third and fourth holes, the one with the 12 fingers of grass rising like welts across its face.</p>
        <p>Instead of trying to hack his way out, García fetched his ball from the tall grass and dropped it in the fairway. That is the neat thing about practice, he quipped at the time, you do not have to play the ball where you hit it.</p>
        <p>On the No. 3 hole Thursday, García's ball again found the Church Pews. This time, he had no choice but to hack his way out of them, and his lack of practice showed. He made a mess of the hole, taking two shots to get out of the bunker on his way to a double-bogey 6.</p>
        <p>Garcia's front nine went downhill from there as he made the turn at seven-over-par 42. He finished with a nine-over 79, then declined to talk about his round. Perhaps he figured his play on the third hole pretty much summed it up.</p>
        <p>Thomas Bjorn found the Church Pews coming and going. His drive on No. 3 landed in the sand and he made a bogey. His tee shot on No. 4 sat like a diamond on one of the long, grassy fingers, and he scrambled for a par.</p>
        <p>After posting a 75, Bjorn emerged from the scorer's room in the clubhouse scowling. Asked about his unheavenly experience at the third and fourth holes, he said, ''I have nothing to say about this golf course.''</p>
        <p>Justin Leonard, the 1997 British Open champion, accepted his visit to the Church Pews with a stiff upper lip. His tee shot on No. 3 landed there, and he wound up with a bogey.</p>
        <p>''You can't really play out of any of the bunkers here, so it's not like, 'Oh, I hit into the Church Pews,' '' Leonard said. ''You actually have a better chance of, you know, having some kind of shot out of those than you do the bunkers on the other side.''</p>
        <p>Leonard was referring to five bunkers lined up like beads on a rosary on the right side of the third fairway. Between the Church Pews and the rosary beads, the fairway is as slender as a swan's neck.</p>
        <p>''It is what it is,'' Steve Stricker said.</p>
        <p>Stricker was one under par when he arrived at the third tee. His tee shot burrowed into the grass in the Church Pews like an ingrown hair. His caddie was right on top of the ball and could not see it.</p>
        <p>When the ball was located at last, Stricker was awarded a free drop. He had a pretty severe uphill lie, but decided to go for the green. His blind faith was not rewarded.</p>
        <p>As Stricker recounted it, ''I hit into the rough up by the green, then knocked it over the green, then knocked it on, then missed the putt.''</p>
        <p>For those counting at home, that was a 6. The missed putt was a harbinger of Stricker's back nine, where he took 20 putts and had to settle for a 75.</p>
        <p>Jim Furyk, the world's third-ranked player, teed off in the afternoon, about 45 minutes after Stricker. He, too, found himself contemplating his fate from the Church Pews. But Furyk did not look for a miracle.</p>
        <p>Because he had an awkward lie, Furyk said, ''The thought in my mind wasn't if I was going to go for the green, it was where I was going to lay up.''</p>
        <p>Furyk took his bogey and moved on. That kind of judicious thinking helped him card a respectable round of 71. For Stricker, it was live and learn.</p>
        <p>''I should have tried not to bite too much off there on that second shot,'' he said. ''I should have just maybe knocked it out there and made sure I had a sand wedge into the green or a wedge or something to spin it. Because where I ended up, in the rough next to the green, I was worse off.''</p>
        <p>So why did he try?</p>
        <p>''I thought I could get it there,'' Stricker said, because he had seen other golfers pull it off during the practice rounds -- excluding García, of course.</p>
        <p>''You can be fine if you hit it in there or you can get an unlucky break,'' Stricker said. ''I've seen guys knock it on from in between those things. It all depends where you are in those Church Pews.''</p>
        <p>In other words, a reporter said, seeking clarification, it's a bit of crapshoot.</p>
        <p>''Yeah,'' Stricker said. He laughed. ''Every hole is.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
