<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Great Divide on Immigration</title>
    <meta content="l15brooks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854600"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E1DD153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Great Divide on Immigration</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''The Next Culture War'' (column, June 12):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''The Next Culture War'' (column, June 12):</p>
        <p>Millions of people who have entered our country and remained here illegally have broken our laws. If we are going to give all of them a pass -- amnesty with full citizenship upon a few years' wait and a minimal fine -- why don't we simply open our borders and accept everyone in the world who wishes to immigrate to the United States? How many millions will come?</p>
        <p>Whenever thoughtful people wish to discuss these policies, we are accused of racism or bias against certain immigrant groups. I have no doubt that such views exist, but not everyone who opposes the immigration bill shares them.</p>
        <p>In school, we are taught that the United States is a nation of laws. Why have we lost control of our borders? I would be happy to see more immigrants from different parts of the world, but let's find the will to put this in a legal context. Education has less to do with many opponents' reasoning than simple common sense.</p>
        <p>Mary St. Laurent  Corning, N.Y., June 12, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As someone who spent 30 years as a machinist and is now retraining in paralegal studies, I believe I've seen both sides of the divide that David Brooks speaks of in regard to attitudes toward immigration.</p>
        <p>In my experience, the root of the national schism over immigration policy is not cultural attitude but economic reality. The fact of the matter is that few if any of the estimated 12 million people here in the United States illegally are here to work as actuarials or English professors or newspaper columnists -- the sorts of jobs normally held by university grads. They are here to work as bricklayers or welders or landscapers.</p>
        <p>I would posit that if illegal immigration were undermining the wages of editors and lawyers instead of janitors and kitchen staff, the current debate might sound quite a bit different.</p>
        <p>Glenn Baldwin  Chicago, June 12, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>David Brooks notes that immigration is not a partisan issue and does not dovetail with racist or nativist attitudes. He then suggests that the current controversy is a cultural clash between an educated elite, favoring a cosmopolitan approach to the world, and a less educated class, worried that increased diversity would threaten ancient ties of community and social solidarity. I believe that this last analysis is wrong.</p>
        <p>As a well-educated liberal, I favor cultural diversity and enabling of individualism, but not at the cost of widening the gap between the haves and have-nots in our society. The Bush-Kennedy-McCain immigration bill was impossibly complex and tried to encompass too much.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, it sided with the Chamber of Commerce in helping unscrupulous businesses attract and exploit illegal immigrant workers, whose subpar wages add to the profits of the rich and lower the prospects of American workers seeking fair employment.</p>
        <p>When it comes to the distribution of America's income and wealth, economists indicate that the disparity between the wealthy and the rest of society is greater than at any time since the Great Depression. This is a trend that must be resisted and reversed.</p>
        <p>William Reusch  Okemos, Mich., June 12, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>David Brooks argues that immigration is not a partisan issue, but study after study has shown that self-identifying as a Republican, particularly a conservative Republican, is one of the most potent predictors of hostility toward immigration.</p>
        <p>Republican politicians have run on anti-immigration platforms because this is an issue that works for them. It is highly effective in mobilizing the part of the Republican base that is culturally conservative and angry about immigrants who are perceived as abusers of tax-supported programs.</p>
        <p>Republicans and Democrats may dislike the current immigration bill in roughly equal proportions, but it is Republican voters who oppose it most intensely.</p>
        <p>Wayne A. Cornelius  Director, Center for  Comparative Immigration Studies  University of California-San Diego  La Jolla, Calif., June 12, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
