<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Go Public, And Face Higher Taxes</title>
    <meta content="15tax" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/business/15tax.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854656"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Partnerships</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Blackstone Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fortress Investment Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Jenny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baucus, Max (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grassley, Charles E (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Partnerships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Blackstone Group</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E0DC153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Go Public, And Face Higher Taxes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bill Would Raise Taxes on Public Equity Firms</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNY ANDERSON and ANDREW ROSS SORKIN; Michael J. de la Merced contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross; Anderson, Jenny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sens Max Baucus and Charles E Grassley introduce bill that would tax as corporations all publicly traded partnerships that derive most of their income by managing other people's assets, like Blackstone Group and Fortress Investment Group, which went public earlier this year; bill would most likely influence other private equity firms and hedge funds that are considering tapping public markets; investors could shave off 15 percent to 20 percent of Blackstone's $40 billion valuation; new tax policy could reduce firm's net earnings by as much as $250 million on annual basis (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Talk about trying to rain on their parade.</p>
        <p>As the Blackstone Group, the giant private equity firm, continues marketing its initial public offering to potential investors, two United States senators last night introduced legislation that could significantly increase taxes on publicly traded private equity firms and hedge funds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New legislation could increase taxes on publicly traded private equity firms and hedge funds, a move that could dampen interest in the Blackstone Group.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Talk about trying to rain on their parade.</p>
        <p>As the Blackstone Group, the giant private equity firm, continues marketing its initial public offering to potential investors, two United States senators last night introduced legislation that could significantly increase taxes on publicly traded private equity firms and hedge funds.</p>
        <p>Senator Max Baucus, the Montana Democrat who leads the Senate Finance Committee, and Senator Charles E. Grassley of Iowa, the ranking Republican member, introduced a bill that would tax as corporations all publicly traded partnerships that derive most of their income by managing other people's assets, like Blackstone and the Fortress Investment Group, which went public earlier this year.</p>
        <p>The bill, if enacted into law, would most likely influence other private equity firms and hedge funds that are considering tapping the public markets.</p>
        <p>If the bill succeeds, investors could shave off 15 percent to 20 percent of Blackstone's $40 billion valuation. On an annual basis, the new tax policy could reduce the firm's net earnings by as much as $250 million.</p>
        <p>Virtually all private equity firms and hedge funds are structured as partnerships. The managers of these funds earn 2 percent of the assets they manage, which is taxed at ordinary income rates, and also take home 20 percent of the profits, which are taxed at the lower 15 percent capital gains rate.</p>
        <p>If the proposed legislation -- sure to be called the Blackstone Bill -- is adopted, publicly traded private equity firms and hedge funds would face an additional corporate tax, bringing the effective tax rate to almost 45 percent.</p>
        <p>''It's unfair to allow a publicly traded company to act like a corporation but not pay corporate tax, contrary to the intent of the tax code,'' Mr. Grassley said. ''We don't have a workable tax code if we don't have structural integrity.''</p>
        <p>Buyout firms like Blackstone raise billions of dollars from pensions funds, endowments and wealthy individuals, which they use to buy companies and take them private. Then they take the companies public again or sell them, seeking to double or triple their money.</p>
        <p>The extraordinary pay packages of those who manage hedge funds and private equity have caught the attention of the Senate Finance Committee, which is looking at whether the manager's portion of a fund's profits -- called carried interest -- should be taxed at the capital gains rate or the higher ordinary income rate. Private equity officials expressed concern last night that this bill could be a first step, with a higher tax on carried interest to follow.</p>
        <p>The proposal clearly rankled a co-founder of the Blackstone Group, Stephen A. Schwarzman, who was speaking at an awards presentation during a Yale-sponsored conference at the New York Stock Exchange yesterday. During his acceptance speech for the ''Legend in Leadership Award,'' Mr. Schwarzman took a call on his cellphone. ''There's a crisis going on,'' he told the audience.</p>
        <p>He later explained: ''We're having an interesting time with our I.P.O. There's some concern in Congress that this is not an ideal thing for a firm like us to do.''</p>
        <p>Lobbyists for private equity firms have been working members of the Senate Finance Committee for months, and it is unclear what level of support the proposal will gain. Moreover, with the election cycle heating up and private equity and hedge funds becoming increasingly important donors, Congress may be reluctant to jeopardize a potential honey pot of political donations.</p>
        <p>Still, the size of the deals and the big pay packages at private equity and hedge funds has led some, including those in Congress, to look more closely at the structural benefits of partnerships.</p>
        <p>Currently, publicly traded partnerships that derive more than 90 percent of their income passively -- from dividends or interest, for example -- can remain a partnership. The bill makes the case that alternative asset management vehicles like private equity and hedge funds do not derive their income passively, but rather act as investment advisers or money managers and so should be considered corporations.</p>
        <p>Last night, Charles D. Rangel, a New York Democrat and chairman of the House Way and Means Committee, lauded the efforts of his colleagues in the Senate. ''It is an issue with substantial implications for the viability of our corporate income tax system and the structure of our investment banking industry,'' Mr. Rangel said in a statement. ''We should not permit one segment of the financial services industry to enjoy a competitive advantage over others.''</p>
        <p>Legislators scrambled to finish writing the bill before the pricing of the Blackstone deal, which will be the first significant private equity firm in America to go public.</p>
        <p>Sen. Baucus and Sen. Grassley wrote a letter to Treasury Secretary Henry M. Paulson Jr., seeking his input. ''We believe that these I.P.O.'s raise serious tax questions that, if left unaddressed, have the potential to jeopardize the integrity of the tax code and the corporate tax base over the long term,'' the letter said. Similar correspondence was sent to Christopher Cox, chairman of the Securities and Exchange Commission.</p>
        <p>Even if the measure is adopted, firms like Blackstone may not be immediately affected. The bill would give companies that have gone public or have filed to go public until 2012 to comply.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
