<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Romney Faces Another 'Flip-Flop' Question: Has He Changed on Stem Cells?</title>
    <meta content="15romney" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/us/politics/15romney.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2008 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Stem Cells</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stem Cells</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mormons (Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stem Cells</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mormons (Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (DC)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Romney, Mitt</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E7DC153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="744" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Romney Faces Another 'Flip-Flop' Question: Has He Changed on Stem Cells?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Romney Faces Another ‘Flip-Flop’ Question: Has He Changed on Stem Cells?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL LUO</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mitt Romney, who as a presidential candidate has already drawn criticism for changes in his positions on other social issues, is now facing questions on whether he has shifted his stand on expanded federal support for embryonic stem cell research.</p>
        <p>Mr. Romney says he has been entirely consistent. But some of his recent statements suggest that he has come to oppose wider financing, which in the past he appeared to support.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Republican presidential candidate Mitt Romney is now facing questions on whether he has shifted his stand on expanded federal support for stem cell research.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mitt Romney, who as a presidential candidate has already drawn criticism for changes in his positions on other social issues, is now facing questions on whether he has shifted his stand on expanded federal support for embryonic stem cell research.</p>
        <p>Mr. Romney says he has been entirely consistent. But some of his recent statements suggest that he has come to oppose wider financing, which in the past he appeared to support.</p>
        <p>The question is not only highly charged but also at least potentially quite personal: Mr. Romney's wife, Ann, suffers from multiple sclerosis, one of the diseases that supporters of the research say could someday be cured by it.</p>
        <p>Because standard research entails destruction of embryos, federal financing is currently allowed only for work on those stem cell lines that already existed in August 2001, when President Bush adopted that cutoff as his administration's policy.</p>
        <p>But in a little-noticed moment at the first Republican presidential debate, last month in California, Mr. Romney was asked whether he would encourage broader federal financing. When he did not directly answer that question, he was pressed on whether scientists should be able to do research at all on embryos that fertility clinics would otherwise discard anyway.</p>
        <p>Mr. Romney said he would be ''happy to allow that,'' then stopped himself and said: ''I shouldn't say happy. It's fine for that to be allowed, to be legal. I won't use our government funds for that.''</p>
        <p>That response on financing was a fairly neat fit with the anti-abortion stance Mr. Romney has carved out, a position he freely admits he arrived at little more than two years ago, timing that has fueled skepticism among some conservatives.</p>
        <p>Peter G. Flaherty, Mr. Romney's deputy campaign manager, who was his deputy chief of staff and his point man on bioethics issues when he was governor of Massachusetts, said his position on stem cell research had been consistent.</p>
        <p>''From the moment we sat down as an administration to formulate a policy on stem cell research, the governor has never been a proponent of expanded federal funding or state funding for embryonic stem cell research,'' Mr. Flaherty said. ''Governor Romney is a strong advocate for federal funding for alternative methods to get pluripotent stem cells, such as altered nuclear transfer and direct reprogramming.''</p>
        <p>But in August 2004, Governor Romney appeared to express support for expanded federal backing of embryonic work. Ann Romney held a news conference that month in which she said that she supported such research and that she believed it could be done ''morally and ethically.'' Soon afterward, in response to questions about the issue, Eric Fehrnstrom, a spokesman for Mr. Romney, told The Boston Globe that the governor ''wants to encourage and support scientific research and the discovery of new cures.''</p>
        <p>''For that reason,'' Mr. Fehrnstrom said, ''he supports stem cell research on new and existing lines, in both private and federally funded settings.''</p>
        <p>Less than a year later, Mr. Romney also spoke favorably of a federal stem cell measure that had just been passed by the House of Representatives but that Mr. Bush eventually vetoed.</p>
        <p>The governor himself had just vetoed a Massachusetts bill that, going further than the federal legislation, would have opened the door to a controversial technique entailing the cloning of embryos for purposes of experimentation. In response to a question then, Mr. Romney drew a distinction between the House bill and the state measure.</p>
        <p>''The United States House of Representatives voted for a bill that was identical to what I proposed,'' Mr. Romney said. ''They voted to provide for surplus embryos from in vitro fertilization processes being used for research and experimentation. That's what I said I support.''</p>
        <p>The stem cell issue took on added relevance this month after the Democratic-led Congress passed a measure similar to the earlier bill that Mr. Bush vetoed and that Mr. Romney spoke favorably about in 2005.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is expected to veto the new measure as well, and Mr. Flaherty said Mr. Romney would also reject it.</p>
        <p>Matthew S. David, a deputy communications director for Senator John McCain's presidential campaign, called that stance another example of a flip-flop by Mr. Romney.</p>
        <p>''It shouldn't surprise any Republican primary voters that Mitt Romney has changed his position on federal funding of stem cells, just like he did on immigration, abortion, taxes and guns,'' Mr. David said. ''This illustrates he is willing to say and do anything to win the nomination.''</p>
        <p>THE 2008 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
