<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Sweep of Cavaliers, Spurs Are Champions Again</title>
    <meta content="15nba" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854699"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/San Antonio Spurs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E3DB153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="841" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Sweep of Cavaliers, Spurs Are Champions Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <dateline>CLEVELAND, June 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The San Antonio Spurs raced to the center of Cleveland's court, jumping together into a tight circle of celebration. LeBron James walked off his home court without turning around, dejected in his first, forgettable trip to the championship stage.</p>
        <p>Overcoming a desperate comeback from James and the Cavaliers, the Spurs closed with a vicious determined run, swatting Cleveland's effort like a cheap souvenir to take an 83-82 victory in Game 4.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The San Antonio Spurs raced to the center of Cleveland's court, jumping together into a tight circle of celebration. LeBron James walked off his home court without turning around, dejected in his first, forgettable trip to the championship stage.</p>
        <p>Overcoming a desperate comeback from James and the Cavaliers, the Spurs closed with a vicious determined run, swatting Cleveland's effort like a cheap souvenir to take an 83-82 victory in Game 4.</p>
        <p>When the Spurs had capped a sweep Thursday night and collected their fourth N.B.A. championship in nine years, there was no confetti. But there will be another banner in San Antonio to add to the ones from 1999, 2003 and 2005.</p>
        <p>And Tony Parker will go home with his own trophy, winning the Most Valuable Player award for his consistent performances in all four games, in which he averaged 24.5 points. Tim Duncan, the previous M.V.P. winner in the finals for the Spurs, gladly bequeathed the honor.</p>
        <p>''It's like a dream,'' Parker said on the podium, before adding quickly, ''I want to thank my teammates.''</p>
        <p>That was exactly the motto of this selfless Spurs team.</p>
        <p>In the fourth quarter, it was Manu Ginóbili, the same player who had not made a field goal in Game 3, who sank the clutch shots for the Spurs. He scored on a driving layup and then a 3-pointer, boosting the Spurs to a 69-66 lead with 4 minutes 15 seconds remaining. And the Cavaliers would never lead again.</p>
        <p>''Any time you get an opportunity to finish off a team, you got to take it,'' said Ginóbili, who scored 13 of his game-high 27 points in the fourth quarter. ''We knew if we could keep it close in the fourth quarter, we would have a good chance. I think we showed our experience in the last five minutes.''</p>
        <p>Said Duncan: ''For them to make a run, for us to answer and keep our composure, to find a way to win, no matter what. I didn't play the greatest, they made plays, but we found a way to win. That's what this team is about.''</p>
        <p>In the first three quarters, when he scored 24 points, Parker was the one who had skimmed through the Cavaliers' defense like a water bug bent on crossing the pond triumphantly.</p>
        <p>In six years, Parker transformed himself from a gangly French teenager whom the Spurs chose 28th over all in the draft, into the N.B.A.'s first finals M.V.P. from Europe After he won his first title with the Spurs, in 2003 over the Nets, Parker was upset when the Spurs pursued point guard Jason Kidd that same summer.</p>
        <p>Two titles and two All-Star games later, this proved to be Parker's and the Spurs' sweet reward.</p>
        <p>James, only 22, left his own arena empty-handed without watching the scene of the celebration. ''I didn't want to turn around and look,'' he said, shaking his head.</p>
        <p>He finished with 24 points on 10-of-30 shooting, had 10 assists and committed 6 turnovers.</p>
        <p>Add one more failure to the city's litany of sports ignominy: The Drive. The Fumble. The Shot. The Sweep.</p>
        <p>The End.</p>
        <p>It came sooner than Cleveland had hoped. Then again, the Cavaliers arrived at the N.B.A. finals sooner than expected. It was clear they were not prepared for San Antonio's sophisticated defenses, and the fiercely focused group of veterans that had never lost a finals series.</p>
        <p>Robert Horry, the active leader in N.B.A. championships, won his seventh title at age 36, surpassing Michael Jordan's six rings. Only seven other players have won more titles than Horry and they all were members of the Boston Celtics' dynasty, led by Bill Russell's 11 championships.</p>
        <p>Michael Finley was just happy to win his first title at age 34, in his 12th season in the league.</p>
        <p>No matter that this was the least competitive series in recent history with the matchup of the smallest television markets in N.B.A. finals history. The Spurs measure their excellence in the consistency of their defense, and if that has no glamour, one can always look to the shine of their trophies.</p>
        <p>In the fourth quarter, Ginóbili sank the clutch shots for the Spurs.</p>
        <p>James had nowhere to go while his teammates stood helplessly watching and waiting for passes they would be unable to convert. By the time the Spurs had opened up an 11-point lead late in the third quarter, James had missed 15 shots. San Antonio led, 60-52, heading into the final quarter.</p>
        <p>The Spurs went into the locker room at halftime with a 39-34 lead -- the lowest combined score at the half in the series. If Popovich said the Spurs' 40-38 halftime lead in Game 3 set the ''western world of basketball back 10 years,'' then this did little to dig the game out of its black hole.</p>
        <p>The denouement was swift and silent as the series unraveled into irrelevancy for the Cavaliers and cemented the Spurs' dynasty.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>At 12:51 a.m. Thursday, LeBron James's girlfriend, Savannah Brinson, delivered their second son, Bryce Maximus James.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
