<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Landis Uses New Book To Address Charges</title>
    <meta content="15landis" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/sports/othersports/15landis.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854579"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CYCLING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tour de France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tour De France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Armstrong, Lance</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Landis, Floyd</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E7DD153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="693" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Landis Uses New Book To Address Charges</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Landis Uses New Book to Address Charges</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WYATT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new book by Floyd Landis, the American cyclist who is facing charges that he used a performance-enhancing drug en route to winning the Tour de France last year, sheds new light on Landis's actions during a hearing over the doping charges last month as well as during last year's Tour.</p>
        <p>In the book, which is scheduled to be released June 26, Landis appears to contradict some of the testimony he gave last month at an arbitration hearing on the doping charges. That testimony concerned his reaction to a phone call that his manager, Will Geoghegan, made to Greg LeMond, a former Tour de France winner, the night before LeMond was scheduled to testify against Landis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the book, Floyd Landis, last year’s Tour de France winner, appears to contradict some of the testimony he gave at an arbitration hearing on charges of doping last month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A new book by Floyd Landis, the American cyclist who is facing charges that he used a performance-enhancing drug en route to winning the Tour de France last year, sheds new light on Landis's actions during a hearing over the doping charges last month as well as during last year's Tour.</p>
        <p>In the book, which is scheduled to be released June 26, Landis appears to contradict some of the testimony he gave last month at an arbitration hearing on the doping charges. That testimony concerned his reaction to a phone call that his manager, Will Geoghegan, made to Greg LeMond, a former Tour de France winner, the night before LeMond was scheduled to testify against Landis.</p>
        <p>In an epilogue, Landis writes that he witnessed Geoghegan's phone call and was shocked by his manager's attempt to intimidate LeMond by bringing up LeMond's previously undisclosed history of being sexually abused as a child. So shocked, he writes, that he immediately decided Geoghegan should be fired.</p>
        <p>''The only thing I knew right away was that Will needed to go,'' Landis writes. ''I went to his room and helped him pack his things.''</p>
        <p>But Geoghegan went to the hearing with Landis the next day and sat behind Landis's defense table, and was not fired until after LeMond testified. Landis later testified that he felt he needed to talk to his lawyers about the call before he took action.</p>
        <p>In addition, Landis says in the book that he received a shot of cortisone during last year's Tour to ease the pain of his damaged hip. Although cortisone is a banned substance in cycling, Landis had special permission to use the drug because of his medical condition. But it has not previously been widely reported that he received an injection during the three-week race itself.</p>
        <p>The book, titled ''Positively False: The Real Story of How I Won the Tour de France,'' co-written with Loren Mooney, is being published by Simon Spotlight Entertainment, part of Simon &amp; Schuster, and is scheduled to be released June 26. The New York Times obtained a copy by placing a regular order for the book with an online bookseller.</p>
        <p>Much of the material in the book has been aired previously, including at the recent hearing into the allegations of drug use during the Tour. Landis tested positive for an abnormal testosterone ratio after his stunning comeback in Stage 17 of the Tour; subsequent analysis of urine samples given during the race revealed the presence of traces of artificial testosterone in his system.</p>
        <p>Landis has disputed those results, maintaining his innocence and saying that he was the victim of flawed analysis by the French laboratory that conducted the tests.</p>
        <p>''I did not use performance-enhancing drugs in the 2006 Tour de France or any other time in my career,'' Landis writes in the book. ''All I ever did was train.''</p>
        <p>Landis also asserts in the book, as he did last month before the doping hearing, that officials at the United States Anti-Doping Agency told him that they would be lenient on him if he provided information about the suspected doping practices of Lance Armstrong, on whose team Landis rode for three years.</p>
        <p>In the book, Landis writes that he was stunned by the offer. ''I didn't have any evidence to give them about Lance, anyway,'' he wrote. ''If Lance had been doping, he sure didn't tell me about it. He would have been a fool to do so.''</p>
        <p>Noting that numerous allegations, none of them proven, have surfaced about Armstrong over the years, Landis continued: ''All I know is that I never saw anything to indicate that Lance used performance-enhancing drugs, that his blood and urine were tested more than anyone else's, and that he never returned a positive test.''</p>
        <p>Landis also gives an intimate peek at the inner world of professional cycling, detailing his salary in the years he rode for Armstrong's team -- between $60,000 and $240,000 -- and the disagreements with Armstrong and the team director, Johan Bruyneel. Those disagreements led Landis to accept a job as leader of the Phonak squad, where, he said, he was paid $900,000 over two years.</p>
        <p>CYCLING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
