<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge Promises Speedy Trial in Fort Dix Case</title>
    <meta content="15dix" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/15/nyregion/15dix.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854647"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Fort Dix (NJ)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Kugler, Robert B</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E1DC153FF936A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="598" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge Promises Speedy Trial in Fort Dix Case</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Judge Promises Speedy Trial in Fort Dix Case</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREEM FAHIM</byline>
      <dateline>CAMDEN, N.J., June 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The federal judge presiding over the case of six men accused of plotting to kill soldiers at the Fort Dix military base compared the investigation on Thursday to ''an undercover drug operation'' and promised a speedy trial by year's end that he expected to last three or four weeks.</p>
        <p>The United States district judge, Robert B. Kugler, said the suspects would be in leg shackles throughout the trial, that there would be extra security checks at the courthouse and that the high-profile nature of the case would demand a ''huge'' jury pool. He also said he would consider piping video of the proceedings to Fort Dix, but added, ''I don't know if they qualify as victims.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The judge gave extensive commentary after six men charged with planning an attack on the army base pleaded not guilty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The federal judge presiding over the case of six men accused of plotting to kill soldiers at the Fort Dix military base compared the investigation on Thursday to ''an undercover drug operation'' and promised a speedy trial by year's end that he expected to last three or four weeks.</p>
        <p>The United States district judge, Robert B. Kugler, said the suspects would be in leg shackles throughout the trial, that there would be extra security checks at the courthouse and that the high-profile nature of the case would demand a ''huge'' jury pool. He also said he would consider piping video of the proceedings to Fort Dix, but added, ''I don't know if they qualify as victims.''</p>
        <p>''This is an unusual case,'' Judge Kugler told the packed courtroom, referring to the intense public interest, as the accused men, in drab olive jumpsuits and blue slippers, watched from the jury box. ''If the government is not able to prove their case, they should not be in jail.''</p>
        <p>The judge's extensive commentary came in a lengthy hearing after a routine arraignment in which the six men pleaded not guilty to the charges against them. Five of the men -- Mohamed Ibrahim Shnewer, 22; Serdar Tatar, 23; and three brothers, Eljvir, 23, Shain, 26, and Dritan Duka, 28 -- face charges including conspiring to kill members of the United States military. The Duka brothers, Albanians who overstayed their visas, also face charges of possession of firearms by an illegal immigrant.</p>
        <p>The sixth suspect, Agron Abdullahu, 24, is charged with supplying the Duka brothers with weapons.</p>
        <p>The men, from southern New Jersey and Philadelphia, were arrested last month after trying to buy high-powered weapons from a government informer who had infiltrated their group, according to court records.</p>
        <p>Federal agents had been monitoring the men's activities, including shooting assault weapons at a range in upstate New York and surveying military bases, since January 2006, when a clerk at an electronics store passed along a videotape of the weapons training.</p>
        <p>Along with that evidence, United States Attorney William Fitzpatrick told the court Thursday, the government has other surveillance recordings of the men that document more than hundreds of conversations.</p>
        <p>When asked by Judge Kugler if there were wiretap recordings, Mr. Fitzpatrick said that he was ''not at liberty to answer.''</p>
        <p>Dritan Duka, who is also known as Tony, and Eljvir Duka entered the courtroom on Thursday and greeted court officers in Arabic. Mr. Tatar looked stunned throughout the proceedings. He mouthed greetings to his relatives in the courtroom, and their sobbing could be heard throughout his appearance.</p>
        <p>The authorities have called the men Islamic extremists, and said they watched terrorist videos and spoke about ''calling for jihad.'' Two government informers infiltrated the group, and recorded some of the conversations cited by prosecutors.</p>
        <p>The trial is tentatively set to begin Aug. 13, but defense lawyers said on Thursday that they had conflicts that could push it well into the fall.</p>
        <p>Given the intense media and public interest in the case, Judge Kugler said the court would try to post evidence online as it is presented.</p>
        <p>Invoking the federal trial of Zacarias Moussaoui, who pleaded guilty in April 2005 to conspiracy for involvement in the Sept. 11 terrorist attacks, and who received a life sentence last year, the judge noted that evidence in that trial was made available to the press at 10 a.m. the day after.</p>
        <p>Referring to the possibility of sending audio and video files from the trial to a Web site for the press, he said he would ''try and make it simultaneous.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
