<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To the Envelope Pushers, Cheers!</title>
    <meta content="06pour" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/dining/06pour.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852479"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE POUR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E5DF1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To the Envelope Pushers, Cheers!</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">To the Envelope Pushers, Cheers!</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eric Asimov</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY go by many names. Most familiarly and perhaps most unkindly, they're called wine geeks. They're also known as zealots, extremists and even the wine counterculture.</p>
        <p>I prefer the term saviors. For without these rambunctious voices on the margins assailing the mainstream and praising the little-known and the offbeat, the wine world would be a far more monotonous place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The world owes a debt of gratitude to wine geeks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEY go by many names. Most familiarly and perhaps most unkindly, they're called wine geeks. They're also known as zealots, extremists and even the wine counterculture.</p>
        <p>I prefer the term saviors. For without these rambunctious voices on the margins assailing the mainstream and praising the little-known and the offbeat, the wine world would be a far more monotonous place.</p>
        <p>The movie ''Mondovino'' and the doom-and-gloomers notwithstanding, we live in the greatest era ever for wine lovers. Never has such a diversity of great wines been so widely available.</p>
        <p>From the chateaux of Bordeaux to the hillside hamlets of Valle d'Aosta, from windswept volcanic rocks of Santorini to foggy ridges of the Sonoma Coast, wine from anywhere can be found almost everywhere.</p>
        <p>For that we have a long list of people to thank. Here's to you in the wine trade. Without you, well, we'd all be reaching for another lemonade. But I'm not addressing you, nor am I talking about writers and critics, though you inspire us all with your enthusiasm. No, I'm talking about the subversives, people who have left the mainstream to discover new worlds of wonderful, offbeat wines.</p>
        <p>Some are in the business, sommeliers like Paul Grieco of Hearth and Insieme in New York, who worships at the altar of riesling and plies a willing clientele with such oddball grapes as savagnin, rkatsiteli, romorantin and others even harder to pronounce.</p>
        <p>Some are importers, like Joe Dressner of Louis/Dressner Selections, who brings in a fair share of wines that nobody ever heard of from places nobody knows. Some are retailers, like David Lillie of Chambers Street Wines in New York, who introduces his clientele to the more esoteric glories of the Loire Valley.</p>
        <p>But they might not get very far if it weren't for a hard-core cadre of largely anonymous consumers, some known only by Internet handles and noms de blog. They pepper sites like erobertparker.com, wineloverspage.com and, especially, Wine Therapy (enemyvessel.com/forum/) with their pointed opinions, tenaciously held and contentiously delivered, usually with all the subtlety of a Molotov cocktail through a window.</p>
        <p>What are they talking about? Not the latest Bordeaux barrel tastings or 90-point wines. Wines like those might be considered ''spoofulated,'' a geekdom term for engineered wines that, in another vernacular, is a synonym for gag-me-with-a-spoon.</p>
        <p>No, they are writing about ''real wines,'' those made and sold without particular manipulations in the vineyard, the cellar or the marketplace. Mr. Dressner, the importer, refers to the good stuff as ''heirloom wines,'' with flavors and aromas that can't be replicated on a mass scale.</p>
        <p>''There's a revulsion to everything being manufactured, distributed and consumed,'' he said of the wine subversives. ''They appreciate a fickleness and something unknowable about wine.''</p>
        <p>Wine geeks are not a monolithic group, although certain characteristics emerge, like a preference for minerality and acidity in a wine over soft fruitiness, an abhorrence for new oak flavors and a reverence for terroir and traditional methods. If anything has brought these iconoclasts together into something like a community, it is the Internet.</p>
        <p>Years ago, before the Web engulfed the world, Internet user groups like alt.food.wine and services like Prodigy and CompuServe were the main hangouts.</p>
        <p>''I don't think the mainstream was as enforced back then,'' said Joe Dougherty, an investment banker in New York who uses the screen name SFJoe on the Web.</p>
        <p>''There wasn't an orthodox church of Robert Parker then to either be a member of or try to reform.''</p>
        <p>Back in the 1970s and '80s, Mr. Parker himself might have qualified as a wine geek. Producers he championed, like Vega Sicilia from the Ribera del Duero in Spain, once a geek wine, are now some of the most in-demand around. In fact, a lot of fringe producers once prized by the iconoclasts are now universally admired, at a much higher price.</p>
        <p>''In some ways it's sort of bad for us old wine geeks,'' said Michael Wheeler, a partner in Polaner Selections, a distributor, who has been in the business for 30 years. ''We used to be able to get the Raveneau Chablis, Roumier and the Cotat Sancerre. Now, with the Internet and people talking about them, they became much harder to get.''</p>
        <p>The wine underground is driven by the search for great bottles at moderate prices, which means little-known, under-valued wines. That search has led to such out-of-the-way places as Cour Cheverny, Valtellina and Brda.</p>
        <p>''You've got to move on,'' said Mr. Wheeler, who spends much of his time prospecting for unusual wines. ''You have to fish where the fish are. Germany is one of the leading lands for wine geeks. Italy, there are still plenty of wines coming out.''</p>
        <p>Retail shops, especially newly opened ones, contribute to the thirst for new and different wines. Established shops can offer dozens of wines that have been rated highly by leading critics, but new shops need other distinguishing features.</p>
        <p>''All want to offer something that nobody else has, something different,'' Mr. Wheeler said. ''It's all contributing to creating this wine geek world.''</p>
        <p>In 20 years, the wine pantheon may look much different than it does now. Underground favorites of today like Jacques Puffeney of Arbois, Luneau-Papin of Muscadet and Frank Cornelissen in Sicily may be the mainstream favorites of tomorrow, impossible to get unless you have a place on the mailing list. Not likely, but it could happen. If it does, a new generation of wine iconoclasts will be on hand to boldly go where few wine lovers have gone before. And it suggests a better term than wine geeks: the vanguard.</p>
        <p>THE POUR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
