<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Routine Traffic Stop Leads To Gunshots and Questions</title>
    <meta content="06chase" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/nyregion/06chase.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852554"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E2DD1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Routine Traffic Stop Leads To Gunshots and Questions</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Routine Traffic Stop Leads to Gunshots and Questions</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD G. JONES</byline>
      <dateline>CLIFTON, N.J., June 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Kubasta has spent much of his life defying the notion that being permanently disabled means being permanently dependent on others.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kubasta, who has learning disabilities and whom family members compared to the title character in the movie ''Forrest Gump,'' has maintained a measure of self-sufficiency by holding a job at a Home Depot store and earning a New Jersey driver's license three years ago, at age 39.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Officials are investigating the shooting of a man with learning disabilities who was shot six times by the police after he ignored a routine traffic stop in New Jersey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John Kubasta has spent much of his life defying the notion that being permanently disabled means being permanently dependent on others.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kubasta, who has learning disabilities and whom family members compared to the title character in the movie ''Forrest Gump,'' has maintained a measure of self-sufficiency by holding a job at a Home Depot store and earning a New Jersey driver's license three years ago, at age 39.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, his family was questioning how a man who had lived independently for so long could get in such trouble with the police.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kubasta, 42, was shot six times by the police on Sunday after ignoring a routine traffic stop in Garfield, N.J., and leading officers on a chase for several miles that ended here at the intersection of Broad Street and Route 19. The shooting occurred, the police said, when Mr. Kubasta seemed to aim his car at officers after he pulled over.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kubasta was in critical condition on Tuesday at St. Joseph's Regional Medical Center in Paterson. Family members said doctors were trying to stabilize his condition before deciding whether to remove three remaining bullets -- one near his spine, one near his heart and one in an arm.</p>
        <p>''The only way I can describe him is like Forrest Gump,'' Eileen DeNobile, Mr. Kubasta's aunt, said in a telephone interview on Tuesday. ''We can't comprehend how this happened. How do you justify shooting into his car? We want answers.''</p>
        <p>Ms. DeNobile said that Mr. Kubasta probably became confused during the initial traffic stop in Garfield and did not follow the instructions of the police officers who stopped his car in Clifton because he did not grasp what was happening.</p>
        <p>''If he didn't stop, he didn't understand,'' Ms. DeNobile said, sobbing. ''He doesn't know how to do anything wrong. He knows love.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kubasta's sister, Michele Verity, said she believed the officers used excessive force. ''I'm absolutely outraged and disgusted and appalled,'' she said. ''This is just unfathomable to me.''</p>
        <p>The shooting is being investigated by the Passaic County prosecutor, James F. Avigliano, who promised a thorough review of the events leading to the shooting. ''We take our time with these things,'' Mr. Avigliano said. ''We have a serious obligation to the police and the public.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Avigliano said the events began around 10 p.m. on Sunday when officers in Garfield, where Mr. Kubasta lives with his parents, tried to stop his Toyota Corolla during a seat-belt check on Route 19.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kubasta, who the police said was not speeding, did not stop, and officers followed him into neighboring Clifton, where three patrol cars joined the pursuit, Mr. Avigliano said.</p>
        <p>He said that Mr. Kubasta stopped his car near Broad Street. As officers approached, Mr. Avigliano said, Mr. Kubasta's car lurched into reverse, in the officers' direction.</p>
        <p>''At that point, the Clifton police officers opened fire,'' Mr. Avigliano said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kubasta's car then traveled about 400 yards, crossing the median on Route 19 at one point and heading north in the southbound lanes before it stopped. Along the way, the car struck another vehicle, but no serious injuries were reported.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, a spray of broken glass sprinkled the roadway near a Route 19 traffic island, a twisted guardrail sat near a lopsided ''Yield'' sign, and a tattered piece of yellow caution tape wrapped a speed-limit sign like a bow.</p>
        <p>Ms. Verity said Mr. Kubasta told family members that he had been returning from a trip to the Jersey Shore town of Seaside Heights when he was stopped.</p>
        <p>''He likes the boardwalk,'' Ms. Verity said. ''He's very good-hearted. He wouldn't harm a fly.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kubasta drifted in and out of consciousness when family members visited on Tuesday, Ms. Verity said. Mr. Kubasta was in police custody while in the hospital.</p>
        <p>''He's in a lot of pain,'' Ms. Verity said. ''He doesn't understand what happened.''</p>
        <p>While they were growing up, Ms. Verity, 39, said that she often protected her big brother from the barbs of other youngsters. ''Children can be so cruel,'' she said. ''He was always in special ed.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kubasta did not let his disability deter him from trying to lead as independent a life as possible. When he decided to get his driver's license, Mr. Kubasta enlisted his 85-year-old grandmother, Eleanor Baird, to teach him to drive.</p>
        <p>''He failed the test to get his learner's permit the first couple of times,'' Ms. Verity said. ''He was so proud when he got it.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Verity said that her brother had a job at the Home Depot in Lodi, where his duties included collecting shopping carts from the parking lot.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Kubasta regained consciousness at the hospital, Ms. Verity said officials asked if he had a message for his family.</p>
        <p>''The first thing he thought of he said, 'Tell them to take care of my cat, Dusty,' '' Ms. Verity said. ''That's the kind of person my brother is.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
