<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paternity Case Is Dismissed, But Unsolved</title>
    <meta content="06about" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/nyregion/06about.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852590"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ABOUT NEW YORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/About New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/About New York/About New York - Dwyer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Child Custody and Support</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Custody and Support</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Human Resources Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E6DC1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="730" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paternity Case Is Dismissed, But Unsolved</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Case of the Deadbeat Dad Is Closed but Unsolved</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM DWYER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the official letter began with the inspiring words, ''You are hereby summoned,'' Mike Shaieb took a minute to digest the contents. Well, several minutes.</p>
        <p>A baby had been born in December. The mother had named Mr. Shaieb as the father. The city wanted him to pay his share. And it, meaning the city, had his Social Security number.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Officials haven’t explained how the wrong man was lined up as a deadbeat in a paternity case.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the official letter began with the inspiring words, ''You are hereby summoned,'' Mike Shaieb took a minute to digest the contents. Well, several minutes.</p>
        <p>A baby had been born in December. The mother had named Mr. Shaieb as the father. The city wanted him to pay his share. And it, meaning the city, had his Social Security number.</p>
        <p>A few readings later, Mr. Shaieb realized that he was due in court in less than two weeks, and that if he didn't show up, his absence would be regarded as deadbeat-ism, and he could be arrested. He also, the letter warned, might lose his licenses to drive, fish or hunt, or practice barbering, accounting or dental hygiene.</p>
        <p>A musical composer who works in film, television and theater, Mr. Shaieb does none of those things, other than drive and brush his own personal teeth. But he often travels from his apartment in Greenwich Village for projects. Lucky for him, he had been home to get the mail.</p>
        <p>He hired a lawyer named Susan Robbins to accompany him to Family Court at 60 Lafayette Street. They sat at the appointed hour in the waiting area. Then they sat some more. Ms. Robbins appeared to be the sole lawyer on hand. Court officials pointedly told Mr. Shaieb that he could handle the case himself, without a lawyer. He declined, even if he was the only one in the throng already shelling out.</p>
        <p>''You're cattle'd up,'' Mr. Shaieb said. ''The court people deal with this every day.''</p>
        <p>Finally, the case was called. Ms. Robbins asked the city attorney what the circumstances of the paternity had been: a one-night stand, or a longer relationship. No one was talking. ''It's not like criminal court; they don't have to disclose anything to us,'' Mr. Shaieb said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shaieb's lawyer said he had never met the woman in question. The magistrate said Ms. Robbins could discuss those particulars afterward with the city attorney.</p>
        <p>Ms. Robbins leaned over.</p>
        <p>''Do you mind if I tell them?'' Ms. Robbins asked.</p>
        <p>''Not at all,'' Mr. Shaieb replied. ''It's fine.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Robbins addressed the magistrate.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Shaieb is gay,'' she said. ''He's never had sex with a woman in his life.''</p>
        <p>As Mr. Shaieb later put it, ''In my entire 45 years of living, I have never seen a vagina in person.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps, but seeing is not the cause of pregnancy. Moreover, being gay did not necessarily get him off the hook, even though Mr. Shaieb's partner of nine years, Brent Lord, was waiting outside the courtroom.</p>
        <p>Somehow, the government had zeroed in on Michael Shaieb as the missing father of a child born on Dec. 6. It was a mystery to Mr. Shaieb and to Ms. Robbins. The mother, who had apparently provided the name to city officials when she applied for welfare, was not in court to further identify him. The case was adjourned for a month.</p>
        <p>Afterward, the city lawyer would not explain to Ms. Robbins how the law had fallen on this particular Michael Shaieb. ''She wouldn't tell me anything, except that the mother said the father was born in Jordan,'' Ms. Robbins said. She told Mr. Shaieb to get his birth certificate -- from Michigan, where he was born.</p>
        <p>MEANWHILE, as friends heard the story, they asked a few probing questions.</p>
        <p>As the partner, Mr. Lord, said: ''I started to feel eyes on me a little bit. People would look to me to see my reaction, if I believed it or was just reciting the party line.''</p>
        <p>He confessed: ''I did have the slightest split second -- there it was on paper, from the state, bullet points of 'whereas and what-forth.' Then we said, it's got to be a scam. Someone who got a credit card slip, or our address.''</p>
        <p>Last week, everyone returned to Family Court -- everyone except the mother. Mr. Shaieb produced his birth certificate, showing that he had been born nowhere near Jordan. The judge dismissed the case without the ado of a DNA test. The city's Human Resources Administration, which initiated the proceedings, did not explain yesterday how it had lined up the wrong man as a deadbeat.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Shaieb expects his legal tab to run to $3,000, money spent wisely, if not well.</p>
        <p>''It's like I had a drunken night and this happened,'' Mr. Shaieb said. ''Except it didn't.''</p>
        <p>ABOUT NEW YORK E-mail: dwyer@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: dwyer@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
