<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Farnsworth Sees No Need to Clear the Air With Clemens</title>
    <meta content="06pins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852612"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE2DC1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Farnsworth Sees No Need to Clear the Air With Clemens</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, June 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kyle Farnsworth first met Roger Clemens at one of the lowest points of his career. Farnsworth, then the closer for the Atlanta Braves, had blown the save in the final game of a division series against Clemens's Houston Astros in 2005.</p>
        <p>''They beat us in the playoffs, and I saw him in the tunnel there and wished him luck,'' Farnsworth said. ''I have nothing against him at all.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kyle Farnsworth first met Roger Clemens at one of the lowest points of his career. Farnsworth, then the closer for the Atlanta Braves, had blown the save in the final game of a division series against Clemens's Houston Astros in 2005.</p>
        <p>''They beat us in the playoffs, and I saw him in the tunnel there and wished him luck,'' Farnsworth said. ''I have nothing against him at all.''</p>
        <p>Yet Farnsworth, the Yankees' setup man, was cast in the role of Clemens critic when the Yankees came here last month. Farnsworth, who rarely has much to say, told a Chicago radio station that Clemens's agreement with the Yankees, which allows him to leave the team on days he is not pitching, might cause tension. ''To be a part of the team, you have to be there with the team,'' Farnsworth said.</p>
        <p>Three weeks later, with Clemens preparing to join the Yankees, Farnsworth said people took his words out of context. In the same interview, he said he spoke positively about Clemens and acknowledged his accomplishments.</p>
        <p>''I never said I did have a problem with it, personally,'' Farnsworth said. ''I just said I thought everyone should be here with the team. That's the only thing I said. No one listened to the whole thing; they just took what they wanted out of it. I said I respect him as a person and as a professional baseball player. He's here to help the team. It's not like I bashed the guy.''</p>
        <p>When they become teammates, Farnsworth said, he will not approach Clemens to clear the air.</p>
        <p>''If he asks me what was going on, I'll tell him,'' Farnsworth said. ''But we're all professionals and we know how to go out and get the job done. That's the only thing we have to worry about.''</p>
        <p>Clemens, who pushed back his first Yankees start because of a right groin injury, will throw in the bullpen in Tampa, Fla., on Wednesday. If he completes the session with no discomfort, he will join the Yankees and start on Saturday against Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>Though Clemens will be monitored by the Yankees' staff, unlike in his last bullpen session in Houston, the decision to start will be left to him.</p>
        <p>''It's going to depend on how his bullpen goes,'' Manager Joe Torre said. ''We're ready when he is, no question, if he feels physically able. You've got to remember, he's the one who volunteered the fact that he was feeling something in his groin. So if he says he's O.K., you've got to believe it.''</p>
        <p>BASAK AND HENN PROMOTED -- It was around midnight when the Class AAA Scranton/Wilkes-Barre Yankees arrived at their hotel in Buffalo after Monday's game. As the players were getting their room keys, a staffer told Chris Basak: ''You're not going to need this. Go talk to Miley.''</p>
        <p>Dave Miley, the team's manager, told Basak he was going to the major leagues, a call Basak has waited eight years to get. Basak, 28, spent parts of the last five seasons with the Mets' Class AAA team.</p>
        <p>''Definitely, your dream is to make it to the big leagues, and not to have that happen, it was frustrating,'' said Basak, who can play several infield and outfield positions. ''But this right here makes it all worth it.''</p>
        <p>The call to join the Yankees in Chicago was doubly sweet for Basak, who grew up in nearby Joliet and attended the University of Illinois. He called his mother after speaking with Miley and left at least 15 tickets for friends and family for Tuesday's game.</p>
        <p>''We liked him in spring training,'' Joe Torre said. ''He was one of the last invites, and he sort of caught our attention.''</p>
        <p>Basak hit .311 in spring training and .265 in 52 games for Scranton. Torre said the Yankees promoted him for his versatility; Basak can play the corner outfield spots and all four infield positions.</p>
        <p>Torre said he wanted to give a day off, or at least a day as the designated hitter, to Alex Rodriguez and Derek Jeter. Having a player like Basak will help him do that. ''Jeter's beat up pretty good,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>The left-hander Sean Henn was also promoted to give the Yankees a long reliever after they taxed their bullpen Monday. Starter Matt DeSalvo and outfielder Kevin Thompson were optioned to Scranton.</p>
        <p>YANKEES SIGN HERNÁNDEZ -- The Yankees signed the veteran starter Runelvys Hernández and put him in the rotation at Class AAA Scranton. In seven starts this season for Boston's Class AAA team, Hernández was 0-3 with a 3.06 earned run average. He was 25-33 as a starter for the Kansas City Royals from 2002 to 2006.</p>
        <p>The Yankees have also promoted last year's No. 1 draft pick, starter Ian Kennedy, to Class AA Trenton from Class A Tampa. Kennedy dominated the Florida State League, leading the league in E.R.A. (1.29) while going 6-1.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
