<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Constant Comfort of an Old Friend</title>
    <meta content="06rest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/dining/reviews/06rest.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852453"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Gramercy Tavern</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Meyer, Danny</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E0D61130F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1268" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Constant Comfort of an Old Friend</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Constant Comfort of an Old Friend</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank Bruni</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE are restaurants with more shimmer, and there are certainly restaurants with more spark. There are restaurants that take bigger chances and stake bolder claims to your attention.</p>
        <p>But is there a restaurant in this city more beloved than Gramercy Tavern? For nearly 13 years it has held a place in the hearts of New Yorkers and visitors to Manhattan that's arguably unrivaled. And it has proven that at the end of the day, both literally and figuratively, what most diners want isn't nerve-jangling sensation or cutting-edge surprise. It's a kind of unstrained graciousness and unlabored sophistication that Gramercy Tavern has pretty much defined.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gramercy Tavern is not an exciting restaurant, but it’s a soothing, warm, rewarding one that’s as understandably beloved as any in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE are restaurants with more shimmer, and there are certainly restaurants with more spark. There are restaurants that take bigger chances and stake bolder claims to your attention.</p>
        <p>But is there a restaurant in this city more beloved than Gramercy Tavern? For nearly 13 years it has held a place in the hearts of New Yorkers and visitors to Manhattan that's arguably unrivaled. And it has proven that at the end of the day, both literally and figuratively, what most diners want isn't nerve-jangling sensation or cutting-edge surprise. It's a kind of unstrained graciousness and unlabored sophistication that Gramercy Tavern has pretty much defined.</p>
        <p>Diners found that here in the past and can find it here again now, though there was an interval when all wasn't well, when Gramercy seemed to be coasting, or rather drifting, its service erratic, its cooking off key.</p>
        <p>Even before the chef Tom Colicchio formally left the restaurant last August, it wasn't getting the lion's share of his attention: I had a few forgettable dinners here between mid-2004 and early 2006. Late last year, shortly after Michael Anthony took charge of the kitchen, I had a clumsy, laughable one.</p>
        <p>The next morning one of my guests sent me an e-mail message: ''I have to ask you -- beg you, really -- to stop the abomination that is Gramercy Tavern. You have no higher journalistic calling.''</p>
        <p>She was right about that meal, wrong about my charge. What I needed to do was keep a watchful but hopeful eye on a restaurant that had earned the benefit of the doubt, and give Mr. Anthony some time.</p>
        <p>He and Gramercy's principal owner, Danny Meyer, have clearly been busy. Over the last five months, they have restored a needed discipline to the restaurant, which relies less on swagger than on finesse and draws its strength from ingredients that are carefully selected and sharply reflective of the season. Mr. Anthony came to Gramercy from the Blue Hill restaurants in Manhattan and Westchester County, and the Blue Hill farm-to-table ethos -- a more finicky application of values Gramercy already celebrated -- has come with him, embodied in a new vegetarian tasting menu.</p>
        <p>For the most part he cooks with the gentleness of Dan Barber, the chef at Blue Hill, rather than the gusto of Mr. Colicchio. Whether the centerpiece of a dish was fish, bird or mammal, whether it was roasted, poached or smoked, it took as supple a form as possible, and it seldom receded behind grandstanding effects.</p>
        <p>Pale slices of sturgeon fillet were as silky as rose petals, and the sauce on which these petals fell -- with saffron, lemon, fennel and pickled mustard seeds -- added bite to the dish without chomping down on it.</p>
        <p>By slow-roasting halibut and basting it with brown butter, the kitchen teased out all the richness and moistness halibut can muster.</p>
        <p>It produced boneless rack of veal as tender as could be and underscored its luxuriousness with morels braised in a sherry-like savagnin from the Jura and sauced with veal jus and a whisper of whipped cream. Thin slices of raw asparagus gave the dish some crunch and an even firmer tether to the season.</p>
        <p>Almost everything I had in my recent visits was exquisitely cooked. I say almost because the lobster in a salad with pickled ginger and pistachio vinaigrette was a stringy disappointment. The smoking of lobster in an entree with a celery root purée only obscured its sweetness.</p>
        <p>Maybe the kitchen should just stick with crab, whose sweetness came through clearly in the best appetizer, an ''open ravioli.'' House-made pasta cradled and defined strands of snow crab while a profusion of herbs, including parsley and dill, contributed color and nuance. Pale orange mussels, removed from their shells, were arrayed like a corona around everything else.</p>
        <p>Mr. Anthony's menus for both the modestly elegant dining rooms and the more casual tables around the bar are new and different, but they respect the longstanding Gramercy spirit. They champion the ''new American'' style of cobbled-together influences in the service of relatively straightforward dishes. And they seem designed to appeal to a broad base, balancing a smoked trout appetizer with a tuna and beet tartare, tempering venison in two enormously appealing guises (loin and sausage) with pork two excellent ways (roasted rack and braised belly).</p>
        <p>They steer clear of anything too challenging, and if tameness is a consequence, so be it. Gramercy has never been a destination for the most adventurous or jaded gourmands.</p>
        <p>Its current roster of desserts, now under the stewardship of the pastry chef Nancy Olson, may not be its strongest ever, but there are fine choices. Chief among them is a warm chocolate bread pudding that stands in, blessedly, for the molten chocolate cake on too many other menus and does that stalwart's gooey business more arrestingly.</p>
        <p>Ms. Olson deftly tweaks the familiar, producing a quark cheesecake with fruity sidekicks -- candied kumquat, a blood orange sorbet -- more exotic than the usual suspects.</p>
        <p>The thoughtfully assembled wine list spans many styles and budgets. The service is back on track, with its trademark blend of coddling and unpretentiousness, a mix that Gramercy nailed well before other restaurants and that explains a lot about diners' loyalty to the restaurant. They find comfort in rooms with well-spaced tables and one rustic touch for every two elegant flourishes. Gramercy Tavern is a homey retort to the slickness of some fine-dining peers, and minor changes to lighting and art have made it look fresher, less where your grandmother goes after needlepoint class and more where your aunt goes after Italian for the Umbria-bound.</p>
        <p>It doesn't scale peaks as high as those at Eleven Madison Park, currently the most exciting restaurant in Mr. Meyer's collection. But like a solid marriage rather than a heady love affair, it has stood the test of time, righting itself when it starts to go wrong, knowing that what's at stake are a great many warm memories, some yet to be made.</p>
        <p>Gramercy Tavern  *** [Rating: Three Star]  42 East 20th Street; (212) 477-0777, gramercytavern.com.</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE A homey series of rooms that temper elegance with rustic touches and leave real space between tables.  SOUND LEVEL Somewhat loud in front; moderate in back.  RECOMMENDED DISHES Farro with carrots and pine nuts; open crab ravioli; scallop crudo; calamari and carrot salad; smoked mackerel with cilantro; bacon-wrapped trout; sturgeon; halibut; veal with morels; pork two ways; chocolate bread pudding; quark cheesecake.  WINE LIST Extensive, international and well varied in terms of style and price.  PRICE RANGE In the casual ''tavern'' up front, lunch and dinner appetizers, $9 to $12. Entrees, $16 to $22. Desserts, $8. In the dining rooms, lunch appetizers, $11 to $16. Entrees, $21 to $25. Desserts, $11. Tasting menus, $36 to $55. Dinner prix fixe of three courses, including dessert, $76. Tasting menus, $82 to $98.  HOURS For tavern, noon to 11 p.m. Sunday through Thursday and to midnight Friday and Saturday. For dining rooms, lunch from noon to 2 p.m. Monday through Friday and dinner from 5:30 to 10 p.m. Sunday through Thursday and to 11 p.m. Friday and Saturday.  RESERVATIONS Not accepted for tavern. For prime times in dining rooms, call as many as 28 days in advance.  CREDIT CARDS All major cards.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS Ramp at door; accessible restrooms.  WHAT THE STARS MEAN Ratings range from zero to four stars and reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.  PAST REVIEWS from The Times, with additional capsule reviews by Times critics: nytimes.com/dining</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
