<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Looking Beyond L. L. Bean</title>
    <meta content="06maine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/realestate/commercial/06maine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852490"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SQUARE FEET"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maine/Freeport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Freeport (Me)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">LL Bean Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E0DF1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1023" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Looking Beyond L. L. Bean</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Looking Beyond L. L. Bean</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANA SIWOLOP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siwolop, Sana</byline>
      <dateline>FREEPORT, Me.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Downtown Freeport hardly looks like a place that needs to reinvent itself. Perhaps best known as the home of L. L. Bean's three large retail outposts, it also offers luxury names like Burberry, Cole Haan and Polo Ralph Lauren and dozens of well-appointed outlets.</p>
        <p>With its quaint old-New England storefronts and strict design codes (even the local drive-through McDonald's here is tucked into an old colonial home), the town attracts some 3.5 million visitors a year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Maine, the town of Freeport recently approved the development of a $45 million “lifestyle center,” to stay ahead of development in other areas of the state.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Downtown Freeport hardly looks like a place that needs to reinvent itself. Perhaps best known as the home of L. L. Bean's three large retail outposts, it also offers luxury names like Burberry, Cole Haan and Polo Ralph Lauren and dozens of well-appointed outlets.</p>
        <p>With its quaint old-New England storefronts and strict design codes (even the local drive-through McDonald's here is tucked into an old colonial home), the town attracts some 3.5 million visitors a year.</p>
        <p>Still, retail development has been growing rapidly elsewhere in Maine, notably in nearby Portland and in Kittery, an hour away. At the same time, other outdoor outfitters, like Cabela's of Sidney, Neb., have been moving into New England.</p>
        <p>In an effort to stay ahead of the competition, town officials recently approved the development of a $45 million open-air pedestrian-friendly ''lifestyle center,'' basically a shopping center without walls, to be built on a 3.6-acre site owned by L. L. Bean.</p>
        <p>''We want to revitalize Freeport,'' said Dale C. Olmstead Jr., the town manager. ''We want to reinvent ourselves.''</p>
        <p>Spearheading the center is Berenson Associates, a Boston-based shopping center developer. Until this spring, the site was home to L. L. Bean's outlet store, a parking lot and the long-vacant historic Mallet office building. Berenson plans to keep the Mallet Building, but the old outlet center is already being demolished.</p>
        <p>Alfred R. Yebba, Berenson's chief operating officer and the development director for the new center, said one goal was to provide the kind of modern single-floor retail space that is needed to lure larger retailers and restaurants to Freeport. Store space here now tends to run from 2,000 to 5,000 square feet and is often cloistered away in either old multistory buildings or colonial-style homes.</p>
        <p>Berenson, he said, is in the final stages of negotiations with some half-dozen nationally recognized retailers that sell clothing, footwear and accessories.</p>
        <p>By many accounts, downtown Freeport is already an area where shoppers almost always walk, rather than drive, to nearby stores. ''We think a lifestyle center already exists here in Freeport -- we're just trying to build a new wing,'' said Sean K. Selby, an architect at Arrowstreet, a design and planning company in Somerville, Mass., which is working with Berenson.</p>
        <p>The plans call for the center to have a retail plaza with three large two-story buildings surrounding two smaller buildings appropriate for boutiques and kiosks. It would have an old-style clock tower and other features to give it a traditional New England look.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yebba said one large retail building would have about 13,000 square feet of restaurant space, possibly including a sports or entertainment bar, while a 60,000-square-foot building along Depot Street would offer space in the range of 10,000 to 20,000 square feet, possibly accommodating five large tenants.</p>
        <p>He added that all of the new retail tenants would be required to be open from 10 in the morning until 10 at night, and restaurant tenants, when possible, would have similar 12-hour shifts. Now, most of Freeport shuts down by 8 p.m. in the summer and 6 p.m. in the winter. ''We'd like to bring a little edge to town,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Freeport officials say the town has been adding visitor attractions lately, like Maine Distilleries, purveyors of Cold River vodka, which opened on Route 1 about a mile south of downtown in November 2005 and pulled in almost 6,000 tour visitors during its first year.</p>
        <p>They would also like to see large conference facilities built, as well as more spaces for artists and performers, and perhaps even a movie theater. ''We have over 800 hotel rooms here now -- capacity has more than doubled in 10 years -- but now we want to round ourselves out as a destination,'' said Stephanie B. Slocum, executive director of the Freeport Economic Development Corporation.</p>
        <p>Most visitors to Freeport start out at L. L. Bean's stores: a 160,000-square-foot flagship store, a large hunting and fishing store and, as of May 2006, a 16,500-square-foot bike, boat and ski store.</p>
        <p>Gregory W. Boulos, a broker and partner at CB Richard Ellis/the Boulos Company in Portland, said that because of the way Bean's stores are positioned, most shoppers move southward along Main Street or eastward along Bow Street when they leave the stores. As a result, he said, drawing businesses north of the stores or off Bow Street can present a challenge.</p>
        <p>Town officials hope that Freeport Village Station will be a draw eastward, to streets where retailers have previously struggled. Pedestrians would be able to enter the center from four different entrances, including an arched gateway off Main Street.</p>
        <p>Shoppers who come by car would enter on either Mill or Depot Street, to park in a two-level garage. The garage, a first for Freeport, would be large enough to hold 550 cars.</p>
        <p>Lately, L. L. Bean has also been trying to enhance its drawing power. It is in the process of almost doubling the size of its hunting and fishing offerings by adding space at the back of its Main Street flagship store.</p>
        <p>Once that store is moved, the company plans to install its outlet store, which is now in temporary quarters on Route 1, into the building that used to house the hunting and fishing store.</p>
        <p>Another plan is to rebuild a large park, along with a parking lot, to create a giant product-testing area where shoppers could try out mountain bikes, kayaks and skis and see product demonstrations.</p>
        <p>The quickening pace of development oriented toward leisure travel has had fallout elsewhere in town.</p>
        <p>This spring, town officials formally approved the conversion of a largely residential area east of the railroad tracks around Bow and South Streets to a mixed-use district. The aim is to foster higher-density housing development and encourage service businesses like dry-cleaning and video stores to move to the center of town.</p>
        <p>''There was an overwhelming feeling here in the 1990s that people had lost their village and services'' at a time that ''the traditional village gave way to a shopping village,'' said Donna Larson, the town planner. ''The goal now is to create an opportunity for an alternate town center to emerge.''</p>
        <p>SQUARE FEET</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
