<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>British Grocer Set to Tackle U.S. Market</title>
    <meta content="06tesco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/business/worldbusiness/06tesco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852551"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Phoenix (Ariz)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Las Vegas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">San Diego (Calif)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tesco Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Craig S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada/Las Vegas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona/Phoenix</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/San Diego</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Tesco Plc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DD1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1069" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>British Grocer Set to Tackle U.S. Market</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">British Grocer Set to Dip Toe in U.S. Market</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG S. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Craig S</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Britain's largest retailer Tesco will enter United States market by opening Fresh and Easy neighborhood stores, selling mostly food in Los Angeles, Phoenix, Las Vegas and San Diego; plans to take cautious approach to avoid repeating mistakes other foreign retailers have made by trying to grow too quickly; analysts say Tesco will succeed due to amount of research and preparation that has been done; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Britain's largest retailer, Tesco, is finally ready for its American debut.</p>
        <p>It has sent executives to board with American families, watching what they eat and where they shop. The scouts have built a clandestine store inside a California warehouse to test the reactions of selected people, telling any busybodies who inquired that it was a movie set. They have run computer models and pored over economic data and mapped demographic trends.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tesco is treading lightly to avoid the pitfalls that have tripped up other foreign retailers in the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Britain's largest retailer, Tesco, is finally ready for its American debut.</p>
        <p>It has sent executives to board with American families, watching what they eat and where they shop. The scouts have built a clandestine store inside a California warehouse to test the reactions of selected people, telling any busybodies who inquired that it was a movie set. They have run computer models and pored over economic data and mapped demographic trends.</p>
        <p>And, of course, they have sized up the competition.</p>
        <p>''We've been looking at the U.S. for 20 years,'' said Greg Sage, a spokesman at the company's headquarters in Cheshunt, England.</p>
        <p>This year, the company will begin showing the results: neighborhood convenience stores called Fresh and Easy, selling mostly food, in Los Angeles, Phoenix, Las Vegas and San Diego.</p>
        <p>It may sound like a modest parry for a company known for bold thrusts, but Tesco is treading lightly where other big British retailers have fallen before.</p>
        <p>For example, the supermarket chain J Sainsbury left the American market in 2004, and the venerable dry goods retailer Marks &amp; Spencer sold Brooks Brothers in 2001 for less than a third what it paid 13 years earlier.</p>
        <p>Other retailers have found the United States perilous, too. The Dutch supermarket giant Royal Ahold has faced a series of crises, from accounting irregularities to restive unions, at its American operations.</p>
        <p>The Tesco strategy can be considered an end run around the world's other giant retailers, Wal-Mart and Carrefour, which have recently been withdrawing from difficult markets after a race to plant flags in as many countries as possible.</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart's growth at its superstores has faded while Carrefour is pulling back to concentrate on thinning margins in France, its home market. Tesco, meanwhile, is at the top of its game in Britain, where its business is generating plenty of cash for investment overseas. Tesco knows that confronting Wal-Mart head-on in Wal-Mart's home market would be suicidal. By slipping in through a neglected niche, Tesco hopes to build a business where even Carrefour fears to tread.</p>
        <p>''One of the dangers for any company producing a lot of cash flow from their home market is that they invest poorly overseas,'' said Alastair Johnston, a retail analyst at JPMorgan. ''That has not been the case for Tesco as it has been for Carrefour and Wal-Mart.''</p>
        <p>Tesco hopes to avoid the pitfalls that have tripped up other foreign retailers in the United States by starting small and growing organically rather than entering the market with a splashy acquisition. Still, it will spend $500 million on the new stores this year, and analysts predict that figure will grow to nearly $1 billion annually within two or three years.</p>
        <p>''They are one of the few food-retailing expansion success stories internationally,'' said Tim Attenborough, an analyst at Exane BNP Paribas.</p>
        <p>The company has long been a household name in Britain, and since the mid-1990s has been expanding into markets overseas. It now operates in a dozen countries, including China, Turkey and Poland. It has four basic store formats, from corner convenience stores to hypermarkets à la Wal-Mart.</p>
        <p>Fresh and Easy will be based on the company's Tesco Express or Metro stores in Britain, though with a local twist that Tesco prides itself on using in international markets.</p>
        <p>The company will not yet say what that twist will be in the United States, though the stores will be geared toward southwestern American sensibilities, offering a ''fresh&amp;easy'' line of branded products free of trans fats, artificial colors or artificial flavors.</p>
        <p>''They'll be neighborhood markets of 10 to 15,000 square feet, offering fresh, nutritious, affordable food close to where people live,'' Mr. Sage said. The stores, a fifth the size of an average American supermarket, will offer an expanded range of chilled, rather than frozen or hot, ready-to-eat foods, a market that is much more developed in Britain than the United States.</p>
        <p>Tesco is building an 800,000-square-foot distribution center (the size of 14 football fields) on a former Air Force base near Riverside, Calif., and has moved 150 employees to its regional headquarters in El Segundo, Calif. The team is led by Tim Mason, a 25-year company veteran and possible successor to the chief executive of Tesco, Terry Leahy. It is the first time Tesco has sent a main board member to develop a new market overseas.</p>
        <p>Tesco has begun recruiting local employees, hoping to avoid California's tough unions -- for that could be a real vulnerability. Already, the powerful United Food and Commercial Workers International Union has begun a low-key campaign to stop Tesco stores from getting liquor licenses in Arizona.</p>
        <p>But Tesco is ducking the most serious barrier -- competition by other big food retailers -- by entering at an unexpected point in the market.</p>
        <p>''They are not going head-to-head with Wal-Mart or with the big supermarket operators,'' Mr. Attenborough said. ''They have seen a niche opportunity in the market on the West Coast where they think they can make some serious money.''</p>
        <p>Its direct competition, analysts say, include Trader Joe's and Famima minimarkets, both also foreign-owned, by Germans and Japanese, respectively. But Tesco is expected to move faster than either of those chains. There are only about a dozen Famima stores in California, and Trader Joe's, which has been around for many years, has about 220 stores so far, many in California. Analysts expect Tesco to pass that number within three or four years.</p>
        <p>''This is their best-researched project ever,'' said Mr. Attenborough, the Exane BNP Paribas analyst, adding that the company is hoping for a 15 percent return on its investment. That would allow the American operation to finance further expansion on its own.</p>
        <p>Tesco has said that it expects its United States operation to break even by the end of 2009. ''I think this business can have a turnover of more than $4 billion in five years,'' Mr. Attenborough said.</p>
        <p>The investment world has cheered Tesco's move. Berkshire Hathaway, controlled by Warren E. Buffett, took a 2 percent stake in the company after it announced its American expansion plans.</p>
        <p>And the stock has been steadily rising, closing Tuesday in London at 450 pence ($8.94), though that is slightly below its peak on May 14 of 472.25.</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart, meanwhile, has been put on notice. As Tesco learns more about the American market, JPMorgan noted, ''We would not be surprised if it looks to add larger supermarket formats, or even hypermarkets.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
