<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Traditional Korean Marriage Meets Match on the Internet</title>
    <meta content="06korea" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/world/asia/06korea.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852518"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sang-Hun, Choe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">South Korea</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE1DE1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="721" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Traditional Korean Marriage Meets Match on the Internet</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Traditional Korean Marriage Meets Match on the Internet</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHOE SANG-HUN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sang-Hun, Choe</byline>
      <dateline>SEOUL, South Korea, June 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Growing number of services in South Korea merge age-old Korean matchmaking tradition with vibrant South Korean Internet culture; more than 1,000 dating agencies operate in South Korea; with South Korean birth rate among lowest in world, demographers are casting friendlier looks on these agencies, which are banned from advertising on television (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sitting in his office crammed with files and boxes, Lee Woong-jin, a 42-year-old entrepreneur, talks enthusiastically about his latest moneymaking plan: merging the age-old Korean matchmaking tradition with the vibrant South Korean Internet culture.</p>
        <p>His company -- which allows subscribers to search for mates online -- is one of a growing number of matchmaking services in South Korea, where families still arrange many marriages. Many of the services, like Mr. Lee's company, rely heavily on the Internet and bill themselves as being more scientific than one-person shops that use social connections to make matches.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A growing number of matchmaking services in South Korea, where families still arrange many marriages, rely heavily on the Internet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sitting in his office crammed with files and boxes, Lee Woong-jin, a 42-year-old entrepreneur, talks enthusiastically about his latest moneymaking plan: merging the age-old Korean matchmaking tradition with the vibrant South Korean Internet culture.</p>
        <p>His company -- which allows subscribers to search for mates online -- is one of a growing number of matchmaking services in South Korea, where families still arrange many marriages. Many of the services, like Mr. Lee's company, rely heavily on the Internet and bill themselves as being more scientific than one-person shops that use social connections to make matches.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Lee's customers, Kim Su-jong, a 29-year-old pharmacist, recently listed more than 330 pieces of information about herself -- including her height, weight, blood type, drinking and smoking habits and monthly pay. And, in a twist that shows how much weight the society places on the standing of a spouse's family, she also listed the jobs and academic credentials of everyone in her immediate family.</p>
        <p>Within seconds, the computer program produced a marriage consulting report advising her that it would be most realistic for her to get married next year to a 33-year-old dentist or herbal doctor between 5 feet 7 inches tall and 5 feet 8 inches. If she believes in horoscopes, the computer said, August would be the best month to marry, but March and September should be avoided. That information cost her $21.</p>
        <p>For an extra charge the computer will scan a pool of 25,000 clients and send her the names of one or two men whose profiles appear to make them suitable partners.</p>
        <p>''We built our system by analyzing the marrying patterns of 10,000 couples married through our agency,'' said Mr. Lee, the chief executive of Sunoo. ''Our site is not a place for Cinderellas -- people with illusions of finding a prince or princess. Our emphasis is on being scientific and practical.''</p>
        <p>More than 1,000 dating agencies operate in South Korea. They include one-person operations run, typically, by middle-aged women who seek top graduates of prestigious universities and single doctors and lawyers and introduce them to rich families with eligible sons and daughters, and the corporations like Sunoo.</p>
        <p>With the South Korean birth rate among the lowest in the world, demographers are casting friendlier looks on these agencies, which are banned from advertising on television.</p>
        <p>''Our low birth rate is more than a crisis, and it's because fewer people get married,'' said Cho Nam-hoon, director of the government-funded Center for Low Fertility and Aging Studies. ''The government should encourage the matchmaking industry. Perhaps it should start its own matchmaking service.''</p>
        <p>Marriage is becoming optional, not a rite of passage, for South Koreans, with more men insecure about their jobs, and more women favoring work outside the home over rearing children. In 2005, 51 percent of South Koreans in their 20s and 30s were unmarried, five percentage points higher than in 2000.</p>
        <p>In traditional Korea, where Confucian mores frowned on the mingling of the sexes, young people were brought together by matchmakers, usually old women in their villages.</p>
        <p>Even now, marriage is widely viewed as a contract between two families, and parents often take charge. They check a candidate's looks, education, income and horoscope. On weekends, young men and women might face each other awkwardly in a hotel restaurant after being dragged there by their parents for a matchmaking session.</p>
        <p>''More than half our 10,000 clients were brought to us by their parents,'' said Hong Kyung-hee of the Daks Club agency who has helped 100 couples tie the knot. ''South Korea remains very conservative when it comes to marriage.''</p>
        <p>For parents concerned with ''saving face,'' an agency can take care of the awkward business of checking backgrounds and, perhaps, rejecting a candidate introduced by friends.</p>
        <p>For singles, using the agencies can reduce the risks of a blind date by screening potential suitors.</p>
        <p>Leading companies like LG Electronics and Samsung ask agencies to organize group blind dates as a benefit for single employees. And major banks vie for rich private customers by offering free matchmaking for their children.</p>
        <p>''We still find it hard to approach members of the opposite sex,'' said Cha Hyun-seok, 34, an employee at LG Chemicals, who attended a recent matchmaking party organized by a dating agency. ''There must be a go-between. So this is a useful service for me.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
