<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To an Equine Athlete Dying Young</title>
    <meta content="06sand" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/arts/television/06sand.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852467"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Barbaro (Race Horse)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">HBO Sports</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Schreiber, Liev</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Matz, Michael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E7DF1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="578" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To an Equine Athlete Dying Young</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">To an Equine Athlete Dying Young</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Caution: Tears will flow from watching ''Barbaro,'' the HBO Sports documentary that tells the life story of a horse Hemingway would have loved, one who exhibited grace under great pressure. Like the other innocent animals we love, horses ''trust us, live alongside us, honoring our many commands,'' the narrator, Liev Schreiber, says. ''And when we ask them to -- they run.''</p>
        <p>They run because they are bred to, and when they win the Kentucky Derby by 6 1/2 lengths, as Barbaro did last year, they become stars for at least a day in May. Two weeks later, after he shattered his right hind leg just yards out of the starting gate at the Preakness Stakes, Barbaro became a tragic hero whose injury reports were given like presidential health updates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Caution: Tears will flow from watching “Barbaro,” the HBO Sports documentary that tells the life story of a horse Hemingway would have loved, one who exhibited grace under great pressure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Caution: Tears will flow from watching ''Barbaro,'' the HBO Sports documentary that tells the life story of a horse Hemingway would have loved, one who exhibited grace under great pressure. Like the other innocent animals we love, horses ''trust us, live alongside us, honoring our many commands,'' the narrator, Liev Schreiber, says. ''And when we ask them to -- they run.''</p>
        <p>They run because they are bred to, and when they win the Kentucky Derby by 6 1/2 lengths, as Barbaro did last year, they become stars for at least a day in May. Two weeks later, after he shattered his right hind leg just yards out of the starting gate at the Preakness Stakes, Barbaro became a tragic hero whose injury reports were given like presidential health updates.</p>
        <p>''Barbaro'' is a hero's journey told with respect, through his baby pictures (what a cute foal!), naming (for one of six foxhounds in a painting) and competitiveness. He was undefeated when he broke down and dealt with a succession of surgeries with apparent equanimity.</p>
        <p>''He was pretty close to almost a perfect orthopedic patient,'' says Dean Richardson, his surgeon, whose assessment of the horse's personal qualities, like those expressed by others in the film, sound quite human.</p>
        <p>The hero was adored by his wealthy owners, Roy and Gretchen Jackson; his trainer, Michael Matz (himself a hero for saving three children from the wreckage of a jet); sixth graders who wrote and illustrated a children's book about him; and fans who posted signs with messages like ''Believe in Miracles'' on the gates around the animal hospital at the New Bolton Center at the University of Pennsylvania, where Barbaro lived out his final months. Unable to withstand the pain from the complications of surgery, he was euthanized on Jan. 29.</p>
        <p>The documentary is restrained as it shifts from the derby victory to his breakdown at the Preakness. The producer, Margaret Grossi, moves intelligently from NBC's post-race footage to still shots showing the horror on the faces of Barbaro's human family and fans who did not know if the horse would be euthanized within minutes or saved for a life as a stud.</p>
        <p>Video shot inside the hospital shows Barbaro inside his stall, eating carrots and schmoozing with the Jacksons, but never in pain. He is seen grazing and rolling around on the grass as if he had never been hurt. And he is observed in a body sling, dramatically lowered into a post-op pool where he wouldn't hurt himself when he thrashed when his anesthesia wore off.</p>
        <p>Ms. Grossi and the documentary's writer, Frank Deford, do not delve into why so few horses get Barbaro-level care when they break down. They focus on Barbaro and the Jacksons, who had the money for his care but knew it would have been easier to euthanize him and collect on their insurance. They chose a course that extended the lovefest, bonded Barbaro to his fans and cemented his appeal as a documentary subject.</p>
        <p>''If falling in love with a horse is painful at times,'' Ms. Jackson says, offering a rationale for equating a race horse, as sportswriters do, with two-legged athletes, ''it's worth every moment of pain to love deeply.''</p>
        <p>Barbaro  HBO, tonight at 10, Eastern and Pacific times; 9, Central time.</p>
        <p>Ross Greenburg and Rick Bernstein, executive producers; Margaret Grossi, producer; Mary Carillo, story editor; written by Frank Deford; original music composed by Brian Keane; narrated by Liev Schreiber.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
