<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Sports, Unleashing The Dogs That Abhor</title>
    <meta content="06roberts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/sports/football/06roberts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852610"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Selena Roberts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cruelty to Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cruelty to Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Vick, Michael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E2DC1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Sports, Unleashing The Dogs That Abhor</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Unleashing the Dogs That Abhor</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The N.F.L. scene has become the puppy mill for pit-bull lore.</p>
        <p>As the trendiest of bad-boy accessories, the pit bull is the new gun for some players. As a replacement for tired soldier analogies, players are turning to the most mythologized of muscle dogs to define their masculinity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the trendiest of bad-boy accessories, the pit bull is the new gun for some N.F.L. players.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The N.F.L. scene has become the puppy mill for pit-bull lore.</p>
        <p>As the trendiest of bad-boy accessories, the pit bull is the new gun for some players. As a replacement for tired soldier analogies, players are turning to the most mythologized of muscle dogs to define their masculinity.</p>
        <p>''The pit bull is seen as the epitome of the athlete in the animal kingdom,'' said Rhonda Evans, a professor of criminal justice at the University of Louisiana-Lafayette, who has written extensively on dog fighting. ''They fight to the death. None of them would turn away from the fight unless the owner calls it. Turning away is considered the response of a cur, a coward. The definition of stopping is a cur. They fight until the owner calls the fight or they die.''</p>
        <p>It does not take a Pavlovian leap to see why football players who push themselves beyond pain thresholds until the whistle blows, who play broken and bloodied until discarded, would identify with the vision of a relentless icon.</p>
        <p>Brutality has never left the N.F.L. queasy before. The league's pet problem is the unseemly ties of gambling and gang symbols with the dog-fighting ethos. Amid a chronology of canine reflection, the past 12 months have signaled the year of the pit bull for Commissioner Roger Goodell's money machine:</p>
        <p>A miniature horse was mauled to death in September by an escaped pit bull and mastiff owned by linebacker Joey Porter, who was on the Steelers at the time.</p>
        <p>A cache of firearms was discovered at the suburban Chicago home of Bears defensive tackle Tank Johnson by the authorities in December after neighbors complained about three pit bulls he kept caged.</p>
        <p>A drug raid on a house owned by Falcons quarterback Michael Vick uncovered more than 50 pit bulls on the property as well as evidence of dog fighting that included bloody carpets, pry bars to open canine jaws, a rape stand to force mating, and treadmills designed for dogs.</p>
        <p>''The problem is the glamorization of dog fighting, particularly in the gangster rap culture,'' said John Goodwin, an animal-fighting expert and investigator with the Humane Society of the United States. ''Some athletes are simply taking it with them to the N.F.L.''</p>
        <p>A dog once bred for rural dog fighting in the South has morphed into a street figure with every story in the news media about an attack, with every state that lists dog fighting as a felony, with every local ordinance that seeks to ban the pit bull, with every tough guy who walks one using a logging chain as a leash.</p>
        <p>''The gangster culture already existed, but the pit bull, through its image, has the same kind of quality: tenacious and dangerous,'' Evans said. ''It is seen as the outlaw dog in that world.''</p>
        <p>Experts agree that the reputation exceeds reality. Many pit bull owners are responsible caretakers of dogs that live a domesticated life without problems.</p>
        <p>But in the N.F.L., any rebel dog is a reflection not only of its owner, but also of the league. The recent cases involving pit bulls have opened a peephole into pro football, which is, by uniform design, a raging success when its players are viewed as masked gladiators rather than visible individuals perceived as a threat to the suburban sensibilities of its audience.</p>
        <p>You can almost see Goodell, in his deputized form, fighting to ward off the kind of image crises that have undermined the N.B.A. Beyond the Palace fight of Ron Artest infamy and off-court legal issues involving Kobe Bryant, the climate of pit-bull fear has surfaced for the N.B.A. as well.</p>
        <p>Jay-Z is not only a hip-hop artist, but also a part-owner of the Nets who recently cast a pit bull in a violent video from his album. A loose pit bull was the source of one neighbor's complaint that led animal control on visits to the suburban Sacramento home of Artest. And Qyntel Woods was a Portland Trail Blazer when the police suspected him of being involved with dog fighting in 2004.</p>
        <p>''I do believe there is a subculture of dog fighting in the N.F.L. and N.B.A.,'' Goodwin said. ''You hear a lot of rumors, but these guys have layers of protection between themselves and prosecution.''</p>
        <p>Innuendo is enough to unsettle a commissioner. The N.B.A.'s response to bad pub has been to lump everything into its urban renewal project: Players have undergone a Pat Boone cleansing with rules banning gang fashions and jewelry on the bench.</p>
        <p>Regulating pet choices seems a stretch, though. All leagues can do is categorize the abhorrent dog-fighting underworld as another association for players to avoid. All officials can do is ask players to be vigilant about who and what is surrounding them, from people to pets.</p>
        <p>''The dog is going to be a reflection of the owner,'' Porter, now with the Dolphins, told The Palm Beach Post, adding, ''I don't too much care for a passive dog.''</p>
        <p>The pit bull isn't merely a breed; it's the current rallying cry in sports. Michigan State basketball players mentioned the pit bull when describing a playing style before the N.C.A.A. tournament, with Travis Walton telling The Detroit News: ''They lock down. They just keep fighting. They show no mercy. That's how we've got to be.''</p>
        <p>Dog fighting isn't only a cruel competition; it's the new sports metaphor.</p>
        <p>But it's the latest turnoff to the corporate base of the N.F.L., and it's the latest concern for Goodell, part commissioner, part crime dog.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
