<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Paris, Bringing Vegetables Out to Play</title>
    <meta content="06mini" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE MINIMALIST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/The Minimalist</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFD61130F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Paris, Bringing Vegetables Out to Play</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mark Bittman</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON Sunday mornings, there's an organic market on Boulevard Raspail in Paris where everything screams ''Eat me.''</p>
        <p>Even in early spring, the place manages to make the best markets of the rest of the world look shabby. On display are not only deep black radishes, the darkest green savoy cabbage and the to-be-expected but nevertheless mind-boggling cheese assortment, but also plate-size scallops replete with roe, a dozen types of oysters -- including the coveted but increasingly rare Belon -- crème fraîche, yogurt that looks just as rich as crème fraîche, and the herbs and vegetables Patricia Wells craves: cress (there are two kinds), lemon thyme, spinach, zucchini, fennel, baby cukes, fresh garlic (with stalks), spring onions and more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON Sunday mornings, there's an organic market on Boulevard Raspail in Paris where everything screams ''Eat me.''</p>
        <p>Even in early spring, the place manages to make the best markets of the rest of the world look shabby. On display are not only deep black radishes, the darkest green savoy cabbage and the to-be-expected but nevertheless mind-boggling cheese assortment, but also plate-size scallops replete with roe, a dozen types of oysters -- including the coveted but increasingly rare Belon -- crème fraîche, yogurt that looks just as rich as crème fraîche, and the herbs and vegetables Patricia Wells craves: cress (there are two kinds), lemon thyme, spinach, zucchini, fennel, baby cukes, fresh garlic (with stalks), spring onions and more.</p>
        <p>The author of the recently released ''Vegetable Harvest'' (William Morrow) -- not a vegetarian book, but very much a vegetables-at-the-center-of-the-plate one -- Ms. Wells is about to cook lunch for a couple of guests.</p>
        <p>She lives just a short walk from the market and seems as much at home on the Left Bank as an American could hope to be. More than at home, in fact, because among the great paradoxes of modern cuisine is that she, a Midwesterner who grew up in an era when ''all the food was Betty Crocker,'' has become one of the world's strongest, most knowledgeable and most celebrated advocates of French cuisine.</p>
        <p>Nearly 30 years ago, Walter Wells -- whom Patricia had married two years earlier -- was invited to move to Paris to work for The International Herald Tribune. They consulted their friend Craig Claiborne, the legendary New York Times food writer and editor, asking him if the move was wise.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wells recalled, ''Craig said, 'If you have to ask you don't deserve it,' '' and the couple were on their way. Mr. Wells eventually became executive editor of The Trib, which is now fully owned by The New York Times Company. (He retired last August.) And she became Patricia Wells, restaurant reviewer and food writer at The Trib, as well as a stellar cookbook author and teacher.</p>
        <p>Perhaps most impressively, she became the American to whom Americans (and often the French as well) turn when they want to know about French food, one of the few nonchef icons in the world of good cooking, and the envy of practically everyone. (''You're going to see Patricia Wells?'' a well-respected food writer who is friend of mine asked, before I left on my trip. ''Tell her I want to be her.'')</p>
        <p>Over the course of those 30 years, Ms. Wells has written or co-written nine books, of which about half are classics, unlikely to go out of print any time soon and as close to must-haves as one could imagine.</p>
        <p>These include ''Bistro Cooking'' (Workman, 1989), still a near-perfect collection of family-restaurant recipes from around the country; the less-well-known ''Patricia Wells's Trattoria'' (William Morrow, 1991), which is nearly as valuable; ''Simply French'' (William Morrow, 1991), her carefully assembled and accessible recipe collection based on her collaboration with Joël Robuchon, then and now one of the world's most creatively brilliant chefs; and ''The Food Lover's Guide to Paris'' (Workman, fourth edition, 1999) and ''The Food Lover's Guide to France'' (Workman, 1987), in need of updating but still useful resources, and fonts of memories for people who discovered Parisian food through Ms. Wells's insights.</p>
        <p>Now 60 years old and retired from The Trib, Ms. Wells shows no signs of slowing down. Each year, she teaches about a dozen exclusive, weeklong cooking classes in Paris and Provence. (Almost all are booked through 2008, but there is a waiting list: patriciawells.com.) Her plans include at least two more books: a memoir with Mr. Wells, followed by a salad-as-a-meal book. She also has a rigorous travel schedule and is a dedicated runner. (She ran in the New York Marathon last year, and one of her Provence classes combines cooking and fitness, a pairing many food writers find beneficial.)</p>
        <p>And, she can cook. She displays none of the abrupt intensity of the chef, or the hurried, frenzied manner of the home cook, or the off-the-cuff ease of a grandmother, but rather a combination that feels relaxed, confident and supremely competent.</p>
        <p>How did she get this way? ''I cooked pretty well before I worked with Joël,'' she said, referring to Mr. Robuchon, ''but going to cook with him was like going to church. Every day, I got up, got dressed, put on my makeup -- I always work better that way -- and worked with him all day. Ever since then, even now, I can hear him over my shoulder.''</p>
        <p>Average home cooks can't have a teacher like Mr. Robuchon, but they do have Ms. Wells, whose palate is clear and clean. Her style is not strictly French, Mediterranean (she spends a great deal of time in Provence) or American, but instead an unusual combination -- light, smart and flavorful.</p>
        <p>After 30 years of writing about food, of eating at the world's best restaurants, of cooking with whomever she chooses, of teaching people who are as passionate about cooking as most professionals, she has become inventive in a way that few home cooks ever are. And her eclectic, sophisticated approach translates to many of her books, including ''Vegetable Harvest.''</p>
        <p>On this day, she prepares what appears to be an ordinary dish of sautéed mixed vegetables -- red peppers, onions and tomatoes -- but seasons it with cumin, an unexpected and delicious choice. She thinly slices zucchini (O.K., she calls it carpaccio, but one can forgive that) and layers it with avocado, lemon thyme and pistachio oil, creating another fresh and surprising combination.</p>
        <p>There's a salad of shaved fennel with a fair amount of parsley, lemon juice and fresh sheep cheese, and it's filled with sweetness, lightly sour, rich and lean, a lovely bundle of contrasts.</p>
        <p>A more-or-less standard date-walnut bread is expertly done, and is served with shredded zucchini with creamy lemon-chive dressing (the dressing is mostly cream, the richest thing on the table, and a spectacular combination of old and new) and a couscous salad with spinach, parsley and spring onions, which highlights the exemplary ingredients.</p>
        <p>For dessert, she serves almond-buttermilk sorbet with almond macaroons, another triumph of balance, this one between crunchy-creamy and sweet-sour.</p>
        <p>These are typical of the book's recipes, though there are poultry, meat and fish dishes that play with vegetable combinations in strikingly new ways.</p>
        <p>They're ''French'' in that they're made in France, with French ingredients and a certain sensibility. They're American in that they're made by an American, and unmistakably eclectic. This, after all, may be Patricia Wells's greatest gift, an ability to combine the two in a way no one else could.</p>
        <p>Zucchini Carpaccio with Avocado  Adapted from ''Vegetable Harvest'' (Morrow, 2007)  Time: 10 minutes, plus 30 to 60 minutes' marinating</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon freshly squeezed lemon juice  1/2 teaspoon fine sea salt, plus additional as needed  1/4 cup best-quality pistachio oil, almond oil or extra virgin olive oil  4 small zucchini (about 4 ounces each), trimmed  1 ripe avocado, peeled and very thinly sliced  1/4 cup salted pistachio nuts  4 sprigs fresh lemon thyme, preferably with flowers.</p>
        <p>1. Stir together lemon juice and 1/2 teaspoon salt in small jar. Add oil, cover and shake to blend.  2. Slice zucchini lengthwise as thinly as possible, using mandoline or very sharp knife. Spread slices on platter and drizzle with lemon mixture. Tilt platter to evenly coat slices. Cover with plastic wrap and marinate at room temperature for 30 minutes to an hour.  3. Alternate zucchini and avocado slices on individual salad plates, slightly overlapping each slice. Sprinkle with pistachio nuts. Season with salt to taste, garnish with lemon thyme, and serve.  Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Couscous Salad with Spinach  Adapted from ''Vegetable Harvest'' (Morrow, 2007)  Time: 15 minutes</p>
        <p>1 cup medium-grain instant couscous  1 teaspoon fine sea salt  1 tablespoon freshly squeezed lemon juice  2 cups loosely packed parsley leaves  1 tablespoon extra virgin olive oil  3 spring onions or scallions, trimmed and cut into very thin rings  5 ounces fresh spinach leaves, cut into a chiffonade (4 cups, loosely packed)  3 tablespoons creamy lemon-chive dressing (see recipe), or as needed.</p>
        <p>1. Combine couscous and salt in large shallow bowl. Toss with fork to blend. Add 11/3 cups of hottest possible tap water, and fluff until grains are separated. Set aside and occasionally fluff until all liquid has been absorbed, about 3 minutes.  2. Combine lemon juice, parsley leaves and olive oil in food processor or blender. Process until parsley is finely chopped, then toss with couscous and spring onions. (May be prepared and refrigerated for up to 8 hours.)  3. To serve, toss spinach chiffonade with just enough dressing to evenly coat. Add to couscous mixture and toss gently until blended.  Yield: 12 servings.</p>
        <p>Creamy Lemon-Chive Dressing  Adapted from ''Vegetable Harvest'' (Morrow, 2007)  Time: 5 minutes</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons freshly squeezed lemon juice  1/2 teaspoon fine sea salt, or as needed  1 cup light cream  1/3 cup finely minced chives.</p>
        <p>1. Put lemon juice and 1/2 teaspoon salt in small jar, cover and shake to dissolve salt.  2. Add cream and chives. Shake to blend. Adjust salt to taste. Store, covered and refrigerated, for up to 1 week. Shake to blend before using.  Yield: 11/4 cups.</p>
        <p>Almond and Buttermilk Sorbet  Adapted from''Vegetable Harvest'' (Morrow, 2007)  Time: About 15 minutes, plus 1 hour and 45 minutes chilling and freezing</p>
        <p>1/3 cup freshly squeezed lemon juice  1 1/4 cups sugar  1/4 cup light corn syrup  1/2 cup whole (unblanched) almonds  2 cups buttermilk, shaken to blend  1/2 teaspoon almond extract.</p>
        <p>1. Combine lemon juice, 1 cup sugar and corn syrup in small saucepan. Place over medium-low heat and simmer until sugar is dissolved. Cool to room temperature.  2. Place almonds in small, dry skillet over medium heat. Shake until nuts are fragrant and evenly toasted, about 2 minutes. Transfer to a plate to cool.  3. Mix almonds and remaining 1/4 cup sugar in food processor or blender. Process to a powder, and set aside.  4. Stir cooled lemon syrup, buttermilk and almond extract in bowl. Refrigerate well. Transfer to ice cream maker and freeze according to manufacturer's instructions. Serve in small bowls, with almond and sugar topping.  Yield: 12 servings (about 1 quart).</p>
        <p>THE MINIMALIST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
