<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ready for the N.B.A. Throne, but Not Like Mike</title>
    <meta content="06lebron" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/sports/basketball/06lebron.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852597"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cleveland Cavaliers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Antonio Spurs</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beck, Howard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Lebron</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Detroit Pistons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/San Antonio Spurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Basketball Assn</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Cleveland Cavaliers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">San Antonio Spurs</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Detroit Pistons</org>
        <person class="online_producer">James, LeBron</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jordan, Michael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E5DC1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ready for the N.B.A. Throne, but Not Like Mike</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ready for N.B.A. Throne, but Not Like Mike</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK; Liz Robbins contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
      <dateline>CLEVELAND, June 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>LeBron James of Cleveland Cavaliers is new kind of NBA superstar; in four seasons, he has developed nuanced game, cultivated dynamic image in pop culture and led Cavaliers into NBA finals for first time in their 37-year history; other NBA stars jump highest, run fastest, dunk hardest and score most points; LeBron can score, but also can pass, and seems smart enough to know which style to choose from minute to minute; NBA is often criticized for being league of too many one-on-one players; LeBron is testament to good teamwork; Cavaliers will face three-time champion San Antonio Spurs in series that opens June 7 in San Antonio; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LeBron James was still a teenager when he was cast as a basketball messiah in television commercials and labeled The Chosen One on magazine covers. Now at the age of 22, James may soon fulfill all of the hyperbolic promise -- if the viewing public can adapt to a new kind of superstar.</p>
        <p>The Cleveland Cavaliers are in the National Basketball Association finals for the first time in their 37-year history, and James -- their preternaturally polished, selfless star forward -- is the reason. Cleveland will face the three-time champion Spurs in a series that opens Thursday night in San Antonio.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>LeBron James might soon fulfill the media’s hype  if the viewing public can adapt to a new kind of superstar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LeBron James was still a teenager when he was cast as a basketball messiah in television commercials and labeled The Chosen One on magazine covers. Now at the age of 22, James may soon fulfill all of the hyperbolic promise -- if the viewing public can adapt to a new kind of superstar.</p>
        <p>The Cleveland Cavaliers are in the National Basketball Association finals for the first time in their 37-year history, and James -- their preternaturally polished, selfless star forward -- is the reason. Cleveland will face the three-time champion Spurs in a series that opens Thursday night in San Antonio.</p>
        <p>It took James just four seasons to deliver the Cavaliers to the promised land, and he did it with a six-game upset of the Detroit Pistons in the Eastern Conference finals, a series in which his clever passing and team-first mind-set were on display almost as much as his ability to soar and score.</p>
        <p>The N.B.A. has been in search of a transcendent star with staying power since Michael Jordan retired from the Chicago Bulls in 1998. Television viewership of the finals is down 55 percent since that year. James, already a household name, could be the incentive for casual fans to tune in this week, but, then again, it could take a large national audience a little time to embrace all the dimensions of James's game.</p>
        <p>Although he can dominate as a scorer, and did so last week when he scored 29 of Cleveland's final 30 points in a dazzling double-overtime victory over Detroit, James is just as likely to defer to teammates and control a game with his passes. On some nights, his points come almost quietly.</p>
        <p>He can go for a quarter, a half or an entire game without looking for his shot at all.</p>
        <p>''LeBron is beyond a highlight reel,'' said Commissioner David Stern in acknowledging that there is a certain subtlety to James's brilliance.</p>
        <p>Yet fans are used to a particular kind of N.B.A. superstar, the guys who jump the highest, run the fastest, dunk the hardest and, more often than not, score the most points every night. The public adores scoring and expects its stars to be a little selfish. Jordan was the high-flying archetype, leading the Bulls to six championships in the 1990s.</p>
        <p>James, in contrast, is a brawny 6-foot-8 player who can sometimes score like Jordan or Kobe Bryant but who can also pass like the former N.B.A. star Magic Johnson, and who seems smart enough to know which style to choose from minute to minute. His emergence comes at a time when the N.B.A. is often criticized for being a league of too many one-on-one players and at a time when the United States national team, with numerous N.B.A. stars, has been embarrassed more than once on the world stage.</p>
        <p>The belief is that the United States still has the best talent in the world, if not the best teamwork. James would seem to be a testament to the latter.</p>
        <p>''He has an unbelievable feel for the game,'' Cavaliers General Manager Danny Ferry said.</p>
        <p>Johnson, the rare N.B.A. superstar renowned more for his passing than his shooting, said: ''He's much like me when he controls the game, and he dominates it that way and helps his teammates become better. He's more like Jordan when he goes into the scoring mode and takes it to the basket with all the fantastic moves. To me, he's more like me than he is like Michael. He's more into controlling the game than he is dominating it with scoring.''</p>
        <p>The viewers who tune into Game 1 on Thursday night will see a well-rounded Spurs team that has won three championships since 1999, that has a star in Tim Duncan, but that has failed to capture the imagination of the public. Instead, many of those watching will be hoping for a big show from James, with his electrifying 48-point performance in Cleveland's Game 5 victory over Detroit still fresh in their minds.</p>
        <p>But a more typical James performance came in the series clincher two nights later. In Game 6, James scored only 20 points, missed 8 of his 11 field-goal attempts and spent most of the night turning a formerly anonymous rookie into a playoff star. Daniel Gibson, a second-round draft pick, scored 31 points, largely because of James's ability to draw in, and pick apart, the Pistons' defense.</p>
        <p>During the broadcast, the TNT analyst Steve Kerr said James was ''like a man playing among children.''</p>
        <p>''Watching him, you forget that these other guys on the floor are some of the greatest athletes in the world,'' Kerr said.</p>
        <p>The Cavaliers lost the first game of the series to Detroit when James passed up a potential tying layup in the final seconds and instead passed the ball to Donyell Marshall for a 3-point attempt. It was, by any definition, a smart basketball play. But Marshall missed, and James was second-guessed for the next 48 hours. No one could imagine Jordan or Bryant doing such a thing in a game of that magnitude.</p>
        <p>''You can go out and score 40 points a game, but if your team is losing, then you're going to get criticized for shooting too much,'' Marshall said. ''I would prefer a guy who takes what the other team is going to give him, to help us win, not a guy who feels they have to score 40 every night.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Marshall says teammates sometimes have to urge James to take over in the fourth quarter of a tight game.</p>
        <p>Off the court, James embraces his celebrity status, endorsing shoes, soda and lawn mowers and referring to himself by his pop-culture nickname, King James. But on the court, he seems to lack a self-indulgent impulse.</p>
        <p>''People are still trying to figure him out,'' Cavaliers Coach Mike Brown said with a knowing grin. ''He impacts a game in a lot of areas that people don't appreciate.''</p>
        <p>James, who became a national phenomenon in high school, was taken by Cleveland with the No. 1 pick in the 2003 draft.</p>
        <p>In four N.B.A. seasons, he has been a model of balance, averaging 26.7 points, 6.7 rebounds and 6.4 assists. In the series against Detroit, he averaged 25.7 points, 9.2 rebounds and 8.5 assists, placing him in truly elite company. Only the Hall of Famers Oscar Robertson (in 1963), John Havlicek (1968) and Larry Bird (1986) had ever averaged at least 25 points, 9 rebounds and 8 assists in a conference finals.</p>
        <p>James is not regarded as a great defender, although he has shown vast improvement in that area. What James does best, other than win, is make the game look simple.</p>
        <p>He can fill a box score and dominate on the court without ever looking as if he is trying to do either. The greatest measure of an N.B.A. star is how much he lifts up his teammates, and James excels in this category.</p>
        <p>The Cavaliers were regarded as no better than the third-best team in the Eastern Conference when the season began, behind the Pistons and the defending champion Miami Heat. Cleveland's starting lineup has no other established stars besides James, and few reliable scorers.</p>
        <p>Now the Cavaliers are four victories from a championship, partly because of a defense that has become one of the league's best, but mostly because of James, who now has the ultimate stage to make himself the face of the N.B.A.</p>
        <p>''It means nothing to me; it means everything to my team,'' he said of the Cavaliers' ascension. ''I don't care what happens to me as an individual.''</p>
        <p>Stern said he would rather not place the N.B.A.'s hopes on one player's shoulders, even shoulders as broad and steady as James's. He called James merely the ''leader of the pack'' in a new generation of N.B.A. stars and said that the fixation on James might be short-lived if the Cavaliers did not build on their breakthrough season.</p>
        <p>In some ways, his careful appraisal contrasted with the undisguised enthusiasm from others who cannot seem to get James's Jordan-like performance from Game 5 out of their heads.</p>
        <p>''You know, I was watching that and I thought to myself, things are never going to be the same,'' Donnie Walsh, the president of the Indiana Pacers, said. ''It was like watching Michael Jordan before your eyes.''</p>
        <p>Jordan himself weighed in, telling The Chicago Tribune on Monday that ''what just transpired was something I felt was needed for the league.''</p>
        <p>But there may not be another Game 5 performance in the series against the Spurs. James may pass more than he shoots as he attempts to lead the Cavaliers to one more upset. And it may be worth keeping in mind a somewhat over-the-top TV commercial depicting James as a messiah. The commercial was broadcast in 2004, when James was only several months into his rookie season.</p>
        <p>The N.B.A. legends Jerry West and Julius Erving sat in as elders clad in white, while the preacher, played by the comedian Bernie Mac, read from ''the King James playbook'' and sang praises to ''basketball's chosen one.''</p>
        <p>''Why did the chosen one ask for court vision?'' Bernie Mac's preacher bellowed. ''He wanted glory. For the team!''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
