<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Best of the Bad Cops Keeps Walking a Hard Line</title>
    <meta content="06shie" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/arts/television/06shie.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852469"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">FX</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Chiklis, Michael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Leary, Denis</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E7DF1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1002" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Best of the Bad Cops Keeps Walking a Hard Line</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Best of the Bad Cops Keeps Walking a Hard Line</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIRGINIA HEFFERNAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Michael Chiklis's agent first read the script for ''The Shield'' in 2001, he advised the actor not to audition. If Mr. Chiklis wanted the lead role in the cops-and-gangs drama -- and he did -- he shouldn't have to abase himself with a tryout, his agent argued. Mr. Chiklis, after all, had already starred in ''The Commish'' on ABC and ''Daddio'' on NBC. He was almost a household name.</p>
        <p>''As a status thing; it's FX,'' Mr. Chiklis explains in the DVD commentary to the pilot episode. He was determined to audition anyway, but he dug his agent's reasoning. ''My agent at the time was effusive about the material. He loved the material. But he was afraid of me going in and reading for a 'netlet.' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In its six seasons, “The Shield” has won Emmys and Golden Globes but never squandered the stakes or the suspense of that first episode.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Michael Chiklis's agent first read the script for ''The Shield'' in 2001, he advised the actor not to audition. If Mr. Chiklis wanted the lead role in the cops-and-gangs drama -- and he did -- he shouldn't have to abase himself with a tryout, his agent argued. Mr. Chiklis, after all, had already starred in ''The Commish'' on ABC and ''Daddio'' on NBC. He was almost a household name.</p>
        <p>''As a status thing; it's FX,'' Mr. Chiklis explains in the DVD commentary to the pilot episode. He was determined to audition anyway, but he dug his agent's reasoning. ''My agent at the time was effusive about the material. He loved the material. But he was afraid of me going in and reading for a 'netlet.' ''</p>
        <p>A netlet. In the commentary, Mr. Chiklis's colleagues snort at the old FX putdown. And in the incongruous way of DVD extras, this industry jargon and banter can be heard over the fearsome images of that tense, audacious hour of television -- one of the greatest dramatic pilots ever made.</p>
        <p>In other words, while Vic Mackey (Mr. Chiklis) can be seen making nice with a new cop only to murder him point blank at a crime scene, Mr. Chiklis on the audio track breezily reminisces with Shawn Ryan, who created the series; Clark Johnson, who directed the pilot; and Scott Brazil, an executive producer and regular director of the series. (Mr. Brazil died last year.)</p>
        <p>In its six seasons, ''The Shield'' has won Emmys and Golden Globes but never squandered the stakes or the suspense of that first episode. At the same time, FX, the channel that once seemed beneath an audition from a jovial ABC star, is now home to a variety of film actors, including Denis Leary (''Rescue Me'') and Minnie Driver (''The Riches'') -- to say nothing of Mr. Chiklis himself, who effortlessly controls his basic-cable dominion as Mackey. He seems positively jubilant with doughnuts and street-cop work.</p>
        <p>In his appearances at awards ceremonies -- he won an Emmy for best actor in the first year of the series -- Mr. Chiklis is amused and amazed that circumstances have conspired to let a performer like him, who once appeared headed for clowning or minor roles, help redefine television acting.</p>
        <p>Season 6 of ''The Shield,'' the penultimate one, ended last night. It wasn't a knock-the-wind-out-of-you finale, but ''The Shield'' knows itself -- its strengths, its limits -- and, beginning with Mackey's shooting of the traitorous cop in the pilot, it has a way with unresolved resolutions.</p>
        <p>By the time last night's episode wrapped, the heart of ''The Shield'' was still pumping steadily and hard, though this viewer's stunned and pleasurable sense of being thrown down, which had begun with the murder of Mackey's buddy Curtis Lemansky (Kenny Johnson) in Season 5, had let up. I was on my feet again, and I had mixed feelings about that.</p>
        <p>When Mackey freaked out trying to find Lem's killer -- torturing to death the wrong guy, hiding while his own name was cleared, imprisoning the guy who framed him, pointing the finger idiotically at a fat cat in jail -- his frenzy turned feral, porcine. With his pink dome and deep-set eyes Mr. Chiklis is a weird, wonderful-looking creature. I like watching him run wild much more than squabble with bureaucracies. But I also know he had to confront Shane Vendrell (Walton Goggins), the friend who killed Lem, in an astoundingly good episode last month, ''Chasing Ghosts.''</p>
        <p>The various gangs of Los Angeles have distinct ethnicities on ''The Shield'': Ecuadorean, Armenian, Mexican and so on. But the cops are black and white, known by nicknames like Vic, Lem, Ronnie, Shane and Dutch that don't especially load the ethnic dice. Neither do the leads here have families -- unlike on that other tough-guy show with a finale coming up. Their dads are blanks. And Los Angeles is not filled with their brothers and uncles and cousins, men they're ready to die for.</p>
        <p>Sure, they have children, and wives to cheat on, but mostly their ties are to other cops. Their loyalty to colleagues is grounded in blackmail: their partners know exactly how they make so many arrests, how few warrants they get, how on the take they are and where all the many, many bodies are buried.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ryan says he came up with the idea for ''The Shield'' when he noticed front-page news about the drop in violent crime in Los Angeles, with news about police brutality and corruption buried in the back pages. He wanted to combine those parts of the newspaper in one man. He was also scheduled to deliver a comedy, and he managed to work lightness into his series -- a back-room ''that's not what your wife said'' style of hazing -- that keeps the series from becoming too dark and manages (when necessary) to express its utter bleakness. It's an impressive trick.</p>
        <p>But everyone involved in the series has also become serious about the theme of protection -- of ''shielding.'' If every episode seems to tighten the noose around Mackey, every episode also hands him a victory. He collars criminals of every description, as other officers look so decisively the other way that they by now are guilty of collusion.</p>
        <p>Still, fans of the series, which is often -- make that always -- praised for its ''moral ambiguity,'' root for Mackey. One Web commenter on the first season put it simply: ''The thing is, Vic hates criminals and he does care about innocent people and crime victims. I feel like he would protect me. In fact, he and Shane, Lem, and Ronnie can protect me any day!!''</p>
        <p>If Mackey is clearing the streets, he is also making criminals of the police, including himself. He creates witnesses, aiders and abettors, blackmailers, liars, kidnappers, addicts, prostitutes, bribers, torturers and corpses. And then, having done all that, he insists that he is the only shield from the danger he himself has created. And the scary thing about ''The Shield'' -- the terrifying thing -- is that you believe him.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
