<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Praise at U.N. for a New U.S. Envoy's Inclusive Tactics and Convivial Style</title>
    <meta content="06khalilzad" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/world/06khalilzad.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852577"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lebanon</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syria</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoge, Warren</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Khalilzad, Zalmay (Amb)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bolton, John R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hariri, Rafik (1945-2005)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Khalilzad, Zalmay</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01EEDD1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1039" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Praise at U.N. for a New U.S. Envoy's Inclusive Tactics and Convivial Style</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Praise at U.N. for a New U.S. Envoy’s Inclusive Tactics and Convivial Style</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN HOGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoge, Warren</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, June 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Zalmay Khalilzad, United States ambassador to United Nations, has been welcomed effusively since his arrival six weeks ago, and one frequently mentioned reason is that he strikes people as so different from his combative predecessor John R Bolton; as Khalilzad confronts many of same issues that Bolton did, he emphasizes his confidence in power of personal diplomacy; in first major test of his influence, he pushed for vote on resolution creating international tribunal to judge suspects in assassination of former Lebanese prime minister Rafik Hariri, despite warnings that it could inflame volatile politics of Lebanon; measure passed 10 to 0, with five countries abstaining; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One by one, the ambassadors at an unusually jolly diplomatic dinner last month rose to pay tribute to the new American ambassador, Zalmay Khalilzad.</p>
        <p>He was a needed ''breath of fresh air,'' said one. Another described bonding with him on a Security Council trip the way a child might talk up a new friend at summer camp. A third said that while no one expected disagreements with American policy to end, he liked the ''sensitive'' way that policy was now presented.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Zalmay Khalilzad, the new U.S. ambassador to the United Nations, has been welcomed with open arms by his fellow delegates since he arrived six weeks ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One by one, the ambassadors at an unusually jolly diplomatic dinner last month rose to pay tribute to the new American ambassador, Zalmay Khalilzad.</p>
        <p>He was a needed ''breath of fresh air,'' said one. Another described bonding with him on a Security Council trip the way a child might talk up a new friend at summer camp. A third said that while no one expected disagreements with American policy to end, he liked the ''sensitive'' way that policy was now presented.</p>
        <p>His turn to respond, Mr. Khalilzad stood and said, ''I have discovered from your comments that the best thing I have done was to choose my predecessor.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Khalilzad, the former American ambassador to Afghanistan and Iraq, has been welcomed effusively since his arrival six weeks ago, and one frequently mentioned reason is that he strikes people as so different from John R. Bolton, the combative former American ambassador.</p>
        <p>''I've heard universally good things about Khalilzad from ambassadors,'' said Edward C. Luck, a professor of international affairs at Columbia who has followed the United Nations for more than three decades. ''You couldn't have two more contrasting approaches to the job, and all of them bring up Bolton and say what a welcome relief Khalilzad is to the old approach, which was so much preaching and in your face.''</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for Mr. Bolton said that he had heard about the remark by Mr. Khalilzad and that he would have no comment.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Khalilzad confronts many of the same issues for the United States that Mr. Bolton did -- Darfur, Iran, Lebanon, the Middle East, overhauling United Nations management -- he emphasizes his confidence in the power of personal diplomacy and says he believes it can produce better results.</p>
        <p>''We need to work harder to explain what we are about because there is a lot of mistrust here, a degree of automaticity that if the U.S. wants something, then a range of countries, a significant number, will immediately be suspicious and question our motives,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Acknowledging his remarkable reception thus far, he cautioned: ''I've been around long enough to know I should enjoy it while it lasts. Also, maybe they're thinking, 'Look at the places this guy has just been, so let's be nice to him.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Khalilzad, 56, likes to describe himself as a deal maker, a conciliator eager to listen to others and someone respectful of the points of views of small countries. ''I am a problem solver,'' he said on his first day in office. ''I will not posture.''</p>
        <p>The next day, he joined other Security Council ambassadors on a three-day trip to Kosovo and Serbia. The next week, on becoming president of the Council for May, he took the unusual step of inviting all the envoys and their spouses out for a weekend retreat to Kykuit, a Rockefeller estate in Westchester County.</p>
        <p>''I have tried to develop personal relationships with my colleagues here, I have tried to create a sense of trust, I level with them, I don't demean them,'' he said. ''Even if we disagree, we have to do it in a way that is not disagreeable.''</p>
        <p>Afghan-born, educated in Lebanon and able to converse in five Central Asian languages, Mr. Khalilzad says his origins, appearance and accented English give him an advantage with the envoys, particularly those from the developing world who eye American policy with such doubt. ''The way I look and my background and style resonate with many of them,'' he said. ''I try to explain to them that I understand their culture and I know where they are coming from, that they are seeing conspiracies where the motives are really innocent. Often when I make a comment like that, they laugh because they can see I have read them correctly.''</p>
        <p>In his remarks at the ambassadorial dinner, he went out of his way to quote Rumi, the 13th-century Persian poet born in what is now Afghanistan, and mentioned his friendship with Lakhdar Brahimi, a former Algerian foreign minister revered at the United Nations for his troubleshooting successes and known as a harsh critic of the war in Iraq.</p>
        <p>Inside the United States mission, the changes appear to be just as dramatic. ''Ambassador Khalilzad has a totally different style than Ambassador Bolton,'' said an American official who has worked closely with both men but said he could not speak about internal matters for attribution. ''Khalilzad is informal, inclusive, not at all hierarchal and secretive the way Bolton was.''</p>
        <p>A second official, who also said he was not authorized to speak by name, said: ''There are officers up and down the line at the mission who are having their first exposure and dialogue with the chief. Khalilzad doesn't care whether someone's a third-year junior officer or a senior foreign service officer with 18 years' experience, he wants the direct contact, not something summarized by a minister counselor.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Khalilzad said he had expected to find that ''members of the Security Council were hostile and tense with fights all the time.'' Instead, he said, ''things are much more convivial and people at a personal level want to work together.''</p>
        <p>In the first major test of his influence this past month, Mr. Khalilzad pushed for a vote on a resolution creating an international tribunal to judge suspects in the assassination of the former Lebanese prime minister, Rafik Hariri, despite warnings that acting now could inflame the already volatile politics of Lebanon.</p>
        <p>The measure passed 10 to 0, with five countries abstaining.</p>
        <p>Did he think his personal approach kept Vitaly I. Churkin, the envoy of Russia, which had voiced objections, from using his veto to kill the measure? ''I don't know,'' he said, ''but he opposed it in an agreeable way.''</p>
        <p>Facing him now is the far more fraught Kosovo issue, where Russia has been hinting broadly that it may veto a plan before the Security Council that would give the breakaway Serbian province independence. ''What Churkin has said publicly, and what the discussion between him and me has been, I don't want to signal an agreement,'' he said. ''But I also don't want you to assume that there is no chance of an agreement, that we won't reach an understanding.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
