<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Partition That Divided a City and a Civilization</title>
    <meta content="06grimes" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/books/06grimes.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852452"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE1D61130F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="995" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Partition That Divided a City and a Civilization</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Partition That Divided a City and a Civilization</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GRIMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Berlin Wall  A World Divided, 1961-1989  By Frederick Taylor  Illustrated. 486 pages. HarperCollins. $27.95.</p>
        <p>After the Berlin Wall came down in 1989, the government of the soon-to-be-former German Democratic Republic pulled off a breathtakingly cynical stunt. It auctioned the thing off, one piece at a time. Adding a special piquancy to the event, at the Hotel Parc Pallas in Monte Carlo, was the official responsible for transporting the wall from Germany.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Frederick Taylor does a great service in carefully separating myth from reality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Berlin Wall  A World Divided, 1961-1989  By Frederick Taylor  Illustrated. 486 pages. HarperCollins. $27.95.</p>
        <p>After the Berlin Wall came down in 1989, the government of the soon-to-be-former German Democratic Republic pulled off a breathtakingly cynical stunt. It auctioned the thing off, one piece at a time. Adding a special piquancy to the event, at the Hotel Parc Pallas in Monte Carlo, was the official responsible for transporting the wall from Germany.</p>
        <p>Sharp-eyed German reporters recognized him as none other than Hagen Koch. Nearly 30 years earlier, Mr. Koch, then a 21-year-old mapper for the military arm of the security services, had defied jeering crowds of West Berliners, and moving along the newly installed tangle of barbed wire dividing East and West Berlin, had painted a white line that neatly demarcated the border and, as it were, put the finishing touch on the postwar division of the world.</p>
        <p>Rarely does history wind up its dramas so neatly, with the same actor reciting both prologue and epilogue, and Frederick Taylor quite rightly savors the coincidence in ''The Berlin Wall,'' his gripping, impassioned history of the cold war's most malevolent symbol. From the beginning, the wall was as much theater as fact, a floodlit stage for the postwar passion play of nuclear brinkmanship, ideological struggle and political grandstanding. On both sides of Mr. Koch's white line, leaders postured, posed and snarled, while the wall itself stood silent and immovable.</p>
        <p>The wall gave the world enduring images of suffering and heroism as desperate East Germans leaped from buildings, jumped across the barbed wire or tunneled their way to freedom. It inspired John F. Kennedy's ringing declaration ''Ich bin ein Berliner'' (which, as Mr. Taylor carefully explains, does not mean ''I am a jelly doughnut,'' despite the myth) and Ronald Reagan's ''Mr. Gorbachev, tear down this wall.'' The wall was always more than concrete.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor, the author of ''Dresden,'' does a great service in carefully separating myth from reality, symbol from substance as he traces the history of the wall from its beginnings in August 1961 as a hastily thrown-down barbed-wire barrier to its final form: 30 miles of concrete, with 300 watchtowers manned by soldiers with orders to shoot to kill.</p>
        <p>As a physical presence, and one government's cruel policy toward its own citizens, the wall was an abomination. Its geopolitical role was much more ambiguous. The wall, Mr. Taylor argues, was in some respects the solution to several problems, and Western leaders, despite their hostile criticism, came to regard it as a stabilizing influence. Like Berliners, both East and West, they learned to live with it.</p>
        <p>The larger political picture is always on Mr. Taylor's mind. Berlin provided the chessboard and the pieces, but the game was controlled from Moscow and Washington. Mr. Taylor begins, therefore, with the awkward, hastily improvised partition of Germany and Berlin after the war, and the irreconcilable differences that would make Berlin a trigger for potential East-West conflict, and an insoluble problem for both adversaries, especially as German leaders, East and West, learned how to manipulate their masters.</p>
        <p>The wall appeared overnight, but it had gestated for years. Stalin's failed attempt to seal off Berlin in 1948, leading to the Berlin airlift, marked the end of one phase and led to a deceptively tranquil period of coexistence.</p>
        <p>''Berlin still functioned, in many ways, as one city,'' Mr. Taylor writes. ''There were signs showing sector borders, occasional checkpoints and restrictions, temporary or permanent, but for a dozen years after the end of the Berlin blockade, citizens moved freely around the former German capital. Telephone lines, sewage, transport were all shared.''</p>
        <p>Walter Ulbricht, East Germany's rigidly Stalinist leader, was constantly scheming, however. As early as January 1953, he had obtained permission to create a fortified border between East and West Berlin. Stalin's sudden death in March robbed him of the opportunity to proceed, but a workers' revolt later that year, followed by a steady stream of emigration, legal and illegal, forced the issue. The border would have to be sealed if the East German state were to survive.</p>
        <p>The tension-filled weeks leading to the creation of the wall provide Mr. Taylor with his best material, and he makes the most of it, setting out in precise detail the progress of Project Rose, the East German government's audacious plan to divide East from West Berlin over the course of a quiet weekend.</p>
        <p>For years Westerners had scoffed at the idea that the city could be physically divided. But the impossible was accomplished in a matter of hours. Early on Monday, Aug. 14, an elderly woman in the Friedrichstrasse station nervously approached a policeman and asked him when the next train was leaving for West Berlin.</p>
        <p>''None of that anymore, Grandma,'' he told her. ''You're all sat in a mousetrap now.''</p>
        <p>What Mr. Taylor calls the ''heroic period'' of the wall began almost immediately. As barbed wire gave way to concrete, East Berliners grew desperate. The tales are both horrific and thrilling. A train driver simply crashed through the wall at high speed, in a hail of bullets, with family and friends aboard. Several unsuspecting passengers, finding themselves in the West, turned right around and returned to the East.</p>
        <p>Organized groups of West Berliners, mostly students, braved arrest and imprisonment to sneak East Germans through checkpoints or lead them through tunnels. Some later became professionals for hire.</p>
        <p>As political confrontation gave way to accommodation, the wall -- known simply as ''the border marker'' in the East -- ceased to be news. East and West learned to avert their eyes from the concrete scar running through their city. The wall came to seem almost normal, simply a part of life. All the more shocking then, when it finally came crashing down.</p>
        <p>At the time, Mr. Taylor writes, the East German government had plans in hand for a new high-tech replacement. That wall would have been built to last for a hundred years.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
