<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Afghanistan Exhibition Provokes Questions</title>
    <meta content="06muse" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/arts/design/06muse.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852476"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gold</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Geographic Society</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Metropolitan Museum of Art</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Gallery of Art</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Munson, Lynne</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E6DF1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Afghanistan Exhibition Provokes Questions</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Afghanistan Exhibition Provokes Questions</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The National Geographic Society has struck a $1 million deal with the Afghan government to bring a rare cache of gold artifacts to the United States in a traveling exhibition. But some cultural experts who have followed the negotiations are questioning whether Afghanistan is being properly compensated.</p>
        <p>Plans call for the ancient Afghan pieces -- part of the storied 2,000-year-old Bactrian hoard -- to be displayed at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the National Gallery of Art in Washington, the Asian Art Museum in San Francisco and the Museum of Fine Arts in Houston, although contracts have not yet been signed by those institutions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some cultural experts are questioning whether Afghanistan is being properly compensated in a $1 million deal to bring a rare cache of gold artifacts to the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The National Geographic Society has struck a $1 million deal with the Afghan government to bring a rare cache of gold artifacts to the United States in a traveling exhibition. But some cultural experts who have followed the negotiations are questioning whether Afghanistan is being properly compensated.</p>
        <p>Plans call for the ancient Afghan pieces -- part of the storied 2,000-year-old Bactrian hoard -- to be displayed at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the National Gallery of Art in Washington, the Asian Art Museum in San Francisco and the Museum of Fine Arts in Houston, although contracts have not yet been signed by those institutions.</p>
        <p>The National Geographic Society and the Afghan government signed a protocol accord over the weekend in Kabul, Afghanistan's capital, outlining an exhibition schedule that would begin in May 2008 at the National Gallery. The document calls for Afghanistan to receive $1 million as well as 40 percent of ''total revenue,'' which is defined as exhibition revenue, minus expenses.</p>
        <p>Lynne Munson, the former deputy chairwoman of the National Endowment for the Humanities, which helped finance the cataloging of the Afghan treasures, said the arrangement would leave Afghanistan with ''40 percent of absolutely nothing,'' because expenses would be significant.</p>
        <p>''This is a travesty,'' she said in a telephone interview from Washington. ''The Bactrian hoard is simply the most valuable possession of the poorest people on earth. To ask them to lend it and give so little in return is unconscionable.''</p>
        <p>She said she had ceased working for the endowment in 2005 because of internal conflicts within the agency over arrangements for the show.</p>
        <p>The protocol accord signed over the weekend says that the exhibition revenue going to the Afghans will be derived from the fees paid by the museums as hosts of the show and from corporate sponsorships. It does not guarantee them proceeds from ticket, catalog or merchandise sales.</p>
        <p>Reached by telephone in Washington, Terry D. Garcia, the executive vice president of the National Geographic Society's mission programs, said that the financial terms ''were dictated by the Afghans.''</p>
        <p>He said that no decision had been made on proceeds from the merchandising or the catalog sales. He added, ''Those categories of revenue are in fact included in what the Afghans would receive.''</p>
        <p>Ana Rosa Rodriguez, executive director of the Society for the Preservation of Afghanistan's Cultural Heritage, said in a telephone interview from Kabul that she felt the society had taken advantage of a country that has endured nearly three decades of violent upheaval.</p>
        <p>''I think it is my duty to express my concerns about this deal,'' Ms. Rodrguez said, complaining of ''the unacceptable manner'' in which ''a prestigious American society has dealt with a postconflict country with a devastated cultural heritage.''</p>
        <p>The collection includes more than 20,000 pieces of gold jewelry, funeral ornaments and personal items from the Silk Road culture of Bactria, an ancient nation that covered parts of what is now Afghanistan. The hoard was discovered in 1978 by a Russian-Greek archaeologist, Viktor Sarianidi, at a grave site in Tillia-Tepe, in northern Afghanistan. The works blend Greek, Bactrian and nomadic traditions, reflecting Afghanistan's historical position at the crossroads of ancient civilizations.</p>
        <p>The treasures were only sporadically displayed over the next decade and then packed away. Then, in 1989, when Afghanistan's last Communist president was facing a growing insurgency by the Islamic rebels known as the mujahedeen and the imminent withdrawal of Soviet troop support, he ordered that the treasures be hidden. He was ousted in 1992, and for years it was widely assumed that the gold had been looted or destroyed and would never resurface.</p>
        <p>The treasures were unearthed from a bank vault beneath a former royal palace in Kabul in 2004. They were among the few examples of Afghanistan's rich cultural heritage to survive decades of war. The collection had been kept hidden by curators and employees of the Kabul Museum at tremendous personal risk under the fractious mujahedeen and then the Taliban, who ruled from 1996 to 2001.</p>
        <p>''It's a compelling story, not just of the Silk Road but also the work of these modern-day heroes,'' Mr. Garcia said. ''We think people are going to love it.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Munson said that if the show proved to be a blockbuster, an impoverished Afghanistan should reap more of the benefit.</p>
        <p>When an exhibition of 130 objects from Tutankhamen's tomb began touring in 2004, the Egyptian government set out to clear $10 million in every city visited and to take more than 50 percent of the gross revenue.</p>
        <p>Thomas Hoving, who pioneered the museum blockbuster concept as director of the Metropolitan Museum from 1967 to 1977, said Afghanistan should have held out for more. ''They don't get enough money,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''The Egyptians are getting all admissions, 80 percent of the sales in the shop, and they should have patterned it after that,'' Mr. Hoving said. ''Or a flat fee of a million a venue. The entity that ought to get most of the bucks should be Afghanistan.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcia declined to discuss how the traveling objects would be insured.</p>
        <p>He said the museums had each signed a letter of commitment regarding the artifacts, though only the National Gallery would confirm this. ''They've all expressed their keen interest and hope to be a venue,'' Mr. Garcia said, adding, ''We're working on contract negotiations.''</p>
        <p>The protocol signed by the society and the Afghan government stipulates that a new museum would be selected should any of the four museums not be able to play host to the exhibition. Ms. Munson said she was concerned that this could lead to the objects' being displayed at an insufficiently secure location.</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcia said the National Gallery was expected to be the lead museum, subject to completion of the agreement.</p>
        <p>Asked about its plans, the National Gallery said through a spokeswoman, ''The National Gallery of Art is interested but has nothing to confirm at this time.'' The Asian Art Museum and the Museum of Fine Arts both referred calls to the National Geographic Society. Harold Holzer, a spokesman for the Metropolitan Museum, would not comment on any agreement but added, ''This would make a valuable contribution to the exhibition schedule.''</p>
        <p>The accord signed last weekend calls for the exhibition to run at the National Gallery from May 25 to Sept. 7, 2008; at the Asian Art Museum from Oct. 17, 2008, to Jan. 25, 2009; at the Museum of Fine Arts from Feb. 22 to May 17, 2009; and at the Met from June 14 to Sept 17, 2009.</p>
        <p>''The timing sequence is subject to change till we become able to work through scheduling,'' Mr. Garcia said. The agreement with the society was signed by Afghanistan's information and culture minister, Abdul Karim Khoram, Mr. Garcia said.</p>
        <p>About 100 of the Bactrian gold objects were recently on display at the Musée Guimet in Paris, along with 131 objects from three other Afghan archaeological collections, and are now in Turin. The terms of that exhibition were unclear.</p>
        <p>The new show is to be overseen by Frederik Hiebert, an archaeologist formerly affiliated with the University of Pennsylvania who specializes in Silk Road artifacts and is a fellow at the National Geographic Society. Mr. Hiebert led the effort to compile an inventory of the collection in 2004. The National Endowment for the Humanities helped underwrite the project with two $30,000 grants.</p>
        <p>The society also paid for Omar Sul tan, an Afghan exile and archaeologist, to assist Mr. Hiebert in his dealings with the Afghans. Mr. Sultan became Afghanistan's deputy culture minister in January 2005, while still a consultant to the National Geographic Society. He also led a committee responsible for selecting the institutions that would display the objects.</p>
        <p>''Did this create a conflict of interest?'' Ms. Munson asked. ''We'll never know.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Garcia said in response: ''Our selection as organizer of the exhibition was made by the full Afghan exhibition committee, and approved by the minister of information and culture, Minister Khoram. The process had the full support of the entire committee as well as the ambassador to the U.S., Said Jawad.'' He said that the Afghan president, Hamid Karzai, ''was aware and fully supportive of the process.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Munson said that during a 2005 trip she made to Kabul, Omara Khan Massoudi, who leads Afghanistan's Museums Ministry and is now the director of the Kabul Museum, expressed concern about how the National Geographic Society had handled the inventory of the hoard.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Omara Khan Massoudi told me repeatedly and in no uncertain terms that he thought National Geographic had disrespected the Afghans and their objects during the inventory,'' she said. ''Massoudi said the Afghans had no more need for National Geographic. So that they're being awarded the exhibition means something has gone awry.''</p>
        <p>Asked about his position by telephone, Mr. Massoudi said, ''It's out of my hands,'' but declined to elaborate.</p>
        <p>Ms. Munson suggested that there should have been an open competition among museums for the show to assure maximal revenue to aid in Afghanistan's cultural reconstruction, and that the National Endowment for the Humanities should have exerted greater oversight.</p>
        <p>''Instead it seems we've ended up with a National Geographic monopoly and a very poor deal for the Afghans,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
