<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Red Bulls Import A Little Excellence</title>
    <meta content="06soccer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/sports/soccer/06soccer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852503"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER: EXTRA TIME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Chicago Bulls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Red Bulls</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Major League Soccer</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE6DE1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1121" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Red Bulls Import A Little Excellence</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Red Bulls Import a Little Excellence</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK BELL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gone are the shoulder-length hair and the wide headband, and the disdain for the generally miserable weather of the English midlands.</p>
        <p>What has not deserted Juan Pablo Ángel is his assemblage of wonderful skills with the soccer ball, born of hours of practice in his native Colombia, honed in the hardscrabble top league of Argentina, and finely tuned the past seven seasons in perhaps the best and most competitive circuit in the world, the English Premier League.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Juan Pablo Ángel of Colombia is is the most lethal goal scorer the New York/New Jersey area has seen since Giorgio Chinaglia played for the Cosmos.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gone are the shoulder-length hair and the wide headband, and the disdain for the generally miserable weather of the English midlands.</p>
        <p>What has not deserted Juan Pablo Ángel is his assemblage of wonderful skills with the soccer ball, born of hours of practice in his native Colombia, honed in the hardscrabble top league of Argentina, and finely tuned the past seven seasons in perhaps the best and most competitive circuit in the world, the English Premier League.</p>
        <p>Now Ángel, 31, is in Major League Soccer, a designated player of distinction only four games into his tenure with the Red Bulls. He is the most lethal goal scorer the New York/New Jersey area has seen since Giorgio Chinaglia of the Cosmos made Giants Stadium his predator's paradise in the late 1970s and early '80s.</p>
        <p>Ángel scored a masterly goal in a 3-0 victory against Chicago on May 24. As a cross rolled into the penalty area from the right side, he shielded the ball from Chris Armas, let it roll between his legs, then quickly turned and fired a shot past goalkeeper Matt Pickens for his second goal of the game.</p>
        <p>Ángel, who last week was named the league's top player in May after scoring four goals and two assists since joining the club from Aston Villa, has also seemed to make his teammates better with his skillful control, positioning, deft passing and high soccer I.Q. That has made the Red Bulls, who play at Toronto F.C. tonight, a serious challenger for the league title for the first time in the club's often-feeble history.</p>
        <p>''Honestly, I did not expect the league to be so good,'' Ángel said in a telephone interview yesterday before the Red Bulls (5-2-2, 17 points) left for Canada. ''This is a very tough league to play in. It's physical. It's fast. And it looks like the teams are pretty even, which makes it more competitive because in Europe most leagues only have a few top teams.''</p>
        <p>Ángel is one of the Red Bulls' two designated players (Claudio Reyna is the other) in a system, put in by the league this season, that allows teams to sign up to two players and pay them more than the team's modest budget of about $2 million for all players. The league will pay the first $400,000 of a designated player's salary; the club must pay the rest.</p>
        <p>While most of the attention, media hype and marketing mania have focused on David Beckham's impending arrival in Los Angeles, players like Ángel; the Brazilian Luciano Emilio at D.C. United; and two Argentines, Guillermo Schelotto in Columbus and Carlos Marinelli with Kansas City, are having an impact.</p>
        <p>Although the Galaxy will pay Beckham $5.5 million a year in large part because of his name and marketability, the Red Bulls are paying Ángel $1.5 million to score goals (he signed for this season and two more). He has come into the league and raised the level of play, while also giving fans a glimpse of the influence highly skilled players can have on their teammates.</p>
        <p>If Ángel has had a problem, it has been the general lack of support from the area's large Colombian population. The Red Bulls have averaged only 9,765 fans, second worst in the league, for home games at Giants Stadium.</p>
        <p>''I have been surprised that there are not the people in the stadium,'' Ángel said. ''I'm not used to that. But for me, it's no good to have the designative player name and not do the business on the field. As a veteran, I'm here to show the younger players that they have to perform day in and day out, and prepare for every single match. It's all about surviving in a competitive league.''</p>
        <p>Summer Tournaments</p>
        <p>The first of four international tournaments involving United States men's national teams, the Concacaf Gold Cup, begins tonight with a doubleheader at the Orange Bowl in Miami (Costa Rica-Canada and Guadeloupe-Haiti). The United States starts play tomorrow night in California against Guatemala (El Salvador faces Trinidad and Tobago in the second game of the doubleheader at the Home Depot Center in Carson). Friday night's games at Giants Stadium in East Rutherford, N.J., with Panama-Honduras followed by Mexico-Cuba, are expected to draw more than 50,000 fans. The tournament will be played in six United States cities, with the semifinals (June 21) and final (June 24) at Soldier Field in Chicago.</p>
        <p>After the Gold Cup, the United States and the Mexican national teams will travel to Venezuela as guest teams playing in Copa América (June 26-July 15), the South American championship. The United States is also making its final preparations for the FIFA U-20 World Cup (June 30-July 22) in Canada and the U-17 World Cup (Aug. 18-Sept. 9) in South Korea.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most interesting team in the Gold Cup is Guadeloupe, a collection of Caribbean islands that remains a French overseas department -- a colony, which means it is not a member of FIFA. Guadeloupe is an associate member of Concacaf, the regional confederation, and will be playing in its first international tournament on the senior level. Its small population, less than 500,000, has managed to send a handful of players to France to play for the national team and for some top club teams in Europe. That list includes Lilian Thuram, Louis Saha, William Gallas, Sylvain Wiltord and Mikael Sylvestre.</p>
        <p>But the greatest player produced by Guadeloupe was the stalwart defender Marius Trésor, who played for France in the 1978 and 1982 World Cups.</p>
        <p>More remarkably, midfielder/defender Jocelyn Angloma, who will turn 42 on Aug. 7, came out of retirement last year and is on the team's Gold Cup roster. He has played more than 400 games professionally in France for Rennes, Lille, Paris Saint-Germain and Marseille; in Italy for Torino and Inter Milan; and in Spain for Valencia.</p>
        <p>Although Angloma played 37 times internationally for France, he is permitted to play for his native Guadeloupe because he now plays for an amateur team.</p>
        <p>Notes</p>
        <p>The main training field used by United States national teams at the Home Depot Center has been named for Glenn Myernick, the former national team assistant coach. Myernick, a New Jersey native, died from a heart attack in October at age 41.</p>
        <p>The Sky Blue select women's team, a collection of professionals and amateurs, will play the national team of China in an exhibition match Tuesday night at Yurcak Field on the campus of Rutgers University in Piscataway, N.J. The select team will include Formiga (Brazil), Lena Mosebo (South Africa), Susanna Lehtinen (Finland) and Yael Averbuch (voted the top female player in the United States while playing at the University of North Carolina last season).</p>
        <p>SOCCER: EXTRA TIME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
