<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mechanical Problems Suspected in Crash That Killed Transplant Team</title>
    <meta content="06docs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/us/06docs.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852494"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lungs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Lake Michigan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">National Transportation Safety Board</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03EFDF1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="883" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mechanical Problems Suspected in Crash That Killed Transplant Team</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Transplant Team Dies in Jet Crash; Mechanical Problems Suspected</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICK BUNKLEY; Barbara Miner contributed reporting from Milwaukee, and Mary Chapman from Detroit.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Miner, Barbara; Bunkley, Nick; Chapman, Mary M</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, June 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What was meant to be a mission to save the life of a man in desperate need of a lung transplant ended instead on Monday in the deaths of four members of a medical team and two pilots of a plane that crashed while racing to fly the organs from Milwaukee to Michigan.</p>
        <p>Investigators from the National Transportation Safety Board said Tuesday that they thought mechanical difficulties, not a light rain or wind, caused the plane, an eight-seat Cessna jet, to slam into Lake Michigan at about 190 miles an hour on Monday afternoon, just minutes after taking off from General Mitchell International Airport in Milwaukee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four members of a medical team and two pilots died in a crash in Lake Michigan on Monday, as they rushed to perform a lung transplant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What was meant to be a mission to save the life of a man in desperate need of a lung transplant ended instead on Monday in the deaths of four members of a medical team and two pilots of a plane that crashed while racing to fly the organs from Milwaukee to Michigan.</p>
        <p>Investigators from the National Transportation Safety Board said Tuesday that they thought mechanical difficulties, not a light rain or wind, caused the plane, an eight-seat Cessna jet, to slam into Lake Michigan at about 190 miles an hour on Monday afternoon, just minutes after taking off from General Mitchell International Airport in Milwaukee.</p>
        <p>Besides the two pilots, the accident killed two transplant surgeons and two perfusionists -- specialists in transplanting organs -- from the University of Michigan Medical Center.</p>
        <p>The unidentified patient, who was being prepared for surgery to receive his long-awaited transplant when the crash occurred, remained in critical condition.</p>
        <p>Hospital officials vowed that their transplant program would not be interrupted, despite the loss to their transplant team. The surgeons were among 15 transplant surgeons at the University of Michigan. The perfusionists were among three full-time perfusionists.</p>
        <p>A second team of doctors had begun operating on the intended recipient of the organs about three hours before they received word of the crash and halted the procedure.</p>
        <p>''It's never a good thing to have a patient that is next in line for a transplant not get that transplanted organ,'' said Jeffrey Punch, director of the hospital's transplant center.</p>
        <p>Darrell Campbell, the university health system's chief of staff, said transplant candidates are ''usually desperately ill and even putting them to sleep is not helpful if you're not able to transplant the organ.''</p>
        <p>Officials would not release details about the patient or discuss his prognosis, but information about the recipient was posted on Internet message boards here on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The University of Michigan has 11 male patients on the waiting list for lungs, six of whom have been waiting at least three years for a match, according to the United Network for Organ Sharing, which operates the national Organ Procurement and Transplantation Network. All are at least 18 years old.</p>
        <p>The crash highlighted the inherent dangers for air ambulance crews, under pressure from transplant programs to move quickly when an organ becomes available. Both the safety board and the Federal Aviation Administration began scrutinizing medical flights several years ago after an increase in accidents.</p>
        <p>Susan Baker, an epidemiologist at the Bloomberg School of Public Health at Johns Hopkins University who has studied the industry, said that the rapid pace can sometimes compromise safety, although she saw no evidence of that happening in this case.</p>
        <p>''For the flight crews who are doing this routinely, they have a very high death rate,'' Dr. Baker said. ''It's a very high-risk occupation.''</p>
        <p>Monday's mission started at 7:30 a.m. when a hospital in Milwaukee alerted transplant programs in the Midwest that it had a donor for a pair of lungs. At the University of Michigan, Dr. Martinus Spoor and Dr. David Ashburn, both surgeons, evaluated the donor's records online and agreed to pick them up.</p>
        <p>The doctors were joined several hours later by two perfusionists, Richard Chenault II and Richard Lapensee, and all four sped to Willow Run Airport, a cargo terminal in Ypsilanti, Mich., about 15 miles east of the hospital.</p>
        <p>From there, they flew to Milwaukee in the Cessna, a 550 Citation II, which the university leases for long-distance medical flights.</p>
        <p>After Dr. Spoor removed the lungs from the donor they were packaged and loaded onto the plane for the 227-mile flight back, which normally takes about 40 minutes. A helicopter was waiting at Willow Run to collect the team and the lungs and transport them directly to the hospital. Experts say lungs must be transplanted within about four hours of their removal.</p>
        <p>The plane took off at 3:58 p.m. local time, but five minutes later one of the pilots reported a control problem known as trim runaway, which can make a plane difficult to steer, the safety board said.</p>
        <p>Pilots received clearance to return to the airport, where a runway was closed for an emergency landing. But while making a left turn at an altitude of 4,000 feet, the plane disappeared from radar view, investigators said.</p>
        <p>The pilots were identified as Dennis Hoyes and William Serra, who work for Marlin Air.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ashburn was a resident in pediatric cardiothoracic surgery who was scheduled to begin a fellowship this summer. Dr. Spoor, a thoracic surgeon, had been at the university for five years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lapensee, who also worked as a medic and a firefighter, was an aircraft buff who joined the transplant program so he could ''get free plane rides and do something rewarding, help to save people,'' said Jon Ichesco, the fire chief in Ypsilanti.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chenault, who joined the university in 1985, received the United States Department of Health and Human Services distinguished Medal of Honor last year for his efforts to increase organ donation.</p>
        <p>Dr. Campbell said Mr. Chenault was skilled at comforting families who had lost loved ones and were preparing to donate their organs. ''Now we're left to do the same thing with his family,'' Dr. Campbell said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
