<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HBO Moves to Fill the Executive Void Left by Chief's Recent Departure</title>
    <meta content="06hbo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/business/media/06hbo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852508"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Home Box Office</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Time Warner Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Albrecht, Chris</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DE1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="849" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HBO Moves to Fill the Executive Void Left by Chief's Recent Departure</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">HBO Moves to Fill Executive Void</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HBO announced a new lineup of four top corporate officers yesterday to succeed Chris Albrecht, the chief executive who resigned last month. The group will be led by Bill Nelson as the chairman and chief executive.</p>
        <p>The channel elevated three other executives -- Richard Plepler, Eric Kessler and Hal Akselrad -- to the new title of co-presidents, all with specific duties at the pay cable channel with its 30 million subscribers. Additionally, HBO named Michael Lombardo as president of its programming group and head of its West Coast office.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bill Nelson and three other top executives with long careers at HBO will replace Chris Albrecht, who resigned.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HBO announced a new lineup of four top corporate officers yesterday to succeed Chris Albrecht, the chief executive who resigned last month. The group will be led by Bill Nelson as the chairman and chief executive.</p>
        <p>The channel elevated three other executives -- Richard Plepler, Eric Kessler and Hal Akselrad -- to the new title of co-presidents, all with specific duties at the pay cable channel with its 30 million subscribers. Additionally, HBO named Michael Lombardo as president of its programming group and head of its West Coast office.</p>
        <p>The announcements were made by the two top executives of HBO's parent company, Time Warner: Richard D. Parsons, the chairman, and Jeffrey L. Bewkes, the president, who is also a former chief executive of HBO.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bewkes said in a telephone interview that he was essentially putting the future of the company in the hands of the team that has been running it for about 20 years.</p>
        <p>''It has always been a team at HBO,'' Mr. Bewkes said. ''HBO is on a winning streak and we'd like to keep it going.''</p>
        <p>All the promoted executives have had long careers at HBO, with all but Mr. Plepler having joined the channel in the 1980s. Mr. Plepler joined HBO in 1992.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nelson has been acting as the chief executive since Mr. Albrecht's ouster, which took place in the aftermath of his arrest in Las Vegas on charges of assaulting his girlfriend.</p>
        <p>Previously, Mr. Nelson had been the longtime chief operating officer for HBO, in charge of most of the channel's finances. He will continue to oversee that part of the business, and the three co-presidents will report to him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bewkes said Mr. Nelson had been instrumental in establishing HBO's video-on-demand business, which Mr. Bewkes called ''the first of its kind.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Plepler is taking on the most significant new role, Mr. Bewkes said, as the executive in overall charge of HBO's programming, which has long been essential to its success. Mr. Plepler has risen from the top corporate communications officer in the company to become an executive vice president and its most visible executive in New York. Mr. Albrecht had been based mainly in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>''Richard is moving to have full program oversight from being half-involved with the programming decisions,'' Mr. Bewkes said. ''Richard did quite a bit of shaping of program ideas previously. Chris relied on him quite a bit.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Plepler will continue to oversee the channel's media relations department, Mr. Bewkes said, ''staying in charge of the overall image of HBO's content.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kessler's new role will also be an extension of his previous duties managing the channel's distribution and marketing divisions. Mr. Bewkes said Mr. Kessler's main added responsibilities would be coordinating HBO's ''new digital initiatives, in areas like downloads of programs,'' as well as overseeing the company's international operations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Akselrad has been HBO's top corporate lawyer and will continue to manage the company's legal and business affairs. He has been in charge of negotiating film acquisitions for the channel and will now add supervision of HBO's technology group.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lombardo has been the chief deal maker for HBO in Hollywood as its head of business affairs on the West Coast. Mr. Bewkes said he would oversee the program department, reporting to Mr. Plepler. But he said that the heads of the separate HBO departments, including Sheila Nevins on documentaries, Colin Callendar on original movies, Ross Greenberg on sports and Carolyn Strauss on series, would remain ''largely independent.''</p>
        <p>HBO declined to make the newly appointed executives available for interviews yesterday.</p>
        <p>In a statement, Mr. Parsons said, ''Today's appointments highlight the depth and strength of HBO's senior leadership.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bewkes said the promotions reflected his conclusion that ''HBO has a deep bench.''</p>
        <p>All the executives promoted yesterday had served under Mr. Albrecht and under Mr. Bewkes before that. None have the public profile that Mr. Albrecht enjoyed, because he was the chief programmer when HBO added its most celebrated series like ''The Sopranos'' and ''Sex and the City.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bewkes said: ''We'll all miss Chris. He was a valued colleague and did brilliant work. Everyone learned a lot from Chris.''</p>
        <p>But he noted that when he himself took over as chief executive he was following Michael Fuchs, who had become one of the best-known executives in television.</p>
        <p>''I faced the same questions when Michael left,'' Mr. Bewkes said.</p>
        <p>Executives at HBO have long said that the channel operates unlike other media outlets and so had expected that the management taking over for Mr. Albrecht would come from inside the company.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bewkes said: ''At Time Warner, we always think about succession and we have plans in place. If we need somebody from outside, we go out and get them. But in this case we thought that the talent was inside.''</p>
        <p>He acknowledged that the transition was taking place at a moment when HBO is about to lose the most popular program it has ever presented, ''The Sopranos,'' which concludes Sunday night. But, he said, ''I feel very good about what's coming up at HBO.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
