<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>First Mound Session Pleases Mets' Martínez</title>
    <meta content="06pedro" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/sports/baseball/06pedro.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852580"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEEDD1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>First Mound Session Pleases Mets' Martínez</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Martínez Is Taking Awhile to Find His Comfort Zone</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE NOBLES</byline>
      <dateline>PORT ST. LUCIE, Fla., June 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an obscure warm-up area at the Mets' minor league camp Tuesday, Pedro Martínez pitched off a mound for the first time in more than eight months. He came away feeling he had passed a basic first test toward rebuilding his career.</p>
        <p>The right-handed Martínez, out possibly until August as he recovers from shoulder surgery last October, threw 38 pitches.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pedro Martínez came away feeling he had passed a basic first test toward rebuilding his career after his first pitches in eight months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In an obscure warm-up area at the Mets' minor league camp Tuesday, Pedro Martínez pitched off a mound for the first time in more than eight months. He came away feeling he had passed a basic first test toward rebuilding his career.</p>
        <p>The right-handed Martínez, out possibly until August as he recovers from shoulder surgery last October, threw 38 pitches.</p>
        <p>After Martínez threw seven warm-up pitches, the Mets divided his session into innings, allowing him a three-minute pause when he reached his 15th pitch. He said the goal had been a total of 25 pitches, but he said he felt so good that he wanted to keep going.</p>
        <p>Randy Niemann, the Mets' rehabilitation pitching coordinator, blurted ''that's enough'' after Martínez threw 16 pitches in the second inning.</p>
        <p>Martínez, 35, who is recovering from a torn rotator cuff, acknowledged some tentativeness. He said he thought of Mets reliever Duaner Sánchez, who in spring training had a setback from his shoulder injury sustained last season and needed surgery. Martínez said he thought the Mets had rushed him back.</p>
        <p>''I was just trying to let my natural release take over,'' Martínez said. ''More than anything, I was just making sure that nothing happened to me like happened to Duaner. I was hesitant to actually get to the mound and see how it felt. I thought I was going to be rushing and sliding over.''</p>
        <p>So Martínez said he ''held back'' some in the first inning. His personal trainer, Chris Correnti, one of several people following him around, implored him to trust his legs. ''After that,'' Martínez said, ''it felt right at home.''</p>
        <p>Niemann said Martínez would pitch off a mound again Friday providing he had no setbacks. Niemann plans to add more repetitions as Martínez shows he can handle them. Rick Peterson, the Mets' pitching coach, has estimated that Martínez may require six to eight bullpen sessions before they advance to the next phase.</p>
        <p>''We just wanted him to get on the mound and feel comfortable and get the delivery we all know Pedro has,'' Niemann said. ''He got to the point where it felt good. That's really what we all wanted to see.''</p>
        <p>It did not take long for the news of Martínez's productive day to reach Mets Manager Willie Randolph, who hopes to have him through the regular-season stretch and into the postseason.</p>
        <p>''The fact he is on the mound is very encouraging,'' Randolph told reporters.</p>
        <p>Martínez has 206 major league victories in 15 seasons. He was an atypical 9-8 for the Mets last season, with a bloated 4.48 earned run average. He said that with his arm bothering him, he debated whether to come back last season in September after missing a month with a calf injury.</p>
        <p>That example, he said, taught him a lesson.</p>
        <p>''Before I came back in September, I had a meeting with my teammates, and they all agreed that if I didn't feel fine, don't get out there,'' he said. ''And I still went over their worries and got hurt, got really hurt, got banged up. After they saw that, I'm pretty sure they want me to just be healthy.''</p>
        <p>Martínez arrived at the minor league clubhouse at 10:50 a.m. Tuesday in a white Range Rover and stayed in the weight room until 12:30, when he went onto the field for agility exercises. He finally stepped on a mound at 1:10 p.m., with a cluster of photographers shooting away.</p>
        <p>Martínez threw all fastballs Tuesday, and nobody seemed concerned about his velocity. That will be for another day. Among the spectators were two other rehabilitating Mets, Sánchez and Juan Padilla, who pulled up in a golf cart to provide encouragement.</p>
        <p>Martínez's catcher was Danny Cummings, who played at Class A Brooklyn last season. Asked afterward if he thought he could have gotten a hit off Martínez, Cummings thought a moment, then said with a sheepish smile: ''Yes, I'd like to say I would. But don't tell him I said that.''</p>
        <p>Martínez would probably not mind.</p>
        <p>Tuesday was solely about getting a feel for his craft again. And when it was over, Martínez stood in the minor league clubhouse with a smile on his face. ''I'm really excited and happy with the way everything went,'' he said. ''I'm very optimistic the way I feel.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
