<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Glavine Does All He Can, But Mets Don't Do Enough</title>
    <meta content="06mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/sports/baseball/06mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070608T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852609"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Philadelphia Phillies</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Glavine, Tom</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Utley, Chase</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2DC1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1024" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Glavine Does All He Can, But Mets Don't Do Enough</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Glavine Does His Part, but the Mets Don’t Help Him Out</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Tom Glavine were granted three wishes, he might consider bypassing the rigmarole of the first two and get right down to business. He would like to have won his 300th career game three weeks ago -- as soon as possible, in other words -- so that life can return to normal.</p>
        <p>But right now, that milestone seems as far away as his suburban Atlanta home. Through little fault of Glavine's, the Mets have lost the last three times he has pitched, including last night's 4-2 setback in 11 innings against the Philadelphia Phillies at Shea Stadium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chase Utley’s leadoff homer in the 11th inning propelled the Philadelphia Phillies to a victory at Shea Stadium and robbed Tom Glavine of a win.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If Tom Glavine were granted three wishes, he might consider bypassing the rigmarole of the first two and get right down to business. He would like to have won his 300th career game three weeks ago -- as soon as possible, in other words -- so that life can return to normal.</p>
        <p>But right now, that milestone seems as far away as his suburban Atlanta home. Through little fault of Glavine's, the Mets have lost the last three times he has pitched, including last night's 4-2 setback in 11 innings against the Philadelphia Phillies at Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>Glavine pitched seven strong innings, but the score stayed at 2-2 until Chase Utley belted a leadoff homer against Pedro Feliciano in the 11th, and the Phillies tacked on another run to win almost in spite of themselves. They overcame a dropped fly ball in the ninth inning. Earlier in the game, one of their runners was picked off and, in an especially comic moment, two others stood on third base simultaneously.</p>
        <p>But at least Philadelphia had the good fortune of having Utley leading off the 11th. To that point, left-handed hitters had hit .087 (2 for 23) this season against Feliciano, who shook off Paul Lo Duca's sign for a slider in favor of a sinker. Utley blasted that 1-0 pitch into the seats in left-center field. For Utley it was, 10 months later, a little revenge against the pitcher who ended his 35-game hitting streak at Shea last August. ''Sometimes I get him; this time he got me,'' Feliciano said.</p>
        <p>Not even the return of Carlos Beltrán, who had missed the last three games with a bruised right knee, could invigorate the Mets' slumbering offense. Freely admitting he was not playing at full strength, Beltrán went 0 for 5, including a flyout to the left-field fence in the seventh that could have propelled Glavine toward victory.</p>
        <p>Missing Moises Alou and Shawn Green, the Mets have scored 15 runs in their last six games, going 2-4. They went 3 for 13 with runners in scoring position last night, and José Reyes was picked off trying to steal third with one out in the seventh.</p>
        <p>''We're obviously not picking up a lot of big runs, but I don't think it's a rut,'' Manager Willie Randolph said.</p>
        <p>That explanation is little consolation to Glavine, whose chase for 300 victories has slowed to a stroll. Stuck at 295 for the third consecutive start, Glavine will most likely get six more starts before the All-Star Game break to notch the five victories he needs. Through 13 starts, Glavine has as many no-decisions as victories (five), and in his last three he has opposed three of the more accomplished pitchers in the National League in John Smoltz, Barry Zito and Jamie Moyer. The Mets have scored a total of two runs during the 20 innings he has pitched.</p>
        <p>''It's hard going out there and pitching well and you're not getting the results,'' Glavine said. ''I don't know how to put it any differently than that.''</p>
        <p>Asked if he felt his teammates, aware of his quest, were pressing at the plate when he pitches, he said: ''I'm not sure the guys are feeling, I don't ask what they're feeling. I just go out there and pitch.''</p>
        <p>In a reprise of their April 12 matchup, when, for a short time, they held the record for the oldest combined age of any opposing left-handed starting pitchers in baseball history, Glavine and Moyer each allowed two runs and eight hits over seven innings.</p>
        <p>The symmetry was a natural extension of his last start, when Glavine and Zito threw the same number of strikes and pitches, but it didn't end there. Glavine had to deal with the fate he endured in his game against Zito. A pitch away from getting out of an inning, he allowed the Phillies to rally with two outs and no one on base, and the hits were of the dink-and-dunk variety.</p>
        <p>''Personally, not a lot of things are going my way,'' Glavine said.</p>
        <p>For a change, Glavine threw a pitch with a lead, even if it didn't last long. The Mets went up, 2-0, in the second when, with runners on second and third and no outs, Lo Duca blooped a single to shallow center. Playing deep, Aaron Rowand took a stutter step before throwing home, and the extra time cost him a chance at throwing out David Wright, who scored the second run only seconds after Carlos Delgado crossed the plate with the first.</p>
        <p>Glavine breezed through the first two innings -- and the first two hitters of the third -- before Jimmy Rollins reached on an infield single. Shane Victorino followed by poking an outside pitch over Delgado's head and down the first-base line for a double.</p>
        <p>Even if Glavine was making the pitches he wanted, he could blame only himself for the hit that knocked in the Phillies' runs. Facing Utley, who entered the at-bat 2 for 19 against him, Glavine left a pitch over the inside third of the plate that Utley hammered to right for a two-run single. Ryan Howard broke his bat on a single to center, but Glavine struck out Pat Burrell on an 86 mile-an-hour cutter to end the inning.</p>
        <p>Glavine then scattered four hits over five scoreless innings and watched from the dugout as no one crossed the plate again until the 11th.</p>
        <p>''Right now, I'm in one of those ruts where wins are hard to come by,'' Glavine said.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Shawn Green, out since May 26 with a broken right foot, said he would have a better idea when he would return after visiting the doctor this morning. Green is walking without pain, and if doctors clear him to start running, he said he hoped to come off the disabled list Sunday to play against Detroit.  Moises Alou had fluid drained from his left quadriceps on Monday and was scheduled to be examined before last night's game. If he can resume running and hitting within the next few days, Alou may serve as the designated hitter this weekend.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 8, 2007, Friday  A picture caption on Wednesday with a sports article about the Mets' 4-2 extra-innings loss to the Phillies carried an incorrect credit. The photograph of a play at home plate involving the Mets' David Wright and the Philliles' Carlos Ruiz was by Ray Stubblebine of Reuters, not Barton Silverman of The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 8, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Wednesday with a sports article about the Mets' 4-2 extra-innings loss to the Phillies carried an incorrect credit. The photograph of a play at home plate involving the Mets' David Wright and the Philliles' Carlos Ruiz was by Ray Stubblebine of Reuters, not Barton Silverman of The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
