<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Talking the Dream, Growing the Brand</title>
    <meta content="06perr" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/arts/television/06perr.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852477"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Perry, Tyler</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DF1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1467" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Talking the Dream, Growing the Brand</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Talking the Dream, Growing the Brand</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICIA R. LEE</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What looks from the outside like roughly 70,000 square feet of warehouse space near the King Center is the home of Tyler Perry Studios, where Mr. Perry is living his dream of running a media empire. On this day in late May, the dream meant talking and talking, so he really wanted something for his chapped lips.</p>
        <p>''I got you,'' a woman in the front row of the studio cooed, reaching into her handbag for some ChapStick. The bubbly, diverse audience laughed as Mr. Perry joked about calling security. It was a break in a long day of taping three 30-minute talk-show segments. One was about the efforts to help New Orleans residents; one focused on his 2005 film, ''Diary of a Mad Black Woman''; and yet another introduced the cast of his new TV show, ''Tyler Perry's House of Payne,'' a comedy about an extended family that has its premiere on TBS tonight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If “House of Payne” and the talk show “The Tyler Perry Show” hit their mark, it will represent the continuation of the Perry media juggernaut.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What looks from the outside like roughly 70,000 square feet of warehouse space near the King Center is the home of Tyler Perry Studios, where Mr. Perry is living his dream of running a media empire. On this day in late May, the dream meant talking and talking, so he really wanted something for his chapped lips.</p>
        <p>''I got you,'' a woman in the front row of the studio cooed, reaching into her handbag for some ChapStick. The bubbly, diverse audience laughed as Mr. Perry joked about calling security. It was a break in a long day of taping three 30-minute talk-show segments. One was about the efforts to help New Orleans residents; one focused on his 2005 film, ''Diary of a Mad Black Woman''; and yet another introduced the cast of his new TV show, ''Tyler Perry's House of Payne,'' a comedy about an extended family that has its premiere on TBS tonight.</p>
        <p>Viewers in some cities saw a version of ''House of Payne'' last year as part of test marketing for the series, which now has new sets and additional characters.</p>
        <p>If ''House of Payne'' and the talk show ''The Tyler Perry Show'' hit their mark, that will represent the continuation of the Perry media juggernaut. It started with the success in 1998 of his urban morality play ''I Know I've Been Changed,'' which was followed by a string of similar plays blending soap opera, religion and humor with serious subjects like abuse and drug use. Then came moneymaking films like ''Diary'' and ''Madea's Family Reunion'' in 2006 and last year's best-selling book ''Don't Make a Black Woman Take Off Her Earrings: Madea's Uninhibited Commentaries on Love and Life.'' The message in all the stories is that faith and perseverance can lead to redemption and that people don't need to end up where they started.</p>
        <p>''I saw a need for positive, inspiring entertainment,'' Mr. Perry said in an interview in his studio, ''especially in the African-American community.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Perry's plays have made more than $150 million, according to his business associates. His three films (''Daddy's Little Girls'' was in theaters this year), released by Lionsgate, have grossed almost $145 million in total. The cash register keeps ringing for the DVDs of his stage plays and films, which have sold more than 11 million copies.</p>
        <p>A major character in the Perry universe is Madea (black Southern-speak for ''Mother Dear''). She is the muscular, 37-year-old, 6-foot-6 Mr. Perry in a fat suit, a wig and huge glasses. That blunt-spoken, pistol-packing grandmother has made Mr. Perry, who grew up poor and abused in New Orleans, rich and famous.</p>
        <p>''Tyler Perry found a niche and created something new by figuring out how to get those folks out of their living rooms and out of their churches and into the theaters,'' said Mark Anthony Neal, a professor of black popular culture at Duke University and director of its Institute for Critical U.S. Studies.</p>
        <p>''He finds a way among the comedy to tell these moralistic tales: Black women, keep your legs closed. Black men, take care of your children,'' Mr. Neal said. ''It creates a space for a non-hip-hop audience that you see in the incredible growth of ministers like T. D. Jakes, a 24-hour gospel music station and black Christian fiction.''</p>
        <p>TBS is betting on similar success for ''House of Payne,'' a 30-minute comedy-drama about Curtis Payne (LaVan Davis), a grumpy, middle-aged firefighter, and his wife, Ella (Cassi Davis). The couple share their home with their trifling college-student son, Calvin (Lance Gross), as well as Curtis's nephew, C J (Allen Payne), and Malik and Jazmine, C J's two children. In subsequent episodes it turns out that Janine, C J's crack-addicted wife, burned down their home.</p>
        <p>The talk show, which Mr. Perry expects to broadcast on the Internet, is his way to stay connected to fans loyal to his message of redemption through the help of God and family, he said. These days, the single Mr. Perry lives mostly in Atlanta and also has a home in the Hollywood Hills. But he said his brand of entertainment was not exactly familiar to most film and TV studios.</p>
        <p>''I went to L.A. and pitched to a room full of studio execs,'' Mr. Perry told the audience in his studio that day about how ''House of Payne'' got started. ''They told me I couldn't say 'Jesus' on television and nobody would watch it.''</p>
        <p>As he chatted with the cast, Mr. Perry turned to his audience. ''If you give up on your dream and stop right where you are, you never know what's around that corner,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That was the belief that kept him going during his early days, he said, when he took his plays on the road and spread the word through churches, barbershops, black radio. Inspired by an episode of ''The Oprah Winfrey Show'' that said writing was cathartic, Mr. Perry began scribbling plays in a notebook. He eventually booked them into urban theaters, where he would be director, producer and, often, star.</p>
        <p>Niyi Coker Jr., a professor of theater and media studies at the University of Missouri-St. Louis, said Mr. Perry's work was filling a void in many mediums. ''It's not sophisticated or theatrical in the Western context,'' he said, but it strikes a deep chord with Mr. Perry's audience, which does not see their stories in many places.</p>
        <p>Serious, soft-spoken, with a calm demeanor, Mr. Perry said he was now creating content for his own future TV network. ''It would be somewhere when you turn it on, no matter what you tuned into, it uplifts you, you feel lighter, you feel better,'' he said. He has shot episodes of a second comedy series, ''Meet the Browns'' (based on one of his plays and a film due out in 2008), about a man who turns an old house into a home for the elderly.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Perry, ''House of Payne'' is but another example of doing things his own way. He took the highly unusual step of using his own $5 million to make 10 episodes of the show, which is shot at his studio. Working with the television distribution company Debmar-Mercury, he put together a deal to give those episodes to stations in 10 cities across the country so the series could be test marketed last year. High ratings created a bidding war. TBS won broadcast rights to the show exclusively until September 2008.</p>
        <p>The usual route for a TV series is to find a network, sell 13 episodes or so, and cross fingers that the show continues and finds its way to syndication.</p>
        <p>Steve Koonin, president of Turner Entertainment Networks, which owns TBS, said, ''What Tyler is trying to do is in the spirit of great family comedy that is colorblind.''</p>
        <p>But is it art? Some critics don't think so, and some people say they find Mr. Perry's work demeaning to African-Americans.</p>
        <p>Several Web site forums and blogs have featured lively debates about whether Mr. Perry and the comedians Eddie Murphy, Jamie Foxx and Martin Lawrence are culturally castrating black men by playing women. Madea seems to be a particular flash point.</p>
        <p>''It's not funny,'' Jill Nelson, the writer and cultural critic, said in an interview. She took Mr. Perry and the comedians to task in the May issue of Essence magazine. ''It's a disturbing kind of body snatching,'' Ms. Nelson said, ''and generates contempt for and ridicule of and erasure of black women as complex and substantive.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Perry said he does not worry about the criticism. He is not making fun of overweight black women, he said.</p>
        <p>He admires Lorraine Hansberry and August Wilson, Mr. Perry said, but their acceptance by non-African-Americans does not mean that theirs is the only way to tell a story.</p>
        <p>It could be that Mr. Perry will help Hollywood broaden the range of what is considered marketable, said Michael Paseornek, president of film production at Lionsgate. ''Tyler has changed Hollywood in that the studio is recognizing the value in a market they never saw before,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In addition to ''Meet the Browns,'' the studio plans to release more films from Mr. Perry ''Why Did I Get Married?,'' starring Janet Jackson, is about couples re-examining their vows; it is scheduled to be in theaters in November. ''Madea Goes to Jail'' is scheduled for release in 2009.</p>
        <p>One man cannot reinvent Hollywood, but perhaps he has provoked a conversation, Mr. Perry said. And his new television show will allow him into millions of homes unfamiliar with his kind of stories.</p>
        <p>''We've been told that what sells is a lot of negativity,'' Mr. Perry said, ''but in this country we're looking for answers to a lot of questions, for the way out, how to get through the pain.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
