<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Panel Asks Official About Politics in Hiring</title>
    <meta content="06justice" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/washington/06justice.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852505"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Civil Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Justice Department</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Leahy, Patrick J</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E4DE1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Panel Asks Official About Politics in Hiring</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Panel Asks Official About Politics in Hiring</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC LIPTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipton, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A senior Justice Department official acknowledged to Senate investigators Tuesday that he once bragged about his success in hiring conservative Republican lawyers onto his staff that handled civil rights cases.</p>
        <p>The admission came in a testy three-hour hearing, where Senator Patrick J. Leahy, the Vermont Democrat who is chairman of the Judiciary Committee, at times yelled at the witness, Bradley J. Schlozman. Congress has been investigating the dismissals last year of nine United States attorneys, and allegations that the Bush administration has allowed politics to influence the work of the Justice Department.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Justice Department official acknowledged that he once bragged about hiring conservative lawyers onto his staff that handled civil rights cases.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A senior Justice Department official acknowledged to Senate investigators Tuesday that he once bragged about his success in hiring conservative Republican lawyers onto his staff that handled civil rights cases.</p>
        <p>The admission came in a testy three-hour hearing, where Senator Patrick J. Leahy, the Vermont Democrat who is chairman of the Judiciary Committee, at times yelled at the witness, Bradley J. Schlozman. Congress has been investigating the dismissals last year of nine United States attorneys, and allegations that the Bush administration has allowed politics to influence the work of the Justice Department.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schlozman insisted that he did not violate the civil service rules that bar taking politics into consideration when hiring career lawyers, as a second former Justice official, Monica M. Goodling, conceded doing to House investigators last month.</p>
        <p>But he did say that he actively recruited job applicants from conservative groups like the Federalist Society and the Heritage Foundation and advised some Republican candidates to remove references to their conservative background from their résumés so that would not be held against them by others at the department.</p>
        <p>Former career lawyers in the civil rights division have charged that it turned decidedly more partisan in the Bush administration.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schlozman also acknowledged ordering changes in the performance evaluations of some longtime lawyers who were not perceived to be Bush administration loyalists.</p>
        <p>''If I didn't change what I felt to be an inaccurate evaluation, I'd be shirking my own responsibility,'' said Mr. Schlozman, who joined the Justice Department in 2001, shortly after the Bush administration took over.</p>
        <p>The five senators present for Tuesday's hearing -- only Democrats showed up -- made it clear they had little respect for Mr. Schlozman, openly mocking him at times.</p>
        <p>''I'm glad to hear how spectacular you were,'' Mr. Leahy said, after Mr. Schlozman ran through his accomplishments since joining the department. ''It makes you sometimes wonder what we ever have to worry about at the Department of Justice.'' Mr. Schlozman currently serves as associate counsel to the director of the office at Justice headquarters that supervises United States attorneys.</p>
        <p>The Democrats took turns holding up a manual of department rules, asking Mr. Schlozman, who left department headquarters for a year to become the interim United States attorney in Kansas City, Mo., why his office there filed a fraud case against former employees of a liberal group that registers voters just a week before the 2006 election.</p>
        <p>The manual, the senators pointed out, said that ''most, if not all, investigations of an alleged election crime must await the end of the election,'' to avoid influencing the outcome.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schlozman, 36, who kept his voice low and his demeanor polite through the hostile questioning, said he was aware of this rule. But he said he had been given approval by the head of the Justice Department election crimes section to move ahead.</p>
        <p>''I didn't think this was going to have any impact on any election,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Then Senator Russ Feingold, Democrat of Wisconsin, read a news release issued by the Republican Party in Missouri just after the case was filed, which accused the voter registration group of trying ''to cause chaos and controversy at the polls in order to help Democrats to try to steal next week's elections.''</p>
        <p>''Would you say that this statement was intended to effect voters' decisions?'' Mr. Feingold asked.</p>
        <p>''Senator, I can't speak for anybody else,'' Mr. Schlozman replied.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schlozman, who had not tried a criminal or civil case before coming to the Justice Department, rapidly moved up the ranks like Ms. Goodling and D. Kyle Sampson, the attorney general's former chief of staff, the other young conservative lawyers who have become a focus of Congressional investigators.</p>
        <p>He started as an adviser to the deputy attorney general, then was promoted in May 2003 to assistant attorney general in the civil rights division, whose duties include supervising voting-rights cases. For five months he was the acting head of the division.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Schlozman was in the civil rights division, he approved a Justice Department document endorsing a new Georgia voter identification law that most members of his own staff had concluded would probably discourage poor minority voters from going to the polls.</p>
        <p>Under questioning, Mr. Schlozman defended the decision on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schlozman also acknowledged, in response to questions from Senator Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York, that he tried to change the makeup of the office staff and that he had once boasted that he had been able to hire a certain number of conservative lawyers. But he repeated he never hired career lawyers based on their politics.</p>
        <p>''These individuals, senator, were not hired because they were Republican,'' he told Mr. Schumer, who responded, ''Mr. Schlozman, it sure seems a contradiction to me.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
