<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Six-Day War, Plus 40 Years</title>
    <meta content="l06mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852532"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EEDE1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1052" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Six-Day War, Plus 40 Years</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Tom Segev poses some interesting ''what if'' questions in connection with Israel's capture of East Jerusalem and the West Bank in the Six-Day War in 1967 (''What if Israel Had Turned Back?,'' Op-Ed, June 5). Here are some additional ''what ifs'' that deserve equal consideration:</p>
        <p>What if the Arabs had accepted the United Nations partition plan of 1947, dividing the remainder of mandatory Palestine into a Jewish state and an Arab state? What if in the aftermath of Israel's 1948 war of independence the Arab states had assimilated the refugees into their societies, rather than leave them to fester in refugee camps for generations?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Tom Segev poses some interesting ''what if'' questions in connection with Israel's capture of East Jerusalem and the West Bank in the Six-Day War in 1967 (''What if Israel Had Turned Back?,'' Op-Ed, June 5). Here are some additional ''what ifs'' that deserve equal consideration:</p>
        <p>What if the Arabs had accepted the United Nations partition plan of 1947, dividing the remainder of mandatory Palestine into a Jewish state and an Arab state? What if in the aftermath of Israel's 1948 war of independence the Arab states had assimilated the refugees into their societies, rather than leave them to fester in refugee camps for generations?</p>
        <p>What if the Arabs had created a Palestinian state in the West Bank between 1948 and 1967, when it was held by Jordan? What if Jordan had heeded Israel's pleas at the outbreak of the Six-Day War and not joined the attack?</p>
        <p>What if the Palestinians had accepted the ''Clinton parameters'' in late 2000, calling for the creation of a Palestinian state on more than 90 percent of the West Bank, all of Gaza and with East Jerusalem as its capital? What if in the wake of Israel's unilateral disengagement from Gaza in 2005 the Palestinians had sought to create a viable society rather than a launching pad for rockets aimed at Israel?</p>
        <p>And what if the Saudi peace proposal was not premised on the ''right of return'' of Palestinians into pre-1967 Israel?</p>
        <p>Rather than young Israelis questioning why their parents didn't turn back in 1967, young Palestinians should be asking why, at every opportunity, their parents have chosen conflict over compromise.</p>
        <p>Gregg M. Mashberg  New Rochelle, N.Y., June 5, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Writing about young Israelis, Tom Segev concludes: ''With fewer hopes and lower expectations they just may be able to make life at least somewhat more livable for both Israelis and Palestinians. Given the present circumstances, that would be no small accomplishment.''</p>
        <p>I pray this doesn't mean accepting another 40 years of occupation! It is impossible to imagine in today's world that an ''occupation'' can last 40 years.</p>
        <p>I was 7 years old in Ramallah in 1967, but I was lucky that my family was able to move to Southern California. Imagine a Palestinian child living his entire life under occupation -- with no real opportunity and no real rights of citizenship.</p>
        <p>Israelis won the war in 1967. They could have annexed all the land and made a citizen of everyone (they still can). But they always wanted the land, not the people. Where's the morality in that? That's the question I wish Israelis were asking themselves.</p>
        <p>Peter Salameh  Carlsbad, Calif., June 5, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The major obstacle to peace between Israelis and Palestinians is not Israel's control of East Jerusalem, despite what Tom Segev writes. There is no peace today in the region because of Hamas's firing Qassam rockets into the south of Israel and the continued threat of Hezbollah's launching rockets into the north, as it did all last summer.</p>
        <p>This, in conjunction with weak Palestinian leadership and the continued teaching of anti-Israel propaganda in the Palestinian school system, contributes largely to the complete lack of even a vision for a peaceful co-existence.</p>
        <p>Stuart Pilichowski  Mevaseret Zion, Israel  June 5, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Tom Segev points in his article to ''Islamism'' as the ''driving force'' among Palestinians that is helping perpetuate the conflict. But the political history of the Palestinian struggle, which spans 70 years at least, points to national aspirations as the moving force behind the Palestinian movement.</p>
        <p>These aspirations were and remain overwhelmingly secular, with the right to self-determination at the cornerstone of the Palestinian political movement, despite the victory of Hamas in the recent elections in the West Bank and Gaza.</p>
        <p>The means of achieving these aspirations have changed over time, and will likely continue to evolve: from family and tribal affiliations in the 1940s and 50s, to the socialist and quasi-Marxist movements of the 60s and 70s to the secular Fatah movement in the 80s and 90s and the recent rise in religious parties like Hamas.</p>
        <p>To reduce the driving force behind the Palestinian political and military struggle to religious extremism contributes to the continuous misunderstanding of the ''Palestinian other,'' thus decreasing the chances of a mutual peaceful accord between Israelis and Palestinians.</p>
        <p>Hana El Sahly  Houston, June 5, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Tom Segev argues that, although ''some kind of retaliation'' by Israel against Jordan's June 1967 attack was justified, it should have stopped short of taking East Jerusalem and the West Bank.</p>
        <p>Mr. Segev tells us that in January 1967, Israel's leaders concluded that it would not be in the country's interest to occupy those areas. That's hardly surprising, since doing so then would have meant initiating an aggressive war against what appeared to be a relatively moderate Arab state.</p>
        <p>But in June, King Hussein attacked Israel, ignoring the pleas of its leaders to stay out of the fighting. Had it turned out differently, the war Jordan entered would have been one of extermination, as evidenced by the blood-curdling Arab calls that preceded it for the destruction of Israel and the death of the Jews.</p>
        <p>Israel's only possible response to such aggression was to destroy Jordan's capacity to pose a future threat; to suggest that it could or should have done so without achieving borders with some defensive depth ignores reality.</p>
        <p>Howard F. Jaeckel  New York, June 5, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>While the Six-Day War left Israel and the Palestinians in their current deadlock, the war did have its benefits for the Jewish state. The unequivocal victory in 1967 demonstrated to the Arab world that it could not destroy Israel militarily. And it was this recognition by Egypt and Jordan that led to peace agreements with Israel.</p>
        <p>The war also laid the foundation for Security Council Resolution 242, which formed the basis for Arab-Israeli peacemaking over the last four decades. Negotiated compromise over territories and assured security arrangements, rather than attempts to obliterate Israel, then the status quo ante, became the new rules of engagement.</p>
        <p>Today, these principles remain the best hope for reaching a permanent-status agreement between Israelis and Palestinians.</p>
        <p>Ari Fridman  New York, June 5, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
