<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Kentucky's Bourbon Trail</title>
    <meta content="06frugalweb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/travel/06frugalweb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852445"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FRUGAL TRAVELER | AMERICAN ROAD TRIP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Frugal Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Whiskey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Kentucky</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00EFDD103EF935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1604" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Kentucky's Bourbon Trail</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On Kentucky’s Bourbon Trail</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT GROSS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GRADUALLY the hills and pastures of Tennessee, which for hours had rolled on like a sinuous green wave, came to an end. The stands of hilltop trees, once so bulbous and neat, like broccoli tops, grew wilder and chaotic. And instead of flowing up, over and around the swells in the earth, U.S. Route 31E now cut right through them, exposing the white limestone below the topsoil. It was the only ''Welcome to Kentucky'' sign I needed.</p>
        <p>In a way, limestone was the reason I'd come to Kentucky, after spending two days in Tennessee searching for ''old Nashville''. The state sits upon a massive shelf of sedimentary rock-- mostly calcium carbonate -- that filters the mountain springs and streams. Kentucky therefore has great, clean water, full of calcium to nurture the bones of thoroughbreds who munch the ubiquitous bluegrass.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Frugal Traveler heads to Bardstown, Ky., the ancient heart of bourbon country, in search of whiskey and comraderie.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GRADUALLY the hills and pastures of Tennessee, which for hours had rolled on like a sinuous green wave, came to an end. The stands of hilltop trees, once so bulbous and neat, like broccoli tops, grew wilder and chaotic. And instead of flowing up, over and around the swells in the earth, U.S. Route 31E now cut right through them, exposing the white limestone below the topsoil. It was the only ''Welcome to Kentucky'' sign I needed.</p>
        <p>In a way, limestone was the reason I'd come to Kentucky, after spending two days in Tennessee searching for ''old Nashville''. The state sits upon a massive shelf of sedimentary rock-- mostly calcium carbonate -- that filters the mountain springs and streams. Kentucky therefore has great, clean water, full of calcium to nurture the bones of thoroughbreds who munch the ubiquitous bluegrass.</p>
        <p>And thanks to that water, naturally cleansed of iron, Kentucky also has bourbon. Now, I've been a fan of Scotch for several years, especially smoky single malts from Islay, but I'd always wanted to expand my knowledge of whiskey. Bardstown, the ancient heart of bourbon country, seemed like the place to do so -- and to do so frugally. Many distilleries offer free tours and, even better, free tastings.</p>
        <p>Moreover, I hoped the sharing of spirits would help me make a friend or two. Alcohol, as Barbara Holland wrote in ''The Joy of Drinking,'' is the ''social glue of the human race,'' the starter of conversations, ideas and relationships. Surely, I would find in Bardstown more than just a juicy dram -- I'd find relief from the loneliness of the open road.</p>
        <p>Founded in 1780 about 30 miles south of Louisville, Bardstown looks more like a New England town than a Southern one, with well-kept Federal-style brick houses clustered tightly about a central square. Once, this was a major outpost of Catholicism, with the country's first cathedral west of the Allegheny mountains. Later, it was home to the writer Thomas Merton, who was a monk at the nearby Abbey of Gethsemani.</p>
        <p>In fact, it was a religious man who was responsible for developing bourbon. Around 1789, the Rev. Elijah Craig, a Baptist minister, accidentally discovered that if he charred the oak barrels in which he stored his moonshine, the resulting liquor was far smoother and more palatable. Other bootleggers soon followed suit, and an industry was born.</p>
        <p>My game plan was to see the distilleries in action, but I arrived too late last Friday, not having known that Nashville and Bardstown lie in different time zones. I used the time to settle in. Though I could have sprung for an inexpensive motel, I wanted to save my cash for good whiskey. So I headed to My Old Kentucky Home State Park (501 East Stephen Foster Avenue, 502-348-3502; www.parks.ky.gov/stateparks/mk/), part of the estate that inspired Stephen Foster, the 19th-century songwriter, to compose the famous tune. It cost only $12 a night to camp there.</p>
        <p>After I pitched my tent in a field of clover, I walked to Old Talbott Tavern (107 West Stephen Foster Avenue, 502-348-3494, www.talbotts.com). The tavern, recommendedbynumerousreaders, is one of the oldest structures in Bardstown, an ancient stop on the western stagecoach route and, it is said, the occasional bunk of illustrious figures like Daniel Boone and the young Abraham Lincoln. (It's still a bed-and-breakfast, with rooms starting at about $65 a night.) I began my evening in the bar, a dark room where a few dour patrons were drinking beers and gin-and-tonics -- not a bourbon aficionado in sight, despite the extensive list. I ordered an old-fashioned ($7) and consumed it in silence.</p>
        <p>Hoping for more camaraderie, I moved to the dining room, but that stone-walled, wood-beamed space was nearly as desolate. A mother and her child ate cheeseburgers, and three older guys sipped sweet tea. In the corner, however, was a likely candidate for conversation -- a single woman in her early 30s, whose accent indicated she wasn't from Kentucky.</p>
        <p>But how do you approach someone at random without seeming like a weirdo? I chewed over the question as I chewed my pork chops, but no answer emerged. In the end, I finished my meal and walked out alone, lingering in the tavern's lobby-cum-gift shop to examine an array of tourist pamphlets.</p>
        <p>Then she walked out -- and spoke to me: ''You're from New York?''</p>
        <p>I answered by inviting her to the bar for a drink.</p>
        <p>Patricia was from Westchester County, in New York, and as we sipped a variety of bourbons (five for $29; I loved the supple Noah's Mill), I learned that she was a diehard road-tripper. Whenever she had vacation time, she'd fly somewhere, rent a car and simply drive around, indulging her love of American history everywhere from the Shenandoah Valley of Virginia to Sioux City, Iowa. This, not her job as a secretary, was her life's passion. And although bourbon wasn't her thing, and she'd be leaving the next day, it didn't matter -- I'd found kinship, however brief, and I tottered happily back to my old Kentucky campground.</p>
        <p>Saturday was devoted to touring distilleries, tracing a bourbon trail that several readers had enthusiastically endorsed. The first was Heaven Hill Distilleries Bourbon Heritage Center (1311 Gilkey Run Road, 502-337-1000, www.bourbonheritagecenter.com), which offers free tours of a seven-story warehouse, where rack upon rack of barrels perfume the air with a luscious scent known as the ''angels' share.'' The highlight, of course, was the tasting, held in a domed, light-filled room.</p>
        <p>We sampled two single-barrel bourbons, including a rich 18-year Elijah Craig, and as I glanced up to let the sunlight shine through my glass, I noticed that at the center of the metal struts of the ceiling was a star of David. It might have seemed out of place, but Heaven Hill's post-Prohibition founders, the Shapiras, were Jews continuing a tradition begun by Scotch-Irish pioneers and refined by a Baptist minister in a Catholic settlement. How very American, I thought, draining my glass.</p>
        <p>Though I'd connected with history, I hadn't connected with my fellow tourists. There was still that barrier of shyness, and I hadn't drunk enough to lower my inhibitions.</p>
        <p>I was counting on my next stop, Maker's Mark (3350 Burks Spring Road, Loretto, 270-865-2099, www.makersmark.com), to do the trick. This was a stunning distillery: dark brown wooden barns with shutters painted the company's trademark red. But it was two of the 30-odd tourists that caught my eye: a young woman in fancy Pumas, a guy with thick beard and black rectangular eyeglasses. Yes, hipsters.</p>
        <p>As we walked from the fermenting vats to the barrel warehouse, I had hoped to catch their eyes and, by my own quasi-hip appearance and engaging demeanor, encourage them to approach me. It didn't work, and only at the end of the tour did I work up some courage, despite the lack of free tastings.</p>
        <p>''Where are you guys from?'' I asked, feeling pathetic and uninspired.</p>
        <p>Luke and Rachel lived in Louisville and had embarked on this day trip because Luke was, he said, ''a big fan of Maker's.'' We chatted amiably for a few minutes and quickly said good-bye.</p>
        <p>The rest of the day, I regretted not asking them out. At dusk, I drove to BJ's Bar and Grill (1008 Commerce Boulevard, 502-348-5070), which the Heaven Hill tour guide had suggested as a more bourbon-centric alternative to the Old Talbott Tavern. It wasn't. I drank a Knob Creek, ate a foul Kentucky concoction called ''hot brown'' -- a cross between a turkey sandwich and cheese fondue -- and despaired of finding someone who'd share my love of whiskey.</p>
        <p>By Sunday, I was ready to leave Bardstown and bourbon behind. I droveeast to the Old Frankfort Pike, a hilly, swerving lane bordered by leafy trees and low limestone walls. Beyond the fences, million-dollar stallions cantered, and the ominous rain clouds behind me made the sunny land ahead seem that much brighter. The journey filled me with optimism -- who needs new friends when you've got the open road?</p>
        <p>That evening, I stopped in Louisville to hole up and write this column, and as I walked through the eclectic Highlands neighborhood toward Lynn's Paradise Cafe, a ''treasure'' recommended by a reader, Eric Brach, and many others (984 Barret Avenue, 502-583-3447, www.lynnsparadisecafe.com), a white sedan pulled up next to me and honked. It was Luke and Rachel.</p>
        <p>This time, there would be no regrets. As we marveled at the coincidence, I asked if they might like to grab a drink the next night, and they said yes. My inhibitions -- and, apparently, theirs -- had evaporated, even though we hadn't had a single drop of bourbon. At least, not yet.</p>
        <p>Next stop: Indiana.</p>
        <p>Share Your Suggestions | Read Comments</p>
        <p>FRUGAL TRAVELER | AMERICAN ROAD TRIP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
