<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Symbolism Takes a Back Seat To the World's Abrasive Realities</title>
    <meta content="06kere" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/arts/music/06kere.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852459"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CEFD61130F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Symbolism Takes a Back Seat To the World's Abrasive Realities</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Symbolism Takes a Back Seat to the World’s Abrasive Realities</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATE CHINEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Within the first few minutes of her show at the Bowery Ballroom on Monday night, Keren Ann charted a complex constellation of feelings: wistfulness, disdain, self-pity, indignation, whimsy. She was singing a breakup song, naturally -- ''In Your Back,'' from her self-titled fifth album -- but making it sound more momentous than most.</p>
        <p>''Don't ever mention the stains that you left on my track,'' she sang evenly in the first verse. ''How from a beautiful girl I became someone ruined and wrecked.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Within the first few minutes of her show at the Bowery Ballroom on Monday night, Keren Ann charted a complex constellation of feelings: wistfulness, disdain, self-pity, indignation, whimsy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Within the first few minutes of her show at the Bowery Ballroom on Monday night, Keren Ann charted a complex constellation of feelings: wistfulness, disdain, self-pity, indignation, whimsy. She was singing a breakup song, naturally -- ''In Your Back,'' from her self-titled fifth album -- but making it sound more momentous than most.</p>
        <p>''Don't ever mention the stains that you left on my track,'' she sang evenly in the first verse. ''How from a beautiful girl I became someone ruined and wrecked.''</p>
        <p>Keren Ann has been creeping toward this sort of declarative impact, and the change is palpable. On her previous two Blue Note albums, ''Nolita'' and ''Not Going Anywhere,'' she often sounded diffident and distracted, her appealingly airy voice conveying more than a wisp of the cosmopolitanism that is her birthright. (Born Keren Ann Zeidel of Israeli, Dutch and Javanese heritage, she spent her adolescence in Paris, where she still resides part time.) The new album has its share of ethereal vocal overdubs and reflects her fondness for minor-key ruminations. But it's a grittier proposition all around.</p>
        <p>Comparatively speaking, the show was grittier still. Though chicly turned out in a black dress and high heels, Keren Ann behaved more like a lead singer than a chanteuse. For each of her fingerpicked acoustic guitar arpeggios, there was a corresponding round of reverb-heavy electric chugging.</p>
        <p>She led her four-piece backing band assertively, ceding the spotlight in measured doses to the trumpeter Avishai Cohen, who fed his sound through various filters and wah-wah striations. The closest thing Keren Ann had to a solo involved a brace-mounted harmonica that inevitably conjured Bob Dylan.</p>
        <p>That was in ''Lay Your Head Down,'' the strongest track on ''Keren Ann'' and the clearest indication yet of the singer's attraction to the terse and self-conscious style of the Velvet Underground.</p>
        <p>Another clue came next in the set: ''Chelsea Burns,'' a track from ''Nolita.'' Keren Ann used the song as an opportunity to sing with a guest, the lap steel guitarist Dayna Kurtz.</p>
        <p>Keren Ann's lyrics have grown less artful as her music has hardened. In some of the older songs in the set, implications were fastened to symbolic objects: a raincoat, a cathedral, ''an empty bottle left in the shade.''</p>
        <p>A few of the new songs confront bigger issues and grapple plainly with a sense of hopelessness provoked by current events. On ''Where No Endings End,'' a postmodern chanson that she played in a stark acoustic setting, Keren Ann referred to ''a cold-blooded war'' before cooing a dispirited refrain:</p>
        <p>But we can't change the world</p>
        <p>No we can't change the world</p>
        <p>It's been done</p>
        <p>By someone</p>
        <p>Long ago</p>
        <p>Another passage from the song was more direct. ''I can't win,'' Keren Ann exhaled. ''I give in. I give in.''</p>
        <p>Given her history of rapturous languor, or languorous rapture, the sentiment was characteristic. But where the lyric might have once suggested a contented sort of resignation, it offered no such consolations in the context of the show. Maybe Keren Ann didn't sound remotely ruined, but she clearly had more than heartbreak on her mind.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
