<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Serena Williams Falters and Henin Capitalizes</title>
    <meta content="06tennis" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/sports/tennis/06tennis.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852556"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Paris (France)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Williams, Serena</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Henin-Hardenne, Justine</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jankovic, Jelena</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kuznetsova, Svetlana</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sharapova, Maria</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Federer, Roger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE2DD1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="828" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Serena Williams Falters and Henin Capitalizes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Serena Williams Falters and Henin Capitalizes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIET MACUR</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The most anticipated and potentially heated match at the French Open so far -- Serena Williams against Justine Henin -- fizzled nearly from the start Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Williams, an eight-time Grand Slam singles champion, hit backhands long and forehands short. She stretched her muscular limbs to put a racket on some of Henin's shots, only to double over, nearly kissing the clay. She shouted, ''C'mon!'' as motivation, but never took her own advice in a 6-4, 6-3 loss in the quarterfinals that lasted only 78 minutes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Serena Williams's game failed her and Justine Henin rose to the occasion in the most anticipated and potentially heated match at the French Open so far.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The most anticipated and potentially heated match at the French Open so far -- Serena Williams against Justine Henin -- fizzled nearly from the start Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Williams, an eight-time Grand Slam singles champion, hit backhands long and forehands short. She stretched her muscular limbs to put a racket on some of Henin's shots, only to double over, nearly kissing the clay. She shouted, ''C'mon!'' as motivation, but never took her own advice in a 6-4, 6-3 loss in the quarterfinals that lasted only 78 minutes.</p>
        <p>Only once did Williams look as fierce as usual. In the second set, she threw her racket with such force and anger that it landed several feet behind her. The crowd, otherwise polite, jeered and whistled.</p>
        <p>Later, Williams said her performance was ''hideous and horrendous'' and worse than ever.</p>
        <p>''Serena kept hitting the balls in the net and Serena kept making errors,'' she said at her news conference, then flogged herself for playing ''like a maniac.''</p>
        <p>For Henin to win, Williams said, ''I think all she had to do was show up.''</p>
        <p>Exiting in the quarterfinals was particularly deflating for Williams after making such a spectacular comeback to win the Australian Open in January. She was ranked 81st then, after missing several months with an injured left knee. She was No. 8 in the rankings and seedings entering the French Open.</p>
        <p>For the top-seeded Henin, Tuesday's victory was a confidence boost in her pursuit of a third consecutive title at Roland Garros.</p>
        <p>Henin's coach, Carlos Rodríguez, said Henin was surprised at how easy it was to beat Williams. Later, Henin said she had been braced for a tough, unpredictable match.</p>
        <p>''I knew that mentally, she's a real fighter and she can come back in the match at any time,'' Henin said, explaining why she stayed aggressive, even when Williams seemed helpless.</p>
        <p>Henin had seen Williams falter before only to come back. In the final at Miami in March, Henin dominated the first set, 6-0, but Williams rallied to win the next two and take the title.</p>
        <p>Henin, a tiny ball of power compared with Williams, remained stone-faced throughout the match. Only after Williams's final forehand hit the net did Henin let her guard down. She grinned and pointed to the crowd.</p>
        <p>Afterward, as the fans cheered, Henin and Williams shook hands and left the court smiling. The scene was entirely different four years ago, when they met in a semifinal that ended in controversy.</p>
        <p>Then, Williams left the court in tears as the spectators booed. A dispute over Henin's gamesmanship and a hostile crowd left a mark on that match.</p>
        <p>This time, Williams, the final American in the singles draw, left dry-eyed but disgusted. She will return to Florida to train in the heat before Wimbledon, a trip she called penance for losing here.</p>
        <p>Henin will meet Jelena Jankovic, the fourth seed, in the semifinals. She is 5-0 against Jankovic, with three victories against her this year.</p>
        <p>Jankovic defeated the sixth-seeded Nicole Vaidisova, 6-3, 7-5, in another quarterfinal Tuesday. She will be joined in the semifinals by her Serbian compatriot Ana Ivanovic, seeded seventh, who beat No. 3 Svetlana Kuznetsova, 6-0, 3-6, 6-1. Kuznetsova, who complained of abdominal pain, was a finalist last year.</p>
        <p>''Wherever you go, it's just Serbians all over the place, winning all these matches,'' Jankovic said. ''It's just incredible.''</p>
        <p>Ivanovic will play No. 2 Maria Sharapova, who defeated a Russian compatriot, No. 9 Anna Chakvetadze, 6-3, 6-4. Earlier in the tournament, Sharapova said she felt like ''a cow on ice'' when she played on clay, but she has managed to remain smooth enough to reach her first semifinal at Roland Garros.</p>
        <p>For the men, No. 1 Roger Federer advanced to the semifinals Tuesday, but showed that he could be beaten -- at least for one set.</p>
        <p>Federer set the record for consecutive sets won at a Grand Slam tournament when he took the first set against No. 9 Tommy Robredo, then immediately lost the second set. Federer had won 36 sets in a row, a string that began at the 2006 United States Open; he broke the record held by John McEnroe since 1984.</p>
        <p>''Well, not looking for excuses, but it was windy,'' Federer said of that second set. ''I didn't play well in that set, that's for sure. But he played solid. Didn't miss much, used forehand well.</p>
        <p>''I was actually playing wrong in that point of time.''</p>
        <p>Federer came back to win the match handily, 7-5, 1-6, 6-1, 6-2, setting up a semifinal match against No. 4 Nikolay Davydenko. In the only other men's quarterfinal Tuesday, Davydenko beat Guillermo Cañas, 7-5, 6-4, 6-4.</p>
        <p>Davydenko has never beaten Federer in eight meetings, but Cañas has figured out the secret. He is 3-1 against Federer, including two victories against him in March.</p>
        <p>''Against Federer nobody feel comfortable, only Cañas,'' Davydenko said.</p>
        <p>Then, he laughed.</p>
        <p>''You need to play your best game,'' he said. ''That's what I need to find.''</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
