<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Run, Gobble, Gobble, Run: Vying for Pac-Man Acclaim</title>
    <meta content="06pacman" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/nyregion/06pacman.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852520"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Times Square and 42nd Street (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E0DE1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Run, Gobble, Gobble, Run: Vying for Pac-Man Acclaim</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Run, Gobble, Gobble, Run: Vying for Pac-Man Acclaim</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH SCHIESEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wakka wakka wakka.</p>
        <p>If you happened to wander into the Supper Club in Times Square yesterday, you might have thought that the peculiar noise you heard was the incessant complaint of an ornery goose.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ten of the world’s top players of the famous video game Pac-Man faced off in Times Square on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wakka wakka wakka.</p>
        <p>If you happened to wander into the Supper Club in Times Square yesterday, you might have thought that the peculiar noise you heard was the incessant complaint of an ornery goose.</p>
        <p>If, however, you grew up in the 1980s, you probably would have instantly recognized the signature sound of perhaps the world's most famous video game: Pac-Man.</p>
        <p>From all corners of the globe, 10 of the world's top Pac-Men -- there were no women -- faced off yesterday for pellet-gobbling supremacy at the finals of the first Xbox 360 Pac-Man World Championship.</p>
        <p>More than 30,000 gamers entered the contest's grueling initial stages online last month, and, to be sure, the road to Pac-Man glory requires dedication and sacrifice. It may even cause some family strife.</p>
        <p>Just ask Graham Rodgers, 42, of Ipswich, England. He was not one of the finalists because he came in second among all players in the United Kingdom in the tournament's opening phase. But he came to the contest anyway as chaperone for the United Kingdom champion who bested him: his son James, 13.</p>
        <p>''I'm happy for him, but I actually wanted to win,'' Mr. Rodgers said in an interview. ''On the last night of the preliminaries, I sent James to bed early so I would have a few hours to beat his score, but I just couldn't do it.''</p>
        <p>Before the contest, James said: ''I don't think I really have a chance to win because there are so many great players here I've only heard about.''</p>
        <p>The most famous player was also the oldest: Billy Mitchell, 41, of Hollywood, Fla., who generated headlines around the globe in 1999 when he became the first person to record a perfect score in Pac-Man: 3,333,360.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitchell's perfect score took six hours of continuous play. To speed things up for yesterday's event, Microsoft and Namco Bandai of Japan, the company that first released Pac-Man in Japan in 1980 and around the world a year later, created a quicker version of the game called Pac-Man Championship Edition. The company unveiled the new game for the first time yesterday, and Microsoft said it would be available for downloading on its Xbox Live Internet service today. (In the online rounds of the tournament, players used the original version on the Xbox 360; they did not see the new version until Monday night.)</p>
        <p>''After 26 years of Pac-Man history, we are pleased to introduce a new Pac-Man to the world,'' Toru Iwatani, designer of both the original and new games and one of the fathers of modern gaming, said in an interview. ''This is the first big event in games in the 21st century.''</p>
        <p>The ''championship mode'' used yesterday limits each game to five minutes and allots points more generously that the original version. The tournament directors whittled the field from 10 to 2 over four rounds, eliminating the lowest-scoring two players in each round.</p>
        <p>As the play got under way, it quickly became clear that the unheralded Carlos Daniel Borrego Romero, 27, of Pachuca, Mexico, had devised a brilliant, unorthodox strategy. Most players concentrated on getting to the energizers and eating as many ghosts as possible. (You can eat the ghosts when they turn blue, remember?) Mr. Borrego, however, focused not on the ghosts but on clearing levels quickly and getting to the more valuable bonus fruit prizes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Borrego sailed into the final match and prevailed against Robert Glashuettner, 28, of Vienna by a score of 222,160 to 177,730. (James Rodgers finished sixth. Mr. Mitchell finished eighth.)</p>
        <p>''It just feels amazing,'' Mr. Borrego said after his victory, which won him prizes including a special-edition Xbox 360 and 26 years of weekly free sandwiches from Quiznos, the tournament's sponsor.</p>
        <p>It turns out, though, that Mr. Borrego is not really a video game amateur. He actually runs his own budding video game company in Mexico, Nusof Studios, and is working on his first game.</p>
        <p>''I don't have a publisher yet,'' he said. ''Maybe winning this contest will help.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
