<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Hands-On Hotel Owner Who Values Independence</title>
    <meta content="06hotels" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/realestate/commercial/06hotels.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852486"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Square Feet"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E0DF1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1285" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Hands-On Hotel Owner Who Values Independence</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Hands-On Hotel Owner Who Values Independence</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TERRY PRISTIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pristin, Terry</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Arriving at the InterContinental Hotel on North Michigan Avenue on a warm afternoon, Laurence S. Geller notices that the doorman, Hussain al-Mosawy, is wearing a new addition to his summer uniform: a white safari hat.</p>
        <p>The hat offers good protection from the sun, Mr. al-Mosawy tells Mr. Geller, the chief executive of Strategic Hotels and Resorts, a real estate investment trust that owns the InterContinental and 19 other high-end hotels in North America and Europe. ''I like it,'' the doorman says.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new breed of hands-on owners is actively pushing hotel managers to wring more profit out of their assets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Arriving at the InterContinental Hotel on North Michigan Avenue on a warm afternoon, Laurence S. Geller notices that the doorman, Hussain al-Mosawy, is wearing a new addition to his summer uniform: a white safari hat.</p>
        <p>The hat offers good protection from the sun, Mr. al-Mosawy tells Mr. Geller, the chief executive of Strategic Hotels and Resorts, a real estate investment trust that owns the InterContinental and 19 other high-end hotels in North America and Europe. ''I like it,'' the doorman says.</p>
        <p>''I'm not sure I like it,'' replies Mr. Geller, casting doubt on the hat's prospects.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Geller, 59, who has spent more than four decades in the hotel industry, there is no such thing as a trivial detail. Unlike the passive hotel owners of the past -- often insurance companies and other institutional investors -- Mr. Geller represents a new breed of hands-on owners who actively push hotel managers to wring more profit out of their assets. If one of his managers has found a way to cut laundry costs by 2 cents a pound, he wants all the others to know about it.</p>
        <p>In recent years, most of the top hotel brands have shed much of their real estate to focus more on the management and franchise side of their business. Though his hotels are operated by some of the top brands in the lodging industry, including Ritz-Carlton, Fairmont and Four Seasons, Mr. Geller is not afraid to try to micromanage the hotels he owns.</p>
        <p>''We spend a lot more time worrying about the properties than they do,'' Mr. Geller said in a recent interview in his company headquarters overlooking the Chicago River. ''We're very analytical.'' If an analysis shows that a doorman is idle for two hours every morning, he may be asked to deliver the laundry, Mr. Geller said.</p>
        <p>These days, Strategic is often mentioned as a target for a leveraged buyout. Since February 2006, eight publicly traded hotel companies have been or are in the process of being acquired. Mr. Geller, however, says he is determined not to sell. In his view, the portfolio he began assembling in 1997 is worth more than what potential buyers would be willing to spend. It includes the Hotel del Coronado in San Diego; the Ritz-Carlton Laguna Niguel in Orange County, Calif.; the Four Seasons in Washington; and the Four Seasons Punta Mita Resort Hotel near Puerto Vallarta, Mexico.</p>
        <p>''We are a very highly sought-after acquisition candidate if we wanted to sell,'' Mr. Geller said. ''Most of the major private equity funds are friends, and we chat. But we don't think they will pay us for what future value will be. They would pay us for value today.''</p>
        <p>Strategic, which went public in 2004, has long-range plans to enhance the value of its hotels -- by sprucing up the rooms, adding residential units, or replacing tired hotel dining rooms with spas or sushi bars that appeal to customers under 45. It is an age group that all luxury brands are trying to capture, said Thomas P. McConnell, a senior managing director at Cushman &amp; Wakefield. ''The Versailles look for five-star hotels -- that's gone,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The company has also taken control of the retail space at many of its hotels, tailoring the stores to attract young professionals who are too busy to shop at home. ''Our hotels are mixed-use developments,'' Mr. Geller said. ''You have to make every component fit in.''</p>
        <p>One of Strategic's innovations is Eno, a wine-tasting bar with a California feel, where wines to be sampled are paired with cheese and chocolates. Introduced at the Ritz-Carlton Half Moon Bay, south of San Francisco, Eno ''resonated with the meeting planners'' who had previously avoided booking the hotel, Mr. Geller said, and an Eno is now also at the InterContinental in Chicago. Analysts like the concept. ''It takes up little room, its high margin, and it's in vogue,'' said Bill Crow, a senior vice president for Raymond James.</p>
        <p>To maintain his company's independence, Mr. Geller is currently seeking joint venture partners. [On Thursday, Strategic announced that GIC Real Estate, a company owned by the government of Singapore, would acquire a 49 percent interest in the InterContinental in Chicago and the Hyatt Regency La Jolla. The deal, valued at $450 million, will give Strategic the cash to achieve some of his goals, Mr. Geller said.]</p>
        <p>Raised in London, Mr. Geller learned his industry from the bottom up, becoming a kitchen porter at 13, cooking for the Israeli Defense Forces during the Six-Day War and later rising to senior positions with Holiday Inns and Hyatt, before striking out on his own in 1989. He writes racy novels in his spare time.</p>
        <p>His long experience, his high-quality portfolio and his passion for the hotel business have won him respect, but his company lags behind its peers in the hotel REIT sector. [Its total returns for the year that ended Monday, including dividend and stock appreciation, were 17 percent, compared with 24. 4 percent for SNL Financial's hotel REIT index, which includes 17 companies, according to Fawad Rizwi, an SNL research analyst.]</p>
        <p>Jonathan D. Gray, the co-head of real estate for Blackstone, which last year sold the 1,195-room Westin St. Francis in San Francisco and the 236-room Marriott Grosvenor House in London to Mr. Geller's company for $440 million and $192 million, respectively, said: ''I think he's been unfairly beaten up by Wall Street. He deserves credit for assembling a great collection of assets.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gray would not say whether Blackstone wants to acquire Strategic.</p>
        <p>Will Marks, a hotel and real estate analyst for JMP Securities, says Strategic has ''the best portfolio of hotels that are owned by any REIT.'' Yet, Mr. Marks recently downgraded Strategic's stock because the company is spending heavily to fix up its hotels. ''This could be a year where the upside is limited because of the renovations,'' Mr. Marks said.</p>
        <p>Another hotel REIT analyst, John Arabia of Green Street Advisors, a Newport Beach, Calif., research company, has criticized Strategic in the past, saying it often failed to deliver on its promises, including the InterContinental condominium tower in Chicago and the addition of meeting space at the InterContinental in Miami. ''When these projects were postponed for several years, or maybe forever, it caused credibility issues with the company,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Arabia recently upgraded the stock, in part because the company's assets, including the land it has for future development at InterContinental Prague and the Loews Santa Monica Beach Hotel, have increased significantly in value.</p>
        <p>Mr. Geller has been criticized for getting his hotels at too rich a price. ''He's paid a premium to get into certain markets,'' said Paul W. Whetsell, the former chief executive of MeriStar, a hotel REIT acquired last year by the Blackstone Group. But in recent months, the company has stopped buying and has promised to sell two hotels, the Marriott Lincolnshire in the Chicago suburbs and the Hyatt Regency Phoenix, that do not fit with its other properties.</p>
        <p>Some of the company's problems are not of its own making. Its 1,184-room Hyatt Regency Hotel in New Orleans was damaged by Hurricane Katrina and remains closed, though Mr. Geller said he intended to reopen it in mid-2008. Last year, he announced an ambitious plan to make the hotel part of a tourist magnet that would include a jazz center and a park. But the Hyatt Jazz District has stalled because of a lack of political leadership, he said, adding that it is not up to him to write the check for the entire project.</p>
        <p>''If they want to do it, let them do it,'' he said. ''I don't intend to be St. Laurence of New Orleans.''</p>
        <p>Square Feet</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
