<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suicide Attack Near Falluja Kills 18 in Commercial Area</title>
    <meta content="06iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/world/middleeast/06iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852516"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baghdad (Iraq)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Falluja (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oppel, Richard A Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Al-Ansary, Khalid</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maliki, Nuri Kamal Al- (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E1DE1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="864" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suicide Attack Near Falluja Kills 18 in Commercial Area</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Suicide Attack Near Falluja Kills 18 in Commercial Area</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD A. OPPEL Jr. and KHALID AL-ANSARY; Karim Hilmi and Muhanad Seloom contributed reporting from Baghdad, and Iraqi employees of The New York Times from Diyala, Hilla and Mosul.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Al-Ansary, Khalid; Oppel, Richard A Jr</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, June 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Suicide bomber driving truck packed with explosives plows into busy commercial district south of Falluja, killing 18 people and wounding 15 others; separate suicide bomb attack is foiled in Baghdad when woman wearing explosive belt is stopped by police commandos; also in Baghdad, Iraqi Parliament votes to require government of Prime Min Nuri Kamal al-Maliki to bring matter of how long American troops can stay in Iraq before lawmakers, in order for any additional extensions to occur; 33 bodies are found throughout capital on single day, most of them shot in head, amid continuing sectarian killings; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eighteen people were killed south of Falluja on Tuesday when a suicide bomber driving a truck packed with explosives plowed into a busy commercial district, the local Iraqi police said. Fifteen others were wounded.</p>
        <p>Some witnesses said the attack occurred near a meeting of tribal sheiks who have been fighting Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia. A spokesman for the American military forces in the area could not confirm the information, saying that military explosives experts who examined the scene determined that the bomb went off in a parking lot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some witnesses said the attack occurred near a meeting of tribal sheiks who have been fighting Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Eighteen people were killed south of Falluja on Tuesday when a suicide bomber driving a truck packed with explosives plowed into a busy commercial district, the local Iraqi police said. Fifteen others were wounded.</p>
        <p>Some witnesses said the attack occurred near a meeting of tribal sheiks who have been fighting Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia. A spokesman for the American military forces in the area could not confirm the information, saying that military explosives experts who examined the scene determined that the bomb went off in a parking lot.</p>
        <p>An Iraqi security official in Anbar Province said that just hours after the attack near Falluja on Tuesday morning, another suicide bomber, using a truck full of explosives hidden beneath piles of raw wool, attacked an Iraqi police checkpoint in eastern Ramadi, killing eight policemen and wounding four.</p>
        <p>A Marine spokesman, Maj. Jeff Pool, later said that reports of the bombing in Ramadi were false. ''Nothing happened there,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A separate suicide bomb attack was foiled in Baghdad on Tuesday when a woman wearing an explosive belt approached a line of Shiite police recruits in the eastern part of the capital but was stopped by police commandos.</p>
        <p>Suspecting that the woman was a bomber, the commandos chased her away from the line, an Interior Ministry official said, but her explosive device detonated and wounded three of her pursuers.</p>
        <p>Also in Baghdad, the Iraqi Parliament voted to require the government of Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki to bring the matter of how long American troops can stay in Iraq before lawmakers in order for any additional extensions to occur.</p>
        <p>An American soldier was shot to death on Tuesday in southern Baghdad, the American military reported in a statement. No other details were provided.</p>
        <p>Thirty-three bodies were found throughout the capital on Tuesday, most of them shot in the head, as the number of sectarian killings continues to rise in Baghdad. The number of such killings reported remain below their peak of last year, before President Bush sent additional American troops into the capital. But American and Iraqi officials are acknowledging that the killings are once again increasing.</p>
        <p>An Iraqi Interior Ministry official said recently that the number of unidentified bodies found in Baghdad rose more than 70 percent in May compared with April. The bodies are a key indicator of Shiite death squad activity and other sectarian murders. The senior American commander in Iraq, Gen. David H. Petraeus, acknowledged the rising number of sectarian killings in Baghdad during a televised interview on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Such murders and executions ''had come down by about two-thirds from the height in January to April, and then May it came back up to about half the level in January,'' General Petraeus said during an interview on CBS. ''That's a concern to us, obviously, because it indicates again that the cycle of violence resumed in some areas.''</p>
        <p>Three Iraqi soldiers were killed and two wounded when insurgents detonated a roadside bomb on the soldiers' convoy in Baghdad on Tuesday. Mortars wounded seven people in western Baghdad. A bomb in a parked car killed one Iraqi civilian and wounded another near an American base in Mahmudiya, south of Baghdad.</p>
        <p>In violence-wracked Diyala Province, northeast of Baghdad, unknown gunmen kidnapped a dozen students traveling in a minibus through Khalis, a police official said. The Mahdi Army, the militia loyal to the radical Shiite cleric Moktada al-Sadr, has a large presence in that city, but it has also been the scene of recent attacks by Sunni Arab insurgents.</p>
        <p>Another kidnapping attempt in Khalis on Tuesday failed, however, when insurgents who had used a fake checkpoint to abduct 13 people were then attacked and chased by local residents who later freed the hostages.</p>
        <p>A Diyala police official said two Iraqi soldiers and two Iraqi policemen were killed as American and Iraqi forces battled gunmen north of Khalis. Seven gunmen were also killed, the official said. At least 81 Iraqi policemen were killed in Diyala in April and May, and 275 more were wounded, according to the Diyala police official.</p>
        <p>In eastern Baquba, the provincial capital of Diyala, one civilian was killed and four were wounded by gunmen. Also, two unidentified bodies and a severed head were found in northern Baquba.</p>
        <p>In the northern city of Mosul, police recovered four bodies scattered around the city. Clashes also erupted between gunmen and the Iraqi police. Two gunmen were killed, one a Saudi Arabian and the other an Iraqi, according to Brig. Saeed al-Jibouri, an Iraqi police official in Mosul. He said the dead Saudi gunman had documents in his pocket identifying his nationality.</p>
        <p>The police in eastern Mosul also discovered a booby-trapped body inside a car, the latest example of what Brigadier Saeed described as an increasingly common tactic of the insurgents.</p>
        <p>Insurgents attacked Iraqi policemen north of Hilla with an improvised bomb, killing two policemen and wounding two others. The police in Babel Province also recovered seven bodies, all of them handcuffed and shot in the head.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
