<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seventeen Hits and a Sigh of Relief for the Yankees</title>
    <meta content="06yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/sports/baseball/06yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852611"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago White Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Chicago White Sox</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE2DC1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="876" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seventeen Hits and a Sigh of Relief for the Yankees</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Seventeen Hits and a Sigh of Relief for the Yankees</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, June 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To Johnny Damon, explaining the Yankees' troubles has been simple. When only three everyday players are hitting the way they should, he has said, that leaves six others dragging down the team.</p>
        <p>Damon has not named the culprits, but the stalwarts -- Derek Jeter, Jorge Posada and Alex Rodriguez -- are obvious. That leaves the rest of the team to blame, including Bobby Abreu, Robinson Canó and Damon himself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a team still well under .500, the Yankees enjoyed a rare game when timely hitting, shutdown pitching and crisp defense combined for a victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To Johnny Damon, explaining the Yankees' troubles has been simple. When only three everyday players are hitting the way they should, he has said, that leaves six others dragging down the team.</p>
        <p>Damon has not named the culprits, but the stalwarts -- Derek Jeter, Jorge Posada and Alex Rodriguez -- are obvious. That leaves the rest of the team to blame, including Bobby Abreu, Robinson Canó and Damon himself.</p>
        <p>All three of those players contributed to the Yankees' 7-3 victory against the Chicago White Sox on Tuesday night. So, for that matter, did Jeter, Posada and Rodriguez. For a team still well under .500, at 25-31, the Yankees played a rare game: one with timely hitting, shutdown pitching and crisp defense.</p>
        <p>The rookie Tyler Clippard improved to 3-1, allowing a run and five hits in five innings, and Scott Proctor pitched two scoreless innings behind him. Damon had three hits, Abreu and Canó each had two, and the Yankees as a team had 17, a season high.</p>
        <p>''Some teams are going to start to pay for our lack of offense lately,'' Damon said. ''This was a good night.''</p>
        <p>Relievers Kyle Farnsworth and Brian Bruney were shaky, forcing Manager Joe Torre to use closer Mariano Rivera, but besides that it was an encouraging game all around.</p>
        <p>The Yankees have struggled against left-handed starters, with a 3-9 record coming into the game, but they beat a good one in Mark Buehrle. They have won four of their last six games over all.</p>
        <p>''Right now, I think we're poised to do something special,'' Torre said. ''It comes down to being able to pitch well.''</p>
        <p>Clippard allowed two base runners in four of his five innings, but he mostly came away unharmed. At 22 years old, Clippard is not polished, but since his debut at Shea Stadium on May 20, when he retired José Reyes with the bases loaded, he has shown a survival instinct that has endeared him to Torre.</p>
        <p>''He sometimes loses his release point and he doesn't throw enough strikes, but he competes,'' Torre said. ''Aside from his stuff and his youth and all that stuff, the competing part is really good. He's not afraid of what's going to happen.''</p>
        <p>Clippard walked three and struck out four. His pitches were moving, especially his changeup, which he used to strike out the dangerous Paul Konerko with a runner on third and one out in the fourth inning. He also showed athleticism, covering first on the back end of a double play to end the first inning.</p>
        <p>Torre said he expected to start Josh Phelps at first base on Tuesday, but when he saw that Phelps was 1 for 12 in his career against Buehrle, he reconsidered. With Doug Mientkiewicz and Jason Giambi hurt, Torre gave Miguel Cairo his sixth start of the season, and his first at first base.</p>
        <p>Given the chance, Cairo delivered. The double play in the first inning was the first of two he started. His play was in contrast to that of Phelps in Monday's game, when he threw away a potential double-play ball that starter Matt DeSalvo badly needed.</p>
        <p>Cairo was 2 for 16 entering the game, but he led off the third inning with a bunt single. In the fifth, he drove in Canó with a two-out single to tie the score, 1-1.</p>
        <p>''You take one day off, and it's hard enough to come back and play, let alone sitting down for a couple of weeks,'' Jeter said. ''I don't know how he does it.''</p>
        <p>Canó had reached on a hard-hit double down the right-field line. It was Canó's 11th hit in his last 19 at-bats, and his emergence has bolstered the bottom of the Yankees' order.</p>
        <p>That order must have seemed formidable to Buehrle, an accomplished starter who has struggled against the Yankees. In seven career starts, he is 1-5 with a 6.58 earned run average, his highest against any American League team.</p>
        <p>He succeeded for a while by getting three double plays, but the Yankees went ahead in the sixth, after Damon led off with a double to the left-field corner. Jeter followed with a bunt single to put runners at the corners for Abreu.</p>
        <p>Like Canó, Abreu is showing signs of life after a deep slump. He has reached base three times in each of the last five games, and he singled to right for his second hit of the night, scoring Damon to give the Yankees a 2-1 lead.</p>
        <p>The White Sox' bullpen has been abysmal, and it was up to Buehrle to get out of the jam. He did, but not before the Yankees widened the lead to 5-1 with a double by Rodriguez, a sacrifice fly by Posada and a single by Hideki Matsui.</p>
        <p>''We didn't used to hit with runners in scoring position,'' Abreu said. ''We had a lot of trouble with that. Right now, we're getting on base and starting rallies. I think that's the big difference.''</p>
        <p>Most important, when the rallies start, hitters up and down the order can sustain them, which is just what Damon has wanted.</p>
        <p>''Any time you can get more of your guys involved in the game,'' Damon said, ''our offense is going to click a lot better.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
