<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Victory Is in View for Team New Zealand</title>
    <meta content="06sailing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/sports/othersports/06sailing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="YACHT RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sailboats and Sailing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sailboats and Sailing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E0DD1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Victory Is in View for Team New Zealand</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Victory Is in View for Team New Zealand</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <dateline>VALENCIA, Spain, June 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Emirates Team New Zealand was in front for good again Tuesday, and as usual in this one-sided Louis Vuitton Cup finals, which the Kiwis now lead, 4-0, the crew member with the best view was Adam Beashel.</p>
        <p>While Beashel's teammates hustled about on deck during the downwind legs, Beashel was 80 feet above them, perched on a spreader attached to the mast and searching the race course for signs of breeze.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Emirates Team New Zealand was in front for good again Tuesday, and as usual in this one-sided Louis Vuitton Cup finals, which the Kiwis now lead, 4-0.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Emirates Team New Zealand was in front for good again Tuesday, and as usual in this one-sided Louis Vuitton Cup finals, which the Kiwis now lead, 4-0, the crew member with the best view was Adam Beashel.</p>
        <p>While Beashel's teammates hustled about on deck during the downwind legs, Beashel was 80 feet above them, perched on a spreader attached to the mast and searching the race course for signs of breeze.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't do his job, no way,'' said Terry Hutchinson, Team New Zealand's tactician. ''It takes a special breed to go up there. I talk to him through a microphone, and he comes out on the speaker, and you hear him just getting the heck knocked out of him when he's going up the rig, cursing and swearing when we're going through big waves. He's just hanging on for dear life, basically.''</p>
        <p>Tuesday's race, which featured the lightest winds of this series, provided a smoother ride than usual for Beashel, a 38-year-old Australian strategist with a New Zealand passport. Winds ranged from six to nine knots, and the little chop present on the surface of the Mediterranean was partly because of the large spectator fleet that once again sailed or motored out to see if Luna Rossa Challenge could find a way to make this series more compelling.</p>
        <p>The familiar answer, despite an intriguing first leg, was no. The Kiwis won by 52 seconds. Beashel and his crewmates require one more victory in this best-of-nine series to secure a grudge match with Alinghi in the America's Cup. Alinghi, the Swiss-based team run by the billionaire Ernesto Bertarelli, raided New Zealand's talent last time and ended up winning the America's Cup and denting New Zealand's national pride.</p>
        <p>But the Kiwis on Team New Zealand are refusing to look past the Vuitton finals. ''We wanted to get a good start and take it from there,'' Beashel said of Tuesday's race.</p>
        <p>Most Kiwi wishes have come true quickly against Luna Rossa, but this race forced a slight delay in the gratification.</p>
        <p>There was a split-tack start, with the New Zealanders heading to the left and the Italians to the right. The space between them was close to 1,000 yards before they tacked toward each other. For the first time in the series, the Italians were leading when the boats converged for the first time, having correctly predicted a right-hand wind shift.</p>
        <p>But instead of making the moves that would have allowed them to manage their advantage, they and their tactician, Torben Grael, ended up making the wrong guess. When they came together the second time, the Kiwis had cut into the lead significantly, but instead of aggressively tacking in front of the New Zealanders and trying to affect their wind and their progress, Grael and the Italians chose to tack early.</p>
        <p>The Kiwis maintained their heading and their momentum, and ended up grabbing the lead for good on the long port tack that followed after they benefited more from the wind pressure than the Italians. When they rounded the first mark, New Zealand had a 19-second advantage.</p>
        <p>''Knowing what happened now, I would have got closer,'' Grael said of the second cross. ''But it's a hard situation there. You have to decide right then on the information you have, and with what I had, I felt I was doing the right thing.''</p>
        <p>After a decisive victory over BMW Oracle Racing in the semifinals, it has been a deeply humbling finals for Luna Rossa's crew. Team New Zealand shook free of the Italians on the downwind leg and nearly tripled its lead, with Beashel helping to read the wind from on high.</p>
        <p>His sailing connections are deep. His father, Ken, is a former world 18-foot skiff champion. His brother Colin is an Olympic bronze medalist in the prestigious Star class. His wife, Lanee, is a four-time American Olympian in board sailing.</p>
        <p>Beashel scans the surface for ripples and subtle gradations in color. It is something he was unable to do in the early stages of the Vuitton Cup after seriously injuring his left index finger here in April, days before the official start of the competition. After getting his hand caught in the mainsheet block, he stripped all the flesh off the finger and was told by a doctor that the finger tip would probably have to be amputated.</p>
        <p>But one welcome second opinion and three operations later, the finger remains intact, and he now protects it with a small, carbon splint.</p>
        <p>''I still can't feel the end of my finger, and it may need some more surgery when this is all over,'' he said. ''I can move it at the knuckle, but not at the tip. There's not much you can do right now, just let the healing take time.''</p>
        <p>With Beashel off the boat, Team New Zealand lost three races in the opening round-robin phase. His American replacement, Mark Mendelblatt, earned good reviews from his teammates as a wind-spotting replacement, and the team went through the second round robin undefeated. But Beashel eventually returned to the team during the semifinals against Desafio Español, and Hutchinson said he was one of the big reasons for the team's dominant performance against Luna Rossa.</p>
        <p>''He's an integral part of our afterguard,'' Hutchinson said. ''Mark came on and did just a spectacular job filling in his shoes, but we spent two and a half years with Beasho working on dialogue and communication and all those little things.''</p>
        <p>One more victory and Team New Zealand will get to put that to work in the America's Cup itself, and, unlike Hutchinson, Beashel was part of the team that was swept, 5-0, by Alinghi last time.</p>
        <p>YACHT RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
