<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Theater in Review</title>
    <meta content="06roun-4" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/theater/reviews/06elec.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852588"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Theater Review | 'Electra'"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Classical Theater of Harlem</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hampton, Wilborn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Preisser, Alfred</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sophocles (C495-406 Bc)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jah, Zainab</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Electra (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Electra (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E6DC1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="446" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Theater in Review</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Burritos for Sophocles</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILBORN HAMPTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hampton, Wilborn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wilborn Hampton reviews Classical Theater of Harlem production of Alfred Preisser adaptation of Sophocles' Electra, Zainab Jah stars (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Electra  Classical Theater of Harlem  647 St. Nicholas Avenue  (212) 868-4444  Through June 24</p>
        <p>Vengeance has always been one of the most passionate of human Pursuits and Sophocles' ''Electra'' is one of dramatic literature's most compelling studies of the extremes to which it can lead. Unfortunately, an adaptation of the play by Alfred Preisser being staged by the Classical Theater of Harlem is more of a spoof of a Greek tragedy than a serious attempt to revive one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Classical Theater of Harlem’s production of Sophocles’ ”Electra” is more of a spoof of a Greek tragedy than a serious attempt to revive one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Electra  Classical Theater of Harlem  647 St. Nicholas Avenue  (212) 868-4444  Through June 24</p>
        <p>Vengeance has always been one of the most passionate of human Pursuits and Sophocles' ''Electra'' is one of dramatic literature's most compelling studies of the extremes to which it can lead. Unfortunately, an adaptation of the play by Alfred Preisser being staged by the Classical Theater of Harlem is more of a spoof of a Greek tragedy than a serious attempt to revive one.</p>
        <p>It is clear from the opening that this ''Electra'' is primarily a conceit of Mr. Preisser's. There are references to TV, burritos, wheelchairs and robots, and the ghost of Agamemnon explains he was ''the Man'' and the ''king of the hill.'' The chorus of four then mentions Christmas and ''eight tiny reindeer.'' That's all in the first few minutes.</p>
        <p>To be sure, productions of classic theater, from the Greeks to Shakespeare, are often successfully moved to different times and locales, and some adaptations even take liberties with texts to make archaic language more accessible. But when such changes alter the basic intent of a play, such as turning a tragedy into a comedy, it means the adapter/director does not trust the original material or does not believe the audience can understand it.</p>
        <p>By the time Electra and her mother, Clytemnestra, have their first confrontation, Mr. Preisser has turned the House of Atreus into a Greek version of ''Big Momma's House.'' For example, Clytemnestra pokes fun at Electra's hairdo, then threatens to send her to ''a finishing school.'' Chrysothemis, Electra's sister in Sophocles' play, enters with a tray of ''finger sandwiches,'' which she keeps offering to her mother and sister. The dialogue is peppered with vulgarities.</p>
        <p>Even the plot has been changed. Sophocles' play begins after the murder of Agamemnon by his wife, Clytemnestra, and her lover, Aegisthus, with Electra burning for revenge. When her brother, Orestes, returns from war, he first kills his mother, then her lover. For some reason Mr. Preisser, who also directed, reverses the order of their deaths. By this time, however, Sophocles' play has been turned into a sitcom, and everyone is waiting for the next laugh cue. When Orestes finally pumps five bullets into Aegisthus, even the overkill gets a chuckle.</p>
        <p>As Electra, Zainab Jah has her moments, especially in her opening speech that begins ''Do you know what it is to hate for 20 years?'' Ms. Jah and Samuel Ray Gates, who plays Orestes, make the most of his homecoming scene. (''Your face is my father's face'') Petronia Paley's Clytemnestra seems to have stepped out of a Noël Coward satire rather than a Sophocles tragedy.</p>
        <p>WILBORN HAMPTON</p>
        <p>Theater Review | 'Electra'</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
