<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Expanding Meatball Universe</title>
    <meta content="06lees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852454"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E0D61130F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Expanding Meatball Universe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT LEE and TED LEE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you've ever suspected that meatballs were a dead end for a restaurant's leftovers, you no longer have reason to fear. These days, chefs are free associating with well-sourced ingredients, clever substitutions and dazzling techniques. Others are refining more authentic variations that highlight the meatball's global appeal (see also: kofte, nem nuong, frikadell, kottbuller, albóndigas, keftedes, tsukune).</p>
        <p>In New York, at the seafood restaurant Esca, the fish specialist David Pasternack brings a classic Italian veal and pancetta meatball into his comfort zone, substituting tuna for the veal. Joey Campanaro uses his grandmother's recipe for meatballs in the sliders he serves at the Little Owl, in Greenwich Village, but the crispy, yeasty-sweet garlic-and-pecorino buns are an innovation he spent months perfecting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you've ever suspected that meatballs were a dead end for a restaurant's leftovers, you no longer have reason to fear. These days, chefs are free associating with well-sourced ingredients, clever substitutions and dazzling techniques. Others are refining more authentic variations that highlight the meatball's global appeal (see also: kofte, nem nuong, frikadell, kottbuller, albóndigas, keftedes, tsukune).</p>
        <p>In New York, at the seafood restaurant Esca, the fish specialist David Pasternack brings a classic Italian veal and pancetta meatball into his comfort zone, substituting tuna for the veal. Joey Campanaro uses his grandmother's recipe for meatballs in the sliders he serves at the Little Owl, in Greenwich Village, but the crispy, yeasty-sweet garlic-and-pecorino buns are an innovation he spent months perfecting.</p>
        <p>Certain chefs lavish as much care and attention on meatballs as they do on foie gras. Some even combine the two. At 112 Eatery in Minneapolis, Isaac Becker grinds top-quality chicken with foie gras, rolling the blend into little spheres that are poached and served by the dozen over fresh tagliatelle. And at A Voce, Andrew Carmellini brushes duck and foie gras meatballs with a dried cherry mostarda, rooting them to the plate with a slick of celery-root purée.</p>
        <p>Whether the interpretations are classical or modernist, one thing is certain: there's never been a better time to order meatballs in America. Perhaps a meatball renaissance was inevitable, the natural next target in the procession of comfort foods (Exhibit A: pizza; Exhibit B: hamburgers; Exhibit C: mac 'n' cheese) that chefs have updated in recent years.</p>
        <p>The dawn of the meatball enlightenment may have occurred five years ago, in 2002, when the diamond-merchant-turned-restaurateur John LaFemina, who was born in Canarsie, Brooklyn, opened Ápizz on the Lower East Side of Manhattan. He took his mother's recipe for veal, beef and pork meatballs, and tweaked it heavily, tripling the meatball's size to that of a softball, coring it like an apple and stuffing the cavity with whipped ricotta and Parmigiano-Reggiano (leaving a beret of the mixture on top), and giving it a smoky finish in a wood-fired oven. An immediate signature dish, it spawned a memoir, ''A Man and His Meatballs'' (Regan Books, 2006), but more important, Mr. LaFemina showed that simple, rustic food could be over-the-top decadent.</p>
        <p>And remember Mama? Rocco DiSpirito's mother, Nicolina DiSpirito, proved her tender, salty meatballs to be the only appealing player in the 2003 reality television drama ''The Restaurant'' (and with a future on QVC no less).</p>
        <p>By about 2004, the dining public was primed to gobble meatballs up, a fact that Nate Appleman, executive chef at the San Francisco restaurant A16, discovered almost by accident. On a Monday shortly after opening his restaurant, which serves food inspired by the cuisine of Campania, he had a bunch of scraps lying around and decided to make meatballs.</p>
        <p>''I thought, no one's going to buy these, they don't even come with a pasta,'' Mr. Appleman said. In fact, they sold out by 8 o'clock, ushering in the tradition of Meatball Mondays. And though he has cycled through about 30 different meatball recipes at the restaurant, Mr. Appleman has settled on a Monday night recipe: pork, ricotta and pancetta meatballs braised in San Marzano tomatoes.</p>
        <p>But the name that trips off the tongue in any meatball discussion among New York chefs is Marco Canora, who put on the bar menu at Craftbar a recipe inspired by the chicken meatballs he learned to make while working in Florence for Fabio Picchi at the restaurant Cibrèo.</p>
        <p>''I changed my recipe to veal and ricotta, and added a ton of grated Parmesan,'' Mr. Canora said. ''They're delicate and super-light with a subtle cheesiness.''</p>
        <p>He brought the recipe with him when he opened his own place, Hearth, but he serves the dish only on Sundays because, he said: ''Meatballs are too trattoria. They don't really fit in with the food at Hearth, which is more elevated. But Sunday's a family night, and if there was any night we could get away with it, it would be Sunday.''</p>
        <p>And although Mr. Canora adapted Mr. Picchi's recipe, he maintains that his own is deeply rooted in Italian tradition. ''I don't need to take meatballs and turn them into some fancy-pants New York 2007 restaurant dish,'' he said.</p>
        <p>While no smart chef these days would admit to fancy-pants aspirations, some do appear eager to indulge the kid-with-a-chemistry-set impulse that itself seems part of the appeal of making meatballs.</p>
        <p>''Before we opened, we decided we wanted to go beyond spaghetti and meatballs,'' Mr. Carmellini of A Voce said. ''And we started to have some fun with it. We came up with a list -- lobster, shrimp, tuna. Duck and cherry seemed like a natural combination.''</p>
        <p>But the duck and cherry pairing was just the beginning. Through multiple tests, Mr. Carmellini found his formula: duck-leg meat, pork shoulder and fatback, ground together and enriched with fresh foie gras that has been strained to a pasty consistency. Eggs and breadcrumbs -- both dry and fresh -- provide the binding for the meatballs, which are baked, then brushed with a mostarda. Mr. Carmellini makes this classic Italian condiment of fruit and mustard extract from dried cherries, grappa, red wine vinegar and Japanese mustard paste. A creamy, aromatic purée of celery root fixes the meatballs in place on the plate and offers an herbal note, a tonic respite from all that meaty matter.</p>
        <p>At 112 Eatery, Mr. Becker's foie gras meatball, slightly simpler than Mr. Carmellini's, came about from a similar experiment. But at the testing stage, he was somewhat apprehensive. ''I had no idea whether the foie gras would melt into the poaching broth and become mush or what,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Not only did the meatballs hold together, but the fat that liquefied into the poaching stock helped form an intense consommé that became the foundation for the dish. ''I just heat the meatballs up in that stock, add a little parsley and butter, and that's it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>For some chefs, like Akhtar Nawab at the E.U. in the East Village, developing a recipe was about finding an angle in a crowded market.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to make sure that if we were going to do meatballs, we were going to do them differently,'' Mr. Nawab said. Prior to assuming the kitchen at the E.U. he had been Mr. Canora's successor at Craftbar, serving Mr. Canora's meatballs. At Mr. Nawab's new restaurant, short for European Union, he had the flexibility to draw from more than just Italian influences.</p>
        <p>''I did some research into an Eastern European recipe, but it evolved into a more Greek recipe, with Moorish and North African influences,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The cumin-, fennel- and coriander-spiced pork meatballs Mr. Nawab serves are roasted in butter and oil, and served on a skewer, drizzled with two sauces: a sweet-tart slurry of shallot, mint and sherry vinegar, and a yogurt sauce made of thick Greek yogurt emulsified with olive oil and fired up with toasted ground cumin. Mr. Nawab credits their tenderness mostly to his treatment of the protein and the fat.</p>
        <p>''I do a really fine grind on the meat, and I use richer pork -- 35 percent fat to 65 percent meat. That makes the meatballs a little more succulent, and helps to caramelize them when they go into the fryer.''</p>
        <p>On the vital issue of meatball texture, all the chefs we interviewed had good tips and pointers, most of which spoke to the same issue: water. For Mr. Campanaro, the key is simple. ''Just like in Italian sausage, the filling is very wet when it goes into the casing,'' he said. ''So when it cooks, it's juicy. That liquid that comes out when you cut it? That's pork stock!''</p>
        <p>Moisture is paramount for Michael Psilakis, the chef of the Greek restaurants Anthos in Midtown and Kefi on the Upper West Side, where he serves tsoutsoukakia, a modified version of the keftedes his grandmother made in Crete. (While she was content to fry them and squeeze lemon over them, Mr. Psilakis fries them, then braises them in a rich sauce of tomato and onions that is spiked with garlic confit, olives, fresh dill, mint, parsley and pecorino). But in his meatballs, the liquid in the mixture comes from store-bought bread that is soaked in milk. Mr. Psilakis recommends refrigerating the meatball mixture to make rolling the balls easier.</p>
        <p>''Most people are afraid when it's sticky,'' Mr. Psilakis said. ''They shouldn't be. The mixture that's going to get you that light, airy texture is going to be a wet, tacky substance that's not so easy to roll.'' He recommends a light dusting of flour on your hands, and just a gentle once or twice around in your palms -- no kneading -- as well as frequent washing of hands and redusting with flour.</p>
        <p>Naturally, there are some voices of dissent about meatball mania. Some chefs have found them to be sticky in more than one sense: once they add meatballs to the menu they can't take them off. And some diners bristle at the more creative high jinks of the cherries-and-foie-gras set. Mr. Carmellini's duck meatballs reportedly inspired one diner to exclaim, ''This is not Italian cooking!''</p>
        <p>''You're absolutely right, it's not,'' he said he replied. ''But they taste so good.''</p>
        <p>Where meatballs are concerned, results are more important than authenticity. Kenny Tufo, the chef at Bocca Lupo in Cobble Hill, Brooklyn, and a third-generation Sicilian-American, said he was deeply influenced by Maremma, the Manhattan restaurant where he cooked for two years (and where the executive chef, Cesare Casella, offers at least two and sometimes three varieties of meatballs).</p>
        <p>''There's only a couple chefs in the U.S. as authentically Tuscan as Cesare,'' he said, ''and I learned a lot from him about how to build flavors the Italian way.''</p>
        <p>So are the turbocharged veal and porcini meatballs he serves at Bocca Lupo with porcini-infused marinara a Tuscan recipe? He hesitated before answering: ''Well, no; it's Brooklyn.''</p>
        <p>Veal and Ricotta Meatballs  Adapted from Marco Canora  Time: 31/4 hours, plus 1 hour chilling and overnight draining of ricotta</p>
        <p>1 pound ricotta cheese  1 pound ground veal (triple ground by butcher or at home), chilled  2 large eggs  1 cup freshly grated Parmigiano-Reggiano, plus more for serving  1 tablespoon salt, or as needed  Freshly ground black pepper  Freshly grated nutmeg, as needed  Vegetable oil for frying  1 cup flour, or as needed  4 cups mild tomato sauce.</p>
        <p>1. Wrap ricotta in cheesecloth a day before serving and place in a sieve set over a bowl. Weight cheese, cover and refrigerate overnight. (Cheese should then have consistency of tofu.)  2. The next day, combine all ingredients except flour, oil and sauce in a bowl and mix with hands until completely smooth, pale and homogenized, about 4 minutes. Test seasoning by frying a bit in hot oil. It should taste assertively salty (braising in sauce tames seasoning); adjust salt if needed. Cover and chill before shaping into meatballs.  3. Dust a baking sheet and your hands with flour. Keep remaining flour nearby in bowl. Gently form meat into nine balls. Place on baking sheet, cover with plastic wrap and refrigerate until chilled, about 1 hour.  4. Place about 11/2 inches oil in large skillet over medium-high heat. When oil is hot, fry meatballs, moving them as little as possible. When bottoms are golden brown, after about 2 minutes, gently turn them. Fry until uniformly brown on all sides. Meanwhile, heat sauce in pot over medium-low heat and when meatballs are done, remove from oil with slotted spoon and add to sauce.  5. Simmer over medium-low heat for at least 30 minutes; they can remain in the sauce for hours. Season with salt and pepper to taste. Can be refrigerated overnight, and gently reheated. Serve meatballs in sauce alone, or over pasta, with grated Parmigiano-Reggiano passed separately.  Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Pork Meatballs With Yogurt Dressing  Adapted from Akhtar Nawab  Time: 1 hour</p>
        <p>For yogurt dressing  1 cup high-fat Greek yogurt  11/2 tablespoons ground cumin  1 tablespoon sugar  1/4 cup extra virgin olive oil  Salt and freshly ground black pepper</p>
        <p>For mint dressing  1/2 cup finely sliced mint leaves  11/2 teaspoons minced shallots  11/2 tablespoons sherry vinegar  1/2 cup extra virgin olive oil  Salt and freshly ground black pepper</p>
        <p>For meatballs  1 cup crustless country bread, torn into pieces  2 tablespoons milk  3 tablespoons olive oil  Half a large onion, peeled and thinly sliced  2 teaspoons coriander seeds  1 tablespoon cumin seeds  1 teaspoon fennel seeds  1/2 teaspoon hot red-pepper flakes  21/2 pounds ground pork, chilled  1 tablespoon kosher salt  2 teaspoons finely chopped parsley leaves  1 tablespoon finely chopped fresh oregano  4 tablespoons butter.</p>
        <p>1. For yogurt dressing, combine yogurt, cumin, and sugar. Slowly whisk in oil. Season to taste with salt and pepper, cover and refrigerate.  2. For mint dressing, combine mint, shallot and vinegar in small bowl. Slowly whisk in oil. Season with salt and pepper to taste, cover and refrigerate.  3. For meatballs, combine bread and milk in a bowl, and stir until bread has absorbed milk.  4. Combine 1 tablespoon of oil and onion in a saucepan over medium heat. Stir until sizzling, then cover, reduce heat to low and cook until onion is softened but not colored. Transfer to food processor, add bread mixture and purée.  5. Combine coriander, cumin, fennel and hot red-pepper flakes in small skillet over medium heat and stir until lightly toasted and fragrant. Remove from heat and grind to a powder in a spice grinder.  6. Mix meat, the bread mixture, spices and salt in a large stand mixer with paddle attachment. Add parsley and oregano, and mix again. With wet hands, roll into 1-inch balls.  7. Place large skillet over medium heat. Add butter and remaining 2 tablespoons olive oil. When butter has melted, reduce heat slightly and begin adding meatballs, allowing them to brown on the bottom, then turning gently to continue browning on all sides. Work in batches, transferring meatballs to a platter when they are cooked. To serve, drizzle with yogurt dressing and sprinkle with mint dressing.  Yield: 50 1-inch meatballs (serves about 12 as an hors d'oeuvre).</p>
        <p>Tuna Meatballs  Adapted from 'The Young Man and the Sea,' by David Pasternack and Ed Levine (Artisan, 2007)  Time: 2 hours</p>
        <p>3/4 cup bread cubes from stale baguette  1/2 cup whole milk  5 tablespoons extra virgin olive oil  2 cloves garlic, thinly sliced  11/2 pounds tuna, cut into 1-inch chunks  2 ounces pancetta, finely diced (1/4 cup)  1 large egg, lightly beaten  1 tablespoon chopped flat-leaf parsley  1/4 teaspoon red-pepper flakes  Sea salt  Freshly ground black pepper  4 cups mild tomato sauce  1 pound spaghetti.</p>
        <p>1. Soak bread in milk in small bowl for 30 minutes. Place work bowl and blade of food processor in freezer.  2. Heat 2 tablespoons of oil in medium pan over medium heat. Add garlic and stir occasionally until translucent, about 3 minutes. Set pan aside to cool.  3. Squeeze bread to remove excess milk, put in chilled food processor bowl with tuna and pancetta. Pulse until just coarsely ground and combined. Refrigerate briefly. Add garlic and its oil, 2 tablespoons water, egg, parsley and red-pepper flakes. Season with 1/2 teaspoon salt and a few grindings of pepper. Lightly but thoroughly mix with hands.  4. Make a small meatball and sauté in a bit of oil over medium-high heat to taste for seasoning. Adjusting seasonings if necessary.  5. Heat sauce in a 6-quart pot over low heat.  6. With moistened hands, form 20 meatballs, each about 13/4 inch in diameter (about 11/2 ounces). Heat remaining 3 tablespoons olive oil in pan on medium high until hot but not smoking. Cook meatballs in batches until well browned all around, 6 to 8 minutes. When done, transfer to sauce with slotted spoon. When all the meatballs are in sauce, partially cover pot and gently simmer for 1 hour, stirring carefully occasionally.  7. Bring large pot of salted water to a boil and cook spaghetti until almost al dente. Drain and serve in bowl with sauce and meatballs spooned over.  Yield: 4 servings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
