<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Eternal Vaudeville Of the Spiritual Mind</title>
    <meta content="06bran" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/06/theater/reviews/06bran.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852474"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eckert, Rinde</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schweizer, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Horizon (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Theater Workshop</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Eckert, Rinde</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Niebuhr, Reinhold</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Horizon (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E6DF1E30F935A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="995" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Eternal Vaudeville Of the Spiritual Mind</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Eternal Vaudeville of the Spiritual Mind</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley reviews Rinde Eckert play Horizon, directed by David Schweizer; Eckert stars; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>God is in the curriculum in the lively lecture hall that has been made of the New York Theater Workshop, where Rinde Eckert's ''Horizon'' opened last night. But even the fiercest secularist should find pleasure in this engaging performance piece, which is set in the seminary-without-walls of one man's mind.</p>
        <p>The furnishings of that mind will look familiar to anyone with a glancing knowledge of Christian philosophy in the 20th century. ''Horizon,'' directed by David Schweizer, is Mr. Eckert's homage in song, sketch and rumination to Reinhold Niebuhr (1892-1971), generally acknowledged as the most influential American theologian of his time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even the fiercest secularist should find pleasure in Rinde Eckert’s engaging performance piece about Reinhold Niebuhr, the influential American theologian.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>God is in the curriculum in the lively lecture hall that has been made of the New York Theater Workshop, where Rinde Eckert's ''Horizon'' opened last night. But even the fiercest secularist should find pleasure in this engaging performance piece, which is set in the seminary-without-walls of one man's mind.</p>
        <p>The furnishings of that mind will look familiar to anyone with a glancing knowledge of Christian philosophy in the 20th century. ''Horizon,'' directed by David Schweizer, is Mr. Eckert's homage in song, sketch and rumination to Reinhold Niebuhr (1892-1971), generally acknowledged as the most influential American theologian of his time.</p>
        <p>Not that Reinhart Poole, the character portrayed by Mr. Eckert, is a biographical facsimile of Niebuhr, whose writings on the practical applications of Christianity to political conduct have been appropriated in recent years by both neoconservatives and liberals, including Barack Obama.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eckert is less concerned with presenting the worldly details of his character's life than with distilling the intellectual essence behind it. There are no equivalents in ''Horizon'' to the varying (and to some of his disciples, perplexingly varied) political stances adopted by Niebuhr during a career that lasted through and was shaped by the vicissitudes of World War II, the cold war and the Vietnam War -- subjects on which Niebuhr had much to say.</p>
        <p>Instead Mr. Eckert has deliberately placed his man of God in a sort of spiritual laboratory: a seminary, to be exact, where Poole has taught for 25 years and from which he is being forced to depart for ominous but unspecified reasons. ''Horizon'' is set on the day of his last class, which becomes in a sense his last day in an academic Eden, where theory is unchallenged and uncontaminated by practice.</p>
        <p>This framework gives a grounding dramatic tension to a work that might otherwise float entirely in the clouds of cerebration. It is also an ideal structure to consider the worldview of a man who advocated what came to be called ''Christian realism,'' a theory that embraces the necessity of adaptation and the danger of absolutes in a universe of flux.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eckert and Mr. Schweizer are faced with their own, appropriately Niebuhrian adaptive challenges, those of transforming the vapors of intellectual discourse into the flashy flesh of showbiz. How do you hold the attention of a nonacademic audience on subjects -- ethics, God's judgment, allegory, doubt -- that Mr. Eckert regularly spells out in capital letters on a bank of blackboards?</p>
        <p>Mr. Eckert's felicitous discovery here is that Niebuhr's philosophical approach translates naturally into theatrical terms. For Niebuhr, man always saw God through a glass darkly; you needed the interpretive tools of parable and allegory to begin to comprehend the ineffable, with the important caveat that the symbol must never be mistaken for the real thing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eckert's rangy, magnetically restless Poole, assisted by two vivacious shape-shifting actors (David Barlow and Howard Swain), keeps these levels of intellectual awareness in play with the verve of a vaudevillian juggler. His instructional devices include a play-within-the-play, an eternally unfinished work by Poole about the construction of an eternally unfinished church; brisk story-theater enactments of parables and songs that vary in tone from hymnal to hillbilly, from barbershop harmonies to arias of anguish.</p>
        <p>Occasional personal detours are integrated into the flow of ideas: remembered catechisms with Poole's father (also a minister, as was Niebuhr's) and mother; childhood arguments with the brother who later disappeared from his life (giving a visceral relevance to the tale of the prodigal son); admonitions from his long-suffering wife, who wants Poole to look up from his notes and see the sunset.</p>
        <p>Some of the vignettes have the grating didactic preciousness of a ''Sesame Street'' for grown-ups. (Can you say ''original sin,'' boys and girls?) But Mr. Eckert, whose previous works have drawn inspiration from the knotty minds of W. B. Yeats and Herman Melville, is undeniably expert in anchoring elusive ideas to the point at which they become graspable. The forms he uses are often deliberately simple, precisely because the content is anything but.</p>
        <p>The notion of allegory as a means of comprehension extends to Alexander V. Nichols's set, a combination of construction site and classroom, with an assortment of cinderblocks, wooden planks and sheets of plastic, as well as the professorial blackboards.</p>
        <p>The cinderblocks, those unpromising deadweights, become wondrously fluid elements of transformation, especially in a parable about the dangers of idol worship, which is what happens when symbol is mistaken for substance. This cautionary tale could be applied to the rigorously literal-minded of any faith and sets off unsettling echoes in this age of raging religious divisiveness.</p>
        <p>In 2005 the historian Arthur M. Schlesinger Jr., who died earlier this year, wrote an essay in these pages suggesting that it was time to rediscover Niebuhr, a writer who warned against the dangers of nations that ''try to play the role of God in history.'' Without ever making specific political references, and keeping his character poised on the edge of active engagement, Mr. Eckert has invitingly and unobtrusively opened the door for such a reacquaintance.</p>
        <p>At the same time, he finds vivifying parallels between the theological quest of one man and the theatrical quest to capture and illuminate life. In ''Horizon,'' the dynamics of art and religion are remarkably and nobly the same.</p>
        <p>Horizon</p>
        <p>Created, written and composed by Rinde Eckert; directed by David Schweizer; sets and lighting by Alexander V. Nichols; sound by Gregory T. Kuhn; choreography by David Barlow; production stage managers, Chad Brown and Odessa (Niki) Spruill; assistant stage manager, Richard A. Hodge; executive producer, Susan Endrizzi. Presented by the New York Theater Workshop, James C. Nicola, artistic director; Lynn Moffat, managing director. At the New York Theater Workshop, 79 East Fourth Street, East Village; (212) 239-6200. Through July 1. Running time: 1 hour, 25 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: David Barlow (Mason No. 1/Reinhart's Wife/Reinhart's Brother), Rinde Eckert (Reinhart Poole) and Howard Swain (Mason No. 2/Reinhart's Mother/Reinhart's Father).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
