<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge Says He Will Suspend Durham Prosecutor Immediately</title>
    <meta content="19duke" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/us/19duke.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina/Durham</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Duke University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Nifong, Michael B</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Evans, David F</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Seligmann, Reade</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Finnerty, Collin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E1DF133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="709" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge Says He Will Suspend Durham Prosecutor Immediately</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Judge Says He Will Suspend Durham Prosecutor</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DUFF WILSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilson, Duff</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The senior judge in Durham, N.C., said last night that he would file orders this morning to immediately suspend from office Michael B. Nifong, the district attorney at the center of the Duke lacrosse case.</p>
        <p>Also yesterday, Duke University announced an agreement to head off any possible legal claims against the university by three former lacrosse players who were falsely accused of sexual assault by a woman hired to strip at a team party.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Also, Duke University announced an agreement to avoid legal action by three former lacrosse players falsely accused of sexual assault.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The senior judge in Durham, N.C., said last night that he would file orders this morning to immediately suspend from office Michael B. Nifong, the district attorney at the center of the Duke lacrosse case.</p>
        <p>Also yesterday, Duke University announced an agreement to head off any possible legal claims against the university by three former lacrosse players who were falsely accused of sexual assault by a woman hired to strip at a team party.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nifong was disbarred Saturday and had promised to resign, but he told the governor he planned to stay in office four more weeks.</p>
        <p>''I will suspend him in the morning,'' Judge Orlando F. Hudson Jr. of Superior Court said in a telephone interview last night.</p>
        <p>Judge Hudson said he would also authorize Sheriff Worth Hill to ''enforce the order to the best of his ability.''</p>
        <p>''That is,'' the judge said, ''if that means removal of Mr. Nifong from the building, I think the sheriff can do that, or take away his parking pass or his key.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nifong did not answer his home phone last night, and his lawyer did not return calls.</p>
        <p>Judge Hudson said a state law gave the senior judge in a county the power to remove a prosecutor if the judge believed  there was  probable cause in a petition for removal. Such a petition was filed earlier this year against Mr. Nifong, but Judge Hudson  delayed hearing it while the bar association ethics proceedings against the prosecutor were pending.</p>
        <p>''I watched the proceedings just like everybody else did,'' Judge Hudson said last night. ''I felt that he should resign immediately.''</p>
        <p>The disbarment by a state panel takes effect 30 days after papers are filed. Mr. Nifong said Friday that he would resign, and he sent a letter to Gov. Michael F. Easley giving July 13 as his resignation date.</p>
        <p>In a letter to Judge Hudson, he said,  ''It is my fervent hope that this action will spare this community the further anguish that a removal hearing would entail and allow the healing process to move forward.''</p>
        <p>Judge Hudson said Mr. Nifong would  be suspended with pay.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the terms of the agreement reached by Duke and the three lacrosse players were undisclosed under a confidentiality agreement. Duke had faced the possibility of lawsuits by the players, but none had been filed.</p>
        <p>The university had been criticized for actions by the lacrosse coach and the dean of students, who told the 46 lacrosse team members to go to a police station to have their pictures taken and to provide DNA samples without first advising them to talk to their parents and lawyers. It has also come under criticism for statements by some faculty members who thanked protesters in the wake of the incident in March 2006 and statements by Richard H. Brodhead, the Duke president, initially viewed as insufficiently supportive of the three former players.</p>
        <p>In more recent months, Mr. Brodhead has been harshly critical of Mr. Nifong, who pursued the case despite a lack of evidence.</p>
        <p>The North Carolina attorney general took the case from Mr. Nifong in January and announced in April that the woman was not credible and that the former students -- David F. Evans, 24, Reade W. Seligmann, 21, and Collin Finnerty, 20 -- were innocent.</p>
        <p>In a statement Monday, Mr. Brodhead and the Duke Board of Trustees said: ''We welcomed their exoneration and deeply regret the difficult year they and their families have had to endure. They conducted themselves with great dignity during their long ordeal.''</p>
        <p>John F. Burness, senior vice president for public affairs at Duke, said the parties wanted to avoid the possibility of months and years of litigation.</p>
        <p>''We all agreed it's best to put it behind us,'' Mr. Burness said in an interview.</p>
        <p>A statement from the three men said: ''The events of the last year tore the Duke community apart, and forcibly separated us from the university we love.''</p>
        <p>It concluded, ''We hope that today's resolution will begin to bring the Duke family back together again, and we look forward to working with the university to develop and implement initiatives that will prevent similar injustices and ensure that the lessons of the last year are never forgotten.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
