<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Unfreezes Millions in Aid To Palestinians</title>
    <meta content="19diplo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/world/middleeast/19diplo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855558"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assets, Frozen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Bank</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza Strip</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fatah</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hamas</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Helene</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abbas, Mahmoud (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olmert, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (DC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">European Union</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E1DF133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1062" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Unfreezes Millions in Aid To Palestinians</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Unfreezes Millions in Aid to Palestinians</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HELENE COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Helene</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States ends its economic and political embargo of Palestinian Authority in bid to bolster Pres Mahmoud Abbas and new Fatah-led emergency government he established in West Bank as counterweight to Hamas-controlled Gaza; tens of millions of dollars in aid to Palestinians has been frozen since Hamas victory in legislative elections in early 2006; European Union also announces plans to resume direct aid to Palestinians; Prime Min Ehud Olmert says Israel would release to Abbas Palestinian tax revenues that Israel has withheld since Hamas took control of Palestinian parliament; Bush administration has steered into new territory by siding so firmly with Abbas; his decision to strip Hamas of its representation in National Security Council and to form new emergency government has already kindled legal battle over whether he has overstepped boundaries laid out in Palestinian constitution; American moves seen as step toward 'West Bank first' strategy in which money, aid and international political recognition would be heaped on West Bank in order to provide Palestinians there and in Gaza with preview of what life could be like with pro-Western government in charge; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States on Monday ended an economic and political embargo of the Palestinian Authority in a bid to bolster President Mahmoud Abbas and the new Fatah-led emergency government he has established in the West Bank as a counterweight to Hamas-controlled Gaza.</p>
        <p>The American decision freed up tens of millions of dollars in aid to the Palestinians that has been frozen since the Hamas victory in legislative elections in early 2006. The European Union similarly announced plans to resume direct aid to the Palestinians, while Prime Minister Ehud Olmert said Israel would release to Mr. Abbas Palestinian tax revenues that Israel has withheld since Hamas took control of the Palestinian parliament.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The decision ending an embargo of the Palestinian Authority was a bid to bolster President Mahmoud Abbas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States on Monday ended an economic and political embargo of the Palestinian Authority in a bid to bolster President Mahmoud Abbas and the new Fatah-led emergency government he has established in the West Bank as a counterweight to Hamas-controlled Gaza.</p>
        <p>The American decision freed up tens of millions of dollars in aid to the Palestinians that has been frozen since the Hamas victory in legislative elections in early 2006. The European Union similarly announced plans to resume direct aid to the Palestinians, while Prime Minister Ehud Olmert said Israel would release to Mr. Abbas Palestinian tax revenues that Israel has withheld since Hamas took control of the Palestinian parliament.</p>
        <p>But in siding so firmly with Mr. Abbas, the Bush administration steered into new territory in its dealings with the Palestinians, as it essentially threw its support behind the dismantling of a democratically elected government. Mr. Abbas's decision to strip Hamas of its representation in the National Security Council to form a new emergency government has already kindled a legal battle over whether he has overstepped boundaries laid out in the Palestinian constitution.</p>
        <p>The American moves amount to a major step toward what some call a ''West Bank first'' strategy in which money, aid and international political recognition would be heaped on the West Bank, leaving Gaza to be ruled by Hamas, largely as its fief.</p>
        <p>But Middle East experts said the Palestinian constitution might allow Mr. Abbas's emergency government to remain in power for only 60 days, and Hamas, which won the last legislative elections, has indicated that it will not agree to new elections on Mr. Abbas's timetable.</p>
        <p>''We are going to support President Abbas and what he wants to do,'' Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice said in announcing the change in policy. She said the United States would work to ''restructure'' and unfreeze $86 million in aid that was originally set out to help Mr. Abbas build up his security forces. It was frozen because Hamas would not renounce violence, was considered a terrorist group and did not believe Israel had a right to exist.</p>
        <p>By diplomatic standards, the American response to the upheaval in the Palestinian territories has come about at the speed of lightning. It was less than a week ago that Hamas gunmen routed rival Fatah forces in Gaza, and took control over Fatah-run outposts on the teeming strip on the Mediterranean. Mr. Abbas called it a coup, dissolved the national unity government and announced a new cabinet made up of his allies and situated in the West Bank, where Fatah remains strong.</p>
        <p>At least for now, the United States and Europe appear in agreement that perhaps the only way to salvage some advantage from the Hamas victory in Gaza is to bolster Mr. Abbas in the West Bank, in order to provide Palestinians there and in Gaza with a preview of what life could be like with a pro-Western government in charge.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rice, in response to a question at a news conference on Monday, said she considered Mr. Abbas's new government to be legitimate. ''I think we will leave to the Palestinians issues of how they work through their own constitutional issues,'' she said. ''Our view, very strongly, is that what President Abbas has done is legitimate and it is responsible and we're going to support that action.''</p>
        <p>But Daniel Levy, a senior fellow at the New America Foundation and a former Israeli peace negotiator, said the American move to back Mr. Abbas ''looks suspiciously like there's an effort afoot to reimpose single party rule on the Palestinian body politic.''</p>
        <p>President Bush, who is to meet with Mr. Olmert at the White House on Tuesday, informed Mr. Abbas of the policy shift during a telephone conversation on Monday. Mr. Abbas moved quickly to capitalize on the shift, telling Mr. Bush that it was time to restart Middle East peace talks with Israel, his spokesman said. That is something that Ms. Rice has been pushing but, so far, with little overt backing from Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>''Everyone has looked over into the abyss and seen what happens when moderates don't come together,'' said David Makovsky, a senior fellow at the Washington Institute for Near East Policy. ''What we're seeing now is a second chance for everybody.''</p>
        <p>Administration officials said Monday that Mr. Bush might use the coming five-year anniversary of his announcement of a roadmap toward a two-state solution for Israelis and Palestinians as an occasion to throw his weight behind a renewed push for peace talks.</p>
        <p>Plans for a regional meeting next week between Arab and Israeli officials, along with representatives from Europe, the United Nations and the United States, were put on the shelf for now, Arab officials said. But in a telephone call with Mr. Olmert, King Abdullah II of Jordan urged Israelis and Palestinians to restart the peace process.</p>
        <p>Officially, Bush administration officials insisted they would not write off Gaza, and Ms. Rice said the United States would give $40 million to the United Nations to finance relief projects there. ''It is the position of the United States that there is one Palestinian people and there should be one Palestinian state,'' she said. ''We will not leave one and a half million Palestinians at the mercy of terrorist organizations.''</p>
        <p>A ''West Bank first'' strategy would mean leaning on the Israeli government to dismantle settlements, ease up on travel restrictions for Palestinians moving around the West Bank, and release a substantial number of Palestinian prisoners being held by Israel, Middle East experts said. Such moves would probably require significant prodding from the Bush administration; it is unclear whether Mr. Bush, who has thus far refrained from pressuring Israel to make political concessions to Mr. Abbas, will actually do so now.</p>
        <p>''This is as serious as it gets,'' said Ziad Asali, head of the American Task Force on Palestine. ''It is time to lift the siege off the Palestinian people. This is the time to open up the political and economic horizons, and wage a campaign for the hearts and minds of the Palestinian people.''</p>
        <p>The Associated Press reported that a Hamas spokesman, Sami Abu Zuhri, accused the international community of hypocrisy, noting that Hamas had defeated Fatah in parliamentary elections in 2006. ''This confirms the falseness of the international community's support for democracy,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
