<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Zimbabwe Opens First Talks With Opposition</title>
    <meta content="19zimbabwe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/world/africa/19zimbabwe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Zimbabwe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wines, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mugabe, Robert G (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Zimbabwe</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Mugabe, Robert</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E1DE133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="505" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Zimbabwe Opens First Talks With Opposition</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Zimbabwe Opens First Talks With Opposition</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wines, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>JOHANNESBURG, June 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Members of Zimbabwe's government and its political opposition meet in Pretoria for their first face-to-face talks since South Africa was asked in March to mediate; both sides agree not to reveal details of talks, which are aimed at establishing rules for presidential election scheduled for March 2008; efforts to make peace between government and opposition have been virtually stalled since Pres Robert G Mugabe agreed to talks under pressure from southern African political leaders (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Members of Zimbabwe's government and its political opposition met in Pretoria over the weekend for their first face-to-face talks since South Africa was asked in March to mediate between them.</p>
        <p>Both sides have agreed not to reveal details of the talks, which are aimed at establishing rules for Zimbabwe's presidential election, scheduled for March 2008. But one person knowledgeable about the negotiations said the meeting had been a preliminary session, held to set the agenda for further talks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Both sides have agreed not to reveal details of the talks, which are aimed at establishing rules for Zimbabwe’s presidential election, scheduled for March 2008.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Members of Zimbabwe's government and its political opposition met in Pretoria over the weekend for their first face-to-face talks since South Africa was asked in March to mediate between them.</p>
        <p>Both sides have agreed not to reveal details of the talks, which are aimed at establishing rules for Zimbabwe's presidential election, scheduled for March 2008. But one person knowledgeable about the negotiations said the meeting had been a preliminary session, held to set the agenda for further talks.</p>
        <p>That person, who spoke on condition of anonymity because negotiations were still under way, said there had been some evidence of progress at the meeting.</p>
        <p>Efforts to make peace between the government and the opposition have been virtually stalled since Zimbabwe's president, Robert G. Mugabe, agreed to the talks under pressure from southern African political leaders at a regional meeting in March.</p>
        <p>Leaders of the opposition, the Movement for Democratic Change, had gone to Pretoria to begin the talks several weeks ago, but government negotiators did not show up. Last week, the police confiscated the passport of one of the opposition leaders, Arthur Mutambara, the head of a breakaway faction of the opposition group.</p>
        <p>Critics of the 27-year rule of Mr. Mugabe have been under steady assault by the police and government loyalists since January, and hundreds of civic leaders, human rights advocates and members of the Movement for Democratic Change have been beaten, abducted or arrested in recent months.</p>
        <p>In recent days, however, Mr. Mugabe has seemed to soften his stance. Last week, a government-controlled daily newspaper, The Herald, reported that Mr. Mugabe had distributed tractors and plows to a clutch of political leaders, including opposition politicians, saying: ''There must be occasions when we must be together. After all, we eat together.''</p>
        <p>The gesture was almost unprecedented for Mr. Mugabe, who calls his political opponents tools of Britain and the United States and has openly threatened them with beatings.</p>
        <p>Opposition leaders dismissed the remarks as political theater. But Zimbabwe's rulers have come under growing pressure to change their governing style in the wake of a disastrous April harvest, which will mean widespread hunger in a few months, and amid uncontrolled inflation.</p>
        <p>Zimbabwe newspapers, citing leaked government documents, reported in the past week that the annual inflation rate leapt to 4,530 percent in May, up from 3,714 percent in April. Most economists say  those figures do not reflect the true inflation rate, which they say is far higher.</p>
        <p>The government also appears to be in growing peril from internal dissent. The Herald reported in recent days that six men, including officials of the military and the police, had been charged with treason in connection with a plot to oust Mr. Mugabe and replace him with the government's housing minister, Emmerson Mnangagwa. The report could not be independently verified.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mnangagwa, who has denied any connection with such a plot, once hoped to succeed Mr. Mugabe, who is 83, but Mr. Mnangagwa has fallen out of favor among Mr. Mugabe's backers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
