<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New DVDs</title>
    <meta content="19dvd" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/movies/19dvd.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855562"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC$(RSQUO$)S CHOICE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/DVD and Video</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Martial Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Martial Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Weinstein Company</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE1DF133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1030" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New DVDs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New DVDs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE KEHR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE 36TH CHAMBER OF SHAOLIN</p>
        <p>A frequent candidate for the finest martial arts movie ever made, ''The 36th Chamber of Shaolin'' has at last been rescued from the video bargain bins (where it has long languished under the title ''Shaolin Master Killer'') and given a first-class release by the Weinstein Company's new Asian action label, Dragon Dynasty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A frequent candidate for the finest martial arts movie ever made, “The 36th Chamber of Shaolin” has at last been rescued from video bargain bins by the Weinstein Company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE 36TH CHAMBER OF SHAOLIN</p>
        <p>A frequent candidate for the finest martial arts movie ever made, ''The 36th Chamber of Shaolin'' has at last been rescued from the video bargain bins (where it has long languished under the title ''Shaolin Master Killer'') and given a first-class release by the Weinstein Company's new Asian action label, Dragon Dynasty.</p>
        <p>Produced by the storied Shaw Brothers studio, ''36th Chamber'' (1978) belongs to the second wave of the golden age of Hong Kong action filmmaking. It was released when the ground rules laid down in the mid-1960s by the genre's pioneers, King Hu and Chang Cheh, were giving way to the harsher vision of a younger generation of directors, much as the epic westerns of John Ford and Howard Hawks led to the tighter, nervier work of Anthony Mann and Budd Boetticher.</p>
        <p>But the western analogy goes only so far: structurally, the Hollywood genre the martial arts films most resemble is the musical. The trick in both genres is to find a plausible, unobtrusive and emotionally satisfying way to arrange a series of disconnected performance pieces, and ''36th Chamber,'' written by the prolific Ni Kuang and directed by Liu Chia-liang,  finds an elegant solution.</p>
        <p>Loosely based on the traditional story of San Te, the Shaolin monk who introduced the secrets of kung fu to the Chinese masses oppressed by Manchurian rule, ''36th Chamber'' follows San Te's training at the legendary Shaolin temple, as he progresses from a spoiled merchant's son to a grand master.  His training takes him through a series of chambers in which he confronts different tactical and physical challenges, ranging from balancing on floating logs to head-butting his way through a corridor blocked by low-hanging sandbags.</p>
        <p>This is, of course, the structure of practically every video game ever designed, but it makes for a beautifully paced and consistently surprising movie. Mr. Liu, directing his brother Gordon Liu as San Te, brings different styles and rhythms to each chamber, ranging from horror-movie intensity to slapstick comic relief.</p>
        <p>Mr. Liu, who also directs and does action choreography (most recently for Tsui Hark's ill-fated ''Seven Swords'') under the Cantonese transcription of his name, Lau Kar-leung, possesses an impeccable sense of how action is amplified and energized by editing, and there are passages here that approach the purity of dance. (Gordon Liu, with his unsmiling, classical poise and clarity of line, would not seem out of place in a ballet company.)The Dragon Dynasty transfer actually improves on the Hong Kong DVD release, with a brighter, sharper image and a heap of supplementary material. The extras  include an interview with Gordon Liu (recently seen in two roles in the ''Kill Bill'' films) and a commentary track by the musician RZA of Wu-Tang Clan (a Shaolin scholar of some standing) and the Los Angeles film critic Andy Klein. (The Weinstein Company, $19.95, R)</p>
        <p>THE THREE MUSKETEERS</p>
        <p>A peer of D. W. Griffith's and one of the most formally innovative of early filmmakers, Allan Dwan directed several of the best-known films of the silent swashbuckler Douglas Fairbanks. Their last film together was ''The Iron Mask'' (1929), in which Fairbanks played D'Artagnan, the dashing leader of the Three Musketeers.</p>
        <p>Ten years later Mr. Dwan found himself at 20th Century Fox with a D'Artagnan to be played by Don Ameche, the golden-voiced but less than athletic leading man of countless period musicals, and Musketeers to be played by the Ritz Brothers, a trio of knockabout vaudeville comedians.</p>
        <p>Instead of throwing up his hands or walking off the set  --  directors didn't do things like that in those days  -- Mr. Dwan set to work and spun this terrific entertainment out of a four-song score and a one-joke script. (The Ritzes are kitchen lackeys caught borrowing the real Musketeers' uniforms.)</p>
        <p>Working very much in the Fairbanks spirit of smiling insouciance, Mr. Dwan maximizes the resources of the studio, including three glamorous female stars (Binnie Barnes, Gloria Stuart and Pauline Moore); an amazing roster of character actors (Joseph Schildkraut, John Carradine, Lionel Atwill, Miles Mander, Douglass Dumbrille, Russell Hicks, Moroni Olsen); and acres of elaborate period sets that covered the hills of what is now the Century City section of Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dwan's great gift, which he discovered early on, was for opening up practically any shot into a complex, three-dimensional space that pulled in the viewer by strategically placed fore- and midground objects, a gift that gives his work a weight and presence equaled by few other filmmakers.</p>
        <p>The tireless Mr. Dwan found time to make two other films in that magical movie year of 1939: ''The Gorilla,'' a rousing old dark-house comedy that teamed the Ritz Brothers with Bela Lugosi, and the altogether remarkable ''Frontier Marshal,'' a sharp, cynical version of the Wyatt Earp myth that initiates a chain of comically disillusioned westerns that leads straight to Sergio Leone.</p>
        <p>The Fox disc, part of the studio's Cinema Classics Collection, offers a dark, rich transfer with excellent contrast and detail. (20th Century Fox Home Entertainment, $19.98, not rated)</p>
        <p>ALSO OUT TODAY</p>
        <p>THE BRIDGE TO TERABITHIA Two lonely fifth graders imagine a magic kingdom of their own in Gabor Csupo's adaptation of Katherine Paterson's young-adult novel. With Josh Hutcherson and AnnaSophia Robb. (Walt Disney Video, $29.99, PG)</p>
        <p>MISS POTTER The tale of Beatrix Potter (Renée Zellweger) and how she came to create Peter Rabbit. Chris Noonan (''Babe'') directed. (The Weinstein Company, $28.95, PG)</p>
        <p>IF.  ...</p>
        <p>Lindsay Anderson's 1968 fable of revolt in a British boys' school, led by the charismatic Malcolm McDowell in his first of three appearances as Anderson's much abused Everyman, Mick Travis. (The Criterion Collection, $39.95, R)</p>
        <p>PERRY MASON: SEASON 2, VOLUME 1 After a decade of playing sadistic heavies (from ''Raw Deal'' to ''Rear Window''), Raymond Burr became America's most stolid representative of law and order as ''Perry Mason'' hit its stride in its second season, 1958-59. This four-disc set has 15 shows from the season's first half  and includes episodes directed by Gerd Oswald (''The Case of 'the Purple Woman' ''), Arthur Hiller (''The Case of the Fancy Figures'') and Andrew V. McLaglen (''The Case of the Shattered Dream''). (Paramount, $38.99, not rated)</p>
        <p>CRITIC$(RSQUO$)S CHOICE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
