<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>While Giambi Deals With His Problems, the Yankees Put Theirs Behind</title>
    <meta content="19pins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855624"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="YANKEES NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E4DE133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>While Giambi Deals With His Problems, the Yankees Put Theirs Behind</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has been a long, lonely period for Jason Giambi. He has not played for the Yankees this month because of a foot injury, and he may not play again this season. In addition, Giambi must decide by Thursday if he plans to cooperate with baseball's investigation into steroid use.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for Major League Baseball and the players union continued to negotiate the parameters yesterday for a possible meeting with the former Senator George J. Mitchell. Commissioner Bud Selig asked that Giambi cooperate with Mitchell after Giambi tacitly admitted to using steroids. Indications were that Giambi was leaning toward meeting with Mitchell.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has been a long, lonely period for Jason Giambi. He has not played for the Yankees this month because of a foot injury, and he may not play again this season. In addition, Giambi must decide by Thursday if he plans to cooperate with baseball's investigation into steroid use.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for Major League Baseball and the players union continued to negotiate the parameters yesterday for a possible meeting with the former Senator George J. Mitchell. Commissioner Bud Selig asked that Giambi cooperate with Mitchell after Giambi tacitly admitted to using steroids. Indications were that Giambi was leaning toward meeting with Mitchell.</p>
        <p>The commissioner's office first said that Giambi's deadline for responding was tomorrow. But, since Selig's statement was released late in the afternoon June 6, M.L.B. officials told Arn Tellem, Giambi's agent, that they could have until Thursday to respond. Giambi is expected to wait until Thursday.</p>
        <p>Either way, the Yankees have moved on without him. In fact, they are playing their best baseball of the season, by far, without him.</p>
        <p>When Manager Joe Torre was asked Sunday to pinpoint when he thought the Yankees started turning it around, he mentioned Giambi's being placed on the disabled list with a torn left plantar fascia on June 1.</p>
        <p>''You hate to say this,'' Torre said. ''A big part of it was when Giambi went on the disabled list. At least you knew he wasn't available.''</p>
        <p>Without Giambi, the Yankees are 13-3 and have scored 6.9 runs a game. With Giambi, the Yankees were 22-29 and averaged 5.3 runs. After Giambi went on the disabled list, Torre moved Johnny Damon and his wobbly legs from center field to designated hitter and inserted the energetic Melky Cabrera in center. Also, Bobby Abreu, Robinson Canó and Hideki Matsui, left-handed hitters who were slumping, have contributed more.</p>
        <p>Since Giambi went on the disabled list, the Yankees' designated hitters have batted .299, with 3 home runs and 11 runs batted in. While Damon has started 12 of 16 games as the designated hitter, Jorge Posada, Alex Rodriguez and Josh Phelps have also started at D.H. Giambi hit .177 with three homers in May.</p>
        <p>Cabrera, who is a far superior defensive outfielder to Damon, is batting .286 in June. The Yankees start a three-game series tonight against the Colorado Rockies in Denver, and since the games are being played in a National League park, Torre will not have a designated hitter. He will have to choose between Cabrera or Damon to play center at Coors Field, but it would be sensible to have the younger Cabrera roaming the expansive outfield there.</p>
        <p>Of course, the most significant part of the Yankees' offensive turnaround has been Rodriguez's incredible June. He is batting .393 with 8 homers and 28 R.B.I. this month.</p>
        <p>''The guy is amazing,'' Damon said about Rodriguez. ''He works harder than everybody. He's dedicated. He's definitely got a lot of records in his future.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees initially said Giambi would miss at least five weeks. General Manager Brian Cashman said yesterday that there was no new timetable. Giambi said he would have another magnetic resonance imaging test this week, but Cashman said it had not yet been scheduled.</p>
        <p>GIRARDI A CANDIDATE IN BALTIMORE The Baltimore Orioles fired Manager Sam Perlozzo yesterday, and Joe Girardi, a former Yankee who is broadcasting for the YES Network, is a leading candidate to replace him.</p>
        <p>If Girardi succeeds Perlozzo, it could have some ramifications for the Yankees. Once Joe Torre is done managing the Yankees, which could be after this season, Girardi and Don Mattingly, the bench coach, were considered the top candidates to succeed him.</p>
        <p>Mattingly would appear to be the favorite, since he is Torre's bench coach, but the Yankees have never told him that he will succeed Torre. Girardi made a strong impression on the Yankees' hierarchy during his one season as a bench coach in 2005.</p>
        <p>Girardi, who did not respond to a telephone message, spoke yesterday about managing on his paid segment on the ''Michael Kay Show'' on ESPN Radio.</p>
        <p>When Kay asked Girardi if he would forgo accepting a managing job to wait for the Yankees' job, Girardi said: ''Will I wait? I don't know. It all depends on the situation that's presented to me, if it is presented to me.''</p>
        <p>Brian Cashman would not discuss Torre's successor, stressing that the Yankees have a manager they are happy with and are focused on winning this season.</p>
        <p>TWO CHINESE PLAYERS SIGN Five months ago, the Yankees announced that they had a working agreement with the Chinese Baseball Association.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, they announced that they had signed the left-handed pitcher Kai Liu and catcher Zhenwang Zhang to minor league contracts. The Yankees said they were the first team to sign a player from the People's Republic of China with approval from the Chinese association.</p>
        <p>Liu, 19, played on the Guangdong Leopards in the six-team Chinese Baseball League. Zhang, 19, helped the Tianjin Lions to the league championship series in three of the past five seasons. Zhang played in one game for China in the World Baseball Classic last year but did not bat.</p>
        <p>After the players are introduced at a news conference July 6 at Yankee Stadium, they will report to the Yankees' development complex in Tampa, Fla. Brian Cashman said it was too early to predict which minor league team they would eventually join.</p>
        <p>''I don't think we know where their potential can lead them just yet,'' Cashman said. ''The programs over there are in their infancy stages.''</p>
        <p>YANKEES NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
