<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senate Republicans Propose Changes to Congestion Plan</title>
    <meta content="19congest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/nyregion/19congest.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855555"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E1DF133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senate Republicans Propose Changes to Congestion Plan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Senate Republicans Propose Changes to Congestion Plan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, June 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's ''congestion pricing'' proposal received  mixed political signals on Monday and appeared unlikely to be resolved in the last week of the legislative session.</p>
        <p>In a bill introduced over the weekend, Senate Republicans broadly amended the mayor's plan -- which they had previously introduced -- and proposed to eliminate hundreds of millions of dollars of new state money for mass transit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg’s “congestion pricing” proposal appeared unlikely to be resolved in the last week of the legislative session.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's ''congestion pricing'' proposal received  mixed political signals on Monday and appeared unlikely to be resolved in the last week of the legislative session.</p>
        <p>In a bill introduced over the weekend, Senate Republicans broadly amended the mayor's plan -- which they had previously introduced -- and proposed to eliminate hundreds of millions of dollars of new state money for mass transit.</p>
        <p>The move demonstrated the challenge the mayor faces in persuading lawmakers, because Senate Republicans are his strongest allies in the Legislature. The mayor's plan has not yet been introduced in the Democratic-led Assembly.</p>
        <p>The debate also crossed state lines, with Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey saying he had concerns about the ''economic hardship'' that might befall his state and its commuters if the plan were implemented. The only clearly positive news for the mayor came when City Council Speaker Christine C. Quinn endorsed the plan, calling it ''a tough choice'' and ''a bold idea.''</p>
        <p>Several people with knowledge of the Senate's new proposal said it represented an effort by Republicans to devise a bill they could vote on by the end of the legislative session on Thursday as an appeasement to the mayor, who has been one of their largest campaign contributors.</p>
        <p>''We're pretty much ready to go with a concept just to continue the discussion,'' said Joseph L. Bruno, the Senate majority leader. ''It's a question of getting an agreement.''</p>
        <p>Farrell Sklerov, a spokesman for the mayor, called the new Senate bill ''a positive step.''</p>
        <p>''They're doing what we've been asking everyone to do, which is to work on the plan to build a consensus,'' he added.</p>
        <p>But opposition remained strong in the Assembly.</p>
        <p>''We had no discussion with the Senate,'' Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver said on Monday, but he did say he had problems with the Senate bill and still had ''a lot of questions'' on the mayor's proposal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloomberg is proposing to charge fees to most drivers who enter Manhattan below 86th Street on weekdays as part of a broad plan to improve air quality and ease traffic by 2030. The Senate's latest proposal would change several aspects of Mr. Bloomberg's plan, which included a new public authority to oversee congestion pricing that would be controlled by the mayor and the governor. The Senate is proposing a state board with the Legislature equally represented.</p>
        <p>The Senate proposal, first reported in The Daily News, would also reduce penalties for failing to pay congestion fees and wipe away hundreds of millions of dollars of new state aid for mass transit. The proposal would also end the congestion program after three years, meaning it would have to go through a full approval process again to become permanent. Mr. Bloomberg's plan would leave the decision to extend the program to the mayor's discretion.</p>
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer reiterated on Monday that it was likely that the Legislature would return for a special session to deal with the proposal.</p>
        <p>''There are issues we have to confront,'' he said. Mr. Spitzer has endorsed the plan in principle but has said he had problems with the details.</p>
        <p>Like the Senate, the governor objected to the structure of the mayor's proposed oversight authority.</p>
        <p>''The initial structure that was created by the mayor, I think, was not the best; he and I had some conversations about that,'' the governor said. ''I think we can still do better than what the Senate proposed.''</p>
        <p>The comments by his counterpart in New Jersey added another complication.</p>
        <p>Governor Corzine said on Monday that he was concerned that congestion pricing would lead to a surge in mass transit that New Jersey would not be able to handle. ''There's lots of implications,'' he said. ''A lot of people find congestion pricing intriguing; I'd like to find out what its real impact is going to be on New Jersey.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine's voice is an important one because of New Jersey's longstanding relationship with New York on numerous transportation issues, highlighted by their joint role overseeing the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey.</p>
        <p>''We'd like to be cooperative,'' he said. ''We have to see whether we can actually be able to sustain the huge surge in mass transit.''</p>
        <p>The mayor did receive a more positive assessment from Speaker Quinn. She did not immediately take a position on congestion pricing when Mr. Bloomberg first announced it, but she said she had been persuaded by studying the details of the plan. She warned that a failure to institute such restrictions would lead to people being ''literally choked by the level of traffic in this city.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
