<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Militant Fights From a Basement on Emergency Street</title>
    <meta content="19lebanon" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/world/middleeast/19lebanon.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855596"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AIN AL HILWE JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lebanon</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bakri, Nada</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abu Omar (Chehadeh Jawhar)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hariri, Rafik (1945-2005)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Lebanon</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E7DE133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1057" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Militant Fights From a Basement on Emergency Street</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Militant Fights From a Basement on Emergency Street</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NADA BAKRI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bakri, Nada</byline>
      <dateline>AIN AL HILWE REFUGEE CAMP, Lebanon</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Abu Omar, militant Islamist, is among most charismatic leaders in 12 Palestinian refugee camps in Lebanon; camps give him 12 places to set up shop, run to, hide in and conduct operations; explosives stored in his basement are similar to those used to destabilize Lebanon since assassination of former prime minister Rafik Hariri in 2005; Lebanese military official confirms that Abu Omar is wanted in connection with numerous killings and bombings; Abu Omar, whose real name is Chehadeh Jawhar, is quick to say he would not hesitate to shoot at civilians if army shoots at him or his followers; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a recent afternoon, with the smoke still rising from buildings burned in fierce fighting here between Islamist militants and the Lebanese Army, a man calling himself Abu Omar gave a tour of his squalid neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Abu Omar, a militant Islamist, is among the most charismatic leaders in the camp, loved by his supporters but detested by those who say militants bring nothing but destruction to the Palestinians.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Abu Omar, a militant Islamist fighting the Lebanese Army, is a charismatic leader in a Palestinian refugee camp near Sidon, in southern Lebanon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a recent afternoon, with the smoke still rising from buildings burned in fierce fighting here between Islamist militants and the Lebanese Army, a man calling himself Abu Omar gave a tour of his squalid neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Abu Omar, a militant Islamist, is among the most charismatic leaders in the camp, loved by his supporters but detested by those who say militants bring nothing but destruction to the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>An old woman stopped him. ''Thank God you are safe,'' she said, hugging and kissing him three times on each bearded cheek. ''My house is completely burned,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''Don't worry about it,'' he replied as he took her hands. ''We will fix it or get you a new one. Do not worry. Everything will be fixed.''</p>
        <p>The fighting was a sign of just how fragile Lebanon has become. As the Lebanese Army battled militants in the Nahr al Bared refugee camp in the north, gunfire broke out between the army and militants here in this camp, near Sidon. Abu Omar says the fighting started after a soldier provoked a ''brother.''</p>
        <p>''He was telling him that 'we are defeating you in Nahr al Bared, we are burning you,' '' Abu Omar said. ''Then he started shooting toward him; the brother went home, brought his gun and started shooting back.''</p>
        <p>The government disputes that version of events, but by either account, the camp is a tinderbox, and Abu Omar, whose real name is Chehadeh Jawhar, is an apt symbol of the weakness of the Lebanese state.</p>
        <p>Even before the current political crisis, with pro-American factions struggling to keep power from pro-Syrian and pro-Iranian parties, Lebanon was a nation without institutions, a place where power was divided among religious sects. It was a state that gave Palestinians free license to live in 12 refugee camps within its borders. Within the camps' confines, they were immune from the country's rules, laws, police and oversight, but condemned to a life of degradation and second-class status.</p>
        <p>For those like Abu Omar, with a militant political agenda, the arrangement created 12 different places to set up shop and 12 bases to run to, hide in and conduct operations. Abu Omar lives on Emergency Street, a free-wheeling alley of martial faith surrounded by squalor. He takes visitors into his basement.</p>
        <p>With a shrug of his shoulders, he pointed to a corner in the darkened room where he has stored TNT, plastic explosives and guns. He smiled, then opened boxes and black school backpacks, rummaging through a potpourri of ammunition, makeshift land mines and detonating wires.</p>
        <p>The explosives stored in his basement were similar to those that have been used to destabilize Lebanon since the assassination of the former prime minister Rafik Hariri in February 2005. There is no way to know if the basement was the source of any of those bombs.</p>
        <p>An explosion recently ripped through a tire shop on Emergency Street as Abu Omar and other militants were extracting TNT from a 107-millimeter shell, apparently to use in making a bomb, according to Lebanese security officials who spoke on condition of anonymity, because they were not authorized to speak to the news media.</p>
        <p>Abu Omar and two other militants were wounded, and two others died.</p>
        <p>''Victory is not required from us,'' he said in an interview  before the explosion. ''What is required is to be ready for a jihad in the name of God, ready to reinstate Islam's rule and Muslim caliphate. It is normal, if the army shoots at us, we will shoot back at them -- normal.'' Abu Omar, 37, was once a fighter with the mainstream Fatah faction of Yasir Arafat, the former Palestinian Authority president. An electrician turned arms smuggler, he said he left the group when he said he felt its leaders ''were minimizing'' the Palestinian cause. ''Palestine is not only for Palestinians, Jerusalem is not only for Palestinians,'' he said. ''It is for all Arabs and Muslims.''</p>
        <p>He says he has been wanted by the Lebanese government since 1991 for scores of felonies. ''Crimes that cannot be counted,'' he boasted. ''It is normal, normal.''</p>
        <p>A senior Lebanese military official confirmed that Abu Omar is wanted in connection with numerous killings and bombings.</p>
        <p>He cannot leave the camp. Not, at least, through the front gate in daylight. He says he is now a member of Asbat al Ansar, a group listed by Washington as a terrorist group. In the camp, he built a house, married and had eight children.</p>
        <p>The military official said Abu Omar is believed to have left the ranks of Asbat al Ansar and is now a member of a splinter faction called Jund al Sham.</p>
        <p>Abu Omar struts through the camp like a sports star, or the mayor. He stopped at his mother's house. She had just returned from a pilgrimage to Mecca, Saudi Arabia. He hugged and kissed her; she thanked God for his safety. His sisters showered him with yet more kisses. ''We miss you,'' they said.</p>
        <p>Taxi drivers and their customers passing by also stopped to give thanks that he had survived the battle. More residents and neighbors joined the line.</p>
        <p>But caught between the army and Abu Omar and his supporters are those who simply struggle to get through their days, and see in the militant groups the seeds of their own devastation.</p>
        <p>''They burned the houses, they burned our houses,'' said a Palestinian refugee who gave his name as Abu Iyad for fear of reprisal. He said his perfume shop and his house, both on Emergency Street, had been set on fire. ''If the army gives me a uniform, I will shoot at them now,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''We want to get rid of all these problems,'' said Mustapha Razi, another refugee. ''If my brother is creating problems, I want to get rid of him.''</p>
        <p>But they know they can't, and that the army can't either. If fighting erupts again, they all said they would do what they did a few days ago: flee.</p>
        <p>Abu Omar says it is unlikely those clashes would resume. But if they do, he said, civilians outside the camp are fair game. ''If the army shoots at us again, we will shoot at civilians in Sidon.''</p>
        <p>And off he walked to visit his mother and sisters.</p>
        <p>AIN AL HILWE JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
