<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For the Angler, a Flash of Color Among the Freighters</title>
    <meta content="19outdoors" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/sports/othersports/19outdoors.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855622"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OUTDOORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Panama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Panama/Panama Canal and Canal Zone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Canals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Canals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waterways and Other Bodies of Water</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Panama Canal and Canal Zone</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4DE133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1008" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For the Angler, a Flash of Color Among the Freighters</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For the Angler, a Flash of Color Among the Freighters</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE SHERWOOD</byline>
      <dateline>PANAMA</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are several ways to experience the Panama Canal.</p>
        <p>You can make the eight-hour trip aboard a giant freight ship, riding high in the bow, saluting onlookers as your broad hull cuts through the water and your ship's flag waves in the freshening afternoon trades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An eight-hour trip on a giant freight ship through the Panama Canal costs an average of $30,000. Because my wife and I were on a tight budget, we went fishing for peacock bass instead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are several ways to experience the Panama Canal.</p>
        <p>You can make the eight-hour trip aboard a giant freight ship, riding high in the bow, saluting onlookers as your broad hull cuts through the water and your ship's flag waves in the freshening afternoon trades.</p>
        <p>Such a trip costs an average of $30,000, according to the Canal Authority. Because my wife and I were on a tight budget, we went fishing for peacock bass instead.</p>
        <p>We met our guide, Ché, at a marina and public boat launch on the winding, jungle-flanked road that runs between Panama City, on the Pacific Ocean, and Colón, on the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>We had arranged for the four-hour trip through a friend of a Panamanian friend, who warned us that because we had waited until the last second and because it was a Sunday and even the fishermen would be in church, our guide -- although well versed in the ways of the canal's abundant peacock bass -- had never fished with tourists and was unlikely to know anything about fly fishing.</p>
        <p>''Perfect,'' I said.</p>
        <p>We arrived at the small marina at 7 a.m. and walked down the dock -- rickety planks slick with mold and rotted through in places -- looking for our guide. A few old boats, including a couple of dugout canoes, were tethered alongside.</p>
        <p>A crew of feisty Panamanians in rolled-up jeans and baseball caps had gathered for coffee, lamenting in rapid-fire Spanish the mist that hung like a curtain over the distant canal and the previous night's Yankees game. Panamanians, we discovered, are baseball fanatics -- a trait no doubt inherited from the homesick American troops once stationed in the former Canal Zone.</p>
        <p>Parked at the end of the dock was a 13-foot, old aluminum boat -- 952 feet shy of the canal maximum. Ché, our guide, sat back by the motor, bailing water from the previous night's rainstorm.</p>
        <p>He motioned, and we climbed aboard. Before we could introduce ourselves, he had pull-started an ancient Evinrude motor and we sputtered off through weed-choked water.</p>
        <p>Ché's skin was dark and pulled tight as horse leather, the whites of his eyes well shaded in deep hollows reflecting the ever-present equatorial sun.</p>
        <p>We made small talk, but he was not interested. He did not smile, either, a habit he tried hard not to break in four hours with us.</p>
        <p>The sun crested the horizon, and the fog lifted. We saw the enormous red and green buoys that marked the channel, and the steep, steamy hillsides that marked the forest beyond.</p>
        <p>We thought of a museum exhibit we had seen the day before at Miraflores Locks, nearer to Panama City, and the countless thousands of canal workers who succumbed a century ago to yellow fever, malaria and who knows how many poisonous spider and snake bites in the country's sweltering jungles.</p>
        <p>We heard a horn. The water trembled. A freighter, the Korean Gio Quiang, rounded a bend and, like a skyscraper, abruptly dominated the horizon.</p>
        <p>I looked back at Ché, hoping he would slow down so I could take a picture. He did not.</p>
        <p>Stalwart, and with that singularity of focus that marks all good anglers, he continued. We stopped in a lush jungle cove that bristled with life.</p>
        <p>A troop of howler monkeys swung branch to branch above us, shaking loose softball-sized mangoes and watching in glee as the fruit splashed around us.</p>
        <p>A long, skinny water snake slithered in front of us, and four freshwater turtles painted with brilliant orange stripes sunned themselves on a half-submerged log. Birds flitted about, including a gaudy blue-headed parrot that watched us as it plucked nuts from an almond tree.</p>
        <p>The Canal Zone watershed, according to the Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute, is a haven of biodiversity, its dense tropical forest a buffer against erosion and silt. Abundant wildlife is a fringe benefit.</p>
        <p>Ché nudged a bucket of minnows toward me. I shook my head.</p>
        <p>''I'd rather fly fish,'' I said, enjoying the scenery as I strung up my 8-weight fly rod.</p>
        <p>Ché shrugged, and spit over the transom. Then he pulled an empty one-liter Pepsi bottle from the bilge. He had wound three yards of heavy monofilament hand line around it and tucked a rusted bait hook underneath.</p>
        <p>''Feel free to fish, Ché,'' I said. Before I could finish the sentence, he was hauling in his first peacock bass, and grunting for effect.</p>
        <p>He motioned at the bait bucket again, eyeing my fly rod with suspicion. I refused, then tied on my fly -- a small green and yellow cork popper, and flipped it out. A bass rose and inhaled it with a splash. I pulled the line tight. My reel ran.</p>
        <p>Peacocks, nicknamed sergeants by Canal Zone troops for their stripes (sargentos in Spanish), are native to the Amazon and Orinoco river basins in Brazil, not Panama. They appeared in the canal around 1958, much to the delight of local fishermen.</p>
        <p>After a few belly-flop style jumps, we hauled the fish aboard and admired its bright colors, smeared like moist paint along its flanks: green, gold and black stripes and the trademark ''third eye'' on its tail.</p>
        <p>I asked my wife to take a picture.</p>
        <p>Despite our early success, we caught nothing more that morning. Recent heavy rains, Ché said, had turned the fish off.</p>
        <p>On the way back to the dock, we saw another enormous tanker ship, this one more impressive than the first. Multicolored cargo containers lined its deck like shoeboxes at a factory store.</p>
        <p>It was now or never.</p>
        <p>''Stop, stop!'' I yelled in Spanish.</p>
        <p>Ché hit the kill switch on the motor, and the boat jolted and spun.</p>
        <p>I took my peacock bass from the cooler behind my seat, then vaulted to the bow, fish in hand. The freighter passed behind me down the main channel of the canal.</p>
        <p>''O.K., now!'' I said.</p>
        <p>My wife snapped the photograph -- me, a peacock and the Panama Canal -- then we looked back at Ché.</p>
        <p>He smiled.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
