<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Train Wreck</title>
    <meta content="19thomas" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/business/19thomas.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855631"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lead</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paints and Painting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rc2 Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barboza, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Story, Louise</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jennings, Angel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vega, Tanzina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Culotta, Karen Ann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Paints and Painting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lead</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Mattel Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Hasbro Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E3DE133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1590" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Train Wreck</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">RC2’s Train Wreck</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARBOZA and LOUISE STORY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barboza, David; Story, Louise</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>How RC2's recall of Thomas the Tank Engine wooden trains and other railroad components that were contaminated with paint containing lead will affect company long term is unclear; disclosure has unnerved some parents, who say they will avoid buying Thomas and Friends products; crisis management experts generally advise companies to be as open as possible early in crisis to show customers they are aggressively addressing problem, but RC2 has been quiet since it first disclosed recall last week; stock price of RC2, which went public in 1997, has not suffered since recall announcement, which said there had been no reported illnesses or injuries from products; graphs; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the toy business, RC2 was the little company that could.</p>
        <p>Though much smaller and less prominent than Mattel and Hasbro, RC2 has grown steadily and its stock price has soared over the last five years, thanks largely to a strategy of sewing up licensing deals with big-name brands like Sesame Street, Winnie the Pooh, Disney, Nickelodeon, and Thomas &amp; Friends. Its revenues have risen from $213 million in 2002 to $519 million last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The company that recalled Thomas the Tank Engine wooden trains, which were contaminated with paint containing lead, is learning about crisis management.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the toy business, RC2 was the little company that could.</p>
        <p>Though much smaller and less prominent than Mattel and Hasbro, RC2 has grown steadily and its stock price has soared over the last five years, thanks largely to a strategy of sewing up licensing deals with big-name brands like Sesame Street, Winnie the Pooh, Disney, Nickelodeon, and Thomas &amp; Friends. Its revenues have risen from $213 million in 2002 to $519 million last year.</p>
        <p>Until now the 18-year-old company, which is based in Oak Brook, Ill., has gone largely unknown by the general public. But many people -- parents in particular -- took note of it last week, when RC2 issued a recall of 1.5 million Thomas the Tank Engine wooden trains and other railroad components that were contaminated with paint containing lead. The toys, sold in retail stores like Wal-Mart and Toys ''R'' Us, were made in the same factory in Dongguan, China as many of the company's other popular products.</p>
        <p>How the recall will affect the company long term is unclear, but the disclosure has unnerved some parents, who say that they will avoid buying Thomas and Friends products.</p>
        <p>''It's killing me that you're telling me this,'' said Ramya Narayanan, 39, who was visiting the Toys ''R'' Us in  Times Square over the weekend with her son Harish, 3, who will start preschool this fall.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of scary because all his stuff is Thomas stuff,'' Ms. Narayanan said.</p>
        <p>On Friday, when Carrie Shultz gathered at a regular morning play group in Chicago with her two sons, Eli, 5, and Zach, 13 months, the motherly buzz was all about the recent recall of Thomas toys.</p>
        <p>''After this, I'm definitely going to be more cognizant of where my children's toys are manufactured,'' said Mrs. Shultz, 33. ''With my youngest son, everything goes in his mouth. I can't take any chances.''</p>
        <p>RC2 is clearly not used to the spotlight. Crisis management experts generally advise companies to be as open as possible early in a crisis to show customers that they are aggressively addressing a problem, but RC2 has been quiet since it first disclosed the recall last week and listed the products involved on a Web site, www.recalls.rc2.com. Company executives did not return repeated phone calls left at their homes and offices. A manager at the RC2 factory in Dongguan detained a New York Times reporter for more than nine hours after he had been admitted to the premises by security guards to ask questions about the operation.</p>
        <p>But the stock price of RC2, which went public in 1997, has not suffered  since the recall announcement, which said that there had been no reported illnesses or injuries from the products. The company's share price closed at $42.91 on Monday, which is less than $1 a share below its level before the recall and is two and a half times its trading price five years ago.</p>
        <p>Indeed, RC2's stock, listed on Nasdaq, has steadily climbed  since 2003, when the company acquired the Learning Curve, then the maker of many of RC2's preschool toys -- including Thomas and Friends trains. Last year, more than two-thirds of RC2's sales came from products for young children.</p>
        <p>And business partners seem to be standing by the company. ''We're not reconsidering our license agreement,'' said a spokesman for Nickelodeon. ''None of our products were affected, and they're a good partner to us.''</p>
        <p>RC2 has emerged in the past few years as a popular link in the toy manufacturing chain, connecting media outlets like Disney, Nickelodeon and Discovery Communications with inexpensive labor in China. RC2's toys indicate their country of origin, as is required by regulators.</p>
        <p>Outsourcing toy making is by no means unusual, and the largest toy makers have operated factories in Asia for decades. But RC2, with a market capitalization of about $900 million, is relatively new to the preschool toy market. Over the last few years, it has turned the focus of its business away from trading cards and model cars as older children began spending more time playing video games.</p>
        <p>And last week was not the first time that RC2  issued a lead paint recall. In 2003, the company recalled some Lamaze toys because of lead paint on the wires along which toddlers were meant to slide beads.</p>
        <p>''People recognized the company is doing the right thing by issuing the recall,'' said Timothy Conder, an analyst at A. G. Edwards who covers RC2, in a telephone interview yesterday. ''This was caught by the company and they proactively went'' to the Consumer Product Safety Commission to issue a recall.</p>
        <p>Past recalls, however, received meager attention, perhaps because they were less well-known brands. Analysts that cover the company said RC2 executives were probably hoping to remain under the radar this time, too.</p>
        <p>''These recalls happen fairly often,'' said Gerrick Johnson, an equity analyst with BMO Capital Market US. ''It's when the recall becomes botched and children are hurt when it takes on a life of its own.''</p>
        <p>This recall, he said, ''should not have any long-term damage.''</p>
        <p>Analysts have issued positive reports about the company for the last several years because of its skill in marketing toys and landing big-name license agreements. Analysts said the Thomas and Friends recall is unlikely to dim RC2's prospects.</p>
        <p>''I think the company does a great job,'' said Sean McGowan, managing director and toy industry analyst at Wedbush Morgan Securities, a brokerage firm in Los Angeles. ''Yes, this should have been caught earlier. But it wasn't caught by some kid getting sick. They caught it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McGowan said he had spoken with Curt Stoelting, RC2's chief executive, after the news came out, and that Mr. Stoelting told him the problem was found during a routine quality check.</p>
        <p>RC2 works with third-party suppliers in China and Hong Kong to manufacture its products. Last year, 91.8 percent of RC2's products came from China, the company said in February when it filed its annual report for last year.</p>
        <p>''All products are manufactured to our specifications using molds and tooling that we own,'' the company said in the filing. ''These suppliers own the manufacturing equipment and machinery, purchase raw materials, hire workers and plan production. We purchase fully assembled and packaged finished goods in master cartons for distribution to our customers.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday in Dongguan, a factory town that is now the center of the world's toy production, a group of Chinese suppliers, working under the American RC2 banner, produced miniature-sized John Deere trucks, Nascar racing models and even M&amp;M-branded toy cars.</p>
        <p>A manager there denied that suppliers were responsible for coating the popular Thomas and Friends wooden railway sets with lead-based paint.</p>
        <p>Just a few hundred yards away from RC2's main office here, a group of about 30 young workers were seen boxing, folding and packaging the Thomas and Friends products on an assembly line. In interviews over the last two days, several workers said that metal and wooden train sets were often made here, and that the paint for some of those toys appeared to be produced on the factory grounds.</p>
        <p>The recall issued last week covered products made from January 2005 to June 2007, suggesting that for two years RC2 failed to noticed that some of its best-selling toys were being produced with lead-based paint.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the factory's zone's manager was angered after his security guards allowed several journalists to visit the factory and take photographs. He identified himself only as Mr. Zhong.</p>
        <p>''You're intruding,'' Mr. Zhong said in a discussion in his office. ''Tell me, why exactly are you here?'' Mr. Zhong and the zone's security staff  detained a journalist from this newspaper, photographer and translator for over nine hours.  The three were eventually released by police and local government officials early this morning.</p>
        <p>RC2, formerly called Racing Champions, built itself as a company that made collectible items and miniature car models, including Nascar-branded cars. The company started migrating toward children's toys in part because of the lagging popularity of Nascar, Mr. McGowan said. RC2 presented itself to media companies that owned famous characters as a company that would pay more attention to their products than giants like Hasbro and Mattel.</p>
        <p>''A $35 million product doesn't get anyone's attention at Hasbro,'' Mr. McGowan said. But, he added, ''$35 million gets everyone's attention at RC2.''</p>
        <p>Some observers said that RC2 may have won some of its prominent brands by offering a bigger cut of profit to media companies. One RC2 notable win from Hasbro in 2005 was Bob the Builder, a brand like Thomas and Friends that is owned by HIT Entertainment, the property of the private equity firm Apax Partners. A spokeswoman for HIT declined to comment yesterday on whether HIT would continue to work with RC2.</p>
        <p>RC2 has often stated to analysts that it does not want to own its factories and would rather contract with third-parties. RC2 says in its financial filings that it outsources to seven companies that  produce nearly half of its products in China. RC2 notes that it has worked with those companies for several years.</p>
        <p>Some people this week have said that companies involved in recent recalls appear to have leaned too heavily on outsourcing.</p>
        <p>''Many companies have gone to China lured there by low-cost labor and in many ways, what happens there is they end up not only outsourcing production but outsourcing a lot of the design of their products,'' said M. Eric Johnson, a professor of management at the Tuck School of Business at Dartmouth.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
