<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Maine Is Back on Track, and So Are the Mets</title>
    <meta content="19mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/sports/baseball/19mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855607"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="METS 8, TWINS 1"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Minnesota Twins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Minnesota Twins</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Maine, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Reyes, Jose</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E6DE133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="945" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Maine Is Back on Track, and So Are the Mets</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Maine Is Back on Track, and So Are the Mets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Maine had certainly been part of the problem of late for the Mets, who entered last night having lost seven of eight games. After a strong start to the season, Maine had won only once since May 9. But last night, he was the solution.</p>
        <p>The Mets will not have too many more extended losing streaks this season if Maine keeps pitching like this. In one of his best starts this season, Maine gave up  one run and four hits in seven and a third innings to lead the Mets to an 8-1 victory over the Minnesota Twins.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In one of his best starts this season, John Maine gave up only one run in seven and a third innings to lead the Mets to a victory against the Twins.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John Maine had certainly been part of the problem of late for the Mets, who entered last night having lost seven of eight games. After a strong start to the season, Maine had won only once since May 9. But last night, he was the solution.</p>
        <p>The Mets will not have too many more extended losing streaks this season if Maine keeps pitching like this. In one of his best starts this season, Maine gave up  one run and four hits in seven and a third innings to lead the Mets to an 8-1 victory over the Minnesota Twins.</p>
        <p>The Mets' hitting and pitching were clicking. Maine walked only two and struck out four.</p>
        <p>''It starts with pitching,'' Mets Manager Willie Randolph said. ''John threw the ball real well and stayed real focused. He kept grinding and going after them, pitch after pitch. We're going to hit. I'm not so concerned about that. Guys will get into a rhythm and gain their confidence back. Pitching is the key.''</p>
        <p>But good hitting certainly does not hurt. The Mets pounded out 15 hits and received major contributions from several players, including Carlos Delgado, who had been slumping.</p>
        <p>Delgado's towering solo home run, which barely cleared the fence in right field in the second inning, gave the Mets the lead for good. But Twins starter Carlos Silva settled down, holding the Mets to one run over the next three innings. They took a 2-0 lead in the fourth, on a single by Ricky Ledee.</p>
        <p>The Mets scored again in the sixth, on a two-run single by Paul Lo Duca. A day earlier, he left the game against the Yankees with a bruised left arm.</p>
        <p>''This was the best game we've played in a long time,'' Lo Duca said. ''Offense, defense, pitching. It was the whole nine yards. We knew we were too good of a team to keep playing the way we've been playing. This was a good win for us.''</p>
        <p>Maine received warm applause when he left with one out in the eighth and a man on. Pedro Feliciano came in and struck out the dangerous Joe Mauer. But Michael Cuddyer followed with a bloop single just over the head of Delgado at first base, driving in the Twins' only run.</p>
        <p>Feliciano then got out of trouble when Justin Morneau grounded out to third.</p>
        <p>''I threw a lot more off-speed pitches and I threw a lot more strikes with them,'' said Maine ( 7-4). ''They're a good hitting team. They get the bat on the ball. I just let our defense play.''</p>
        <p>The Mets scored four runs in the eighth, starting with a home run by Ledee to right-center field. His last homer for the Mets was Sept. 22. He went 2 for 3 last night and also walked.</p>
        <p>Even the struggling Carlos Beltr치n joined in on offense. He was 0 for 4 entering the eighth and had been booed after his third and fourth at-bats. But Beltr치n hit a double down the right-field line to drive in a run.</p>
        <p>''It was just a matter of time before some of these guys in the middle of our lineup got going,'' said David Wright, who had three hits and drove in a run. ''Both Carloses, they're just too good for anybody to hold them down for too long.</p>
        <p>''Everybody is going to go through their ups and downs. Those guys are two of the best players in the game. Hopefully, that last at-bat will get Beltr치n going, and Delgado is looking better and better all the time.''</p>
        <p>Entering the seventh, the Twins had not mounted a serious threat against Maine, failing to advance a runner beyond second base. At one point, Maine retired seven batters in a row.</p>
        <p>Maine had not pitched poorly in recent weeks. He was 5-0 with a 1.37 earned run average after defeating Arizona on May 4. In his three previous starts this month, he allowed eight  earned runs in 18 1/3 innings, all Mets losses.</p>
        <p>Aaron Heilman pitched the ninth for the Mets and retired the side in order.</p>
        <p>The Mets will have their hands full tonight against the Twins' ace, Johan Santana.</p>
        <p>''This doesn't have to mean anything,'' Randolph said. ''We've got to come out tomorrow and do what we did tonight. Every day, we have to do well and sustain this. We played with some energy tonight. We need to feed off that and keep it going.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Willie Randolph continued to play down the seriousness of Carlos Beltr치n's injured left quadriceps before last night's game, questioning why it seems to have developed into a major story. ''He's been sore, like a lot of guys have been during the course of the season,'' he said. '' I've never at any time recently, or in the last month and a half, been concerned or asked him about his leg. Everyone looked at me Sunday like I was hiding something. It's not an issue for me because it's not an issue for Carlos.''... The Mets had a full-blown campaign going last night, urging fans to vote for Paul Lo Duca for the All-Star team. ''It was hard not to notice it,'' Lo Duca said. ''I had a couple of Twins batters come to the plate,  and they said they voted for me. It was pretty funny.'' ... Lastings Milledge, who has been sidelined with a sprained ligament in his foot, has begun working out in Florida and will soon start a rehabilitation assignment with Port St. Lucie, Mets General Manager Omar Minaya said yesterday. ''He is running and swinging the bat and doing those kind of things,'' he said.</p>
        <p>METS 8, TWINS 1</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
