<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Not All Plane Beds Are Equally Restful</title>
    <meta content="19seats" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/business/worldbusiness/19seats.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855620"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beds and Bedding</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">British Airways Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garfinkel, Perry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Sleep</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beds and Bedding</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sleep</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beds and Bedding</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sleep</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">British Airways Plc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Thai Airways</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Virgin Atlantic Airways</org>
        <org class="online_producer">South African Airways</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E4DE133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1286" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Not All Plane Beds Are Equally Restful</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Not All Plane Beds Are Equally Restful</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PERRY GARFINKEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Garfinkel, Perry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article making well-informed booking decision when it comes to selecting airline carrier that provides best plane bed; says when British Airways spent 200 million pounds in 2000 ($300 million) to become first international airline with seats that convert to completely flat six-foot beds, it set off seat wars; holds conflict has escalated, with dozens of airlines rushing to market with their version of seats that provide relaxation and comfort; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The latest dogfight in the highly competitive airline industry is for bragging rights to the best night's sleep in the sky.</p>
        <p>When British Airways spent £200 million in 2000 ($300 million) to become the first international airline with seats that convert to completely flat six-foot beds, it set off  the seat wars. Now the conflict has escalated, with dozens of airlines rushing to market with their version of seats that ''transform your journey into a moment of sublime relaxation and comfort,'' as Thai Airways promises in its Royal Silk business class.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The latest dogfight in the highly competitive airline industry is for bragging rights to the best night’s sleep in the sky.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The latest dogfight in the highly competitive airline industry is for bragging rights to the best night's sleep in the sky.</p>
        <p>When British Airways spent £200 million in 2000 ($300 million) to become the first international airline with seats that convert to completely flat six-foot beds, it set off  the seat wars. Now the conflict has escalated, with dozens of airlines rushing to market with their version of seats that ''transform your journey into a moment of sublime relaxation and comfort,'' as Thai Airways promises in its Royal Silk business class.</p>
        <p>But unless fliers can see through the marketing smoke and decipher airline terminology, it is difficult to make well-informed booking decisions, experts say.</p>
        <p>The first step is knowing that while  ''lie-flat seats'' and  ''flat-bed seats'' sound like different ways of saying the same thing, they are not. Understanding the distinction could save you from spending upward of $8,000 on a night of fitful sleep.  ''There's so much airline marketing-speak that even educated buyers are not sure what their options are,'' said Susan Daimler, vice president of marketing for SeatGuru.com, which evaluates airline seats through customer feedback.</p>
        <p>Adding to the obfuscation, there is no standard system for measuring seat width, angle or legroom, and the Federal Aviation Administration has no jurisdiction over plane seats, ''so we are left to trust the airline and rely on anecdotal evidence by customers,'' said Matthew J. Bennett, an  airline seat expert who publishes  3/5cq 4/5First Class Flyer, a newsletter and Web site.</p>
        <p>Interest in seats that become beds has grown  with the size of planes. The bigger the planes, the longer they can fly  --  consider Singapore Airlines' 18-hour nonstop route from Los Angeles to Singapore on an Airbus A340-500, which can accommodate 313 -- and the more critical the need for a comfortable space to lay one's head for six or seven hours of  sleep.</p>
        <p>And while airlines promote the bells and whistles  in the expensive real estate at the front of the plane -- replete with complimentary second helpings on gourmet food,  multichannel entertainment centers, even massages -- airline executives know that solid sleep is still the most valuable commodity they can offer.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't take too many of those 16-hour international long-haul flights, after which you're expected to walk almost immediately into a meeting, to get how important that seat is,'' said John Lampl, vice president for communications at British Airways.</p>
        <p>Ms. Daimler advised travelers to learn the vocabulary and then realize that some words may not match their meaning. According to SeatGuru.com,  the ''recliner'' seat back goes as far as 160 degrees from the seat base. The ''lie-flat seat'' does not actually lie flat. While marketed as having 180 degrees of recline, in its fully reclined position it is slightly angled. Some go back as far as 172 degrees. The ''flat-bed seat'' goes to a full 180-degree (horizontal) position when fully reclined.</p>
        <p>Using arcane and often inconsistent measurement systems, airlines further obscure what passengers can expect when they take a seat. Airlines define the distance from any point on one seat to the same point on the seat in front as ''pitch,'' which translates roughly to legroom, though how much room there actually is depends on the length of the passenger's legs. Seat width is typically the distance between armrests on a seat or waist area; more and more airlines taper the width toward the legs, an adjustment their research shows provides more comfort during sleep.</p>
        <p>A Web site that evaluates seats, called Flatseats.com,  lists seat pitches for about 160 airlines worldwide. In one of the toughest head-to-head seat skirmishes, Virgin Atlantic Airways and British Airways have sidestepped the legroom problem in their top class by positioning the seats so they angle toward the aisle in a herringbone pattern. Virgin Atlantic's head-to-toe seat length is 79.5 inches (it has only Upper Class seating); British Airways' is 72 inches in business class and 78 inches in first class. In width, Virgin offers 22 inches, and British Air  measures 25.25 at the waist.</p>
        <p>While flat-bed seats recline 180 degrees,  the bed is not  parallel to the floor,  leaving the passenger's head higher than his feet.  ''Airlines conveniently do not report this angle of incline,'' Mr. Bennett said. ''But that tilt dictates how far you will slide off your seat.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bennett suggested a flier's decision should depend on three variables: the quality of the airline, the type of aircraft and, for those who track  frequent-flier miles, the alliance team of the airline. The availability of the better seats changes  even on the same routes depending  whether the plane is, for example, an Airbus A340-600 or a Boeing 747.</p>
        <p>SeatGuru.com currently lists Air New Zealand, Virgin Atlantic, South African Airways, British Airways, Singapore Airlines and Air Canada as companies offering flat-bed seats in first and business class on some but not all of their international flights. But smaller airlines are entering the fray.</p>
        <p>For example, two years ago the tiny Eos Airlines, an all-premium airline that flies only between New York and  London, knew it had to build a better flat bed, said its founder and chief strategist, David Spurlock. With research showing that passengers had ''zero tolerance for angled seats,'' he rejected off-the-shelf seats that  cost  $25,000 to $45,000 each. Instead, he  oversaw the  design of  a patented flat-bed seat.</p>
        <p>''No matter how much you invest in creating a premium experience, at the end of the day and especially through the night, if you don't get a comfortable sleep, the perception of service comes down a notch,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Among the findings that surprised him was how much the seat foam affects comfort. The density, thickness and contour that make a seat comfortable will make a bed uncomfortable. Mr. Spurlock  said that research showed that  passengers want soft seats that are not contoured to their body from the waist up.</p>
        <p>Virgin Atlantic solved the problem of making one piece of furniture serve two purposes with the touch of a button. The passenger stands up, presses the button and the seat back electronically flips to become a flat bed. The seat side is contoured and covered in soft leather; the reverse is built of firm foam.</p>
        <p>How airlines differentiate their seats from their competition's ''is so important these days that it drives their brand strategy,'' said Michael B. Baughan, president of B/E Aerospace, a company that  has designed and built seats for dozens of airlines.</p>
        <p>There is a tension between the consumer's  demand for  space and the airline's desire to install  as many seats as possible. Mr. Baughan said the angled lie-flat seat permits airlines to  ''save some space, but  flat beds repeatedly perform the best.''</p>
        <p>In any case, a flier like Ron Cucos is the seat designer's worst nightmare. ''Just put it this way --  the world of air travel was not built for people my size,'' said Mr. Cucos, 54, a stagehand in Manhattan who at 6 feet 5 inches has to duck to keep from hitting his head on overhanging TVs.</p>
        <p>''My knees either stab into the backrest of the person in front of me or stab my own chin,'' he said. Whenever he flies, he takes an Ambien to help him sleep, he said.</p>
        <p>In 2004,  he flew business class to Johannesburg on South African Airways, which at the time had lie-flat seats. ''It was comfortable enough for me to lie with my knees a little bent,'' he said. But when he flew again after the airline upgraded to flat-bed seats, he experienced what he called ''a true in-flight spiritual epiphany -- who knew a guy even my size could sleep at 35,000 feet?''  Even so, he said, he still takes an Ambien.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
