<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>700 Pedophile Suspects Identified as Global Ring Is Broken Up</title>
    <meta content="19pedophile" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Technology; World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/world/europe/19pedophile.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855623"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gamble, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cox, Timothy David Martyn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Canada</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E4DE133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="913" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>700 Pedophile Suspects Identified as Global Ring Is Broken Up</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">700 Pedophile Suspects Identified as Global Ring Is Broken Up</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THE ASSOCIATED PRESS</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, June 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Team of international investigators infiltrates Internet chat room used by pedophiles who stream live videos of children being raped, rescuing 31 children and identifying more than 700 suspects worldwide; Jim Gamble, chief executive of Child Exploitation and Online Protection Center in Britain, says more than 15 children were found in Britain; official in Canada says 24 Canadians were arrested and seven Canadian children rescued; Gamble says investigation involved agencies from 35 countries, including US, Canada and Australia; case was made public after sentencing in London of ringleader Timothy David Martyn Cox; he was given indeterminate jail sentence, meaning he will remain in prison until he is no longer seen as threat to children; Cox operated chat room out of his bedroom in his family's farmhouse outside London (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A team of international investigators infiltrated an Internet chat room used by pedophiles who streamed live videos of children being raped, rescuing 31 children and identifying more than 700 suspects worldwide, officials said Monday.</p>
        <p>The chat room, which was called ''Kids the Light of Our Lives,'' featured images, including live videos, of children -- some only months old -- being subjected to horrific sexual abuse, said Jim Gamble, chief executive of the  Child Exploitation and Online Protection Center in Britain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A team of international investigators infiltrated an Internet chat room used by pedophiles who streamed live videos of children being raped, rescuing 31 children.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A team of international investigators infiltrated an Internet chat room used by pedophiles who streamed live videos of children being raped, rescuing 31 children and identifying more than 700 suspects worldwide, officials said Monday.</p>
        <p>The chat room, which was called ''Kids the Light of Our Lives,'' featured images, including live videos, of children -- some only months old -- being subjected to horrific sexual abuse, said Jim Gamble, chief executive of the  Child Exploitation and Online Protection Center in Britain.</p>
        <p>''You could go and if you were in the club, arrange a time and a place when online you could view a child being raped and brutalized in real time,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The police analyzed images and videos traded by the chat room's members for the smallest clues that could help them identify, locate and rescue the victims. More than 15 children were found in Britain, Mr. Gamble said, declining to give further details.</p>
        <p>An official in Canada said authorities there arrested 24 Canadians and rescued seven Canadian children as part of an inquiry  started in 2005.</p>
        <p>Some 200 of the suspects are based in Britain, and officials said more than half of them were already being prosecuted. Officials would not give a breakdown of the countries where the other suspects or children live.</p>
        <p>Describing it as ''a massive leap forward,'' Mr. Gamble said the investigation involved agencies from 35 countries, including the United States, Canada and Australia. Investigators made the case public after the sentencing of the ringleader, Timothy David Martyn Cox, on Monday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cox, 27, was given an indeterminate jail sentence, meaning he will remain in prison until authorities decide he is no longer a threat to children. One of his accomplices, Gordon Mackintosh, pleaded guilty to 27 charges of making, possessing and distributing indecent images and videos. He is awaiting sentencing.</p>
        <p>The inquiry began in Canada in the spring of 2005, then expanded internationally in August 2006 after Canadian officials tipped off authorities in London that they believed the chat room's host was based in Britain.</p>
        <p>''Every arrest we make, we seize computers and information,'' said Detective Sgt. Kim Scanlan of the Toronto police sex crimes unit.</p>
        <p>Working with their Canadian counterparts, the British police infiltrated the chat room posing as contributors. They traced the host to a farmhouse in Buxhall, 90 miles northeast of London, where Mr. Cox lived with his parents and sister. He had operated the chat room out of his bedroom while working for the family's microbrewery.</p>
        <p>The evidence the police collected in the inquiry documented shocking abuse, Mr. Gamble said.</p>
        <p>He said the abuse involved ''not sharing a historic video,'' but was a live video of ''a child brought into a room -- on Web cam -- and brutalized for the pleasure of some deviant individual who might not even be in the same country as that child.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cox had been a member of an American-based online pedophile ring shut down by American authorities in March 2006, Mr. Gamble said. Mr. Cox's online identity, ''Son of God,'' was believed to be a reference to the host of the ''Kiddypics'' and ''Kiddyvids'' site in the United States case who adopted the user name ''G.O.D.''</p>
        <p>The British police arrested Mr. Cox on Sept. 28, charging him with nine offenses related to possessing and distributing indecent images of children. Forensic teams examining Mr. Cox's computer found 75,960 indecent and explicit images as well as evidence that he had supplied 11,491 images to other users of the site.</p>
        <p>But as Mr. Cox was taken from the house in handcuffs, the police stepped up their operation. British and Canadian officers immediately assumed his identity and secretly ran the site for 10 days before shutting it down -- gathering evidence on the chat room's hundreds of members. The police at no point distributed illegal images, Mr. Gamble said.</p>
        <p>Weeks later, the British police saw that the chat room had been resurrected. Working with Canadian, Australian and American authorities in December, they again infiltrated the chat room, working around the clock.</p>
        <p>Authorities traced the new host to an apartment in Welwyn Garden City, 30 miles north of London, belonging to the 33-year-old Mr. Mackintosh, a manager at a video streaming company.</p>
        <p>After he was arrested, the police took over his identity and continued to run the chat room, collecting more evidence. Mr. Mackintosh told investigators that every few months he was overcome by guilt and would delete all his files, but he was addicted and would start downloading again, Mr. Gamble said. He had 5,167 indecent and explicit images and 392 indecent movie files on his computer when he was arrested.</p>
        <p>United States Immigration and Customs EnforcementImmigration declined to comment because its investigation is continuing in at least 12 states, which were not identified. The German police are also investigating two men in connection with the ring, the country's Federal Crime Office said.</p>
        <p>It was unclear whether any of the children had been reported missing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gamble said he hoped the 10-month operation to break up the ring would act as a powerful warning.</p>
        <p>''Anyone who even thinks about going online to share an image, to view an image, to arrange access to a child or to share live access to a child is now taking a hell of a chance,'' Mr. Gamble said.</p>
        <p>Authorities said the surveillance tactics they used were more commonly used against terrorism suspects and drug traffickers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
