<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Military Strikes Insurgents' Base East of Baghdad</title>
    <meta content="19iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/world/middleeast/19iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855590"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baquba (Iraq)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Diyala Province (Iraq)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baghdad (Iraq)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Anbar Province (Iraq)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, Michael R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cave, Damien</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402EEDF133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1399" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Military Strikes Insurgents' Base East of Baghdad</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Military Strikes Insurgents’ Base East of Baghdad</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL R. GORDON  and DAMIEN CAVE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gordon, Michael R; Cave, Damien</byline>
      <dateline>BAQUBA, Iraq, Tuesday, June 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American military begins major attack against Sunni insurgent positions in Baquba, capital of Diyala Province, part of larger operation aimed at blunting persistent car and suicide bombings that terrorize Iraqis and thwart political reconciliation; commanders hope to break cycle of sectarian killings and retribution that has swept country; assault, unusual in its scope and ambition, reflects acknowledgment that fresh infusions of American troops focused on Baghdad has prompted insurgents to move their bases outside capital; fighting is expected to be hard; Baquba insurgents are said to be increasingly well trained and highly disciplined; Diyala has emerged as center of Sunni Arab insurgency led by Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia and other groups; it has supplanted Anbar Province, where Sunni Arab tribes have joined forces with Americans to drive out Qaeda fighters; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The American military began a major attack against Sunni insurgent positions here in the capital of Diyala Province overnight, part of a larger operation aimed at blunting the persistent car and suicide bombings that have terrorized Iraqis and thwarted political reconciliation.</p>
        <p>The assault by more than 2,000 American troops is unusual in its scope and ambition, representing a more aggressive strategy of attacking several insurgent strongholds simultaneously to tamp down violence throughout the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The assault by more than 2,000 American troops represents a more aggressive strategy of attacking several insurgent strongholds at the same time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The American military began a major attack against Sunni insurgent positions here in the capital of Diyala Province overnight, part of a larger operation aimed at blunting the persistent car and suicide bombings that have terrorized Iraqis and thwarted political reconciliation.</p>
        <p>The assault by more than 2,000 American troops is unusual in its scope and ambition, representing a more aggressive strategy of attacking several insurgent strongholds simultaneously to tamp down violence throughout the country.</p>
        <p>It reflects an acknowledgment that as fresh infusions of American troops focused on Baghdad in recent months, insurgents moved their bases outside the city. The goal, commanders said, was to break the cycle of sectarian killings and retribution that has swept Iraq.</p>
        <p>The fighting is expected to be hard. In recent months, Diyala has emerged as a center of the Sunni Arab insurgency as Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia and other groups have made it their deadliest base of operations, supplanting Anbar Province. Violence in Anbar dropped after Sunni Arab tribes joined forces with the Americans to drive out Qaeda fighters.</p>
        <p>American military officials say Diyala Province is now home to as many as 2,000 fighters who have flocked there from throughout the country, not only from Anbar but also from Mosul and, since the security crackdown, Baghdad.</p>
        <p>But American commanders say the Baquba insurgents, a mix of former members of Saddam Hussein's army and paramilitary forces, embittered Sunni Arab men, criminal gangs and Qaeda Islamists, are increasingly well trained and highly disciplined. In the past year or more, the militias have terrorized the mixed Sunni and Shiite population, wiping out Shiite families and turning the city into a ghost town.</p>
        <p>The tense political situation in Baquba and surrounding Diyala Province, which is north and east of Baghdad, has been further inflamed over the past year by Shiite-dominated militias, some of whom had infiltrated the security forces and persecuted Sunni Arabs. They proved ill prepared to take on the insurgents.</p>
        <p>Some of the fighters are also believed to be natives of the province who shifted to the western part of Baquba after an American battalion began operating in the eastern section of the capital several months ago. It is not clear if senior insurgent leaders are still in the city, but some American officials suspect they may have moved to other parts of Diyala in anticipation of the assault.</p>
        <p>The Baquba operation is being led by the Third Stryker Brigade Combat Team, Second Infantry Division, with support from units from two other brigades. The American troops are either directly involved in the assault or in supporting efforts on the flanks, along with combat aircraft and artillery.</p>
        <p>In the initial attack early Tuesday, American forces cut off the western portion of Baquba, where the commander of the brigade, Col. Steve Townsend, said 300 to 500 Qaeda fighters are believed to have been operating. Helicopters took part in the assault to cut off escape routes and tank fire could be heard down the streets.</p>
        <p>In the next phase, American forces will begin the dangerous and painstaking process of clearing the city, which is still occupied by thousands of civilians. Iraqi security forces will have a role in securing the western section of the city after it has been captured by American troops, but are not involved in the initial assault.</p>
        <p>The Qaeda and insurgent strongholds in Baquba are strongly defended, according to American intelligence reports. The insurgents' defenses include enormous buried bombs that are powerful enough to destroy or disable an armored vehicle. Combat engineers recently cleared a main road in Baquba of 17 roadside bombs in a stretch of less than a mile, Colonel Townsend said. Of those, 14 were disarmed and three exploded but did not cause casualties.</p>
        <p>Houses are believed to have been rigged with explosives, and enemy fighters -- including expert snipers -- are believed to have machine gun nests.</p>
        <p>American forces are already operating in the eastern section of Baquba. A Stryker battalion began clearing the area several months ago and succeeded in the face of tough resistance. But those operations channeled some fighters to the western part of the provincial capital.</p>
        <p>Initially, however, in at least some parts of the city, resistance seemed to be limited.</p>
        <p>In what appeared to be a preliminary operation in Baquba, police officials and witnesses said that early on Monday, a small contingent of Iraqi security forces moved into one area of Baquba, encountering little fire.</p>
        <p>The Iraqi forces were joined by some members of the 1920s Revolutionary Brigade, a Sunni Arab group with units that have recently repudiated a longstanding alliance with Al Qaeda, and witnesses said the two groups were welcomed by the residents. American helicopters could be heard overhead, ready to assist, but residents told the Iraqis they wanted help stopping the sectarian bloodshed and ridding Iraq of the Americans.</p>
        <p>''Why didn't you do this in the past?'' said a man in who gave his name as Abu Muhammad, as he pulled together the hands of a police captain and a brigade commander. He added: ''If you work together you can secure Iraq, and the occupation will have no choice but to leave. But if you stay divided Al Qaeda will stay and the occupation will stay.''</p>
        <p>The Iraqi police said the assault on Baquba led to the deaths of at least four insurgents by Monday afternoon. Fourteen others were arrested, the police said, and a large arms cache was seized, though American officials did not confirm the deaths or detainments. It was unclear if there were any casualties among Iraqi or American troops.</p>
        <p>In what appeared to be a separate operation deep in the south near the Iranian border, a ferocious battle between American troops and Shiite militants left at least 20 people dead and wounded scores more, Iraqi and American officials said.</p>
        <p>The clashes, in Amara and Majjar al-Kabir, a pair of mostly Shiite towns just north of Basra, started early Monday. They were sparked by raids on what American officials described as a secret network involved in transporting ''lethal aid'' from Iran to Iraq, particularly deadly roadside bombs known as explosively formed penetrators, or E.F.P.'s.</p>
        <p>Lt. Col. Christopher Garver, an American military spokesman in Iraq, said American troops have intensified their focus on finding and dismantling places where those weapons are built, like the towns raided Monday, because the weapons were especially hard to stop at the border. ''It's hard to catch because they are shipped as components, not completed weapons,'' he said.</p>
        <p>According to officials aligned with the Shiite cleric Moktada al-Sadr in Basra, the fighting involved members of Mr. Sadr's Mahdi Army militia. The battle appeared to be the largest clash with Mr. Sadr's loosely affiliated gunmen since the start of the new American security plan in February.</p>
        <p>In addition to the 20 dead, six suspects were wounded and one was detained, officials said. A hospital official said that at least 60 people were wounded.</p>
        <p>A few hours later, members of the Mahdi Army marched alongside the coffins of those killed, but the battle did not resume, said Abdul Karim al-Muhammadawi, a senior tribal and political figure in Amara. By Monday afternoon, he said, ''The armed presence of the Mahdi Army was gone.''</p>
        <p>Despite the heightened military operation, violence churned on elsewhere in Iraq. In southern Baghdad, two consecutive car bombs near a gas line killed at least seven people and wounded 29, an Interior Ministry official said. Baghdad authorities found 33 unidentified bodies, many showing signs of torture, as mortar shells, shootings and bombs across the capital killed at least nine people, including a national police commander.</p>
        <p>Between violence in Anbar, west of Baghdad; Hilla, south of Baghdad; and Kirkuk, to the north, eight people were killed and more than a dozen wounded. The United States military said one soldier was killed late Sunday when an improvised explosive device exploded near a foot patrol in a southern part of the capital.</p>
        <p>In Samarra, where insurgents destroyed the two remaining minarets of a Shiite shrine on Wednesday, gunmen and a suicide bomber attacked the headquarters of the area's national police commandos, killing four policemen and wounding eight, security officials said. A civilian was also killed in the assault, which came the day after the lifting of a curfew that was imposed when the shrine was bombed.</p>
        <p>Michael R. Gordon reported from Baquba, and Damien Cave from Baghdad. Reporting was contributed by Ali Adeeb, Karim Hilmi and Alissa J. Rubin from Baghdad, and Iraqi employees of The New York Times from Basra and Baquba.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Michael R. Gordon reported from Baquba, and Damien Cave from Baghdad. Reporting was contributed by Ali Adeeb, Karim Hilmi and Alissa J. Rubin from Baghdad, and Iraqi employees of The New York Times from Basra and Baquba.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
