<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Woods Faces Challenges, Being a Father Among Them</title>
    <meta content="19golf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/sports/golf/19golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855570"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E0DF133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="700" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Woods Faces Challenges, Being a Father Among Them</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Woods Faces Challenges, Being a Father Among Them</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa., June 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Tiger Woods tapped in for par Sunday on the final hole at Oakmont Country Club, his work in the 107th United States Open was not finished.</p>
        <p>It is protocol for the runner-up to return to the 18th green for the trophy presentation, and Woods and Jim Furyk, who tied for second, were asked to help fill the background of bodies flanking the champion, Ángel Cabrera.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the first time in his career, Tiger Woods has posted second-place finishes in consecutive majors  a stretch that at the least reveals some vulnerability in the No. 1 ranked player in the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Tiger Woods tapped in for par Sunday on the final hole at Oakmont Country Club, his work in the 107th United States Open was not finished.</p>
        <p>It is protocol for the runner-up to return to the 18th green for the trophy presentation, and Woods and Jim Furyk, who tied for second, were asked to help fill the background of bodies flanking the champion, Ángel Cabrera.</p>
        <p>Woods clapped his hands and made small talk with Furyk as Cabrera hugged his prize as if it were a teddy bear.  ''Finishing second is never fun,'' he said after the round.</p>
        <p>For the first time in his career, Woods has posted second-place finishes in consecutive majors. In a golf year past its midpoint, Woods could face difficulty in adding to his career haul of majors, which stands at 12, 6 behind Jack Nicklaus's record total. The British Open at Carnoustie Golf Links begins July 19. But Woods's presence at the tournament is not certain because his wife, Elin, gave birth early Monday to their first child, a daughter named Sam Alexis Woods.</p>
        <p>''I don't know how much I'm going to play after that or how much I'm going to play before that,'' he said of the birth about two weeks ago, according to The Associated Press. ''A lot of that is depending on what happens and the health of Elin and our child.''</p>
        <p>The P.G.A. Championship presents another challenge. It begins Aug. 9 in Tulsa, Okla., at Southern Hills Country Club, a narrow course filled with doglegs where Woods finished tied for 12th in the 2001 United States Open.</p>
        <p>Woods's recent stretch in the majors reveals at  least some vulnerability for a player ranked No. 1 in the world.</p>
        <p>His back-to-back runner-up finishes at the Masters and the Open put him in company with the game's greatest champions and some of its hard-luck cases.</p>
        <p>Greg Norman, whose Hall of Fame career was peppered with near misses in majors, finished second in the 1986 P.G.A. Championship and the 1987 Masters. Ernie Els, sometimes referred to as a modern-day Norman, was the runner-up in three majors in a row -- the 2000 Masters, the United States Open and the British Open.</p>
        <p>Even golf's icons have been back-to-back bridesmaids.</p>
        <p>Tom Watson, an eight-time major champion, finished second at the 1978 P.G.A. and the 1979 Masters. And Nicklaus was often seen shaking the victor's hand. He finished second at the 1964 British Open and the P.G.A. Championship, the 1968 United States and the British Opens, and the 1971 Masters and the United States Open -- 6 of his record 19 runner-up finishes in majors.</p>
        <p>In pursuing of Nicklaus's record, Woods has been 12 for 12 when going into the final round with at least a share of the 54-hole lead. But that accomplishment has its opposite, as well -- he is 0 for 29 when trailing going into the final 18 holes.</p>
        <p>''I haven't gotten it done,'' he said Sunday. ''Put myself there and haven't gotten it done.''</p>
        <p>At Augusta National Golf Club in the final round, with the little-known Zach Johnson making birdies in front of him, Woods made an eagle on the 13th hole but stalled to lose by two shots.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, with Cabrera grinding out birdies, pars and two late bogeys, Woods closed with a bogey and seven pars and lost by a shot.</p>
        <p>During the third round, Woods hit 17 of 18 greens in regulation and 9 of 14 fairways in a round of 69 that would have been lower if not for several missed birdie putts.</p>
        <p>The final round -- and most of the championship -- was similar for Woods.</p>
        <p>''I certainly played well all week,'' he said. ''I just need to analyze it and see where I went right and see what went wrong.''</p>
        <p>So for two majors in a row, Woods has had to watch someone else stand where he has so often basked in adulation.</p>
        <p>With Cabrera holding the trophy, Woods stepped beside him and studied the names engraved on it. The  players joked with each other, but it was Cabrera who left with the national championship of American golf.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
