<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Writer Gets 18 Years to Life For Sexually Tormenting Former Colleague in 2005</title>
    <meta content="19fake" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/nyregion/19fake.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855575"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Women's Wear Daily</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Braunstein, Peter</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EFDF133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="983" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Writer Gets 18 Years to Life For Sexually Tormenting Former Colleague in 2005</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Writer Sentenced for Sexually Tormenting Former Colleague</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Peter Braunstein, the former Women's Wear Daily writer convicted of terrorizing a former colleague for 13 hours in 2005 after dressing as a firefighter to gain access to her apartment, was sentenced to 18 years to life in prison yesterday.</p>
        <p>In pronouncing the sentence, Justice Thomas Farber of State Supreme Court in Manhattan said that he knew that no sentence could undo the ''pain and terror'' of the crimes, and that he deplored Mr. Braunstein's lack of empathy toward his victim.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Peter Braunstein, the former Women’s Wear Daily writer, was sentenced to 18 years to life in prison.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Peter Braunstein, the former Women's Wear Daily writer convicted of terrorizing a former colleague for 13 hours in 2005 after dressing as a firefighter to gain access to her apartment, was sentenced to 18 years to life in prison yesterday.</p>
        <p>In pronouncing the sentence, Justice Thomas Farber of State Supreme Court in Manhattan said that he knew that no sentence could undo the ''pain and terror'' of the crimes, and that he deplored Mr. Braunstein's lack of empathy toward his victim.</p>
        <p>But he said that as serious as those crimes were, including kidnapping, sexual abuse and robbery, they did not rise to the level of the maximum sentence, 25 years to life, requested by the prosecution.</p>
        <p>''I have seen enough sentencings with victim impact statements delivered by grieving mothers to know the type of case that truly deserves a maximum sentence,'' the judge said.</p>
        <p>Justice Farber said that by committing the crime while disguised as a firefighter, Mr. Braunstein had terrorized not just the victim, but ''every woman living in New York who might trust a fireman or a policeman in a similar situation.''</p>
        <p>The sentence was three years more than the minimum of 15 years to life requested by Mr. Braunstein's lawyer, Robert Gottlieb.</p>
        <p>The judge said he was cognizant that ''any sentence I pronounce on this profoundly disturbed man may well result in his dying in jail.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Braunstein, 43, was sentenced to 18 years to life on the top charge of kidnapping and a fixed term of 20 years on the combined sexual abuse and robbery charges. But the district attorney's office said the 18-years-to-life sentence superseded the other. He will not be eligible for release until he has served 18 years in prison, a spokeswoman for the State Parole Board said in a telephone interview yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gottlieb said later that the judge seemed to be acknowledging the possibility that Mr. Braunstein would not be paroled for a long time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Braunstein was given an opportunity to speak before sentencing.</p>
        <p>It was the first public statement that Mr. Braunstein, who did not testify in his own defense, had made since his trial began. He wore a gray button-down shirt and khaki slacks. His hair was cut in a jailhouse buzz cut, and he had stubble on his face.</p>
        <p>He spoke in a barely audible, high-pitched voice, articulating his words thickly, as if his tongue were swollen. He focused on his own feelings about the crime, saying it was ''random'' and motivated by ''irrationality.'' He never mentioned his victim.</p>
        <p>''You can feel you have nothing to live for and severe depression,'' Mr. Braunstein said. ''Either way, it's much more complicated.''</p>
        <p>Prosecutors said Mr. Braunstein dressed as a firefighter and set off a smoke bomb to trick his 36-year-old victim into letting him into her Chelsea apartment on Oct. 31, 2005. Once inside, he knocked her out with chloroform, stripped her, tied her to her bed and sexually molested her for 13 hours.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors said Mr. Braunstein had chosen the victim, an editor at W magazine -- which shares a newsroom with Women's Wear Daily -- as a surrogate for his former girlfriend, Jane Larkworthy, the beauty editor at W. Ms. Larkworthy testified that Mr. Braunstein had persuaded her to play bondage games.</p>
        <p>Justice Farber noted yesterday that the crime ''permitted the defendant to act out his own bondage fetish.''</p>
        <p>A jury convicted Mr. Braunstein last month of 10 counts of kidnapping, burglary, robbery and sexual abuse, nearly every charge against him. He was acquitted only of arson.</p>
        <p>The judge said yesterday that he believed the prosecution evidence that Mr. Braunstein was narcissistic, not the defense case that he was schizophrenic. He said Mr. Braunstein had been reduced by mental illness from a man of ''extraordinary'' intellect, wit and humor into ''a pathetic shell of a man.''</p>
        <p>But he said that a note from the jury during the trial, in which Mr. Braunstein was referred to by his first name, convinced him that the jury saw Mr. Braunstein as a human being, not as the caricature labeled ''Pervy Pete'' and ''Fire Fiend'' by the city's tabloid newspapers.</p>
        <p>In that way, the judge said, the jury showed more empathy than Mr. Braunstein.</p>
        <p>Mr. Braunstein's victim did not attend the sentencing. A prosecutor, Maxine Rosenthal, spoke for her. She said the woman had never spent another night at the apartment where Mr. Braunstein attacked her. She said that while the woman's name was known by many in the fashion industry, she ''constantly feared who might find out'' that she had been Mr. Braunstein's victim. The news media have withheld her name because of the sexual nature of the crime.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rosenthal said that for the victim, every Halloween and every encounter with a firefighter would be a reminder.</p>
        <p>In his statement yesterday, Mr. Braunstein described his crimes as ''suicide-based.'' After he entered the woman's apartment, he said, ''it dawned on me that I did not know why I was entering.''</p>
        <p>''So I just watched TV and waited until dawn and then I left.''</p>
        <p>This contradicted the victim's account that he had taken a sleeping pill and had lain down next to her while she was tied naked in her bed.</p>
        <p>Of his six weeks as a fugitive, Mr. Braunstein said: ''I thought that I'd see America and then die. You know, have the cops shoot me to death.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Braunstein was captured in Memphis on Dec. 16, 2005, he pointed a dagger at the officer who confronted him, but the officer did not shoot, and Mr. Braunstein stabbed himself in the neck.</p>
        <p>Mr. Braunstein ended his statement yesterday with the word ''So.  ... '' and a shrug, as if he had run out of things to say. As court officers led him away in handcuffs, he nodded to his father, Alberto, sitting in the front row of the courtroom.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
