<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Liberating Effects of Captive Conversation</title>
    <meta content="19flier" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855660"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FREQUENT FLIER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Berger, Russ, Design Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berger, Russ</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raymond, Joan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bolton, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Frequent Flier</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Business Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E0DA1731F93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="609" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Liberating Effects of Captive Conversation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RUSS BERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berger, Russ</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russ Berger Design Group president Russ Berger, in Frequent Flier column, on meeting singer Michael Bolton during flight back to Dallas from New York about 20 years ago; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I've been in the business of designing broadcast and recording studios for about 30 years, and since the beginning I've been traveling at least once a week. I've learned that the captive conversation between me and my seatmate can have some unexpected business or personal consequences that are downright karmic.</p>
        <p>About 20 years ago on a flight back to Dallas from New York, my seatmate was this tall long-haired guy. I was a little tired after winding up several productive days working on a project at NBC in Rockefeller Center, designing and overseeing construction of Edit 7, ''Saturday Night Live's''  primary audio post-control room. And I wasn't sure if I wanted to chat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I've been in the business of designing broadcast and recording studios for about 30 years, and since the beginning I've been traveling at least once a week. I've learned that the captive conversation between me and my seatmate can have some unexpected business or personal consequences that are downright karmic.</p>
        <p>About 20 years ago on a flight back to Dallas from New York, my seatmate was this tall long-haired guy. I was a little tired after winding up several productive days working on a project at NBC in Rockefeller Center, designing and overseeing construction of Edit 7, ''Saturday Night Live's''  primary audio post-control room. And I wasn't sure if I wanted to chat.</p>
        <p>But this guy and I did start to talk. He shared that he was a musician and songwriter. I conveyed that I designed recording studios and broadcast facilities. Both of us were just starting out in a really tough industry. We got along really well, sharing stories about our love of music and our families.</p>
        <p>He told me he had just renegotiated a recording contract, and his first breakthrough album would be released soon. I told him I'd look for his record, and he said that he'd try to record in one of the studios that I designed.</p>
        <p>Some four years later, while I was working on the Sony Music Entertainment Studios, I received a call from someone who worked on the recording engineering staff of the artist who was next to me on the plane. They wanted me to help with the design of a recording and mix studio at his residence. By now, this guy, Michael Bolton, had Grammy Awards, multi-platinum records, sold-out concerts, and was a success in both his career and personal life -- respected not only for his talent but for the charitable work he conducted within the community.</p>
        <p>When I visited his house in 1992 to work with him and his engineer on the design of the studio area, Mr. Bolton recognized me but couldn't place where we had met. It came back once I recounted the story of the airplane ride from New York to Dallas some four years earlier.</p>
        <p>We had a lot of fun working on his recording room and went on to work together building a pet project for the Michael Bolton Foundation called Safe Space. It's an outreach project to help inner-city kids find productive outlets through music and careers in the music business.</p>
        <p>So, a simple plane ride home turned into something of an extended adventure. All because I took the time to talk.</p>
        <p>On a recent flight back to Dallas from Los Angeles, I sat next to a gentleman who owns a marketing and innovations firm. Although we had never met, we started talking before we even took our seats. The more we talked, the more it became apparent how much we had in common.</p>
        <p>I told him how my daughter chose to complete degrees both in cultural anthropology and corporate communications. He said his company had a division that used cultural anthropology in marketing. He offered to introduce her to some people. My daughter wound up with an internship that morphed into a full-time position.</p>
        <p>Again, a chance meeting on a plane and a friendly conversation with a stranger turned into something extraordinary: an excellent career opportunity for the daughter of a very proud father.</p>
        <p>You never know what a conversation will reap. So I'm going to try to talk a little bit more. If you happen to be one of my seatmates and don't want to talk, just let me know. But you never know what might transpire.</p>
        <p>FREQUENT FLIER</p>
        <p>Russ Berger, as told to Joan Raymond. E-mail:  joan.raymond@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Russ Berger, as told to Joan Raymond. E-mail:  joan.raymond@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
