<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Owners Push New Arena, But Residents Fear Change</title>
    <meta content="19arena" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/nyregion/19arena.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855510"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Newark (NJ)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE7DF133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1450" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Owners Push New Arena, But Residents Fear Change</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Owners Push New Arena, but Residents Fear Change</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW JACOBS</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, June 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After all the years of hyperbolic talk, the failed promises and the false starts, the  behemoth looming over downtown is a steel and glass affirmation that good things can happen to this star-crossed city.</p>
        <p>''I never thought I'd see something like this in my lifetime,''  Ada Wells,  82,  said as she ambled by the hulking frame of the Prudential Center, a $375 million arena that will be home to the New Jersey Devils, Seton Hall University's basketball team and, the arena's owners say,  boxing matches, ice-skating shows and concerts, starting with 10 nights of Bon Jovi when the arena opens in late October.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many wonder if Newark’s largely poor and minority population will benefit from one of the most ambitious and expensive ventures in New Jersey in a generation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After all the years of hyperbolic talk, the failed promises and the false starts, the  behemoth looming over downtown is a steel and glass affirmation that good things can happen to this star-crossed city.</p>
        <p>''I never thought I'd see something like this in my lifetime,''  Ada Wells,  82,  said as she ambled by the hulking frame of the Prudential Center, a $375 million arena that will be home to the New Jersey Devils, Seton Hall University's basketball team and, the arena's owners say,  boxing matches, ice-skating shows and concerts, starting with 10 nights of Bon Jovi when the arena opens in late October.</p>
        <p>But like many residents, Ms. Wells, a retired housekeeper who has lived here most of her life, seemed stumped when asked if she would be buying tickets for an event at the arena. ''Well, I'm not sure this thing is really for people like me,'' she said hesitantly before continuing down Broad Street with a battered shopping cart.</p>
        <p>The subtext of her comment was whether Newark's largely poor and minority population will benefit from one of the most ambitious and expensive ventures in New Jersey in a generation. As King Cooley, 58, a Customs Service employee put it, ''Everyone knows hockey is a white man's sport.''</p>
        <p>City officials and the arena's owners speak rapturously about the building's potential: the hundreds of food concession and maintenance jobs on the inside, the employment possibilities offered by the upscale restaurants, sports bars and hotels that are expected to take root nearby.</p>
        <p>''I'm optimistic that the arena will create enduring opportunities for Newark residents and it will be a revenue generator for the city for years to come,'' said Mayor Cory A. Booker. He was once a vociferous critic of the project's financing, which required a $210 million investment from City Hall under the previous administration, but is now a booster.</p>
        <p>To gain Mr. Booker's backing last fall, the Devils' principal owner, Jeffrey Vanderbeek, agreed to provide close to 5,000 free tickets each season for local children and $250,000 each year for youth sports and recreation. He also promised that Newark residents would get first dibs on permanent arena jobs.</p>
        <p>As 700 construction workers raced toward an Oct. 25 deadline, Mr. Vanderbeek led visitors on a tour on Friday</p>
        <p>of the sales center of one of the nation's most tricked-out sports arenas.  There will be 750 flat-screen televisions,  five ribbons of advertising zippers and a half dozen meeting rooms for community groups.</p>
        <p>It remains unclear how well the Prudential Center's 14,500 general admission seats will sell on game nights. But Mr. Vanderbeek said that 96 percent of the 10,000 season ticket holders at the Devils' former home in the Meadowlands had renewed, and that 3,000 new season tickets had been sold. All of the most expensive luxury suites -- $285,000 for 18-seat boxes -- have been bought, as have the arena's 2,114 ''club seats,'' which run along both sides of the arena's midsection with access to a pair of private lounges.</p>
        <p>''We've got a waiting list of 420 names,'' he said with feigned disappointment about the club seats. ''I wish we had more to sell.''</p>
        <p>Prospective buyers have clearly been swayed by the dog-and-pony show that takes place day and night on the 33rd floor of the nearby National Newark Building, where sales agents entertain corporate executives and show off full-scale models of the Fire Lounge</p>
        <p>and a luxury box with plush seating and granite countertops.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vanderbeek began a tour on Friday</p>
        <p>at the elevator banks, where a window provides a bird's-eye glimpse of Newark's Pennsylvania Station three blocks from the arena, the tangle of highways just beyond and the smog-cloaked Manhattan skyline in the distance. The view gives Mr. Vanderbeek an opportunity to talk up ''accessibility,'' the idea that Newark is a 19-minute train ride from New York or Hoboken and a quick dash from Newark Liberty International Airport.</p>
        <p>The final punch is delivered in a luxury box mock-up. After he reviews the touch-screen food menus and the suites' proximity to the ice, a promotional film gives close-ups of body-checking hockey players, cocktail parties full of smartly dressed executives and a gushing testimonial by the mayor. ''See you in Newark,'' a player exclaims at the end. ''You better save me a seat!''</p>
        <p>Then the screen retracts to reveal a bank of windows that perfectly frame the new arena, a block-wide structure wedged into the center of Newark's long-suffering downtown. Before their eyes have fully adjusted to the daylight, potential buyers are gently ushered into the ''closing room,'' where they can opt to buy one of the remaining 12-seat boxes for $225,000 a year for a minimum of three years.</p>
        <p>A former Lehman Brothers investment banker, Mr. Vanderbeek has made a calculated gamble that hockey fans will find Newark more appealing than the Meadowlands, where the Devils have spent more than two decades playing to dismal crowds in the aging Continental Airlines Arena.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vanderbeek's investment was significantly burnished in February, when AEG, which owns and operates stadiums and arenas across the country, announced it would manage the Prudential Center and bring in 30 to 40 nonsporting events a year, including concerts and professional wrestling matches. Executives of the company, which is also building a 25,000-seat soccer stadium for the Red Bulls in nearby Harrison, say they hope to draw three million visitors a year to what they describe as an entertainment district.</p>
        <p>By now both Mr. Vanderbeek and Nick Sakiewicz, president of AEG New York/New Jersey, have become well practiced at swatting away those who suggest that hockey's largely suburban fan base  will be skittish about traveling to a city that has a stubborn reputation for lawlessness. ''This is a way for people to get a taste of Newark,'' Mr. Sakiewicz said as he walked through the arena. ''And to see that there aren't burning cars in the streets, that there are thousands of professionals working here and that there is a reason to stay after dark.''</p>
        <p>On the streets surrounding the arena, property owners who have sat on vacant buildings for years are beginning to stir.</p>
        <p>Two hockey-themed taverns have opened in recent months, Hell's Kitchen and the Arena Bar, and a third, the Devil's Advocate, is under renovation in a nearby building used as a residence by Seton Hall students.  Samer Hanini, a developer, is renovating a loft building whose residents will be near</p>
        <p>the arena's brick and glass facade. A hotel is slated to be built on Mulberry Street across from the arena's main entrance, but ground is not expected to be broken until well after the arena opens.</p>
        <p>Stefan Pryor, the city's deputy mayor for economic development, said he began receiving  calls from potential investors soon after the arena's skeleton began rising outside the window of his City Hall office. Earlier this month, the city created the Brick City Development Corporation, a quasi-public agency that will dole out $11 million  in incentives to prospective businesses.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pryor said he hoped developers would be further entranced by the $17 million streetscape project, financed with state, city and private money, that in the coming months will improve the area around Broad and Market Streets.</p>
        <p>''Interest has been swirling around this arena,'' he said. ''No doubt about it.''</p>
        <p>But those who study the economic impact of urban arenas say much of the profit, at least early on, typically ends up in the pockets of owners, not residents of surrounding neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>Mark S. Rosentraub, dean of theCollege of Urban Affairs at Cleveland State University who has analyzed similar projects, said the most successful arenas are those planned as part of ambitious redevelopment proposals that use public money to leverage private investment in the surrounding area.</p>
        <p>''The problem is if you don't have a large commitment of private dollars, it can be risky,'' he said. While city officials are working with developers to build thousands of market-rate apartments near the arena, those plans remain on the drawing board.</p>
        <p>Then there are those who worry that too much success will doom the hair-braiding salons, hip-hop clothing stores and other downtown businesses that cater to residents.</p>
        <p>Soon H. Yu, the owner of Three Stars Clothing, has done well selling Tupac Shakur T-shirts and dollar-sign pendants encrusted with cubic zirconia. Although she does not know much about the Devils, Ms. Yu has learned a thing or two from the shoppers who come  to her store, which is across  Broad Street from the arena.</p>
        <p>''If it was basketball, that is a good thing, but hockey is no good,'' she said flashing a sour expression. ''I don't want to lose black people because they make good business.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
