<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Santana, a Fine Line Leads Straight to .500</title>
    <meta content="19twins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/sports/baseball/19twins.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855646"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Minnesota Twins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Minnesota Twins</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Santana, Johan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E2DE133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="995" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Santana, a Fine Line Leads Straight to .500</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Twins’ Santana, Pitching’s Fine Line Leads Straight to .500</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAT BORZI</byline>
      <dateline>MINNEAPOLIS, June 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 2-2 fastball from Johan Santana in the sixth inning Thursday night crossed the plate low, not by much, but enough for Atlanta's Matt Diaz to take it for ball three. Santana's next pitch, a slider, did not break down and away enough, and the right-handed-hitting Diaz flicked a ground ball inside the first-base line for a two-out double that drove in a run.</p>
        <p>Santana, the Minnesota Twins' All-Star left-hander, watched the ball scoot across the FieldTurf with the disgusted look of someone who had seen this happen far too often lately.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scouts say Johan Santana’s stuff remains exceptional but his command is slightly off, which may be some small consolation for a Mets team that needs all the help it can get.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 2-2 fastball from Johan Santana in the sixth inning Thursday night crossed the plate low, not by much, but enough for Atlanta's Matt Diaz to take it for ball three. Santana's next pitch, a slider, did not break down and away enough, and the right-handed-hitting Diaz flicked a ground ball inside the first-base line for a two-out double that drove in a run.</p>
        <p>Santana, the Minnesota Twins' All-Star left-hander, watched the ball scoot across the FieldTurf with the disgusted look of someone who had seen this happen far too often lately.</p>
        <p>That two-pitch sequence at the Metrodome illustrated the difference between the hard-luck Santana who will face the Mets on Tuesday night at Shea Stadium and the dominating Santana who won the American League Cy Young Award two of the past three seasons.</p>
        <p>Major league scouts who have seen Santana recently say his stuff remains exceptional but his command is slightly off, which may be some small consolation for a Mets team that has been in a tailspin and needs all the help it can get.</p>
        <p>Although Santana remains among the American League leaders in strikeouts, and his 3.19 earned run average nearly equals his career mark coming into the season (3.20), his record is only 6-6, and he has given up 14 home runs in 14 starts.</p>
        <p>''Everybody is so used to him dominating,'' Twins Manager Ron Gardenhire said. ''The expectation when he takes the mound is, he's going to shut everybody out. For whatever reason, hitters are making it a lot harder for him to get them out.''</p>
        <p>In one sense, this is a typical early season for Santana, whose career record is masterful after the All-Star Game break (45-10, 2.55 E.R.A.) but not so much before it (39-27, 3.68). In 2004, the year he won 20 games and his first Cy Young Award, Santana had a 4-4 record and a 4.84 E.R.A. through his first 14 starts. And at this point last year, he was 6-4 with a 2.99 E.R.A.</p>
        <p>But Santana, whose 17-game winning streak at home ended in April, already has as many losses at the Metrodome (four) this season as he had in both 2004 and 2005. Santana has been prone to the big mistake at a time when the Twins have struggled offensively. Only 4 times in his 14 starts have the Twins managed more than three runs, and Santana's last four losses have all been what are known as quality starts -- at least six innings pitched and no more than three runs allowed. In three of the games, he gave up only two earned runs.</p>
        <p>On Thursday night, Santana left after seven innings trailing the Braves and Tim Hudson, 2-0. Had Minnesota not rallied in the ninth for a 3-2 victory to get Santana off the hook, he would have had his seventh loss -- as many as he has ever had in a season since breaking into the majors as a reliever in 2000.</p>
        <p>''I try not to think about it,'' Santana said about the absence of run support. ''I don't try to do anything different. I just hope my team will step it up next time.''</p>
        <p>Santana's failure to dominate so far has added one more level of uncertainty to Minnesota's already shaky starting rotation.</p>
        <p>The Twins signed the veterans Ramón Ortiz and Sidney Ponson to replace the scintillating rookie Francisco Liriano, who is out for the season after ligament transplant surgery, and the retired Brad Radke. Both newcomers flopped. Ponson was released, and Ortiz, after a good April, floundered and pitched himself into the bullpen.</p>
        <p>Now Santana fronts a rotation that includes the inconsistent veteran Carlos Silva [who is 4-8 after Monday night's 8-1 loss to the Mets], and the youngsters Boof Bonser, Kevin Slowey and Scott Baker. The Twins' pitching coach, Rick Anderson, says Santana realizes the burden he carries and tries too hard to make perfect pitches.</p>
        <p>''It's just a mistake here and there getting hammered in a big situation,'' Anderson said.</p>
        <p>In Santana's previous start before Thursday's, Washington's Ryan Zimmerman belted a 1-2 changeup for a three-run homer, the only runs Santana allowed in seven innings in a 3-1 loss. And on Thursday, Atlanta catcher Brian McCann, whom Santana struck out with fastballs in his first at-bat, sat on one leading off the fifth inning and drove the pitch over the center-field wall to break a scoreless tie. McCann had not homered against a left-hander since Sept. 6. That, and Diaz's double, nearly beat Santana.</p>
        <p>''If you don't score any runs, it looks even worse,'' Santana said. ''If we had scored four or five runs, we wouldn't even be talking about this.''</p>
        <p>Mike Redmond, who caught four of Santana's starts while Joe Mauer was sidelined with a left quadriceps strain, and Gardenhire noted that hitters were fouling off more of Santana's pitches than they remembered. Redmond said, ''For whatever reason, teams are grinding him out more.''</p>
        <p>Anderson said Santana had been tipping his pitches early in the season, holding his glove in a way that told hitters whether to expect a fastball or Santana's normally nasty changeup. That was corrected, Anderson said, and had not been an issue in his past six or seven starts.</p>
        <p>This is usually the month in which Santana starts rolling. Last June, Santana was named the American League pitcher of the month after going 5-0 with a 1.05 E.R.A., and his career mark for the month is 16-6. Interleague play also brings out the best in Santana. His 14-4 interleague record includes two victories in two starts against the Mets, the first a 6-1 decision at Shea on June 18, 2002.</p>
        <p>Of course, if this year's Twins scored like that more often, Santana would not be on the verge of tying his career high for losses.</p>
        <p>''He's doing his job,'' Gardenhire said. ''That's all we ever ask of anybody around here. We need to pick him up.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
