<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Despite Bush's Promises, Georgians Remain Skeptical About Immigration Bill</title>
    <meta content="19immig" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/washington/19immig.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855588"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Illegal Immigrants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Citizenship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Citizenship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Identification Devices</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Georgia</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Chambliss, Saxby</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kennedy, Edward M</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Isakson, Johnny</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00EEDF133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1068" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Despite Bush's Promises, Georgians Remain Skeptical About Immigration Bill</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Despite Bush’s Promises, Georgians Remain Skeptical About Immigration Bill</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>MARIETTA, Ga., June 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If President Bush thought he could win support for a comprehensive immigration bill by promising to secure the border and step up law enforcement, he would be dismayed by the reaction here.</p>
        <p>''It's all window dressing,'' said Mark A. Johnson, a real estate lawyer in this fast-growing suburb of Atlanta. ''We don't believe the government has the will to enforce any of these promises. Everybody can see the folly of it, everybody but the politicians.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The bill is expected to return to the Senate late this week, but the storm raging around immigration shows no sign of abating.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If President Bush thought he could win support for a comprehensive immigration bill by promising to secure the border and step up law enforcement, he would be dismayed by the reaction here.</p>
        <p>''It's all window dressing,'' said Mark A. Johnson, a real estate lawyer in this fast-growing suburb of Atlanta. ''We don't believe the government has the will to enforce any of these promises. Everybody can see the folly of it, everybody but the politicians.''</p>
        <p>Georgia's two Republican senators would almost certainly be on the list of politicians arousing Mr. Johnson's skepticism. The two, Saxby Chambliss and Johnny Isakson, were part of the small bipartisan group that wrote the original bill. But they have been edging away from it since being strongly  criticized in the state.</p>
        <p>The storm raging around the bill shows no sign of abating despite reassuring presidential words about strengthening border security.</p>
        <p>Reagan W. Dean, a Georgia state employee, said: ''Maybe it is possible to secure the border. Maybe it is possible to establish an employee identification system. But I don't have any confidence that it will be done.''</p>
        <p>''It really upsets me to find out that my government says, 'Yes, we can secure the border, we can detain illegal aliens, we can take all sorts of actions to enforce the law, but we will do so only if Congress provides legal status to those who are here illegally,' '' Mr. Dean said.</p>
        <p>The provision of the bill that appeals most to Hispanic groups and many Democrats -- a path to citizenship for millions of illegal immigrants -- generates the most opposition from conservatives. After the measure stalled in the Senate on June 7, President Bush and sponsors of the bill pledged to strengthen its security provisions in an effort to defuse opposition to the legalization program. The legislation,  Mr. Bush's top domestic priority, is expected to return to the Senate floor late this week.</p>
        <p>If a sampling of Georgia opinion is any evidence, the bill's path has not gotten much smoother.</p>
        <p>Louis S. Hunter, a pollster and political analyst based in Atlanta, said, ''Congress and the president are completely out of touch with how people here feel about illegal immigration.''</p>
        <p>Senator Chambliss, who is up for re-election next year, was booed last month when he defended the bill at the state Republican convention. In nearby Gwinnett County, the local Republican Party adopted a resolution last week urging both senators to ''vote no on this amnesty bill.''</p>
        <p>Jane V. Kidd, chairwoman of the Democratic Party of Georgia, said: ''This is not a partisan issue in Georgia. A small percentage of Democrats are supporting the bill as it stands, but a majority of Democrats and Republicans in the state do not like it.''</p>
        <p>Three Democrats who hope to unseat Mr. Chambliss have criticized the bill and his role in drafting it, Ms. Kidd said.</p>
        <p>Joan Kirchner, a spokesman for Mr. Isakson, said he had ''heard the message loud and clear.'' The senator believes that border security and law enforcement ''should be decoupled'' from proposals to legitimize the status of illegal immigrants and establish a guest-worker program, Ms. Kirchner said.</p>
        <p>Douglas C. Dromey,  a land broker in Kennesaw, Ga., said, ''I have written off both parties on this issue.''</p>
        <p>In a speech last week, Mr. Bush said, ''This bill sets clear benchmarks for border security that must be met before other elements of this legislation are triggered.'' The president  endorsed a proposed amendment to provide $4.4 billion to help secure the border and enforce a 1986 law that forbids the hiring of illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hunter, a former Republican member of the Cobb County Board of Commissioners, in Marietta, said: ''Words on paper don't mean anything. When I see the fence built and guards on the border, that's when they -- Congress and the political class -- will have done their job.''</p>
        <p>On the other hand, Jeffrey M. Smith, an Atlanta lawyer with many clients from China, India and Mexico, said: ''The idea of a fence is just nuts. It will not stop people coming to this country. It will cost a lot of money. It will create a lot of ill will in Central and South America. It will look as if we are keeping out Hispanics, and that's what we would be doing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith endorsed the idea of legal status for illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>''They should be naturalized, become citizens and pay taxes,'' Mr. Smith said. ''If you don't give them an amnesty, you will drive them further underground.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dean, the state employee and a lifelong Republican, said: ''I can understand why Ted Kennedy and the Democratic Party are behind this bill. What I don't understand is why President Bush and some Republican senators are behind it. I frankly see this legislation as assisted suicide, for America, for the Republican Party and for all the individual politicians who support it.''</p>
        <p>Senator Kennedy of Massachusetts, the chief Democratic architect of the bill, has been its staunchest defender.</p>
        <p>People here say they believe that Mr. Isakson, a resident of Marietta, shares their concerns. More than a year ago he insisted on ''border security first,'' as a prerequisite to ''any immigration reform.'' On May 17, he and Mr. Chambliss joined Mr. Kennedy at a news conference announcing agreement on the bill.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson, the real estate lawyer, said: ''Senator Kennedy must have some sort of Svengali influence on people. They go into a backroom negotiation with him, and they come out bamboozled.''</p>
        <p>Some Georgians say that politics helps explain support for the bill by President Bush and some Republican senators.</p>
        <p>''It's a political calculus,'' Mr. Johnson said. ''They believe that the Hispanic vote is in play, and that if we're friendly to them, they'll vote Republican.''</p>
        <p>A streak of economic populism runs through the comments of many Georgians.</p>
        <p>''This problem was created by corporate America, which wants to keep the low-wage labor already here and bring in more through a temporary-worker program,'' said Mr. Hunter, the pollster and analyst.</p>
        <p>Farms, poultry plants, a booming construction industry and thousands of landscaping jobs have attracted illegal immigrants to Georgia.</p>
        <p>''Nobody thinks you can round them all up and send them home,'' Mr. Hunter said. ''Nor would we want to. But if we enforce the laws, the job market will diminish somewhat. And for every job that's lost, somebody is going home.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
