<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Literary Dynasty, Warts And All</title>
    <meta content="19kaku" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/books/19kaku.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855592"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Fathers and Sons (Book)&gt;</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Fathers and Sons (Book)&gt;</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Waugh, Alexander</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Waugh, Auberon</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Waugh, Evelyn</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Fathers and Sons (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEEDF133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1097" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Literary Dynasty, Warts And All</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Literary Dynasty, Warts and All</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a letter to his 6-year-old son, which closes this volume, Alexander Waugh  --  son of the satirist Auberon Waugh and grandson of the novelist Evelyn Waugh  --  dispenses some advice: ''Beware of seriousness: it is a form of stupidity,'' ''Fear boredom,'' ''Never use the word 'ersatz,' '' and ''Bear the name of Waugh with pride.'' The Waugh name, he goes on, ''is not a satchel of rocks, or a blotchy birthmark, or a tuxedo with medals for you to swank about in'': ''Do not let it browbeat you into thinking you have to become a writer, that it is your destiny or your duty to do so. It isn't. There is no point in writing unless you have something to say and are determined to say it well.''</p>
        <p>With this ''autobiography'' of his family, Alexander Waugh --  who long resisted joining the family business, trying his hand at producing records, composing music and drawing cartoons  --  demonstrates that he's inherited the literary gene in spades, as well as a gift for very funny, coruscating prose. He has created a vivid, Dickensian portrait of his eccentric relatives and he's done so with enormous irreverence and élan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With this “autobiography” of his family, Alexander Waugh demonstrates that he’s inherited the literary gene in spades, as well as a gift for very funny, coruscating prose.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a letter to his 6-year-old son, which closes this volume, Alexander Waugh  --  son of the satirist Auberon Waugh and grandson of the novelist Evelyn Waugh  --  dispenses some advice: ''Beware of seriousness: it is a form of stupidity,'' ''Fear boredom,'' ''Never use the word 'ersatz,' '' and ''Bear the name of Waugh with pride.'' The Waugh name, he goes on, ''is not a satchel of rocks, or a blotchy birthmark, or a tuxedo with medals for you to swank about in'': ''Do not let it browbeat you into thinking you have to become a writer, that it is your destiny or your duty to do so. It isn't. There is no point in writing unless you have something to say and are determined to say it well.''</p>
        <p>With this ''autobiography'' of his family, Alexander Waugh --  who long resisted joining the family business, trying his hand at producing records, composing music and drawing cartoons  --  demonstrates that he's inherited the literary gene in spades, as well as a gift for very funny, coruscating prose. He has created a vivid, Dickensian portrait of his eccentric relatives and he's done so with enormous irreverence and élan.</p>
        <p>Somehow the word ''dysfunctional'' seems far too American and therapeutic a term for a family that loathed what Auberon Waugh once called ''odious clouds of self-think''  --  ''barmy'' and ''outlandish'' might be closer to the truth.</p>
        <p>Descendants of the family's literary patriarch, Arthur Waugh,  have produced 180 books among them, and torrents of ink have been spilled by family members recounting their own misadventures (and those of their parents, children and siblings) in diaries, letters and memoirs. Nothing seems too private for any of them to write about, and in this volume Alexander Waugh serves up one outrageous family story after another (many dealing with his relatives' shocking lack of parental  skills) with a mixture of bemusement and sangfroid. Many of the absurd characters in Evelyn Waugh's blackly comic novels, the reader comes to realize, were drawn from  --  or at least inspired by  --  life.</p>
        <p>In ''Fathers and Sons'' the Waugh story begins with the author's great-great-grandfather, known to his family  as ''the Brute'':  a sadistic  Victorian paterfamilias, who believed in the aphorism '' 'Tis fear as makes 'em brave.'' The Brute used an ivory-tipped whip to flog his dog and forced his eldest son to kiss his gun case in an effort to make him love the sport of hunting.</p>
        <p>The Brute begat Arthur Waugh, the first of the literary Waughs, who pursued a career in publishing despite his father's objections.  And Arthur Waugh begat two writers, Alec and Evelyn. Alec, who would never rival his younger brother in literary achievements, was his father's cherished favorite --  so much so that Arthur Waugh would compare himself to God the Father and Alec to Jesus Christ .</p>
        <p>Evelyn, who yearned for his father's approval, was routinely dismissed: ''As future 'head of family,' Alec was always served first at table. He always got the best presents. Everything Evelyn was given came to him 'shop-soiled and second-hand,' and he knew it.''</p>
        <p>Alec was sent to a posh boarding school, while Evelyn was sent to a cheaper day school. Alec received doting, love-sick letters from his father, while Evelyn received far more perfunctory epistles.</p>
        <p>After several years in the wilderness  --  drinking, overspending, feeling suicidal  --  Evelyn Waugh made a splash with his biography of Dante Gabriel Rossetti and two novels, ''Decline and Fall'' and ''Vile Bodies,'' the latter of which established him as a genuine literary star and put him ''at the forefront of modern English letters,'' where he would remain to the end of his life.</p>
        <p>''The father-and-son relationship provides one of the central themes of his fiction, running, almost obsessively through every book,'' Alexander Waugh writes of his grandfather's work. ''But not until his last novel does the reader get to witness a father-son relationship that is even partially successful. In 'Unconditional Surrender,' for the first time, a father is seen to take his paternal responsibilities seriously, and the advice he gives to his son is both meaningful and beneficial. To Evelyn, full realization of his own father's worth only became apparent after Arthur's death.''</p>
        <p>In the view of Alec Waugh, their father's death would also bring a new emotionalism to his brother's work: having rebelled for years against his father's theatricality, Evelyn finally allowed himself, with books like ''Brideshead Revisited,'' to probe feelings he had once dismissed as sentimental. What's more, he would become more and more like his father with the passage of time. As his grandson writes:</p>
        <p>''In the 1930's Evelyn was a figurehead of the younger generation. He stood for all that was fast, brash, witty and loud, but after the war he transformed himself into an old-fashioned clown not unlike his father. He wore outmoded and outlandish suits and hats, insisted on changing for dinner, surrounded himself with Victorian furniture and bric-a-brac and, like his father, appeared to the world as an arcane eccentric from a Victorian novel.''</p>
        <p>Though Evelyn Waugh mellowed in his later years (a development his son curiously attributed to a dental operation in which he had all of his teeth removed without anesthetic),  he was for many years a terrifying parent, reserving the right, as Auberon put it, ''not just to deny affection to his children but to advertise an acute and unqualified dislike for them.'' His wife Laura  seems to have been an equally wanting parent, more concerned with her beloved pet cows than with her children.</p>
        <p>Despite his appalling childhood, Auberon Waugh  --  whose essays and satirical writings, in the view of critics like A. N. Wilson and V. S. Naipaul, surpassed even the achievement of his famous progenitor  --  would become, in his son's words, ''a loyal, generous father,'' albeit an unconventional one.</p>
        <p>''He took no interest in my homework or my school marks,'' Alexander Waugh writes, ''or whether I made it into the school cricket team.'' He never recommended books his son might like and never had serious conversations with the boy.  And yet, in the wake of his death in 2001, his son seems to have decided to write this book,</p>
        <p>at least in part as a kind of tribute to him.</p>
        <p>''He provided a more stable upbringing to his four children than he himself had ever received, and left more goodwill towards the name than he had inherited from his father,'' Alexander Waugh writes at the end of this compelling family portrait. ''Papa was the most impressive man I have ever met.''</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
