<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Randolph Isn't Concerned With Beltrán's Leg Woes</title>
    <meta content="19shea" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/sports/baseball/19shea.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855639"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="METS NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Beltran, Carlos</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Randolph, Willie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE3DE133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="649" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Randolph Isn't Concerned With Beltrán's Leg Woes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Randolph Isn’t Concerned With Beltrán’s Leg Woes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Manager Willie Randolph continued to play down the seriousness of Carlos Beltrán's injured left quadriceps before last night's game against the Minnesota Twins, and he questioned why the leg problem seems to have developed into a major story.</p>
        <p>''I'm not concerned about Beltrán or anything that has kind of been created about his leg,'' he said. ''He's been sore, like a lot of guys have been during the course of the season. I've never at any time recently, or in the last month and a half, been concerned or asked him about his leg.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Manager Willie Randolph continued to play down the seriousness of Carlos Beltrán’s injured left quadriceps before Monday night’s game against the Minnesota Twins.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Manager Willie Randolph continued to play down the seriousness of Carlos Beltrán's injured left quadriceps before last night's game against the Minnesota Twins, and he questioned why the leg problem seems to have developed into a major story.</p>
        <p>''I'm not concerned about Beltrán or anything that has kind of been created about his leg,'' he said. ''He's been sore, like a lot of guys have been during the course of the season. I've never at any time recently, or in the last month and a half, been concerned or asked him about his leg.</p>
        <p>''Everyone looked at me Sunday like I was hiding something. It's not an issue for me because it's not an issue for Carlos. People asked him about his leg. He said it was sore. That becomes a big story, I guess.''</p>
        <p>Entering last night's game, Beltrán  was  in one of the worst slumps of his career. He was hitting only .151 in June, with one home run and two runs batted in.</p>
        <p>Randolph and General Manager Omar Minaya said it was unlikely that Beltrán would be kept out of the All-Star Game, on July 10 in San Francisco, if he is selected to play. Minaya said a three-day break was not enough to have a significant impact on Beltrán's aches and pains.</p>
        <p>In the voting released yesterday, Beltrán led all National League outfielders with 1,343,727 votes. Barry Bonds was fourth with 893,159.</p>
        <p>ALL-STAR VOTING Paul Lo Duca still trails Los Angeles Dodgers catcher Russell Martin in voting to start the All-Star Game. Lo Duca led the early balloting, but he now trails Martin, 936,712 to 814,870.</p>
        <p>Carlos Delgado is fifth among first baseman, behind the leader, Prince Fielder of Milwaukee.</p>
        <p>José Valentín is also fifth at second base, behind the leader, Chase Utley of Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>At shortstop, José Reyes leads Milwaukee's J. J. Hardy by more than 250,000 votes, 1,017,893 to 761,471.</p>
        <p>And at third base, David Wright also has a comfortable lead. He has 1,055,723 votes to</p>
        <p>822,435 for Miguel Cabrera of Florida.</p>
        <p>LO DUCA BACK IN LINEUP Paul Lo Duca, who left Sunday's game against the Yankees with a bruised left triceps after being hit by a pitch, returned to the lineup last night against Minnesota. Willie Randolph delayed his decision concerning Lo Duca, who wore a protective sleeve on his arm in the locker room, until after he was able to take pregame batting practice.</p>
        <p>''If he's not favoring his arm, Paul will be in there,'' Randolph said. ''Paul is pretty tough. It's just a bruise. You deal with the discomfort when you swing the bat. If it doesn't hinder you and you can tolerate the pain, then you play. It's not like it's a pulled muscle or something.''</p>
        <p>MILLEDGE BEGINS WORKOUTS The minor league outfielder Lastings Milledge, who has been sidelined with a sprained ligament in his right foot, has begun working out in Florida and will start a rehabilitation assignment with Port St. Lucie, Fla.,  shortly, Omar Minaya said yesterday,</p>
        <p>''He is running and swinging the bat and doing those kind of things,'' he said. ''He started that on Friday. We are seeing some progress in that sense.''</p>
        <p>SUPPORT FOR MANUEL Should  Baltimore  show interest in the Mets' bench coach, Jerry Manuel, for their managing vacancy, expect Willie Randolph to give him a glowing recommendation. The Orioles fired Manager Sam Perlozzo yesterday.</p>
        <p>''Jerry deserves to manage in the major leagues,'' Randolph said. ''He's an excellent bench coach. I think it would be a smart move on Baltimore's part to interview him and find out what he's all about. I'd hate to lose him, but he's a solid baseball man.''</p>
        <p>A SHEA STREAK AT STAKE  The Twins' Luis Castillo entered last night's game having hit safely in his previous 32 games at Shea Stadium. Castillo played for  Florida  from 1996 to 2005, before he was traded to Minnesota.</p>
        <p>METS NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
