<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Airbus Logs Orders for 114 of Its A350 as Air Show Begins</title>
    <meta content="19airbus" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/business/worldbusiness/19airbus.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paris Air Show</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Airbus Industrie</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boeing Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jazeera Airways</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ge Commercial Aviation Services</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">S7 Airline</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Emirates Airlines</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Qatar Airways</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Air France</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clark, Nicola</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Airbus Industrie</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boeing Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E7DF133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="687" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Airbus Logs Orders for 114 of Its A350 as Air Show Begins</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Airbus Secures Big Orders at Air Show</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICOLA CLARK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clark, Nicola</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Airlines give big lift to order book for next-generation Airbus A350, announcing contracts for 114 of planes on first day of Paris air show; vote of confidence puts program on more solid footing, although it is still well behind Boeing Co's rival jet; A350 orders, worth more than $27 billion, are part of total of 219 firm orders and 120 provisional ones with combined value of $45.7 billion at list price; Airbus orders announced include contract for 30 Airbus A320s from Jazeera Airways worth $2.1 billion to $2.4 billion; GE Commercial Aviation Services announces orders of up to 60 A320s, and Russian carrier S7 places firm order for 25 of planes; orders for A380 are placed by Emirates, Qatar Airways and Air France; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Airlines gave a big lift to the order book for the next-generation Airbus A350 on Monday, announcing contracts for 114 of the planes on the first day of the Paris air show. The vote of confidence puts the program on more solid footing, although it is still well behind the Boeing Company's rival jet.</p>
        <p>The A350  orders, worth more than $27 billion, were part of a total of 219 firm orders and 120 provisional ones -- including 13 for the much-delayed A380 superjumbo -- with a combined value of $45.7 billion at list price.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Airlines gave a big lift to the order book for the next generation Airbus A350, announcing contracts for 114 of the planes on the first day of the Paris air show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Airlines gave a big lift to the order book for the next-generation Airbus A350 on Monday, announcing contracts for 114 of the planes on the first day of the Paris air show. The vote of confidence puts the program on more solid footing, although it is still well behind the Boeing Company's rival jet.</p>
        <p>The A350  orders, worth more than $27 billion, were part of a total of 219 firm orders and 120 provisional ones -- including 13 for the much-delayed A380 superjumbo -- with a combined value of $45.7 billion at list price.</p>
        <p>''The A350 program is now confirmed,'' said Doug McVitie, a former Airbus salesman who is managing director of Arran Aerospace in Dinan, France. ''They have industry money to build it, and they have gained credibility.''</p>
        <p>Airbus views the A350, which it began marketing in 2004 as a competitor to the popular Boeing 787, as crucial to its recovery while it carries out a broad restructuring.</p>
        <p>The orders announced Monday put the company, a unit of the giant European aerospace consortium EADS, more than halfway to its goal of securing 200 orders this year.</p>
        <p>They  came from several airlines that had been pursued by both Airbus and Boeing, including US Airways.</p>
        <p>The airline said it had agreed to terms with Airbus for 22 of the long-range A350s, part of a 92-plane deal that includes 60 A320 single-aisle aircraft and 10 A330s. Airbus valued the order at $10 billion at list price.</p>
        <p>John Leahy, the Airbus chief operating officer for customer affairs, said the order for single-aisle jets would give US Airways the largest fleet of A320s in the world.</p>
        <p>Airbus had been engaged in an intense competition with the Boeing 787 for the US Airways contract, and recent speculation said the deal could go to Boeing.</p>
        <p>Andrew Nocella, a US Airways senior vice president for planning, offered little insight into the carrier's decision to opt for the Airbus plane. ''The A350 is the right machine for US Airways at the right time,'' he said. ''The timing for delivery worked out very well for us.'' US Airways expects to receive its first A350s in 2014.</p>
        <p>The announcement followed a contract-signing ceremony at Le Bourget airfield of a previously disclosed order from Qatar Airways for 80 new A350s.</p>
        <p>Akbar al-Baker,  chief executive of Qatar Airways, said the order was worth $16 billion. Louis Gallois, co-chief executive of  Airbus, said Qatar would be the first airline to receive the A350s, in 2013.</p>
        <p>Aviation Lease and Finance, based in Kuwait, converted a previous purchase option for 12 A350s into a firm order, the first  for the plane from a leasing company. The company, known in the industry as Alafco, also placed an order for seven A320s in a combined deal worth $3 billion.</p>
        <p>''Any leasing-company order is good news because it means they believe the aircraft will get market acceptance,'' Mr. McVitie said.</p>
        <p>Alafco previously announced an order for 12 Boeing 787s in March.</p>
        <p>Other Airbus orders announced Monday included a contract for 30 Airbus A320s from Jazeera Airways worth $2.1 billion to $2.4 billion. The carrier, a private company based in Kuwait and Dubai, began operation in October 2005 and currently flies five A320s.</p>
        <p>GE Commercial Aviation Services announced orders for up to 60 A320s, and a Russian carrier, S7, placed a firm order for 25 of the planes.</p>
        <p>Airbus also obtained more than a dozen orders for the 555-seat twin-deck A380 from existing customers: eight from Emirates, which has already ordered 47 of the superjumbos; three from Qatar Airways; and a commitment for two orders from Air France.</p>
        <p>''This is really more than Airbus could have expected for the A380,'' Mr. McVitie said. ''Even though they are not coming from new A380 customers, any news is good news.''</p>
        <p>Production of the A380 has been hampered by incompatible computer systems and by a series of manufacturing delays linked to the installation of its electrical wiring, which have put deliveries almost two years behind schedule. Airbus says it is on track to deliver the first A380 to Singapore Airlines in October.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
