<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>POLICE MAY FACE AN ALCOHOL TEST AFTER SHOOTINGS</title>
    <meta content="19undercover" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/nyregion/19undercover.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855647"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcohol Abuse</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baker, Al</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelly, Raymond W (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bell, Sean</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Guzman, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Benefield, Trent</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcohol Abuse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Kelly, Raymond W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bell, Sean</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E2DE133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1223" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>POLICE MAY FACE AN ALCOHOL TEST AFTER SHOOTINGS</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Police May Face an Alcohol Test After Shootings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AL BAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Baker, Al</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comr Raymond W Kelly announces that New York City Police Dept will require officers to take breath tests for alcohol if they shoot someone and to undergo psychological screening before taking on undercover work; both measures were recommended by panel created after Sean Bell of Queens was fatally shot in Nov in volley of 50 bullets fired by officers; Kelly notes that he has accepted all 19 panel recommendations, including hiring actors to help train officers in their undercover roles and creating programs to teach public about need for such operations; three police detectives have been indicted in connection with fatal shooting of Bell and wounding of his friends Trent Benefield and Joseph Guzman; Bell case--in which five officers fired 50 shots into car carrying three men--prompted calls for Police Dept to rethink tactics and rules of undercover operations; case recalled (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York City Police Department is moving to require officers to take breath tests for alcohol if they shoot someone and to undergo a psychological screening when they become candidates for undercover work, Commissioner Raymond W. Kelly announced yesterday. Both measures are among the recommendations of a panel created after a Queens man was fatally shot in November in a volley of 50 bullets fired by officers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelly, who set up the panel in December, said he had accepted all 19 of its recommendations, which included hiring actors to help train officers in their undercover roles as gun dealers or narcotics traffickers and creating programs to teach the public about the need for such operations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The changes were recommended by a panel formed after an unarmed man was fatally shot in Queens by the police.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York City Police Department is moving to require officers to take breath tests for alcohol if they shoot someone and to undergo a psychological screening when they become candidates for undercover work, Commissioner Raymond W. Kelly announced yesterday. Both measures are among the recommendations of a panel created after a Queens man was fatally shot in November in a volley of 50 bullets fired by officers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelly, who set up the panel in December, said he had accepted all 19 of its recommendations, which included hiring actors to help train officers in their undercover roles as gun dealers or narcotics traffickers and creating programs to teach the public about the need for such operations.</p>
        <p>He said he would send the recommendations to senior commanders for feedback and hoped to have the changes in place quickly after he heard from them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelly said the breath tests probably would be conducted by members of the department's Internal Affairs Bureau.</p>
        <p>The new procedures would be the first substantive changes to the way the Police Department operates since the Queens man, Sean Bell, 23, was killed while leaving a strip club in Jamaica on Nov. 25, the morning of his wedding.</p>
        <p>Two of Mr. Bell's friends, Trent Benefield and Joseph Guzman, were wounded. Three police detectives have been indicted in connection with the shooting.</p>
        <p>Four of the five officers involved in the shooting are detectives, and the union that represents them criticized the breath test recommendation, saying such a measure -- which would apply to all police officers -- was subject to collective bargaining.</p>
        <p>The Bell case -- in which the five officers fired 50 shots into a gray Nissan carrying the three men -- prompted calls for the Police Department to rethink the tactics and rules of undercover operations. The detectives indicted in the Bell case were in a larger group seeking prostitution arrests at the Club Kalua, a topless bar.</p>
        <p>One of the detectives approached Mr. Bell's car. But Mr. Bell drove forward, clipping him, and then hit a police minivan, backed up, nearly hitting the detective again and slammed into the minivan a second time, the police have said.</p>
        <p>Neither Mr. Bell nor his friends were armed, although the police officers apparently believed that they were, and no gun was found in the car.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Al Sharpton and a lawyer representing Mr. Benefield and Mr. Guzman offered measured support for the panel's suggestions. ''It is positive change, and it is a first step in the right direction,'' said the lawyer, Sanford A. Rubenstein, who also represents Mr. Bell's fiancée, Nicole Paultre Bell.</p>
        <p>''It also gives greater authority to the New York State Legislature to amend state law to enact this requirement statewide, and it could be a model to enact this kind legislation across the country,'' Mr. Rubenstein said.</p>
        <p>Although the Police Department review was called in response to the Bell shooting, Mr. Kelly said the panelists, all but one of whom were high-ranking members in the department, did not investigate specifics of that case. ''We didn't say, 'Hey, take a look at this case,' '' the commissioner said.</p>
        <p>At the time of the shooting, one aspect of undercover work -- that officers inside a bar or club are allowed up to two alcoholic drinks during an eight-hour shift so as not to look suspicious -- came under special scrutiny.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelly said yesterday that he supported the two-drink rule, and he reiterated that there is no ''indication or evidence'' that alcohol played a role in the Bell shooting. He said the five officers involved ''were found to be fit for duty.''</p>
        <p>Requiring that police officers take breath tests after shootings -- whether the officers are on duty or off -- is a significant change.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelly said the idea was ''roughly akin'' to federal tests, like those required for railroad operators after crashes, and he said the police department in Milwaukee had a similar policy.</p>
        <p>Albert W. O'Leary, a spokesman for the Patrolmen's Benevolent Association, which represents 23,000 rank-and-file officers, said the union had no comment on the recommendations. But the breath test idea was immediately criticized by Michael J. Palladino, president of the Detectives' Endowment Association.</p>
        <p>''I would challenge that,'' Mr. Palladino said of the breath tests. ''I think it is a mandatory subject of collective bargaining, so if the department chooses to just unilaterally impose that, I would challenge that in the appropriate arena, whether that is in the office of collective bargaining or State Supreme Court.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Palladino said the unions also were ''taking a look'' at the 18 other recommendations on the list announced by Mr. Kelly.</p>
        <p>Paul J. Browne, the department's chief spokesman, said the Court of Appeals, the state's highest court, ruled last year that department discipline falls within the authority of the police commissioner ''and is not subject to negotiation through collective bargaining.''</p>
        <p>Psychological screening for potential undercover officers would involve interviews by psychologists or psychiatrists who would determine the candidates' mental suitability for the job, the police said.</p>
        <p>The screenings would be in addition to the current practice, in which candidates for undercover work are observed by supervisors in field situations to see how they cope. Normally, psychological exams are required when police officers are hired.</p>
        <p>The committee also recommended that commanders not limit undercover candidates to those officers who have at least two years of experience on the job. It proposed the commanders consider ''particularly suitable'' candidates who have less experience.</p>
        <p>The panel also proposed that officers wear the same type of jacket -- known as a ''raid jacket' -- when they sweep in to make arrests after an undercover operation is completed. It recommended that undercover officers, like all members of the department, complete firearms training sessions twice a year. To help achieve that, Mr. Kelly said that ''special accommodations be made'' so that ''their identify is protected.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelly said the breath tests could begin as soon as September. He said the guidelines for the tests, and how they will be implemented, are subject to the responses of commanders. He said commanders at shooting scenes will still be required to determine if an officer involved in a shooting was fit for duty.</p>
        <p>Police officials said the goal of the breath tests is an attempt to gather all the facts for the standard post-shooting analysis. ''You're not required to take a Breathalyzer test now,'' Mr. Kelly said. ''That's the big difference.''</p>
        <p>Last year, police officers were involved in 36 shootings in which individuals were injured or killed. (Thirteen people were killed in such shootings.) In recent years, such shootings have numbered in the ''double digits,'' Mr. Browne said, much lower than in earlier eras.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharpton said the call to test officers' sobriety after shootings was a ''rallying cry'' among black religious leaders and elected officials when they met with Mr. Kelly and Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg at City Hall on Nov. 27 to calm frayed tempers after the Bell shooting. Still, Mr. Sharpton had concerns.</p>
        <p>''In the Bell shooting, the Breathalyzer could have been conducted by the cops in the shooting, or by those who responded to the shooting who may have been witnesses or implicated in the case,'' Mr. Sharpton said. ''But other than that, it is a step in the right direction.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
