<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Veteran Umpire Isn't Ready to Toss Himself</title>
    <meta content="19chass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/sports/baseball/19chass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Umpires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Umpires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Froemming, Bruce</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E3DF133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="949" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Veteran Umpire Isn't Ready to Toss Himself</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Veteran Umpire Isn’t Ready to Toss Himself</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Headlines in some newspapers last Friday said: ''Veteran umpire calling it quits,'' ''Froemming to retire at end of season'' or ''Froemming announces he'll retire at end of season.'' The daily agate transactions said, ''Major League Baseball -- announced that umpire Bruce Froemming will retire at end of season.''</p>
        <p>But neither M.L.B. nor Froemming made such an announcement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some newspapers reported last Friday that veteran umpire Bruce Froemming was retiring at the end of the season. But neither M.L.B. nor Froemming made such an announcement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Headlines in some newspapers last Friday said: ''Veteran umpire calling it quits,'' ''Froemming to retire at end of season'' or ''Froemming announces he'll retire at end of season.'' The daily agate transactions said, ''Major League Baseball -- announced that umpire Bruce Froemming will retire at end of season.''</p>
        <p>But neither M.L.B. nor Froemming made such an announcement.</p>
        <p>''I never announced my retirement,'' Froemming said over the weekend at Yankee Stadium. ''That came out of Park Avenue. I don't know why.''</p>
        <p>But Major League Baseball, whose headquarters is on Park Avenue in Manhattan, has not made an announcement.</p>
        <p>''We have not announced anything about his retirement,'' said Mike Port, the official in charge of umpiring.</p>
        <p>''I saw that the other day on A.P. I know he's going to retire at the end of the year, but Bruce hasn't decided which year that's going to be.''</p>
        <p>Froemming said he talked to Port earlier in the year and told him he would make a decision by the All-Star Game.</p>
        <p>''Maybe I'll come back in 2008,'' Froemming said. ''I don't know what I'm going to do. If I get one more game like today, I might go home in July.''</p>
        <p>He was referring to Saturday's game between the Mets and the Yankees, which seemed to last forever but actually took 3 hours 43 minutes, not to mention a 40-minute rain delay.</p>
        <p>The next day, Froemming said of his reported retirement: ''It all may be true. This may be my last year. But I haven't made that decision. Right now, I'm thinking about umpiring next year. That all could change.''</p>
        <p>Froemming, 67, is baseball's senior umpire. Working in his 37th major league season, he holds the record for most years umpired in succession, and his 5,082 games rank second to Bill Klem's 5,368.</p>
        <p>''I'd have almost 6,000 if not for vacations,'' Froemming said. ''We started vacations in 1979. We get 28 days off, so 28 times 28 years is almost 900.''</p>
        <p>In-season vacations for umpires began in 1979 as part of an agreement that settled a labor dispute. As a major league umpire since 1971, Froemming has lived through labor disputes and a 1999 intramural dispute among umpires that ripped apart the umpires union and resulted in the ouster of Richie Phillips as the umpires' lawyer.</p>
        <p>It has taken this long for the umpires to patch up their differences and agree to work once again as a cohesive group.</p>
        <p>''They're in repair mode right now,'' Froemming said. ''As of today, all 70 guys belong to one association. That is new this year. This was all put together last month. As of June 1, everybody belongs to the same organization. They're in the process of hiring new lawyers.''</p>
        <p>Froemming was off by one. Jerry Crawford, the president of the defunct Major League Umpires Association, has declined to join the World Umpires Association. Asked why, Crawford said by telephone yesterday, ''I'd really rather not comment.''</p>
        <p>Fourteen other holdouts have decided to join, bringing peace to the union for the first time since 1999, when the umpires followed Phillips's bizarre strategy to submit their resignations. The failed strategy cost 22 umpires their jobs.</p>
        <p>Tom Hallion and Ed Hickox had been among the 14 union holdouts. This season, they became the last 2 of the 22 who wanted to continue working to umpire again in the majors.</p>
        <p>''I think they've seen the way the union has been run and are pleased with some things that have been done,'' John Hirschbeck, the union president, said yesterday, discussing the June 1 development. ''That encouraged both groups to talk.''</p>
        <p>Froemming had previously joined the new union.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to have a say in the business,'' he said. ''I thought it was in my best interests to belong. I wanted to have a voice whether they heard me or not.''</p>
        <p>Given his seniority and his outspoken nature, Froemming usually gets attention when he speaks, though not necessarily at home in Milwaukee, where his wife of 47 years, Rose, listens but does not necessarily react.</p>
        <p>''Without her being mother, father, bus driver, Cub Scout leader and everything else, I couldn't have hung in there,'' Froemming said.</p>
        <p>When he works, Froemming has to listen to others, as in managers questioning calls. His crew was the victim of the latest Lou Piniella tantrum, for which Piniella, the Cubs' manager, was suspended.</p>
        <p>''It was silly and it was premeditated,'' Froemming said. ''As a person, I like Lou Piniella, but that was silly and out of line and abusive to the umpire, Mark Wegner.''</p>
        <p>Froemming, however, has not witnessed an on-field incident as wild as one that his call precipitated in his rookie season.</p>
        <p>In the seventh inning of a  game between Philadelphia and Houston on July 19, 1971, Froemming called Tim McCarver of the Phillies for interference as he tried to break up a double play with the bases loaded, turning the play into an inning-ending double play that cost the Phillies a run (they wound up losing by a run).</p>
        <p>''He threw a football block outside the three-foot area,'' Froemming said. ''He has three feet on either side of the bag. He was outside that.''</p>
        <p>The call outraged the Phillies.</p>
        <p>''That was the longest and most vicious argument I was ever in,'' Froemming said. ''It lasted 14 minutes. I had the play right, but I was a rookie and I didn't have the credibility to stop the landslide. The whole team came running from the dugout and the bullpen.''</p>
        <p>At his age and with his seniority, no one will chase Froemming out of baseball, but he will very likely tell Port he is retiring -- at the end of this season.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
