<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Duncan And Jeter: Fundamental Similarity</title>
    <meta content="19araton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7DF133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Duncan And Jeter: Fundamental Similarity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The reporter had a question and, as usual, Derek Jeter gave an answer, if not exactly the one being sought.</p>
        <p>This was before the start of the weekend Subway Series and the reporter, from a New Jersey newspaper, asked Jeter about a letter he had written to the Rutgers women's basketball team -- which was honored at Yankee Stadium on Friday night -- in the wake of the Don Imus debacle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The reporter had a question and, as usual, Derek Jeter gave an answer, if not exactly the one being sought.</p>
        <p>This was before the start of the weekend Subway Series and the reporter, from a New Jersey newspaper, asked Jeter about a letter he had written to the Rutgers women's basketball team -- which was honored at Yankee Stadium on Friday night -- in the wake of the Don Imus debacle.</p>
        <p>Jeter spoke of his admiration for C. Vivian Stringer, the Rutgers coach, and for how her players handled themselves during their nationally televised post-Imus news conference in April. But the contents of the letter were personal, for the Rutgers women and no one else.</p>
        <p>''I mean, they can tell you whatever they want to tell you,'' he said, adding, ''I didn't do it for anyone to cover it.''</p>
        <p>This was classic clubhouse Jeter: accessible but not acquiescent, gracious but guarded. Or perhaps downright boring, by the standards often applied to another minimalist sports personality, Tim Duncan of the San Antonio Spurs, who last week matched Jeter when he earned a fourth championship ring.</p>
        <p>On the subject of Duncan, supposedly the bane of the N.B.A.'s television ratings-challenged existence, Jeter said, incredulously and sarcastically: ''Boring? I'm sure a lot of people would like to be as boring as Tim Duncan.''</p>
        <p>Listening to Jeter steer the subject of his Scarlet Knights letter away from the territory onto which he views most incursions as a social trespass, it occurred to me that Jeter and Duncan are spiritual soul mates, cut from  the same concealed cloth.</p>
        <p>Sure, Duncan toils in small-market San Antonio, in near obscurity relative to Jeter, captain of America's most known and newsworthy sports franchise and a bachelor who has been romantically linked to glamorous celebrities of the all-star, first-team variety.</p>
        <p>But in the 12 seasons since he arrived in the Bronx to make shortstop his showcase, how much of the private Jeter has he allowed the public to see? What really has made him the New York City deity, besides the fundamental excellence and championship character he has demonstrated between the lines?</p>
        <p>It's the same athletic persona and straight-line professionalism that Duncan took to a now-reverent San Antonio in 1998 as a lasting endowment. The same unapologetic, methodical intensity that made Jeter, Mariano Rivera, Paul O'Neill, Scott Brosius &amp; Company much more than the most expensive team George Steinbrenner's money could buy from 1996 to 2001.</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner is still waiting for today's $200 million, and much showier, Yankees to develop the chemistry that will carry through October. In the meantime, Jeter, a basketball fan, knows when he sees it elsewhere. ''You have to respect Duncan because he pretty much does everything,'' he said. ''And you have to respect that team because together they do everything right.''</p>
        <p>Then why is the Spurs' national popularity so anemic compared with other teams that have strung together years of championship valor? Jeter paused for a few seconds before citing a crass sports culture. ''It's probably because it's all about the highlights now, always about who's dunking over who,'' he said. ''Just like baseball, the only thing they want to show is people hitting home runs. But then once you get into the playoffs, you realize that you have to be fundamentally sound in order to win. And that's when people pay more attention to the little things.''</p>
        <p>Just not as many people, it seems, as a decade ago or more.</p>
        <p>There are a multitude of potential explanations for the general shifts in viewing habits, but can it be a coincidence that pro basketball and major league baseball have experienced precipitous declines for their championship events even as they boast of record regular-season attendance? What is it that isn't translating beyond provincial loyalty on a national level anymore?</p>
        <p>The noncompetitive Spurs-Cavaliers series had roughly a third of the viewers Michael Jordan and the Bulls pulled for their swan song in 1998, and the N.B.A. is continuously derided for its shrinking national audience. But guess what? For a St. Louis-Detroit World Series last fall, baseball's ratings were barely in double digits, or less than half of what they annually were as recently as the early 1990s.</p>
        <p>Both sports stand accused of tailoring their games more to the casual fan than to the dedicated one, of foolishly embracing muscle over mind and of conditioning young fans to relate to their games in grandiose but superficial ways. Both were warned long ago about the long-term fallout of alienating viewers east of the Mississippi with late-night championship games.</p>
        <p>N.B.A. Commissioner David Stern loves to point out that technology reaches fans in ways that escape the conventional ratings measure. But do streamed highlights and chat sessions help develop a fondness for nuance, an appreciation for fundamentals and team play, an ability to sustain interest over the long playoff haul?</p>
        <p>Critiquing a sport favorably for achieving a high television rating interests me about as much as praising McDonald's for those billions served. But if the after-hours model is so sacrosanct, why is it that golf's United States Open, an adult-driven, daylight spectacle, is increasingly generating more attention and favorable national news media coverage at the expense of the N.B.A. finals?</p>
        <p>As Jeter said, referring to Duncan and no doubt himself, ''Commercials and sound bites don't define a player or a team.'' Time for the marketing geniuses to wake up to that fact, to realize that boring can only be in the eye of the beholder, not in the eye of those who don't watch because they have no appreciation for the game.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
