<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Staple of the News Media, But Is Rodriguez a YES Man?</title>
    <meta content="19sandomir" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855663"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TV SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02EEDA1731F93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="853" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Staple of the News Media, But Is Rodriguez a YES Man?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Except for a plaque or a retired number in Monument Park at Yankee Stadium, there appears to be no greater confirmation of greatness for a past or present Yankee than to be the subject of a ''Yankeeography'' on the YES Network.</p>
        <p>Even being the august assistant to the traveling secretary, who slept on a shelf under his desk, seems like a hollow honor, as George Costanza learned.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Except for a plaque or a retired number in Monument Park at Yankee Stadium, there appears to be no greater confirmation of greatness for a past or present Yankee than to be the subject of a ''Yankeeography'' on the YES Network.</p>
        <p>Even being the august assistant to the traveling secretary, who slept on a shelf under his desk, seems like a hollow honor, as George Costanza learned.</p>
        <p>Everyone with a retired number, save for Bill Dickey, who wore No. 8 before Yogi Berra did, has been the subject of a ''Yankeeography.'' And among the 20 with plaques, 9 lack an episode in the series, including Dickey, Lefty Gomez, Allie Reynolds and Red Ruffing.</p>
        <p>But the series is not entirely about the old, the dead or the retired.</p>
        <p>Four current players -- Derek Jeter, Mariano Rivera, Jorge Posada and Roger Clemens -- have been featured. Two more, Hideki Matsui and Andy Pettitte, will join them in the YES canon of greats later this season.</p>
        <p>The conspicuous omission is Alex Rodriguez.</p>
        <p>''My rule of thumb is you have to be a Yankee for three years,'' said John Filippelli, the president of production and programming for YES.</p>
        <p>But Rodriguez is in his fourth.</p>
        <p>''We were going to do him this year,'' Filippelli said. ''But based on his un-A-Rodish year last season, I figured I'd wait another season to see if he'd become A-Rod again and have another Hall of Fame year. That's what I'm hoping for. If the stars align, we'll have one next year.''</p>
        <p>Rodriguez's statistics in 2006 (35 homers, 121 runs batted in and a .290 batting average) have been redeemed so far this season. With 27 home runs, 73 R.B.I. and a .315 average, Rodriguez is closer than ever to entering the ''Yankeeography'' pantheon. It would cement his ties to John Sterling, the team's radio voice and the host of the series, who has won 11 local Emmys.</p>
        <p>Sterling's deep connection to Rodriguez and the team is based largely on his nutty, occasionally catchy, somehow memorable home run calls. Sterling follows his standard ''It is high, it is far, it is gone'' -- which is unchanged even for line-drive homers based on his call of Posada's screamer Sunday night -- with ''it's an A-bomb for A-Rod,'' topped off with, ''How A-Rodian!''</p>
        <p>The last portion evoked some hooting in yesterday's morning version of ''Mike and the Mad Dog'' program on WFAN and prompted Charles McCord, Don Imus's erstwhile newsman, to dream of ''A-Rodian tableaux.''</p>
        <p>What about the notion that Rodriguez has been denied his ''Yankeeography'' because he is not a true Yankee? He's not homegrown like Jeter, Rivera, Posada or Pettitte in this generation; a Japanese import like the stoic Matsui; or a sainted Yankee like Babe Ruth, Lou Gehrig, Mickey Mantle, Joe DiMaggio or Don Mattingly. All have ''Yankeeography'' profiles.</p>
        <p>Joe Morgan and Jon Miller touched on the subject of true Yankees during the broadcast of the Mets-Yankees game Sunday night on ESPN. After a replay of Rodriguez's first-inning home run, Morgan said, ''I think Alex is working his way toward being a true Yankee.'' Miller replied, ''You think he's getting close?''</p>
        <p>Close to a ''Yankeeography,'' perhaps?</p>
        <p>Filippelli said he was not judging Rodriguez by what defined a ''true'' Yankee or by his dismal playoff performances the past two Octobers.</p>
        <p>''You look at his April this year and his June, and you see what he can do,'' he said. ''He's had some postseason struggles, but I don't think this season is an aberration. He's a great player. Some great players struggle in the postseason. Look at Gil Hodges.''</p>
        <p>But even a phenomenal season is not a guarantee that a Rodriguez ''Yankeeography'' will join those of Paul O'Neill, Bernie Williams, Sparky Lyle and David Cone on fans' DVD shelves. If he opts out of his contract to join the Angels or the Cubs, a biographical tribute to Rodriguez ''would not fit the motif of the Yankees Entertainment &amp; Sports Network,'' Filippelli said.</p>
        <p>I hope distance will yield a ''Yankeeography'' for Don Zimmer.</p>
        <p>If a Rodriguez ''Yankeeography'' becomes a reality, Filippelli said that no mention would be made of the woman, who was not Rodriguez's wife, who was seen with him recently in photos published in The New York Post. ''You don't have empirical evidence,'' he said. ''You have anecdotal suggestion.''</p>
        <p>YES's roster of dwindling ''Yankeeography'' possibilities includes Robinson Canó, who needs better third-season statistics to join Tino Martinez and Elston Howard in YES's video Acropolis; and Chien-Ming Wang, who is only in his second full season. But an even better choice would be Mel Stottlemyre, a three-time 20-game winner who had a distinguished run as Torre's pitching coach.</p>
        <p>''He's a possibility,'' Filippelli said. ''He'd certainly qualify.''</p>
        <p>One notion at YES that will not change soon is the invincibility of the Yankees in the classic games shown on the network. I thought wrongly that YES had carried the Game 7 loss to Arizona in the 2001 World Series.</p>
        <p>''We're 776 and 0,'' Filippelli said. ''The Yankees never lose on 'Yankee Classics.' But down the road, I might change my mind.''</p>
        <p>TV SPORTS</p>
        <p>E-mail: sportsbiz@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: sportsbiz@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
