<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Handel Instead of Tchaikovsky With the Rockets' Red Glare</title>
    <meta content="19seap" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855618"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW | BROOKLYN PHILHARMONIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE5DE133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="346" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Handel Instead of Tchaikovsky With the Rockets' Red Glare</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES R. OESTREICH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mimi has died, poor thing; cue the fireworks. Though a staple at Central Park concerts by the Metropolitan Opera and the New York Philharmonic, fireworks often sit oddly on a program. How often can the Met  offer the exultant ''Fidelio,'' after all, and how often does it  offer the star-crossed ''Bohème''? And how often can the Philharmonic present  Tchaikovsky's ''1812''?</p>
        <p>So it was a good choice to end the Brooklyn Philharmonic's little concert at the South Street Seaport on Saturday night with Handel's ''Music for the Royal Fireworks'' as accompaniment for a dazzling display of pyrotechnics by the Zambelli family,  set off from barges in the East River. Not that Handel could have anticipated the firepower available to 21st-century revelers. Loudly amplified as it was, the music was no match for the bone-rattling percussion from the sky.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mimi has died, poor thing; cue the fireworks. Though a staple at Central Park concerts by the Metropolitan Opera and the New York Philharmonic, fireworks often sit oddly on a program. How often can the Met  offer the exultant ''Fidelio,'' after all, and how often does it  offer the star-crossed ''Bohème''? And how often can the Philharmonic present  Tchaikovsky's ''1812''?</p>
        <p>So it was a good choice to end the Brooklyn Philharmonic's little concert at the South Street Seaport on Saturday night with Handel's ''Music for the Royal Fireworks'' as accompaniment for a dazzling display of pyrotechnics by the Zambelli family,  set off from barges in the East River. Not that Handel could have anticipated the firepower available to 21st-century revelers. Loudly amplified as it was, the music was no match for the bone-rattling percussion from the sky.</p>
        <p>The climax of Target Children's Day at the seaport, part of the River to River Festival, the fireworks flowed profusely throughout the piece, some 20 minutes' worth. Said to be choreographed to the music, they didn't follow it in any detail, though a change of visual texture generally came with a new movement. Whatever --  it was all a grand spectacle.</p>
        <p>The musical program itself, conducted by George Mathew, drew a large and diverse audience that seemed appreciative despite the typical encumbrances of outdoor performance: intrusive ambient noise countered by shrill and unbalanced amplification.</p>
        <p>The program opened with a few movements from Handel's ''Water Music,'' also appropriate to the setting. And in Mendelssohn's wave-tossed overture ''The Hebrides,'' a mast of the Ambrose lightship, moored at the seaport, could be seen swaying back and forth above the stage canopy, a particularly atmospheric touch.</p>
        <p>What exactly ''The Dance of the Blessed Spirits''  from Gluck's ''Orfeo ed Euridice'' was doing in such hellish acoustical surroundings was not clear, but it afforded the opportunity for a lovely flute solo by David Wechsler. Then the energy picked up, with Romanian dances by Bartok and the overture to Rossini's ''Barber of Seville.'' The ''Fireworks'' -- and fireworks -- did the rest.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW | BROOKLYN PHILHARMONIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
