<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Arrington Injured in a Motorcycle Accident</title>
    <meta content="19nfl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/sports/football/19nfl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855611"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="N.F.L. ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Arrington, LaVar</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE6DE133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="741" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Arrington Injured in a Motorcycle Accident</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Arrington Injured in a Motorcycle Accident</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The former Giants and Washington Redskins linebacker LaVar Arrington was hospitalized yesterday with multiple injuries after crashing his motorcycle. His agent, Carl Poston, said Arrington sustained a broken arm, at least one broken rib and a leg contusion.</p>
        <p>''He's banged up but lucky to be alive,'' Poston said in a telephone interview, adding that Arrington might have also had internal bleeding. ''He was in surgery, but I'm not certain which injury the surgery was for,'' Poston said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The former Giants and Washington Redskins linebacker LaVar Arrington was hospitalized Monday with multiple injuries after crashing his motorcycle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The former Giants and Washington Redskins linebacker LaVar Arrington was hospitalized yesterday with multiple injuries after crashing his motorcycle. His agent, Carl Poston, said Arrington sustained a broken arm, at least one broken rib and a leg contusion.</p>
        <p>''He's banged up but lucky to be alive,'' Poston said in a telephone interview, adding that Arrington might have also had internal bleeding. ''He was in surgery, but I'm not certain which injury the surgery was for,'' Poston said.</p>
        <p>Arrington, who turns 29 tomorrow, was taken to Prince George's Hospital Center in Cheverly, Md.</p>
        <p>Sgt. Russell Newell of the Maryland state police said the accident occurred shortly after 10 a.m. in Glenarden, Md., where Arrington crashed into a guardrail after losing control of his 2007 Kawasaki ZX-14 motorcycle on a highway exit ramp. The police said they did not consider alcohol to be a contributing factor, and it was not immediately known how fast Arrington was traveling. No other vehicles were involved.</p>
        <p>Arrington was wearing a helmet and had a valid Maryland driver's license, but he did not have a motorcycle license, the police said. He was issued a citation for driving without a proper class license and one for failure to control speed to avoid a collision. Asked how long Arrington had been riding a motorcycle, Poston said, ''I didn't even know he had a motorcycle.''</p>
        <p>Once one of the N.F.L.'s best pass-rushing linebackers, Arrington signed as a free agent with the Giants before last season. He played in only six games before a torn Achilles' tendon ended his season. The Giants released Arrington in February.</p>
        <p>Poston said Arrington had been rehabilitating and planned to test the free-agent market this summer.</p>
        <p>''Anybody would be interested in a healthy LaVar Arrington,''  Poston said. ''I think his rehabilitation was coming along pretty well. Right now, of course, the Achilles' is the least of his worries.''</p>
        <p>The Redskins drafted Arrington with the No. 2 overall pick in 2000. He made three Pro Bowls during his six seasons in Washington. But after Joe Gibbs began his second tenure as the Redskins' coach in 2004, Arrington clashed with the defensive coordinator, Gregg Williams, and sustained a knee injury that required two operations.</p>
        <p>JONES SOUGHT FOR QUESTIONING The suspended Tennessee Titans cornerback Pacman Jones was being sought by the police for questioning about a shooting early yesterday involving members of his entourage after a fight at an Atlanta strip club.</p>
        <p>Jones and his group are suspected of fighting with three men, apparently over a woman, at a club  about 4 a.m., the officer Ariel Toledo said.</p>
        <p>After everyone involved left the strip club -- the three people in one car, and Jones and his entourage in three other cars -- someone in Jones's group is suspected of shooting several times into the car at a red light, the police said.</p>
        <p>Toledo said that Jones, who was suspended by the  N.F.L. after a melee and shooting at a Las Vegas strip club, was not present when the shots were fired and that no charges had been filed against him.(AP)</p>
        <p>ANOTHER BENGAL IS ARRESTED Running back Quincy Wilson was charged with disorderly conduct for failing to disperse after a weekend wedding party, making him the 10th Cincinnati Bengals player arrested in the last 14 months. Wilson was celebrating outside a  bar in downtown Huntington, W.Va., at about 3 a.m., when he and 13 others refused a police request to leave, the assistant prosecuting attorney Lora Maynard said yesterday.(AP)</p>
        <p>FORMER STEELER HEADED TO COURT A 19-year-old woman testified yesterday in Las Vegas that the former Pittsburgh Steelers reserve linebacker Richard Seigler spent several months last year persuading her to become a prostitute, and took the first $450 she earned.  Seigler, 26, was ordered to stand  trial July 10 on felony charges of pandering, providing transportation for a prostitute and living from the earnings of a prostitute. Seigler's lawyer, Stephen Stein, called it ''absurd'' that an N.F.L. player earning $450,000 a year would work as a pimp or live off the earnings of a prostitute.(AP)</p>
        <p>A.F.L. ALL-STAR DIES Jim Norton, a four-time American Football League All-Star safety and an original member of the Houston Oilers, died June 12 in Garland, Tex., according to an obituary released by the Gonzalez Funeral Home. He was 68. The cause of death was not given.</p>
        <p>Norton, who retired in 1969 after nine seasons with the Oilers, is the franchise leader with 45 interceptions.(AP)</p>
        <p>N.F.L. ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
