<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Across the Borders, Across the Years</title>
    <meta content="l19immig" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855635"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amnesties and Pardons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E3DE133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="468" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Across the Borders, Across the Years</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''The Scarlet Letter'' (editorial, June 16):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''The Scarlet Letter'' (editorial, June 16):</p>
        <p>The biggest problem with ''illegal immigration'' is the process. When my grandparents came to this country, they were running away from oppression. They didn't care to file the proper paperwork to enter the country. But we had Ellis Island to process their admission.</p>
        <p>What we need today is a way to process immigrants as they arrive so that they aren't ''illegal.'' But for Ellis Island, I am sure that I would be the grandson of illegals.</p>
        <p>Hal Cohen</p>
        <p>New York, June 16, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Why do so many people who preach forgiveness in church fail to find it in their hearts to forgive illegal immigrants for trespasses undertaken out of a desperate need to work and survive? Why can't we stop calling them illegal immigrants and refer to them simply as neighbors?</p>
        <p>Why turn the word ''amnesty'' into something obscene instead of what it is, a sign of decency and compassion?</p>
        <p>Carolyn D. Lewis</p>
        <p>Ocean View, Del., June 17, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Hey, France, would you mind terribly if we gave back the Statue of Liberty?</p>
        <p>We're shutting the doors to liberty-loving people here and everywhere else, so the statue no longer holds much meaning for our country. Please take it back, it's an embarrassment for the United States right now.</p>
        <p>Barry Naiditch</p>
        <p>El Cajon, Calif., June 17, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>You are so out of touch with the common people regarding this immigration matter. You attribute the heated atmosphere solely to  conservative mongering, but that is not true. The common people in America have been hearing about the virtues of multiculturalism, diversity and globalism since the 1960s. Now they see their culture, opportunities and their America disappearing.</p>
        <p>You are witnessing a pot beginning to boil. The common people are confused and angry in a very visceral sort of way, rivaling the frustration and rage of earlier eras in American history. Media and academic elites, you people with secure careers, full benefits and cavalier social ideals, simply infuriate them.</p>
        <p>Duane Pierson</p>
        <p>Portland, Me., June 16, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>It's well past time that the intense, unwarranted fear of leprosy be relegated to a dark footnote of human history (''When Demagogues Play the Leprosy Card, Watch Out,'' by Lawrence Downes, Editorial Observer, June 17).</p>
        <p>In our era of rapidly emerging infectious diseases, it would be far preferable to apply the lessons leprosy provides than to repeat a shameful instinct to isolate those unlucky enough to contract a contagious disease.</p>
        <p>Public fear should never be allowed to trump scientific knowledge, especially when that fear runs the risk of destroying the lives of human beings most in need of medical attention and public compassion.</p>
        <p>Paul Mange Johansen</p>
        <p>Cambridge, Mass., June 17, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
