<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Midst of Slump, the Orioles Fire Perlozzo</title>
    <meta content="19base" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855525"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MAJOR LEAGUE ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Baltimore Orioles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E5DF133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Midst of Slump, the Orioles Fire Perlozzo</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THE ASSOCIATED PRESS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sam Perlozzo was fired as Baltimore's manager yesterday, the result of his inability to bring the last-place Orioles out of a lengthy slump that culminated in an eight-game losing streak. He was the first major league manager to be fired this year.</p>
        <p>The bullpen coach Dave Trembley will be the interim manager when the Orioles begin a six-game trip in San Diego today. One of the leading candidates to fill the position on a full-time basis is Joe Girardi, voted the National League manager of the year in 2006 before being fired after a dispute with the ownership of the Florida Marlins.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sam Perlozzo was fired as Baltimore's manager yesterday, the result of his inability to bring the last-place Orioles out of a lengthy slump that culminated in an eight-game losing streak. He was the first major league manager to be fired this year.</p>
        <p>The bullpen coach Dave Trembley will be the interim manager when the Orioles begin a six-game trip in San Diego today. One of the leading candidates to fill the position on a full-time basis is Joe Girardi, voted the National League manager of the year in 2006 before being fired after a dispute with the ownership of the Florida Marlins.</p>
        <p>Perlozzo was hurt by an underachieving bullpen and an unproductive offense that ranks last in the American League in home runs. Baltimore was 27-27 and second in the A.L. East on May 31 before losing 13 of 15 in June, including the last eight games of a 1-8 homestand that ended Sunday. The Orioles' 29-40 record is the fifth worst in the major leagues.</p>
        <p>''We felt Sam was prepared, we felt the club was prepared to do battle every night,'' the team's  executive vice president, Mike Flanagan, said in a news conference. ''For whatever reason, it just wasn't working.''</p>
        <p>The Orioles are also negotiating with the former Chicago Cubs president Andy MacPhail about becoming their chief operating officer, a job left vacant since Joe Foss resigned earlier this year.</p>
        <p>BRAVES 9, RED SOX 4 Brian McCann homered and drove in four runs against Curt Schilling, who endured his first strikeout-free start since 1993, as Atlanta beat visiting Boston.</p>
        <p>Schilling gave up 10 hits and 6 runs in four and a third innings, his second-shortest outing of the season.</p>
        <p>BREWERS 5, GIANTS 4 Prince Fielder hit his National League-leading 26th home run, pitcher Yovani Gallardo was dazzling in his major league debut and Milwaukee beat struggling San Francisco  at home.</p>
        <p>INDIANS 10, PHILLIES 1 Cliff Lee improved to 10-1 in interleague play and Kelly Shoppach hit a three-run homer against Cole Hamels as Cleveland won in a rout at home.</p>
        <p>Lee (4-4) won for  the second time in six starts, allowing one run and five hits in seven innings  --  his longest start since May 8. TIGERS 9, NATIONALS 8 Carlos Guillén and Marcus Thames homered, and Detroit scored six times in the fifth and held on to win at Washington. The Tigers had to withstand a three-run ninth-inning rally against Todd Jones, who got Ronnie Belliard to ground out to short with runners at first and third for the final out.</p>
        <p>WHITE SOX 10, MARLINS 6 Jim Thome hit his major league-leading 53rd career interleague home run, a three-run shot, and struggling Chicago matched its season high for runs in winning at home. ROYALS 5, CARDINALS 3 Odalis Pérez won for  the second time in 10 starts and Kansas City took advantage of two errors by St. Louis  starting pitcher Adam Wainwright to win the first game of a 10-game  trip.</p>
        <p>ATHLETICS 6, REDS 1 Mark Ellis hit a three-run homer to help host Oakland improve to 7-0 against Cincinnati in regular-season games.</p>
        <p>SUSPENSIONS FOR WRIGLEY BRAWL Chicago Cubs first baseman Derrek Lee and San Diego pitcher Chris Young were suspended for five games each for starting a bench-clearing brawl last Saturday at Wrigley Field. The Cubs' hitting coach, Gerald Perry, was suspended for three games for his role. Both players  were also fined, as were San Diego's Brian Giles and Jake Peavy.</p>
        <p>HITTING STREAK SNAPPED Brandon Watson's International League-record hitting streak was snapped at 43 games after he went 0 for 5 with three strikeouts in Columbus's 6-0 victory at Rochester.</p>
        <p>AROUND THE MAJORS The Phillies' third-base coach, Steve Smith, was suspended for three games and catcher Carlos Ruiz for one after arguing with an umpire in a game against Detroit on Sunday. ...  Dodgers pitcher Jason Schmidt, who missed 45 games with bursitis in his right shoulder, is going back on the disabled list with the same problem.</p>
        <p>MAJOR LEAGUE ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
