<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Power Of Memory To Triumph Over Death</title>
    <meta content="19seco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/theater/reviews/19seco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855638"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW | 'EURYDICE'"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Isherwood, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ruhl, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waters, Les</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dizzia, Maria</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robinson, Charles Shaw</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Parks, Joseph</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Eurydice (Play)&gt;</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Eurydice (Play)&gt;</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Eurydice (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Second Stage Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ruhl, Sarah</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Waters, Les</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bradley, Scott</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Eurydice (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE3DE133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1201" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Power Of Memory To Triumph Over Death</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Power of Memory to Triumph Over Death</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES ISHERWOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Isherwood, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Isherwood reviews Sarah Ruhl play Eurydice, directed by Les Waters; Maria Dizzia, Charles Shaw Robinson and Joseph Parks star; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The most famous unheeded advice in the history of Western literature may be the admonition given by the ruler of the underworld to Orpheus, when that grieving youth went down to retrieve his wife, Eurydice, from the depths, and the lovers began their journey back upward.</p>
        <p>It was something along these lines: ''Hey, fella, remember: Don't look back.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sarah Ruhl’s tenderhearted comedy opened at the Second Stage Theater in a rhapsodically beautiful production.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The most famous unheeded advice in the history of Western literature may be the admonition given by the ruler of the underworld to Orpheus, when that grieving youth went down to retrieve his wife, Eurydice, from the depths, and the lovers began their journey back upward.</p>
        <p>It was something along these lines: ''Hey, fella, remember: Don't look back.''</p>
        <p>Spoiler alert! He did.</p>
        <p>From this woeful act of disobedience a whole universe of art has been spun over the last couple of millenniums, poems and operas and ballets in the double digits by now, even a classic movie or two. No doubt somewhere on YouTube, a Greek-myth-loving geek with a Webcam has done a two-minute goof on the tale.</p>
        <p>In her weird and wonderful new play, ''Eurydice,'' the gifted young writer Sarah Ruhl has adapted this mournful legend with a fresh eye, concentrating not on the passionate pilgrimage of Orpheus to retrieve his bride but on Eurydice's descent into the jaws of death. What she finds there, and what she learns about love, loss  and the pleasures and pains of memory, is the subject of Ms. Ruhl's tender-hearted comedy, which opened last night at the Second Stage Theater in a rhapsodically beautiful production directed by Les Waters.</p>
        <p>I suspect that ''Eurydice'' will get under your skin either in all the right ways or all the wrong ones. I first saw the play, in this production, at Yale Repertory Theater last fall, and its hallucinatory imagery and emotional allure have remained with me. Encountering it again, I staggered out of the theater in the same state of sad-happy disorientation that I recall from my initial viewing.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ruhl's theatrical vision is an idiosyncratic one. She is not a journalist of domestic life, as so many playwrights today seem to be, but an adventurer who is not afraid to blend the quotidian and the fantastic, deep feeling and airy whimsy. The plot of Ms. Ruhl's surreal comedy ''The Clean House,'' seen at Lincoln Center Theater earlier this year, sometimes turned on jokes told in Portuguese that were left untranslated. Likewise, much in ''Eurydice'' could mystify theatergoers used to reclining on the comforting cushions of linear narrative and naturalistic dialogue.</p>
        <p>The fabled creatures of ''Eurydice'' may look like people you've seen on the subway, but they speak in images plucked from the blue sky of their mythic imaginations. You might almost wish there were subtitles here, alerting you to the inner meaning of the lyrical, illogical and, yes, sometimes overly quirky dialogue. (The most sensibly spoken characters onstage are probably the blunt-spoken chorus of stones, strange creatures with pea-green faces, in Victorian garb, who keep telling Eurydice to shut up and get used to being dead.)</p>
        <p>But to be moved by ''Eurydice,'' you just need to tune in to the play's insistent heartbeat, the rhythmic threnody woven by its language, its subterranean feeling and its strangely potent imagery. Ms. Ruhl sees her plays as much as she hears them  -- a rare gift among playwrights  -- and some of the most striking moments in the play are wordless ones.</p>
        <p>Take, for instance, the tender, wrenchingly sad vision of Eurydice's dead father, who can watch his daughter's progress from the underworld below, miming the act of walking  her down the aisle on her wedding day. He nods proudly at the guests on either side, gives her an encouraging smile, offers her up with a mixture of resignation and worry and joy. And he is utterly alone. As performed with impeccable simplicity and grace by Charles Shaw Robinson, this small vignette is among the most desolate and moving moments I can remember seeing on a stage.</p>
        <p>Eurydice, played with radiant open-heartedness by Maria Dizzia, falls to her death just after marrying Orpheus. She descends in an elevator to the underworld, but her reunion with her father is bittersweet. The dead are dipped in the waters of forgetfulness, and Eurydice has lost all that she once knew, her husband's name, much of her own history, language itself. She takes Dad for a hotel porter.</p>
        <p>The helpful stones, played with pop-eyed intensity by Gian-Murray Gianino, Carla Harting and Ramiz Monsef, insistently bray at Eurydice that death is much easier if you take refuge in the easy solace of forgetting. (Life is that way, too, of course.)</p>
        <p>But ''Eurydice'' movingly suggests that commemorating life, its pleasures and problems, its transience and pain, is the only way to triumph over death and loss. Eurydice's father helps restore her memory, anecdote by anecdote, and her vocabulary, word by word, rebuilding the universe of the world they have lost in the prison of death.</p>
        <p>At one point he reads to her from ''King Lear'': ''We two alone will sing like birds in the cage.'' ''Eurydice'' is on one level an ode to the sustaining power of the love between father and daughter. (Ms. Ruhl wrote it after the death of her father.) It considers, too, how hard it is for two human beings to achieve the harmony of perfect romantic love.</p>
        <p>Orpheus, played with a fine, fierce ardor by Joseph Parks, is, of course, a composer; Eurydice hears music mostly in words. When he descends to fetch her back, Eurydice faces a painful choice: to re-enter the world above, where imperfect human love and the potential for pain awaits, or remain below where she is beyond its reach? Either choice involves risk and loss.</p>
        <p>Mr. Waters and his design collaborators have framed Ms. Ruhl's play with uncommon sensitivity and stylistic sympathy. (In a less felicitous production, I can imagine the play cloying into preciousness.) Scott Bradley's tilted vision of the underworld as a slightly dilapidated spa, wallpapered in letters written from the dead to the living, perfectly matches the writing's off-kilter tone. The shimmery, dank lighting by Russell H. Champa  echoes the quicksilver changes in tenor.</p>
        <p>And the selection of music likewise parallels the emotional currents without overwhelming the breezy playfulness of the dialogue. (Arvo Pärt's haunting ''Spiegel im Spiegel,'' for piano and violin, is used to particularly fine effect.)</p>
        <p>''What happiness it would be to cry,'' Eurydice says when she enters the underworld and discovers that she's lost her grasp on emotional response,  along with her memory. Perhaps more than anything else, the eerie wonderland of ''Eurydice'' evokes the discombobulating experience of grief and loss, the desperate need to move on and the overwhelming desire never to let go  -- to turn and look back just one more time.</p>
        <p>EURYDICE</p>
        <p>By Sarah Ruhl; directed by Les Waters; sets by Scott Bradley; costumes by Meg Neville; lighting by Russell H. Champa; sound by Bray Poor; production stage manager, Michael Suenkel; stage manager, Stephanie Gatton; associate artistic director, Christopher Burney; production manager, Jeff Wild. Presented by Second Stage Theater, Carole Rothman, artistic director; Ellen Richard, executive director; in association with Berkeley Repertory Theater and Yale Repertory Theater. At Second Stage Theater, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton; (212) 246-4422. Through July 21. Running time: 1 hour 30 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Maria Dizzia (Eurydice), Gian-Murray Gianino (Loud Stone), Carla Harting (Little Stone), Ramiz Monsef (Big Stone), Joseph Parks (Orpheus), Charles Shaw Robinson (Father) and Mark Zeisler (The Nasty and Interesting Man/Lord of the Underworld).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW | 'EURYDICE'</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
