<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Desperation Rises at Closed Border Crossings Between Gaza Strip and Israel</title>
    <meta content="19mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/19/world/middleeast/19mideast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1855608"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza Strip</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hamas</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fatah</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Ian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershner, Isabel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Gaza Strip</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6DE133FF93AA25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="923" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Desperation Rises at Closed Border Crossings Between Gaza Strip and Israel</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Desperation Rises at Closed Border Crossings Between Gaza Strip and Israel</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN FISHER and ISABEL KERSHNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershner, Isabel; Fisher, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, June 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Palestinian man is killed at volatile and closed border between Israel and Gaza after Palestinian gunmen open fire on Israeli soldiers; incident highlights growing problem at border crossings between Israel and Gaza, closed since Hamas defeated rival Fatah in Gaza after five days of fighting; several hundred Fatah supporters camped out at crossing say they fear for their lives unless they are allowed to escape through Israel to West Bank; Israel says it will not allow crossing by group; Gaza has been cut off for four days, with Israel refusing even low level of coordinating trucks through checkpoints; Israeli official says Israel will not work with terrorist organization that seeks to destroy Israel; other officials say they are trying to find way to prevent humanitarian crisis without dealing with Hamas; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Palestinian man was killed Monday at the volatile and closed border between Israel and Gaza after Palestinian gunmen opened fire on Israeli soldiers, officials said. The attack took place near the area where several hundred people trying to flee Gaza had been camped out and Israeli troops fired back.</p>
        <p>Hospital officials said that Jihad Madhoun, 35, had died and that five other people had been wounded. A spokeswoman for the Israeli Army said its soldiers responded to shooting from across the Erez checkpoint amid a flurry of gunfire that pinned down bystanders and reporters on the Israeli side. The spokeswoman said the army had not confirmed hitting anyone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Several hundred people, most of them Fatah supporters, have been camped out at the closed border between Israel and Gaza, saying they fear for their lives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Palestinian man was killed Monday at the volatile and closed border between Israel and Gaza after Palestinian gunmen opened fire on Israeli soldiers, officials said. The attack took place near the area where several hundred people trying to flee Gaza had been camped out and Israeli troops fired back.</p>
        <p>Hospital officials said that Jihad Madhoun, 35, had died and that five other people had been wounded. A spokeswoman for the Israeli Army said its soldiers responded to shooting from across the Erez checkpoint amid a flurry of gunfire that pinned down bystanders and reporters on the Israeli side. The spokeswoman said the army had not confirmed hitting anyone.</p>
        <p>''If there were injuries, it was not necessarily because of our fire,'' the spokeswoman said.</p>
        <p>The incident highlighted the growing problem at the border crossings between Israel and Gaza, closed since the Islamic group Hamas defeated its rival, Fatah, in Gaza after five days of fighting last week.</p>
        <p>Several hundred people, most of them Fatah supporters, have been camped out at Erez, saying they fear for their lives unless they are allowed to escape through Israel to the West Bank. The dead man was a close relative of Samih Madhoun, a senior Fatah leader executed by Hamas militants last week, though it was unclear whether he and the wounded people were among those camped out.</p>
        <p>Israel, which closed the checkpoint on Thursday, has said it will not allow a crossing by the group, which includes some women and children.</p>
        <p>More broadly, Gaza has been cut off for four days now. While aid officials say the situation is not yet dire, Israel will not deal with Hamas,  even at the low level of coordinating trucks through checkpoints.</p>
        <p>''Hamas is a terrorist organization,'' said Shlomo Dror, a spokesman for the Coordinator of Activities in the Territories, the Israeli government agency that deals with the Palestinian areas. ''They can't say on the one hand that they want to destroy Israel, and on the other  'we need your help.' We won't help Hamas. From our point of view, let them fail.''</p>
        <p>Some officials said, though, that they were trying to find a way to prevent a humanitarian crisis without dealing with Hamas. ''We have no interest in creating hardship -- that would play into Hamas's hands,'' said Mark Regev, a spokesman for the Foreign Ministry. ''We want to ensure a flow into Gaza of humanitarian support and we are currently looking for solutions. We will have to be creative.''</p>
        <p>Israel has periodically closed the borders to put pressure on Palestinians, but in the past, the Israelis were willing to talk to members of the Fatah party in the Palestinian government to coordinate the traffic of food, commerce and relief supplies.</p>
        <p>Now, independent aid agencies say, the situation is different, though Israel has allowed  shipments of medical supplies and there have been some inconclusive talks with aid groups. With Gaza almost wholly dependent on the outside world for food, and with 1.1 million of its 1.5 million people receiving some sort of food assistance, the clock is ticking toward crisis.</p>
        <p>Fresh foods like milk and meat are running out, and prices on items like flour are rising, aid officials said Monday. Hospitals are reporting supplies,  despite new shipments.</p>
        <p>Human rights advocates say  Israel will have to find some new way of letting assistance and supplies in. ''Israel is going to have to rethink its treatment of Hamas,'' said Sari Bashi, director of Gisha, an Israeli human rights group. ''You can't provide for the needs of the civilian population of Gaza without talking to someone in power.''</p>
        <p>Aid officials say privately that several ideas have been floated, including asking the United Nations or an aid group to coordinate cross-border traffic on the Gaza side. As long as the solution does not involve dealing with Hamas, Israeli officials say they are willing to consider anything.</p>
        <p>The immediate problem, Israeli and aid officials agree, is a breakdown of the Palestinian side of the border: Most of the regular border guards have fled, the offices and terminals looted after Hamas overran Fatah and its militiamen ransacked Fatah-controlled installations.</p>
        <p>For the moment, Kevin Kennedy, relief coordinator for the United Nations Office of the Humanitarian Coordinator for Palestinian areas, said the United Nations had stockpiled enough food to last six weeks for people now getting aid. But, he said, that amount assumes that regular supplies from the outside  and that those supplies would dwindle more quickly if the borders were not reopened and more people needed their help.</p>
        <p>Kirstie Campbell, of the United Nations World Food Program, said the aim was to head off a crisis before it happened: Now, she said, bakers have between five and six days of flour left to make bread, and bread shortages are likely to cause yet more instability in an already uncertain atmosphere.</p>
        <p>''It's a main staple of the Palestinian diet, so when there is no bread available at the bakeries, people start to panic,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Israel has been letting a small number of people into Gaza: on Monday they included a Palestinian man released from an Israeli jail; a woman who had been treated in a hospital in Tel Aviv; and Nahim Alian, who arrived at Erez and rested on the customs counter a package wrapped in blue plastic. It contained the body of his son, Mahmoud, just a few months old, who had died in an Israeli hospital. He was going  home to bury him.</p>
        <p>Taghreed El-Khodary contributed reporting from Gaza.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Taghreed El-Khodary contributed reporting from Gaza.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
