<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Spot as Appealing As Its Namesake</title>
    <meta content="10dinenjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/10dinenj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853571"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/JERSEY CITY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Light Horse Tavern (Jersey City, NJ)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corcoran, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803EFDE1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="880" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Spot as Appealing As Its Namesake</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Spot as Appealing as Its Namesake</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CORCORAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Corcoran, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Corcoran reviews Light Horse Tavern in Jersey City, NJ; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF your grasp of the American Revolution is as shaky as mine, Light Horse Harry Lee is just a dashing name. But he was a genuine hero, and a local one at that.</p>
        <p>On Aug. 19, 1779, after an 11-day march, the 23-year-old Maj. Henry Lee III arrived with 300 exhausted, mosquito-bitten Continental soldiers at the British fort at Paulus Hook, in what is now Jersey City. With stealth and bayonets, they managed to seize 158 prisoners. And while the British didn't surrender the fort, their morale was battered and their plans for dominion over that strategic stretch of the Hudson River had to be set aside.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The main dishes at Light Horse Tavern in Jersey City have a brawny, foursquare quality, with a bit of refinement around the edges.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF your grasp of the American Revolution is as shaky as mine, Light Horse Harry Lee is just a dashing name. But he was a genuine hero, and a local one at that.</p>
        <p>On Aug. 19, 1779, after an 11-day march, the 23-year-old Maj. Henry Lee III arrived with 300 exhausted, mosquito-bitten Continental soldiers at the British fort at Paulus Hook, in what is now Jersey City. With stealth and bayonets, they managed to seize 158 prisoners. And while the British didn't surrender the fort, their morale was battered and their plans for dominion over that strategic stretch of the Hudson River had to be set aside.</p>
        <p>The Light Horse Tavern occupies a manicured corner of the city's Paulus Hook section, on the street grid laid down over the old fort. Its owners, Bill Gray and Ron Smith, are brothers-in-law who became local history buffs in the course of restoring two adjoining 1850s brownstones that held a grimy, rundown gin mill. When they unearthed the legend of Light Horse Harry, they instantly named him their patron saint.</p>
        <p>The restoration is a thing of wonder, with oak-plank floors, pressed-tin ceilings, soaring windows, iron scrollwork, a long, mirrored mahogany bar and a portrait of Light Horse Harry himself. And while the two-story main room is a locus of noisy, after-hours urban energy, the best place to eat is a more intimate balcony that overlooks the action; a third dining area, in a room behind the bar, is quieter but almost too subdued.</p>
        <p>Light Horse opened in 2002, but the kitchen really took off two years ago, when the owners hired Ian Topper-Kapitan away from the cozy, eclectic Marco &amp; Pepe, in the City Hall neighborhood. Mr. Topper-Kapitan, 36, is working on a much bigger canvas here, and his menu is more crowd-pleasingly mainstream. Still, while cooking for 100 people at a time, he manages to turn out dishes as accomplished as he once did for a few dozen.</p>
        <p>Appetizers as diverse as ceviche, minestrone, beet salad and salmon spring rolls each held a satisfying depth of taste and texture. The ceviche, with squid rings, steamed mussels and chunks of cod and halibut, was bracingly fresh, the seafood flavors lifted but not overpowered by yuzu marinade. Minestrone was stout and filling, with a hot-smoky note of chorizo. The beet salad had a lovely lemon-peel vinaigrette, and the spring rolls balanced the crunch of wrappers and julienned vegetables with the unctuous texture of cured salmon. A $29 raw-bar platter was unimpeachably fresh and well handled.</p>
        <p>Main dishes have a brawny, foursquare quality, with a bit of refinement around the edges. A thick cut of pan-roasted salmon came atop beluga lentils that had a pleasing hint of smoke. Pan-roasted striped bass was moist and nutty, with chunks of earthy roasted potatoes.</p>
        <p>A juicy, ample Berkshire pork chop was buried under a fragrant mound of sautéed fennel and leeks. The short rib, braised for six hours in a deep, fruity red-wine sauce, needed no knife to cut it. Crayfish ravioli was actually a pasta sandwich: two five-inch disks of tender pasta filled with chopped crayfish and topped with mushrooms, tomatoes and goat cheese.</p>
        <p>In a tribute to the proletarian food that was doubtless dished up here when the tavern's predecessor served three shifts of workers a day from the shipyards and the Colgate plant on the waterfront, there's meatloaf and a crisp, greaseless version of fish and chips.</p>
        <p>That earlier tavern probably didn't have a pastry chef. Light Horse does -- his name is Marco Runanin -- and he turns out a line of comfort-food desserts, including a lovely warm apple charlotte; a dense, dark, berry-scented chocolate fondant; a generous, well-balanced cheese plate; and sorbets in flavors like lemon-lime and cassis.</p>
        <p>There's also a wine steward, Roland Arnold, who has gotten his hands on some excellent, unfamiliar bargain-priced bottles, like the Jibe, a New Zealand pinot noir whose flavor opened in the glass until it reminded me of that chocolate fondant. It's a wine that sneaks up and takes you by storm -- as Light Horse Harry Lee did to the British, and as his namesake tavern has done to Jersey City.</p>
        <p>Light Horse Tavern  199 Washington Street  Jersey City  (201) 946-2028  www.lighthorsetavern.com</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE A spacious, lovingly restored corner building. Wheelchair access to the main level via a side entrance.  THE CROWD Young, hip and affluent, in smart-casual dress.  THE STAFF Companionable and well informed.  THE BAR Long and lively, a scene all its own. Extensive, well-chosen wine and beer lists.  THE BILL Lunch entrees, $10 to $19 (brunch, $10 to $14). Dinner entrees, $10 to $35. All major credit cards.  WHAT WE LIKE Raw-bar platter, ceviche, beet salad, minestrone, salmon spring rolls, roasted-tomato salad, short ribs, pork chop, striped bass, shrimp with gnocchi, salmon, apple charlotte, chocolate bread pudding, chocolate fondant, cheese platter, sorbets.  IF YOU GO Open daily. Lunch: Monday to Saturday, 11:30 a.m. to 3:30 p.m. Dinner: Sunday to Thursday, 5 to 10 p.m.; Friday and Saturday, 5 to 11 p.m. Brunch: Saturday and Sunday, 10:30 a.m. to 3 p.m. On-street parking is very limited; the garage at 33 Hudson Street offers free parking with validation from the restaurant.  Reviewed June 10, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/JERSEY CITY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
