<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For the Best Views of This Performance, Stake Out a Sidewalk Spot</title>
    <meta content="10dance" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="40" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/10dance.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853354"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Cuba</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Ailey, Alvin, American Dance Theater</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E3D9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="648" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For the Best Views of This Performance, Stake Out a Sidewalk Spot</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For the Best Views of This Performance, Stake Out a Sidewalk Spot</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The curtain rises just before 6:30 p.m. But the audience takes its time showing up.</p>
        <p>On Friday night, inside Room 1-C of the Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater building, 19 dance students shimmied, shook, stomped and twirled to drums and an insistent whistle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater holds classes for the public in ballet, hip-hop and other dance forms, including Afro-Cuban.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The curtain rises just before 6:30 p.m. But the audience takes its time showing up.</p>
        <p>On Friday night, inside Room 1-C of the Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater building, 19 dance students shimmied, shook, stomped and twirled to drums and an insistent whistle.</p>
        <p>On the other side of Room 1-C's floor-to-ceiling windows, a woman took a picture with her cellphone. A wide-eyed toddler fogged the glass. And a horse-drawn carriage was stopped at a green light so its driver could squint for a better look.</p>
        <p>Every weeknight, Alvin Ailey holds classes for the general public in ballet, hip-hop, Middle Eastern dance and other dance forms, including, on Friday, Afro-Cuban, the swaying dance and ecstatic music of the plantation workers of Cuba. It is an eye-catching performance at the corner of Ninth Avenue and 55th Street, and passers-by -- sometimes one, sometimes 30 -- take in the free show.</p>
        <p>For the Ailey theater, directed by Judith Jamison and founded in 1958 by the choreographer Alvin Ailey and a band of African-American dancers, it is a canny form of marketing, both for its professional performances and its adult education classes. The theater even built a roomy bench outside 1-C for spectators. (Rehearsals for the Ailey professional company are closed to the public.)</p>
        <p>For the sidewalk-arts fan, it is the sweetest form of New York theater, polished yet spontaneous, top-notch yet accessible, a kind of amateur Lincoln Center.</p>
        <p>Carol Matthews, who owns a bakery in Columbus, Ohio, sat Friday night on the bench, eating and watching the class.</p>
        <p>''I've got my cheese pizza, $2, and I have my show,'' Ms. Matthews said over the roar of Ninth Avenue traffic and the muffled bass of bongo drums behind the glass. ''It's very entertaining and very rejuvenating.''</p>
        <p>Cees and Daisy van de Kreeke of the Netherlands, visiting New York on their honeymoon, held hands as they watched the class.</p>
        <p>''You have to have guts to do this in front of all these people,'' Mrs. van de Kreeke said.</p>
        <p>Another spectator, Vickie Sanchez, 19, an archaeology student at City University of New York, said, ''I just had to look.''</p>
        <p>The class is taught by Danis Perez Prades, who was a respected dancer and instructor in Cuba. Known as ''La Mora,'' or ''the Moor,'' Spanish slang for dark-skinned blacks, Ms. Perez is an expert in Afro-Cuban and Afro-Haitian dance.</p>
        <p>Her husband, Francisco Mora, 59, a jazz musician, accompanies her on the bongo drums and cowbell. He also acts as Ms. Perez's interpreter.</p>
        <p>''The open window is stimulating for the students and a promotion for the class,'' Ms. Perez said. ''Nothing is better than a big window and a big audience.''</p>
        <p>The class of mostly women (only three men were in Friday's session) has ''high talent and good spirits,'' Ms. Perez said. Three-quarters of the students are strong intermediates or advanced, she said.</p>
        <p>The skill showed even in the warm-up exercises. As the class slowly advanced, barefoot, flapping their arms like geese in slow-motion migration, they were synchronized with one another and seemingly with the traffic as it flowed south on Ninth Avenue.</p>
        <p>About a half dozen people stopped and stared.</p>
        <p>By 7:15 p.m., halfway through the class, there was a visitors-at-the-zoo feeling, as nearly all the space on the sidewalk and the bench was filled.</p>
        <p>By the time the class was on to the more frenzied steps, like ''gaga,'' where a white sheet was twisted and stretched like a rope and dancers shimmied underneath, limbo-style, some spectators were open-mouthed and applauding.</p>
        <p>''We have the option of closing the curtains should we choose to,'' said Michaeo Adams, 32, a student in the class and a yoga instructor from Crown Heights, Brooklyn. ''If you're a beginner and you're struggling with the movements, you might be a little less comfortable.''</p>
        <p>He added, however, ''Dance is not supposed to be shut up in a room all by itself.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
