<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets' Batters Cannot Get Back What the Pitchers Give Away</title>
    <meta content="10mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/sports/baseball/10mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Detroit Tigers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Delgado, Carlos</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Pérez, Oliver</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EED9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets' Batters Cannot Get Back What the Pitchers Give Away</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mets’ Batters Cannot Get Back What the Pitchers Give Away</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, June 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The early evening shadows were creeping over the infield at Comerica Park at the same leisurely pace that the Mets' bullpen, and then the Tigers', were trying their best to help the other team win.</p>
        <p>This was not a game. This was a survival-of-the-fittest competition that, after nearly three and a half hours, was finally settled when the Tigers' embattled closer, Todd Jones, retired Carlos Delgado on a grounder to second with the tying run on first base Saturday to preserve Detroit's 8-7 nail-biter of a victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets’ comeback came up short, as the team’s pitching, headlined by a rare, uninspiring outing by Oliver Pérez, did little to help.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The early evening shadows were creeping over the infield at Comerica Park at the same leisurely pace that the Mets' bullpen, and then the Tigers', were trying their best to help the other team win.</p>
        <p>This was not a game. This was a survival-of-the-fittest competition that, after nearly three and a half hours, was finally settled when the Tigers' embattled closer, Todd Jones, retired Carlos Delgado on a grounder to second with the tying run on first base Saturday to preserve Detroit's 8-7 nail-biter of a victory.</p>
        <p>''We fought back, but I don't want to call that consolation,'' Delgado said. ''We want to win. That's how I look at it.''</p>
        <p>Delgado was also at the plate when the Mets, having scored three runs in the seventh to draw to 8-6, loaded the bases with two out. He grounded out to second then, too, but to ascribe him any fault for the outcome would be undeserved. The culpability in this one partly falls, for a change, to the usually reliable Oliver Pérez, whose magic number was five -- for his runs, walks and innings pitched -- and also to Guillermo Mota, who retired only one of six batters in the pivotal sixth inning, allowing three runs on four consecutive hits.</p>
        <p>''I just didn't get the pitches where I wanted to,'' said Mota, whose earned run average in five appearances has ballooned to 8.10. ''I tried to start them with changeups but I left them up. Sometimes you don't have your location.''</p>
        <p>For the first time in several starts, Pérez did not have control of his slider, which he often throws with two strikes. The Tigers' offense, seemingly incapable of being suppressed for a second consecutive game, noticed as much.</p>
        <p>After walking Magglio Ordóñez with two outs in the first, Pérez got ahead, 1-2, on Carlos Guillén, then hung a slider that Guillén blasted for a three-run homer. In the fifth, after Ordóñez led off with a walk and moved to third on a double by Guillén, Iván Rodríguez socked another slider into left field for a two-run single. The five runs were the most allowed by a Mets starter since Jorge Sosa gave up five May 22 in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>''When you've got a guy 1-2 or 0-2 and you give up something big, you've got to be able to execute your pitches,'' Mets Manager Willie Randolph said. ''At times, he didn't put guys away, and that's what he needs to do to get to the next level.''</p>
        <p>Perez had thrown 105 pitches through five innings and was due to face a left-handed hitter, Curtis Granderson, to begin the sixth. Rather than let Pérez pitch to Granderson, who was batting .119 against left-handers, and then insert Mota to counteract the Tigers' three straight right-handed hitters, Randolph brought in Mota immediately. The decision backfired when Granderson doubled to right-center field, and the inning deteriorated from there. Singles by Plácido Polanco and Gary Sheffield added one run, and a double by Ordóñez, his major-league leading 30th, drove in two more and extended the Tigers' lead to 8-3.</p>
        <p>The Detroit right-hander Jeremy Bonderman, who won his sixth consecutive start, allowed three runs through six innings, with José Reyes's two-out, two-run single in the fifth briefly tying the score at 3-3, before the Tigers' combustible bullpen started stirring.</p>
        <p>Detroit's relief pitchers, such an asset in its march to the World Series last season, entered the game with the third-worst E.R.A. (5.11) in baseball. It no longer has the hard-throwing Joel Zumaya (injury) or the dependable Jamie Walker (free agency), and Jason Grilli and Wil Ledezma have been inconsistent.</p>
        <p>After the Mets led off the seventh by rapping three consecutive hits to chase Bonderman, Yorman Bazardo, who was not even in the Tigers' organization last season, came in to allow a sacrifice fly by Ramón Castro, cutting the Tigers' lead to 8-5. The pinch-hitter Rubén Gotay hit an infield single that drove in Ricky Ledee, and then Ledezma recorded an out while loading the bases for Delgado.</p>
        <p>''We had all the momentum,'' David Wright said.</p>
        <p>Ledezma threw two pitches out of the strike zone before throwing a fastball down the middle that Delgado said he missed. On a full count, Delgado grounded out. The Mets added a run in the eighth on Wright's third home run in three games.</p>
        <p>Jones, who was 0-2 with a 20.77 E.R.A. in his previous five outings, struck out the first two batters he faced in the ninth before Carlos Beltrán singled to shallow right field between Polanco and Ordóñez. Up again, Delgado grounded to deep second, and the Mets' offense, which had scored four or fewer runs in six of the past seven games, could not bail out its pitching.</p>
        <p>''For us to battle back like we did, hopefully our offense has woken up,'' Wright said. ''Let's just hope it keeps going.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Shawn Green (broken bone in right foot) said that he expected to be activated from the disabled list Sunday, but Willie Randolph would not confirm it. Whenever Green is activated, the corresponding roster move will probably involve Ben Johnson and not Carlos Gómez. Randolph indicated that the speedy Gómez could help offset the loss of Endy Chávez, who is not expected to return until after the All-Star Game break.  Gary Sheffield's backswing in the first inning hit Ramón Castro's left forearm, but Castro remained in the game and said he felt fine.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
