<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Charming, Sunny Décor; The Food Is Even Better</title>
    <meta content="10dineliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/10dineli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853512"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/SOUTHAMPTON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wildthyme Restaurant and Bar (Southampton, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starkey, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Hamptons (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3D91E30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="843" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Charming, Sunny Décor; The Food Is Even Better</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Charming, Sunny Décor; The Food Is Even Better</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Starkey, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joanne Starkey reviews Wildthyme Restaurant and Bar in Southampton, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A SWEET, simple spot, Wildthyme gives few clues to the fireworks generated in the kitchen. The rousing food sets off sparks, turning a meal into a party. Every dish sampled, with one lone exception, deserved cheers.</p>
        <p>The restaurant, which opened in June 2006, is viewed by its owners, Delaney Oser and her husband, Myles Romanow, as a kind of evening extension of Ms. Oser's 11-year-old catering business, Thyme and Again in Southampton. The exterior of this tiny roadside place in the hamlet of North Sea in Southampton features a small dining porch with red market umbrellas, a handful of tables for two and windows and railings outlined in tiny white lights. Tables are topped with white cloths and round fishbowls holding marbles and floating tea lights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A sweet, simple spot, Wildthyme in Southampton gives few clues to the fireworks generated in the kitchen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A SWEET, simple spot, Wildthyme gives few clues to the fireworks generated in the kitchen. The rousing food sets off sparks, turning a meal into a party. Every dish sampled, with one lone exception, deserved cheers.</p>
        <p>The restaurant, which opened in June 2006, is viewed by its owners, Delaney Oser and her husband, Myles Romanow, as a kind of evening extension of Ms. Oser's 11-year-old catering business, Thyme and Again in Southampton. The exterior of this tiny roadside place in the hamlet of North Sea in Southampton features a small dining porch with red market umbrellas, a handful of tables for two and windows and railings outlined in tiny white lights. Tables are topped with white cloths and round fishbowls holding marbles and floating tea lights.</p>
        <p>Indoors, the space is nearly evenly divided between the bar and the lounge, which has a few tables for dining, and the sunny dining room. The latter is bright with white and pale yellow walls, the backdrop for colorful race car posters. Each table contains a nosegay of garden flowers -- tulips and lilacs at the time of my visits. The place is cheery and charming; service is concerned and attentive. But the food impresses most.</p>
        <p>Salads are not run-of-the-mill offerings. Take the Cobb. It is a towering construction with a topknot of romaine and layers of grilled chicken, avocado, tomato, Roquefort and hard-boiled egg, all in a smooth sherry-shallot vinaigrette. The chopped salad is a balanced creation with salty feta and sweet golden raisins playing off each other and sparking the other ingredients (romaine, cucumber, chickpeas, roasted peppers, Bermuda onions, grape tomatoes). The lobster salad had abundant seafood, avocado, hearts of palm and white truffle oil.</p>
        <p>The heirloom tomato salad is a standout, reminiscent of Italian panzanella, or bread salad. Wildthyme's rendition includes slices of big, juicy yellow and red beauties along with halves of smaller red, yellow and green ones and a few roasted tomatoes in a thick tomato water with basil and oil. Thick fingers of sourdough toasts at the base of the dish soak up the juices.</p>
        <p>Four jumbo roasted oysters on beds of braised spinach and bacon were worthy, as was the lump crab cake with a refreshing papaya salad. Two soups sampled, a briny lobster bisque and a velvety butternut squash, kept the winning streak going.</p>
        <p>Most dishes were perfectly seasoned, but you might want to request salt to see the array that arrives: apricot sea salt, a garlic-infused variety and regular table salt.</p>
        <p>The poached pound-and-a-half Maine lobster, the star entree at a recent meal, was split and stuffed with crab meat and chopped leeks. The shallow bowl it came in also held a tasty white wine reduction that was a great dipping sauce for the sweet lobster meat. Another headliner was a porcini-crusted rack of lamb, a special, which included slices of the mushroom and a mound of creamy, spinach-laced risotto.</p>
        <p>Don't overlook the juicy strip steak. Far from ordinary, it shares the plate with crisp fries, a mustard-touched Béarnaise and a cucumber-heirloom tomato salad. The pan-roasted chicken is elevated by its accompaniments: ratatouille, wild mushrooms and a hash of fingerling potato and cipollini onion.</p>
        <p>The crispy salmon fillet was memorable for its lightly cooked, moist flesh and plate mates of grilled asparagus, creamed corn and a sherry vinegar-brown butter sauce. Sake-marinated halibut also hit the spot, with its wok-seared Asian vegetables. The only misfire among two dozen dishes sampled was a drab, slightly dry striped bass fillet with a lackluster watercress garnish.</p>
        <p>One night, two young women at the next table shared four desserts. They had the right idea. We loved every one we tried. The biggest crowd pleaser was the banana split with dulce de leche ice cream, chocolate sauce and clouds of freshly whipped cream. My favorite was the satiny panna cotta with fresh berries and a raspberry sauce. Molten-center chocolate cake, tiramisù and a layering of three tropical mousses also more than made the grade. Sweet little Wildthyme is in that same lofty category.</p>
        <p>Wildthyme Restaurant And Bar  129 Noyac Road  Southampton  (631) 204-0007</p>
        <p>EXCELLENT</p>
        <p>THE SPACE -- Small, simple roadside spot with a few outdoor tables. Not wheelchair accessible.</p>
        <p>THE CROWD -- Trendy Hamptonites have discovered it. Very few children.</p>
        <p>THE BAR -- A long wood bar with seating and a few cloth-covered tables for dining. Small list of around 50 still wines ($24 to $150), with a dozen by the glass ($7 to $14).</p>
        <p>THE BILL -- Entrees $21 to $38 (lobster). Most are in the $20s. American Express, Visa and MasterCard are accepted.</p>
        <p>WHAT WE LIKE -- Lobster salad, chopped salad, Cobb salad, tomato salad, crab cake, roasted oysters, lobster bisque, butternut squash soup, halibut, salmon, chicken, strip steak, lobster, rack of lamb, all desserts.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO -- Open from 6 to 10 p.m. Wednesday to Friday and from 5:30 to 10 p.m. Saturday and Sunday. Closed Monday and Tuesday. Reservations are essential on weekends.</p>
        <p>Reviewed June 10, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/SOUTHAMPTON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
