<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Keeper of the Faith</title>
    <meta content="10colnjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/10colnj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853581"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="JERSEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Metuchen (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kim, Bede Hong (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coyne, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Roman Catholic Church</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E6DD1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Keeper of the Faith</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A New Keeper of the Faith</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Kevin Coyne</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Coyne, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>Metuchen</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kevin Coyne Jersey column on Bede Hong Kim, South Korean native who was recently ordained as Roman Catholic priest in Metuchen, NJ; Kim is only priest to be ordained this year in diocese of Metuchen; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON a sunny, stained-glass morning, in a packed cathedral decked out in all its finery, the young man about to become New Jersey's newest Roman Catholic priest stood alone before the marble altar, hands folded prayerfully, facing the bishop.</p>
        <p>''Do you resolve, with the help of the Holy Spirit, to discharge without fail the office of the priesthood?'' Bishop Paul G. Bootkoski asked Bede Hong Kim.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the diocese of Metuchen, an effort to bring more men to the priesthood begins within.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON a sunny, stained-glass morning, in a packed cathedral decked out in all its finery, the young man about to become New Jersey's newest Roman Catholic priest stood alone before the marble altar, hands folded prayerfully, facing the bishop.</p>
        <p>''Do you resolve, with the help of the Holy Spirit, to discharge without fail the office of the priesthood?'' Bishop Paul G. Bootkoski asked Bede Hong Kim.</p>
        <p>''I do,'' Mr. Kim answered in a strong, clear voice that didn't break, as he had feared it might, making a vow that no one else among the more than half-million Catholics in the diocese of Metuchen would make this year.</p>
        <p>Spring is a season of transformation: weddings, graduations and, in the Catholic church, the ordination of priests, a ritual that has dwindled in size if not in pageantry in recent years. Fewer men are answering a call that Mr. Kim first heard as a schoolboy in South Korea, where he lived until his family moved to Edison when he was 12. In 1965, 994 new priests were ordained in America; this year 475 will be. In New Jersey, the Newark Archdiocese ordained 13; the diocese of Paterson, 4; Camden and Trenton, 5 each; and Metuchen, just Mr. Kim.</p>
        <p>After the last of his promises to the bishop -- six ''I do's'' in all -- Mr. Kim stretched himself out face down on a carpet that had been laid on the terrazzo floor. He rested his forehead on his folded arms, and closed his eyes as the litany of the saints was chanted, one name after another, for eight full minutes before he finally stood and walked over to the bishop's seat. He knelt, and the bishop laid his hands on his thick thatch of black hair for 10 silent seconds, the solemn center of the sacrament.</p>
        <p>''That's really when you become a priest,'' Father Kim, 27, said later. ''It went by so quickly. I couldn't feel anything. I was so overwhelmed with my emotions.''</p>
        <p>Still, nobody said anything -- there was no sound at all but the harpist in the choir loft beneath the rose window gently playing a medieval French melody -- and Father Kim knelt before the altar as all the priests that had accompanied him into the cathedral filed past and laid their hands on his head, too. Among them was the Rev. Randy Vachon, appointed by the bishop two years ago as the diocese's first full-time vocations director.</p>
        <p>''Things have started to pick up a little, but we're still not anywhere near where we need to be,'' Father Vachon said about the effort to attract more men to the priesthood. Next year, Metuchen will again ordain one new priest; the following year, two, possibly three, are expected.</p>
        <p>Some dioceses try to keep their ranks filled by recruiting overseas, in nations where the worldly allure of other careers isn't as tempting, and where devotion to the church is more pervasive than it has become in America in recent years. ''We're working very hard to build within our own house,'' said Father Vachon, 51, who was a software designer before he was ordained seven years ago. ''Will that change? It's tempting. You can go to places like Colombia and the Philippines and you can double your seminarians easily. But at the moment we're trying very hard to focus within.''</p>
        <p>It was in New Brunswick that the diocese found Father Kim, in the Korean community that worships in Sacred Heart parish. In high school he thought briefly about following his father's career path and going to art school, but then he learned of the college seminary at Seton Hall University. After four years there he went to Immaculate Conception Seminary on the same campus. He became an American citizen last December.</p>
        <p>Unlike many American dioceses, Metuchen has managed not to close any parishes, although it has consolidated some under a single priest. It has 215 active priests to serve 108 parishes. Three of them will retire this year.</p>
        <p>''I'll be lying if I say I don't feel it,'' Father Kim said of the burden implied by those numbers -- a large flock and a shrinking clergy. His first assignment will be as one of the assistants at Immaculate Conception in Spotswood, which serves 3,200 families.</p>
        <p>At the end of the Mass, Father Kim had a blessing of his own to bestow. He stood at the altar, alone no longer, as two bishops -- Bishop Bootkoski and Bishop Emeritus Edward Hughes, who was ordained almost 60 years ago -- knelt before him, and he laid his hands upon their heads. A full minute of raucous applause and cheering followed Father Kim down the aisle, mingling with the joyous pealing from the bell tower and the thumping, gonging Korean drummers outside.</p>
        <p>A few minutes later, he was back in the cathedral, standing at the altar again, laying his hands upon the heads of his parents, his family and friends, and then a long, growing line of other people, many of them strangers, who were eager for a blessing from a new priest.</p>
        <p>JERSEY E-mail: jersey@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: jersey@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
