<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>His and Not Hers</title>
    <meta content="10wwln--ethicist.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/magazine/10wwln-ethicist-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853461"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 6-10-07: THE ETHICIST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/The Ethicist</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE0D81130F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="564" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>His and Not Hers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">His and Not Hers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Randy Cohen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Randy Cohen Ethicist column answers questions on whether a husband and wife should share their expenses equally if one has much more money than the other and whether you should donate old clothes to charities in they send them to poor countries where they undermine local garment industries (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a long stretch of unemployment, I might have lined up a modestly paying job. The man I am involved with earns at least $200,000 a year and has several million dollars in savings. Despite this disparity, he insists that if we wed I must then bear half the cost of everything. I think married people should pool their resources, contributing what they can. He thinks I am looking for a sugar daddy. You? name withheld, New York</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In with the new; out with the old.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a long stretch of unemployment, I might have lined up a modestly paying job. The man I am involved with earns at least $200,000 a year and has several million dollars in savings. Despite this disparity, he insists that if we wed I must then bear half the cost of everything. I think married people should pool their resources, contributing what they can. He thinks I am looking for a sugar daddy. You? name withheld, New York</p>
        <p>Your beau seems, if you'll excuse a technical term, nutty -- but not unethical. Yours is a difference of inclination, not morality. As long as they harm no one, a couple may live in a way that outsiders find peculiar (by which I mean utterly risible): they need please only each other. But you have not pleased each other. And while your beau has the right to propose this goofy arrangement, you need not accept it.</p>
        <p>When faced with great differences in wealth, wise couples seek a mutually acceptable accommodation. Some share daily expenses while leaving major expenditures -- house, car -- to the wealthier partner. Some pool their money, the ''Measure for Measure'' approach: ''What's mine is yours, and what is yours is mine.'' Others heed that great marriage counselor Karl Marx: ''from each according to his ability, to each according to his needs.'' With love, trust and generosity of spirit, diverse solutions are possible. Maybe you could strive for two out of three.</p>
        <p>But it doesn't sound as if you will have to worry about marital financial plans. More urgent, I fear, is for you to be sure to put your name on any books or CDs you lend this tightfisted and suspicious fellow.</p>
        <p>For years, I've donated old clothes to charity. Then I learned that many of these garments are shipped to poor countries where they are sold, devastating local industries and thus creating more poverty. The recipients do get inexpensive clothing, and my local charity makes money, but I fear I'm doing more harm than good. Advice?</p>
        <p>Georgia Vogelsang, Baltimore</p>
        <p>Even benevolent acts can have unintended consequences. Bama Athreya, executive director of the International Labor Rights Fund, says that the used-clothing trade ''has contributed to the decimation of local garment industries, and therefore contributed to unemployment in Africa.'' He suggests you ask your local charity what it does with used clothing and that you give only to charities that bypass middlemen and distribute donations directly to people in need, particularly to people in your community. This seems wise, maximizing the good and minimizing the ill done by your old ''I'm With Stupid'' T-shirt.</p>
        <p>And yet. . . . Eric Stubin, executive vice president of Trans-Americas FSC, an exporter of used clothing, asserts that these are the only clothes the world's poorest people can afford, and that companies like his ''provide thousands of jobs while providing the essential clothing that has actually become part of the culture of Africa.'' Stubin argues that as a country's economy develops and its people are able to earn more, the used-clothing trade recedes. Until then, he says, the trade's net effect is benign.</p>
        <p>Alas, much that has ''become part of the culture of Africa'' is lamentable. But when experts clash over the facts, what is a civilian to do? She is to learn more. Doing good requires not only good intentions but due diligence -- exhausting but unavoidable.</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 6-10-07: THE ETHICIST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
