<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clemens Lives Up to the Moment, Then Takes Time to Enjoy It</title>
    <meta content="10yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/sports/baseball/10yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853383"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Clemens, Roger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EED9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clemens Lives Up to the Moment, Then Takes Time to Enjoy It</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Clemens Returns as Yankees Gain Momentum</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Roger Clemens is a historic baseball figure and Yankee Stadium is a historic baseball park. But their active days are dwindling. After Clemens was the winning pitcher in a 9-3 victory against Pittsburgh in his return to the Yankees yesterday, he sighed deeply and spoke about the past, the present and the near future.</p>
        <p>''I've got to take a little deep breath now,'' Clemens said. ''I understand the excitement that's there and the expectations that are there, and there's a lot of both. As an athlete, I have the opportunity to perform in this setting. This stadium's not going to be around much longer. It sure is a joy.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees’ offense gave Roger Clemens plenty of run support as he pitched six solid innings to earn a victory in his first start of the season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Roger Clemens is a historic baseball figure and Yankee Stadium is a historic baseball park. But their active days are dwindling. After Clemens was the winning pitcher in a 9-3 victory against Pittsburgh in his return to the Yankees yesterday, he sighed deeply and spoke about the past, the present and the near future.</p>
        <p>''I've got to take a little deep breath now,'' Clemens said. ''I understand the excitement that's there and the expectations that are there, and there's a lot of both. As an athlete, I have the opportunity to perform in this setting. This stadium's not going to be around much longer. It sure is a joy.''</p>
        <p>He was a 44-year-old pitcher performing in an 84-year-old stadium that is to close after next season and be replaced by a new one next door. Clemens's 24-year career has taken a circuitous route that has returned him to a place where he was a star from 1999 through 2003.</p>
        <p>His two youngest sons -- Kacy, 12, and Kody, 11 -- sat beside him as he discussed a six-inning outing that gave him a 1-0 record this season and a 349-178 career mark. The best, Clemens said, is yet to come.</p>
        <p>''Each start I go through now, I expect to get stronger,'' said Clemens, who gave up three runs, struck out seven and walked two while throwing 108 pitches, 69 for strikes. His best fastballs were in the range of 91 miles an hour. He mixed in splitters, sliders and an occasional curve.</p>
        <p>Clemens said he listened to the cheering and chanting of the fans. ''I was feeling everybody's energy,'' he said. ''Good energy here, as expected. I'm going to savor this moment. Bottom line, I feel blessed.''</p>
        <p>Clemens squandered a two-run lead in the fourth inning, but he finished strong, retiring the last seven batters he faced, the final two on strikeouts. The victory was the Yankees' fifth in succession, their longest winning streak of the season.</p>
        <p>It was also their eighth triumph in their past 10 games, their best stretch so far. But they were still two games below .500 at 29-31 in the American League East and well behind first-place Boston, which played last night at Arizona.</p>
        <p>Clemens will be paid $17.4 million this season to help stabilize a starting rotation that has struggled because of injuries and inconsistency. He joins Chien-Ming Wang, Andy Pettitte and Mike Mussina to make an experienced foursome.</p>
        <p>The rookie Tyler Clippard will start today against Pittsburgh's Shawn Chacon. The Yankees have started seven rookie pitchers this season. Clemens has said frequently in recent weeks that part of his role is to tutor young pitchers.</p>
        <p>But there are greater priorities. It is often said that the Yankees, who have won the World Series 26 times, regard anything short of a championship as a failure. But they have not won one since 2000 and did not advance past the first round of the playoffs last season.</p>
        <p>Clemens alluded to that drought and to the high-salaried talent on the roster. ''It's been too long since this type of talent on this team has been in the winner's circle,'' he said.</p>
        <p>When Clemens left the mound with a 4-3 lead after the top of the sixth, the 54,296 fans stood and gave him a loud ovation. Derek Jeter, the captain and shortstop, patted his back. When Clemens reached the dugout, he was greeted by fist bumps and hand slaps from his teammates.</p>
        <p>Clemens pitched the past three seasons in the National League with Houston. He broke in with Boston in 1984 and was there for 13 seasons. He also pitched for Toronto for two seasons. Clemens announced his return to the Yankees on May 6 from the owner's box, his words and image broadcast to the crowd on the scoreboard screen and to the television audience.</p>
        <p>He was supposed to pitch last Monday night against the White Sox in Chicago but missed the start because of a sore groin muscle. Yesterday, Clemens described the problem as scar tissue and reported no new injury. But he acknowledged the difficulty of doing what he is doing with his body at his age.</p>
        <p>''I can only hope and pray it continues to respond,'' Clemens said.</p>
        <p>He allowed a run in the first inning on a single by Adam LaRoche and two runs in the fourth on a double by Jack Wilson. Alex Rodriguez drove in two runs for the Yankees, who scored three in the first.</p>
        <p>Robinson Canó had three hits to raise his average to .275. Bobby Abreu had two hits to raise his to .260. They each drove in a run, as did Johnny Damon, Jorge Posada and Hideki Matsui. Melky Cabrera made a spectacular catch in center field. The Yankees stole five bases.</p>
        <p>Before the game, Yankees Manager Joe Torre discussed the effect that Clemens could have on a team.</p>
        <p>''He's always been that guy who always does special things,'' Torre said. ''Guys are glad to see him. There were a lot of hugs in there early. This guy maintains that kidlike attitude. It's unique. Pete Rose had it. This is the start of something we hope will be very special for the rest of the way.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
