<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Mixed Messages of the Primaries</title>
    <meta content="10polnjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/10polnj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853578"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON POLITICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smothers, Ronald</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E6DD1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="529" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Mixed Messages of the Primaries</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Mixed Messages of the Primaries</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ronald Smothers On Politics column on lack of unifying theme in results of northern New Jersey primaries; comments on results in several districts; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GOOD luck in any search for a grand unifying theme in the results of primaries last Tuesday in northern New Jersey. The lessons were as varied as the races.</p>
        <p>In Bergen County, the lesson for Republicans may be that there is indeed a level below the rock bottom they thought they had hit earlier this year when they could not pay the rent on their headquarters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRENTON.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GOOD luck in any search for a grand unifying theme in the results of primaries last Tuesday in northern New Jersey. The lessons were as varied as the races.</p>
        <p>In Bergen County, the lesson for Republicans may be that there is indeed a level below the rock bottom they thought they had hit earlier this year when they could not pay the rent on their headquarters.</p>
        <p>Todd C. Caliguire, the Bergen County Republican organization's candidate for State Senate, came away with his third successive loss in a run for elective office. Friends and political opponents alike speculated that this loss, after defeats in runs for the party's gubernatorial nomination and for county executive, qualified as his political swan song.</p>
        <p>Mr. Caliguire was convincingly beaten by Assemblyman Kevin J. O'Toole, a former state senator who lives in Essex County, which is the smallest portion of a Senate district that stretches over Passaic and Bergen as well. Mr. O'Toole received a plurality in all three counties in his bid to take the seat held by Senator Henry P. McNamara, who is retiring.</p>
        <p>Political consultants like Rick Shaftan suggested that Mr. O'Toole benefited from voter backlash to a mailing financed by the county party and the Caliguire campaign. It pictured Mr. O'Toole, who has a Korean mother and Irish-American father, alongside the Rev. Al Sharpton and included text that suggested that they both support affirmative action.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Toole has in the past expressed opposition to affirmative action. And the only evidence of his support for affirmative action was the mailing's suggestion that he managed to land in a safe Republican Assembly district after his former Senate district was carved up in the last redistricting simply because of his Korean ancestry and the Democrats' drive to maintain seats for racial minorities.</p>
        <p>On the heels of the primary outcome, the county Republican chairman, Guy Talarico, announced his resignation. He conceded that the mailing, which he opposed, was a mistake.</p>
        <p>In Hudson County the primary was a validation of the time-honored lesson that there are no permanent political enemies or permanent political friends.</p>
        <p>Sandra A. Bolden Cunningham, the widow of Glenn D. Cunningham, won his old 31st District Senate seat with the backing of the Hudson County Democratic organization he had furiously fought. She defeated Assemblyman Louis M. Manzo (who was Mr. Cunningham's handpicked running mate in 2003, a year before his death) and carried along two organization-backed Assembly candidates.</p>
        <p>In Newark the lesson may be what happens when one's reach exceeds one's grasp. Mayor Cory A. Booker, seeking to put supporters in six legislative posts representing parts of the city, succeeded in four races but failed to get the brass ring. The 28th District incumbent, Senator Ronald L. Rice, whom Mr. Booker had handily defeated in the mayoral race last year, held off a challenge by Booker forces to win the Democratic nomination.</p>
        <p>And in Sussex County, the lesson may be that tradition can trump ideological purity. Senator Robert E. Littell, the longest-serving state lawmaker in New Jersey history, is retiring after four decades, and his protégé Steve Oroho, a wealthy businessman, defeated Assemblyman Guy R. Gregg, a staunch conservative Republican.</p>
        <p>ON POLITICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
