<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN THE REGION/New Jersey; Mostly Sunny in Asbury Park</title>
    <meta content="10njzo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/realestate/10njzo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853598"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="In the Region | New Jersey"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E6DC1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1093" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN THE REGION/New Jersey; Mostly Sunny in Asbury Park</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mostly Sunny in Asbury Park</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTOINETTE MARTIN</byline>
      <dateline>ASBURY PARK</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THREE years and $30 million into the redevelopment project designed to bring back Asbury Park as a high-energy, high-end seaside resort, there is still a work-in-progress feel about the place.</p>
        <p>But there has been progress. Later this summer, the first residents of two condominium developments at either end of the beach are to begin moving in. The sales office for a third -- the two-tower 224-unit Esperanza, envisioned as a centerpiece for the entire 56-acre project -- is open, and construction is under way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three years and $30 million into the redevelopment project designed to bring back Asbury Park, there is still a work-in-progress feel about the place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THREE years and $30 million into the redevelopment project designed to bring back Asbury Park as a high-energy, high-end seaside resort, there is still a work-in-progress feel about the place.</p>
        <p>But there has been progress. Later this summer, the first residents of two condominium developments at either end of the beach are to begin moving in. The sales office for a third -- the two-tower 224-unit Esperanza, envisioned as a centerpiece for the entire 56-acre project -- is open, and construction is under way.</p>
        <p>The refurbished Paramount Theater on the boardwalk is to open next month, and a new restaurant has already opened on the boardwalk. On the beach itself, the sand is clean and smooth as never before, thanks to daily grooming with a newly purchased machine that does for the oceanfront what Zambonis do for ice.</p>
        <p>''Still, you need a little imagination'' to really believe the grand plan for revitalization will fully materialize, conceded Larry Fishman of Asbury Partners, the company overseeing redevelopment.</p>
        <p>At its low point -- before the plan for resurgence even emerged four years ago -- the gritty beachfront sank well below gritty, beyond disreputable, all the way to just plain scary after sundown.</p>
        <p>Even now, the police say, they struggle to keep gang activity under control, although the past year has been quiet compared with the year before. There are still plenty of shabby structures and bedraggled lots, even down by the shore and the Stone Pony, the club Bruce Springsteen made famous, which redevelopers promise will be ''respected'' and kept open.</p>
        <p>Imagination is still required -- but less and less, Mr. Fishman asserts. Lending credence to his sunny view are streetscape improvements, new boardwalk shops and a miniature golf course, and the metal columns beginning to peek over the fence around the Esperanza site.</p>
        <p>''This is going to be a landmark,'' Mr. Fishman said, standing at the center of Asbury's rebuilt boardwalk and gesturing across Ocean Avenue to the condo site, where piles have been driven to bedrock to support what will be 16- and 10-story towers.</p>
        <p>The towers will stand on either side of a parking garage with a rooftop pool, entertainment and dining areas.</p>
        <p>Dean Geibel, the principal of Metro Homes, which is building the condo complex, is also ebullient about the project, of course.</p>
        <p>He showed off the marble-floored lobby of the sales center -- a replica of the Esperanza lobby of the future -- as well as several model kitchens and baths, and one complete mockup of a two-bedroom, two-bath apartment with a den and oceanfront terrace. ''This is really and truly going to be incredibly, incredibly cool,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The model apartment is meant to have the look of South Beach, with Venetian plaster walls in the baths -- the surface is like marble, but ''hipper'' and more colorful, Mr. Geibel said. It is priced at about $750,000.</p>
        <p>Condos will range in size from 545-square-foot studios to approximately 3,000-square-foot four-bedroom penthouses. Prices start in the low $400,000s and exceed $2 million.</p>
        <p>Local skeptics, including many longtime residents of adjacent Ocean Grove, who bought Victorian cottages 15 or 20 years ago for prices in the low $100,000s, insist that the lavish new condos in Asbury Park are fated to flop.</p>
        <p>''They are not going to get people to buy at those prices,'' scoffed an antiques dealer with a shop on Ocean Grove's main boulevard, a five-minute walk across Wesley Lake Bridge from the southern end of the Asbury boardwalk. ''Off the record,'' she added with a wink, ''I'm still afraid to carry cash in my wallet if I go over there.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Geibel said he knew that ''people still carry around outdated notions'' about Asbury Park. He noted, however, that his family -- including teenagers and a toddler -- will occupy a penthouse in the taller tower of the Esperanza, and that the complex will have 24-hour concierge service.</p>
        <p>Residents will be permitted to rent out their apartments for short or long stays, with security maintained through a code to be typed into a keypad on the front door for the duration of the rental period.</p>
        <p>Hotel-style services -- housekeeping, grocery shopping, laundry -- will be available to residents and renters through the concierge.</p>
        <p>As for amenities, besides the shore just outside, the Esperanza will have two in-house restaurants, a club room, screening rooms and 23 poolside cabanas, each outfitted with a daybed, plasma-screen television, wet bar, private safe and full bathroom, Mr. Geibel said. There will also be poolside food service and a dining area, a children's play area and a landscaped lawn.</p>
        <p>Sales have just opened for the complex, and Mr. Geibel says he does not expect them to take off until the building rises high enough to become a ''presence.'' Even so, he said, several choice units have already been sold to buyers from affluent New Jersey towns like Summit and Westfield.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, at the North Beach complex, which is to have three buildings with 154 units, only about a dozen condos remain for sale. The first building in the Paramount Homes project opens for occupancy in August, Mr. Fishman said.</p>
        <p>At Wesley Grove, being built by Westminster Properties, more than half of the 91 town house units have been sold, the first of them to be occupied, also, in August. In addition, some units are being offered as rentals as of August.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fishman said a new condo/hotel complex had been proposed at the Wesley Grove end of the beach.</p>
        <p>Following are other developments on the Asbury Park waterfront:</p>
        <p>The 300-room Berkeley Carteret Hotel, once owned by the Maharishi Mahesh Yogi and recently in a state of serious decline, was sold in February to the New York real estate investors Joseph and Jacob Chetrit, and renovation work has begun.</p>
        <p>The old Howard Johnson's hotel/restaurant on the boardwalk has been renovated and reopened as the Salt Water Beach Cafe. Madison Marquette, a Las Vegas-based company named to oversee retail and entertainment redevelopment in Asbury Park, brought in the restaurant.</p>
        <p>The company is also planning to install a ''festive market'' offering local Jersey produce, as well as jewelry and crafts, inside the Carousel building on the boardwalk once it is restored, Mr. Fishman said.</p>
        <p>The old casino structure on the beachfront opposite the Carousel building has been demolished. A boardwalk billboard shows the design for a hall to be built on the site, featuring Victorian architecture like that of the original.</p>
        <p>Work is also under way to create studio space on the boardwalk for a professional glass blower, with large windows so passers-by can see the artist at work.</p>
        <p>In the Region | New Jersey</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
