<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rocket Scientist or Auto Mechanic? The Distinction Is Blurring</title>
    <meta content="10TRAINING" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles; Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/automobiles/10TRAINING.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853590"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MOTORING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Vocational Training</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vocational Training</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE5DD1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1248" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rocket Scientist or Auto Mechanic? The Distinction Is Blurring</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rocket Scientist or Auto Mechanic? The Distinction Is Blurring</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SCOTT STURGIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CRAIG VAN BATENBURG is not your average mechanic.</p>
        <p>He got his start pumping gas in the 1960s and messing around in his father's repair shop. But while his fellow gearheads souped up Mustangs, Mr. Van Batenburg fell in love with what was then a new import brand that put its focus on wringing the most out of a gallon of gas: Honda.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As cars grow more complex, automotive experts say many teenagers are unwilling to undertake the necessary training for jobs that don’t initially pay much.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CRAIG VAN BATENBURG is not your average mechanic.</p>
        <p>He got his start pumping gas in the 1960s and messing around in his father's repair shop. But while his fellow gearheads souped up Mustangs, Mr. Van Batenburg fell in love with what was then a new import brand that put its focus on wringing the most out of a gallon of gas: Honda.</p>
        <p>He learned Datsun and Toyota as well, and repaired them professionally. But he came back to just Honda, which his shop specialized in for years. When Honda introduced the Insight hybrid in 1999, he said he was one of the first to buy one.</p>
        <p>Now he runs the Automotive Career Development Center from his home in Worcester, Mass., and travels the country teaching hybrid repair to automotive technicians. And he wonders where the next Craig Van Batenburg will come from.</p>
        <p>''Cars are an unbelievable phenomenon,'' Mr. Van Batenburg, 56, said. ''We need to get kids interested in them.''</p>
        <p>People who know cars know that it's getting tougher to find skilled mechanics. Cars have become increasingly complex, and require the kind of specialized training that teenagers can't pick up hanging around the local gas station. Although these students are part of the video-game generation and are comfortable around computers, automotive experts said many teenagers were unwilling to undertake the training for jobs that don't initially pay much, when they can learn similar skills to enter higher-paying professions that get more respect.</p>
        <p>''It requires many of the same aptitudes that go into science and engineering,'' John Cabaniss, director of environment and energy for the Association of International Automobile Manufacturers in Arlington, Va., said about a mechanic's job. He said that repairing automobiles might not offer students the kind of financial rewards and sense of personal achievement that come with other professions.</p>
        <p>A Labor Department study in May 2005 found that there was a growing need for automotive technicians. The study said there were 818,000 technicians in 2002, but the need would grow to 919,000 by 2012. But the difference is not simply 101,000. Because of retirement and workers leaving the field during those 10 years, the nation will have to train 319,000 new technicians to meet the need, the study said.</p>
        <p>That need is being felt on the local level. Mark Schienberg, president of the Greater New York Automobile Dealers Association, said that when area dealers were asked in 2005 how many technicians they would like to hire, the total was 625 in 2005 but 900 a year through 2010. The industry is concerned about filling those positions.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Schienberg said master mechanics with the right certifications could earn about $100,000 a year, other experts said most mechanics don't finish the required training, which can take five to seven years. Many older mechanics, for example, don't want to go back to school and current students often don't go beyond learning basic mechanics, failing to take the more difficult high-tech classes. That often confines them to low-paying jobs, and many eventually leave the profession.</p>
        <p>High schools that steer students not bound for college into automotive tech classes have the same problem: many students who wouldn't do well in college also don't do well with complex diagnostics. Dean Ulrich, who teaches automotive technology at the Gibson Technical Center, a vocational school in Reeds Spring, Mo., said high school counselors were often to blame. He said counselors often told students, '' 'If your grades are not good enough for college, go to vocational school.' It's disappointing because I don't get the highly intelligent individuals that can understand electrical flow and computer diagnostics well to get in there and make the big money. Out of 30, maybe one will do really well and the others will be more mechanics and not technicians.''</p>
        <p>Bill Haas, vice president of education and training for the Automotive Service Association in Bedford, Tex., said it could indeed be a long process. Students first need to learn the basics: mechanics, hydraulics, the electrical system and electronics. The students won't be qualified to use the diagnostic machines until they have been through a second year of training and had experience at a repair shop.</p>
        <p>The New York dealers association was so eager for more mechanics that it opened its own $28 million training center in Queens. It includes an automotive school operated by the Lincoln Technical Institute, which offers training around the nation. Of the 47 students who graduated in 2006 from the first one-year program in Queens, 46 were hired, all by dealerships, for an average starting salary of $35,000 a year. The current class has 400 students and the association hopes to increase that to 750 in about a year.</p>
        <p>Eleven automakers offer classes in their specific brands at Lincoln, and although the school's one-year program sticks to more basic skills, the automakers' courses get more advanced, with only Toyota offering training year-round.</p>
        <p>''When we started the center it was with the idea that we could start from beginning to end, from the high-school level to post-secondary to preparing them for the industry,'' Mr. Schienberg said. He said the school hoped to offer its own high-tech training eventually.</p>
        <p>Toyota offers the Toyota Technical Education Network, which began in 1986 and trains students on Toyotas. The entry-level and work-study program works with 50 vocational and community colleges across the country and has trained more than 3,500 people, according to Toyota's Web site.</p>
        <p>Lydia Cisaruk, a Ford spokeswoman, wrote in an e-mail message that the company managed the training curriculums for technicians at more than 100 colleges and vocational schools. She said the Ford programs had more than 2,900 graduates in 2006, up from 2,300 in 2005. It does not have a program at the Lincoln institute.</p>
        <p>One success story from an automaker's training program is Cody Smith.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith, 22, works at Molle Audi in Kansas City, Mo., where after 18 months he has reached the expert level, the second of four levels Audi has for its dealer technicians. He graduated from the Gibson Technical Center and the Universal Technical Institute, an automotive trade school, in Chicago. He was then accepted into the Audi Academy at the institute. After four months of training, he joined Molle Audi.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith said he went into technician training for the same reason most do: ''I was always kind of interested in cars, and I liked to take things apart and put them back together.''</p>
        <p>Teachers, dealers, and mechanics have been trying to get young people involved, including Mr. Van Batenburg. He opened his automotive center in 1999 and travels about 250 days a year offering training in automotive repair and management.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ulrich, of Gibson Technical School, said some of his high school students were worried about their futures in auto repair. Discouraged students fell into two categories, Mr. Ulrich said: those who were unprepared for the amount of technological knowledge required and those who thought the pay was inadequate, at least at the starting level.</p>
        <p>They also have to deal with the public's image of auto mechanics.</p>
        <p>''Auto repair technicians don't get enough respect for what they have to know, what they have to learn on an annual basis to remain current with rampant product technology, and what they have to invest in tools to be productive,'' Mark Saxonberg, service technology manager with Toyota Motor Sales USA in Torrance, Calif., wrote in an e-mail message.</p>
        <p>''You have to love it to want to stay in it.''</p>
        <p>MOTORING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
