<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tracing a Hudson Valley Legend in Spain</title>
    <meta content="10colweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/10colwe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853562"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Spain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Irving, Washington (1783-1859)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berger, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burstein, Andrew</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Tales of the Alhambra (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Original Knickerbocker, the (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Spain</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Irving, Washington</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EEDF1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tracing a Hudson Valley Legend in Spain</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tracing a Hudson Valley Legend in Spain</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH BERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berger, Joseph</byline>
      <dateline>TARRYTOWN</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joseph Berger column on Washington Irving and his role, as world traveler and author of 1832 book Tales of the Alhambra, in introducing beauty of Spain to American readers; Andrew Burstein, professor of 19th-century American history at University of Tulsa and author of new biography, The Original Knickerbocker, comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HE showed up everywhere we went in Spain. That Westchester immortal, Washington Irving, is memorialized in Seville and in Granada, a city he made famous long before Sinatra sang of its charms. If tour guides are to be believed, the attention that Irving's 1832 ''Tales of the Alhambra'' received was responsible for halting the decay of the splendidly ornamented fortress that is one of several sites competing in an online contest to name the new Seven Wonders of the World.</p>
        <p>But what, we wondered, had Irving been doing in Spain? Irving is the most fundamentally American of writers, known for concocting that henpecked Hudson Highlands dreamer, Rip Van Winkle -- whose 20-year nap through the American Revolution took him Back to the Future -- and Sleepy Hollow's Headless Horseman, who still petrifies Halloweeners of all ages. He popularized Gotham as an alias for New York and anointed Father Knickerbocker as its trademark citizen, a name that survives in the moniker of its losing basketball team. He bequeathed the names of two Westchester villages -- Irvington and Sleepy Hollow. But where does Spain come in?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>That Westchester immortal, Washington Irving, is memorialized in many places in Spain. What had he been doing there?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HE showed up everywhere we went in Spain. That Westchester immortal, Washington Irving, is memorialized in Seville and in Granada, a city he made famous long before Sinatra sang of its charms. If tour guides are to be believed, the attention that Irving's 1832 ''Tales of the Alhambra'' received was responsible for halting the decay of the splendidly ornamented fortress that is one of several sites competing in an online contest to name the new Seven Wonders of the World.</p>
        <p>But what, we wondered, had Irving been doing in Spain? Irving is the most fundamentally American of writers, known for concocting that henpecked Hudson Highlands dreamer, Rip Van Winkle -- whose 20-year nap through the American Revolution took him Back to the Future -- and Sleepy Hollow's Headless Horseman, who still petrifies Halloweeners of all ages. He popularized Gotham as an alias for New York and anointed Father Knickerbocker as its trademark citizen, a name that survives in the moniker of its losing basketball team. He bequeathed the names of two Westchester villages -- Irvington and Sleepy Hollow. But where does Spain come in?</p>
        <p>Irving's literary stock has fallen as charming 19th-century authors get bled out of the canon, so few Americans -- this one included -- remember that Irving was one of his age's champion travelers, making three Atlantic crossings, one that lasted 17 years, and spending eight years in Spain, including three months inside the Alhambra Palace.</p>
        <p>Spain transformed Irving, offering landscapes and characters for stories that interwove romantic history with fairy-tale whimsy and made him America's first international literary celebrity. Like other writers who toiled productively in exile, Irving wrote the Van Winkle and Sleepy Hollow stories during a European sojourn. But Irving also transformed Spain, giving it a luster in the American imagination that endured until Hemingway and his bullfighters went further and made Spain a must-stop.</p>
        <p>''In Spain,'' Andrew Burstein, a professor of 19th-century American history at the University of Tulsa, writes in ''The Original Knickerbocker'' (Basic Books), a new biography of Irving, ''he became a true Romantic, living out a fantasy of time travel during his residence at the Alhambra, resurrecting the myths of a lost culture.''</p>
        <p>Irving's wanderlust was liberating and broadening. But like many vagabonds, he came away from travel with the realization of how essential it was to have an anchor, and he made anchor in Westchester. As a 50-ish bachelor who had always lived in other people's homes, he chose the Hudson as the site of his first home, expending great energy on the design of a two-room fixer-upper that grew into the handsome Sunnyside estate that today draws visitors to the Tarrytown-Irvington border.</p>
        <p>Siblings and nieces lived with him at times, and there were guests galore at his table, offering the clamor and tenderness of family even if he had not generated that family himself. When the railroad cut through his property, he became a pioneer commuter, though he had to flag the train whenever he wanted a night out at Manhattan's salons.</p>
        <p>''Irving, it can be argued, was part of the rise of suburbia,'' said Dina Rose Friedman, Sunnyside's site director. ''He took advantage of it without living in it.''</p>
        <p>But he never forgot Spain. He filled the house with Spanish books and tchotchkes like the three Moorish daggers on his desk. Like all proper suburbanites, he built an addition, in his case a three-story steeple sometimes called the Spanish tower because it echoes Alhambra's arches. His home was, as Mr. Burstein says, ''his castle on the Hudson,'' fitting for someone enchanted by Spain's castles. (The view, like the one from the Alhambra, is breathtaking.)</p>
        <p>Irving may have been drawn to Spain by his boyhood affection for Don Quixote. But Mr. Burstein writes that he also ''sensed that he required a new immersion in Europe if he was to exert further influence as a writer.'' In the Alhambra volume, Irving describes how he was shown around that ''Oriental pile'' by Mateo Ximenes, a ''son of the Alhambra'' who regaled him with legends that Irving embellished into the book's beguiling fables.</p>
        <p>There is one story, ''Legend of Prince Ahmed al Kamel, or, the Pilgrim of Love,'' about a prince who has been locked in a tower so he can know nothing of ''the allurements of love,'' which a seer has predicted will prove his undoing. Nevertheless, the prince learns about love from the birds, and he and a princess he liberates ride off on a magic silk carpet. The Alhambra tales are mottled with wild mountain scenery and bewitching dark-eyed characters, but are also very American in their occasionally prudish moralizing.</p>
        <p>The Spanish, Mr. Burstein said, ''were well aware of how he was providing American readers with a romantic vision of Spain that would inevitably bring American tourists.''</p>
        <p>He helped them appreciate what a jewel the Alhambra was and what a magnet it could become. (Just try to get an advance ticket.)</p>
        <p>As Ms. Friedman put it, ''a foreigner recognized something the natives didn't.''</p>
        <p>E-mail: joeberg@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: joeberg@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
