<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Don't Tread on Them</title>
    <meta content="10goods" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/business/yourmoney/10goods.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853696"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE GOODS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/The Goods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Operations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804EFD61F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Don't Tread on Them</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Don’t Tread on Them</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRENDAN I. KOERNER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR video game aficionados who came of age in the late 1970s, the aliens from Space Invaders are symbols of menace. Shaped like robotic jellyfish, they would descend inexorably toward a player's laser cannon, coming in ever-faster swarms as the game progressed. Sooner or later, the aliens would triumph, leaving the defeated player to contemplate -- if only for an instant -- the horrors of life on a conquered planet.</p>
        <p>Jérôme Fischbach, a partner in the Paris design firm La Tête au Cube, hopes that consumers of a certain age -- roughly 30 to 45 -- still tremble at the sight of Space Invaders' two-dimensional villains. His company has incorporated the aliens into the Back Off, a rubber doormat meant to frighten unwanted visitors. When someone comes within six feet of the mat, a row of flashing green Invaders appears on a rectangular panel, moving slowly from left to right.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A doormat meant to frighten unwanted visitors  and to appeal to video game aficionados  features flashing images of the green aliens from Space Invaders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR video game aficionados who came of age in the late 1970s, the aliens from Space Invaders are symbols of menace. Shaped like robotic jellyfish, they would descend inexorably toward a player's laser cannon, coming in ever-faster swarms as the game progressed. Sooner or later, the aliens would triumph, leaving the defeated player to contemplate -- if only for an instant -- the horrors of life on a conquered planet.</p>
        <p>Jérôme Fischbach, a partner in the Paris design firm La Tête au Cube, hopes that consumers of a certain age -- roughly 30 to 45 -- still tremble at the sight of Space Invaders' two-dimensional villains. His company has incorporated the aliens into the Back Off, a rubber doormat meant to frighten unwanted visitors. When someone comes within six feet of the mat, a row of flashing green Invaders appears on a rectangular panel, moving slowly from left to right.</p>
        <p>''Usually a doormat is supposed to welcome you,'' said Mr. Fischbach, a co-founder of La Tête au Cube in 2005 with his design collaborator, Thierry Galloni d'Istria. ''What we wanted was a doormat that would guard your door, like a guard dog.''</p>
        <p>The Back Off grew out of a meeting that Mr. Fischbach and Mr. d'Istria had last summer with representatives of Shygaon, a lighting company based in the Paris suburb of Aubervilliers. Shygaon sells a patented lighting technology, called B-Blink, that allows for optical fibers to be embedded in thin objects: posters, necklaces, even T-shirts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fischbach and Mr. d'Istria were impressed by B-Blink, and they brainstormed about ways to use it in a La Tête au Cube product. They tried creating a handbag with a light-up interior, but couldn't quite overcome a power supply issue: illuminating a cluttered purse required an outsized battery pack. So the two designers moved to Plan B: an arcade-themed doormat that would be equal parts security device and nostalgic ornament.</p>
        <p>''Space Invaders means something to our generation,'' said Mr. Fischbach, who is 36, explaining why he and Mr. d'Istria chose the aliens. He added that they were also influenced by the work of a French artist named Invader, who travels the world installing mosaic aliens in public places.</p>
        <p>Designing the Back Off, Mr. Fischbach said, was fairly straightforward. He and Mr. d'Istria placed a motion sensor on the doormat's upper-left corner, a spot where it is unlikely to be stepped on. The product's screen is powered by a box containing four 1.5-volt batteries; a footlong cord connects the box to the mat.</p>
        <p>The cord doubles as a crude anti-theft device.</p>
        <p>''People, of course, are afraid of having the doormat stolen,'' Mr. Fischbach said. ''But you can stick the box behind the door, and have the cable go underneath the door.'' If the Back Off is secured that way, he continued, swiping the mat will cause its power supply to break.</p>
        <p>THE mats are made at a Shygaon facility in Tunisia. They went on sale in late April, and the initial 300 were snapped up by video game connoisseurs. The Back Off, priced at $110, is currently available to American consumers at a lifestyle Web site, CharlesandMarie.com; La Tête au Cube's own site, LaTeteAuCube.com, also has the mats in stock, though priced at 90 euros (around $122).</p>
        <p>Despite the Back Off's success so far, Mr. Fischbach said that there were no plans to create versions with non-green aliens. That might upset some purists: in the original Space Invaders, released in 1978, the aliens were white.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Fischbach thinks that white aliens aren't quite the stuff of nightmares. ''I don't know why,'' he said, ''but when you imagine things from space, you imagine things that are fluorescent green.''</p>
        <p>THE GOODS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
