<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New President for the Long Island Rail Road</title>
    <meta content="10weekliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/10weekli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853546"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Farmingdale (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Transportation Authority</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Island Rail Road Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Guard (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Helena E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Israel, Steve (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Suozzi, Thomas R (County Exec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saslow, Linda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE1DF1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="876" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New President for the Long Island Rail Road</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Week on Long Island</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA SASLOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Saslow, Linda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Week column; Metropolitan Transportation Authority names Helena Williams president of Long Island Rail Road, effective June 18; US Repr Steve Israel announces plan to build $86 million center in Farmingdale to be used for New York National Guard training, equipment storage and administrative functions; Nassau County Executive Thomas Suozzi calls for consulting firms to devise detailed blueprint for consolidating functions of local government entities; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Long Island Rail Road will soon have a new president, one with a background in mass transit but none in running a railroad.</p>
        <p>The Metropolitan Transportation Authority announced on Monday that Helena E. Williams, 51, had been chosen to head the L.I.R.R., the nation's busiest commuter railroad. Ms. Williams was the president of Long Island Bus, which is also overseen by the authority, from 1993 to 1998. After that, she was a deputy Nassau County executive before becoming senior counsel at Cablevision. She will be the first woman to run the L.I.R.R.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Long Island Rail Road will soon have a new president, one with a background in mass transit but none in running a railroad.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Long Island Rail Road will soon have a new president, one with a background in mass transit but none in running a railroad.</p>
        <p>The Metropolitan Transportation Authority announced on Monday that Helena E. Williams, 51, had been chosen to head the L.I.R.R., the nation's busiest commuter railroad. Ms. Williams was the president of Long Island Bus, which is also overseen by the authority, from 1993 to 1998. After that, she was a deputy Nassau County executive before becoming senior counsel at Cablevision. She will be the first woman to run the L.I.R.R.</p>
        <p>She will take over on June 18 for the acting president, Raymond P. Kenny, who has overseen the railroad agency since James J. Dermody departed last September.</p>
        <p>The selection of Ms. Williams to run an agency with 6,300 employees and 700 miles of track on 11 branches surprised many people involved in transportation because of her lack of commuter railroad experience.</p>
        <p>Bill Henderson, the executive director of the Permanent Citizens Advisory Committee to the Metropolitan Transportation Authority, said that while Ms. Williams was an insider to the authority, ''it was not in the way we might have expected.''</p>
        <p>''The Long Island Rail Road is a challenging operation to run,'' Mr. Henderson said.</p>
        <p>Among those challenges, he said, were the gaps between trains and platforms at stations; labor issues; and changes that will accompany the East Side Access to Grand Central Terminal and the third-track Main Line corridor improvement.</p>
        <p>Mitchell H. Pally, the authority board member for Suffolk, was not concerned. ''Regardless of whether she actually ran a railroad or not, I have no qualms about her ability to do the job,'' he said. ''Helena Williams is one of the most professional transportation experts in our region.</p>
        <p>At the bus system, Ms. Williams, a longtime Nassau resident, oversaw the introduction of the MetroCard, the transition to a fleet of natural-gas buses and a service for disabled riders.</p>
        <p>L.I. Is Getting a Center To Mobilize the Guard</p>
        <p>Long Island will soon have a central location for mobilizing New York National Guard and reserve forces in the event of a natural disaster or terrorist attack.</p>
        <p>United States Representative Steve Israel, a Democrat from Huntington, announced a plan on Monday to build a four-story, $86 million center in Farmingdale, on the Nassau-Suffolk border, to be used for training, equipment storage and administrative functions. It will be at the site of a former Nike missile base on Baiting Place Road, west of Route 110 and south of Republic Airport.</p>
        <p>The 224,000-square-foot center will have the capacity to house 1,275 uniformed personnel from the New York Army National Guard and reserves from the Navy, Marine Corps and Army.</p>
        <p>It will enable training, coordinating and mobilizing for any disaster that requires the deployment of the Guard, Mr. Israel said. He also said it would ''bolster the homeland security and emergency preparedness of Long Island as a region.''</p>
        <p>The Farmingdale center is New York's first to combine four components of the armed forces. Troops from the Air National Guard and the Air Force are stationed at the Niagara Falls Air Reserve Station, and a facility is under construction in upstate Scotia that will house Army, Navy and Marine units.</p>
        <p>The center, to be paid for by the federal government, is expected to be completed by July 2010. Demolition of existing buildings will begin this month.</p>
        <p>Suozzi Calls for Plans To Shrink Local Government</p>
        <p>In an effort to reduce property taxes for Nassau County residents, County Executive Thomas R. Suozzi has announced more plans to reduce the size of local government.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, he called for consulting firms to devise a detailed blueprint for consolidating the functions of local government entities.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, Mr. Suozzi and State Comptroller Thomas P. DiNapoli proposed measures to make special districts statewide more accountable and make information more accessible to taxpayers. The plan would require special districts, which levy their own taxes, to obtain public input during the budget process and to disclose all financial information at public meetings.</p>
        <p>''One of the contributing factors to our high taxes is that we have too many governments,'' Mr. Suozzi said. ''While we were the first county to form a centralized police department and a centralized department for health services, nothing has happened since then. At the end of this process, we should be able to say, 'If we consolidate these entities, it will save you X dollars, and your services will either remain as good as they are now or improve.' ''</p>
        <p>The blueprint for government consolidation will receive $500,000 from the County Legislature and a $250,000 grant from the Horace Hagedorn Foundation.</p>
        <p>Last month, Mr. Suozzi called on 17 sewer and sewage-treatment districts to study how to work toward consolidation into a countywide system. The study has begun, he said.</p>
        <p>Nassau will issue a request for proposals to provide a feasibility study and cost analysis for six other service areas: libraries, school districts, parks, road maintenance, garbage and water supply.</p>
        <p>''I personally think we should have one library system in Nassau County,'' Mr. Suozzi said. ''But after we study how much money that would save and how it would impact the services, only then we will know if it makes sense.''</p>
        <p>THE WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
