<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Keeper of the Bees Faces His Biggest Task Yet</title>
    <meta content="10colctCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/10colct.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853548"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hirshey, Gerri</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weiss, Edward A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erickson, Edna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E0DF1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="861" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Keeper of the Bees Faces His Biggest Task Yet</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Keeper of the Bees Faces His Biggest Task Yet</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERRI HIRSHEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hirshey, Gerri</byline>
      <dateline>WILTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gerri Hirshey column on Edward Weiss of Wilton, Conn, who gave up work as marketer of heavy industrial equipment in 1974 and turned to beekeeping; Weiss, in interview, comments on his mentor, late Edna Erickson, and his take on mysterious syndrome known as colony collapse disorder; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A scrawled note in Edward A. Weiss's workroom directs a visitor behind the garage, whence a strong voice yells: ''I'm bottling. Be right there.''</p>
        <p>Rivers of gorgeous amber honey have flowed into jars labeled Wilton Gold since 1974, when Mr. Weiss gave up his work as a marketer of heavy industrial equipment and turned to beekeeping full time. He was first entranced by the secret and wondrously complex lives of bees in 1966, when he moved to Fairfield County.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A master beekeeper is fielding questions from all over the state about a mysterious syndrome that is threatening honeybees and the agricultural food chain worldwide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A scrawled note in Edward A. Weiss's workroom directs a visitor behind the garage, whence a strong voice yells: ''I'm bottling. Be right there.''</p>
        <p>Rivers of gorgeous amber honey have flowed into jars labeled Wilton Gold since 1974, when Mr. Weiss gave up his work as a marketer of heavy industrial equipment and turned to beekeeping full time. He was first entranced by the secret and wondrously complex lives of bees in 1966, when he moved to Fairfield County.</p>
        <p>The life-altering seduction is explained in his beekeeper's handbook, ''The Queen and I,'' a comprehensive and charming classic now in its third printing. It is a love story -- albeit with hive hardware and brood chamber specs -- that begins, ''I have been having an affair.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Weiss, known simply as Ed to his many apiculture acolytes, will turn 88 in August. He pulls on a cardigan to sit in the cool stone-walled room piled with wares for his beekeeping supply business: honeycomb frames, smokers, hive tools. On a wall behind him are snapshots of his ''two queens.'' The late Edna Erickson, a reclusive Danbury bee whisperer, first instructed him in the ancient arts of apiculture, then willed him her beekeeping-supply business. ''What could I do?'' Mr. Weiss says of the pushy bequest. ''I was already hooked.''</p>
        <p>The other photo is of his late wife, Anita, ''my partner in bees and absolutely everything else.''</p>
        <p>He is silent for a moment. The drone of the hives just outside is barely audible. ''On this very day, we would have been married 66 years,'' he says. At the height of their sweet venture in the late '80s, the couple had several hundred hives producing between 10,000 and 30,000 pounds of pure, unprocessed wildflower honey each season. Now, with the help of an assistant, Mr. Weiss is bottling 1,200 pounds of an accumulated honey reserve from those banquet years. And he keeps from 8 to 10 hives, which he expects will yield 400 to 500 pounds of honey a year.</p>
        <p>The taste of Wilton Gold is slightly savage, its floral sweetness haunting. ''It's the real deal,'' Mr. Weiss says.</p>
        <p>Western honeybees, Apis mellifera, live an average of six weeks, fulfilling their life's mission -- maintenance of the colony -- with a brilliant division of labor that has sustained them for 40 million years. Now that a mysterious syndrome known as colony collapse disorder, or C.C.D., is threatening honeybees and the agricultural food chain worldwide, Mr. Weiss finds himself fielding anxious questions from beekeepers all over the state.</p>
        <p>''I'm no scientist,'' he grumps. But he does know bees, well enough to be called the Bee Master of Connecticut, a patient and galvanizing educator revered by hobbyist beekeepers, entomologists, Boy Scouts earning beekeeping merit badges under his tutelage -- even Martha Stewart. ''I taught her beekeeping right here in this room when she was still a local caterer,'' Mr. Weiss says.</p>
        <p>O.K., so as a man of experience, if not hard science, what about this C.C.D. business?</p>
        <p>''Since I'm an old man, I've seen a lifetime of bee problems. I think perhaps a strange new virus is afoot. My attitude is that it will be solved eventually. But we're all holding our breaths.'' He cites stepped-up research on C.C.D. at Cornell and Penn State. ''They're hot on it,'' he says. ''Looking into pesticides, stress, viruses. And the bees just may figure it out first and heal themselves. Bees are so doggone smart.''</p>
        <p>Brilliant bee physics can keep the internal temperature of a hive at 90 degrees in the dead of a New England winter. Mr. Weiss says it is most often the carelessness of humans that thwarts such genius. ''I don't understand these hoity-toity types who can't stand a dandelion in their perfect lawns,'' he says. ''They apply chemicals like crazy. It's absolutely criminal.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Weiss has not had a hive collapse due to C.C.D., but says: ''I have losses up the kazoo from pesticides. It's heartbreaking every time. First, you notice the quiet, a cessation of activity. You open the top of the hive and the combs are empty. Then when you slide out the bottom tray, dead bees are piled high -- an unmistakable pesticide kill.''</p>
        <p>Years ago, he says, a local registry of beekeepers accessible to landscapers and arborists assured early warning. ''They'd call to say when and where they'd be spraying, and you could keep the bees safely in the hive that day.'' In the absence of such civility these days, the Backyard Beekeepers Association, a 200-member organization that Ed and Anita Weiss founded in 1993, is vigilant and proactive in guarding the local apian population. Members participate in a program to produce locally bred disease-free queen bees; they stay in touch with one another and state entomologists.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weiss's phone is trilling with urgent requests -- to pick up mail-order queens, order more supplies. I leave him in the company of many buzzing thousands of ''my girls,'' a 21-year-old feline and a visiting crow that makes off with cat food leftovers daily, then deposits the can back in the driveway. ''If a crow can recycle,'' Mr. Weiss says, ''you'd think we humans can safeguard these marvelous bees.''</p>
        <p>E-mail: conn@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: conn@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
