<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pakistani Papers Are Snatched, And Their Publishers Warned</title>
    <meta content="10paki" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/thecity/10paki.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853676"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Threats and Threatening Messages</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pakistani Post (Newspaper)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Urdu Times (Newspaper)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Farooqi, Mahammed</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rehman, Khalil Ur</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brady, Emily</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Threats and Threatening Messages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Pakistan</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Committee to Protect Journalists</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E3D61F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="505" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pakistani Papers Are Snatched, And Their Publishers Warned</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pakistani Papers Are Snatched, and Their Publishers Warned</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EMILY BRADY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brady, Emily</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Publishers of Pakistani Post and Urdu Times, free weekly newspapers delivered to Pakistani markets and restaurants around New York metropolitan area, say copies of their papers have been snatched; publishers Mahammed Farooqi and Khalil Ur Rehman say they have been threatened; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS the owner and publisher of an Urdu-language paper based in Jamaica, Queens, Mahammed Farooqi has grown accustomed over the years to his paper disappearing on occasion. But with two recent issues of his Pakistan Post, every copy vanished. And then he was threatened.</p>
        <p>The trouble began on May 23, a Wednesday, the day Mr. Farooqi's free weekly is delivered to Pakistani markets and restaurants around the metropolitan area. Mr. Farooqi's phone began ringing that day with calls from business owners notifying him that a group of men driving around in a van were snatching all his papers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The publishers of two Urdu-language newspapers in Queens are facing harassment and threats by unknown critics who want them to stop printing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS the owner and publisher of an Urdu-language paper based in Jamaica, Queens, Mahammed Farooqi has grown accustomed over the years to his paper disappearing on occasion. But with two recent issues of his Pakistan Post, every copy vanished. And then he was threatened.</p>
        <p>The trouble began on May 23, a Wednesday, the day Mr. Farooqi's free weekly is delivered to Pakistani markets and restaurants around the metropolitan area. Mr. Farooqi's phone began ringing that day with calls from business owners notifying him that a group of men driving around in a van were snatching all his papers.</p>
        <p>''This is the first time they pick up the newspaper from all over,'' said Mr. Farooqi, 48, a determined man with thick white hair who began his journalism career in Pakistan at age 19. Virtually the entire May 23 press run, 10,000 copies, was taken, he said.</p>
        <p>But The Pakistan Post has not been the only vanishing Urdu-language newspaper. Many copies of The Urdu Times, another weekly, also disappeared that Wednesday, according to Khalil Ur Rehman, its publisher and editor. More copies of both papers also disappeared the following Wednesday, May 30. Last Thursday, Mr. Farooqi said that copies of the issue distributed June 6 had disappeared from four places in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Mr. Farooqi, Mr. Rehman and the Committee to Protect Journalists, which has investigated the situation, cited several articles that appeared in one or both newspapers that may have sparked the seizure of the newspapers. They included regular columns written by Jack Rosen, the chairman of the American Jewish Congress; an article about a press conference by Israel's representative to the United Nations; and several pieces about alleged financial wrongdoing with respect to the Pakistan Independence Day parade, held annually in August.</p>
        <p>On May 24, Mr. Farooqi drove around Brooklyn replacing the missing papers with what few copies he had left. As he was leaving a Pakistani restaurant in Brighton Beach, he said, two men approached him. ''They told me, 'Look, just stop printing this newspaper; if you don't, you and your family will face the consequences,' '' said Mr. Farooqi, who filed a complaint with the police. Mr. Rehman said he was similarly warned.</p>
        <p>Joel Simon, the executive director of the Committee to Protect Journalists, said that violence against journalists in the United States, while rare, is much more common in the ethnic press. His organization wrote a letter to Mayor Bloomberg last week asking him to help speed the police investigation into the disappearance of the newspapers and the threats against the editors.</p>
        <p>Members of the Pakistani community have urged Mr. Farooqi to attempt to meet with whoever is objecting to his coverage, but the publisher has refused. He wants to handle things in a more American way: he wants to sue. ''I am from a tribal society and I don't want to live in a tribal society here, too,'' he said. ''I don't want to hug each other and resolve the problem like that. I want to go to court.''</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
