<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shop Stewards On Fantasy Island?</title>
    <meta content="10fisher.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="58" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="RESIDENTS/WORKERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Fisher Island (Fla)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Service Employees International Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swartz, Mimi</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E0D81130F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="4602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shop Stewards On Fantasy Island?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mimi Swartz</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Swartz, Mimi</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mimi Swartz article on effort by Service Employees International Union to organize people who work on Fisher Island, Fla, condominium complex where starting salaries can be as low as $8.50 an hour even though island's 1,400 residents have estimated average income of $10 million a year; describes island as stark metaphor for income inequality in America; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One thing that can be said about the war for Fisher Island is that everyone involved wants only what's best for the place. This 216-acre property with 34 sprawling Mediterranean-style luxury condominium buildings sits conveniently surrounded by Miami Beach, the city of Miami, Biscayne Bay and the Atlantic Ocean. It is an island paradise containing every possible indulgence that someone with a great deal of money and an enormous need to be coddled might desire. Fisher Island's fortunate 1,400, fewer than one-third of them full-time residents, can play on the golf course created by P. B. Dye, of the famed course-design family, or on one of 18 tennis courts -- clay, grass and hard court surfaces. There are two marinas -- one for large yachts and one for larger yachts -- and a state-of-the-art gym, complete with a Roman waterfall for aching backs and, along with yoga and Pilates, classes with names like Waves of Steel and Esto Es Tango! The sand on the beach is imported from the Bahamas and cleared daily of seaweed, so it is always soft and white. There are swimming pools, not just at the health spa, but also in each condo complex. Perpetually blooming tropical flowers perfume the air; caged toucans twitter in banyan trees, flamingos wade lazily in their own private pond. Kids attend a special island private school where cameras, wired into the condos, allow anxious parents to monitor their offspring from home; the playground, naturally, is gently padded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One thing that can be said about the war for Fisher Island is that everyone involved wants only what's best for the place. This 216-acre property with 34 sprawling Mediterranean-style luxury condominium buildings sits conveniently surrounded by Miami Beach, the city of Miami, Biscayne Bay and the Atlantic Ocean. It is an island paradise containing every possible indulgence that someone with a great deal of money and an enormous need to be coddled might desire. Fisher Island's fortunate 1,400, fewer than one-third of them full-time residents, can play on the golf course created by P. B. Dye, of the famed course-design family, or on one of 18 tennis courts -- clay, grass and hard court surfaces. There are two marinas -- one for large yachts and one for larger yachts -- and a state-of-the-art gym, complete with a Roman waterfall for aching backs and, along with yoga and Pilates, classes with names like Waves of Steel and Esto Es Tango! The sand on the beach is imported from the Bahamas and cleared daily of seaweed, so it is always soft and white. There are swimming pools, not just at the health spa, but also in each condo complex. Perpetually blooming tropical flowers perfume the air; caged toucans twitter in banyan trees, flamingos wade lazily in their own private pond. Kids attend a special island private school where cameras, wired into the condos, allow anxious parents to monitor their offspring from home; the playground, naturally, is gently padded.</p>
        <p>Fisher Island residents expect the best because, even though they come from all over the globe -- the U.S., South America, Europe or Asia -- they all have one thing in common, which is that they are among the world's wealthiest people. The 2000 census described the island as having the highest per capita income in the United States; the average net worth of the grown-up inhabitants has been estimated at around $10 million. In a lot of ways, it's a very precious small town, or as one resident put it, ''This is really like a little 'Mayberry R.F.D.' ''</p>
        <p>This Mayberry, however, is only accessible by ferry or private helicopter or seaplane. The curious who linger too long at the island's ferry station just off Miami's MacArthur Causeway inevitably come face to face with uniformed, clipboard-wielding security guards wearing the obligatory aviator sunglasses, who will explain politely but in no uncertain terms that no one makes the crossing without authorization from an island resident. But this much-prized seclusion -- evoking both the White House and the most exclusive 1980s Manhattan nightclub -- is currently threatened with the massing on the mainland of the Service Employees International Union. Organizers are trying to convince the island's residents that the people who trim their hibiscus hedges, wipe smudges off their porticos and change the sheets at the Fisher Island Hotel and Resort (suites: $1,200 a night) deserve better than a starting wage of as little as $8.50 an hour. The workers themselves -- many of them immigrants -- readily agree that it's nearly impossible to support a family on $17,680 a year, but organizers are still trying to persuade enough of them that joining a union will make matters better.</p>
        <p>You could say that the trouble between the people who live on Fisher Island and the people who work there began with a shrewd, combative man named Stephen Lerner, who is in charge of organizing janitors, landscapers, housekeepers and kitchen workers nationally for the S.E.I.U., headquartered in Washington. For some time, Lerner, 49, had been looking for a way to fight growing income inequities around the country, but at the same time to ask, in a metaphorical way, just what kind of country America was becoming by allowing those inequities to persist. He saw people happy to spend money on tanning butlers and poodle pedicures but unwilling to pay more to those who made their pampered lives possible -- those who almost invisibly cleaned up after them.</p>
        <p>Lerner, who has dark eager eyes and an intense, ironic manner, never went to college -- he was busy organizing farmworkers as a young man in the 1970s and has been organizing ever since -- but he has always been a reader and a thinker. Over time, he became intrigued with the notion that we are now less a world of nations than one of global cities that serve as corporate and financial trade capitals. The prosperous and powerful -- corporate executives, investment bankers, private-equity firm managers -- conduct their business from London or New York or Singapore or Dubai while the poor follow in their wake, hoping to escape their lot by working for the international corporations that serve them, providing janitorial, landscaping and security services. ''Workers everywhere have the same employers,'' Lerner likes to say. Eventually he began to wonder whether there might be a place where he could shift that dynamic: a locale with wealthy residents and poor workers, and nothing in between. A place where a union like his could show the rich how easy it would be to propel the less fortunate into the rapidly disappearing American middle class.</p>
        <p>Then, while organizing janitors at three Miami-area universities last year, Lerner began to hear talk of an island where people with stratospheric wealth were tended by workers making near poverty-level wages. Fisher Island, it seemed to Lerner, was the perfect microcosm of, and the perfect metaphor for, the growing divide between rich and poor, not just in Miami, but in South Florida, the U.S. and beyond. ''This is not a traditional union campaign,'' he told me of the struggle for Fisher Island. ''This is a fight for what kind of world we are going to have.'' And then Stephen Lerner grinned, like a man taking aim at a very large target he couldn't wait to hit.</p>
        <p>To the untrained eye, Miami looks like a gleaming, modern Xanadu. The high-rise condos that stretch past Boca Raton, the glamorous South Beach hotel guests chattering in English, Spanish, German and Portuguese, the building cranes dotting the skyline all suggest a mind-boggling, global prosperity. As more land is filled and more luxury high-rises built, more jobs are created; Miami's unemployment rate is a slim 3.4 percent. But there has been surprisingly little trickle down to the city's poorest residents, many of them immigrants from Haiti and South and Central America. Most of the new jobs are at the bottom of the income scale. According to a Census Bureau survey of cities conducted in 2005, Miami ranked close to the bottom for annual household median income -- $25,211. Twenty-eight percent of its residents live in poverty, according to the same survey, the third-highest poverty rate in the nation behind Cleveland and Detroit. The same luxury buildings that create jobs have also displaced potential workers; developers have razed low-income neighborhoods to make way for wealthier newcomers, mostly from Europe and South America, who see Miami as a perfect spot for second, third or fourth homes.</p>
        <p>The income disparity in Miami has become a cause célÃ  RESIDENTS/WORKERS Mimi Swartz is an executive editor at Texas Monthly.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Mimi Swartz is an executive editor at Texas Monthly.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
