<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Story Line at Stadium, the Pirates Play the Part of Extras Perfectly</title>
    <meta content="10pins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/sports/baseball/10pins.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Pittsburgh Pirates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Pittsburgh Pirates</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Clemens, Roger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sanchez, Freddy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E1D9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="790" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Story Line at Stadium, the Pirates Play the Part of Extras Perfectly</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Story Line at Stadium, the Pirates Play the Part of Extras Perfectly</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Freddy Sanchez was waiting to field grounders before the bottom of the sixth inning, but, like a fan, the Pirates second baseman peeked into the Yankees dugout at Roger Clemens. Even Sanchez was wondering what Clemens would do next.</p>
        <p>As Clemens marched through the dugout and accepted congratulations yesterday, the decibel level at Yankee Stadium increased. It grew louder and louder, the fans hoping that Clemens would acknowledge them. Sanchez was curious enough about how Clemens would react to hang out by shortstop and stare at him as well.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Pirates stumbled around the Bronx Saturday and showed why they were a safe team for Roger Clemens’s ballyhooed return to the baseball grind.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Freddy Sanchez was waiting to field grounders before the bottom of the sixth inning, but, like a fan, the Pirates second baseman peeked into the Yankees dugout at Roger Clemens. Even Sanchez was wondering what Clemens would do next.</p>
        <p>As Clemens marched through the dugout and accepted congratulations yesterday, the decibel level at Yankee Stadium increased. It grew louder and louder, the fans hoping that Clemens would acknowledge them. Sanchez was curious enough about how Clemens would react to hang out by shortstop and stare at him as well.</p>
        <p>Clemens never provided the curtain call. He perhaps figured it was too early to celebrate, especially since the Yankees had a one-run lead. Eventually, behind Clemens's six respectable innings and with the sloppy Pirates acting as the perfect foils, the Yankees prevailed, 9-3.</p>
        <p>The Pirates were charged with two errors, but they made several defensive mistakes. Catcher Ronny Paulino allowed five stolen bases and did not pursue a foul pop that landed in the first few rows of seats. Shortstop Jack Wilson let a grounder sneak under his glove. Left fielder Jason Bay made one throw that could have been measured for hang time. José Bautista did not cover third on one steal attempt.</p>
        <p>The Pirates were not as challenging for Clemens as the Chicago White Sox would have been at U.S. Cellular Field. Clemens would have started in Chicago on Monday if he had not aggravated a groin problem. Instead, the Pirates stumbled around the Bronx and showed why they were a safe team for Clemens's ballyhooed return to the baseball grind.</p>
        <p>''It's fun any time you face Clemens,'' Wilson said. ''He's a competitor. He's a future Hall of Famer.''</p>
        <p>Ten months, 10,000 story lines and one prorated $28 million contract later, the Pirates were once again extras in Clemens's baseball show. Clemens was with the Yankees, not the Houston Astros, yesterday, but the result was the same. He stifled the Pirates twice in a 16-day stretch last August while with the Astros.</p>
        <p>Seven of the eight position players in Pittsburgh's lineup played in those games. Adam LaRoche, the only player who did not, opposed Clemens as a member of the Atlanta Braves in Clemens's last start of the regular season. So the Pirates who took the first swings of 2007 against Clemens had a lot of recent experience against him.</p>
        <p>What did the Pirates see? They saw a spirited 44-year-old pitcher whose fastball averaged 89 to 91 miles an hour, who, as always, depended heavily on his split-fingered fastball and who sweated to squeeze 108 pitches out of his ancient arm. Clemens struck out seven, five with his splitter, but did not seem as intimidating as he has been in the past. Still, the Pirates praised Clemens and his trusty splitter.</p>
        <p>''I certainly didn't see any rust on his split-finger,'' right fielder Ryan Doumit said. Clemens's splitter, Wilson said, looks exactly like his fastball and then ''dives down in the dirt,'' making hitters look defensive or foolish or both if they have a two-strike count. Wilson said that Clemens also threw a slow curveball that he had not previously seen.</p>
        <p>The Pirates, a young team, used a patient strategy in trying to boost Clemens's pitch count. Bautista, the leadoff hitter, singled and scored in the first. He saw 19 pitches in three at-bats. Clemens unleashed 43 pitches in the first two innings, tossing mostly fastballs, but he calmed down to make it through six while allowing three runs.</p>
        <p>''To his credit, when he needed to get a couple of outs, he got them,'' Pittsburgh Manager Jim Tracy said.</p>
        <p>Actually, that was only partly true. With the Yankees leading, 3-1, in the fourth, Clemens walked Paulino to put Pirates on first and second with two outs. He made the hole deeper by going 2-0 on Wilson. After a strike, Wilson drilled a fastball to right-center field for a two-run double that tied the score.</p>
        <p>Should Clemens be able to bury a light hitter like Wilson in such a vital situation? Even Clemens would acknowledge that he should. While Clemens had not pitched in the majors in more than eight months, he is not graded on a curve. The Yankees are paying Clemens huge money and hope that he will have a major impact on their push for a postseason berth.</p>
        <p>There will be much greater challenges for Clemens than the Pirates, who started the day with the seventh fewest runs in the majors. Those challenges begin with Clemens's next assignment: a start against the Mets.</p>
        <p>''I think he's motivated them right now,'' Paulino said. ''You have a guy who is going to the Hall of Fame. They're going to try and get the win, no matter what.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
