<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knowing Not</title>
    <meta content="Oppenheimer.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/books/review/Oppenheimer-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bible</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bible</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Prothero, Stephen</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Religious Literacy: What Every American Needs to Know  and Doesnt (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E5DD1530F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knowing Not</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Knowing Not</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RELIGIOUS LITERACY</p>
        <p>What Every American Needs to</p>
        <p>Know -- and Doesn't.</p>
        <p>By Stephen Prothero.</p>
        <p>296 pp. HarperSanFrancisco. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most Americans are ignorant of the Bible and key concepts of religion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RELIGIOUS LITERACY</p>
        <p>What Every American Needs to</p>
        <p>Know -- and Doesn't.</p>
        <p>By Stephen Prothero.</p>
        <p>296 pp. HarperSanFrancisco. $24.95.</p>
        <p>By MARK OPPENHEIMER</p>
        <p>Decline-and-fall books, like E. D. Hirsch Jr.'s ''Cultural Literacy'' and Allan Bloom's ''Closing of the American Mind,'' can leave the reader torn between depression and elation: by detailing how stupid everyone else is, the authors leave us feeling better about ourselves. (''I know which has more members, the Supreme Court or the Supremes!'') So it was with smug anticipation that I opened ''Religious Literacy,'' Stephen Prothero's jeremiad about declining religious knowledge. Most Americans ''cannot name one of the four Gospels,'' Prothero writes, ''and many high school seniors think that Sodom and Gomorrah were husband and wife.'' Religious illiteracy cuts across generations, and the devout scarcely know more than the secular do. In one survey of high school students, most evangelicals did not recognize that ''Blessed are the poor in spirit'' is from the Sermon on the Mount.</p>
        <p>Alas, unlike Jay Leno humiliating an audience that can't name any of the Twelve Apostles, Prothero, a professor of religion at Boston University and author of ''American Jesus: How the Son of God Became a National Icon,'' does not simply let us enjoy this intellectual condescension. After all, he wants us to remember, it's the rare world crisis that is not at least partly rooted in religion -- consider Sudan, Iraq, Israel. And because domestic controversies, like those over intelligent design or gay marriage, are also often bound up with religion, Prothero writes, ''you need religious literacy in order to be an effective citizen.'' Raising the stakes further, he argues (as other scholars have before him) that the 1993 conflagration that killed the Branch Davidians at Waco might have been averted had the F.B.I. better understood David Koresh's apocalyptic theology.</p>
        <p>Prothero's corrective proceeds in two parts. First, he offers a diagnosis: a 100-page précis of American religious history that tells a familiar story, from the Puritans to today's pluralism, remarkably well. He also argues, persuasively, that both conservatives and liberals are to blame for American religious illiteracy. Beginning with 19th-century Unitarians, liberal Christians dropped Bible learning for good deeds and progressive politics. But conservatives have also turned away from religious study. From Charles Finney in the Second Great Awakening to contemporary megachurch preachers, evangelicals have won converts by advocating enthusiastic faith at the expense of religious study. For most American Christians, Prothero laments, catechisms, confessions and even reading the Bible itself are often Sunday-school afterthoughts.</p>
        <p>Conservative evangelicals, uniting in pursuit of political influence, played down old denominational differences. ''Family values'' became for the right what ''justice'' or ''peace'' was for the left -- a catchphrase that obviates the need for religious literacy. The specifics of Prothero's thesis are not new, but his formulation makes the culture wars seem more misguided than ever. Left, right, ecumenical, evangelical -- we all abandoned the Bible.</p>
        <p>I say ''the Bible'' because although Prothero gives generous space to Islam and other world religions, he is adamant, against multicultural pieties, that Americans most need to know Christianity. Prothero also risks angering liberals by dismissing popular writers like Karen Armstrong and Huston Smith, who ''in the name of pluralism'' have furthered the view ''that all religions were different paths up the same mountain.'' Prothero's admirably old-fashioned opinion is that to rebuild core knowledge we must resist comforting ecumenical myths. He calls for requiring that all high schoolers take both a Bible class and a world religions class.</p>
        <p>The second half of the book is a glossary of religious terms that ''Americans need to know.'' Prothero's judicious selection includes descriptions of the major world religions, the largest Christian denominations, key figures from the Bible (Abraham, Judas Iscariot, the prodigal son), various concepts (nonviolence, jihad) and several living figures (Billy Graham, the Dalai Lama). For a sense, here are the contents of a pair of facing pages, chosen at random: hijab, Hinduism, Holocaust, Holy Communion.</p>
        <p>I would have omitted Billy Graham, who's irrelevant today, and given Rick Warren his own entry. And I'd have avoided the cultural trivia: Hanukkah need not be defined with reference to Adam Sandler's ''Hanukkah Song,'' and Moses does not, in fact, ''figure in'' William Faulkner's ''Go Down, Moses.'' But the bigger problem is with Prothero's premise, that deeper religious knowledge would produce saner, wiser public discourse. Would wider knowledge of the Baltimore Catechism or New Testament stories really advance debates on, say, stem-cell research? Or would people find new reasons to cling to their old opinions?</p>
        <p>George W. Bush did say that Jesus Christ was his ''favorite philosopher,'' but Susan Sontag was correct to point out that ''Bush didn't mean, and was not understood to mean, that ... his administration would actually feel bound by any of the precepts or social programs expounded by Jesus.'' Americans have crafted a religiosity that is more an idea of religiosity; together we have largely agreed to forgo its content. Prothero, raised Episcopal, loves doctrine and Scripture, and I sympathize. But with some exceptions -- a grasp of the Sunni/Shia distinction comes to mind -- religious knowledge is not necessary to be a good citizen. It's just necessary if one wants to be an educated person. It enriches our lives. That's blessing enough.</p>
        <p>Mark Oppenheimer is the author of ''Knocking on Heaven's Door: American Religion in the Age of Counterculture.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Mark Oppenheimer is the author of ''Knocking on Heaven's Door: American Religion in the Age of Counterculture.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
