<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WHAT'S ON SUNDAY NIGHT</title>
    <meta content="10tvcol" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/arts/television/10tvcol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853481"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E4DF1E30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WHAT'S ON SUNDAY NIGHT</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What’s on Sunday Night</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHRYN SHATTUCK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>8 P.M. (CBS) THE 61ST ANNUAL TONY AWARDS -- This ceremony honoring excellence on Broadway features the stiffest competition for best actor (Boyd Gaines, Frank Langella, Brian F. O'Byrne, Christopher Plummer and Liev Schreiber) in years. It also includes some notable musical performances, including numbers from ''Grey Gardens,'' ''Spring Awakening'' and ''110 in the Shade.'' More than 60 nominees and other celebrities, including Harry Connick Jr., Claire Danes, Jeff Daniels, Brian Dennehy, Carla Gugino, Neil Patrick Harris, Audra McDonald, Bernadette Peters, Kevin Spacey and Rainn Wilson, are scheduled to appear. But not one gets to lay claim to the title of host.</p>
        <p>8:30 P.M. (Fox) THE LOOP -- In this second-season premiere, Sam (Bret Harrison) continues his journey through less-than-friendly skies as the youngest executive at a major airline. Joining him on the flight: Russ (Philip Baker Hall), his relentlessly demanding boss; Meryl (Mimi Rogers), his zealously affectionate colleague; Darcy (Joy Osmanski), his bitterly overqualified secretary; and Sully (Eric Christian Olsen), his older brother, who seems to want to bring the plane down. First stop: Iceland.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (Discovery) BUILDING THE FUTURE -- This four-part series looks at new methods of survival as the globe warms up and renewable resources dwindle, starting with the search for new energy sources, at 9, and the development of innovative shelters for those combating earthquakes, floods, storms and other natural disasters, at 10. Parts 3 and 4 will be shown on June 17 at 9 and 10 p.m.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (HBO) THE SOPRANOS -- The conclusion to the Sopranos saga, written and directed by the series's creator, David Chase, and starring James Gandolfini (above right, with Tony Sirico) as the man in charge of everyone's life except his own.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (HGTV) RED HOT AND GREEN -- The designers Danny Seo and Carter Oosterhouse offer advice on building homes that look good while incorporating environmentally friendly materials and energy-efficient strategies.</p>
        <p>10 P.M. (Showtime) THE TUDORS -- It's time to loosen your cinch: This bodice ripper starring Jonathan Rhys Meyers as a sizzling hot Henry VIII comes to an end with Cardinal Thomas Wolsey (Sam Neill) paying the ultimate price.</p>
        <p>10:05 P.M. (HBO) JOHN FROM CINCINNATI -- We know, we know. His name isn't really John, and he's not from Cincinnati. Just who he is, exactly, is the mystery at the heart of this new drama series from David Milch, the creator of ''Deadwood,'' and the novelist Kem Nunn. In it a stranger arrives in the coastal town of Imperial Beach, Calif., and brings redemption to a family of surfers for whom catching the perfect wave is a distant memory. Bruce Green plays Mitch Yost, the clan patriarch; Rebecca De Mornay is Cissy, his wife; and Luke Perry is Linc, a surf entrepreneur hoping to sponsor Shaun (Greyson Fletcher), Mitch's 13-year-old grandson. Also involved are Brian Van Holt as Shaun's father, a drug-addicted derelict, and Ed O'Neill as a neurotic family friend and former cop. Austin Nichols stars as the mysterious, wealthy stranger named John.</p>
        <p>KATHRYN SHATTUCK</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>8 P.M. (CBS) THE 61ST ANNUAL TONY AWARDS This ceremony honoring excellence on Broadway features the stiffest competition for best actor (Boyd Gaines, Frank Langella, Brian F. O’Byrne, Christopher Plummer and Liev Schreiber) in years. It also includes some notable musical performances, including numbers from “Grey Gardens,” “Spring Awakening” and “110 in the Shade.” More than 60 nominees and other celebrities, including Harry Connick Jr., Claire Danes, Jeff Daniels, Brian Dennehy, Carla Gugino, Neil Patrick Harris, Audra McDonald, Bernadette Peters, Kevin Spacey and Rainn Wilson, are scheduled to appear. But not one gets to lay claim to the title of host.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>8 P.M. (CBS) THE 61ST ANNUAL TONY AWARDS -- This ceremony honoring excellence on Broadway features the stiffest competition for best actor (Boyd Gaines, Frank Langella, Brian F. O'Byrne, Christopher Plummer and Liev Schreiber) in years. It also includes some notable musical performances, including numbers from ''Grey Gardens,'' ''Spring Awakening'' and ''110 in the Shade.'' More than 60 nominees and other celebrities, including Harry Connick Jr., Claire Danes, Jeff Daniels, Brian Dennehy, Carla Gugino, Neil Patrick Harris, Audra McDonald, Bernadette Peters, Kevin Spacey and Rainn Wilson, are scheduled to appear. But not one gets to lay claim to the title of host.</p>
        <p>8:30 P.M. (Fox) THE LOOP -- In this second-season premiere, Sam (Bret Harrison) continues his journey through less-than-friendly skies as the youngest executive at a major airline. Joining him on the flight: Russ (Philip Baker Hall), his relentlessly demanding boss; Meryl (Mimi Rogers), his zealously affectionate colleague; Darcy (Joy Osmanski), his bitterly overqualified secretary; and Sully (Eric Christian Olsen), his older brother, who seems to want to bring the plane down. First stop: Iceland.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (Discovery) BUILDING THE FUTURE -- This four-part series looks at new methods of survival as the globe warms up and renewable resources dwindle, starting with the search for new energy sources, at 9, and the development of innovative shelters for those combating earthquakes, floods, storms and other natural disasters, at 10. Parts 3 and 4 will be shown on June 17 at 9 and 10 p.m.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (HBO) THE SOPRANOS -- The conclusion to the Sopranos saga, written and directed by the series's creator, David Chase, and starring James Gandolfini (above right, with Tony Sirico) as the man in charge of everyone's life except his own.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (HGTV) RED HOT AND GREEN -- The designers Danny Seo and Carter Oosterhouse offer advice on building homes that look good while incorporating environmentally friendly materials and energy-efficient strategies.</p>
        <p>10 P.M. (Showtime) THE TUDORS -- It's time to loosen your cinch: This bodice ripper starring Jonathan Rhys Meyers as a sizzling hot Henry VIII comes to an end with Cardinal Thomas Wolsey (Sam Neill) paying the ultimate price.</p>
        <p>10:05 P.M. (HBO) JOHN FROM CINCINNATI -- We know, we know. His name isn't really John, and he's not from Cincinnati. Just who he is, exactly, is the mystery at the heart of this new drama series from David Milch, the creator of ''Deadwood,'' and the novelist Kem Nunn. In it a stranger arrives in the coastal town of Imperial Beach, Calif., and brings redemption to a family of surfers for whom catching the perfect wave is a distant memory. Bruce Green plays Mitch Yost, the clan patriarch; Rebecca De Mornay is Cissy, his wife; and Luke Perry is Linc, a surf entrepreneur hoping to sponsor Shaun (Greyson Fletcher), Mitch's 13-year-old grandson. Also involved are Brian Van Holt as Shaun's father, a drug-addicted derelict, and Ed O'Neill as a neurotic family friend and former cop. Austin Nichols stars as the mysterious, wealthy stranger named John.</p>
        <p>KATHRYN SHATTUCK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
