<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Not-So-Private Idaho, Pursuing Democracy</title>
    <meta content="10jens" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/arts/television/10jens.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853486"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Idaho</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Public Broadcasting Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jensen, Elizabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wiseman, Frederick</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">State Legislature (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Idaho</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Idaho</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE4DF1E30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="857" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Not-So-Private Idaho, Pursuing Democracy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Not-So-Private Idaho, Pursuing Democracy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH JENSEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jensen, Elizabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on new 217-minute long Frederick Wiseman documentary State Legislature, about twelve-week session of Idaho state legislature, which will be shown on PBS; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A DOCUMENTARY by Frederick Wiseman is always a slowly unfolding story, but even by those standards ''State Legislature,'' his latest, promises little in the way of pulse-quickening drama.</p>
        <p>Filmed in 2004 during an entire 12-week session of the Idaho Legislature, the documentary runs 217 minutes, in the range of his recent work. But those 3 1/2 hours were culled from 160 hours of 16-millimeter film, which is ''a lot even for me,'' said Mr. Wiseman, who typically shoots 80 to 100 hours per project. ''I discovered that politicians like to talk, and so, unlike some of my other movies, it's a very talk-dependent movie.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A documentary by Frederick Wiseman is always a slowly unfolding story, but even by those standards “State Legislature,” his latest, promises little in the way of pulse-quickening drama.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A DOCUMENTARY by Frederick Wiseman is always a slowly unfolding story, but even by those standards ''State Legislature,'' his latest, promises little in the way of pulse-quickening drama.</p>
        <p>Filmed in 2004 during an entire 12-week session of the Idaho Legislature, the documentary runs 217 minutes, in the range of his recent work. But those 3 1/2 hours were culled from 160 hours of 16-millimeter film, which is ''a lot even for me,'' said Mr. Wiseman, who typically shoots 80 to 100 hours per project. ''I discovered that politicians like to talk, and so, unlike some of my other movies, it's a very talk-dependent movie.''</p>
        <p>As with all but one of the 34 other documentaries this 77-year-old filmmaker has reliably turned out over four decades, ''State Legislature'' will be shown on PBS. (In New York it will be seen at 9 p.m. Wednesday on WNET.)</p>
        <p>The one exception was his previous film, on the inner workings of Madison Square Garden. It was abruptly pulled on the eve of its public release when officials at the Cablevision Systems Corporation, the Garden's owner, withheld final approval, which Mr. Wiseman had uncharacteristically granted the company. His lawsuit to get the film released is in the pretrial phase.</p>
        <p>As a result of that impasse it has been a four-year drought for viewers accustomed to getting a Wiseman fix every year or two. Meanwhile documentaries have flourished. Michael Moore's ''Fahrenheit 9/11'' set box office records in 2004 for a documentary; ''Spellbound'' captivated audiences as it followed charming spelling bee contestants. The Iraq war, the 2004 presidential candidates, corporate fraud at Enron, the politics of Fox News: all came under the scrutiny of filmmakers with strong points of view, employing distinctly lively techniques.</p>
        <p>By comparison Mr. Wiseman's no-narration, profoundly subtle, intricate examinations of enduring institutions can seem quaintly outmoded. ''State Legislature,'' for one, makes no partisan claims, and it doesn't emphasize the private meetings between lobbyists and politicians, to which his cameras had access, over the testimony of average citizens.</p>
        <p>At a time when the United States is debating the merits of exporting democracy, Mr. Wiseman said, ''I thought it would be interesting to show how it works at one of the very basic institutions, namely a state legislature.'' (Idaho was chosen because, with just two floors, Mr. Wiseman thought it would be logistically easy, and also because the state gave permission.)</p>
        <p>He said he grappled with what the film was about but ultimately came to this conclusion: ''It's not about how the votes came out on specific issues and my taking a partisan view about the results, but it was more to show the process -- unless it sounds pretentious -- of how democracy works. The debates, the committee hearings, the discussions in the corridor: I was very impressed with the seriousness with which they took the task and the civility toward each other and their respect for the process.''</p>
        <p>The politicians, he noted, spent their time on water rights, mad cow disease, cellphone voyeurism, secondhand smoke and telephone rates, ''things most of us don't think about, don't want to think about, don't care about but are nonetheless extremely important to the way we live.'' He added, ''I think I came away with a great deal of respect for people who are willing to take the time to participate in the democratic process, as opposed to someone like me who has all sorts of opinions but doesn't participate.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wiseman's old-fashioned approach still attracts plenty of fans among those for whom the mainstream media have become too superficial. European critics in particular found plenty of insights into the American system when the film made its premiere at the Berlin Film Festival in February. He managed to find humor in the hours of talk as well, most notably when a John Stossel-quoting libertarian went up against a prosecutorial politician in a debate over whether contractors should be licensed.</p>
        <p>The recent flourishing of the documentary landscape hasn't made much impact on Mr. Wiseman. ''For me things are as they always have been,'' he said. ''I work in relative isolation.'' He would like theatrical distribution for his films, he said, but the offers have been scant -- because of the length of his films, he speculated -- and the money offered not lucrative enough to give up the rights. He said he depended on the ''small but steady'' educational sales of his films.</p>
        <p>A wider audience will soon be able to discover Mr. Wiseman's work however. Plans aren't final, but at some point in the fall his Web site, zipporah.com, will start selling all his old work to the public on DVD, going back to the groundbreaking ''Titicut Follies'' (1967), about horrific conditions inside a prison for the criminally insane. Previously only tapes were available, and only to the educational market.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wiseman is in Paris working on a movie about Catherine Samie, the Comédie Française actress who starred in a Samuel Beckett play he recently directed there. He hasn't made release plans but said he was hopeful PBS would show it. ''They have never turned one down,'' he said, ''but you can't ever take anything for granted.''</p>
        <p>TELEVISION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
