<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For 40-Somethings, 'Retire' Still Means Getting Hitters Out</title>
    <meta content="10chass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/sports/baseball/10chass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853351"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Texas Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Clemens, Roger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ryan, Nolan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Spahn, Warren</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Chass, Murray</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hernandez, Orlando</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Maddux, Greg</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE4D9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1597" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For 40-Somethings, 'Retire' Still Means Getting Hitters Out</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For 40-Somethings, ‘Retire’ Still Means Getting Hitters Out</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nolan Ryan pitched his sixth no-hitter when he was 43. Then he pitched his seventh no-hitter when he was 44. Warren Spahn won 21 games when he was 40. Two birthdays later, he won 23 games.</p>
        <p>Ryan retired at 46, Spahn at 44. Phil Niekro last pitched when he was 48, Tommy John when he was 46.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This season has featured a record number of 40-year-old starting pitchers, and that was even before Roger Clemens returned to pitch for the Yankees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nolan Ryan pitched his sixth no-hitter when he was 43. Then he pitched his seventh no-hitter when he was 44. Warren Spahn won 21 games when he was 40. Two birthdays later, he won 23 games.</p>
        <p>Ryan retired at 46, Spahn at 44. Phil Niekro last pitched when he was 48, Tommy John when he was 46.</p>
        <p>''My body was 46, but my arm had just had its bar mitzvah,'' John said, alluding to his groundbreaking elbow reconstruction in 1974.</p>
        <p>Forty-year-old pitchers are not a new development in the major leagues, but their population is growing. This season has featured a record number of 40-year-old starting pitchers, and that was even before Roger Clemens returned to the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Clemens, who will be 45 in August, is the oldest. With his start yesterday -- he was credited with the victory at Yankee Stadium -- he became the 11th pitcher 40 or older to start this season.</p>
        <p>Orlando Hernández of the Mets would argue that the number is only 10. He says he is only 37, and that's how the Mets list him on their roster. But other records show him to be four years older, and even the Mets' general manager, Omar Minaya, said before they joined the Mets that Hernández, a Cuban defector, was four years older.</p>
        <p>El Duque's age, however, did not discourage Minaya from trading for him a year ago and signing him to a two-year, $12 million contract last November, right after he probably turned 41.</p>
        <p>Jamie Moyer (44), David Wells (44), Randy Johnson (43), Tom Glavine (41), Greg Maddux (41), Tim Wakefield (40), Woody Williams (40), Curt Schilling (40) and John Smoltz (40) do not dispute their age.</p>
        <p>Never before have so many 40-year-olds pitched in the majors. Previously, the largest contingent of pitchers who made at least 20 starts in a season, according to Elias Sports Bureau, which doesn't count Hernández, was last season when Clemens, Moyer, Wells, Johnson, Glavine, Wakefield and Williams qualified at that level. Wakefield and Williams didn't turn 40 until August.</p>
        <p>The largest group before that was six in 1987: John, Ryan, Don Sutton, Steve Carlton and the Niekros, Phil and Joe.</p>
        <p>Reflecting on the trend toward more active 40-year-olds, John said: ''What does that tell you? It tells you there is a dearth of talent.''</p>
        <p>John, however, wasn't questioning the talent of the senior contingent.</p>
        <p>''If you look at the guys who are pitching other than Clemens and Randy and Smoltz, they have captured the essence of how to pitch,'' he said. ''You don't have to blow the doors off the wagons to be really good. The younger guys would do well to take heed on that.''</p>
        <p>Young pitchers have had plenty of opportunities to watch 40-year-olds pitch this season and even pitch against each other. Six times, the seniors have started the same games.</p>
        <p>Moyer and Johnson started against each other three weeks apart last month, each time establishing plateaus for the combined age of starting left-handers, the second time at 88 years 90 days.</p>
        <p>Moyer and Glavine have started against each other twice and very likely will again as the Phillies and the Mets contend for the National League East title.</p>
        <p>Johnson and Wells opposed each other April 24, as did Glavine and Smoltz on May 24. It was the third time for Glavine and Smoltz, but the first two games came before Smoltz joined the 40 crowd. Maddux and Smoltz started against each other six days before Smoltz turned 40. Johnson and Glavine missed each other by a day.</p>
        <p>Eight of the 10 40-years-olds pitch in the National League, giving new meaning to the league's old name, the senior circuit. No senior matchups have occurred in the American League because Schilling and Wakefield are teammates. Now that Clemens is returning to the majors, that absence could be corrected when the Yankees and the Red Sox resume their rivalry later in the season.</p>
        <p>Entering yesterday, most of the 40-year-olds had winning records. Only Williams (2-8) and Wakefield (5-7) did not. Smoltz had the most victories among the group (seven), and Hernández had the lowest earned run average (1.94). Smoltz, at 2.83, had the lowest among admitted 40-year-olds.</p>
        <p>''I would say this is a unique group,'' said John, who manages the Bridgeport (Conn.) Bluefish in the independent Atlantic League. ''They are dedicated, intelligent, baseball savvy, they take care of themselves and they enjoy pitching.''</p>
        <p>None of them, however, have reached John's retirement age, 46.</p>
        <p>''They retired me,'' he said. ''I sent out tapes to teams I thought I could help either starting or out of the bullpen. But no one called, so I went into my managerial career. I managed my sons in Little League.''</p>
        <p>Told You So</p>
        <p>A recent column suggesting that the Yankees erred in trading Gary Sheffield last winter prompted disagreement from some readers who raised several issues about him.</p>
        <p>They questioned his clubhouse demeanor without ever having been in a clubhouse with him (his teammates have liked him wherever he has played), they recalled how he admitted once deliberately throwing away a grounder (when he was a young, immature kid) and they said he was past his prime as a hitter.</p>
        <p>For the last point, the critics might have been looking at Sheffield's April performance. Through April 29, Sheffield batted .193 with six runs batted in and one home run in 23 games. In 35 games since, before yesterday's game with the Mets, Sheffield batted .317 with 34 R.B.I. and 15 home runs.</p>
        <p>His slugging percentage in the first 23 games was .265; it was .676 in the next 35. The Yankees, vulnerable to left-handed starting pitchers, could have used that kind of right-handed production.</p>
        <p>Something Brewin'</p>
        <p>Prince Fielder is threatening to be this season's Ryan Howard.</p>
        <p>Fielder, the Milwaukee first baseman, slugged his N.L.-leading 22nd home run in the Brewers' 61st game. Last season, Howard hit his 21st home run in Philadelphia's 59th game.</p>
        <p>It was after the All-Star Game, though, that Howard took off on his way to 58 home runs, making him the eighth player to hit that many.</p>
        <p>In his first 53 games after the All-Star Game, the 26-year-old Howard hit 28 home runs, including two on Sept. 8 to raise his total to 56. He had only two homers in his last 21 games as teams walked him with greater frequency.</p>
        <p>Fielder, 23, hit 10 home runs in 17 games heading into last night's game.</p>
        <p>Short on Offense</p>
        <p>If they had not bolstered their infield defense, the 2004 Boston Red Sox weren't going anywhere. Acquiring Orlando Cabrera and installing him at shortstop was part of their solution.</p>
        <p>But five days after the Red Sox won the World Series, Cabrera became a free agent and the Red Sox let him leave. He signed with the Angels three days after the Red Sox signed Édgar Rentería to play short.</p>
        <p>Rentería, however, lasted only one season in Boston. The Red Sox were especially dissatisfied with his major-league-leading 30 errors and traded him to Atlanta. Their new shortstop was the slick-fielding Álex González.</p>
        <p>He committed only seven errors last season, but the Red Sox weren't satisfied with his hitting, so they let him go, instead signing Julio Lugo to a four-year, $36 million contract. González signed with Cincinnati for three years and $14 million.</p>
        <p>Has Lugo satisfied the Red Sox' desire for more offense at shortstop? He was hitting .217 before last night's game, declining steadily from a .256 average in April to .209 in May to .133 in June. González was hitting .268 for the Reds with 11 home runs, compared with four for Lugo.</p>
        <p>Good Pitching Beats No Hitting</p>
        <p>In the first 65 days of the season, teams played a total of five 1-0 games. Then in a three-day stretch last week, teams played four 1-0 games.</p>
        <p>Two of last week's games were in the National League West, where San Diego edged Los Angeles and Arizona topped San Francisco.</p>
        <p>The American League, which had no 1-0 games until June 2, had a pair of 1-0 games last Tuesday and Thursday. Cleveland defeated Kansas City on a home run by Franklin Gutiérrez, and Boston edged Oakland on a home run by David Ortiz.</p>
        <p>Texas-Size Disaster</p>
        <p>Through no fault of their new owner, the Texas Rangers won the A.L. West title in 1998 and 1999, giving them three division championships in four years. Since then, they have been one of the worst-run organizations in the major leagues. That development can be attributed to the owner, Tom Hicks.</p>
        <p>Hicks became the Rangers' owner in June 1998. After enjoying the fruits of the previous ownership -- which at one time included George W. Bush -- Hicks has overseen four consecutive last-place finishes and three successive third-place finishes. This season, the Rangers are back in last place by a sizable margin.</p>
        <p>After the 2001 season, Hicks fired Doug Melvin, the general manager who built the division winners, and replaced him with the very expensive John Hart, under whom the Rangers have made no progress in four years. An inexperienced Jon Daniels, Hart's assistant for not much more than a season, replaced Hart in October 2005.</p>
        <p>Hicks also became an easy mark for the agent Scott Boras, who induced Hicks to give Alex Rodriguez a record $252 million contract and to give Chan Ho Park, an unproductive pitcher, $65 million for five years.</p>
        <p>Melvin became the general manager of the Milwaukee Brewers and has turned a perennial loser into a team that is in first place in the N.L. Central.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
