<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Stirring Belmont, the Filly Beats the Fellas</title>
    <meta content="10belmont" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/sports/othersports/10belmont.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853387"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Velazquez, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Pletcher, Todd</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEED9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="966" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Stirring Belmont, the Filly Beats the Fellas</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In a Stirring Belmont, the Filly Beats the Fellas</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>No, it did not start well for Rags to Riches, or for that matter the filly's jockey, John Velazquez, or her trainer, Todd Pletcher. She stumbled out of the gate for the 139th running of the Belmont Stakes, and for a heart-in-your-throat moment, Velazquez and Pletcher had a simultaneous and bitter thought: Why did we do this? Why did we run this girl against the boys when history told us it was foolish?</p>
        <p>Two minutes later, however, Velazquez had Rags to Riches eyeball-to-eyeball with the Preakness champion, Curlin, and Pletcher was on his feet in a clubhouse box, his heart thumping in his chest, his voice uncharacteristically growing louder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rags to Riches, a filly, became the first of her sex to take the final leg of the Triple Crown in more than a century.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>No, it did not start well for Rags to Riches, or for that matter the filly's jockey, John Velazquez, or her trainer, Todd Pletcher. She stumbled out of the gate for the 139th running of the Belmont Stakes, and for a heart-in-your-throat moment, Velazquez and Pletcher had a simultaneous and bitter thought: Why did we do this? Why did we run this girl against the boys when history told us it was foolish?</p>
        <p>Two minutes later, however, Velazquez had Rags to Riches eyeball-to-eyeball with the Preakness champion, Curlin, and Pletcher was on his feet in a clubhouse box, his heart thumping in his chest, his voice uncharacteristically growing louder.</p>
        <p>''Come on, baby! Come on, baby! Come on, baby!'' Pletcher cried, his voice growing more urgent with every stride.</p>
        <p>He is a placid man by nature, and a humbled one when it comes to Triple Crown races. He has been the nation's leading trainer three years running, but before yesterday he had saddled 28 horses in the Kentucky Derby, the Preakness Stakes and the Belmont, and had not visited the winner's circle.</p>
        <p>Both Rags to Riches and Curlin had 4-for-5 records, but Curlin was a mammoth colt and Rags to Riches was just the 22nd filly to enter the Belmont. Only two had won the race, the last a filly named Tanya in 1905.</p>
        <p>Now, they were alone in the final quarter-mile of the Belmont's grueling and once-in-a-lifetime distance of a mile and a half, rolling like a pair of freight trains, with Curlin taking the inside rail and Rags to Riches, a head in front of him, simply refusing to give up. Suddenly, the 46,870 spectators at this grand old racetrack on Long Island were on their feet and echoing Pletcher's cry of ''Come on, baby!''</p>
        <p>This was a Belmont for the ages. No matter which horse anyone here had bet on, it was clear in the final strides that the only payoff anyone wanted was to witness something they would not forget. When Rags to Riches crossed the finish line an elegant head in front of Curlin, Pletcher was pumping his arm in full exultation, as was Velazquez aboard the filly, and the crowd erupted in a deafening ovation.</p>
        <p>''It hadn't been done in 102 years,'' said Pletcher, his face flushed from Rags to Riches' feat.</p>
        <p>Velazquez, too, was stunned. In 2004, he was awarded the Eclipse Award as the nation's outstanding jockey, but he entered yesterday's race 0 for 20 in Triple Crown races.</p>
        <p>''My heart stopped,'' Velazquez said of the initial stumble. ''Good thing this was a mile and half and she had time to get herself together.''</p>
        <p>The Belmont's marathon distance, indeed, played to Rags to Riches' strengths. Her father, A. P. Indy, won the Belmont in 1992, and her mother, Better Than Honour, produced last year's winner, Jazil. While C P West and Slew's Tizzy led the field of seven around the track for the first mile in a tepid 1:40.23, Velazquez angled Rags to Riches to the outside and let her settle into fifth place, still within four lengths of the leaders.</p>
        <p>''Todd and I had talked and all we wanted was to give her a good chance around the turn,'' Velazquez said. ''We didn't want her jumping up and wasting a lot of energy. We didn't want too much dirt kicked in her face.''</p>
        <p>Robby Albarado aboard Curlin knew exactly where Rags to Riches was located. First, he bulled Hard Spun and jockey Garrett Gomez out of the way.</p>
        <p>''The filly jumped right on top of me,'' Albarado said.</p>
        <p>She inched ahead of Curlin in the stretch. Still, there was a long half-mile to go, and Albarado believed that Curlin was going to run down Rags to Riches just as he did the Kentucky Derby winner Street Sense in the Preakness.</p>
        <p>But it was not happening this time. ''They came home fast and he never stopped,'' Albarado said of Curlin.</p>
        <p>Rags to Riches and Curlin were actually going super fast -- they covered the last quarter-mile in 23 4/5 seconds, trading head bobs like painted horses on a carousel.</p>
        <p>''I thought at one point he could come back and get her, but she is tough,'' Albarado said.</p>
        <p>How tough? Beyond the dismal record of fillies in the Belmont, consider the fact that only 38 of them have started in the Kentucky Derby since it began in 1875, and only 3 have won: Regret in 1915, Genuine Risk in 1980 and Winning Colors in 1988. In the Preakness, which was first run in 1873, a total of 52 have tried to beat the boys and 4 came out winners, the last being Nellie Morse in 1924.</p>
        <p>The owners of Rags to Riches, Michael Tabor and Derrick Smith, knew what they were up against when they decided to try her here. They hoped their move would be received as a sporting gesture because, beyond the $600,000 first-place check, it hardly increased the horse's value.</p>
        <p>''It was all about prestige,'' Tabor said.</p>
        <p>When Velazquez guided Rags to Riches back to the winner's circle with the blanket of white carnations draped over her neck, Smith, Tabor, Pletcher and Velazquez knew it was about much more than prestige. What had started with a stumble out of the starting gate was ending with a coronation for an unlikely queen in the sport of kings.</p>
        <p>Rags to Riches was greeted with raucous cheers by a crowd that understood it had witnessed something special. Why had Tabor, Smith and Pletcher entered Rags to Riches in a grueling race when history told them they were likely to end up looking like fools?</p>
        <p>''We thought it was something the public would like to see,'' Tabor said. ''It was a fantastic feat.''</p>
        <p>He was correct on both counts.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
