<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Rendezvous in New Jersey</title>
    <meta content="10cheer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/sports/baseball/10cheer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853329"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CHEERING SECTION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Memorabilia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Memorabilia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E1DC163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="874" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Rendezvous in New Jersey</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Rendezvous in New Jersey</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VINCENT M. MALLOZZI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Our eyes met across a baseball field, where our 6-year-old sons, who are teammates, were taking batting practice. We exchanged awkward smiles and quick head bobs. I glanced at my wife to make sure she had not picked up any of our signs.</p>
        <p>No words were spoken, but we knew that we would see each other later that evening, as we had on several occasions the two previous weeks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A tale of two collectors and their love affair with sports memorabilia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Our eyes met across a baseball field, where our 6-year-old sons, who are teammates, were taking batting practice. We exchanged awkward smiles and quick head bobs. I glanced at my wife to make sure she had not picked up any of our signs.</p>
        <p>No words were spoken, but we knew that we would see each other later that evening, as we had on several occasions the two previous weeks.</p>
        <p>We felt safest meeting in the dark but guilty about keeping our spouses there. We knew that it was only a matter of time before we were caught.</p>
        <p>''Where are you going now?'' my wife said after we put our two sons to bed.</p>
        <p>Another excuse. Another rendezvous. Another expensive, late night out on the town.</p>
        <p>''We need milk,'' was all I heard as I walked out the door.</p>
        <p>I drove excitedly to our secret meeting place, where passions would soon collide. A light rain began to fall as I arrived. I got out of my car and was greeted by the same devilish grin I must have been wearing on my face. We spoke briefly in the glow of our headlights, then I was handed a card. My heart thumped the way it did when I wore a younger man's cleats.</p>
        <p>''It's Barry Bonds's rookie card,'' said Matt, my friend and fellow collector. ''After all the business you've given me, I'm throwing it in for free.''</p>
        <p>Matt and I have been carrying on a love affair with sports memorabilia since we were children. But lately, Matt's vast collection of autographed, game-used, professionally graded, laminated and authenticated items have begun to take over his home, so he has decided to start selling off a few of his most treasured pieces.</p>
        <p>Our wives never understood this passion. They never appreciated the sentimental and monetary value attached to such gems as a football autographed by Joe Montana, a hockey stick signed by Wayne Gretzky or a Julius Erving rookie card as mint as Dr. J's game was back in his high-flying prime.</p>
        <p>Our wives cannot see the whole picture. They will never know the amount of determination, patience and good fortune it takes to put together a piece of baseball history like the rawhide relic in my den signed by most members of the 3,000-hit club. To our wives, all the time we spend collecting this stuff is a waste of time.</p>
        <p>So we decided to meet and conduct our business in private.</p>
        <p>Matt, a Yankees fan, drove his pickup that night to a parking lot adjacent to a baseball field in town. The back of his truck was stockpiled with pinstriped goodies that even a die-hard Mets fan like myself could not resist.</p>
        <p>I spent several hours admiring dozens of items, like bats signed by Reggie Jackson and Alfonso Soriano, a baseball signed by members of the 500-home run club and a duplicate of Mickey Mantle's signed rookie contract.</p>
        <p>I raced home late that night with the score of a lifetime: a baseball autographed by Joe DiMaggio and photos autographed by Mantle and Roger Clemens. I picked up several other balls signed by Whitey Ford, Phil Rizzuto and Hideki Matsui, and Matt was nice enough to toss in an autographed photo of Joe Torre, a Mike Schmidt bobblehead, ceramic statues of Babe Ruth and Lou Gehrig, and an assorted pile of Mike Piazza cards. I even remembered to make a pit-stop at a 7-Eleven for milk.</p>
        <p>I hoped that my wife would be asleep when I got home, but this time, she was waiting for me. She demanded I give her an explanation for staying out late, but all I gave her was the milk.</p>
        <p>She asked if I had lipstick on my face.</p>
        <p>''No,'' I said, as I began to walk away. ''I bought a Slurpee at 7-Eleven.''</p>
        <p>She would not let it go.</p>
        <p>''Where were you?'' she insisted.</p>
        <p>Gulp.</p>
        <p>I finally confessed -- to everything. I told her about Matt and about all those wild nights in Atlantic City hotels when I was supposed to be away on business, but was really attending card shows and memorabilia auctions. I told her about the many garage sales I had visited over the years and about all those late nights online, exchanging messages with perfect strangers while she slept.</p>
        <p>''EBay,'' I told her, ''might have been the worst thing that ever happened to us.''</p>
        <p>After I confessed, I apologized about spending too much time on a hobby that has become an obsession, if not an addiction. I apologized for signing her birthday card with a Sharpie, but denied buying her a pair of shoes because I needed the box to store additional baseball cards. I said I was sorry for booking our Las Vegas vacation in February without telling her that the N.B.A. All-Star Game was to be played there, and for saying that getting Shaquille O'Neal's autograph was the highlight of the trip.</p>
        <p>I let her tee off on me for a while as I stood there doing my best bobblehead impersonation. I stopped bobbing and began to babble, and then the phone rang.</p>
        <p>It was Matt.</p>
        <p>''I just told my wife everything, she knows all about us,'' he said. ''It's over.''</p>
        <p>CHEERING SECTION E-mail: cheers@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: cheers@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
