<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kiplagat Leaves All the Rest Behind</title>
    <meta content="10run" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/sports/othersports/10run.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853346"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="RUNNING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">New York City Marathon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York City Marathon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Kiplagat, Lornah</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E6D9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kiplagat Leaves All the Rest Behind</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kiplagat Leaves All the Rest Behind</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the hint of the horn, Lornah Kiplagat broke like a sprinter out of imaginary starting blocks. In two steps, she was in the lead on Central Park West. Barely a block later, Kiplagat again made the New York Mini women's 10-kilometer a race for second place.</p>
        <p>She cut a solitary but familiar figure yesterday morning as she entered Central Park, surging up the hills and gliding elegantly down. Fans cried out, ''Lornah!'' or her nickname, ''Simba!'' -- Swahili for lion -- while Kiplagat, a Kenyan-born Dutch citizen, left the elite women's field in the dust on the way to her third straight victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lornah Kiplagat finished in 32 minutes 10 seconds for her fourth victory in the 36th running of the New York Mini women’s 10-kilometer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the hint of the horn, Lornah Kiplagat broke like a sprinter out of imaginary starting blocks. In two steps, she was in the lead on Central Park West. Barely a block later, Kiplagat again made the New York Mini women's 10-kilometer a race for second place.</p>
        <p>She cut a solitary but familiar figure yesterday morning as she entered Central Park, surging up the hills and gliding elegantly down. Fans cried out, ''Lornah!'' or her nickname, ''Simba!'' -- Swahili for lion -- while Kiplagat, a Kenyan-born Dutch citizen, left the elite women's field in the dust on the way to her third straight victory.</p>
        <p>''When I start, I don't have a strategy,'' Kiplagat, 33, said, smiling. ''I just go.''</p>
        <p>Her five-second lead in the first mile grew to 25 seconds at the halfway mark, 3.1 miles. Kiplagat slowed toward the end to high-five fans and finished in 32 minutes 10 seconds for her fourth victory in the 36th running of this race.</p>
        <p>Kim Smith, a Providence College graduate from New Zealand, came in eight seconds behind. Mara Yamauchi of Britain leaned past Benita Johnson of Australia to grab third place in 32:21, providing the only real drama of the race.</p>
        <p>Smith, 25, said that in the first mile she thought to herself: ''All right, Lornah's won this. Let's try to go for second place.''</p>
        <p>When, exactly, in the first mile did she know? ''Probably at the start,'' Smith said, laughing. ''It would be like suicide to go with her.''</p>
        <p>This is the intimidating hold Kiplagat has over her competitors on the road, especially this road. Only Grete Waitz and Tegla Loroupe have more victories (five) at the Mini, sponsored by the New York Road Runners.</p>
        <p>Kiplagat, coming off the biggest victory of her career, at the eight-kilometer world cross-country championship in March, said she would like to surpass Waitz and Loroupe here.</p>
        <p>''It's my race,'' she said. ''I have no pressure. I have no stress going into it.''</p>
        <p>Since winning last year's title, Kiplagat set the 20K world record last October. She finished eighth in the New York City Marathon and clocked the fastest 10K this year, 31:05, at the World's Best 10K in Puerto Rico in February.</p>
        <p>Kiplagat lives in and has competed for the Netherlands since 2003 after marrying her coach, Pieter Langerhorst. Winning the world cross-country title in Kenya, where she operates the High Altitude Training Center to help young female runners, gave Kiplagat confidence.</p>
        <p>''I can do more than I think,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Kiplagat said yesterday that she struggled to maintain a healthy distance from the lead pack. Fear kept her from boredom.</p>
        <p>''You are a human being,'' she said. ''It's not like you drop in a quarter coin and you're going automatically. You never know, it could be the last two miles where I'm dead completely.</p>
        <p>''I'm trying to push more and more in case they catch me at the finish line. You just think about going harder and harder.''</p>
        <p>Her competition was resigned to that.</p>
        <p>''She's not known for going out too fast and dying,'' Yamauchi said. ''I thought, 'She'll stay strong.' ''</p>
        <p>Kiplagat made irrelevant the deep field that included Jelena Prokopcuka of Latvia, a two-time New York City Marathon winner who wanted to avenge her second-place finishes to Kiplagat in the Mini. Prokopcuka, bothered by the humid conditions, finished fifth in 32:26.</p>
        <p>Lidiya Grigoryeva, the 2007 Boston Marathon winner, was the only elite runner to drop out, because of leg cramps at the halfway point.</p>
        <p>By the time Kiplagat made it there in 15:39, she knew she could not break the course record of 30:29. So she savored the high-fives.</p>
        <p>''I am always going so quick past the finish line that I thought this was my time today to thank those people who are always coming out there for us,'' Kiplagat said.</p>
        <p>RUNNING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
