<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sharpe James Gets Warning About Charges</title>
    <meta content="10james" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/10james.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853374"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Newark (NJ)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">James, Sharpe</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EFD9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sharpe James Gets Warning About Charges</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Former Newark Mayor Warned About Charges</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal investigators have informed former Newark Mayor Sharpe James that he could soon face criminal charges for billing the city for tens of thousands of dollars in travel expenses during his final months in office and allowing his advisers and political allies to buy municipal property at rates far below market rates, according to a lawyer familiar with the case.</p>
        <p>Mr. James, who left office last June after 20 years as mayor, has been the subject of a federal inquiry for more than a year, after complaints from community leaders and political opponents that he was conducting a ''fire sale'' of vacant city lots to his associates at low prices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal investigators have informed Sharpe James that he could soon face criminal charges, according to a lawyer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal investigators have informed former Newark Mayor Sharpe James that he could soon face criminal charges for billing the city for tens of thousands of dollars in travel expenses during his final months in office and allowing his advisers and political allies to buy municipal property at rates far below market rates, according to a lawyer familiar with the case.</p>
        <p>Mr. James, who left office last June after 20 years as mayor, has been the subject of a federal inquiry for more than a year, after complaints from community leaders and political opponents that he was conducting a ''fire sale'' of vacant city lots to his associates at low prices.</p>
        <p>During the course of the investigation, federal agents have subpoenaed records and questioned city police officers who accompanied Mr. James and his aides on trips to Martha's Vineyard, Brazil and the Caribbean to determine whether he used his two city credit cards to pay for legitimate business expenses or for vacations.</p>
        <p>Early this month, the United States attorney's office sent Mr. James a ''target letter,'' offering him a chance to testify to the grand jury before its members vote on whether to hand up an indictment, according to the lawyer, who declined to be identified because the investigation was ongoing. The letter was first reported yesterday by The Star-Ledger of Newark.</p>
        <p>Neither Mr. James nor his lawyer, Raymond M. Brown, returned repeated calls for comment, but in the past they have insisted that the land sales and travel benefited Newark and its taxpayers.</p>
        <p>Michael Drewniak, a spokesman for United States Attorney Christopher J. Christie, also did not return calls requesting information about the case.</p>
        <p>The escalation of the investigation is an ominous sign for Mr. James, a brash and skilled politician who dominated Newark's affairs for a generation.</p>
        <p>He was swept into office as a reformer in 1986, unseating Kenneth Gibson, Newark's first black mayor, and presided over a surge in downtown development and rising real estate prices. But Mr. James's critics say he often overlooked the city's neighborhoods and schools at the expense of the power brokers and business leaders who contributed to his campaigns.</p>
        <p>Mr. James has been dogged by allegations of financial impropriety since 1995, when a federal investigation into his charitable foundation, the Sharpe James Civic Association, which could not account for hundreds of thousands of dollars, ended without any charges against the mayor. A separate investigation in 1997 led to the conviction of his chief of staff, who took kickbacks from insurance brokers.</p>
        <p>The reduced-rate sale of city property, which occurred mostly in 2005 and 2006, became a major issue in the campaign of Mayor Cory A. Booker, who was easily elected after Mr. James decided not to run.</p>
        <p>Mr. Booker criticized the James administration for selling property for $4 a square foot when similar parcels were appraised at more than $20, saying they were a giveaway of city resources to people with political connections. The Booker campaign also won an injunction blocking dozens of sales.</p>
        <p>Among those who were allowed to buy the low-priced property was Tamika Riley, a public relations consultant who occasionally traveled with Mr. James. Ms. Riley bought at least nine city-owned properties for $46,000 and later resold them for $700,000. She was also scheduled to buy three more properties before those sales were blocked by the injunction.</p>
        <p>Federal agents also subpoenaed records regarding a series of transactions involving Karen Hilliard-Johnson, who worked for Mr. James as a director in the city's Department of Economic and Housing Development. Property records show that in 2000, Ms. Hilliard-Johnson bought a home for $200,000 -- when similar homes were selling for well over $300,000 -- from a developer who later purchased dozens of low-cost city lots from the department where she worked. In an interview earlier this year, Ms. Hilliard-Johnson said she had done nothing improper.</p>
        <p>The investigation into the financial dealings of Mr. James's administration is one of a wide range of corruption inquires conducted by Mr. Christie since he took office in 2002. His office has won convictions or guilty pleas from more than 100 elected officials, including former Essex County Executive James Treffinger; former State Senate President John Lynch; and a variety of Monmouth County officials.</p>
        <p>Federal agents are now conducting at least two other high profile inquiries -- one into appropriations by the State Legislature and the other into a leasing deal involving United States Senator Robert Menendez, who was paid thousands of dollars in rent by a social service agency he helped get federal funding when he was a United States Representative -- but it is unclear whether either of those cases will lead to charges.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
