<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Doors Open: Chapter 5: Mr. Hate</title>
    <meta content="10funny--serial.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="44" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/magazine/10funny-serial-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853452"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE FUNNY PAGES: III: SUNDAY SERIAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rankin, Ian</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Doors Open (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1D81130F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2661" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Doors Open: Chapter 5: Mr. Hate</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">‘Doors Open’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ian Rankin
&lt;p&gt;</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chapter 5 of Ian Rankin's novel Doors Open; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last week: Mike, Allan and Professor Gissing paid a visit to Westie, one of Gissing's art students. Westie's skill is in mimicking other paintings, and the three men asked him whether he would be willing to paint exact replicas of six works for a fee. Westie soon came to understand that the men were planning a heist and asked to be part of it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This week, Chapter 5: Last thing Chib Calloway ever expected to see on a park bench in Edinburgh was a 6-foot-3 Hells Angel in a tailored, double-breasted suit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last week: Mike, Allan and Professor Gissing paid a visit to Westie, one of Gissing's art students. Westie's skill is in mimicking other paintings, and the three men asked him whether he would be willing to paint exact replicas of six works for a fee. Westie soon came to understand that the men were planning a heist and asked to be part of it.</p>
        <p>Last thing Chib Calloway ever expected to see on a park bench in Edinburgh was a 6-foot-3 Hells Angel in a tailored, double-breasted suit. Polished black brogues on his feet and a crisp white shirt with mauve silk tie. Long brown hair tied back into a presentable ponytail, just the single stud earring (though with lobes pierced for plenty more). He'd removed any other facial jewelry and was clean-shaven, cheeks glowing. When he raised his head, there was a giveaway blue dotted line along his throat</p>
        <p>-- a prison tattoo with the words cut here. As the man scratched his hands down his face, Chib noticed more tattoos on both sets of knuckles</p>
        <p>-- hate on the right, hate on the left. The guy sported laughter lines around his eyes, but the eyes themselves glowed with malevolence.</p>
        <p>Now this is more like it, Chib thought to himself. This I understand . . . sort of.</p>
        <p>It wasn't the bonniest part of town. Chib owned a couple of neighborhood bars and had been doing his weekly check. He was realistic enough to know the staff would be skimming but needed them to know he knew; that way, no one got too greedy. And if temptation struck, he would get out the photos of Donny Devlin, telling them: ''This is what I do to friends who cheat me. So consider what I'll do to you if that cash doesn't make its way back into my till. . . . ''</p>
        <p>Exiting the bar, happy enough with its turnover, he was crossing the road toward his car when he caught sight of the figure on the bench. It wasn't much of a park, just a playing field for soccer, crisscrossed with paths and a few benches where teenagers could gather on an evening to scare their elders. The figure rose from the bench and started pacing across the grass, measuring each stride. Chib clicked his fingers, letting his boys, Johnno and Glenn, know something was happening. Glenn reached a hand into the front of his jacket, even though there was nothing there -- the stranger wouldn't know that. All the same, the man grinned at the action, seeming to dismiss it. His eyes bore into Chib's. He was still advancing.</p>
        <p>''Easy, pal,'' Johnno said, stretching an arm in front of him. The man stopped and rubbed his hands down his face.</p>
        <p>HATE AND HATE.</p>
        <p>''I represent some people, Mr. Calloway.'' The accent was foreign, but Chib had expected as much. Had to be the Norwegians, that biker gang from Haugesund. ''You owe my friends for a shipment, and you have not been forthcoming.''</p>
        <p>Johnno had taken a step forward, but Chib swiped a hand against his shoulder. ''I've already told them the money's on its way,'' he rasped.</p>
        <p>''Repeatedly so, Mr. Calloway, but it's hardly a sustainable bargaining position, is it?''</p>
        <p>''Chewed a bloody dictionary,'' Glenn snorted. Johnno added a chuckle.</p>
        <p>''You mean because I speak English better than you?'' the stranger asked Glenn.</p>
        <p>''You don't just come barging up to Mr. Calloway,'' Glenn barked back. ''You show him some respect.''</p>
        <p>''The same respect he has displayed to my clients?''</p>
        <p>''You're not part of the gang then?'' Chib interrupted.</p>
        <p>''I'm a collector of debts, Mr. Calloway.''</p>
        <p>''For a percentage?''</p>
        <p>The man shook his head slowly. ''Straight fee, half in advance.''</p>
        <p>''Always collect the other half?''</p>
        <p>''So far.''</p>
        <p>''First time for everything,'' Johnno spat.</p>
        <p>The man ignored him; he had eyes only for Chib Calloway.</p>
        <p>''Tell them,'' Chib said, ''the money's coming. I've never let them down before, and I'm insulted they've sent you.'' He decided a wagged finger was in order. ''You report back to them, and we'll talk again next week.''</p>
        <p>''That won't be necessary, Mr. Calloway.''</p>
        <p>Chib's eyes narrowed. ''Why not?''</p>
        <p>The man offered a sliver of a smile. ''Because by next week, they'll have their money, paid in full.''</p>
        <p>Johnno guffawed; Glenn joined him. But to Chib, they suddenly seemed as useful as infants in a playground. The stranger appeared to agree, because he was already turning to leave. He paused long enough, however, to hand a folded scrap of paper to Chib. A row of numbers: cellphone.</p>
        <p>''Hey!'' Chib called out to him. ''What's your name, big man?''</p>
        <p>''People have a habit of calling me Hate,'' the giant said, striding away across the park.</p>
        <p>''I don't like this,'' Mike Mackenzie said.</p>
        <p>He was in Prof. Robert Gissing's office, door locked and with the plan of the warehouse spread across the desk and weighted down at its corners with oversize art books. Gissing had paid another visit to the warehouse and amended the plan accordingly.</p>
        <p>''Gatehouse,'' Mike recited, ''CCTV room, maybe a couple of guards with the tour party, and everyone on the tour itself. If you're sitting in the getaway van, that leaves just three of us to cope with all that.''</p>
        <p>''And one of you,'' Gissing reminded Mike, ''will need to be collecting the actual paintings.''</p>
        <p>Mike started nodding, then shook his head instead. ''We'll never manage.''</p>
        <p>''Cold feet, Michael?'</p>
        <p>''That's Allan's department, not mine.''</p>
        <p>''I think Allan will be fine,'' Gissing said, attempting reassurance.</p>
        <p>''It's just that it all seemed so perfect at the time,'' Mike complained, rubbing a palm across his forehead.</p>
        <p>''Most plans do, when you first think of them,'' Gissing offered.</p>
        <p>''Bottom line, Robert: We've been over this a dozen times, and you know it comes down to the same thing -- we need more hands.''</p>
        <p>Gissing folded his arms. ''Remember the old adage about too many cooks?''</p>
        <p>Mike just shrugged. ''The only other alternative is, this stays on the drawing board -- a nice dream, never realized.''</p>
        <p>Gissing pursed his lips in thought. ''So where would these hands come from?''</p>
        <p>Mike made sure he had eye contact before speaking. ''I've been giving it some thought. Someone who knows a bit about heists . . . someone you mentioned right at the start of the project.''</p>
        <p>Gissing's eyes widened. ''We'd be mad to let him near this.''</p>
        <p>''Think about it, Robert: Calloway has the know-how and the manpower.'' Mike paused. ''And how else are we going to get firearms?''</p>
        <p>''I believe the gangland terminology is 'shooters.' ''</p>
        <p>Mike gave a conciliatory smile. ''I mean, if there's anyone else who springs to mind . . . anyone equally qualified. . . . Because if we bring in more amateurs like us, how do we know we can trust them?''</p>
        <p>''You seriously think Chib Calloway's a man to be trusted?''</p>
        <p>Mike gnawed his bottom lip as he considered this. ''He's got more to lose than any of us. With a record like his, the law would come down on him like Carl Andre's bricks.''</p>
        <p>''So why would he offer assistance?''</p>
        <p>Mike shrugged. ''Maybe I can persuade him it's good for art. The least I can do is sound him out.''</p>
        <p>''I'm not sure, Mike. Calloway's . . . well, I'm just not sure.'' Gissing sank back into his chair.</p>
        <p>''We can always call it off,'' Mike offered. ''No damage done.''</p>
        <p>Gissing seemed to consider this. ''Maybe you're right, my boy. Calloway would bring certain . . . qualities to the project.'' Then, his eyes meeting Mike's: ''How exactly would you pitch it at him?''</p>
        <p>Gissing's sudden reversal caused Mike to wonder at his own powers of persuasion. Except that, really, Gissing hadn't needed much persuading at all.</p>
        <p>''Good for art?'' Chib Calloway echoed, laughing out loud. ''I'll tell you, Mike, I've been needing a bit of light relief all day, so bless you for that.''</p>
        <p>They were seated in Chib's BMW. He had picked Mike up from outside the Last Drop pub on the Grassmarket. Johnno and Glenn in the back, eyes open for anyone following.</p>
        <p>''Safer this way,'' Chib explained. Mike asked if there was some trouble. ''No trouble,'' Chib assured him. All the same, he had taken right turns and left and right again, doubling back on himself in places, until a voice from the back seat had announced that they were ''clear,'' which was when Chib pulled the car to a stop and ordered his men out before driving off again, seeming to relax a little.</p>
        <p>''So what's on your mind, Michael?'' he asked, and Mike told him, starting the story as if it were theory only, but Chib quickly realized the truth.</p>
        <p>They were sitting in a parking lot halfway around Arthur's Seat in Holyrood Park. Mike seldom ventured up here: it was a place for dog walkers and tourists. Incredible, panoramic views over the city, with wilderness and the humped shape of the vast rock itself fooling you into thinking you were miles from civilization. Yet you were still in the middle of Edinburgh.</p>
        <p>''Good for art,'' Chib said again, shaking his head. But then he sniffed and rubbed a finger across his nostrils and asked Mike to repeat the plan. This time, he had questions, concerns and ideas of his own. The ideas were too elaborate, but Mike listened patiently. He'd experienced a frisson from the moment he set foot in the car with those two gorillas hulking in the back. He couldn't help thinking about other people who'd taken a ride with Chib Calloway, many of them fearful, a few perhaps never seen again. But what Mike felt was excitement. There was something feral about Chib. Mike's first week in high school, the weakest newcomers had been selected and given a kicking by Chib and his cronies. It hadn't bothered Mike -- better to be picked on than ignored. But afterward that was just what Chib had done -- ignored him. And a year later, he was gone from the school, leaving behind only the legend. There were still bullies and gangs, but nothing like Chib. Later, Mike studied at college, found himself an apartment in the New Town. He'd witnessed a few brawls outside nightclubs but had never been in a fight in his life.</p>
        <p>It interested him that Chib wasn't merely about anger and the need to be the alpha male. There was intelligence in those piercing eyes and a thirst for knowledge. Perhaps the gangster was realizing how narrow his world had become.</p>
        <p>When Chib got out of the car, Mike followed. The two men walked to the edge of the parking lot, from where they could stare at a nearby pond. There was a small island in the middle; a swan was nesting while its mate swam in protective circles. A woman had brought her child along so they could toss chunks of bread to a nearby cacophony of ducks, coots, gulls and moorhens. But it was the swans that interested Chib. He slipped his hands into his pockets as he watched them. Mike wished he knew what the man was thinking. Maybe he wanted the same sense of poise and certainty. It was another two or three minutes before he spoke.</p>
        <p>''You'll need to be tooled up, Mike. Think you can handle a gun?''</p>
        <p>''As long as it's not real.''</p>
        <p>Chib shook his head. ''Just needs to look real . . . if that's what you want.''</p>
        <p>''That's all we'll need.''</p>
        <p>''And four more crew, I reckon. One apiece for the gatehouse and guard room, and two to keep the visitors quiet. That leaves the three of you clear to do the actual fetching.''</p>
        <p>''The four crew: got anyone in mind?''</p>
        <p>''You want them young, means they're hungry, on top of which there's all that testosterone . . . makes them even scarier.''</p>
        <p>''We'll pay them, of course.''</p>
        <p>But Chib waved this aside. ''Guns and bodies aren't a problem. Don't even need to tell the crew who they're working for -- a word from me'll be enough. All they'll see is a warehouse, won't know what's being taken.''</p>
        <p>''Nothing's being taken,'' Mike reminded him with a smile.</p>
        <p>''Received and understood,'' Chib said, returning the smile. ''Which just leaves my fee for us to discuss.''</p>
        <p>''I'm sure you've got a figure in mind.''</p>
        <p>''How does 150 thou sound?''</p>
        <p>Mike's Adam's apple bobbed as he swallowed. ''A bit steep, actually,'' he was eventually able to tell the gangster.</p>
        <p>Chib laughed again and slapped him on the arm. ''I'd be willing to take a painting of equal value.''</p>
        <p>''What?''</p>
        <p>''I don't seem to be having much luck at the auctions, Mike. You're planning on lifting seven paintings, seems to me one extra won't make much difference.''</p>
        <p>''Our forger is pushed as it is.''</p>
        <p>''Then we push him harder.'' Chib had turned to face Mike. Although Mike was a couple of inches taller, it seemed as if the gangster was towering over him. ''I want a painting, Mike. That's my price, and it's nonnegotiable.''</p>
        <p>Chib was having dinner that evening with a woman who ran an escort agency. A couple of years back, he offered to help her with the business, an offer she turned down out of hand. All the same, Chib had grown to like her. She was tougher than most guys he knew. It wasn't serious between them -- just dinner now and then, maybe a film or a show. They swapped news and gossip, rumors and anecdotes. Sometimes he even let her pick up the tab.</p>
        <p>Tonight's venue was a new restaurant in one of the gentrified sections of Leith. Chib remembered Leith when it had been all about the docks and the hard men, drinking dens and tattoo parlors. There was still that side to it, but a lot of the dockside had been spruced up, stylish bars opening, bonded warehouses turning into apartments. Chib often wondered what happened to the old-timers when these makeovers took place. All over the city, neighborhoods were changing. Where Chib lived, there hadn't been any homes until 10 years ago. Now it had its own railway station. Sometimes it was hard to keep up.</p>
        <p>He was early at the restaurant. Drove there himself. Didn't like taking Johnno and Glenn; they always made jokes the next day about whether his lady friend snored and how she liked her eggs at breakfast. Seated at the table the best table in the place he felt himself studying the art on the walls. Splotches of paint, primary colors. Not even reproductions of anything worthwhile, just bought as a job lot to cover the pale yellow plaster. He'd been reading up on the subject ever since visiting the auction house. A bookshop in town suggested various ''primary texts'' the very words the assistant had used. ''Primary'' to Chib meant elementary school, and he started to argue that he wasn't thick until the assistant explained what she meant. After that, they got along fine. Elementary school then made him think of high school . . . funny that he didn't remember Mike. Recognized the type though: the kind who still wanted the hard kids to notice him, even 20-odd years on. He reached into his pocket and took out one of his cellphones, along with the slip of paper. Punched in the numbers and waited. Saw his friend walk in, and wavedto her that he'd only be a moment. She was being fussed over by the maÃ(R)tre d', her coat removed. Chib's call was picked up. He licked his lips.</p>
        <p>''Is that you, Hate?''</p>
        <p>''Calloway?''</p>
        <p>''The one and only. I can't help thinking we got off to a bad start, so let me make it up to you.''</p>
        <p>''How?''</p>
        <p>''Well, while I'm putting the cash together, how about a peace offering? Something you could place under the heading of collateral.''</p>
        <p>''I'm listening. . . . ''</p>
        <p>Next week: Westie's girlfriend makes some demands.</p>
        <p>THE FUNNY PAGES: III: SUNDAY SERIAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
