<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Proximity to Darkness</title>
    <meta content="Simpson.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/books/review/Simpson-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853422"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Michaels, Leonard</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E5DD1530F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1451" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Proximity to Darkness</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Proximity to Darkness</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MONA SIMPSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The COLLECTED STORIES</p>
        <p>By Leonard Michaels.</p>
        <p>403 pp. Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $26.</p>
        <p>SYLVIA</p>
        <p>By Leonard Michaels.</p>
        <p>129 pp. Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. Paper, $13.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The republication of Leonard Michaels’s work in two new volumes should bring him to a new generation of readers and remind us of his lasting achievement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The COLLECTED STORIES</p>
        <p>By Leonard Michaels.</p>
        <p>403 pp. Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $26.</p>
        <p>SYLVIA</p>
        <p>By Leonard Michaels.</p>
        <p>129 pp. Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. Paper, $13.</p>
        <p>Larky, fitfully brilliant, as profane as they are aphoristic, Leonard Michaels's stories stand alongside those of his best Jewish contemporaries -- Grace Paley and Philip Roth. Like theirs, Michaels's vernacular achieves the level of song. And yet, though much celebrated during his lifetime -- Michaels died at 70 in 2003 -- his sexually kinetic work is little read today. But perhaps now it will be, with the republication of his work in two new volumes that should bring Michaels to a new generation of readers and remind us of his lasting achievement. ''The Collected Stories'' includes the full contents of his acclaimed first two volumes, ''Going Places'' (1969) and ''I Would Have Saved Them if I Could'' (1975), as well as selections from his later writing, including all the existing Nachman stories. ''Sylvia'' is a fictionalized memoir, first published in 1992, about Michaels's first wife, Sylvia Bloch, who committed suicide.</p>
        <p>Why is Michaels not better known? For one thing, during his lifetime he was liked, as mothers used to say of girls who displayed their breasts, for the wrong reasons. ''The Men's Club'' (1981), Michaels's third book -- the one story long enough and conventional enough for his publishers to label a ''novel'' -- attracted the most readers and was made into a film. Michaels also wrote the screenplay, and the experience seemed to have undone him. In a typically Michaelsian ending, the movie was terrible; almost a decade elapsed before another book appeared. And what grabbed attention for his early collections was Michaels's gruesome, swaggering depiction of the sexual rampage that was the swinging '60s in New York -- ''the worm bucket,'' as Michaels described an orgy. Michaels was talked about, when he was talked about at all, because of his subject matter. He ''seems to write about sex almost exclusively,'' Anatole Broyard said in these pages in 1990. It's no surprise that the post-AIDS generation wasn't interested. Michaels didn't live to complete his last, great Nachman stories. Had he been able to work another decade, I suspect he'd have seen the resurrection of his audience and won respect from a new generation, as Philip Roth deservedly and luckily has.</p>
        <p>But unlike Roth, Michaels was not in any sense prolific. ''My lifetime production of fiction,'' he once said, ''is equal to what some writers do in six months, or Joyce Carol Oates does in six minutes.'' Then again, to be remembered for ''a handful of writings'' as Lorrie Moore has said, ''is really all any writer, even a great one, can hope for.'' Michaels left a handful and a half.</p>
        <p>Take the much anthologized story ''Murderers.'' Its narrator, Phillip Liebowitz, remembering his boyhood, declares that he ''wanted proximity to darkness, strangeness. Who doesn't?'' He provides the answer himself:</p>
        <p>''The poor in spirit, the ignorant and frightened. My family came from Poland, then never went anyplace until they had heart attacks. ... We should have buried Uncle Moe where he shuffled away his life, in the kitchen or toilet, under the linoleum, near the coffeepot.'' With three other Jewish boys, Phillip climbs to the top of a tenement water tower so they can watch their rabbi and his ''sacramentally bald'' wife make love. Far above the world of their immigrant parents, the boys witness glamour.</p>
        <p>''Today she was a blonde. Bald didn't mean no wigs. She had 10 wigs, 10 colors, 50 styles. She looked different, the same, and very good.''</p>
        <p>The naked rabbi and his wife dance to a rumba. One boy masturbates. The rabbi's wife cries ''Oi, oi, oi.'' The youngest boy slides off the slanted tin roof. ''Arnold's ring hooked a nailhead and the ring and ring finger remained. The hand, the arm, the rest of him, were gone.''</p>
        <p>The surviving boys are sent to camp in New Jersey, where the counselors are World War II veterans. ''One had a metal plate in his head. Whatever you said to them they seemed to be thinking of something else.''</p>
        <p>The story, with its juxtapositions (the constriction of immigrant life, the enormous American appetite for sex and possibility, the almost unbearable legacy of sorrow) is told in three and a half pages and measures up to that other masterpiece about a young boy on a rooftop, Philip Roth's ''Conversion of the Jews.''</p>
        <p>Himself the son of Polish Jewish immigrants, Michaels was born in 1933 (the same year as Roth) and grew up on the Lower East Side. Until he was 6 he spoke only Yiddish. His mother bought a complete set of Charles Dickens. ''If you can imagine a little boy ... listening to his mother, who can hardly speak English, reading Dickens hour after hour in the most extraordinary accent, it might help account for my ear,'' Michaels recalled. And, God, what an ear!</p>
        <p>In these concise stories, driven by a lyric impulse, the line remains the primary unit, as it is in borscht belt comedy and in the poetry of Wallace Stevens. Michaels's sentences, musical in their attention to rhythm and phrasing, were his greatest stunts and assets.</p>
        <p>''She didn't like me,'' a story begins. ''So I phoned her every day.''</p>
        <p>''My name was Phillip, my style New York City.''</p>
        <p>A journal entry: ''I eat standing up, leaning over the sink. I wouldn't eat like this if anyone could see me.''</p>
        <p>Physical comedy abounds. His young Jewish men are athletes and lovers. Liebowitz, atop his girlfriend in her parents' posh apartment, feels her father's foot atop him. ''He drove me into his daughter. I drove her into his rug.''</p>
        <p>Jokes alternate with exegesis. In the story ''I Would Have Saved Them if I Could,'' Michaels talks back to Borges. This allusive tendency led the critic Robert Towers to judge the early stories ''excessively literary in their inspiration,'' and it's true that Michaels's influences -- Kafka, Borges, Byron, Stevens and a gaggle of lyric poets -- aren't hard to glean because Michaels names them. His presiding god seems to be Isaac Babel, not only for the staccato precision of his stories but for the image of the young Jew as Cossack rather than yeshiva boy. I suspect this literary freight was meant to offset his natural (and to him somewhat shameful) gift for shtick. In his diaries he said he could write ''a book of etiquette for neurotics.''</p>
        <p>Michaels's later work, much of it published by the small, independent Mercury House, contains his greatest writing. At 129 pages, the reissue of ''Sylvia,'' though billed as a novel, has the power and the rawness of memoir. It's clear that Sylvia Bloch's suicide haunted Michaels throughout his writing life. ''Manikin,'' the first story in his first collection, is about a Jewish undergraduate's suicide. Told in Michael's nervy, fast, taunting sentences, the story links her death to her rape by a Turkish student and to her fiancé's chilling response. At the end, the only expression of sorrow is the Turk's cursing and wailing.</p>
        <p>Despite the years that passed between Bloch's death and Michaels's working and reworking of the material, ''Sylvia'' feels unresolved. The narrator doesn't seem to grasp his own role in his very troubled young wife's despair, and seems unable to understand how things he did or didn't do might have affected her. He can only watch her descent and grieve. ''Sylvia'' is told plainly -- there are no pyrotechnics, few literary allusions, no dead elder relatives. With this suicide, Michaels had a tragedy as intractable as his grandparents', as flabbergasting, and all his own. He'd been given his obsession early, in the form of love, and like Ahab he chased it all his life.</p>
        <p>Though finally not as realized as Peter Handke's great memoir, ''A Sorrow Beyond Dreams,'' about his mother's suicide, ''Sylvia'' nonetheless resonates with the grim misery -- childlike, plaintive and endlessly circular -- of incomprehensible loss. Had Michaels lived longer, one feels, ''Sylvia'' would have endured another revision. Michaels will be remembered for his stories --''Manikin,'' ''Murderers,'' ''City Boy,'' ''Going Places'' -- along with ''A Girl With a Monkey,'' ''Honeymoon,'' ''Tell Me Everything'' -- and the seven astonishing Nachman stories, which transpire without sex as they chronicle the life of a gifted Santa Monica mathematician who keeps house alone. These stories consider moral problems freshly. All the ornament seems burned off, purified; the narratives distilled and gorgeously plain, as only a great stylist's can become. Less crackling than the earlier work, they're smoother in the mouth, stark in form. Michaels was writing more Nachman stories when he died. If finished and published together, they might have made a novel. As it is, they're seven irregular beauties, to be read again and again.</p>
        <p>Mona Simpson's fifth book, ''My Hollywood,'' will be published next year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Mona Simpson's fifth book, ''My Hollywood,'' will be published next year.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
