<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taking the I-95 Exit To El Salvador</title>
    <meta content="10dinectCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/10dinect.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853541"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/WEST HAVEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Restaurante Salvadoreno (West Haven, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyness, Stephanie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E1DF1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="789" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taking the I-95 Exit To El Salvador</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Taking the I-95 Exit to El Salvador</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE LYNESS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyness, Stephanie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephanie Lyness reviews Restaurante Salvadoreno in West Haven, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEXT to a convenience store on Campbell Street in West Haven is a storefront identified by a long, white, hand-painted sign above the door as the Restaurante Salvadoreño. The window also advertises a deal on papusas, savory homemade stuffed tortillas that are a staple of Salvadoran cuisine, and one of several excellent reasons to seek out this restaurant.</p>
        <p>Restaurante Salvadoreño, owned and operated by the Lemus family (originally from El Salvador), has been open for about a year. It doesn't feel like America inside, in part because everyone is speaking Spanish (including the television, avidly watched during my first dinner by a group of Latino men who sat around a large table, drinking beers and carrying on as if they were in someone's living room). There is the indefinable atmosphere of a space that has been inspirited by a foreign culture.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are several reasons to seek out Restaurante Salvadoreño in West Haven.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEXT to a convenience store on Campbell Street in West Haven is a storefront identified by a long, white, hand-painted sign above the door as the Restaurante Salvadoreño. The window also advertises a deal on papusas, savory homemade stuffed tortillas that are a staple of Salvadoran cuisine, and one of several excellent reasons to seek out this restaurant.</p>
        <p>Restaurante Salvadoreño, owned and operated by the Lemus family (originally from El Salvador), has been open for about a year. It doesn't feel like America inside, in part because everyone is speaking Spanish (including the television, avidly watched during my first dinner by a group of Latino men who sat around a large table, drinking beers and carrying on as if they were in someone's living room). There is the indefinable atmosphere of a space that has been inspirited by a foreign culture.</p>
        <p>Because of this, and because the menu, though almost entirely translated into English, didn't allow me a clear grasp of the cuisine, I invited a friend from Nicaragua along on my second visit to give me a culinary tour.</p>
        <p>She started by ordering typical Salvadoran cold drinks called refrescos: tamarindo, horchata and marañon. The tamarind didn't have much flavor beyond its sweetness; the horchata was a pleasantly sweet, milky-looking drink made with ground, strained rice and vanilla; and the exotic marañon was my favorite, made with the fruit from the cashew tree.</p>
        <p>Then my friend ordered the papusas, handmade cornmeal disks that are slightly thicker than a tortilla, and stuffed with a choice of mild homemade cheese, beans or pork. (Revueltas on the menu refers to papusas in which the stuffing ingredients are combined; for example, beans and cheese.) These are all terrific, served with marinated cabbage, a house-made sour cream and a block of fresh cheese.</p>
        <p>Another intriguing appetizer was the tamale de elote, made from a batter of ground fresh corn, sugar and margarine, which is steamed. The fresh corn gives these tamales an appealing sweetness and a rougher texture than the version we know.</p>
        <p>Then came an enormous bowl of tripe soup, made with a mild meat broth, green pepper and hunks of corn on the cob. It tasted a little bland at first, but a squeeze of lime and hot sauce woke it up. (The chicken soup is also simple and lovely, with big chunks of bone-in chicken and a variety of vegetables. Both are served with thick homemade corn tortillas.)</p>
        <p>We also tried a chicken stew, seasoned with red bell pepper, onion, garlic and tomato, and found it to be an excellent homemade dish (the beef stew is similar). But the surprise of the evening was a dish of yucca and pork ''rind'' (I suspect the fatty, tasty meat was, in fact, pork belly). Not for the faint of heart, it was all deep-fried: small pieces of crisp pork and hunks of yucca, fried in the same oil as the pork so that the yucca took on the savory taste of the meat --I thought it excellent, and I don't even like yucca.</p>
        <p>That meal ended with another Salvadoran specialty, a thin, milky soup called atol de elote, made with puréed strained corn, sugared, spiced with cinnamon and served hot.</p>
        <p>Later meals were no less satisfying. A combination plate of beef taco and chicken enchilada were not Tex-Mex style; the taco comprised grilled beef strips rolled into a soft tortilla, and the enchilada was a pile of lettuce, sliced tomato, bits of chicken and lots of homemade cheese on top of a tortilla. I also loved the chicken tamale -- a good-size chunk of chicken on the bone, blanketed in a soft cornmeal dough, and steamed in a banana leaf.</p>
        <p>This is great homemade food, and the prices are hard to beat: $7 for a huge plate of chicken stew with rice, beans and salad and $2.50 for a large tamale.</p>
        <p>Restaurante Salvadoreño  931 Campbell Avenue  West Haven  (203) 931-7457</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE Single room with booths, a table for large parties and a television tuned to a Spanish-speaking station. Pool table in the adjacent room and a refrigerated case next to the counter up front for cold drinks. Ramp for wheelchair access at side door.  THE CROWD Local folks, almost exclusively Spanish-speaking.  THE BAR Small selection of beer.  THE BILL Entrées, $4 to $15. Cash only.  WHAT WE LIKE Papusas, chicken tamale, tamale de elote (corn tamale); tripe soup, chicken soup, stewed chicken, stewed beef, beans and fried plantains, yucca con chicharron (yucca with pork), taco, enchilada; atol de elote (dessert corn soup).  IF YOU GO Tuesday to Thursday, noon to 9 p.m.; Friday to Sunday, 11 a.m. to 10 p.m.  Reviewed June 10, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/WEST HAVEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
