<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Half Century of Memories That Won't Stay Buried</title>
    <meta content="10land" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/us/10land.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853325"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THIS LAND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Time Capsules</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tulsa (Okla)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Plymouth Division of Chrysler Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barry, Dan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Columns/This Land</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Oklahoma</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oklahoma</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Time</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Oklahoma</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E3DC163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="922" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Half Century of Memories That Won't Stay Buried</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Half Century of Memories That Won’t Stay Buried</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN BARRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barry, Dan</byline>
      <dateline>TULSA, Okla.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dan Barry, in This Land column, notes that on June 15, 2007, exceptionally large time capsule, Plymouth automobile that was buried in front of Tulsa, Okla, county courthouse 50 years ago, will be dug up; car contained flag, city directory and contents of woman's purse, among other things; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A good crowd gathered in front of the county courthouse that summer day to witness the burial of an exceptionally large time capsule: a new gold-and-white Plymouth Belvedere, containing a flag, a city directory, a case of beer, an unpaid parking ticket and the contents of a woman's purse, among other things.</p>
        <p>City dignitaries explained that exactly 50 years in the future, on June 15, 2007, this fin-tailed hardtop would be unearthed to show the world who we were and how we lived, in Tulsa, in 1957. Earle Davenport of Memorial Park Cemetery had been kind enough to donate a bronze marker to be set in the ground above the Plymouth, lest we forget.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If a Plymouth Belvedere is in driving condition when it is unearthed on Friday, its headlamps will flicker across a different Tulsa, Okla.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A good crowd gathered in front of the county courthouse that summer day to witness the burial of an exceptionally large time capsule: a new gold-and-white Plymouth Belvedere, containing a flag, a city directory, a case of beer, an unpaid parking ticket and the contents of a woman's purse, among other things.</p>
        <p>City dignitaries explained that exactly 50 years in the future, on June 15, 2007, this fin-tailed hardtop would be unearthed to show the world who we were and how we lived, in Tulsa, in 1957. Earle Davenport of Memorial Park Cemetery had been kind enough to donate a bronze marker to be set in the ground above the Plymouth, lest we forget.</p>
        <p>The curious event, which twinned a commemoration of the 50th anniversary of Oklahoma's statehood with a Plymouth promotion, drew all sorts of people to Denver Avenue that day. Some thought that burying a new car was dumb; others thought it sublime.</p>
        <p>Here was Teddy Baxter, staring at this Plymouth raised high before its entombment. He and an older brother, Henry, had left their father's downtown cafe to see what all the commotion was about, and now Henry was explaining to Teddy that the car would be resurrected in a new century, a new millennium.</p>
        <p>I'll never be alive, said Teddy, who was 6.</p>
        <p>Sure you will, answered Henry, who was 19. I might not be, but you'll be around for sure.</p>
        <p>Then Henry hoisted his little brother onto his shoulders so that the boy could inscribe his name in pen on one of the Belvedere's whitewall tires.</p>
        <p>Here too was wiry Gene McDaniel, who had fled the family farm at 16 and now, at 20, was doing all right for himself as an auto mechanic in the big city. He was preening with his buddy and two young women in the 1957 black Chevrolet Bel Air convertible he had just bought. Perched high on the red-upholstered back seat, the couples could see everything.</p>
        <p>Gene, who lived to race cars and chase women, considered the meaning of the Belvedere displayed before him. In 2007, he would be 70. No way would he make it.</p>
        <p>And here was Nancy Williams, a newlywed at 20 in a pink-and-black summer dress, proudly watching from the street as her father helped to stage the event. That was her daddy in the dark sunglasses, Luther Williams the public relations whiz, doing his part for posterity.</p>
        <p>The Belvedere, loaded down with bits of Tulsa, was lowered into a concrete vault and buried. Teddy and his brother went back to the cafe. Nancy went home, where she soon learned that her father had included among the buried mementos her wedding portrait. Gene and his buddy took their dates somewhere lost to time.</p>
        <p>What is 50 years but half a century and a finger's snap. Something triggers our memory -- an old photograph, a found earring, a plaque in the ground, ''courtesy of Earle Davenport'' -- and suddenly we notice the change. All we can do is marvel at how time is a sly magician, distracting us with one hand while pocketing our years with the other.</p>
        <p>If the Belvedere is in driving condition when it is unearthed on Friday, its headlamps will flicker across a different Tulsa: a Tulsa that can no longer claim to be the Oil Capital of the World, but a Tulsa with a strong and diverse economy, and a population that has grown by more than 100,000 over those 50 years, to about 390,000.</p>
        <p>The Orpheum, where Gene McDaniel once watched movies, and Bishop's, where Nancy Williams ate after dances -- ''Fine Food Around the Clock,'' its sign said -- may be gone, but Cain's Ballroom is still thriving, and glorious Art Deco buildings still define the cityscape.</p>
        <p>Three years after Teddy Baxter signed his name to that whitewall tire, his mother died, days before turning 50. He grew up to become a quality-control supervisor for a local company, and the father of two children, now grown. He goes by Ted now, not Teddy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baxter says the first 25 years after that day moved slowly, while the second 25 passed in an eye's blink. But no matter its speed, time never diminished his boyhood memory of being held aloft by a patient older brother, who turned out to be right in saying who of them would live to see the day, and who would not.</p>
        <p>Gene McDaniel, meanwhile, married twice, though to neither of those women in his Bel Air convertible that day. He has three children, eight grandchildren and an undying passion for cars. In fact, he kept that Bel Air convertible in near-mint condition, and she's a beauty. In a way, it seems, he managed to stop time.</p>
        <p>As for Nancy Williams, she buried her marriage two years after the city buried the Belvedere, leaving her a working single mother of twin toddlers. But she married again, had another child, married again, then once more.</p>
        <p>In the mid-1970s, a few years before his death, her father sent a letter to the Tulsa Historical Society, asking that on the day of the Belvedere's resurrection, please tear up that wedding picture.</p>
        <p>''Trying to save me from embarrassment,'' says the unembarrassed publicist's daughter, whose name now is Nancy Williams Lawson.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lawson, 70, has seven grandchildren, plays golf four days a week and rarely goes downtown. But when she does, and she sees that plaque in the ground, she's a newlywed again, she's gazing at her daddy, and she's wearing that pink-and-black dress.</p>
        <p>THIS LAND</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
