<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Three Couples, One Party: Just Add Zingers and Angst</title>
    <meta content="10theaternjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/10theaternj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853592"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Repertory Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoban, Phoebe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Canfora, Jack</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Place Setting (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Repertory Company</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E4DD1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="542" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Three Couples, One Party: Just Add Zingers and Angst</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Three Couples, One Party: Just Add Zingers and Angst</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHOEBE HOBAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoban, Phoebe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Phoebe Hoban reviews New Jersey Repertory production of Jack Canfora play Place Setting; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Place Setting,'' at the New Jersey Repertory Company in Long Branch, the first full-length play by the actor and writer Jack Canfora, has all the snap, crackle and pop of a breakfast cereal, even though much of the action takes place at a New Year's dinner party on the eve of the millennium. It's hard to say which of the three couples on stage is more mismatched and miserable: Andrea, a tightly wound Martha Stewart wannabe, and Greg, who can't stop tossing verbal darts; Charlotte, the slinky fiancée of buttoned-up Lenny, Greg's brother; or Laura and Richard, both way too downtown -- in different ways -- for their own good.</p>
        <p>Among the six of them, they manage to cook up a satisfying -- if somewhat superficial -- menu of modern malaise. Greg (aptly inhabited by Mr. Canfora) and Charlotte (Guenia Lemos), the audience soon learns, have the hots for each other but have yet to consummate their guilty romance. Laura and Richard (Kristen Moser and Peter Macklin) use their well-honed claws -- and literary quotes -- to savage each other. And Greg and Andrea (nicely portrayed by Carol Todd) provide a stellar example of why the unexamined marriage might not be worth having.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Place Setting,” at the New Jersey Repertory Company in Long Branch, the first full-length play by the actor and writer Jack Canfora, has all the snap, crackle and pop of a breakfast cereal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Place Setting,'' at the New Jersey Repertory Company in Long Branch, the first full-length play by the actor and writer Jack Canfora, has all the snap, crackle and pop of a breakfast cereal, even though much of the action takes place at a New Year's dinner party on the eve of the millennium. It's hard to say which of the three couples on stage is more mismatched and miserable: Andrea, a tightly wound Martha Stewart wannabe, and Greg, who can't stop tossing verbal darts; Charlotte, the slinky fiancée of buttoned-up Lenny, Greg's brother; or Laura and Richard, both way too downtown -- in different ways -- for their own good.</p>
        <p>Among the six of them, they manage to cook up a satisfying -- if somewhat superficial -- menu of modern malaise. Greg (aptly inhabited by Mr. Canfora) and Charlotte (Guenia Lemos), the audience soon learns, have the hots for each other but have yet to consummate their guilty romance. Laura and Richard (Kristen Moser and Peter Macklin) use their well-honed claws -- and literary quotes -- to savage each other. And Greg and Andrea (nicely portrayed by Carol Todd) provide a stellar example of why the unexamined marriage might not be worth having.</p>
        <p>The ensemble works well together, and David Bishins (Lenny) and Ms. Moser, who shine during the second act, are particularly good. Charlotte is the loose thread in this otherwise tightly knit group. As played by Ms. Lemos, who certainly looks the part of a babe, she is a narcissistic seductress who has more chemistry with herself than with Greg. Although she is the catalyst for much of the action (and reaction) in the play, her character seems the least convincing, and she isn't even onstage after intermission.</p>
        <p>Mr. Canfora has created familiar -- but not clichéd -- characters. We have met all these people, kept on their toes by unusually punchy writing. Laced with fast-flying zingers, ''Place Setting'' if anything suffers from too many good one-liners, whether skewering the suburbs or sending up contemporary culture. At one point, Lenny is reacting to hearing about Greg and Charlotte for the first time, and rather than shutting down, he goes into hyperdrive, producing a staccato string of clever comments. ''He returns these feelings -- I sound like I'm in a Merchant-Ivory film -- let me be a little more Scorsese about this,'' he exclaims when Andrea gives him the bad news. (The rest of his comment can't be printed here.)</p>
        <p>Paced and plotted like one of the better sitcoms (think ''Will and Grace''), the play manages to maintain its momentum right up until the final minute, when it suddenly goes limp. If only Mr. Canfora, who has sharpened his skills with some television writing (''TV411'' on PBS), had brought his poison pen to bear on Andrea's last line. Unlike Lenny -- ''It's like getting marriage counseling from Michael Corleone'' is his response to one of Andrea's banalities -- she serves up a wimpy platitude in summation. As one of these characters themselves might put it, it's like getting a cup of lukewarm Nescafé instead of a jolt of espresso at the end of a well-cooked meal.</p>
        <p>''Place Setting'' is at the New Jersey Repertory Company, 179 Broadway, Long Branch, through June 24. Information: (732) 229-3166 or at njrep.org.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
