<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>STREETSCAPES/ 1020 Fifth Avenue; Where 'Sumptuous' Is No Exaggeration</title>
    <meta content="10scap" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/realestate/10scap.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853607"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Streetscapes | 1020 Fifth Avenue"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Streetscapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Upper East Side (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E3DC1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>STREETSCAPES/ 1020 Fifth Avenue; Where 'Sumptuous' Is No Exaggeration</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Where ‘Sumptuous’ Is No Exaggeration</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER GRAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE swell co-ops on Fifth Avenue are not, in their essentials, a whole lot different from your typical elevator apartment house. After all, there is only so much you can do with the arrangement of windows.</p>
        <p>But 1020 Fifth Avenue, at 83rd Street, is markedly distinct from its neighbors, with six giant banks of windows running up the facade. Behind those windows lie apartments that, in the most giddy and wonderful way, expand the notions of how one can live in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Behind giant banks of windows are apartments that, in the most giddy and wonderful way, expand the notions of how one can live in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE swell co-ops on Fifth Avenue are not, in their essentials, a whole lot different from your typical elevator apartment house. After all, there is only so much you can do with the arrangement of windows.</p>
        <p>But 1020 Fifth Avenue, at 83rd Street, is markedly distinct from its neighbors, with six giant banks of windows running up the facade. Behind those windows lie apartments that, in the most giddy and wonderful way, expand the notions of how one can live in New York.</p>
        <p>With the topmost duplex for sale for $50 million -- leaving the hands of its original owners, the family of Samuel H. Kress, for the first time since construction took place in 1925 -- a look at the building is timely.</p>
        <p>It was the developer Michael Paterno who conceived it, choosing a limestone facade, generous room sizes and three to five servants' rooms per apartment. He also had his architects, Warren &amp; Wetmore, develop an intricate system of staggered floors to give 6 of the 13 apartments ''rooms of truly noble proportions,'' as the original sales brochure put it.</p>
        <p>The first four floors have varied layouts but are fairly standard, if you can so describe apartments verging on 5,000 square feet in size, with ceilings 9 to 12 feet high. But beginning at the fifth floor, the architects staggered the layout from front to back, to produce six salons 20 by 40 feet in size, with ceilings 14 to 18 feet high.</p>
        <p>Originally priced from $87,000 to $150,000, the six apartments in question show no evidence of scrimping: all the salons run the long way on Fifth Avenue, the most luxurious use possible of window exposure. ''There are few such rooms in New York,'' says the Kress apartment brochure from Douglas L. Elliman &amp; Company. ''Many of them are in this building.''</p>
        <p>The larger bedrooms were generally about 16 by 20 feet, with at least one fireplace per apartment. Because of the staggered layout, shareholders on the 6th, 9th and 12th floors had to make do with a smaller salon, 16 by 31 feet, with 10-foot ceilings.</p>
        <p>The early shareholders were people like Irene and Franklyn Hutton, he the brother of Edward, the founder of E. F. Hutton, and a broker with the firm. The 1930 census taker recorded Mr. and Mrs. Hutton and seven servants in the apartment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hutton's daughter by his first marriage, who was in her spring term at Miss Porter's School in Farmington, Conn., was not included.</p>
        <p>That daughter was Barbara Hutton, the granddaughter (through her mother) of Frank W. Woolworth. A New York Times account in 1934 put her fortune the year before at $42 million. Her wealth -- and her seven marriages, including one to Cary Grant -- led the public to call her ''poor little rich girl,'' a sobriquet she rejected absolutely, asserting that she was indeed extremely fortunate despite her troubled married life.</p>
        <p>Frank Woolworth had founded the immensely profitable five-and-dime chain, so there must have been something to talk about when the Huttons shared the elevator with their penthouse neighbor, Samuel H. Kress. In 1896, he had begun his own five-and-dime empire in Memphis and a few years later had come to New York, soon living on Park Avenue near Grand Central Terminal.</p>
        <p>In 1925, The Times reported that Mr. Kress, a bachelor, bought the duplex penthouse, with its 17 rooms and 7 baths, from Mr. Paterno for $150,000. He went on to assemble an astonishing collection of medieval and Renaissance art.</p>
        <p>A trip through an apartment like the Kress family's is a heady experience. Opposite the elevator door is a view down a stairway, offering an unusual sensation to those expecting the standard entry hall. From the stair landing, the salon floor is perhaps only five feet down; but across the room, huge windows start below the level of the top stair, and produce a vertiginous feeling as you look down on the roof of the Metropolitan Museum of Art.</p>
        <p>Jocelyn Kress, who grew up in the apartment, says that after ''Uncle Sam'' died in 1955, the apartment went to his brother Rush, her father.</p>
        <p>It has been occupied off and on in recent years by various family members and has now been cleared of most of the art and furniture. There is just enough in place to make it seem like an Italian family's ancestral castle, with most things in storage for the summer.</p>
        <p>It appears that almost all of the finishes in the apartment are original, or very lightly redone, from the 17th-century coffered Venetian ceiling in the salon to the dreamy azure glaze on Mr. Kress's dressing-room cabinets to the original refrigerator, drainboards and other kitchen equipment. Even the built-in scale set into Mr. Kress's bathroom floor is working, but only if you weigh 200 pounds or less.</p>
        <p>Samuel Kress gave great amounts of his collection to the Metropolitan Museum and the National Gallery of Art. Ms. Kress, the family historian, who also lectures here and abroad on the Kress collection, said, ''This apartment has seen more great art than any other space in the city.''</p>
        <p>Streetscapes | 1020 Fifth Avenue E-mail: streetscapes@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: streetscapes@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
