<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Henins' Reunion Becomes a Victory Celebration</title>
    <meta content="10women" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/sports/tennis/10women.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853344"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Henin-Hardenne, Justine</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E7D9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Henins' Reunion Becomes a Victory Celebration</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Henin Makes French Open Reunion a Threepeat</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIET MACUR</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Standing on the battered earth of Roland Garros's main court, another trophy in her hand, Justine Henin immediately knew this title would be sweeter than the rest.</p>
        <p>Henin, a tiny blond Belgian, won her fourth French Open title, her third in a row, by defeating the Serbian teenager Ana Ivanovic, 6-1, 6-2. But in Saturday's final, for the first time, she looked into the stands to see her brothers and sister looking back, smiling. At last, she could share this championship with them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Justine Henin took advantage of 19-year-old Ana Ivanovic’s shaky play Saturday to win 6-1, 6-2.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Standing on the battered earth of Roland Garros's main court, another trophy in her hand, Justine Henin immediately knew this title would be sweeter than the rest.</p>
        <p>Henin, a tiny blond Belgian, won her fourth French Open title, her third in a row, by defeating the Serbian teenager Ana Ivanovic, 6-1, 6-2. But in Saturday's final, for the first time, she looked into the stands to see her brothers and sister looking back, smiling. At last, she could share this championship with them.</p>
        <p>For Henin, the player who once prided herself on being a loner, the emotions of seeing her family were too much to handle. After hitting a screaming forehand to end the match, she joyfully threw her racket in the air, then leaned over the net.</p>
        <p>She looked directly at her sister, Sarah, and brothers, David and Thomas, when she addressed the crowd. Until two months ago, her brothers had not seen her or spoken to her in seven years.</p>
        <p>''I want to dedicate this victory to my family,'' Henin said. ''I missed you. I want to offer this victory to you. I love you with all my heart.''</p>
        <p>With the victory, Henin became the first woman since Monica Seles in 1992 to win three consecutive French Open titles. But the day meant so much more for the 25-year-old Henin, whose mother died of cancer when she was 12. Her brothers and her father had been missing from her life, too.</p>
        <p>In 1999, Henin cut them out of her life, as she went one way and they went another, for reasons they want to keep private. On Saturday, they cheered her on. Her father, José, watched the match from his village in Belgium, too overwhelmed to be there in person.</p>
        <p>For years, her family had been a taboo topic, but now Henin talks freely about it, saying she is at peace.</p>
        <p>''Everyone suffered a lot from the situation in the last few years,'' she said. ''And today, finally, we are united in this joy, and we can share this moment.''</p>
        <p>While sipping a beer in the players' lounge, Henin's older brother, 33-year-old David, told how the family reconnected. In April, he was in a serious car accident and was in a coma for two days. Sarah, who had some contact with Justine, called her with the news.</p>
        <p>By the time David woke up, Justine was at his side. It caused an avalanche of pent-up emotions. The Henins realized it was a shame to remain apart, so they decided to rebuild their bond.</p>
        <p>''It was very moving,'' said David Henin, who owns a tavern with his brother, Thomas, in Liège, Belgium. ''It really boosted my morale. It was something horrible that turned into something good.''</p>
        <p>The reconciliation came at a time when Henin needed her family the most. She had skipped the Australian Open after separating from her husband of four years, Pierre-Yves Hardenne. Heartbroken, she began to step back and evaluate the relationships in her life.</p>
        <p>Her coach, Carlos Rodriguez, said he had encouraged Henin to take that first step toward her family.</p>
        <p>''I told her a lot of power and love comes from your family, so it's the best for you to go back now,'' Rodriguez said. ''Tennis is just a part of your life, not the entire thing. I told her to remember that.''</p>
        <p>Since taking his advice, Henin has changed drastically, Rodriguez said. During the two weeks of the French Open, she went to dinner with friends, shopped and spent time with her family. She broke out of her cocoon and, Rodriguez said, he had to hold her back.</p>
        <p>''I said, it's a new democracy, this overdose of communication and contentment,'' Rodriguez said. ''It's like you couldn't eat sweets for a year, then I told you that you could eat whatever you want. She wants to give everything, talk to everyone.</p>
        <p>''It's a huge difference. Now people can see what is behind the wall she had built; they can see what I saw in her when I started coaching her 11 years ago.''</p>
        <p>On the court Saturday, the thousands of fans inside Court Philippe Chatrier saw the new Justine Henin or, more appropriately, the reborn Justine Henin.</p>
        <p>She looked distracted at the start of the match, while the 19-year-old Ivanovic came out fearless in her first Grand Slam final. She broke Henin in the opening game and moved ahead, 40-0, on her serve in the second. Then Ivanovic fell apart.</p>
        <p>Ivanovic, who grew up in Belgrade playing on a court built in a drained swimming pool, said that she lost concentration.</p>
        <p>''I was trying to put the nerves aside, the emotions aside,'' Ivanovic said. ''But then, in the first service game, it just hit me, I guess.''</p>
        <p>Watching from the stands, Henin's siblings worried that they would be a distraction, but their presence seemed to only improve her play. In the players' lounge afterward, Henin also looked more relaxed then ever.</p>
        <p>She collapsed into her brothers' chests as they hugged her. She cradled her 6-week-old niece, Kiara -- Thomas's daughter -- in her arms, gently planting a kiss on her head. She smiled.</p>
        <p>Henin said that a year ago, when she won her third French Open title, she could never have imagined being this happy.</p>
        <p>''It's amazing how life can change,'' she said. ''But it's for every person the same. I'm sure a lot of you had some trouble, some ups and downs in their lives, and that it's tough for everyone. But we come back stronger, for sure.''</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
