<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bomber Kills at Least 12 Iraqi Soldiers and Wounds 30</title>
    <meta content="10iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/world/middleeast/10iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853364"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iskandariya (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oppel, Richard A Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E1D9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="822" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bomber Kills at Least 12 Iraqi Soldiers and Wounds 30</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bomber Kills at Least 12 Iraqi Soldiers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD A. OPPEL Jr.; Khalid W. Hassan contributed reporting from Baghdad, Sebnem Arsu from Istanbul, and Iraqi employees of The New York Times from Hilla, Basra and Diyala, Iraq.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Oppel, Richard A Jr</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, June 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Suicide bomber kills at least 12 Iraqi soldiers and wounds 30 more when he drives truck packed with explosives into Iraqi Army checkpoint in Iskandariya; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A suicide bomber killed at least a dozen Iraqi soldiers and wounded 30 more on Saturday when he drove a truck packed with explosives into an Iraqi Army checkpoint guarding a compound in Iskandariya, a restive village south of Baghdad that has long been an insurgent stronghold.</p>
        <p>The casualty toll could have been worse, according to local Iraqi security officials, who said the Iraqi soldiers had fatally shot the bomber before he could get too close to his intended target, a headquarters building.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A suicide bomber killed at least a dozen Iraqi soldiers and wounded 30 more in Iskandariya, an insurgent stronghold south of Baghdad.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A suicide bomber killed at least a dozen Iraqi soldiers and wounded 30 more on Saturday when he drove a truck packed with explosives into an Iraqi Army checkpoint guarding a compound in Iskandariya, a restive village south of Baghdad that has long been an insurgent stronghold.</p>
        <p>The casualty toll could have been worse, according to local Iraqi security officials, who said the Iraqi soldiers had fatally shot the bomber before he could get too close to his intended target, a headquarters building.</p>
        <p>Even though the bomber was stopped short, the huge blast seriously damaged the building, killing some soldiers inside in addition to some on the ground. An Iraqi Army official said he expected the death toll to rise as rescue teams combed through the wreckage.</p>
        <p>The attack occurred hours after a rocket strike killed six detainees and wounded at least 50 more at a huge American military prison near the Kuwaiti border, Camp Bucca.</p>
        <p>The rocket attack happened around lunchtime, and it did not kill or wound any Americans, a military spokesman said. The prison, south of Basra near the Persian Gulf port city of Umm Qasr, houses thousands of people suspected of being insurgents and other prisoners.</p>
        <p>Heavy violence struck again just northeast of Baghdad in Diyala Province, where one American soldier was shot to death and American and Iraqi troops battled insurgents in Baquba, and eventually helicopters fired missiles at a mosque.</p>
        <p>In Basra, Iraq's largest southern city, a decree issued by a sheik has been blamed for the killings of at least eight barbers in the city in the past two days, according to Gen. Ali Hamadi, of the city's emergency services department. The decree forbids barbers to use modern equipment, or use razors to shave facial hair, among other restrictions. Officials from the militant Shiite cleric Moktada al-Sadr's office in Basra denied having anything to do with the decree.</p>
        <p>A car bomb exploded in northern Baghdad, killing one police commando and wounding five, an official at the Interior Ministry said. Twenty-four corpses were found in Baghdad on Saturday, many of them apparently tortured and shot, victims of sectarian killings in the capital, an Interior Ministry official said.</p>
        <p>Also in Baghdad, the Foreign Ministry said it had formally demanded that Turkey stop firing artillery barrages into Kurdish territory near the border between the countries.</p>
        <p>Turkish forces have been firing artillery and massing along the border in an operation against guerrillas from the Kurdistan Workers' Party, or P.K.K. More than 3,000 P.K.K. guerrillas are thought to live in the remote and sheer mountains along the borders of Turkey and Iran, using the territory to stage attacks into Turkey. The State Department classifies the group as a terrorist organization and says the P.K.K. killed more than 500 people in Turkey last year.</p>
        <p>According to a statement from the Iraqi Foreign Ministry, a senior ministry official in Baghdad, Muhammad al-Haj Mahmoud, summoned the Turkish chargé d'affaires on Saturday and handed him a written protest against the shelling, which Iraq says has ignited ''huge fires'' and frightened many people in Dahuk and Erbil Provinces.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the ministry statement struck a conciliatory tone by emphasizing that the Iraqi government ''refuses'' the P.K.K.'s presence within Iraq and considers it an illegal group.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the Turkish Foreign Ministry confirmed that an under secretary from Turkey's embassy in Baghdad was called Saturday to the Iraqi Foreign Ministry and given a diplomatic letter regarding the effects of shelling on the Iraqi side.</p>
        <p>About 30 miles south of Kirkuk, the Iraqi police also said they had found the bodies of three Iraqi soldiers in uniform, all handcuffed and shot.</p>
        <p>In Baquba, the provincial capital of Diyala, insurgents attacked American and Iraqi soldiers with rocket-propelled grenades from inside Al Hussiniya mosque, the military said. Eventually, American helicopters were called in to shoot missiles at the insurgents operating inside, the military said.</p>
        <p>Hours after that battle began, American troops on patrol in Baquba averted a two-stage suicide bomb attack outside a government building, according to a police official in Diyala. One bomber on foot wearing an explosive belt approached soldiers and Iraqi policemen but refused commands to stop, the police official said, and the police shot him to death, but not before he detonated his device and killed one policeman.</p>
        <p>Another bomber rushed toward the soldiers and policemen but exploded before reaching his target. There were conflicting reports about whether the second bomber had been shot dead or the concussion of the first bomb detonated his explosives.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in Diyala, five family members were gunned down on the road between the villages of Kanaan and Nahrawan, the police official said. Iraqi soldiers also shot a man in Muqdadiya, according to a security official there.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
