<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two's a Crowd In This Listing</title>
    <meta content="10Deal1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/realestate/10Deal1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853599"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BIG DEAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/The Big Deal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Upper East Side (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E5DC1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1557" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two's a Crowd In This Listing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Two’s a Crowd in This Listing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSH BARBANEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE developer of a luxury building on the Upper East Side told Dolly Lenz, one of the city's top brokers, six months ago that she was fired as the exclusive agent -- but she's still refusing to go.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lenz, who grew up in Washington Heights and the Bronx, had $750 million in sales last year. Two years ago, she was hired to sell the pricey condominiums that have been created at 813 Park Avenue, near 75th Street, in a narrow 12-story town house previously owned by Sean Combs. It is being converted into three four-story condominiums, priced at up to $16 million each.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The developer of a luxury building told one of the city’s top brokers that she was fired as the exclusive agent six months ago  but she’s still refusing to go.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE developer of a luxury building on the Upper East Side told Dolly Lenz, one of the city's top brokers, six months ago that she was fired as the exclusive agent -- but she's still refusing to go.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lenz, who grew up in Washington Heights and the Bronx, had $750 million in sales last year. Two years ago, she was hired to sell the pricey condominiums that have been created at 813 Park Avenue, near 75th Street, in a narrow 12-story town house previously owned by Sean Combs. It is being converted into three four-story condominiums, priced at up to $16 million each.</p>
        <p>The developer has already chosen a different company, Stribling &amp; Associates, to market the properties. But Ms. Lenz is still advertising the building on her Web site, sending the listing to other brokers and displaying a photograph of the building in the window of the Madison Avenue office of her firm, Prudential Douglas Elliman.</p>
        <p>According to the developer, DCD America, she is no longer the broker because her contract ended without her managing to bring in any buyers, and it has gone to court to try to stop her from advertising it on the Web.</p>
        <p>Though Ms. Lenz's name was once listed in letters more than a foot high on scaffolding outside the building, she has been barred from showing apartments in the building. Ms. Lenz said that the disagreement was merely a ''commercial dispute'' and that under the contract, she was still the exclusive broker for the property.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lenz has ranked first in sales among 70,000 Prudential brokers across the country for the last four years, and last year she had her best year ever. She has a reputation as one of the hardest working brokers around, but disputed suggestions that she was too busy to give the Park Avenue project enough attention.</p>
        <p>She said sales at 813 Park Avenue had lagged because the apartments were still undergoing renovation and were priced too high, and had also suffered because of the awkward placement of staircases in the 25-foot-wide building. ''If it was priced right, it would have sold,'' Ms. Lenz said.</p>
        <p>But in the court papers, the developers complained that Ms. Lenz frequently failed to ''timely respond'' to telephone calls and e-mail messages from Siraj Dadabhoy, a principal of DCD America, and did not produce a single buyer during a 15-month period.</p>
        <p>''Ms. Lenz's enthusiasm for marketing the property waxed and waned,'' Richard Santer, a vice president at DCD America said in an affidavit.</p>
        <p>The dispute is making extra work for brokers at Stribling &amp; Associates, which signed an agreement in January to start a new marketing campaign. ''The dispute is greatly complicating our job,'' said Alexa Lambert, a Stribling broker. ''She is not showing in the building; she is not allowed in the building,'' she said of Ms. Lenz.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Combs sold the building in 2004 for $14.3 million, to DCD America, which is a subsidiary of a London-based banking and real estate investment company, Ms. Lenz represented both the buyer and the seller.</p>
        <p>The court records show that Ms. Lenz reached an agreement in April 2005 to represent the building for a 12-month marketing period. Working with the developer and a marketing consultant, Ms. Lenz developed a magazine advertising campaign, a Web site and signs for the building. By late 2005, the apartment listings were distributed to brokers across the city, brokers said.</p>
        <p>In court papers Ms. Lenz contended that the 12-month marketing period did not begin until last October, and continues to October 2007. It was delayed, she said, because of uncertainty over the asking prices, and because the apartments were not available for showing during construction. Asked about the listing in 2005, Ms. Lenz said it was an error.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the Stribling brokers have taken over the project, lowered prices a bit and shifted the marketing campaign. While Douglas Elliman talked about ''town house grandeur,'' Stribling is emphasizing the loftlike spaces with double-height ceilings and renamed one unit ''the Lofthouse.''</p>
        <p>And with a stronger Manhattan luxury market this year, and few large condos available on the Upper East Side, Ms. Alexa said, buyers have shown strong interest.</p>
        <p>A Tale of Persistence</p>
        <p>JERRY BERNS, an owner and the greeter for many decades at the celebrated ''21'' Club, was a persistent man. He was the first buyer of an apartment at 14 East 75th Street, on the corner of Madison Avenue, when the prewar building was converted to a co-op in 1958. And for years, he lived there in a ninth-floor apartment.</p>
        <p>But according to a story his family passed along to Joan McLaughlin, a broker for the Corcoran Group who is now marketing the property, he also coveted a penthouse three floors above his own. From the late 1970s onward, prodded by his second wife, Suzanne, he repeatedly offered to buy the apartment, but the owner would not sell.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berns joined ''21,'' Manhattan's most celebrated speakeasy, in 1938, years after it was founded during Prohibition by his brother, Charlie, and a cousin, Jack Kreindler. The club was sold in 1985.</p>
        <p>For years, Mr. Berns continued to press for a purchase of the penthouse. Finally, in 1993, property records show, when Mr. Berns was already well into his 80s (and apartment prices were at a nadir), the apartment became available and he bought it.</p>
        <p>He paid $1.3 million for 2,000 square feet of living space and 1,900 square feet of terraces. In June of 2004, the ninth-floor apartment he owned was sold for $955,000.</p>
        <p>He had his new apartment gutted in a lengthy renovation filed in December 1993, and not signed off on by the Department of Buildings until 1997. A marble foyer and three marble bathrooms were constructed, air-conditioning was added, and an electrically controlled green and white striped awning added over parts of the terrace and gardens that surround much of the apartment. An automatic irrigation system was also installed.</p>
        <p>In the last few years, Mr. Berns spent much of his time outside Manhattan, at homes in Rancho Mirage, Calif., and Southampton, N.Y., and used the Manhattan apartment as a pied-à-terre. After Suzanne died, he married for the third time in 2005.</p>
        <p>He died last December at age 99. The penthouse went on the market a few weeks ago, with an asking price of $7.5 million, and appears to be moving toward a quick sale, Ms. McLaughlin said.</p>
        <p>Although the ''21'' Club is celebrated for its clutter -- the toys and sports memorabilia that hang from the ceiling, the line of jockeys out front -- Mr. Berns's apartment was largely tchotchke-free, with one exception. The apartment is strewn with owls: an owl pillow, an owl statue and an owl umbrella stand, to suggest Mr. Berns's role in his later years as a wise old owl, Ms. McLaughlin said.</p>
        <p>A Home to Sing About</p>
        <p>TIMOTHY BLAKE NELSON -- the character actor, playwright and director -- provided the voice of a cockroach living in a Manhattan apartment in the 1996 MTV musical film ''Joe's Apartment.'' But if he has any singing cockroaches in his new penthouse, he will have no one to blame but himself.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nelson recently paid $4.95 million for unfinished space atop a 16-story prewar co-op at 245 West 104th Street on the corner of Broadway. He will now have to rebuild the space, and install fresh interior walls and a fancy kitchen, to turn it into a brand new apartment.</p>
        <p>The penthouse includes 3,700 square feet of living space, surrounded by 2,000 square feet of wraparound terrace, with partial views of the Hudson River and Central Park.</p>
        <p>According to the building's certificate of occupancy, the space was previously occupied by four apartments, two maid's rooms and a storage room. The listing by Deanna Kory, a senior vice president at the Corcoran Group, notes that ''there are currently six full baths to work with and plumbing in five locations for potential kitchen areas.''</p>
        <p>The total price may be a new high for a co-op on the Upper West Side north of 96th Street. Jonathan J. Miller, an appraiser and the president of Miller Samuel Inc., said it was a ''new benchmark'' for co-ops in the area, though Ms. Kory, previously the sales director for the new Ariel condominiums, twin towers on West 99th Street and Broadway, said a penthouse there was listed for $7 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nelson directed the 2001 movie ''O,'' a version of Shakespeare's Othello that takes place at a South Carolina high school, and in recent years he has appeared in the movies ''Holes,'' ''Syriana'' and ''Meet the Fockers.'' His wife, Lisa Benavides, is an actress and acting teacher.</p>
        <p>Public records show that Mr. Nelson and Ms. Benavides currently own a three-bedroom co-op on the 12th floor of 37 Riverside Drive at West 76th Street. It went on the market a few weeks ago, with an asking price of $5.7 million in a listing that notes its ''amazing'' views and a renovated chef's kitchen, according to William Postrion, the Prudential Douglas Elliman broker who represented them in the purchase on West 104th Street.</p>
        <p>From the street, the Riverside Drive building, built in 1925, has a traditional facade, but with a pastiche of old and new windows. The 12th-floor apartment has the new windows, large picture windows with sweeping views.</p>
        <p>BIG DEAL E-mail: bigdeal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: bigdeal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
