<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Breaking, Just Entering</title>
    <meta content="10noticedliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/10noticedli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853545"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NOTICED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gangs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Domash, Shelly Feuer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E1DF1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="505" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Breaking, Just Entering</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Breaking, Just Entering</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHELLY FEUER DOMASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Domash, Shelly Feuer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nassau County Police Department attributes nearly 40 percent of recent spike in home burglaries to organized transient crime group; say more than one band of group members may be working in county; warns homeowners that thieves are walking into houses open during warm weather rather than breaking in (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS Long Islanders open their doors and windows to let in the breeze, the police warn, they may be letting in something dangerous as well. The Nassau County Police Department reports a spike in one pattern of home burglaries from April 1 to May 30, attributing nearly 40 percent of them to an organized transient criminal group.</p>
        <p>Of 95 home burglaries in the two-month period, the police attributed 36 of them to the group, which they called Gypsies. Two men from Brooklyn who fit the pattern of the burglaries were arrested Wednesday, Detective Lt. John May said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS Long Islanders open their doors and windows to let in the breeze, the police warn, they may be letting in something dangerous as well. The Nassau County Police Department reports a spike in one pattern of home burglaries from April 1 to May 30, attributing nearly 40 percent of them to an organized transient criminal group.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS Long Islanders open their doors and windows to let in the breeze, the police warn, they may be letting in something dangerous as well. The Nassau County Police Department reports a spike in one pattern of home burglaries from April 1 to May 30, attributing nearly 40 percent of them to an organized transient criminal group.</p>
        <p>Of 95 home burglaries in the two-month period, the police attributed 36 of them to the group, which they called Gypsies. Two men from Brooklyn who fit the pattern of the burglaries were arrested Wednesday, Detective Lt. John May said.</p>
        <p>The police said that more than one band of group members may be working in the county.</p>
        <p>Detective Sgt. Thomas Reilly, deputy commanding officer of Nassau's Crimes Against Property Squad, said the warm weather made it easier for the burglars to commit their crimes.</p>
        <p>He said that members of the crime group drive through a neighborhood, usually in a car or van with out-of-state plates, looking for residents working outdoors. While one member of the group distracts the resident, another enters the house through an open door or window, Sergeant Reilly said. Members of the group also pose as utility workers or handymen to gain access to a home, the police said.</p>
        <p>''They don't break in, they would rather walk in,'' he said, citing an instance in which a homeowner in Massapequa confronted a woman going through his closets. The woman told the homeowner she was the housekeeper, and when he shouted at her that she was not, she fled, Sergeant Reilly said.</p>
        <p>Sergeant Reilly said there has been a slight increase this year in these kinds of burglaries, many of which are on the North Shore. The police said the group has also been reported to have committed crimes of opportunity, including scams and burglaries that involve deception of the elderly.</p>
        <p>The police described the criminals as members of an ethnic group originating in Europe. They keep to themselves, speak their own language and use assumed names, making it difficult to track them, the police said.</p>
        <p>''Their looks can vary,'' Sergeant Reilly said. ''Sometimes they are mistaken for Indian or Pakistani, sometimes South Asian, sometimes Hispanic.''</p>
        <p>Often, the group members use their children as a means of distraction to commit a crime, saying that the children are sick or need to use a homeowner's bathroom, according to the police.</p>
        <p>''There is nothing they won't do as far as thievery goes, but they are generally nonviolent,'' Sergeant Reilly said.</p>
        <p>Deputy Inspector Mark Griffiths, the commanding officer of Suffolk County's Detective Bureaus, said that while crimes often cross county borders, Suffolk authorities had yet to see evidence of burglaries like those committed by the group in Nassau.</p>
        <p>The Nassau police said that residents should take simple precautions including keeping doors and windows locked even when they are home; setting burglar alarms even if they are leaving for a short time; locking valuables in a safe; and not leaving cash and jewelry out in the open.</p>
        <p>NOTICED</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
