<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plots, Politics and the Weight of Page 1</title>
    <meta content="10hoyt" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="The Public Editor; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/opinion/10hoyt.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853301"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE PUBLIC EDITOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/The Public Editor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kennedy International Airport (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E1DD163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1182" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plots, Politics and the Weight of Page 1</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Plots, Politics and the Weight of Page 1</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Clark Hoyt</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PUBLIC Editor No. 3 doesn't officially open his window for business until next week. But already an issue has popped up that is filled with themes I'm sure to revisit over the next two years of examining and commenting on the news judgment of The Times.</p>
        <p>A decision by editors not to play charges of a terrorism plot at Kennedy Airport on Page 1 last Sunday puzzled me and some readers -- and angered others. Among the questions raised: Was the paper properly skeptical of officialdom, in this case the Bush administration? Was it too skeptical, just because it was the Bush administration? Was a political agenda at work?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A decision by Times editors not to play charges of a terrorism plot at Kennedy Airport on Page 1 last Sunday puzzled me and some readers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PUBLIC Editor No. 3 doesn't officially open his window for business until next week. But already an issue has popped up that is filled with themes I'm sure to revisit over the next two years of examining and commenting on the news judgment of The Times.</p>
        <p>A decision by editors not to play charges of a terrorism plot at Kennedy Airport on Page 1 last Sunday puzzled me and some readers -- and angered others. Among the questions raised: Was the paper properly skeptical of officialdom, in this case the Bush administration? Was it too skeptical, just because it was the Bush administration? Was a political agenda at work?</p>
        <p>With the e-mail still coming in, I couldn't resist opening early. So consider this what they call a ''soft launch'' in the restaurant trade.</p>
        <p>The story began with a news conference in Manhattan on an otherwise slow Saturday. More than a dozen law enforcement officials, including the United States attorney for Brooklyn, the head of the F.B.I. office in New York and New York City's police commissioner, announced that a horrendous plot to blow up fuel tanks, terminal buildings and underground fuel lines at J.F.K. had been broken up. Roslynn R. Mauskopf, the U.S. attorney, said the plot would have caused ''unthinkable'' devastation.</p>
        <p>After substantial discussion through the day, John Geddes, a Times managing editor, decided to put the story inside the newspaper, on the Metro front -- Page 30 in the national edition, 37 in the edition circulated in metropolitan New York.</p>
        <p>Connie McClellan of Portland, Ore., said she had assumed that her paper was printed before editors had a chance to get the story on the front page. But then she saw Bill O'Reilly accusing The Times of a political decision. She couldn't remember O'Reilly's rationale, ''except that it involved invoking the phrase 'far left' several times.''</p>
        <p>She was one of many readers who wondered why the story didn't go on the front page. It's the same question I had when I picked up The Times and The Washington Post on Sunday morning. The J.F.K. story led The Post. On The Times's front page, there was a one-paragraph promo to the story inside.</p>
        <p>Suzanne Daley, the national editor of The Times, addressed the issue earlier this week on the paper's Web site (nytimes.com), saying that a few editors felt the story should have received more prominent play. But the story went inside, she said, because ''law enforcement officials said that J.F.K. was never in immediate danger. The plotters had yet to lay out plans. They had no financing. Nor did they have any explosives.''</p>
        <p>I asked Marty Gottlieb, the weekend editor and the senior editor in the newsroom when the decision was made, and Geddes, who made the call from home, for more detail about their thinking.</p>
        <p>Gottlieb said that as soon as he learned there was going to be a news conference to announce a terror plot, he phoned Geddes and said, ''Don't go to the beach.'' Based on early reporting, he said he told Geddes, ''This could be the lead, Page 1 or an inside story.''</p>
        <p>Gottlieb told me he was mindful of a history of orange alerts that came at politically convenient times and previous terror plots that wound up amounting to less than they first seemed. He mentioned the case of Jose Padilla, who was accused in 2002 of planning to detonate a radioactive bomb. Padilla's arrest was announced by John Ashcroft, then the attorney general, in an unusual news conference via satellite from Moscow. After being held for years without charges, Padilla is now on trial in Miami, accused of conspiring to aid terrorists. A dirty bomb is no part of the case.</p>
        <p>This time, Times reporters were hearing skepticism from sources in the government, Gottlieb said, and he became even more concerned that the newspaper not ''buy into the hype on an issue where stories have frequently been overstated.''</p>
        <p>Once he decided that leading the paper with the story would be overplay, Gottlieb said that the choice between small play on the front page or major play on the Metro front was less significant to him, a decision that could go either way. He talked to Geddes twice more, and Geddes finally made the call.</p>
        <p>Geddes said, ''There was not a threat that was imminent.'' He knew it could be argued that because this was a slow news day and all the talk was about the terror plot, the story should go out front. But he felt that would make more of it than it deserved.</p>
        <p>My own view is that The Times story was very well reported and written. It quickly made clear that the accused men were a long way from action and that despite the apocalyptic comments of the U.S. attorney, their ability to carry out an attack on the airport was very much open to question.</p>
        <p>But instead of being a reason to put the story inside, I think this was a compelling reason to keep it on Page 1. This reporting put the story in an appropriate perspective, far calmer than the day's television coverage. Giving the story subdued play on the front page -- toward the bottom, with a single-column headline -- would have told readers that The Times knew what they were concerned about, that there was something real here, but that it wasn't anywhere near happening and there was no need for alarm.</p>
        <p>This is just the way The Times played the announcement last year of an alleged plot to blow up the Sears Tower in Chicago -- which seems to have had even less substance to it. That story appeared on Page 1, under a one-column headline, below the fold, even though the F.B.I. was quoted at the top of the story saying that the plan was ''more aspirational than operational.''</p>
        <p>Looking back at last week's decision, Geddes told me: ''If I had it to do over again, might I have started it out front? Yes.''</p>
        <p>Why, I asked.</p>
        <p>''I made the purest call in terms of how I view the front page of the newspaper,'' he said. ''But as I look at the rest of the front page that day, could I have started a small story on the front without diminution of the page? Absolutely. We second-guess ourselves all the time.''</p>
        <p>Do I think political motives were at work? I can't read minds, but I believe after talking with these editors that they were focused on the substance of the story, the facts. They were mindful of a history in which terrorism cases have been blown out of proportion. They were trying to make the right call based on solid journalistic grounds.</p>
        <p>Domestic terrorism is a frightening -- and now very political -- issue. Newspapers cannot take sometimes overheated rhetoric from public officials at face value. But they have to be careful not to appear indifferent to plots that, allowed to mature, could pose real threats of death and destruction.</p>
        <p>It can be a fine line, and I expect that, unfortunately, we'll be faced with these questions again.</p>
        <p>THE PUBLIC EDITOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
