<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Reluctant Fraternity, Thinking Post-Black</title>
    <meta content="10fink" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/arts/design/10fink.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070617T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853483"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Johnson Prize (Art Award)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Johnson, William H, Foundation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finkel, Jori</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arceneaux, Edgar</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcmillian, Rodney</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradford, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newkirk, Kori</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E4DF1E30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2001" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Reluctant Fraternity, Thinking Post-Black</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Reluctant Fraternity, Thinking Post-Black</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JORI FINKEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finkel, Jori</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles four black Los Angeles artists, Edgar Arceneaux, Rodney McMillian, Mark Bradford and Kori Newkirk, who are recent winners or runners-up for Johnson Prize given by William H Johnson Foundation; issues involving being black artist today discussed; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was just after 10 on a Saturday night at the California Club, one of the oldest private clubs in town, and the William H. Johnson Foundation gala was winding down. The artist Edgar Arceneaux had received the annual Johnson Prize, and a new lifetime achievement award had just gone to the actor Sidney Poitier.</p>
        <p>Taking a final turn at the microphone, the gala's founder, the Los Angeles art dealer Steve Turner, said, ''Could we have Mr. Poitier join us for a photograph with the artists -- with Edgar, Rodney, Mark, Kori?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four of the most promising artists to emerge recently in Los Angeles tend to be defined, however paradoxically, by not being defined by their race.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was just after 10 on a Saturday night at the California Club, one of the oldest private clubs in town, and the William H. Johnson Foundation gala was winding down. The artist Edgar Arceneaux had received the annual Johnson Prize, and a new lifetime achievement award had just gone to the actor Sidney Poitier.</p>
        <p>Taking a final turn at the microphone, the gala's founder, the Los Angeles art dealer Steve Turner, said, ''Could we have Mr. Poitier join us for a photograph with the artists -- with Edgar, Rodney, Mark, Kori?''</p>
        <p>He was referring to Mr. Arceneaux, Rodney McMillian, Mark Bradford and Kori Newkirk, artists who have been either winners or runners-up for the Johnson Prize in the last five years. Judging from the buzz that quickly ensued among collectors and curators in the oak-paneled room, they are viewed as four of the most promising artists to emerge recently in that vast incubator that is Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>They have all reached a certain level of critical recognition. All share wall space in high-profile private collections.</p>
        <p>And they all happen to be black, which is no longer an inconceivable thing in the mainstream art world (or at the once-restricted California Club) but is still far from the norm.</p>
        <p>''I believe that African-American artists still face more challenges than white artists in the international contemporary art scene,'' said Mr. Turner, who created the William H. Johnson Foundation in 2001 -- the centenary of its namesake, the black painter, who died in 1970 -- to support minority artists early in their careers. (The Johnson Prize, now $25,000, came a year after that.) ''We know that barriers existed in the past, and I don't think it's time to conclude that they have all disappeared.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Turner said barriers persist ''at the very top,'' with the most established museums and biggest collectors. Yet he said he was encouraged by the growing number of black artists represented at art fairs like Art Basel Miami Beach. And he expressed particular enthusiasm for the ''this new group of African-American artists in L.A.''</p>
        <p>That is, if they even qualify as a group. This can be a prickly issue, as a sign of success for almost any artist today is to be appreciated as an individual rather than as part of some larger demographic. The issue can be especially loaded for black artists, who have historically been shortchanged and undervalued by being lumped together under ''African-American'' or ''Negro'' labels.</p>
        <p>Still, the various affinities and alliances among these four Los Angeles artists are hard to deny. So is the camaraderie. ''We're all friends, and we all support each other in as many ways as possible,'' Mr. Newkirk said. ''We hang out together. If one of us has an opening, everyone will be there. As artists of color, we all face the same obstacles, so we have been able to band together.''</p>
        <p>While they come from different backgrounds geographically and economically, three of the four attended graduate school at Cal Arts, where they studied with the conceptual artist Charles Gaines. (Mr. Newkirk went to the University of California, Irvine.) Three of them are now in their mid-30s. (The running joke at the gala was that Mr. Bradford, a decade older, is too established to qualify for the ''early career'' award anymore, especially now that he has a solo show opening in September at the Whitney Museum of American Art.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Newkirk and Mr. Bradford have been included in several group shows and surveys together, including the 2006 Whitney Biennial. Mr. Arceneaux and Mr. McMillian share the same dealer here: Susanne Vielmetter, who has since taken on their mentor Mr. Gaines as well.</p>
        <p>With his knack for collaborations, Mr. Arceneaux has done a lot to create the impression of a network. He came onto the scene in 2002 with a sprawling installation called ''Rootlessness,'' in which he explored the loaded references to sugar in African-American history by, among other things, dipping a copy of Alex Haley's book ''Roots'' into a sugary solution until it crystallized.</p>
        <p>''Of all of my artists,'' Ms. Vielmetter said, ''Edgar is the one who fosters collaboration the most. This kind of openness is at the heart of his work in some way -- having a plan and then opening it up to chance, intuition, improvisation.''</p>
        <p>He worked with Mr. Gaines on a film, ''Snake River,'' for their joint installation at Redcat gallery last year. And he has completed two projects with Mr. McMillian. Now at the Studio Museum in Harlem is their sci-fi riff on Brancusi's ''Endless Column'' sculpture, a collaboration involving three other friends as well.</p>
        <p>Their first work together, staged at Susanne Vielmetter in 2004, was an exploration of Michael Jackson's weirdly magnetic appeal, featuring videos from his hometown and a black clay sculpture of a sadly deflated balloon.</p>
        <p>As Mr. McMillian describes it, that work came out of a shared obsession with Mr. Jackson's music and physical mutations. ''We are always on the phone or in each other's studio, talking about TV, art, music, family, anything.''</p>
        <p>Still, nobody associated with the artists has been so bold -- or crude -- as to call them a new art movement. Rather, the curators who follow their work suggest that, at most, they all belong to the same rather amorphous generation.</p>
        <p>The buzzword is ''post-black.'' According to Christine Y. Kim of the Studio Museum in Harlem, this generally refers to ''the generation that came in the wake of the 1990s, when Glenn Ligon, Lorna Simpson and Kara Walker opened up different possibilities -- from painting to text to photography -- for discussing identity, race, politics, love.''</p>
        <p>''They set up a certain kind of freedom or individualism for artists of color,'' she added.</p>
        <p>In other words the Johnson artists tend to be defined, however paradoxically, by not being defined by their race. This may help to explain why the artists themselves tend to sound such different notes when asked about their artwork.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradford, for one, best known for gritty collage-paintings layered with urban references, like billboards that keep getting papered over, insisted on their individuality.</p>
        <p>''Our work shouldn't be put in the same box,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Newkirk, who was in the last Whitney Biennial with his signature beaded curtains made out of hair ornaments and braids, suggests that their work shares a certain kinship.</p>
        <p>''We're all making work that can be difficult sometimes, with an incredible investigation into materials and a strong basis in conceptual art,'' he said. ''I would say we're all making work that doesn't hit people over the head with the race conversation anymore. It's a juicy conceptualism-- a ghetto-fabulous conceptualism -- based on reality and the intricacies of daily life.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile the comedian David Alan Grier, who owns work by all four artists, sees a loose group of artists united by their sense of social purpose. ''I might put Rodney and Edgar in one group and Mark and Kori in another,'' he said, noting that Mr. Bradford and Mr. Newkirk have more painterly concerns.</p>
        <p>But he soon complicates his own distinction by adding, ''I initially thought Edgar was just intellectual , but he does these beautiful drawings and paintings.'' (When the artist asked Mr. Grier to collaborate on a video about comic timing called ''The Alchemy of Comedy,'' he was no fool. ''I asked for a painting and said, 'Don't make it small and cheesy.' '')</p>
        <p>While their artistic affinities are open to debate, their professional associations are more a matter of record, starting with the Johnson award itself. The existence of the prize is bound to cluster the prizewinners, much as the Turner Prize in Britain helped to define a generation of so-called Young British Artists in the 1990s.</p>
        <p>And of course the Johnson Prize also suggests a lineage, connecting the artists to William Henry Johnson, an African-American who despite poverty and racism managed to dedicate his life to painting. As a student at the National Academy of Design in New York in the 1920s he was passed over for a traveling fellowship to Europe because he was black. According to Mr. Turner, who organized shows of Johnson's work in the 1990s, his instructors pooled money to send him abroad anyway.</p>
        <p>It was an important trip, one on which he met his future wife, the Danish textile artist Holcha Krake, and found his calling. For unlike his Harlem Renaissance contemporaries, Johnson mainly turned out vivid landscapes of the Scandinavian countryside reminiscent of Gauguin or van Gogh.</p>
        <p>As it happens, none of the Los Angeles artists who have won awards in Johnson's name express much interest in his post-Impressionist landscapes (nor, for that matter, in the California Impressionist paintings of poppy fields that decorate the walls of the California Club). But they do connect to the challenges of his life. ''I'm not a painter, so the thing that intrigues me the most about Johnson is the fullness of his life and the richness of his intellect,'' Mr. Arceneaux said.</p>
        <p>He said he saw the various Johnson award fund-raisers and ceremonies as a forum for talking about issues of race, class and more. ''This community -- my inner circle of artists -- is interested in having a dialogue that is politically and socially engaged,'' he said. ''The Johnson Foundation is creating another space in L.A. where we can advance ideas and positions.''</p>
        <p>Which raises a question: Is this a new boys' club to counteract the old?</p>
        <p>Once again it all depends on whom you ask. The ultimate collaborator, Mr. Arceneaux, openly discusses his network as such. ''The art world is so social, and sometimes I'm the only black face in the crowd,'' he said. ''That's part of the reason I work so hard to maintain this community.''</p>
        <p>''My M.O. is simple in terms of how I navigate life and the rocky waters of the art scene,'' he added. ''I align myself with people with whom I think I share the same affinities.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Newkirk also describes a sense of solidarity. ''We will circle the wagons for each other when we need to. We will protect each other.'' But he points out that the Los Angeles art world has plenty of support systems of this kind, which typically take root during art school. ''The other artists have their Cal Arts mafia, and I have my Irvine mafia. But we also have our artists-of-color mafia too.''</p>
        <p>When asked about the presence of any black female artists, he shook his head and smiled. ''They all left L.A. to take on New York,'' he said, referring to artists like Kira Lynn Harris, the runner-up for this year's Johnson Prize. The first two Johnson Prize winners, Laylah Ali and Nadine Robinson, are women who have long been based on the East Coast.</p>
        <p>Though he stops short of expressions like mafia, Mr. Bradford describes a kind of collegiality. ''I've had informal conversations with everyone,'' he said. ''And when I moved out of my studio, I called Kori and offered it to him.''</p>
        <p>But he does not make too much of race as a factor. ''It's just artists supporting each other, not always because we're black,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Others also play down any hint of exclusivity. ''I don't see them as a clique,'' said Ms. Kim at the Studio Museum in Harlem, who suggested that this group might appear to be a group for purely superficial reasons.</p>
        <p>''If you take 100 people at an art event, and there are 7 black artists talking to each other, it's obvious,'' she said. ''If there are seven white art dealers speaking, you wouldn't even notice them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McMillian agreed. While noting that he and Mr. Arceneaux like to give each other informal critiques (or ''a kick in the shins'') before exhibitions, he said he did not want to overstate their ties.</p>
        <p>''There's huge mutual respect here, but we all have individual practices and lives,'' he said. ''We're not the Algonquin Club.''</p>
        <p>With a nod to the Johnson gala, he added, ''We're only a group when you take a photograph of the group.''</p>
        <p>ART</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 17, 2007, Sunday  An article on June 10 about the recipients of prizes awarded by the William H. Johnson Foundation misstated the role of Steve Turner. He is a founder of the organization -- not the founder of the awards gala, which began as a foundation project. The article also omitted another founder. She is Victoria Dailey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 17, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on June 10 about the recipients of prizes awarded by the William H. Johnson Foundation misstated the role of Steve Turner. He is a founder of the organization -- not the founder of the awards gala, which began as a foundation project. The article also omitted another founder. She is Victoria Dailey.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
