<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN THE REGION/Connecticut; First-Time Buyers, in No Rush</title>
    <meta content="10wczo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/realestate/10wczo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853611"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="In the Region | Connecticut"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E2DC1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="938" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN THE REGION/Connecticut; First-Time Buyers, in No Rush</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">First-Time Buyers, in No Rush</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA PREVOST</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY'RE cautious, they're particular, and they're determined not to be taken advantage of.</p>
        <p>They're Fairfield County's first-time home buyers, and for the past year or so, they've been patiently combing listings for the bargains they think they deserve in a market glutted with inventory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fairfield County’s first-time home buyers have been patiently combing listings for the bargains they think they deserve in a market glutted with inventory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEY'RE cautious, they're particular, and they're determined not to be taken advantage of.</p>
        <p>They're Fairfield County's first-time home buyers, and for the past year or so, they've been patiently combing listings for the bargains they think they deserve in a market glutted with inventory.</p>
        <p>''In years past, they were just happy to get a house they could afford,'' said Eileen Murphy, an agent in the Darien office of William Pitt Sotheby's. ''Now, they're wanting more.''</p>
        <p>Take Melissa Axen and her husband, Rafael, an anesthesiologist who works in Mount Kisco. Transplants from San Francisco, they were paying $3,500 a month in rent for a small apartment just below East Harlem, and another $500 a month for a parking space, after they moved last June. Worried they were throwing their money away, the Axens set out to look for a house, first in Westchester, and then, lured by lower property taxes, in Fairfield County.</p>
        <p>''We saw houses that had been sitting on the market for a while, but the people didn't seem very willing to come down in price,'' said Dr. Axen, 31. ''We saw where the market was heading, and we didn't want to meet them at their price, either.''</p>
        <p>With nothing to lose, the Axens tried lowballing. ''We made a couple of offers, and we kind of grossly underbid because we thought the places were grossly overpriced,'' Dr. Axen said, acknowledging, ''We got no counteroffers.''</p>
        <p>That sort of take-it-or-leave-it confidence is prevalent among first-time buyers these days, right up until the moment they find the one house they must have, agents say.</p>
        <p>Despite declining sales, the median price of single-family homes countywide has continued to hold its own, at $530,000 for the first quarter of the year, up 0.1 percent from a year earlier, according to the Warren Group, a real estate research organization.</p>
        <p>''Because of what they've heard or read about it being a buyer's market, buyers are a little disappointed with prices,'' said Brad Kimmelman, an agent with Neumann Real Estate in Ridgefield. ''They're expecting to get bigger bargains than they are.''</p>
        <p>Many are holding out for highly favorable deals. L. J. Marlin, a vice president of a travel management company, has been looking since January for a two-bedroom condominium in Stamford priced below $350,000. A lifelong renter in her early 50s, she currently lives in a downtown high-rise apartment with her elderly father, who moved in about seven years ago. He has grown so accustomed to Stamford that Ms. Marlin is intent on finding a condo within the city.</p>
        <p>She hasn't yet found one that she likes, but even though her lease is up this month, she has not given up. ''It's really very challenging,'' she said. ''I thought there would be more in my price range.''</p>
        <p>Even in cases where first-time buyers do find plenty of properties available in their price ranges, they are demanding more for their money. In towns like Darien, where listings in the $800,000 entry-level range once prompted ''feeding frenzies,'' first-timers are turning up their noses unless those houses have newer baths and kitchens, Ms. Murphy said.</p>
        <p>This market is their friend in that regard. Fairfield County has such a backlog of inventory that in April and May, only 24 percent of the available single-family houses sold, compared with 70 percent for the corresponding period last year, according to Mark Markelz, a sales vice president in the Southport office of William Raveis International.</p>
        <p>Frequently well-versed in market conditions, the most wary first-time buyers are likely to analyze the purchase process endlessly, sometimes driving agents to distraction. Lauren Wendell, an agent with William Pitt Sotheby's Wilton office, described one client who spent nine months looking only at two-bedroom condos. ''After we looked at a property, he would go back and feed all the information into a spreadsheet,'' Ms. Wendell said. The client did eventually buy a condo in Stamford.</p>
        <p>Thaddea Sheridan, an agent in the Stamford office of William Pitt, recalled several first-time buyers who lost houses to competitors because they put in such low bids. ''They don't want to buy something and feel that they could have got it for a little less down the road,'' Ms. Sheridan said.</p>
        <p>Ashleigh Osterhout, 28, says she struggles with ''a guilty feeling'' for having paid full price ($445,000) for a Victorian fixer-upper in Norwalk. She and her husband, Brandon, closed on the deal last month after about four months of house hunting.</p>
        <p>Many of the other properties they had looked at appeared overpriced, she said, and the sellers ''were still stuck in the mind-set of a couple of years ago when everybody was selling for a huge profit.'' The Osterhouts had hoped to pay less for the Victorian but wound up having to top another bid.</p>
        <p>''I'm thinking maybe I should have waited for a house we could have bargained for,'' said Ms. Osterhout, who works in marketing in South Norwalk. ''But we really wanted this house.''</p>
        <p>The Axens feel a little more confident about the deal they struck for a house on Fox Hill Lake in Ridgefield. The half-acre lot is what sold them on the property: the four-bedroom house sits on a hill that slopes down to about 200 feet of lake frontage. The sale price, $560,000, was $90,000 less than the original list price and gave the Axens enough financial leeway to renovate and expand.</p>
        <p>For former city dwellers, living on the lake is ''kind of like living on vacation,'' Dr. Axen said. ''I think we got good value for our money.''</p>
        <p>Yet, he concedes, there is one drawback to the otherwise prime location: no takeout delivery.</p>
        <p>In the Region | Connecticut</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
