<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Pianist for Whom Never Was Never an Option</title>
    <meta content="10brub" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/arts/music/10brub.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853489"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Botox (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brubach, Holly</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fleisher, Leon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Botox (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Botox (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Fleisher, Leon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E3DF1E30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Pianist for Whom Never Was Never an Option</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Pianist for Whom Never Was Never an Option</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOLLY BRUBACH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brubach, Holly</byline>
      <dateline>BALTIMORE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles pianist Leon Fleisher, whose loss of use of right hand brought worldwide attention; with Botox injections to treat his neurological disorder, Fleisher began to recover use of his right hand over ten years ago and continues active career at age 80; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is now more than 10 years since Leon Fleisher began to recover the use of his right hand in an astonishing twist that conferred a Hollywood-style happy ending on a story with all the hallmarks of a tear-jerker. Piano fans know the details: how in 1964, preparing for a tour of the Soviet Union with George Szell and the Cleveland Orchestra, Mr. Fleisher experienced the first signs of a problem. Two of his fingers began to curl under uncontrollably; within 10 months they were clenched in a fist. No pain. Medical experts were baffled.</p>
        <p>He redirected his musical energies to performing the left-hand repertory, teaching and conducting, all the while continuing to seek a cure. Finally, some 30 years later, after the onset of symptoms, a diagnosis of focal dystonia, a neurological disorder, led to an experimental treatment involving Botox injections.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Leon Fleisher, who began to recover the use of his right hand after suffering from a neurological disorder for some three decades, now plays and records widely.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is now more than 10 years since Leon Fleisher began to recover the use of his right hand in an astonishing twist that conferred a Hollywood-style happy ending on a story with all the hallmarks of a tear-jerker. Piano fans know the details: how in 1964, preparing for a tour of the Soviet Union with George Szell and the Cleveland Orchestra, Mr. Fleisher experienced the first signs of a problem. Two of his fingers began to curl under uncontrollably; within 10 months they were clenched in a fist. No pain. Medical experts were baffled.</p>
        <p>He redirected his musical energies to performing the left-hand repertory, teaching and conducting, all the while continuing to seek a cure. Finally, some 30 years later, after the onset of symptoms, a diagnosis of focal dystonia, a neurological disorder, led to an experimental treatment involving Botox injections.</p>
        <p>His comeback has catapulted him up next to Lance Armstrong as a symbol of the indomitable human spirit and an inspiration to a broader public. ''Two Hands,'' a 20-minute documentary about Mr. Fleisher by Nathaniel Kahn, was nominated for an Oscar this year. Mr. Fleisher proudly sports in his lapel the small grosgrain rosette the French government bestowed on him last year. (''And when I go to bed,'' he said, ''I put it on my pajamas.'')</p>
        <p>Several weeks shy of his 80th birthday, Mr. Fleisher maintains a schedule most people half his age would find exhausting, performing widely and recording, most recently, the Brahms Piano Quintet with the Emerson String Quartet, just released by Deutsche Grammophon. He rejects the suggestion that he's making up for lost time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fleisher claims that no matter how bleak his chances for recovery appeared, there was never a moment when he thought he wouldn't play again with two hands. Never? ''I just couldn't accept it,'' he said during a series of conversations this spring at the home in Baltimore that he shares with his third wife, Kathy Jacobson-Fleisher, also a pianist. ''And I guess my fantasy was that with the same mystery with which it had appeared, it would disappear.''</p>
        <p>He pursued every avenue, however unlikely, and his flailing attempts to fix a problem that remained a mystery spanned some 35 years and ran the gamut from A to Z, he said, ''from aromatherapy to Zen Buddhism.'' Nothing worked, though Rolfing helped. ''And the thing that was so insidious,'' he said, ''was the suggestion, for a while unspoken and then spoken, that it's all in your head, man. You know, go get it talked out. So I tried that for a while too.'' To no avail.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Fleisher's recovery has been touted as evidence of the miraculous powers of Botox, Julian Fleisher, his first child from his second marriage (who introduces himself as Opus 2, No. 1) and a musician himself (a jazz singer), is of the firm belief that all those failed attempts added up in the end. ''I don't know if the Botox would have been as effective as it has been,'' his son said, ''had he not spent all those years developing an awareness of his hand and trying all those things.''</p>
        <p>There are works Mr. Fleisher wouldn't try to play now, but then it's probably safe to say that few other pianists his age would try them either. The commotion in the wake of his comeback has occasionally obscured that his ''recovery'' is really a remission, only temporary.</p>
        <p>''I would like to make it clearly understood that I have not been cured of focal dystonia,'' he said. ''A way has been found to ameliorate the symptoms enough to enable me to play this literature to an extent that is not only enjoyable but also presentable in public.'' A protocol that began with Botox shots every six months has been recalibrated to a lower dosage over shorter intervals, enough to keep the muscle contractions at bay but not so much that it triggers an initial period of weakness, which Mr. Fleisher found disorienting.</p>
        <p>Apart from technical considerations his primary criterion for choosing what he plays these days seems to be affection. Of the Brahms quintet he says, ''It's extraordinary that such a grand and in a sense massive work can be realized by just five players.'' Egon Petri's transcription of Bach's ''Sheep May Safely Graze'' has become something of a signature piece, a staple of Mr. Fleisher's solo programs. It is to his mind ''the antiterror piece of our time.''</p>
        <p>''It's like deep breathing or yoga,'' he said. ''It restores balance.''</p>
        <p>It also typifies a willingness on his part to take on repertory that isn't flashy, to locate and articulate the sublime in music that many pianists of his stature wouldn't bother to record. ''The Journey,'' his most recent solo album, includes a fond reading of Beethoven's ''Für Elise,'' a piece more familiar to some listeners from their own piano lessons than from any historic performance etched in memory.</p>
        <p>''Two Hands,'' released in 2004, features Debussy's ''Clair de Lune,'' among the most overexposed works in all of classical music; Mr. Fleisher's rendition forces us to reconsider it and ultimately to reclassify it a masterpiece. He chose it, he said, because ''it seemed like such an appropriate companion to the Chopin nocturne'' with which he pairs it, his mother's favorite piece. Both ''night pieces,'' both in the same key, D flat: ''It's the same material as approached by two different geniuses.'' he added.</p>
        <p>In the few instances in which Mr. Fleisher has returned to a piece he recorded pre-dystonia, it is tempting to compare the performances ''before and after,'' and to hear in the later versions some nuances or shadings that had eluded him in his youth, back when his life was unfolding according to plan. Julian detects ''a certain amount of gratitude'' in his father's playing these days. The elder Mr. Fleisher's rendition of Mozart's Sonata in E flat (K. 272) on ''The Journey'' feels more serene than his 1959 performance, bright and declamatory.</p>
        <p>Yet, it is difficult if not impossible, even for Mr. Fleisher himself, to pinpoint the degree to which his enforced absence from the two-hand repertory has changed him as a person and as a musician. Life knocks the corners off; age, or experience, accounts for some degree of transformation in every artist.</p>
        <p>''One hears new implications,'' he said. ''I think one has a tendency to take more time. One listens and takes time to listen. One is not afraid to more deeply characterize certain ideas.''</p>
        <p>The silences are particularly striking. Mr. Fleisher tells his students that ''silence is not the absence of music'' and urges them to play, judiciously, ''as late as possible, without being late.'' Among the most surprising effects on his recent recordings are heart-stopping moments of anticipation, distending time as the listener waits for a note that begins to seem as if it will never come. ''It's almost an instant of panic: Where is it?'' Mr. Fleisher acknowledged. ''We're talking about nanoseconds.''</p>
        <p>The critics, though respectful and often admiring, have not hesitated to dock him for missed notes, usually in dense passages at a fast tempo. Does he read his reviews? ''No,'' he said. ''I know how I play. I don't need somebody else to tell me. And I don't quite understand why the public reads them. If they enjoy something of a Thursday night, do they need someone to tell them Friday morning, 'Yes, you were right to enjoy that,' or 'That was not enjoyable'? ''</p>
        <p>Julian said: ''Yes, he misses notes, and I think it forces a lot of people to re-examine their priorities when it comes to this kind of music. If there's nobody else who's going to play the slow movement of the Brahms concerto like that, then get over it.''</p>
        <p>Neither of Mr. Fleisher's parents was a musician. The younger son of a San Francisco milliner, he would listen to his brother's piano lessons and then go to the piano and recapitulate the lesson, note for note. He was 5 at the time.</p>
        <p>Does he believe in destiny? ''Yeah, I guess so,'' he replied. ''I believe in karma. 'My karma ran over my dogma': that's one of my favorite bumper stickers.'' Given the chance to rewrite the story of his life, he said, he's not sure he would change it. ''There are forces out there,'' he added, ''and if you keep yourself open to them, if you go along with them, there are wondrous surprises.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fleisher is convinced that he is a better pianist for having become a conductor, as he would probably not have done had his career stayed on course. He may also be, he says, a better teacher. With his remarkable ability to articulate musical ideas in images, he describes a tune as ''rising the way a balloon does, at an ever-decreasing rate of speed, to the point where the pressure outside equals the pressure inside, and it stays suspended.'' He talks about conducting an orchestra around a curve in the musical line and generating the sort of centrifugal force that causes the driver of a car to lean to the left as he turns his wheels to the right.</p>
        <p>''Not being able to push the student off the chair and say, 'This is the way I think it should go,' '' he said, ''I had to find words -- which is tough enough, because music usually begins where words leave off -- to find the words that most precisely describe the ineffable, the ephemeral.''</p>
        <p>Focal dystonia disproportionately strikes musicians (among them, the pianist Gary Graffman, a contemporary of Mr. Fleisher), occurring not at the localized, mechanical level in the hand but at the neurological level in the brain, which issues a command to contract certain muscles involuntarily. Research has confirmed that regions of the somatosensory cortex, responsible for the sense of touch, become blurred over time when signals are repeatedly received so close together (as with two adjacent fingers in a fast tempo) that they come to be perceived as simultaneous.</p>
        <p>The danger, in Mr. Fleisher's opinion, is ''mindless repetition,'' and he uses his teaching as an occasion to warn the next generation. ''Whatever you do with your fingers and your hands must be in the service of an idea,'' he said, ''an ideal that you hear in your head before you play. If before you put the key down for a single note, unless you have a goal for that note, it's an accident.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fleisher describes the performer as three people in one: ''Person A hears before they play. They have to have this ideal in their inner ear of what they're going to try and realize. Person B actually puts the keys down, plays and tries to manifest what Person A hears. Person C sits a little bit apart and listens. And if what C hears is not what A intended, C tells B to adjust to get closer to what A wanted. And this goes on with every note you play, no matter how fast you're playing. It's a simultaneous process that advances horizontally. When it works, when it all meshes, it's a state of ecstasy.''</p>
        <p>History does not lack for examples of great artists who, disabled by some tragic event, an accident or an ailment, lost the capacity to exercise their talent. In the 20th century alone the list includes Paul Wittgenstein, the Austrian-born pianist who lost his right arm as a soldier in World War I and commissioned much of the left-hand repertory Mr. Fleisher played during his long hiatus; Vaslav Nijinsky, the dancer and choreographer, incarcerated in a mental asylum; Tanaquil LeClercq, the ballerina felled by polio; and Mr. Graffman. The Lord giveth and the Lord taketh away, not always for any apparent reason. And if the past is any indication, the Lord rarely giveth back. The list of great artists who ultimately regained the faculties they were forced to relinquish is, at last tally, a list of one.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
