<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Debut, But Hardly A Fresh Start</title>
    <meta content="10roberts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853382"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Selena Roberts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EED9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Debut, But Hardly A Fresh Start</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The rugged deity ambled through the Yankees' clubhouse yesterday like a Clint Eastwood figure in touch with the softer side of his grit-spittin' aura.</p>
        <p>Roger Clemens's cowboy boots were powder blue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The rugged deity ambled through the Yankees' clubhouse yesterday like a Clint Eastwood figure in touch with the softer side of his grit-spittin' aura.</p>
        <p>Roger Clemens's cowboy boots were powder blue.</p>
        <p>The marvel of muscle who graced a Yankee Stadium balcony a month ago as if he were channeling Evita couldn't help making his traditional tour of Monument Park before the first start of his resurrection.</p>
        <p>After all, Clemens plays baseball as if it were tourist season.</p>
        <p>On the sacred ground next to the bullpen, there is a collection of Yankees legends, like Babe Ruth and Lou Gehrig. Bronzed images are everywhere. And in a private moment, it wouldn't be surprising if Clemens asked himself, Where's mine? Why wait for posthumous adoration when, for several weeks, Clemens has been immortalized with life still left in his fastball? Why not engrave his likeness into a plaque when, in his latest incarnation, Clemens lives as a Yankees monument of excess?</p>
        <p>It is impossible to diminish Clemens's virtuosity or work ethic or mythic competitiveness, though scrutiny is fair in the era of steroid suspects. But with his fame in tow yesterday, Clemens didn't arrive as a savior. He simply stood as a replica of the Yankees' past, of the championless time span right before and after he left four years ago.</p>
        <p>Right on cue, the team slipped its old skin in a burst of nostalgia as it dominated a young Pirates team that had peach fuzz, launching a relentless offense and a spirited base-running attack, with agile defense and the Rocket on the mound.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to savor this moment,'' Clemens said after a serviceable debut in which he allowed three runs and five hits, with two walks and seven strikeouts, over six innings. ''I know what's ahead of us.''</p>
        <p>But the past wasn't supposed to be the Yankees' future. The pinstriped pipers had spent the past seven years flogging teams like the Pirates with a band of mercenaries, only to end up humiliated in the playoffs by the Angels or the Tigers. The Yankees had spent an entire off-season purging their aging ghosts and expensive albatrosses in an attempt to move in a younger direction for a brighter future.</p>
        <p>The old star system wasn't working, as Brian Cashman declared on several occasions. With his request for autonomy, Cashman drew up a more sophisticated blueprint, which, as it turned out, had all the shelf life of goat's milk.</p>
        <p>If anything, Clemens is the platinum memento of Cashman's panic. By signing Clemens to a deal that will cost the Yankees $24.4 million counting the luxury tax, Cashman lost patience with his own ambition to be the next Billy Beane.</p>
        <p>Not two seconds ago, Cashman fancied himself as the next baseball stat rat on a CNBC buzz who whipped results from undervalued stocks, as the next basepath genius able to assemble a winning team out of wit, not out of pocket.</p>
        <p>Now the meter is running on Big Hook Cashman. More than any other move by Cashman -- including the notable failures of Carl Pavano and Kei Igawa -- his decision to grab Clemens threatens his standing in George Steinbrenner's orbit.</p>
        <p>''He wanted sole authority,'' Steinbrenner told The Associated Press last month. ''He got it. Now he's got to deliver.''</p>
        <p>Cashman has delivered the same old, same old with Clemens. He overpaid yet another aging pitcher. Clemens is on the verge of 45 with an odometer that has turned over and a groin muscle with no elasticity.</p>
        <p>Yes, he brings a fighting spirit, but Clemens was an unnecessary luxury item. Before Clemens faced the Pirates, the Yankees had started to find themselves.</p>
        <p>''We're feeling pretty good about ourselves,'' Manager Joe Torre said yesterday after the Yankees' fifth victory in a row. ''The players were really upbeat. Part of it is Roger, but it's also how we're feeling right now.''</p>
        <p>They're feeling like survivors. The Yankees have emerged from a sluggish start and Torre's job insecurity, from A-Rod's tabloid pics and Jason Giambi's tacit steroid admission. Now along comes the Rocket.</p>
        <p>His health could become the next distraction. No one is more aware of his precarious status than he is. Unsolicited, Clemens raised the issue of his physical state repeatedly after he pitched. ''My body,'' he said in several variations. ''That's the major concern.''</p>
        <p>Clemens labored through 108 pitches and a nonthreatening Pirates lineup without flinching. Does Clemens play on as a medical miracle or does he concede to reality? How will his celebrated stop in New York end? In glory or on the disabled list?</p>
        <p>''Whatever happens in New York is part of his legacy,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Cashman signed Clemens for his legacy. He landed him to block the Red Sox and relieve the criticism and soothe the Boss. It wasn't the kind of maneuver he longed to be known for among baseball academics. This wasn't a counterculture move of the ''Moneyball'' club. This wasn't an ingenious decision to draw raves from the society of seam savants.</p>
        <p>This was a move out of the past. This was a scene from four years ago.</p>
        <p>There was Clemens, striding off the mound after ending his day with consecutive strikeouts in the sixth inning, with the crowd on its feet and Elton John's ''Rocket Man'' pumping through the loudspeakers.</p>
        <p>''It felt like old times,'' Clemens said.</p>
        <p>Is that a good thing? Replicating the past is no way for the Yankees to move ahead.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
