<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>South Korean Is Leader; Wie Has Worst Day as Pro</title>
    <meta content="10lpga" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/sports/golf/10lpga.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853360"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ladies Professional Golf Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wie, Michelle</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Pak, Se Ri</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2D9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>South Korean Is Leader; Wie Has Worst Day as Pro</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">South Korean Is Leader; Wie Has Worst Day as Pro</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <dateline>HAVRE DE GRACE, Md., June 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A teenager of Korean descent zoomed up the leader board Saturday at the L.P.G.A. Championship, but it was not Michelle Wie.</p>
        <p>For a few hours, at least, an 18-year-old from South Korea, Na On Min, made Wie seem so last year. Min shot a seven-under-par 65 to assume the third-round lead. Wie, who is Min's junior by 11 months, posted her worst 18-hole score as a professional, an 11-over 83, dropping to last place with a 14-over 230 total.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Na On Min made Michelle Wie seem so last year, shooting a seven-under-par 65 to assume the third-round lead at the L.P.G.A. Championship.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A teenager of Korean descent zoomed up the leader board Saturday at the L.P.G.A. Championship, but it was not Michelle Wie.</p>
        <p>For a few hours, at least, an 18-year-old from South Korea, Na On Min, made Wie seem so last year. Min shot a seven-under-par 65 to assume the third-round lead. Wie, who is Min's junior by 11 months, posted her worst 18-hole score as a professional, an 11-over 83, dropping to last place with a 14-over 230 total.</p>
        <p>Min, playing in her sixth L.P.G.A. tournament and her first major, made eight birdies and one bogey on the Bulle Rock Golf Course for a 10-under total of 206. She swept past the second-round leader, Suzann Pettersen, who shot a 71 in blustery conditions and is one shot behind Min.</p>
        <p>Karrie Webb and Angela Park are two strokes back. Morgan Pressel, who is trying to become the eighth player to win the L.P.G.A. Tour's first two majors in the same year, is three shots back.</p>
        <p>Min is nowhere near as well-known as Wie, who had the biggest gallery Saturday but also the biggest score. The 83 was Wie's highest score since turning professional in October 2005 and her worst score since posting an 85 four years ago as a 13-year-old.</p>
        <p>Her round included eight bogeys, two double-bogeys and one birdie. It was the first time since mid-October that the 17-year-old Wie, an American whose parents were born in Korea, has played three competitive rounds in a row.</p>
        <p>''I just have to be patient with myself,'' said Wie, who is coming off two wrist injuries. She added, ''Obviously it was a little tougher today with the wind.''</p>
        <p>The wind turned club selection into a maddening riddle for the golfers. Min was not immune to it. On the 15th hole, a 493-yard par-5, she drove into the fairway and was 200 yards from the green, a distance that left her unsure whether to use her 7-wood or a 4-iron.</p>
        <p>After deciding to go with the wood, she hit the ball onto the fringe of the green and two-putted for a birdie. It was the kind of clutch shot that might give even the most seasoned veterans pause, but Min stepped up and hit it as if she had been playing for decades.</p>
        <p>In fact, she took up the game six years ago, when she was 12. ''It's incredible, knowing how few years she has been playing, to watch her hit the shots she hits and see how she handles herself out there,'' her caddie, Dana Derouaux, said. He added, ''She really is phenomenal.''</p>
        <p>Derouaux was on Min's bag at the L.P.G.A.'s final qualifying tournament in the fall, when she finished tied for 18th to earn nonexempt status for the 2007 season. She turned pro immediately after the qualifying tournament and is now trying to emulate her countrywomen Se Ri Pak and Birdie Kim, whose first victories on the Tour came in majors.</p>
        <p>Min, squinting in the glare of the camera lights, conducted her interviews in English. Asked if she expected to be nervous Sunday, she smiled and said, ''Yeah, because this is my first major.'' She added, ''But I'll do my best and keep focused on each shot.''</p>
        <p>Wie, who was sidelined from competitive golf for four months with a fractured left wrist and tendinitis in her right wrist, emerged from the scoring trailer behind the 18th hole and immediately applied an ice pack to her left wrist.</p>
        <p>If this tournament had not been the year's second major, Wie said, she probably would not have entered. ''I think that I was kind of blinded because I wanted to play so bad,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Her track record in the big events gave her reason to want to take her chances and hope for the best. Of her 11 top-five finishes in L.P.G.A. Tour events, 6 have come in majors. In two previous appearances in this event, Wie did not finish lower than fifth.</p>
        <p>Wie, who shot 73-74 in the first two rounds to make the cut on the nose, stands 84th. Asked if she would play her final 18 holes, she said, ''I don't really know.'' Wie added: ''I really want to play. I think it would be awesome to get another experience, a round under my belt. Just have to see how it goes tonight.''</p>
        <p>At the start of the week, Min was hoping for a top-10 finish. But based on what has happened, that has changed. ''Now,'' she said, ''my goal is to win.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
