<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Manhattan Transfer</title>
    <meta content="10wwln--domains.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/magazine/10wwln-domains-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 6-10-07: DOMAIN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewine, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cassavetes, Zoe R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cassavetes, John (1929-89)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rowlands, Gena</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Broken English (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Cassavetes, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE0D81130F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="928" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Manhattan Transfer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Manhattan Transfer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Edward Lewine</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewine, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Zoe R Cassavetes, writer and director of film Broken English, in her studio apartment in West Village tenement building, where she talks about her parents, John Cassavetes and Gene Rowlands, her daily routines, favorite things and the like; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Her middle initial: I'm usually credited that way; the R is for my mother's last name. I'm proud of both my parents, John Cassavetes and Gena Rowlands, but I don't think I had anything to do with using her initial. It just appeared there one day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Zoe R. Cassavetes, the writer and director of the new film “Broken English,” lives in a studio apartment in a West Village tenement building.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Her middle initial: I'm usually credited that way; the R is for my mother's last name. I'm proud of both my parents, John Cassavetes and Gena Rowlands, but I don't think I had anything to do with using her initial. It just appeared there one day.</p>
        <p>Childhood home: No matter how much chaos was going on in our house in L.A., I was brought up strictly. Even when he was in the middle of a movie, my dad always knew where I was and what I was doing.</p>
        <p>At age 5, she wanted to be: A writer. I guess I was always fond of the typewriter when I was a kid, so I wanted to write. Not that anyone was typing in my house. The typewriter was just sitting there.</p>
        <p>Favorite recent gift: It's a beautiful photograph of Marcello Mastroianni that my sister gave me. It's just the most soulful picture.</p>
        <p>Morning routine: It depends on what happened the night before, but I get up kind of early, around 7 a.m. I read the gossip columns and the news online and then go to the gym.</p>
        <p>Workout routine: It varies. I have been boxing lately. I am pretty disciplined. I run on the treadmill or do yoga.</p>
        <p>Breakfast drink: Fresh-squeezed orange juice. My fiancé lives in Paris, and he started the craze. I have this glass squeezer from the 1940s.</p>
        <p>Hobby: I collect first editions. Peter Bogdanovich gave me my first first edition. It was a Robert Graves book, ''Watch the North Wind Rise.'' That was about 20 years ago. I also have ''Franny and Zooey'' and ''This Side of Paradise,'' among others.</p>
        <p>Last book she read: ''The Dogs of Babel,'' by Carolyn Parkhurst. I loved it. It's a beautiful story. It is very romantic.</p>
        <p>Family pets: I collect Chinese figures. They are all animals. My mother gave me these beautiful old English leopards. Then a friend of mine, whom I lived with for a while, gave me a few. I have around 10 of them.</p>
        <p>Obsolete item she can't part with: A wooden, ancient Chinese dragon carving. It broke on the bottom, but I can't seem to get rid of it. I inherited it from my grandmother.</p>
        <p>Best memento of father: I have a handwritten card of his. It contains a little poem he wrote just for me.</p>
        <p>Chore she's fastidious about: Taking out the trash. This is a small place, so you need to keep it clear.</p>
        <p>Chore she isn't fastidious about: Vacuuming. It's good when you do it, but let's face it, you can always turn off a few lights and it doesn't matter.</p>
        <p>Place she spends most time: My bed. It's my office. I put my computer there. It's the biggest work space I have. I can control everything from there. I have a good relationship with my bed.</p>
        <p>Favorite possession: A bracelet my fiancé, Sébastien Chenut, gave me. He's a French musician and did the music for my movie. The bracelet is gorgeous, and I love it when men take time to pick out jewelry.</p>
        <p>Where she'll live post-marriage: Both places, but I'll spend more of my time in Paris.</p>
        <p>What she misses about New York in Paris: Deliveries; any kind of delivery.</p>
        <p>Traveling ritual: Usually a couple of friends come over and bring a bottle of Champagne while I pack. This leads to incomplete packing, but it's fun while it happens.</p>
        <p>What's on her iPod: I don't have an iPod. I don't like things in my ears.</p>
        <p>Historical figure she'd like to have met: Ernest Hemingway. He seemed like a good time, when he wasn't really depressed and killing himself.</p>
        <p>Evening routine: No matter how much I want to stay in, I go out. I have dinner; come home; chill; have a cup of tea; finish evening calls and e-mails; say good night to my fiancé on video conferencing. Lights out is normally around midnight.</p>
        <p>What's by her bed: Bottle of water; my alarm clock; paper and pens; and hand cream. It's all about the hand cream. I don't want old hands.</p>
        <p>Always in fridge: Yogurt; Fuji apples; low-fat milk; Salvador Dali perfume.</p>
        <p>Always on hand: I keep a supply of toys, books and videos for my friends' kids. I have crayons and paper and save their drawings on the refrigerator.</p>
        <p>Biggest self-indulgence: Watching TV. Though, for someone who likes watching TV so much, I don't have cable. I bought myself a flat screen and I use it to watch DVDs.</p>
        <p>Favorite TV program: ''Weeds,'' on Showtime.</p>
        <p>I watch it on DVD and iTunes. The acting is great, and it's not really what you think it's about. It's about the struggle of living after losing somebody.</p>
        <p>Next big purchase: I have to get a job first.</p>
        <p>Item that defines her: My rug, simply because I've had it for a long time. It's an old Oriental my mom bought for me when I moved to New York.</p>
        <p>Always with her: My purse. I have a bag tree of all my different ones. Inside I keep lipstick, my cellphone, my address book, pens and a notebook.</p>
        <p>Favorite place to shop: Marc Jacobs, because he makes clothes I actually want to wear.</p>
        <p>Superstitions: I grew up Greek, so there were many superstitions around. But I say if you don't believe them, they have no power.</p>
        <p>Best memento of mother: It may seem shallow to say it, but a 1960s Ungaro couture coat. And I do wear it.</p>
        <p>Toughest thing about famous parents: People think you have it much easier than you do.</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 6-10-07: DOMAIN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
