<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Final Piece for Federer; Toughest Puzzle in Nadal</title>
    <meta content="10men" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/sports/tennis/10men.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853343"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Nadal, Rafael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Federer, Roger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E7D9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Final Piece for Federer; Toughest Puzzle in Nadal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Final Piece for Federer; Toughest Puzzle in Nadal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIET MACUR</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sometimes, when his days are quiet and his mind has time to wander, Roger Federer sits back and thinks about his place in the world.</p>
        <p>''It comes more like maybe during vacation sometimes, or, I don't know, when I'm just traveling and I'm going from one place to the next,'' Federer said Saturday. ''I can't believe I'm traveling to another tournament. It's so nice. Everybody is expecting me. I'm No. 1 in the world.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even though he is just 21, Rafael Nadal knows that his rivalry with Roger Federer has already become part of tennis lore. The two will meet Sunday in the French Open final.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sometimes, when his days are quiet and his mind has time to wander, Roger Federer sits back and thinks about his place in the world.</p>
        <p>''It comes more like maybe during vacation sometimes, or, I don't know, when I'm just traveling and I'm going from one place to the next,'' Federer said Saturday. ''I can't believe I'm traveling to another tournament. It's so nice. Everybody is expecting me. I'm No. 1 in the world.''</p>
        <p>For sure, everyone at Roland Garros will be waiting for Federer to arrive Sunday for the French Open final. He plays the two-time defending champion Rafael Nadal, who is seeded second and who has knocked him out of this tournament the past two years. Last year, Nadal defeated Federer in the final. In 2005, he stopped him in a semifinal.</p>
        <p>This time, yet again, Federer has a chance to become the first man since Rod Laver in 1969 to hold all four Grand Slam titles at once. But Federer, who is as reserved off the court as Nadal is lovingly goofy, has learned, perhaps, not to get his hopes up.</p>
        <p>''It would mean a lot,'' Federer, 25, said nonchalantly of holding the four titles concurrently. ''There's not much more I can say, really. I mean, I've put myself in position, now I just have one match to go. So hopefully I can do it this year.''</p>
        <p>For the past four years, Federer has won Wimbledon. For the past three, the United States Open. He also has won the past two Australian Open titles, and three over all.</p>
        <p>But like Pete Sampras, the career leader with 14 Grand Slam victories, Federer is known as one of the best players in history -- but on the red clay, he has never been good enough.</p>
        <p>''To be the best of all time, he's got to win this, and I think this year's his best chance,'' said the seven-time Grand Slam champion John McEnroe, who also came up empty at the French Open.</p>
        <p>''He's got moves like Baryshnikov, balletic moves that I've never seen before. He's incredible. But he needs to win this one. If he does, he would be considered even better than Pete.''</p>
        <p>Nadal beat Federer five times in a row on clay before losing to him last month in Hamburg, Germany. Still, he seems to have the edge in Paris.</p>
        <p>While Federer played uncharacteristically sloppy tennis in his semifinal against fourth-seeded Nikolay Davydenko, with 45 unforced errors, Nadal has been improving with each match.</p>
        <p>In those sleeveless shirts that show off his bulging biceps, Nadal, 21, has come out of the locker room snorting like a bull for the past two weeks. He has not lost a set and is playing his best tennis of his career.</p>
        <p>''He's like the 21st-century version of Bjorn Borg, but bigger and stronger, and Borg was the best clay-court player ever,'' McEnroe said.</p>
        <p>''If Federer plays well enough to beat a guy like Nadal, if he finally wins here, you could really call him the best in history,'' he added. ''It will be sort of like the perfect ending for him.''</p>
        <p>On the way to accomplishing that, though, there is pressure. Federer's father, Robert, said that Roger had been nervous. Still, the younger Federer has said he has been calmer than in the past years. The victory against Nadal in Hamburg helped.</p>
        <p>''I'm ready for a tough opponent,'' Federer said Saturday. ''I'm ready for rain. I'm ready for a five-hour match, so it's no problem.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, Nadal said that he was also ready for a long day, long points and a five-set match, which he has never lost on clay. He has not been overly confident, though. In discussing his matchup against Federer in the final, he has been humble, bowing to Federer and saying it is an honor to play the No. 1 player in the world.</p>
        <p>Nadal, who has been No. 2 behind Federer for 98 weeks, said that he appreciates having a player that good to shoot for.</p>
        <p>And, when his days are quiet and his mind has time to wander, Nadal sits back and thinks about Federer. He says that he envisions Federer's footwork, shot selection and graceful moves. Then, on the practice court, he tries to copy them.</p>
        <p>But when asked if he liked having Federer around to push him, or preferred that Federer not exist, Nadal answered quickly.</p>
        <p>''Well, the second option is better,'' he said, laughing. ''But you never know. If Roger's not here, another one.</p>
        <p>''No, for me, it's nice, and it's always special motivation to have another one better than you, no?''</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
