<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Still True to the Red, White and Black</title>
    <meta content="10light" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/arts/music/10light.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853495"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Audio)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">White Stripes (Band)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Light, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">White, Jack (Singer-Guitarist)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">White Stripes</org>
        <person class="online_producer">White, Jack</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2DF1E30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1910" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Still True to the Red, White and Black</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Still True to the Red, White and Black</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN LIGHT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Light, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LEIPER'S FORK, TENN.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles country singer-guitarist Jack White of band White Stripes upon release of new album; desire to keep band unchanged and unusual publicity techniques discussed; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JACK WHITE, the singer-guitarist of the White Stripes, has always kept a tight rein on his band's image, applying stringent rules to everything from the musical arrangements to the black-white-and-red color scheme. His arrival for an interview felt comparably meticulous.</p>
        <p>Mr. White lives in this tiny, blocklong town, a short drive from Nashville, with his pregnant wife, the model Karen Elson, and their 1-year-old daughter, Scarlett. He pulled into the parking lot of an antiques shop in a cream-colored 1960 Thunderbird, dressed head to toe in black. By his side was the band's drummer, Meg White, his ex-wife, wearing a black top and a red skirt. He ambled through the store and settled onto the back porch, a bucolic spot overlooking a creek. He graciously accepted a bottle of water from an associate after the clerk at the grocery store across the street said he had never heard of sparkling water.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Forget progress. The White Stripes is sticking to its (simple) principles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JACK WHITE, the singer-guitarist of the White Stripes, has always kept a tight rein on his band's image, applying stringent rules to everything from the musical arrangements to the black-white-and-red color scheme. His arrival for an interview felt comparably meticulous.</p>
        <p>Mr. White lives in this tiny, blocklong town, a short drive from Nashville, with his pregnant wife, the model Karen Elson, and their 1-year-old daughter, Scarlett. He pulled into the parking lot of an antiques shop in a cream-colored 1960 Thunderbird, dressed head to toe in black. By his side was the band's drummer, Meg White, his ex-wife, wearing a black top and a red skirt. He ambled through the store and settled onto the back porch, a bucolic spot overlooking a creek. He graciously accepted a bottle of water from an associate after the clerk at the grocery store across the street said he had never heard of sparkling water.</p>
        <p>It was a classic rock star entrance, at a time when there are very few Rock Stars left. While indie-rock tastemakers tend to champion bands that look like them, Mr. White still believes that smoke and mirrors, the kind of approach that once caused detractors to dismiss the White Stripes as a gimmick, are integral to successful art. ''Everything from your haircut to your clothes to the type of instrument you play to the melody of a song to the rhythm -- they're all tricks to get people to pay attention to the story,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''If you just stood up in a crowd and said your story -- 'I came home, and this girl I was dating wasn't there, and I was wondering where she was' -- it's not interesting,'' he said. ''But give it a melody, give it a beat, build it all the way up to a haircut. Now people pay attention.''</p>
        <p>With the release next week of their new album, ''Icky Thump'' (Warner Brothers), the White Stripes hope that more people than ever will pay attention to their bag of tricks. Their last album, 2005's ''Get Behind Me Satan,'' sold only about half as much as 2003's platinum-plus ''Elephant,'' which boasted the hit single ''Seven Nation Army.'' The new release is the duo's first for a major label after a decade spent at the vanguard of the turn-of-the-century garage-rock revival, a movement defined by its outsider attitude.</p>
        <p>Mr. White, 31, had traveled from the band's former hometown, Detroit (Ms. White, 32, now lives in Los Angeles) to places like Memphis and London to seek out funky old analog recording studios, but ''Icky Thump'' was recorded in a conventional, modern Nashville studio. The new White Stripes tour will mark the band's first shows headlining at arenas; it is scheduled to play Madison Square Garden on July 24.</p>
        <p>At a time when the music business is in free fall, and young rock fans seem to lose interest in bands almost overnight, the stakes for the White Stripes are higher than ever with the duo's sixth album. But while most bands respond to the pressures of recording for a bigger company or playing on larger stages with a shinier, more radio-friendly sound, the White Stripes are sticking to their guns. ''Icky Thump'' represents a more traditional sound for the band than ''Get Behind Me Satan,'' which experimented with piano- and marimba-based compositions. The new songs, spotlighting Mr. White's virtuosic guitar noise over the simple, thunderous sound of Ms. White's drums, sometimes echo such blues-based rockers as ZZ Top, AC/DC, or -- as in the first single and title track -- Led Zeppelin.</p>
        <p>The album is licensed to Warner Brothers, with the band retaining ownership of the master recordings. Mr. White said he has no qualms about working with a major label, given some bad experiences with small indies and promoters during the band's early years. ''We've been ripped off by so many independent labels and so many people from the underground,'' he said. ''All that stuff left a really bad taste in my mouth.''</p>
        <p>Andy Gershon, the executive vice president at Epic Records, said, ''Going to a major is a completely logical next step for them.'' He previously ran the independent V2 label, which released the last three White Stripes albums before shutting its doors earlier this year. ''The future growth for them is more mainstream,'' he said, ''and the way to broaden that reach is through Target and Wal-Mart and to really bring a song home at radio.''</p>
        <p>There's a question of just how mainstream a traditionalist rock band can be nowadays, though, and among some of the band's fan base there is skepticism about the move. One blog, productshopnyc.com, recently posted two leaked songs from the album; the site quickly received a cease-and-desist order from Warner Brothers and took the tracks down, only to find itself shut down for a day. ''I'm not sure what all this says about the White Stripes if they sign to a label that employs such heavy-handed tactics,'' read a comment from one of the site's users.</p>
        <p>The music, however, more than holds up its end of the deal. From the country-soul power ballad ''You Don't Know What Love Is (You Just Do as You're Told)'' to the John Lee Hooker-style talking-blues shuffle ''Rag and Bone,'' the songs on ''Icky Thump'' continue to expand upon the sources that have always inspired the White Stripes. Mr. White's guitar playing, honed from a year on the road with his other band, the Raconteurs, has never sounded stronger.</p>
        <p>The usual critical standards of progress and evolution are hard to apply to a band that is so rigorously dedicated to certain simple principles. ''Something that we love about the band is that there's a huge portion of it that will never change,'' Mr. White said. ''It will always be restricted and constricted and stuck in this box.'' While many artists trumpet their artistic growth from project to project, he proudly notes that ''there are songs on this album that could easily have been on our first album.''</p>
        <p>Mr. White said that the Beatles set a near-impossible expectation that rock bands need continually to change to remain creative, and that Madonna upped the ante by making perpetual reinvention the very point of her work. ''I told someone that one of these new songs could be an old 45 of ours,'' he said. ''And they said, would you want the Beatles to have 'I Want to Hold Your Hand' on the White Album? And I said, yeah, I would love that -- what would be wrong with that?''</p>
        <p>Asked if he really believes that listeners hope to hear the same thing over and over from a band, or if such a thing is even possible, he concedes that fans want to hear something new but that they ''also want part of it to stay grounded.''</p>
        <p>As musicians scramble to keep up with the accelerated pace of the digital age, some have been attacked for remaking themselves too quickly and too drastically (the Killers) while others have lost fans for staying too static (the Strokes). By laying their self-imposed rules on the table, the White Stripes have thus far dodged the pressure of audience expectation. The ''Icky Thump'' single is already a hit on modern rock radio.</p>
        <p>The film director Jim Jarmusch, who wrote a scene for the band in his 2003 film ''Coffee and Cigarettes,'' compared the White Stripes' philosophy to the raw naturalism of film's Dogma 95 movement. ''They reinvigorated rock 'n' roll by stripping it down to the point of not even having a bass,'' he said. ''Jack has a meticulous focus on style -- what color are the amp covers, all the little details.''</p>
        <p>Mr. White said that he wanted to be a filmmaker when he was young and that making a good movie is ''the biggest triumph in all creative fields of media.'' (Hollywood has taken notice; he has a small role as Elvis Presley in the coming biopic spoof ''Walk Hard,'' for which Judd Apatow is a writer.) In many ways he approaches the White Stripes project as a director would, creating a whole universe, from the casting to the props.</p>
        <p>Virtually everything about the White Stripes, then, is premeditated and strategic -- except, Mr. White insists, for the music. ''Things happen song by song and by accident,'' he said. ''We are slaves to those songs instead of being in control of them, and if you admit to the song that you are not in control, then some good things start to happen.''</p>
        <p>Two tracks on ''Icky Thump'' feature the swirling drone of a bagpipe; another began life as a video treatment before it became a song. Most surprising is a bombastic version of ''Conquest,'' a Patti Page song from the early 1950s, complete with mariachi horns. ''I'd been wanting to cover that forever,'' he said, ''and the themes of this album seemed to keep pointing to this idea of role reversals and 'who's using who,' which are exactly the topics that song is about.''</p>
        <p>One song, ''Little Cream Soda,'' began life as an onstage, improvised riff: something the band often did in the past, but which Mr. White worries is no longer viable. ''They'd be out within the hour on YouTube or whatever,'' he said. ''Then at the end of the night, do I have to go get a publishing record of that song? Give it a name? I don't know what happens.''</p>
        <p>He expressed deep skepticism at the promotional approach of the MySpace era. A Chicago radio station recently played an advance copy of ''Icky Thump'' in its entirety. It was instantly recorded by a listener and posted as low-quality MP3 files, prompting a furious phone call to the D.J. from Mr. White.</p>
        <p>Since interpreting the relative success or failure of CD sales is confounding when so much music is illegally downloaded, perhaps the best way to track the band's career is through its touring, which has seen the White Stripes move from clubs to bigger clubs to theaters and now to arenas. ''It's shocking to me that a two-piece band can do it, especially one with no safety net, no set list, no DAT tape playing with us,'' Mr. White said. ''I'm surprised people are paying attention after the third song.''</p>
        <p>In addition to their big shows in urban areas, the White Stripes will spend a few weeks this summer touring the outer Canadian provinces: barely-on-the-map locations like Nunavut and Yellowknife. It's these gigs, like the South American jaunt on their last tour, that get the Whites most revved up. Ms. White, who spent much of the interview chain-smoking and listening, interjected enthusiastically, ''If you know you're going to a place where people haven't heard you before, it's more exciting on both ends.''</p>
        <p>They have no idea whether anyone in the Yukon Territory even knows who they are, or if people will just wander into their community theater, grateful to see any music at all; they say that the challenge of the latter scenario appeals to them the most. The tour is a typical White Stripes move. The major-market dates help pay for the little shows, and they get to be both big-league rock stars and experimental artists. It's gimmicky to some and laudably ambitious to others.</p>
        <p>''In South America we showed up, like, do we even have any fans here in Chile?'' Mr. White said with a grin. ''And they were sold out -- with people who had their own handmade White Stripes T-shirts.''</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
