<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>They Came. They Conquered. They Posed.</title>
    <meta content="10footsteps--(essay)" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/travel/10footsteps-essay.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTSTEPS | TRAVEL PHOTOGRAPHY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Exploration and Explorers</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woodward, Richard B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exploration and Explorers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6DB1130F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1266" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>They Came. They Conquered. They Posed.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">They Came. They Conquered. They Posed.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD B. WOODWARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Woodward, Richard B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Woodward travel article on crucial role photography has played in exploration and tourism industry over the years; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TOURISM is by some economic measures the largest business in the world. Oil companies, airlines and manufacturers of ski boots, bikinis and chocolate mints for hotel pillows all depend on its vitality. It is also an unsteady business, erected not on our material need to visit Florence or the Grand Tetons but on the illusions that lead us there, or anywhere beyond the horizon of home.</p>
        <p>Photographers are major purveyors of fantasies, realistic as well as far-fetched, and as such have been crucial to the industry's growth. Vivid as word pictures of the Great Wall of China can be, they don't wow a reader as instantly as a photograph of its pythonic length and girth can transport a viewer. Without enticing images of turquoise waters and ivory sands, the Caribbean would probably be empty of vacationers. The idea of the seaside as a happy destination, a place to shed clothes, worries and inhibitions, is a modern invention, implanted in our heads by photographs and movies. It's no coincidence that the advent of mass tourism, with Thomas Cook's tours in the 1840s, dates to the popularity of the steamship, the railroad and the camera.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Explorers as far back as Livingstone have understood the public relations value of a good photo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TOURISM is by some economic measures the largest business in the world. Oil companies, airlines and manufacturers of ski boots, bikinis and chocolate mints for hotel pillows all depend on its vitality. It is also an unsteady business, erected not on our material need to visit Florence or the Grand Tetons but on the illusions that lead us there, or anywhere beyond the horizon of home.</p>
        <p>Photographers are major purveyors of fantasies, realistic as well as far-fetched, and as such have been crucial to the industry's growth. Vivid as word pictures of the Great Wall of China can be, they don't wow a reader as instantly as a photograph of its pythonic length and girth can transport a viewer. Without enticing images of turquoise waters and ivory sands, the Caribbean would probably be empty of vacationers. The idea of the seaside as a happy destination, a place to shed clothes, worries and inhibitions, is a modern invention, implanted in our heads by photographs and movies. It's no coincidence that the advent of mass tourism, with Thomas Cook's tours in the 1840s, dates to the popularity of the steamship, the railroad and the camera.</p>
        <p>Explorers are glorified tourists, and those who set off in the 19th century, for noble or ignoble purposes, quickly grasped what the new technology might do for their enterprises. A photograph could first of all buttress verbal testimony that you had done what you claimed to have done, or at least that you were there. David Livingstone employed his brother Charles to take pictures on his 1858-64 journey along the Zambezi River in Africa. Their failure to bring back photographs -- Charles was unqualified to handle the equipment in hellish conditions -- did not help charges in newspapers of the time that the mission had been a bust.</p>
        <p>From then on, few daring treks to anywhere set off without a professional cameraman. Timothy O'Sullivan, who accompanied geologic and military surveys of the American West in the 1860s and '70s, and Andrew J. Russell, hired by the Union Pacific Railroad as it laid track across the country, were both veteran Civil War photographers. Their pictures of desert expanses in Utah and Nevada are now considered works of art, but they were made for sale to the government and the public, in various formats, to help defray the costs of what were long, expensive trips.</p>
        <p>Even when an expedition was a disaster, as happened frequently when men were racing to the poles during the early decades of the 20th century, photographs could redeem a botched effort. Frank Hurley's plates from Ernest Shackleton's ill-starred trip in 1914-16 to Antarctica on the Endurance supported accounts of the almost unbelievable hardship faced by the crew. Herbert Ponting's movies of Robert Falcon Scott's tour of the region in 1910-13 were supposed to be shown in paying venues on the explorer's triumphant return, a plan that fizzled when Scott was lost and later discovered frozen dead. This hasn't harmed appreciation for Ponting's work, which required its own brand of toughness and courage.</p>
        <p>To make an independent living, however, photographers have needed to capture dramatic views of places most of us would actually like to visit. Under the right social and political conditions these images can alter the future of the things in the picture.</p>
        <p>Yosemite Valley was crawling with prospectors and timber merchants when Carleton Watkins visited in 1859-61. It was in part his magnificent stereographs and mammoth-plate (18 by 22 inches) prints of the mountains and forests, images he later sold in his own gallery, that helped to persuade Congress in 1864 to pass legislation that preserved the area as a public trust. Yellowstone became the first national park in 1872, thanks in no small way to Thomas Moran's paintings and William Henry Jackson's photographs of the stunning scenery.</p>
        <p>The legacy of Watkins and Jackson, crystallized in the pictures and activism of Ansel Adams, illustrates the ability of photographs to idealize certain places and perhaps shelter them against development. For nature tourism to flourish, a country has to show the world it is still dotted with sanctified areas. Photographers have been essential in that movement.</p>
        <p>As cameras in the 1890s became smaller, cheaper and easier to use, photography was transformed into an amateur's medium. Kodak and other companies advertised the fact that anyone could take a decent snapshot. People recorded family excursions in tiny pictures that went into albums. Photography became a kind of diary.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the picture postcard industry took off -- sales were 850 million a year by 1910 -- and allowed access to an unparalleled selection of foreign views for pennies apiece. Like the explorer's more hard-fought images, these proved to friends back home that you had been somewhere. Or, even if you hadn't, by perusing a rack of postcards and buying one -- a Gothic cathedral, a remote island -- that was tacked above your desk or bed, they functioned as icons for dreaming.</p>
        <p>The golden age of the photo magazine (1920s to 1960s) was often as much about delivering the vicarious thrill of travel as documenting war and injustice. The great French weekly Vu, which in the late '20s had sounded the alarm about Hitler, was also packed with features about skiing and the beach. National Geographic magazine became a monthly in 1896 and specialized in pictorial reports about exotic lands..</p>
        <p>Artist photographers have more often been globe-trotting tourists than stay-at-homes. Henri Cartier-Bresson and his Leica darted around Europe, the United States and Mexico in the '30s and throughout Asia in the '50s as he went in search of the surreal in everyday life.</p>
        <p>''The Americans,'' Robert Frank's classic 1959 book, was imagined as a lonesome highway travelogue about his adopted country. It has been said that Mr. Frank ''proved you could photograph anything anywhere.'' Legions of ambitious photographers, from Stephen Shore to Thomas Struth, have tested themselves against this standard, taking pictures all over the place that highlight the world's strange ordinariness. These photographs were often made to combat the smoothly lovely views of places found in commercial travel magazines.</p>
        <p>The discretion of the camera in relation to the land -- the fact that by taking a picture you are removing something from a scene but disturbing nothing -- has appealed to artists in tune with the ecological movement. Since the '70s the British artist Hamish Fulton has walked 12,000 miles across five continents, along paths as stony as anything seen by O'Sullivan and Russell in the American West. Often the only traces of these journeys are a series of unglamorous black-and-whites, which Mr. Fulton sells to collectors and museums.</p>
        <p>More-fantastic voyages usually call for more-dramatic images. To help sell the space program to the American taxpayer, NASA shrewdly signed the infamous contract in the '60s with the foremost photography magazine of its time, Life. The trippy pictures of astronauts floating against the blackness of the universe and standing among the wastes of the moon somehow justified the billions spent. Many of us felt we had gone into space because we followed the explorers for years on television and in Life.</p>
        <p>Richard Branson says he believes that space is the next frontier of tourism. The rare chance to view the blue marble of earth from a Virgin Galactic spacecraft will be enough, he hopes, to attract wealthy would-be astronauts for a series of suborbital flights. In a sense, the hard part of the sales pitch was already done by NASA.</p>
        <p>We know we want to go. Images of life on Mars are tumbling around in our brains. All we need now is the money.</p>
        <p>FOOTSTEPS | TRAVEL PHOTOGRAPHY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
