<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Mayor Thought He Was Just Helping</title>
    <meta content="10colliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/10colli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853510"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE ISLAND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Day Laborers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Immigrants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Southampton (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Epley, Mark (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finn, Robin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Day Laborers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Hamptons (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E3D91E30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="861" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Mayor Thought He Was Just Helping</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Mayor Thought He Was Just Helping</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robin Finn</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finn, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>SOUTHAMPTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robin Finn The Island column on Mayor Mark Epley of Southampton Village, who landed in hot water and had suit filed against him after he ordered park be used as hiring site for day laborers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DON'T bother griping to Mayor Mark Epley of Southampton Village about the unsightly yellow tape -- if it could talk, it would scream ''Crime Scene! Keep Out!'' rather than ''Welcome to the Summer Playground of the Rich and Famous!'' -- gift-wrapping the entrance to the unembellished park on Aldrich Lane. He put it there. So sue him. But get in line.</p>
        <p>The park, whose most notable neighbor is a 7-Eleven, doesn't rate a name. It abuts a busy corner where day laborers gather each morning to rent out their backs and biceps and perform chores for cash; their grunt work keeps this Hampton's lush landscaping, pristine pools and eye-candy estates in mint condition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Southampton Village, a patch of land intended for day laborers has provoked a lawsuit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DON'T bother griping to Mayor Mark Epley of Southampton Village about the unsightly yellow tape -- if it could talk, it would scream ''Crime Scene! Keep Out!'' rather than ''Welcome to the Summer Playground of the Rich and Famous!'' -- gift-wrapping the entrance to the unembellished park on Aldrich Lane. He put it there. So sue him. But get in line.</p>
        <p>The park, whose most notable neighbor is a 7-Eleven, doesn't rate a name. It abuts a busy corner where day laborers gather each morning to rent out their backs and biceps and perform chores for cash; their grunt work keeps this Hampton's lush landscaping, pristine pools and eye-candy estates in mint condition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Epley is the innovative official who thought he did the village a favor by steering the seasonal influx of day laborers, along with the bargain-minded barrage of contractors and homeowners who hire them, toward the park this spring. They had, he said, been gathering nearby to transact business for the past seven years, had long since outgrown the 7-Eleven parking lot and had spilled onto the roads. But his innovation provoked litigation, and Mr. Epley has since ordered the park (although using ''park'' to describe this bleak six-acre patch is a stretch) taped up like an ugly package.</p>
        <p>He didn't want to do it. Mayors are elected to stamp out eyesores, not enable them. Then again, mayors have no input on federal immigration policy.</p>
        <p>''There are 35,000 deportation warrants outstanding in New York State and two million people in the state illegally, but I can't deport people,'' the mayor observed. Nor can he or his police force prevent workers from entering the village. ''At least out of everyone around here, I tried to do something; I got them off the street and put them behind a hedge,'' Mr. Epley said.</p>
        <p>''For me, it wasn't an immigration problem, it was a safety problem. Maybe it was too simple a solution. No, the park is not the ideal location for this thing; if there were another place to go to, I would gladly step away from this piece of property in a heartbeat. Give me an alternative that doesn't land the village in federal court with a discrimination lawsuit.''</p>
        <p>He admits that if he lived on Aldrich Lane, he'd probably be a plaintiff, too. But his conscience tells him he did the prudent thing; his detractors say he chose the wrong site. Try finding a right one in this village.</p>
        <p>He hauled out the yellow tape after a handful of Aldrich Lane homeowners filed a lawsuit in State Supreme Court protesting the hiring site. The Town of Southampton, named as a co-defendant because it and the village share title to the park, filed a cross-claim against the village, the equivalent of its own lawsuit; it says the site is not a lawful use of dedicated parkland. A temporary injunction was granted.</p>
        <p>The park, which Mr. Epley customized with hedges and a gravel driveway, paid for with $15,000 in private donations (his tactic does have a local fan base), now lies vacant. The workers, who arrive by county bus, are back to congregating on, and creating a traffic hazard at, North Sea Road and County Road 39. Problem not solved.</p>
        <p>The case returns to court on June 20 with an expanded cast: Mr. Epley in defense mode; the town, led by Supervisor Patrick A. Heaney, with its cross-claim; the irate residents of Aldrich Lane, represented by Anton J. Borovina, a Melville lawyer; and the Puerto Rican Legal Defense Fund and other advocacy groups that claim in court papers that the injunction violates the workers' rights. It's an added civil rights wrinkle that some principals in the original lawsuit fear could hijack the litigation beyond the realm of park use.</p>
        <p>Mr. Borovina said his clients were not prejudiced against day laborers; he has fended off support from the Minutemen and other anti-immigrant groups. Mr. Epley's home was picketed by anti-immigration activists until the village outlawed picketing in residential areas on May 29; his teenage son, Nick, faces a harassment charge for shoving a protester. Mr. Epley says the protesters harassed and verbally assaulted Nick. Messy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Heaney, the town supervisor, expressed frustration with big- (federal) and little- (Mr. Epley's solution) picture politics. ''Our major problem is the failure of federal immigration enforcement policy that pushes the reality of it to local neighborhoods where we're the least equipped to deal with it,'' Mr. Heaney said. ''Mark sees this as a way to change the paradigm of workers loitering in the streets; unfortunately, he's used the wrong approach.''</p>
        <p>A brief history of no-name park: The mayor traces it to a cornfield whose owner decided to sell, not farm. The Town of Southampton, intent on preserving the vanishing aesthetic known as community character, purchased it for $1.6 million with community preservation funds in 2001. The open space never quite became a park; according to the mayor, the village lacks the estimated $250,000 to $300,000 necessary to refurbish it. He thought a little gravel and some hedges were a nice start.</p>
        <p>Consider it closed for the summer. Not that it was anybody's vacation destination.</p>
        <p>THE ISLAND E-mail: theisland@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: theisland@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
