<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The House Of Horrors For Mel's Monster?</title>
    <meta content="10ishe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/theater/10ishe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070610T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853506"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hilton Theater (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ford Center for the Performing Arts (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theaters (Buildings)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Isherwood, Charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theaters (Buildings)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EFDC1E30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1851" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The House Of Horrors For Mel's Monster?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The House of Horrors for Mel's Monster?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES ISHERWOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Isherwood, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Isherwood article on coldness and lack of intimacy in second largest Broadway theater in New York, the Hilton Theater (formerly Ford Center for the Performing Arts); photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''THE PIRATE QUEEN'' is a silly and tedious new musical about step-dancing swashbucklers loving and fighting on the waters. I sincerely hoped it would run forever.</p>
        <p>Those statements, apparently perverse and contradictory, are actually linked by cold logic, easily explained by a single fact: Those Irish corsairs have been cavorting at the Hilton Theater. I hoped, sincerely and even fervently, never to have to see another musical in this chilly barn of a house.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The musicals that have played at the Hilton Theater, including Mel Brooks's forthcoming “Young Frankenstein," should give pause even to a producer confident of his show’s superiority.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''THE PIRATE QUEEN'' is a silly and tedious new musical about step-dancing swashbucklers loving and fighting on the waters. I sincerely hoped it would run forever.</p>
        <p>Those statements, apparently perverse and contradictory, are actually linked by cold logic, easily explained by a single fact: Those Irish corsairs have been cavorting at the Hilton Theater. I hoped, sincerely and even fervently, never to have to see another musical in this chilly barn of a house.</p>
        <p>Fat chance. The show opened to a fusillade of critical cannonballs this spring, and you won't hear much or anything about it at Sunday night's Tony Awards. (It was blanked in the nominations.) The producers announced last week that the show would close on June 17, presumably losing its entire $16 million investment.</p>
        <p>Recently rumors have circulated that the next tenant at the Hilton may be ''Young Frankenstein,'' Mel Brooks's eagerly anticipated follow-up to his smash hit ''The Producers.'' This prospect should dismay anyone who harbors hopes that Mr. Brooks's adaptation of his spoof of horror pictures would be the equal of -- or even superior to -- his adorable musical about the machinations of a swindling producer. The level of mugging that would be required to put over a comedy in the cavernous Hilton, at 1,815 seats Broadway's second-largest theater, is terrifying to contemplate.</p>
        <p>If you've seen a show at the Hilton, you are probably aware of its drawbacks. It is about as intimate as a football stadium and as warmly inviting as a convention center. More to the point for the creators and backers of ''Young Frankenstein,'' the history of the musicals that have played at this theater in its 10-year existence should give pause even to a producer confident of his show's superiority.</p>
        <p>Recent tenants of the Hilton, which opened in 1997 under the equally dreary but more highfalutin corporate-branded name the Ford Center for the Performing Arts, have included the cheesy ''Chitty Chitty Bang Bang'' and last season's fast flop ''Hot Feet.'' (You know, the Earth, Wind and Fire musical? What, you don't?) It also played host to a revival of ''42nd Street'' that ran for a long time and didn't make a dime in profit, and a screechy new version of ''Jesus Christ Superstar'' that was also unsuccessful. Possibly the only money-making show in the theater's history was the holiday engagement of ''Dr. Seuss' How the Grinch Stole Christmas!''</p>
        <p>Although many theaters can claim a distinguished history of failed shows -- such is the slim rate of commercial success for Broadway productions -- an astute producer would be wise to ponder the unhappy correlation between flopdom and tenancy in this particular house. Given its size, it theoretically has the potential to be among the industry's most profitable; somehow it hasn't worked out that way.</p>
        <p>I am not sure that is pure coincidence. I found the space to be unwelcoming, aesthetically bland and acoustically dreadful from the start, and can honestly say I've never really enjoyed any of the shows that have played there, including its first tenant, ''Ragtime,'' which was more affecting when I saw it at the now defunct Shubert Theater in Los Angeles, itself not exactly a jewel box. I still recall how my heart sank as I took my seat on the aisle in Row L at the theater to review ''42nd Street,'' one of its more worthy tenants. I felt as if I was a half-mile from the stage. In Row L! Small wonder that that hard-working revival seemed to have polished its brassiness to an off-puttingly blinding degree. If you're tapping those toes to thrill a spectator in the distant corners of the wide orchestra section, you're going to be pounding the stage pretty darn hard. The revival was like a human pinball machine seen from the wrong end of the bar.</p>
        <p>It would be nice to believe that a good show can succeed in any circumstances, but one of the rewards and risks of live theater is that our responses to it are subtly shaped by the environment, in a way that our responses to movies generally are not. I would agree that a great movie should ideally be seen in a comfortable movie theater on a big screen, not on television. But the qualities intrinsic to the film are not really violated by the diminished screen size if you're watching the television from the right distance. A close-up remains a close-up.</p>
        <p>But there are no close-ups in the theater. A good live performance creates a connection between the performers onstage and the people in the audience, an invisible filament of communion that can be strengthened or diminished by the size and shape of the performing space. Just as you don't want to hold a casual conversation with somebody on the other side of a soccer field, or you don't want to listen to chamber music in a high school gym, you don't want to see a Pinter play in a 2,000-seat house. Having seen all the shows that have played there, I don't think you want to see anything, even the splashiest of big musicals, in the gaping Hilton.</p>
        <p>One of the glories of Broadway was how beautifully the theaters built in its heyday suited the kinds of plays and musicals produced there. Part of the romance of Broadway inheres in the history embodied by the theaters. Sure, I'd have enjoyed the recent revival of Clifford Odets's ''Awake and Sing!'' if it had played another theater, but its return to the Belasco, where the original Group Theater production played back in 1935, added a frisson of poetry to the experience. I suspect that most people who are regular New York theatergoers have a fondness, even a reverence, for the finest of the city playhouses. Yes, more leg room would be lovely, as would more bathrooms. But I wouldn't trade either for the classic lightbulb marquees or the ornate prosceniums. My affection is as sensible as it is sentimental. Broadway theaters are, as a rule, both exciting in the decorous sense of occasion they bestow on the theatergoing experience and surprisingly intimate given the number of seats they can hold. They work.</p>
        <p>The handful of Broadway theaters built in the second half of the 20th century, usually on a somewhat larger scale to house the more profitable (and popular) musicals, lack the coziness and charm of even the largest old houses. The model seems to be the big barns on the road that can reap huge grosses in one- or two-week stands. The 1,611-seat Marquis is the most piteous example. Three smaller old playhouses -- the Morosco, the Helen Hayes and the Bijou -- were bulldozed into oblivion to make way for the Marriott hotel complex in the early 1980s, despite a colorful battle led by Joseph Papp to stop the demolition. In subsequent years a renewed awareness of Broadway theaters as spaces worthy of preserving helped stop some of that wholesale destruction. (But not all of it: Just recently Henry Miller's Theater, resurrected in atmospherically dilapidated form to house the hit revival of ''Cabaret,'' was demolished; only its rather pointlessly landmarked facade remains, a ludicrous visual footnote to a big glass tower on 43rd Street. An all-new theater is being built inside.)</p>
        <p>The Walt Disney Company, of all the unlikely heroes, played a sterling role in the resuscitation of old Broadway real estate with its meticulous restoration of the New Amsterdam Theater. (That gorgeous theater inspires dismay at the long-running Disney musicals it is destined to house: I'd love to visit it more often.) More recently the Selwyn was graciously restored by the Roundabout Theater Company (it's now called, ugh, the American Airlines Theater), and Manhattan Theater Club brought back the Biltmore.</p>
        <p>But Garth H. Drabinsky, the impresario whose company Livent financed the creation of the Ford Center on the heels of Disney's reawakening of the New Amsterdam, exemplifies the darker role of corporate machinations in Broadway during the 1990s. A big-talking (and admittedly theater-loving) businessman from Canada, he began producing lavishly in New York in the '90s, using money obtained by the publicly held and highly leveraged Livent. The Ford Center and its first inhabitant, ''Ragtime,'' were to be the jewels in a glittering corporate theatrical crown.</p>
        <p>But Livent essentially destroyed two old theaters, the Lyric and the Apollo, to make way for the new one. (Unlike the New Amsterdam the theaters were not protected by landmark designation.) Some cosmetic elements of the old theaters were incorporated into the new one, but the structures were essentially gutted and combined to create the Ford Center. The resulting space is like an old-time Broadway theater that has been force-fed steroids and had bad plastic surgery.</p>
        <p>Eventually Mr. Drabinsky's company collapsed in a welter of lawsuits and charges of fraud and insider trading. All that is left on Broadway of the empire he hoped to build is that crown jewel, and it is looking pretty tarnished. (When Livent went under, the theater was sold to SFX Entertainment, later bought by Clear Channel Communications, which spun off a new company called Live Nation, which now owns the Hilton.) Mystically inclined observers might point to the theater's history of flops as some sort of cosmic curse left behind by Mr. Drabinsky. But really you need invoke no voodoo to explain the theater's history. The space is spiritless, antiseptic even when it tries to charm with nostalgic touches, and its auditorium is acoustically cold and simply too big. Most musicals are overmiked these days, but at ''The Pirate Queen'' you almost feel the sound and the action onstage are totally disconnected.</p>
        <p>Can anything be done to make it a more workable space for theater? I'm not an architect, and it would surely be fiendishly expensive. Still, slimming the orchestra section, which widens to what seems like twice the size of the already large proscenium, would help. And surely something could be done to warm up the sound.</p>
        <p>It is certainly possible that, as is, the Hilton will at last find a money-making, high-quality tenant in ''Young Frankenstein.'' Most of the productions that have opened at the theater have been below-par musicals, after all. (I daresay ''Hot Feet'' would have trudged quickly into oblivion even in the beloved Shubert Theater.) The Gershwin Theater, Broadway's biggest and even more charmless than the Hilton, has gone for long stretches without a successful tenant. But along came ''Wicked,'' now making money hand over fist.</p>
        <p>No doubt it is the potential for just that kind of coin-spinning that has enticed Mr. Brooks to consider putting his new baby into this big pram. Mindful that ''The Producers'' could have sold out its theater twice over during the early days of its run but lost altitude as the years went by, the thinking must be that to have more seats to sell when you're hot is the way to go.</p>
        <p>Maybe so, but the St. James Theater, where ''Young Frankenstein'' was once expected to land, has about 1,700 seats, only 100 or so fewer than the Hilton. And I'd be happy to watch a musical comedy from any of them.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 10, 2007, Sunday  An article in some copies today on Page 6 of Arts &amp; Leisure about shows at the Hilton Theater on Broadway includes an outdated reference to the current tenant, ''The Pirate Queen,'' which initially had an open-ended run. After the section went to press, producers announced that it would close next Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 10, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article in some copies today on Page 6 of Arts &amp; Leisure about shows at the Hilton Theater on Broadway includes an outdated reference to the current tenant, ''The Pirate Queen,'' which initially had an open-ended run. After the section went to press, producers announced that it would close next Sunday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
