<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Great Midtown Cover-Up</title>
    <meta content="10shed" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/thecity/10shed.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853668"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: MANHATTAN UP CLOSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Delafuente, Charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Buildings Department</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Municipal Art Society</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E4D61F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="651" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Great Midtown Cover-Up</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Great Midtown Cover-Up</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES DELAFUENTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Delafuente, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on sharp rise in number of buildings in Manhattan that are covered with sidewalk sheds so that repairs can be made; notes sheds seem to stay in place longer because unexpected conditions result in delays in repair work; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANYONE strolling down a nine-block stretch of Broadway in Midtown at noon on a sunny day this spring could be forgiven for thinking that it was either nighttime or unexpectedly gloomy. Nine sidewalk sheds, some up to a full block long, could be found between Times Square and Herald Square. All had been erected around existing buildings, not at sites where construction was taking place.</p>
        <p>These tunnel-like contraptions of plywood and steel, which look as if they were built using some gargantuan Erector Set, are an increasingly common sight in the city, in part because of a vibrant economy but also because of an increased emphasis on safety. The city's Buildings Department reports that as of February, permits had been granted for 3,317 sheds in Manhattan in the previous 12 months, compared with only 2,321 permits in effect in early 2003.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tunnel-like contraptions of plywood and steel, which look as if they were built using some gargantuan Erector Set, are an increasingly common sight in the city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANYONE strolling down a nine-block stretch of Broadway in Midtown at noon on a sunny day this spring could be forgiven for thinking that it was either nighttime or unexpectedly gloomy. Nine sidewalk sheds, some up to a full block long, could be found between Times Square and Herald Square. All had been erected around existing buildings, not at sites where construction was taking place.</p>
        <p>These tunnel-like contraptions of plywood and steel, which look as if they were built using some gargantuan Erector Set, are an increasingly common sight in the city, in part because of a vibrant economy but also because of an increased emphasis on safety. The city's Buildings Department reports that as of February, permits had been granted for 3,317 sheds in Manhattan in the previous 12 months, compared with only 2,321 permits in effect in early 2003.</p>
        <p>In large part, the sheds are a consequence of Local Law 11, which was passed in 1998 and requires regular inspections of the exteriors of buildings seven stories or taller. Inspections often reveal work that needs to be done -- hence the erection of a sidewalk shed while repairs are being made.</p>
        <p>That strolling pedestrian this spring could have found 17 sheds along Central Park West. On Riverside Drive, 17 sheds lined the blocks between 96th Street and the George Washington Bridge. On West End Avenue, 10 sheds could be found between 96th and 106th Streets, and 26 sheds sat along Broadway between 66th and 96th Streets.</p>
        <p>On the East Side, the picture was similar. There were a half-dozen sheds on First Avenue between 51st and 57th Streets, 10 on Second Avenue between 42nd and 54th Streets, and a half-dozen on Third Avenue between 15th and 25th Streets. In Midtown, there were nearly 30 sheds on Fifth Avenue between 23rd and 54th Streets and 13 on Park Avenue South, a street barely a mile long. Nor were sheds limited to broad north-south avenues. Eight could be found on West 73rd Street, four on a three-block stretch of Waverly Place in Greenwich Village, several on West 116th Street in Harlem and four on Irving Place.</p>
        <p>To the casual observer, sheds seem to stay in place longer than in the past, often with no evidence of work going on. That is because once work starts, unexpected conditions are often encountered, particularly in older buildings, which may require custom parts. Since it might cost more to remove and reinstall the shed than to leave it in place, the structure is normally kept where it is during the interim.</p>
        <p>''We know that in some cases building owners are leaving sheds up for too long,'' said the city's buildings commissioner, Patricia Lancaster. ''Public safety is always paramount, but we must remember that the street life is what defines our city. The trick is to find the balance between the competing interests.''</p>
        <p>The Police Department did not reply to questions about the extent of crime committed in these sometimes bleak and forbidding places. Few people, however, find them attractive. Vanessa Gruen, director of special projects at the Municipal Art Society, noted that many such sheds in Europe and Asia are ''beautiful designs.'' And she added, ''We can do this.''</p>
        <p>One change for the better is the decreasing use of razor wire atop sheds. Coiled razor wire, intended to keep criminals from entering buildings by climbing onto the roofs of sheds, was popular in an era when the crime rate was higher. But for some New Yorkers, the mere presence of the sheds is eyesore enough.</p>
        <p>Terence Bertele, a doctor who lives and practices in Washington and is trying to rent his two-bedroom condo on Gramercy Park, never before had trouble finding a tenant. But after a shed went up outside the building last fall, one after another prospective tenant has walked away because the contraption is, as Dr. Bertele put it, ''such a monstrosity.''</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: MANHATTAN UP CLOSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
