<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bridgeport Mayor's Office, and Race for It, Drawing Spotlight as Usual</title>
    <meta content="10peoplectCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/10peoplect.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853557"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bridgeport (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fabrizi, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ganim, Joseph P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Torres, Rick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caruso, Christopher L (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finch, Bill (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holtz, Jeff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bridgeport (Conn)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01EFDF1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="740" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bridgeport Mayor's Office, and Race for It, Drawing Spotlight as Usual</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bridgeport Mayor’s Office, and Race for It, Drawing Spotlight as Usual</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF HOLTZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holtz, Jeff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayoral race in Bridgeport, Conn, is, as usual, drawing attention; Democratic Mayor John Fabrizi, who took over for disgraced Mayor Joseph Ganim in 2003, has admitted using cocaine while in office and said he would not seek re-election; Republican Rick Torres, who lost to Fabrizi in 2003, said he would support Democratic State Repr Christopher Caruso; Caruso will face State Sen Bill Finch in election; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A memo to the producers of reality television shows: You might want to take a look at the mayoral race in Bridgeport.</p>
        <p>From the circus magnate P. T. Barnum, elected in 1875, to the first woman to serve as mayor, Mary C. Moran, who filed for municipal bankruptcy in 1991, to Joseph P. Ganim, convicted on corruption charges in 2003, the mayor of the state's largest city has rarely suffered from a lack of attention. And so far, the early approach to this fall's election has received its share too.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A memo to the producers of reality television shows: You might want to take a look at the mayoral race in Bridgeport.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A memo to the producers of reality television shows: You might want to take a look at the mayoral race in Bridgeport.</p>
        <p>From the circus magnate P. T. Barnum, elected in 1875, to the first woman to serve as mayor, Mary C. Moran, who filed for municipal bankruptcy in 1991, to Joseph P. Ganim, convicted on corruption charges in 2003, the mayor of the state's largest city has rarely suffered from a lack of attention. And so far, the early approach to this fall's election has received its share too.</p>
        <p>Last month, John M. Fabrizi, 50, the former City Council president who took over for Mr. Ganim in midterm in 2003 and was elected later that year, said he would not seek re-election. Last year, Mr. Fabrizi admitted using cocaine while in office, then caused an uproar in March by speaking in court on behalf of a convicted sex offender, a friend of his son's who twice impregnated an adolescent girl. The mayor apologized the next day.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fabrizi's decision not to run came amid rumblings that he had finally lost the support of the city's powerful Democratic Town Committee. While admitting that one party leader had told him that the committee would not support him, Mr. Fabrizi said he had decided not to run so he could complete initiatives, like the residential and commercial Steel Point project on the city's East Side, without the distraction of campaigning.</p>
        <p>''I would not be able to concentrate on the job at hand,'' he said.</p>
        <p>John F. Stafstrom Jr., the vice chairman of the committee, said that although Mr. Fabrizi was not told not to run, party leaders did caution him that constituents were concerned because of the sex offender case.</p>
        <p>But in a city where registered Democrats outnumber registered Republicans more than seven to one (34,407 to 4,787), another twist came in mid-May when Rick Torres, 47, the chairman of the Republican Town Committee, who lost to Mr. Fabrizi in 2003, announced that he would not run again either, and would instead support a Democrat, State Representative Christopher L. Caruso.</p>
        <p>Mr. Caruso, 47, who lost in the 2003 mayoral primary, said the city had long suffered under the Democratic Town Committee and insisted that the party had abandoned Mr. Fabrizi.</p>
        <p>''There's a small group of people that have hijacked the Democratic Town Committee through political patronage,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''The hijackers, who frankly ate and drank with John Fabrizi, knew about the drug problem,'' Mr. Caruso said. ''But once he walked into the courtroom and sought leniency for the sex offender, they all felt he would end up losing the election, and that would mean the political machine would lose their jobs. So John Fabrizi got the heave-ho off the boat.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Torres said he agreed with Mr. Caruso, and added that he was willing to cross party lines to endorse him because he thought Mr. Caruso had a better chance of winning than he himself did. ''For me, it's enough of a reason to liberate my city from a tough political machine,'' Mr. Torres said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Caruso will face Bill Finch, 51, a four-term state senator who has the Democratic Town Committee's support. Mr. Finch had praise for some of Mr. Fabrizi's initiatives, like the increase in residential development downtown, but said that people had become ''tired of certain personal situations.''</p>
        <p>Joseph J. Borges Jr., the city's registrar of voters and a member of the city and state Republican committees, said that Mr. Torres had put the Republican Party in a bad position and that the party might not nominate a candidate because of it.</p>
        <p>''As the chairman, anytime you speak, you speak for the party,'' Mr. Borges said. ''He said he was speaking for himself and the intent of the party, but it doesn't work that way.''</p>
        <p>Donald W. Greenberg, the chairman of the political science department at Fairfield University, said the maneuverings revealed a city in political turmoil.</p>
        <p>''The Republican Party in Bridgeport is moribund; it has no vision,'' he said. ''Everyone in the Democratic Party is fractured and splintered. The firm hand of the Democratic Town Committee is breaking apart, and the anti-Democratic-machine force is completely split.''</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Finch said he was not concerned that Mr. Torres was supporting Mr. Caruso. ''They are two unsuccessful candidates trying to make some kind of deal,'' he said. ''And this election shouldn't be about making deals.''</p>
        <p>POLITICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
