<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Win Against Judah, Cotto Announces His Arrival Among Sport's Elite</title>
    <meta content="10boxing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/sports/othersports/10boxing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853394"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Puerto Rico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Puerto Rico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Puerto Rico</location>
        <org class="online_producer">World Boxing Association</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E6D8163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="715" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Win Against Judah, Cotto Announces His Arrival Among Sport's Elite</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Win Against Judah, Cotto Announces His Arrival Among Sport’s Elite</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Through the first 29 fights of his professional boxing career, Miguel Cotto was a fighter with undeniable talent and promise. All he lacked was a marquee moment.</p>
        <p>That changed last night. Cotto, who is from Puerto Rico, retained his World Boxing Association welterweight title with a dominating technical knockout victory against Zab Judah, the former undisputed welterweight world champion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With his Miguel Cotto’s successful welterweight title defense, many people will undoubtedly be calling for his next opponent to be Floyd Mayweather Jr.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Through the first 29 fights of his professional boxing career, Miguel Cotto was a fighter with undeniable talent and promise. All he lacked was a marquee moment.</p>
        <p>That changed last night. Cotto, who is from Puerto Rico, retained his World Boxing Association welterweight title with a dominating technical knockout victory against Zab Judah, the former undisputed welterweight world champion.</p>
        <p>With the victory, Cotto thrust himself into the echelon of boxing's pound-for-pound elite, and many people will undoubtedly be calling for a fight against Floyd Mayweather Jr., considered by many to be the best fighter in the world.</p>
        <p>Cotto (30-0) sent the capacity crowd at Madison Square Garden into a frenzy with a right-left combination that sent Judah (34-5) to the canvas about 20 seconds into the 11th round. Less than 30 seconds later, Cotto had Judah dangling on the ropes and the referee stopped the fight.</p>
        <p>''This is the best fight I've ever had,'' Cotto said afterward.</p>
        <p>It was a shocking ending to a thrilling fight and a night that was as exciting in the ring as it was outside. Although Judah is from Brooklyn, the fans, many of whom waved Puerto Rican flags, were decidedly in Cotto's favor.</p>
        <p>''You receive your pay because people follow you -- the people who pay the pay-per-views, people who pay the tickets,'' Cotto said this week . ''It's important to me that people know who is Miguel Cotto, what Miguel Cotto can do. It's important to me that people from the U.S., if they want, they can follow Miguel Cotto.''</p>
        <p>Cotto already has a stronghold in the Latin American community, especially in his native Puerto Rico.</p>
        <p>This was the third consecutive year that Cotto had fought in the Garden on the eve of the Puerto Rican Day Parade. But this year's fight had added significance, with an opponent of Judah's caliber fighting in his hometown.</p>
        <p>Judah said that he had many Puerto Rican friends and fans. That was difficult to tell because he was widely booed throughout the fight.</p>
        <p>Judah's fiery, uptempo style may have been the perfect foil to Cotto's methodical, yet powerful, approach. In the days leading up to the fight, Judah said that he would pounce on what he called Cotto's robotic approach.</p>
        <p>''He's very slow,'' Judah said during a news conference to promote the fight. ''He has to plant his feet to throw any punches. He has no right hand. He has no jab. He cannot box. He can't fight going backward. There's nothing that Miguel Cotto can do to me.''</p>
        <p>Other than an explosive first round in which he had Cotto wobbling with an uppercut and a flurry of punches, Judah did not have much to show.</p>
        <p>Cotto seemed to bully his smaller opponent. Cotto walked Judah to whatever part of the ring he pleased and fired combinations from close range. Judah's punches did not seem to faze Cotto. The momentum shifted briefly in Judah's favor in the seventh round, when he staggered Cotto with a right hook, followed by a flurry of punches that had the champion hanging on to stay up.</p>
        <p>Cotto regained the momentum for good in the ninth round when he peppered Judah with a series of left-handed shots. With a little more than a minute left in the round, Judah took a knee, forcing the referee to count.</p>
        <p>Judah went down twice before that, but both were because of low blows by Cotto that Judah said affected him throughout the fight. Either way, Cotto dominated Judah, whose future seems in question. He was once a bully in the division, but this seemed to be his last chance to get back on the championship track.</p>
        <p>If this was Judah's last fight of note, it came on an electric night.</p>
        <p>Top Rank, the company that promoted last night's show, tried to enliven an already festive atmosphere with music and nightclub-style lighting. Todd duBoef, the president of Top Rank, said that he got the idea after attending the N.B.A. All-Star Game in Las Vegas and admiring the league's in-game entertainment.</p>
        <p>''We were absent as promoters of being proactive, getting that experience in the arena,'' he said. ''I think what happened was we were dictated by what people were seeing on television, not what they were feeling in the arena.''</p>
        <p>BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
