<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Let's Put On A Car Show!' (Repeat 4 Times)</title>
    <meta content="10SCARSDALE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/automobiles/collectibles/10SCARSDALE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853593"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="COLLECTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E4DD1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1439" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Let's Put On A Car Show!' (Repeat 4 Times)</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">‘Let’s Put on a Car Show!’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TED WEST</byline>
      <dateline>SCARSDALE, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVAN M. CYGLER, who is 19, can't seem to remember -- which charities were they, in which years, that benefited from his Scarsdale Concours?</p>
        <p>Then it comes back: ''In 2004 and 2005, it was the United Way -- and also in 2005, the Kellner Family Pediatric Liver Foundation. Then last year, it was the Habitat for Humanity of Westchester.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When two Scarsdale High School sophomores organized their first car show four years ago, their ambition was to stage a top-notch concours.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVAN M. CYGLER, who is 19, can't seem to remember -- which charities were they, in which years, that benefited from his Scarsdale Concours?</p>
        <p>Then it comes back: ''In 2004 and 2005, it was the United Way -- and also in 2005, the Kellner Family Pediatric Liver Foundation. Then last year, it was the Habitat for Humanity of Westchester.''</p>
        <p>The diminutive college sophomore's head shakes ruefully: ''Starting to forget things,'' he said. ''I'm getting old.'' Such outlandish statements fall from Mr. Cygler's mouth like pearls from a broken string, to clatter on the floor with a priceless racket.</p>
        <p>It all began four years ago, when he and a fellow Scarsdale High School sophomore, Denis O'Leary III, operating on purest American chutzpah, enlisted the help of the Scarsdale Police Department to organize a car show. Without much more than a hearty handshake, the event was set in motion, beginning a fast-growing tradition that is set to play out again today with the fourth annual Scarsdale Concours in the commercial center of this Westchester County village.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cygler recalls the circumstances. ''About that time, Scarsdale High had gotten some bad press over student-body binge drinking at the homecoming dance. We wanted to do something more positive.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cygler and Mr. O'Leary had already formed a sanctioned after-school car club. They had been car-mad since they met as third graders at Windward School, which Mr. Cygler calls ''sort of the Harvard of special-education schools.''</p>
        <p>Subsequently transferred to mainline schools, the two met up again at Scarsdale High. In the interim, both had faithfully attended the New York International Auto Show and the Greenwich Concours d'Élégance year after year. Both were obsessed with cars of all sorts, but most particularly classic cars from Europe.</p>
        <p>So at the tender age of 15, they laid plans for a car show in Scarsdale. But not any Saturday night hot-rod drive past the Dairy Queen: their ambition was to stage a top-notch concours like the one presented each June in Greenwich, Conn. ''We were young -- teenagers,'' Mr. Cygler said with a smile, ''putting on an old man's car show.''</p>
        <p>Their age could have been an insurmountable obstacle, but for the two determined teenagers, it proved the opposite -- a startling reality that earned them a serious hearing. They approached Detective Richard Fatigate of the Scarsdale police (who has since retired) and said, ''We want to shut down the commercial center for a day to put on a top-shelf concours.'' And Detective Fatigate, the department's community resources officer -- himself an auto enthusiast -- listened to every word.</p>
        <p>''At first it was hard to get people to take us seriously,'' Mr. O'Leary recalled. ''Detective Fatigate was the key. He said, 'Just don't make me look like an idiot.' ''</p>
        <p>''They were two very energetic high school kids,'' the retired detective said. ''In an era of widespread under-age drinking, I was amazed at what they were proposing. I told them I'd do what I could -- but to close down the village would take a very good reason. From there on, I acted as a facilitator.''</p>
        <p>Improbably, approval came down from Scarsdale Town Hall. The authorities would shut down half of the handsome Tudor-style Scarsdale Village -- the commercial center near the train station -- for the show. Mr. Cygler and Mr. O'Leary were on.</p>
        <p>They spent hundreds and hundreds of hours trying to get car collectors in the area to commit their treasured vehicles to the first show, which took place in June 2004.</p>
        <p>''If I knew how many hours we'd spend organizing each show,'' Mr. O'Leary said, ''I probably wouldn't do it.'' But luckily, as collectible car ownership goes, the two were working rich soil. Mr. Cygler noted that there are many wealthy car collectors in and around Westchester, ''and we got to know a lot of them going to local car shows together.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''We both have a passion for European classics -- and not much interest in American muscle cars. We think the European cars are more beautiful, like rolling sculpture.</p>
        <p>''Of course, we have some American cars, too -- a Ford GT40 Mk II and a few very special Corvettes. We should be proud of what American manufacturers have made.''</p>
        <p>Despite his age and inexperience, Mr. Cygler found that ''the classic-car owners are all enthusiastic and friendly,'' adding, ''We've gotten a lot of help from major collectors like Malcolm Pray in Greenwich and Peter Kalikow,'' the developer who is retiring as chairman of the Metropolitan Transportation Authority. He said that Mr. Pray, a prominent auto dealer, ''was generous enough to bring five cars -- of our choosing -- to our first concours.''</p>
        <p>Planning for the first show went swimmingly until, with two weeks to go, Scarsdale decided to shut down not half of the commercial center, but all of it. Suddenly, Mr. Cygler and Mr. O'Leary had to dig up twice as many cars. As if by magic, the energetic duo effortlessly met the challenge.</p>
        <p>That first show was a resounding success, raising $17,500 for the United Way, and the Scarsdale concours is now an annual event. In their original proposal, Mr. Cygler and Mr. O'Leary intended to raise $100,000-plus for charity over the first three years (the precocious pair's full term in high school). They met their expectations. ''Now we're going on to our first $1 million,'' Mr. Cygler says with not a hint of vainglory. That is simply a fact.</p>
        <p>After four years, merchants are enthusiastically supportive. Besides generating money for charity -- the beneficiaries this year will be the Scarsdale police and volunteer firefighters -- the show generates attention and income for the village.</p>
        <p>Commercial interests notwithstanding, the heart and soul of the Scarsdale Concours are the cars themselves, which range from the expected classics of the 1930s to the latest in exotic supercars.</p>
        <p>In contrast to many concours, the cars are displayed on pavement, relieving owners of the mud and misery sometimes suffered on grass at rainy shows. To further show the Ferraris, Lamborghinis, Mercedes-Benzes and other classics to best advantage, Mr. Cygler and Mr. O'Leary settled on a distinctive approach. Wherever possible, they amass numerous examples of the same marque -- say, Jaguar or Rolls-Royce. Arranged in historic order, they form a sort of timeline of each marque's growth and development. This engaging strategy is one that other car shows could adopt.</p>
        <p>''I also love art,'' Mr. O'Leary said by way of explanation, ''and how else would you display Rothkos but all in a group? It's the same with each marque in our show.''</p>
        <p>This year's show also follows the two partners' completion of their freshman years in college. Mr. Cygler attended the University of Hartford in Connecticut while Mr. O'Leary was down in Virginia at Washington and Lee University. ''Doing the concours without the Internet would be completely impossible,'' Mr. O'Leary said. ''I'm in the middle of nowhere in Virginia, and Evan is way up in Connecticut. But thanks to the Net, anything's possible.''</p>
        <p>Such a major undertaking may sound far too daunting for a pair of college freshmen, much less a pair of high school sophomores. Yet despite their successes, the young men remain regulation 19-year olds. Mr. Cygler has determined that going to college only two hours away from Scarsdale puts him just a little too close to home. This fall, he will move far beyond the horizon, to the University of Arizona, where he plans to major in business and marketing.</p>
        <p>On the subject of marketing, his professors might well learn from him.</p>
        <p>A Scarsdale resident, Joe Torrisi, has shown several fine cars in the concours, including some pristine Shelby Mustangs from the '60s and a 2005 Ford GT, and he enthusiastically supports the event.</p>
        <p>''It's a great show,'' he said. ''My children keep asking me, 'When is the show? When is the show?' And where else can you test-drive a $300,000 Maybach? At the Scarsdale show, the highest bidder gets to drive one of the cars up to Kensico Dam and back.''</p>
        <p>To generate extra money for charity, bids are taken for drives through Westchester in featured cars. ''If the car owner wants,'' Mr. Cygler said, ''he can auction a drive in his car. It's a fun experience for both owner and driver, and we usually raise a few thousand extra dollars that way.''</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Cygler's and O'Leary's futures, Mr. Fatigate has no reservations. ''This is just the beginning,'' he said. ''They are going to be very successful people in their adult lives.''</p>
        <p>The Scarsdale Concours takes place from 10:30 a.m. to 4 p.m. today at Scarsdale Village. (Rain date is June 24.) Suggested donation is $10. Information is available at scarsdaleconcours.com.</p>
        <p>COLLECTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
