<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cavaliers Put a City in Jeopardy  of Winning</title>
    <meta content="10score" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853331"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="KEEPING SCORE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E1DC163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cavaliers Put a City in Jeopardy  of Winning</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID LEONHARDT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The longest civic losing streak in the nation is now in jeopardy.</p>
        <p>The city of Cleveland last celebrated a major sports title on Dec. 27, 1964, when the Browns upset the Baltimore Colts in the N.F.L. championship game. In the more than four decades since, the Indians once took a lead into the bottom of the ninth inning of Game 7 of the World Series, while the Browns endured three of the more painful playoff losses in National Football League history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The longest civic losing streak in the nation is now in jeopardy.</p>
        <p>The city of Cleveland last celebrated a major sports title on Dec. 27, 1964, when the Browns upset the Baltimore Colts in the N.F.L. championship game. In the more than four decades since, the Indians once took a lead into the bottom of the ninth inning of Game 7 of the World Series, while the Browns endured three of the more painful playoff losses in National Football League history.</p>
        <p>But no major Cleveland pro team has won another championship. Those teams have played 123 combined seasons since the Browns' 1964 title, making Cleveland the hardest-luck sports town in the country. Philadelphia, with 96 straight titleless seasons, ranks a distant second.</p>
        <p>Tonight in San Antonio, the Cavaliers -- trailing in the best-of-seven series, 1-0 -- will play the Spurs in Game 2 of the N.B.A. finals. If Cleveland's streak is going to end this month, it will have to involve an upset as big as the Browns' victory over the Colts.</p>
        <p>The Colts were favored to win the 1964 championship game by a touchdown, even though the game was being played on a freezing, windy day in Cleveland. (At the time, championship games alternated between the home city of the Eastern Division winner -- Cleveland that year -- and the Western Division winner.)</p>
        <p>Behind Johnny Unitas, Baltimore had been the league's dominant team that season. The Colts had finished the regular season at 12-2, scoring more points than any other team in the league and allowing the fewest. Before the game, Tom Melody, who covered the Browns for The Akron Beacon Journal, wrote, ''It is unreasonable to imagine the Browns emerging triumphant.''</p>
        <p>But with an aggressive defensive strategy, heavy on blitzes and bump-and-run coverage, the Browns won, 27-0. Cleveland's quarterback -- Frank Ryan, who was studying for a doctorate in math from Rice University during his playing days -- threw three touchdown passes, all to Gary Collins. The 40-year-old Lou Groza, who was known as the Toe, kicked two field goals, and Jim Brown ran for 114 yards.</p>
        <p>The day after the game, an article in The Plain Dealer in Cleveland suggested that the Browns might be a dynasty in the making.</p>
        <p>Instead, the team lost three title games over the next five years, starting a run of biblical-like misery for Cleveland fans. In a 1981 playoff game, Browns quarterback Brian Sipe threw a last-minute interception in the Raiders' end zone. Cleveland had been on the Raiders' 13-yard line at the time, trailing by 14-12, but its kicker had already missed two field-goal attempts on the icy field.</p>
        <p>Like many of Cleveland's worst moments, this one would be given a name: the Interception.</p>
        <p>Six years later, in January 1987, John Elway led the Broncos on a 98-yard fourth-quarter drive -- the Drive -- to beat the Browns in the American Football Conference title game. In a rematch the next season, Earnest Byner lost the ball -- the Fumble -- on the 3-yard line with 1 minute 12 seconds left and the Browns down by a touchdown. The next year, Michael Jordan hit a last-second shot -- the Shot -- to beat the Cavaliers in a decisive playoff game.</p>
        <p>In the '90s, after decades of simply being bad, the Indians became the city's near-miss team. In 1995, they put together the best regular-season record in Major League Baseball since the 1954 Indians, only to lose the World Series to the Braves. (The 1954 team lost the Series too, thanks in part to the most famous catch in baseball history, by Willie Mays.) In 1997, the Indians led the Marlins, 2-1, in the ninth inning of Game 7, but José Mesa could not get the final three outs and Florida won in the 11th inning.</p>
        <p>There are now Cleveland sports fans in their late 40s who have never rooted for a championship team.</p>
        <p>''I have endured the Shot, the Drive, the Fumble, the Interception, the Braves and even the Florida Marlins,'' said Matthew Rego, 37, who was born a few months before the Cavaliers played their first game. ''So am I excited that the Cavs are playing for a championship? I am pumped beyond measure.''</p>
        <p>This column last ranked the country's most title-starved cities in 2004, and only two cities have come off the list since. The Colts' Super Bowl win this year came after 58 straight seasons without a championship for Indianapolis. The Steelers' 2006 title stopped Pittsburgh's streak at 40 combined seasons.</p>
        <p>But neither of those cities was really in Cleveland's league. In fact, no other city is -- not now and perhaps not ever.</p>
        <p>A number of cities with multiple teams have gone two decades without a title at various times. Washington once went 36 years, between the 1942 Redskins and the 1978 Bullets. But Cleveland may well be the first to put together a losing steak spanning more than 40 years and more than 100 combined seasons.</p>
        <p>''When it comes to Cleveland and its professional sports teams, I have come to accept heartache as a way of life,'' said Rego, a theater producer at the Araca Group in New York.</p>
        <p>Still, he will fly home this week to Cleveland so he can be at Game 3 of the finals.</p>
        <p>KEEPING SCORE E-mail: keepingscore@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: keepingscore@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
