<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fistful of Dollars</title>
    <meta content="10wwln--Q4.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/magazine/10wwln-Q4-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853466"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 6-10-07: QUESTIONS FOR DOUG ELLIN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Home Box Office</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06EFD81130F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="672" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fistful of Dollars</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fistful of Dollars</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SOLOMON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q: As the creator of the hit show ''Entourage,'' which follows four buddies from Queens on their adventures in Hollywood, you've become a leading chronicler of the American dream at its most nakedly materialistic. So perhaps it's not surprising that you're planning a new HBO series devoted to a group of hedge-fund guys in New York. Why do you find the subject of money so interesting? Sadly, right now, that's the world people are aspiring to. You have Harvard-educated medical doctors who would rather work at an investment bank than try to cure cancer, and that's the wish-fulfillment lifestyle that I play into.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The TV producer and writer talks about why ‘‘Entourage’’ is realism not satire, why friends are just like family and why everything, including his next show, is all about easy money.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q: As the creator of the hit show ''Entourage,'' which follows four buddies from Queens on their adventures in Hollywood, you've become a leading chronicler of the American dream at its most nakedly materialistic. So perhaps it's not surprising that you're planning a new HBO series devoted to a group of hedge-fund guys in New York. Why do you find the subject of money so interesting? Sadly, right now, that's the world people are aspiring to. You have Harvard-educated medical doctors who would rather work at an investment bank than try to cure cancer, and that's the wish-fulfillment lifestyle that I play into.</p>
        <p>The desire to make money is nothing new. No, but now people are looking for the home runs constantly. That's the difference. People are seeing shortcuts and easy routes.</p>
        <p>''Entourage'' is itself a study in ''shortcut culture,'' to coin a phrase. The male characters don't work very hard, except at playing video games and having casual sex and wanting to be famous. Is the show intended as a sendup of Hollywood excess? No. In fact when we first started, HBO would say satire, and I said this is not satire. This is scripted reality. I consider the show 100 percent realistic. I have friends who wake up in the morning and want a Bentley and they go get it. I find it funny.</p>
        <p>You seem similarly amused by the characters on ''Entourage,'' despite their questionable values. I never looked at this show as being about values, as you say, or guys with bad values. I look at them as good guys who have each other's back and just want to take care of each other. They watch out for each other like family.</p>
        <p>So what? Nearly all television comedies are about families, or at least surrogate families of friends or workmates, as in ''Seinfeld'' or ''Cheers'' or ''The Office.'' That's true, but I know the way the boys talk on ''Entourage'' would have George Costanza's father giving them a nice, swift kick in the pants. ''Entourage'' is how I perceive friendship and how I experienced it growing up. My friends and I just walked around the neighborhood all day and talked and laughed.</p>
        <p>I assume your milieu was less flashy than the one in ''Entourage.'' My father is an accountant. Growing up on Long Island, I'd have one basketball for seven years. There was no grip left on this basketball. I don't want to sound like I had a cheap father. He was not cheap, but he was very against waste.</p>
        <p>What advantages did that give you? None.</p>
        <p>Great. Tell that to your analyst. Oh, yeah. I've got therapy twice a week. I'm a mess.</p>
        <p>At least you're a productive mess. At 39, you've written and directed two feature films, including ''Phat Beach,'' a critical flop about two pals who make easy money by selling sunglasses on the beach. I went from failed movies to successful TV, but I am going to get back to failed movies someday.</p>
        <p>Good luck with that. In the meantime, does success on HBO pay more or less than other networks? I think the deal I have is on par with the good show-runners in town. I'm very well compensated. I have a four-year contract. I'll be starting a new one on Aug. 1.</p>
        <p>How much do you earn? I'm not going to tell you.</p>
        <p>About $3 million a year? Yeah, you can put it in that neighborhood.</p>
        <p>What do you do with all that dough? I don't really spend a lot of money. I'm not a flashy guy. I drive a Lexus hybrid. I don't have a lot of things that I really care about besides my kids.</p>
        <p>Kids can be costly to raise, especially once they discover batteries. Lucas is 5 and Maya is 3, so a firetruck and a doll keep them happy for a couple of weeks.</p>
        <p>How would you feel if your kids turned out like the guys on ''Entourage''? I'd kill myself.</p>
        <p>DEBORAH SOLOMON</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 6-10-07: QUESTIONS FOR DOUG ELLIN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
