<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With an Exit, a Historic Church Reaches a Crossroads</title>
    <meta content="10riverside" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/10riverside.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853375"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EFD9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1631" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With an Exit, a Historic Church Reaches a Crossroads</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With an Exit, a Historic Church at a Crossroads</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC KONIGSBERG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>During Wednesday night's send-off celebration at Riverside Church, the Rev. Dr. James A. Forbes Jr. indulged in strutting around his pulpit here and there, more like a bantam than a peacock.</p>
        <p>After 18 years as the senior minister at Riverside, who could blame him? The church, on a hill at 120th Street and Riverside Drive, has been a center of activism and political debate since its inception in 1930. Dr. Forbes cherished the adulation of roughly 1,500 congregants and admirers who filled the church's nave to mark his retirement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As its senior minister leaves after 18 years, Riverside Church may face a rough passage into a new era.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>During Wednesday night's send-off celebration at Riverside Church, the Rev. Dr. James A. Forbes Jr. indulged in strutting around his pulpit here and there, more like a bantam than a peacock.</p>
        <p>After 18 years as the senior minister at Riverside, who could blame him? The church, on a hill at 120th Street and Riverside Drive, has been a center of activism and political debate since its inception in 1930. Dr. Forbes cherished the adulation of roughly 1,500 congregants and admirers who filled the church's nave to mark his retirement.</p>
        <p>''It's like drinking coffee and discovering that there's a concentration of sweetness at the bottom of the cup,'' he said afterward.</p>
        <p>The service, which lasted nearly four hours, was a multi-act extravagaria, flamboyant and roaming, in a worship space modeled on the Gothic cathedral of Chartres. There were tributes from David N. Dinkins, Bill Moyers and Cornel West, and -- via video -- from Charles B. Rangel, Desmond Tutu and Bill Clinton.</p>
        <p>Yet despite the display of good cheer, Riverside's movement into its next era might well amount to rough passage. In the coming year, as the church's leadership searches for a successor to Dr. Forbes, a small, admittedly poorly organized but vocal minority, dissatisfied with the shift the church has undergone during his tenure, is intent on having a say in the hopes of bringing about a sort of Restoration era for Riverside.</p>
        <p>The battle has been playing out since before Dr. Forbes announced his resignation last September and reached a more intense pitch at the church's annual meeting on May 20. It involves lawsuits, allegations of financial impropriety and a countermovement to expel two longstanding congregants on the grounds of bad form.</p>
        <p>Though the contretemps appears at first blush to be a simple clash over management styles and church governance, at the core it is a conflict of race, class, theology and the future of one of the country's most prominent churches.</p>
        <p>Riverside was built on ambitious and utopian ideals, with money from John D. Rockefeller Jr. It is affiliated with two denominations, the American Baptist Churches and the United Church of Christ.</p>
        <p>The jacket copy of a history of Riverside Church published in 2004 calls it ''the premier model of Protestant liberalism in the United States'' and ''a multiracial and multiethnic church that has been at the vanguard of social justice advocacy.''</p>
        <p>The church's first senior minister, the Rev. Dr. Harry Emerson Fosdick, was a critic of fundamentalism. Dr. Forbes's immediate predecessor, the Rev. Dr. William Sloane Coffin Jr., came to Riverside in 1977 fresh from the chaplaincy of Yale University, where he had been a crusader against the Vietnam War.</p>
        <p>The timeline of Dr. Forbes's tenure is marked by more than its share of social advocacy, from Nelson Mandela's 1990 visit after he was released from prison to the establishment in 2006 of a ministry for people with H.I.V. or AIDS.</p>
        <p>Along the way, Dr. Forbes was arrested for civil disobedience in the Haitian refugee crisis, was the chairman of a forum on welfare reform with President Clinton, welcomed the Dalai Lama and King Abdullah of Jordan to Riverside, and addressed the 2004 Democratic National Convention.</p>
        <p>Even so, Dr. Forbes's detractors, most of whom have histories at the church that predate him, accuse him of softening Riverside's political involvement and abandoning his predecessors' intellectual approach for something more evangelical. At times, he has shown a fondness for altar calls during services, and his sermons can be long and emotional.</p>
        <p>''The sermons of the senior minister haven't tended to address, to the extent of his predecessors', the burning national and international issues of the day,'' said Howard Geiger, a financial analyst and a former treasurer of the church.</p>
        <p>There have also been undertones of racial discord during Dr. Forbes's time leading the church. And although Dr. Forbes, the first black person to hold the job, said the church's membership had increased during his tenure by more than 10 percent, one congregant, Cleveland Parks Jr., said his style had alienated a segment of the old guard, some of whom are white.</p>
        <p>''There's a significant number of European-American brothers and sisters that are still members but have found other places to worship because they're not happy here,'' said Mr. Parks, who is black.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Dr. Robert L. Polk, who became the first black minister on the staff in 1960, said that when Dr. Forbes arrived, ''I told him: You can do one of two things.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'You can preserve the three ''inters'' -- international, interdenominational, interracial -- or you can forget about that and make it all black,' '' said Dr. Polk, who is retired. ''He did the second.''</p>
        <p>In an interview, Dr. Forbes said his method of preaching had its roots in the sermons of his father, a Pentecostal minister in North Carolina, and had come as a shock to some Riverside members.</p>
        <p>''People thought they were getting Bible Belt values as well as my Bible Belt style,'' he said. ''There were meetings questioning my commitment to social justice. I believe in people anchoring their faith to a more personal relationship with God. But there's plenty of room at the Riverside Church for people to feel uncomfortable.</p>
        <p>''There was a time when the church was viewed in terms of its commentary on social events,'' he went on. ''I felt that having a biblical foundation actually strengthens that,'' he said of his sermons.</p>
        <p>The church has about 2,700 members. ''When I came here, the ethnic breakdown was about 60 percent white and 40 percent black,'' Dr. Forbes said. ''Shortly after my arrival, the incoming membership classes would have a few more blacks than whites. Eventually it was 50-50, then 60-40 blacks to whites. The last census was closer to 70-30 blacks to whites.''</p>
        <p>Adding to the tension, Mr. Geiger and Mr. Parks were among a small group of congregants -- most of whom have been agitating for years -- to accuse church leaders in court last year of cronyism and mismanagement of the church's budget, to the point that the endowment had dwindled. They demanded that a judge appoint a receiver to examine its finances.</p>
        <p>The church denied the allegations, and a State Supreme Court judge in Manhattan dismissed the case. On May 30 of this year, Constance Guice-Mills, one of the original authors of the complaint, filed suit again, with similar allegations.</p>
        <p>''The budget is a serious concern right now, because the church is no longer run in a transparent way, and we can't find out how everything is being spent,'' said Alan Borthwick, who joined the church with his family in 1969. ''It's been a long time since this was a church for people with inherited wealth.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Forbes said the church's finances were sound.</p>
        <p>At Riverside's annual congregation meeting on May 20, members voted on whether to expel from the church two of the congregants who filed the lawsuit. The motion was rejected by a 33-to-30 vote, Mr. Parks said. ''But for them to be able to even initiate that type of vote is nowhere in the church bylaws,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Billy E. Jones, the chairman of the Riverside Church Council and a member of the search committee, said the vote was a result of a petition signed by 105 members of the congregation.</p>
        <p>''Members were saying, 'Do something about these people; they are constantly interrupting and interfering in meetings,' '' he said. ''It went before the church council, and then the council of elders. The whole thing went through a process.''</p>
        <p>The dissenting group also voiced concerns about the church's recently formed senior minister search committee, which they say is heavily weighted with Dr. Forbes's friends and confidants. In particular, they resent that the chairwoman of the committee, Cheryle Wills, has been a Riverside member only since 2004.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jones said the search committee would have its first official meeting today and hoped to have a new senior minister in place within the next year to a year and a half. ''We don't even have any candidates identified,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As for Ms. Wills's role, he said, ''I actually think there's an advantage to having somebody running the search committee who's new to Riverside, so that you have somebody who's neutral to all these different camps. And you know, who's to say that only longtime members know what's best for Riverside?''</p>
        <p>Dr. Forbes acknowledged that his retirement left the church at a critical juncture.</p>
        <p>''Some friends and supporters have said that in order to sustain our multiethnic history, perhaps the pendulum ought to swing back to the way the Riverside Church was before I got here,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''That is going to be one of the tests of the depths of Riverside's liberalism. The members will have to ask themselves: 'What would it be like to return to the ways of the church before Jim Forbes? Would we like to have less diversity? Would we like to have less of an emphasis on the spirit?' ''</p>
        <p>At Wednesday night's celebration, three different choirs and a handful of soloists, including Kathleen Battle, offered hymns and anthems. The musical selections reflected Riverside's evolution -- ''I Don't Feel Noways Tired,'' for example, and the Dottie Peoples gospel staple ''He's an On Time God.'' A corps of young step dancers performed in the central aisle.</p>
        <p>Midway through the evening, a large video screen flashed footage from Dr. Forbes's installation service in 1989, when a group of mostly white church leaders welcomed him with a group hug and one of them addressed him as ''my brother.''</p>
        <p>Cornel West, who teaches religion at Princeton, gave an impassioned tribute at last week's service. A particularly loud burst of applause came when he declared, ''The last 18 years have been a delicious experiment in contemporary American Christianity.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
