<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Shed of One's Own (Just Add the Telescope)</title>
    <meta content="10spaceliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/10spaceli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853517"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL SPACE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sheds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telescopes and Observatories</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Centereach (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lifetime Products Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stallard, Glynn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telescopes and Observatories</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E2D91E30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Shed of One's Own (Just Add the Telescope)</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Shed of One’s Own (Just Add the Telescope)</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <dateline>CENTEREACH</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Glynn Stallard, 53, manufacturing engineer in Centereach, NY, who uses his backyard shed, won in contest sponsored by Lifetime Products, to enjoy his astronomy hobby; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GLYNN STALLARD, 53, a manufacturing engineer, has had a lifelong passion for astronomy.</p>
        <p>But sharing a 1,700-square-foot ranch house here with his wife, Mary Lou, their two teenagers, two dogs, two cats, fish and a bird leaves ''little time or space for his hobby,'' his 18-year-old daughter, Carolyn, noted on the entry form for the national Backyard Guy Getaway contest that she filled out a few months ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Centereach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GLYNN STALLARD, 53, a manufacturing engineer, has had a lifelong passion for astronomy.</p>
        <p>But sharing a 1,700-square-foot ranch house here with his wife, Mary Lou, their two teenagers, two dogs, two cats, fish and a bird leaves ''little time or space for his hobby,'' his 18-year-old daughter, Carolyn, noted on the entry form for the national Backyard Guy Getaway contest that she filled out a few months ago.</p>
        <p>''With a backyard getaway, that could change,'' wrote Carolyn, who was trying to win a weather-resistant shed covering about 150 square feet that could double as her father's very own grown-up hideout, as well as $2,500 to turn it into his dream stargazing den.</p>
        <p>''My father is a frustrated astronomer,'' she added. ''He would use his guy getaway to its utmost extent.''</p>
        <p>Despite a recent expansion of the house, Mr. Stallard's equipment was always in the way, Carolyn said recently. When he parked his three-foot reflector telescope on a tripod near the kitchen door, it blocked access to the parakeet's cage. When he stored it in the garden shed alongside tools and a mower, it blocked the path to her bicycle.</p>
        <p>''It would be in the way of everything,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Thanks to her entry, her father, who by day troubleshoots airplane parts for Northrop Grumman in Bethpage, won the shed, the $2,500 and a slot as one of three semifinalists for a $10,000 grand prize. The do-it-yourself steel-reinforced plastic shed, itself valued at $2,500, has two windows, a skylight, a vaulted ceiling and double steel doors but no electrical hookup; it was screwed together by a handyman on Memorial Day weekend.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stallard put down carpeting, moved in his telescope and a recliner, hung new glow-in-the-dark posters of the night sky, placed his astronomy guides on a bookshelf and started blasting his favorite ''space music'' -- music used in planetarium shows -- from a battery-powered CD player. He has ordered a desk and a new recliner.</p>
        <p>''There are times when you want to get away and be able to concentrate on things other than your family,'' Mr. Stallard said.</p>
        <p>If he wins the grand prize, to be announced tomorrow by Lifetime Products, a manufacturer of sheds and other products in Clearfield, Utah, Mr. Stallard said he would consider putting in a domed observatory roof. Usually he sets up the telescope on the lawn to watch meteor showers and do ''star hopping,'' he said, referring to locating a constellation and trying to ''find the galaxies based on where they should be.''</p>
        <p>Other semifinalists include a movie-lobby-themed shed that Mike Irelan set up in Victorville, Calif., and a landlocked surf shack created by Todd Mosher of Littleton, Colo.</p>
        <p>Mary Lou Stallard, 52, said her husband ''deserves to have a place to put his stuff.''</p>
        <p>Sam Martin, the author of ''ManSpace: A Primal Guide to Marking Your Territory'' (Taunton Press, 2006) and the judge of the contest, said that with a shed a man can create a place to indulge his interests.</p>
        <p>''Women control the house in the sense that they control what it looks like and what can go up on the walls and what type of clutter that gathers,'' Mr. Martin said. ''It's not uncommon for men to have just a small section of the top of a dresser to put their keys and their wallet when they get home. Even that has to be a certain way.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Martin, 38, who does his writing in a shed in his backyard in Austin, Tex., added that no matter how close to the house it is, such a place ''feels like miles away.''</p>
        <p>Mary Lou Stallard, whose own getaway is her garden, hopes the shed will also soon accommodate her husband's camping gear, now stuffed into a corner of the den, and his freshwater-fishing paraphernalia. The binoculars he uses for bird-watching and the gizmo he uses for geo-caching -- a kind of high-tech orienteering -- are already there. Perhaps he'll take his ukulele, too.</p>
        <p>''Everyone needs an escape hatch,'' she said. ''Everyone needs space by themselves.''</p>
        <p>PERSONAL SPACE E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
