<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HABITATS/Red Hook, Brooklyn; Why Ask for the Moon If You Have the Stars?</title>
    <meta content="10habi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/realestate/10habi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853604"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Habitats | Red Hook, Brooklyn"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Brooklyn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Habitats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Red Hook (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E4DC1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1076" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HABITATS/Red Hook, Brooklyn; Why Ask for the Moon If You Have the Stars?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Why Ask for the Moon if You Have the Stars?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN P. WILLIAMS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RED HOOK is one of those rare New York neighborhoods where the stars aren't completely obscured by city lights. By late summer, Gita Nandan and Jens Veneman will be able to track them from their bathtub, which they're preparing to relocate to their back deck. And if the gardening gods are beneficent, they'll be able to reach out of the suds to snag cashew fruit from the scraggly tree they nursed to life from seeds they brought back from Cambodia.</p>
        <p>At the moment, the tub rests on the smooth concrete floor of the unfinished bathroom inside their compact Brooklyn home. In addition to the tub, the bathroom has an old pedestal sink and a toilet, along with rough concrete walls waiting to be tiled in soapstone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the backyard of a renovated house in Red Hook, Brooklyn, a view of the night sky reveals more than just city lights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RED HOOK is one of those rare New York neighborhoods where the stars aren't completely obscured by city lights. By late summer, Gita Nandan and Jens Veneman will be able to track them from their bathtub, which they're preparing to relocate to their back deck. And if the gardening gods are beneficent, they'll be able to reach out of the suds to snag cashew fruit from the scraggly tree they nursed to life from seeds they brought back from Cambodia.</p>
        <p>At the moment, the tub rests on the smooth concrete floor of the unfinished bathroom inside their compact Brooklyn home. In addition to the tub, the bathroom has an old pedestal sink and a toilet, along with rough concrete walls waiting to be tiled in soapstone.</p>
        <p>''It's considered a local building product, since it comes from Vermont, which is less than 500 miles away,'' said Ms. Nandan, an architect who believes in sustainable building practices.</p>
        <p>At the moment, the bathroom is open to the dining room, the living room, the kitchen and the bedroom, which has a mattress on the floor and an Indian print bedspread straight out of Haight-Ashbury, circa 1969.</p>
        <p>Mr. Veneman, 40, arrived in New York in 1986 from Germany, where he was raised by his German mother and Dutch father. He soon found his way to a bar called Tin Pan Alley in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''It was a communist-socialist bar, and I met a lot of artists there, like the painter Kiki Smith and the sculptors Tom Otterness and Mark di Suvero,'' said Mr. Veneman, a lean man with hair that's still more pepper than salt.</p>
        <p>He ended up becoming a sculptor himself and learned a lot about large-scale fabrication while working as a studio manager, first for Mr. Otterness and then for Mr. di Suvero.</p>
        <p>Later, he did other, more traditional construction work, including decorative plastering, before becoming a partner in a construction company called VeGo.</p>
        <p>In 2001, facing landlord problems, he decided to buy his own house. Along with his friend Brian Seitz, a philosophy professor, Mr. Veneman found a broker selling a teardown on Dikeman Street.</p>
        <p>''We got it for $116,000 cash,'' Mr. Veneman said. ''It was the last great deal in Red Hook.''</p>
        <p>At 25 feet by 25 feet, it's a wide but shallow two-story house with only 1,250 square feet of livable space. That space was sagging badly and needed new windows, walls, plumbing and electricity. The two men renovated it themselves, running up about $100,000 in credit-card debt in the process. Professor Seitz lives upstairs.</p>
        <p>''A Slovenian documentarian taped us,'' Mr. Veneman said. ''Who knew that the video of the philosopher and the sculptor drinking whiskey in the morning while renovating their house would be such a big hit on Slovenian TV?''</p>
        <p>At a Fourth of July party in 2001, Mr. Veneman met Ms. Nandan, now 36. Despite the fireworks, it wasn't love at first sight. But there was definitely a lot of ''like.''</p>
        <p>At the time, Ms. Nandan, a striking dark-haired woman with pale blue eyes and a tiny silver nose stud, lived in a Williamsburg loft. She and several school friends from the University of California at Berkeley had formed the Thread Collective, a Brooklyn design firm that focuses on sustainable architecture and landscapes. It has renovated factories into apartments and is developing a condominium building in Bushwick.</p>
        <p>Mr. Veneman says their shared interest in sustainable design enhanced their bond. Growing up in Europe, which is in many ways decades ahead of the United States in conserving energy and avoiding toxic materials, he was accustomed to reusing materials and avoiding chemicals.</p>
        <p>''My mother still collects rainwater in a barrel that she feeds into the washing machine rather than using the city water,'' Mr. Veneman said.</p>
        <p>The couple love to find creative uses for castoffs from job sites, and each of them has dragged home treasures like thick butcher-block counters, the ceiling beams that now form a garden table and slabs of white marble.</p>
        <p>''Those slabs will be the pastry block for my chocolate candy,'' said Mr. Veneman, who invariably prepares a meal for Ms. Nandan at the end of the day.</p>
        <p>As they approach the house, visitors get the sense that there are happy lives unfolding inside. Bicycles are chained to the wrought-iron fence, and a well-used Old Town canoe lies catawampus at the entrance to the cellar.</p>
        <p>Inside, the original 19th-century staircase rises to Professor Seitz's floor, which was gut-renovated save for a bit of tin ceiling in the kitchen. The kitchen cabinets were made of cedar recycled from a decrepit water tank.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nandan and Mr. Veneman's apartment on the ground floor has salvaged oak and Russian pine floors. The walls were insulated with Ultratouch, which is made from shredded blue jeans. ''This place is insanely caulked and insulated,'' Ms. Nandan said. ''Last winter, we paid just $680 for heat.''</p>
        <p>French doors lead into the garden. Piles of bricks and bikes and a small cement mixer and other useful detritus are scattered about the patio. The couple plan to replace the concrete with a deck over the summer and to add rain barrels to collect runoff from the roof.</p>
        <p>Eventually, hops vines will climb the side wall. They'll harvest the fruits to make beer in the cellar.</p>
        <p>But they've already created paradise beyond the patio, at least in terms of South Brooklyn. It wasn't easy. Five years ago, they'd throw bottles at the rats that ran along the rear wall to eat their green tomatoes.</p>
        <p>''Then we got a cat, and rats stayed away,'' Mr. Veneman said. But ''the cat got fleas. So did we. Now we've got the whole thing under control.''</p>
        <p>A mulberry tree draws songbirds and sheds fruit that the couple eat with their morning cereal. There are also peach, cherry and pear trees, and an apple tree said to have been grafted from the original tree that inspired Sir Isaac Newton.</p>
        <p>''They sell them as a fund-raiser,'' Mr. Veneman said.</p>
        <p>During the summer, they'll have gooseberries, raspberries, red currants and strawberries, all manner of herbs and string beans, cabbage and eggplant.</p>
        <p>''By July and August if you haven't gone shopping you can just come home and eat out of the garden,'' Ms. Nandan said. ''This is where we spend most of our time, and where most of our friends spend their time, too, which is why we don't get as much done as we'd like.''</p>
        <p>Habitats | Red Hook, Brooklyn</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
