<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>I'm Outta Here</title>
    <meta content="10LIspiel" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/opinion/nyregionopinions/10LIspiel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853519"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloomberg, Michael R (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spiel, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D91E30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>I'm Outta Here</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">I’m Outta Here</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Spiel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Spiel, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Queens resident David Spiel gives reasons why he opposes New York City Mayor Michael Bloomberg's congestion pricing plan (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE day that New York adopts congestion pricing, charging me to drive from one part of the city to another, is the day I move to Long Island. Why? Because as much as I love Queens and its proximity to Manhattan, I can't afford another tax.</p>
        <p>I have lived in Queens most of my life and have always considered it the best of both worlds. I can drive to Manhattan in 20 minutes, yet I have a yard for my children to play in. And if I forget something in my car, I can go out barefoot to retrieve it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Why congestion pricing means moving to Long Island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE day that New York adopts congestion pricing, charging me to drive from one part of the city to another, is the day I move to Long Island. Why? Because as much as I love Queens and its proximity to Manhattan, I can't afford another tax.</p>
        <p>I have lived in Queens most of my life and have always considered it the best of both worlds. I can drive to Manhattan in 20 minutes, yet I have a yard for my children to play in. And if I forget something in my car, I can go out barefoot to retrieve it.</p>
        <p>While Michael Bloomberg is generally a good mayor, he couldn't give a fig for us bridge and tunnel people. To raise money, he forces us to pay a quarter for seven and a half minutes of parking at meters. Now he wants us to pay $8 for the privilege of getting to them. He has obviously never had to park a car in Manhattan on a workingman's salary.</p>
        <p>I live in Hollis Hills, a couple of miles from Long Island. I pay $5,000 in city income taxes and my real estate taxes have risen to $7,000 from $1,400 in the eight years that I have lived here. My brother, who works with me in Long Island City, lives in Great Neck. He pays higher real estate taxes but no city tax. We both essentially shell out the same amount when it comes to taxes.</p>
        <p>But my brother's services are phenomenal. He has pickups of recyclables twice a week and garbage pickup three times a week. Here in Queens, I'm lucky to get my recyclables picked up once a week and if there is a holiday on Monday, forget about garbage pickup until Thursday. His streets are safe and clean. Mine are filthy. He has a bounty of community parks and swimming pools to choose from.</p>
        <p>I had chosen to live in New York because I love the city and enjoy going into Manhattan frequently for dinner and theater. When I head to Midtown, I normally drive in. I plan my trip so that I can park at a meter for about $10 in quarters. This requires parking at about 5:45 p.m. to avoid the theater rush and the costly garage fees. Now on top of that, Mayor Bloomberg wants to charge me $8 to enter the city below 86th Street from 6 a.m. to 6 p.m., while those who, like him, live in Manhattan are not inconvenienced at all. They can just take a cab.</p>
        <p>Those Manhattanites who are screaming for fewer cars would be less liable to complain if there were a law requiring them to take the subway to and from the opera. The last time I checked, taxis made up a considerable percentage of the cars in Manhattan. Sure, the mayor has called for greener taxis, but why not ban them altogether? After all, they cause as much congestion and pollution as privately owned cars -- perhaps more considering how much time they spend cruising the streets and blocking lanes.</p>
        <p>When I do take public transportation into Manhattan, I have to take a bus and a subway. After a show, I often have to wait up to an hour for the subway and the bus to arrive -- and that's on top of an hourlong ride home. It seems only fair that Manhattanites should have to suffer a little bit by being forced to take public transportation for an evening out.</p>
        <p>Better yet, why not return to the days immediately following 9/11 when cars with less than two people were restricted from Manhattan before 10 a.m. This really reduced traffic, especially the traffic caused by commuters who work in the city but live elsewhere. Why punish random shoppers or those of us coming to the city for an early dinner and theater?</p>
        <p>I have been driving in New York City since the 1970s. Traffic in Manhattan seems no worse now than it was 40 years ago, and it may even be a little better. It is getting into and out of Manhattan that is the problem.</p>
        <p>It's all nice and fine to point to London's success with congestion pricing. But London has a great mass transit system; it's safe and clean. Who can say that about the New York City subway? I have a hard time seeing Mayor Bloomberg taking the subway home after a night at the theater.</p>
        <p>Why do I live in Queens? Because it's closer to Manhattan than Long Island is. I like Manhattan. I go to the Philharmonic a lot. If I have to pay $8 and be forced to park in a garage for $30 then I will go less -- much less. And I will certainly stop eating at a restaurant before a concert. Indeed, I'll move to Long Island and stop paying city taxes.</p>
        <p>The mayor and other Manhattanites need to stop blaming people like me for all the traffic. Recent studies show that a huge percentage of the cars in Manhattan are merely passing through -- maybe the real solution would be to build a tunnel for those passing through the city. But don't punish the working class New Yorkers who live in the outer boroughs because they enjoy the city and what it has to offer.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor David Spiel is the owner of a company that sells and repairs bindery equipment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Spiel is the owner of a company that sells and repairs bindery equipment.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
