<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Authors Of N.F.L. Study On Concussions Dispute Finding</title>
    <meta content="10nfl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/sports/football/10nfl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853384"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Goodell, Roger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Schwarz, Alan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00EED9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1504" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Authors Of N.F.L. Study On Concussions Dispute Finding</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">N.F.L. Study Authors Dispute Concussion Finding</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN SCHWARZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schwarz, Alan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For several years, many medical experts have maintained that high school football players who sustain concussions should not return to the games in which they are injured. So when doctors commissioned by the National Football League published a study two years ago concluding ''it might be safe'' for such players to do so, the assertion sparked widespread criticism. Now the criticism is coming from authors of the paper itself.</p>
        <p>Two of the five authors of the paper published in the journal Neurosurgery, Dr. Henry Feuer of the Indiana University Medical Center and Dr. Cynthia Arfken of Wayne State University, said in telephone interviews last week that the paper's conclusion was inappropriate, and that the research should not be applied to high school and college players.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two of the five co-authors of a paper published in the journal Neurosurgery said research on concussions in football should not be applied to high school and college players.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For several years, many medical experts have maintained that high school football players who sustain concussions should not return to the games in which they are injured. So when doctors commissioned by the National Football League published a study two years ago concluding ''it might be safe'' for such players to do so, the assertion sparked widespread criticism. Now the criticism is coming from authors of the paper itself.</p>
        <p>Two of the five authors of the paper published in the journal Neurosurgery, Dr. Henry Feuer of the Indiana University Medical Center and Dr. Cynthia Arfken of Wayne State University, said in telephone interviews last week that the paper's conclusion was inappropriate, and that the research should not be applied to high school and college players.</p>
        <p>Arfken also said the passage had been added without her knowledge.</p>
        <p>The two principal authors, Dr. David Viano of Wayne State and Dr. Ira Casson of Long Island Jewish Medical Center, acknowledged that they had altered the conclusion but said that all authors had received proof copies before publication. They said the section in question was added to appease peer reviewers who asked for a discussion of high school and college players, and they continued to stand by what was written.</p>
        <p>Arfken and Feuer disavowed the paper's recommendation that high school and college medical personnel ''keep an open mind'' about the paper's analysis of concussions, which deemed safe the league's record of allowing half of the players with concussions to return to the same game. Arfken and Feuer thereby joined critics who had long claimed that such a suggestion was dangerous for younger players. Their less-developed brain tissue is believed to be more susceptible to short- and long-term damage than adults'. They also receive considerably less medical attention than players in the N.F.L.</p>
        <p>Feuer said that he ''would change that sentence; I'd eliminate it.'' Regarding high school players, he added: ''It's been shown that they don't seem to recover as fast. Period.''</p>
        <p>The paper, published in January 2005, was the seventh in a 13-part series that members of an N.F.L.-financed committee on concussions published in Neurosurgery from 2003 through last year. Its conclusion was the most controversial of several parts of those papers disputed by outside experts. At the annual meeting of the American College of Sports Medicine last week in New Orleans, where concussions were a prominent topic, about a dozen high school and college medical people almost unanimously said that the assertions in Neurosurgery had influenced the care that players at lower levels received, whether through the doctors who read it, Internet sites that linked to it or word of mouth.</p>
        <p>''That was a major disservice, and it continues to be an ongoing one in conversations I have with parents and coaches and players,'' Dr. Gerard Malanga, director of the New Jersey Sports Medicine Institute in Verona, and team physician for several high schools and colleges, said in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>''They will reference back to that article,'' Malanga said. ''It creates confusion when there's increasing clarity on the subject. They say what I tell them about it not being safe to go back in the same game is totally wrong, and they're backed by the N.F.L. So they go to a doctor who tells them what they want to hear. It's happened. Sure it's happened. And we remain the guys holding our breath that the kid doesn't get hurt again.''</p>
        <p>Arfken, an assistant professor in Wayne State's department of psychiatry and behavioral neurosciences, is not on the N.F.L.'s concussion committee but was asked to perform data analysis for the paper and therefore received a byline. She said the latest draft of the paper she was asked to proof -- which she showed The New York Times -- did not include the recommendation to high school and college physicians to consider the N.F.L.'s policies with their own players.</p>
        <p>She said that version merely cited previous outside studies emphasizing the difference between amateur and professional players, and that she was not aware of the addition regarding possible applicability of N.F.L. guidelines to amateurs until it was brought to her attention this week.</p>
        <p>''Our data is not about children, so there was no reason to make that extension to children,'' said Arfken, who acknowledged that she received a final galley proof with the insertion in question two months later but did not examine it carefully because she had never expected such a substantive change that late in the process. She said she was ''shocked and appalled'' that it was not specifically pointed out to her.</p>
        <p>''This is about the N.F.L.,'' she said. ''All these players were active. It was only regarding their time when they were active players. That's the only thing you can say about it. It's very dangerous to extrapolate data.''</p>
        <p>Casson and Viano, the paper's principal authors, said Arfken should have carefully examined the final proof for their changes and denied her claim that explicit notice of the passage's insertion was warranted. The editor of Neurosurgery, Dr. Michael Apuzzo of the Keck School of Medicine at the University of Southern California, did not return a phone call seeking comment.</p>
        <p>Regarding the paper's recommendations that doctors consider the N.F.L. findings in their dealings with high school and college players, Casson said: ''The fact that someone may misinterpret what we wrote in that paper does not mean that what we wrote in that paper was inaccurate, incorrect or shouldn't have been done. This paper was aimed at scientists and physicians. If people who are not scientists or physicians are misunderstanding it, then that is not the responsibility of those of us who wrote it.''</p>
        <p>Viano added, ''The sentence was meant to stimulate interest in studying this issue at the college and high school level, not to give guidelines.'' The paper's other author, Dr. Elliot Pellman of the Mount Sinai School of Medicine, was not available for comment. Pellman is the Jets' team physician.</p>
        <p>On behalf of the N.F.L., the league spokesman Greg Aiello said in a statement, ''We do not believe, and have never suggested, that the experience of N.F.L. players, or the return-to-play decisions of team physicians, should guide the management of concussions in high school or college players.''</p>
        <p>He added in a separate telephone interview that the league should not be considered an author of the paper: ''It was all produced by the doctors and the people involved -- the doctors, the scientists, the researchers. We didn't have anything to do with what they produced, other than paying for it.''</p>
        <p>The N.F.L. has long asserted the independence and objectivity of its concussion committee; a league news release last month regarding its guidelines separated the committee into eight non-N.F.L. members and six affiliated with the league.</p>
        <p>But at least four listed as non-N.F.L. members have ties to the league: Feuer is a paid consultant for the Indianapolis Colts who has worked on the sideline for almost every home game since 1984; Dr. Joseph Maroon is listed on the Pittsburgh Steelers' Web site as a member of its medical staff; Dr. Mark Lovell lists himself in marketing materials as the N.F.L.'s director of neuropsychology; and Casson has consulted for and taken occasional referrals from teams.</p>
        <p>Aiello said that the non-N.F.L. distinction was meant to indicate physicians who were not principal team doctors or trainers, and that the league would no longer list them separately.</p>
        <p>The criticisms made by Feuer and Arfken represent the first crack in a united front long presented by the N.F.L.'s concussion committee and its papers' authors. They will presumably add to the discussion at the league's June 19 conference in Chicago on concussion management, which will feature Commissioner Roger Goodell, medical representatives from every team, and some of the most ardent outside critics.</p>
        <p>Two other members of the league's concussion committee, who played no role in the paper in question, shared Feuer's and Arfken's concern that the passage regarding high school or college players' returning to a game after sustaining concussions could be misapplied.</p>
        <p>Dr. Joseph Waeckerle, the emergency doctor for the Kansas City Chiefs who is reviewing the paper for the June 19 meeting, said, ''My recommendation is that we write an editorial, or we write a piece, that explains very clearly that there is no external validity to this paper.''</p>
        <p>Lovell declined to comment about the paper, but did refer to his own published research that recommended heightened caution regarding amateur players' brain injuries.</p>
        <p>''If you read all my papers, I've been pretty clear about the fact that in children and in younger individuals, that I recommend taking people off the field when they're injured,'' Lovell said.</p>
        <p>Other committee members did not return messages or declined to comment.</p>
        <p>''I'm happy that more is coming of this,'' Feuer said. ''We set out to study a finite period of time. Look at what's coming from it -- continuous arguments. That's what's important. We're getting people's ire up. That's how you get good studies done. When people get critical of something, you look into it more.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
