<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LIVING IN/Jamaica Estates, Queens; Tudor Charm Loses Ground to McMansion Space</title>
    <meta content="10livi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/realestate/10livi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853606"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Living In | Jamaica Estates, Queens"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Queens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E3DC1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1646" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LIVING IN/Jamaica Estates, Queens; Tudor Charm Loses Ground to McMansion Space</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tudor Charm Loses Ground to McMansion Space</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. HUGHES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JAMAICA ESTATES, in east-central Queens, hugs a ridge whose steepness discouraged early settlement. Even after that changed, in the early 20th century, and the neighborhood became a car-friendly suburb, residents tended to preserve the trees, which by that point were old and numerous.</p>
        <p>They still are. Jamaica Estates' current tree population is 5,746, mostly maples, oaks and ashes, but also Kentucky coffee trees and Japanese snowbells, according to a recent census from the New York City Department of Parks and Recreation. (For perspective, the Midtown Manhattan ZIP code 10036 has 784 trees.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A recent census shows Jamaica Estates, Queens, has a healthy population of trees. But that may not last, as large lot sizes are making teardowns more frequent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JAMAICA ESTATES, in east-central Queens, hugs a ridge whose steepness discouraged early settlement. Even after that changed, in the early 20th century, and the neighborhood became a car-friendly suburb, residents tended to preserve the trees, which by that point were old and numerous.</p>
        <p>They still are. Jamaica Estates' current tree population is 5,746, mostly maples, oaks and ashes, but also Kentucky coffee trees and Japanese snowbells, according to a recent census from the New York City Department of Parks and Recreation. (For perspective, the Midtown Manhattan ZIP code 10036 has 784 trees.)</p>
        <p>But that abundance may finally be under threat, as new arrivals are chopping trees down to make way for large-scale additions, according to brokers and longtime residents. One in five buyers are going a step further, they say, and razing houses, especially the area's trademark Tudors, some adorned with witch's-hat towers and leaded-glass windows.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people that are new to the community don't respect the traditions,'' said Edward Morrill, who lives with his wife, Joyce, in a 2,000-square-foot home, built in 1935, that has three bedrooms, two and a half baths and a facade with a crosshatch of timbers. The home, which cost $62,000 in 1973, was recently assessed at $1.1 million, he said.</p>
        <p>''It's distasteful and insensitive to the history here and what we call the quality of life,'' Mr. Morrill said.</p>
        <p>What it is not, though, is illegal. Even under the neighborhood's R1 and R2 zoning, which requires generous space between residences, most lots in Jamaica Estates are ample enough to hold larger houses.</p>
        <p>Nor does the area have landmark status, the ultimate protection against teardowns in areas with restrictive zoning. In an unofficial referendum two years ago, officials said, the community clearly voiced resistance to becoming a landmark.</p>
        <p>Modern families sometimes desire more space than diminutive older homes offer, said Isaac Abraham, who in April closed on a 1940s brick colonial in Jamaica Estates, for $750,000. Its 2,300 square feet are insufficient for himself, his wife, Elita, and their three children, so the Abrahams are adding 700 square feet, including a bedroom and a basement. He said he expected the $350,000 renovation to increase the property's value to $1.6 million.</p>
        <p>''The homes need to be renovated for younger tastes,'' said Mr. Abraham, a jewelry importer in Manhattan whose previous address was in nearby Fresh Meadows, where he lived on one 1,500-square-foot floor of a two-family home.</p>
        <p>With its sidewalks and side yards, Jamaica Estates reminds him of his childhood home in Great Neck, N.Y., in nearby Nassau County.</p>
        <p>Another lure was the close-knit group of Jewish immigrants from Bukhara, Uzbekistan, his family homeland. (There are as many as 1,000 here and nearby, said Corey Bearak of the Northeast Queens Jewish Community Council.) Mr. Abraham's family is not fully unpacked, he said, but its religious life has found focus with two synagogues.</p>
        <p>And although the presence of construction equipment may concern some neighbors, he said, the plan is to retain original details like the slate roof and dentil moldings. ''The house has great craftsmanship,'' Mr. Abraham said. ''We are trying to keep as much as possible.''</p>
        <p>But while he and other residents ponder how extensively to alter their single-family homes, zoning issues in the southern part of the neighborhood have the potential for a much greater impact. The city seeks to loosen zoning on Hillside Avenue to allow more high-rises, as part of a 368-block master plan affecting several neighborhoods in the borough.</p>
        <p>Although many residents say Hillside's rough commercial strip needs revitalization, there is concern that adding thousands of residents could overwhelm the subway, the sewers and the schools.</p>
        <p>In March, Community Board 8, which covers Jamaica Estates, voted 36 to 0 to reject the zoning plan, echoing the opinion of the Jamaica Estates Civic Association, a 700-member group. ''We're concerned about the size of buildings overshadowing the private homes in Jamaica Estates,'' said Michael Bookbinder, the association's president and a 61-year resident. ''We actually think the area should be downzoned.''</p>
        <p>What You'll Find</p>
        <p>Though Hillside may be shabby, the area becomes well tended immediately after a turn onto Midland Parkway, which curves through Jamaica Estates' historic heart.</p>
        <p>This summer, Midland's grassy mall will undergo the final phase of a $500,000 renovation, restoring the cupola-topped gatehouse that doubles as a World War II memorial.</p>
        <p>Radiating off Midland are roads lined with detached single-family houses, which make up 80 percent of Jamaica Estates' stock. (The rest is mostly co-ops, clustered in prewar midrises along Wexford Terrace.)</p>
        <p>Because they went up as part of a planned community, the houses have many common traits. Most are set back on rises, reached by twisting stone stairs. Wooden front doors, many with large hinges and latches, recall the English countryside by way of J. R. R. Tolkien, so a passer-by might be forgiven for half-expecting to see a hobbit.</p>
        <p>But the area is not exclusively Tudor. Craftsman, Cape Cod and Mediterranean homes, detailed with terra cotta, add stylistic variety.</p>
        <p>As a microcosm of Queens, the neighborhood is ethnically diverse; 45 percent of its approximately 14,000 residents are foreign-born, according to the 2000 census. Bangladeshis make up 11 percent of the population, while Filipinos are 10 percent. Haitians represent 7 percent; Guyanese, 5 percent; Russians, 4 percent. Forty-three percent of residents identify themselves as white.</p>
        <p>What You'll Pay</p>
        <p>There are few bargains in Jamaica Estates, though homes at its edges, near Homelawn Street or in the Cunningham Park section, are generally more affordable, trading for $725,000, brokers say.</p>
        <p>The more coveted homes, along Henley and Aberdeen Roads, can fetch $2.25 million, and those with double lots are the ripest targets for teardowns, according to brokers.</p>
        <p>A typical property is a 1930s home on Dumfries Place that closed in April, with three bedrooms, an eat-in kitchen and a detached two-car garage, for $900,000, said Julia Shildkret, who has been selling homes in Jamaica Estates for two decades. At that price, she said, ''these aren't for first-time buyers, but people who have already sold a home.''</p>
        <p>Unlike the white-hot Forest Hills to the west, Jamaica Estates has seen its prices climb slowly in the last two years, about 5 percent a year. They are about 25 percent higher than they were in 2002, said David Yudell, the sales manager at Astor Brokerage.</p>
        <p>In Jamaica Estates' headiest year, 2005, homes routinely sold in two weeks. It may now take three months, Mr. Yudell said.</p>
        <p>As for tax, there's a world of difference between Jamaica Estates and towns in Nassau County, despite the proximity. Expect to pay about $5,000 a year on a Tudor here, not including city income tax, Ms. Shildkret said. Such a house in Garden City would cost $15,000 in taxes (including income tax).</p>
        <p>What to Do</p>
        <p>Cunningham Park, which brushes Jamaica Estates' eastern side, once held the Long Island Motor Parkway, the nation's first highway, according to Robert Miller, who gives walking tours of the area.</p>
        <p>The remaining 3.5 miles of the road are used today by joggers and strollers. Nearby, in late May, a tent for the Big Apple Circus towered beyond a baseball diamond.</p>
        <p>Close together on Hillside Avenue are places to savor Colombian plantains, halal Chinese food and pizza. Across the street is a deli decorated with a ''Watch Live Cricket'' sign.</p>
        <p>Union Turnpike has dry cleaners, pharmacies and a bookshop, as well as King Yum, a Polynesian restaurant with a decorative thatched roof over the bar. It offers karaoke on Wednesdays and Fridays, and its ''Five O'' special, with crab, mushrooms, and noodles, costs $17.50.</p>
        <p>The Schools</p>
        <p>The Holliswood School on Radnor Road teaches prekindergarten through fifth grade. Last year, on the annual state exams, 77 percent of third-graders were found proficient in English, 88 percent in math.</p>
        <p>Abigail Adams School, on 84th Avenue, offers kindergarten through fifth. Of third-graders, 94 percent were proficient in English, 89 percent in math.</p>
        <p>George J. Ryan Junior High School, on 175th Street in Fresh Meadows, enrolls more than 1,300 students, of whom 28 went on last year to the Bronx High School of Science, where admission requires a test. For students who stay close, there is Francis Lewis High School, which enrolls about 4,200. On the class of 2006's SAT, students averaged 471 on the verbal section, 536 on math and 463 on writing, versus 493 verbal, 510 math and 483 writing statewide.</p>
        <p>Eighty percent of seniors graduate, compared with 60 percent citywide, and 95 percent attend two- or four-year colleges, said Andrew Jacob, an Education Department spokesman. Greek, Hebrew and Korean are taught, and extracurricular offerings include a debate team, jazz band and Muslim student union. There are 13 varsity-level sports.</p>
        <p>Private Jewish and Catholic schools are also popular, as is the United Nations International School on Croydon Road, which instructs 190 students from kindergarten through Grade 8. For high school, many transfer to the school's Manhattan campus.</p>
        <p>The Commute</p>
        <p>The end of the line for the F train is at Hillside Avenue and 179th Street, and subways deliver riders to Midtown in 35 minutes.</p>
        <p>The QM1A bus runs locally along Union Turnpike, then express to Midtown from the intersection of Main Street. Another option is the Q46, which also follows Union and drops riders at a stop for the F and E trains on Queens Boulevard.</p>
        <p>The History</p>
        <p>Timothy L. Woodruff, New York's lieutenant governor under Theodore Roosevelt, developed Jamaica Estates in the early 1900s, billing the 503-acre community as a close-in version of Tuxedo Park, N.Y., the private enclave in Orange County.</p>
        <p>The developer most closely associated with the neighborhood today is probably Donald J. Trump, who grew up in a colonial on Midland.</p>
        <p>Going Forward</p>
        <p>Despite the new kosher market on Union and a few small stores on Hillside, the area could use a better selection of food stores.</p>
        <p>Living In | Jamaica Estates, Queens</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
