<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Like HBO, Connecticut Has Its Own Seedy Drama</title>
    <meta content="10towns" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/10towns.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853353"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OUR TOWNS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Threats and Threatening Messages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Threats and Threatening Messages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="online_producer">DeLuca, Louis C</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">The Sopranos (TV Program)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E3D9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="809" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Like HBO, Connecticut Has Its Own Seedy Drama</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Hartford, a Drama Nearly Ready for Cable</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER APPLEBOME</byline>
      <dateline>WATERBURY, Conn.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There's no good week for a politician to find himself apologizing for contacting a businessman alleged to have mob ties about knocking around an out-of-favor relative or to be explaining why he didn't report the kind offer of a McDonald's bag stuffed with $100 bills.</p>
        <p>But for Lou DeLuca, make that Senator Louis C. DeLuca, minority leader of the Connecticut State Senate, there cannot be a worse time than now, with everyone and his dog philosophizing about the last episode of ''The Sopranos,'' being broadcast tonight, and its approach to crime, punishment and family values.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For those wondering about the preternatural appeal of “The Sopranos,” it was instructive to change channels to watch Connecticut’s seamy contretemps of the past week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There's no good week for a politician to find himself apologizing for contacting a businessman alleged to have mob ties about knocking around an out-of-favor relative or to be explaining why he didn't report the kind offer of a McDonald's bag stuffed with $100 bills.</p>
        <p>But for Lou DeLuca, make that Senator Louis C. DeLuca, minority leader of the Connecticut State Senate, there cannot be a worse time than now, with everyone and his dog philosophizing about the last episode of ''The Sopranos,'' being broadcast tonight, and its approach to crime, punishment and family values.</p>
        <p>In the end, no one even got slapped around in Mr. DeLuca's plan, which never quite came to fruition. But for those still wondering about the preternatural appeal of ''The Sopranos,'' its too-close-for-comfort mix of the prosaic and the outrageous, of business as usual with people who aren't, it was instructive to change channels for a while to watch Connecticut's seamy little contretemps of the past week.</p>
        <p>Mr. DeLuca's bad hair week began when he was arrested on June 1 and charged with conspiring to threaten his granddaughter's husband, who he believed was abusing her. More specifically, he was accused of meeting with James Galante, a Danbury trash hauler, at Philip's Diner in Woodbury in 2005 to air his concerns. Mr. Galante has since been hit with a 117-count federal indictment charging that he was part of a mob-backed scheme to divide up Connecticut's trash-hauling industry.</p>
        <p>Worried that he was under surveillance, Mr. Galante passed Mr. DeLuca a note reading, ''Do you want me to have someone pay him a visit?'' Mr. DeLuca said, ''Yes,'' and provided him with the name of the lucky family member. Later, Mr. Galante made it clear to an associate that the visit was not intended for the purpose of discussing University of Connecticut basketball, and instead used a colorful, Sopranoesque term signifying a physical assault in expressing his wishes.</p>
        <p>Law officers learned of the plan and made their presence conspicuous enough to prevent the assault from occurring. Mr. DeLuca pleaded guilty Monday to a misdemeanor charge of ''threatening'' and said he went to Mr. Galante only after contacting the police three times and being told they could do nothing unless his granddaughter pressed charges.</p>
        <p>''I am taking responsibility for my misguided actions in trying to protect my family,'' he said. ''I am hoping to now put this matter behind me and my family.''</p>
        <p>That seemed to be the feeling initially for most members of both parties at the legislature, where Mr. DeLuca, a 73-year-old Republican from Woodbury, is viewed as a straight shooter, a good guy, a trusted member of the club. Gov. M. Jodi Rell, who had made fighting corruption a key issue, was among those offering support.</p>
        <p>But, alas, it wasn't that simple. First there was material in an affidavit presented with the case in which Mr. DeLuca repeatedly expressed his willingness to do whatever he could to watch Mr. Galante's back and help him at the Capitol. (Anything that could hurt Mr. Galante, he told an informant, ''I'll try to blunt it as best I can.'')</p>
        <p>He also acknowledged receipt of a bribe offer that he turned down, citing the fear it could be traced, but that he did not report to authorities. And, according to the affidavit, he apparently gave false information to the F.B.I. when he was first contacted about his meeting with Mr. Galante.</p>
        <p>Then, if there were not enough characters in the episode, the would-be assault victim, one Mark Colella, 40, popped up outside the Waterbury courthouse where Mr. DeLuca entered his plea to pronounce himself ''100 percent Sicilian'' and to make it clear he was not afraid of anyone, including Mr. Galante.</p>
        <p>''Just make sure they bring a lot of bullets,'' he announced. He also said he had not abused anyone.</p>
        <p>Next up was the Waterbury police chief, Neil O'Leary, who said that Mr. DeLuca never told him anything about his daughter being abused and that state law requires investigations of abuse whether or not the alleged victim comes forward, so Mr. DeLuca had plenty of options other than the mob. (Mr. DeLuca stands by his account.)</p>
        <p>Finally, Mr. DeLuca held a press conference on Thursday, pleaded guilty to stupidity in meeting with Mr. Galante and said he would not quit the Senate, though it seems clear there is pressure for him, at the least, to give up his leadership post.</p>
        <p>It's not ''The Sopranos.'' No blood. No gore. Still, in a state that has been up there with New Jersey in political corruption, it's a reminder that HBO is not the only place where the mob is alive and well and where more than a few people have a hard time figuring out what's right and what's wrong and just how far personal loyalty should go.</p>
        <p>OUR TOWNS E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
