<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Semiretired Martin Still Makes His Moves</title>
    <meta content="10martin" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/sports/othersports/10martin.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853342"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Martin, Mark</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E7D9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="956" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Semiretired Martin Still Makes His Moves</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Semiretired Martin Still Makes His Moves</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <dateline>LONG POND, Pa., June 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mark Martin, the 48-year-old stock-car driver with snowy hair and a flock of crow's feet perched outside his eyes, is semiretired and plans to stay that way. But he is not exactly puttering into the sunset on a golf cart.</p>
        <p>When Nascar docked Kurt Busch 100 points Friday as a result of an altercation with Tony Stewart during a race on Monday in Dover, Del., Martin rose one place, to 11th, in the Nascar Nextel Cup standings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even though he has not participated in 3 of the 13 races that have been run this season, Mark Martin has put himself in position to qualify for one of the 12 spots in the Chase for the Nextel Cup.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mark Martin, the 48-year-old stock-car driver with snowy hair and a flock of crow's feet perched outside his eyes, is semiretired and plans to stay that way. But he is not exactly puttering into the sunset on a golf cart.</p>
        <p>When Nascar docked Kurt Busch 100 points Friday as a result of an altercation with Tony Stewart during a race on Monday in Dover, Del., Martin rose one place, to 11th, in the Nascar Nextel Cup standings.</p>
        <p>It was the second time in four days he moved up in the standings. Martin finished seventh at Dover to move to 12th from 14th. Martin was in 15th place before he finished 11th in the Coca-Cola 600 at Lowe's Motor Speedway on May 27.</p>
        <p>Even though he has not participated in 3 of the 13 races that have been run this season, Martin has put himself in position to qualify for one of the 12 spots in the 10-race Chase for the Nextel Cup at the end of the season. Over all, he plans to compete in 24 of 36 races.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to race for the driver's championship,'' Martin said Friday as he sat outside his hauler awaiting Sunday's Pocono 500.</p>
        <p>But Martin has never won a driver's championship in Nascar's top series. He has finished second four times, most recently in 2002, and he qualified for the Chase the past three years.</p>
        <p>Now that he has entered the part-time phase of his career, it is not as if he is fading away. He lost the Daytona 500 to Kevin Harvick by a nose on Feb. 18. Then, on May 16, Martin announced that he would add three races to his schedule, two of them before the Chase field is determined. He is scheduled to skip 5 of the next 13 races, but he can always change his mind.</p>
        <p>''I can if I wanted to,'' he said. ''But I don't.''</p>
        <p>What he can do is take points from other drivers by running well on a schedule that for him is not too hard. Asked what he enjoyed most about his part-time schedule, Martin said: ''Being off. The schedule they have today is overkill.''</p>
        <p>Martin moved from Roush Racing to a team owned by Bobby Ginn in the off-season because Ginn promised Martin he could run part time. Ginn's team has been one of the pleasant surprises of an otherwise drab season dominated by the Hendrick Racing combination of Jeff Gordon and Jimmie Johnson.</p>
        <p>''It's an outstanding accomplishment by a team I've come to know as being equal to, or on a par with, the best in the garage,'' Martin said of Ginn's team.</p>
        <p>Martin has been provided with a powerful black Chevrolet that he has driven to six top-10 finishes. Martin, in fact, has not finished lower than 17th in his 10 races. If he wants to add races, he will have a fast car to drive.</p>
        <p>''He says he's not going to do it,'' said Matt Kenseth, his former Roush teammate, who is third in the standings.</p>
        <p>''But if he's sitting 12th in the standings, and he needs to add a race to make it, I think it would be awfully difficult for him not to do it.''</p>
        <p>Martin is a smooth driver, and as a result is well respected, which makes him a little more impervious to most of the histrionics that develop among younger drivers -- the latest example being Busch.</p>
        <p>Busch, the only Dodge driver in the top 12, lost 100 points and was fined $100,000 for parking his car next to Stewart's on pit road and chewing him out after the two were in an accident at Dover. Busch fell to 17th in the standings from 11th.</p>
        <p>''Safety on pit road can't be compromised, and I understand that,'' Busch said Friday.</p>
        <p>Martin took Busch's place in the standings, with Martin Truex Jr., the winner of the Dover race, moving to 12th.</p>
        <p>Martin will start from the middle of the pack in the Pocono 500 but should be a factor: he has finished second six times in 40 top-series races at Pocono.</p>
        <p>Johnson suggested that Martin could become a trendsetter. Other veteran drivers have recently tried part-time schedules, but their cars were not fast enough to deliver consistent results. Martin is three positions ahead of a famous full-time driver, Dale Earnhardt Jr., in the standings.</p>
        <p>''To see team owners willing to go that route, it inspires Jeff, it inspires me and guys who don't want to quit racing,'' Johnson said, referring to Gordon.</p>
        <p>''After 15 or 20 years you want to have a couple weekends off here and there. I think Mark's doing a great job of leading that brigade.''</p>
        <p>Martin is not eager to leave the part-time brigade. He said his schedule was set. He plans to drive next weekend at Michigan, then will skip races in Sonoma, Calif., and Loudon, N.H., before driving in four consecutive races, including another at Pocono on Aug. 5.</p>
        <p>Tension has begun to mount now that the midway point of the 26-race portion of the season that determines the playoff qualifiers has been reached. Even some drivers who are among the top 12 have begun talking about what it will take to make the Chase.</p>
        <p>''We've got to keep stuff from falling off our car,'' Harvick said, smiling.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Martin drives on, carefree. He loves racing, and he loves racing even more when he is in 24 races instead of 36. He has raced enough to know what to do when he gets in a car. He does not need refresher courses after a week or two off.</p>
        <p>''I've been racing for 35 years,'' he said, laughing. ''I don't need any more practice.''</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
