<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At the Movies</title>
    <meta content="10artsnjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/10artsnj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853591"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Newark Museum</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genocchio, Benjamin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hopper, Edward (1882-1967)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Newark Museum</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hopper, Edward</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DD1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="786" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At the Movies</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At the Movies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN GENOCCHIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genocchio, Benjamin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Benjamin Genocchio reviews exhibition of works by Edward Hopper on view at Newark Museum; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A mouthwatering curiosity is what the viewer takes away from Edward Hopper's painting ''The Sheridan Theatre'' (1937), the subject of a splendid little exhibition at the Newark Museum. The painting depicts a disquieting scene of a woman alone at the back of a movie theater, watched by two figures, one of them an usher. Is she waiting for friends, or has she simply arrived late? We don't know, for her behavior doesn't fit with any typical pattern of moviegoing.</p>
        <p>The pleasures of this painting are numerous, from the ambiguity of the central figure to the stylized, evocative architecture and graceful shifts of lighting in the balcony. It is one of Hopper's best movie-theater paintings, which makes it all the more surprising that it wasn't included in the marvelous Hopper retrospective showing at the Boston Museum of Fine Arts before heading to Washington and Chicago. Perhaps they simply overlooked it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Edward Hopper’s painting “The Sheridan Theatre” (1937), is the subject of an exhibition at the Newark Museum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A mouthwatering curiosity is what the viewer takes away from Edward Hopper's painting ''The Sheridan Theatre'' (1937), the subject of a splendid little exhibition at the Newark Museum. The painting depicts a disquieting scene of a woman alone at the back of a movie theater, watched by two figures, one of them an usher. Is she waiting for friends, or has she simply arrived late? We don't know, for her behavior doesn't fit with any typical pattern of moviegoing.</p>
        <p>The pleasures of this painting are numerous, from the ambiguity of the central figure to the stylized, evocative architecture and graceful shifts of lighting in the balcony. It is one of Hopper's best movie-theater paintings, which makes it all the more surprising that it wasn't included in the marvelous Hopper retrospective showing at the Boston Museum of Fine Arts before heading to Washington and Chicago. Perhaps they simply overlooked it.</p>
        <p>Lucky they did, for it is the centerpiece of this engrossing show probing Hopper's love of the movies. A cinéaste, Hopper once remarked to a friend: ''When I don't feel in the mood for painting I go to the movies for a week or more. I go on a regular movie binge!'' His favorite movie theater was the Sheridan in the West Village of Manhattan, not far from a townhouse on Washington Square where he and his wife and model, the artist Josephine Nivison, lived on the top floor for most of their lives.</p>
        <p>Calm, silent and luminous, ''The Sheridan Theatre'' is installed on the main wall as you enter. It oozes strangeness. To the left and right of it are a selection of preparatory sketches borrowed from the Hopper archive at the Whitney Museum of American Art in Manhattan. This is the first time that they have been shown alongside the finished painting. They are typical of Hopper sketches, showing how he liked to isolate areas of a composition for individual detailed studies. Some are finished; others are extremely crude and abstract.</p>
        <p>Also on loan from the Whitney is one of the artist's ledger books (two more are in the Boston show), in which he meticulously recorded with sketches and notes all the paintings he completed and sold. It is open to Page 19, where there is a small pen-and-ink sketch of ''The Sheridan Theatre'' followed by commentary on the finished work and an abbreviated inventory of the paints, brushes and canvas the artist used. At the bottom is the price, $900, and a note that the artist offered a one-third discount to the Newark Museum, which bought it in 1940. It was a shrewd purchase, to say the least.</p>
        <p>The period from about 1925 to 1950 is considered by most art scholars to be the time of Hopper's greatest work. It is also when the movies began to have a profound impact on his painting. Not only did he paint several pictures of the inside of lush old movie theaters, but he also mimicked early cinema in his compositions -- the angles, lighting, and color schemes. Take ''Nighthawks'' (1942), his most famous painting, part of the retrospective in Boston, with its theatrical lighting, stagelike feel, and incongruous grouping of night owls at a diner.</p>
        <p>It is no surprise that ''The Sheridan Theatre'' is infused with cinematic suggestion, coming in the middle of this period in Hopper's career. For starters, it is all about composition, from the stylized setting to the tight cropping that focuses the viewer's gaze on the woman. Then there is her appearance: her voluptuous figure, blond hair and casual sexuality, reminding you of Mae West, who by the late 1930s was already a Hollywood star.</p>
        <p>An additional grouping of early paintings and drawings by Hopper on movie themes is a nice touch, showing us that he had a lifelong interest in the cinema, even if it didn't begin to affect his work until later. Then there is a room of paintings on movie themes by his contemporaries, showing that Hopper was not the only one fascinated by cinema. A surprising number of modern artists painted theater and film scenes.</p>
        <p>It is disappointing that the show doesn't come with a catalog. (There are text panels and a listening station with recorded information.) This work is among the museum's treasures, with visitors coming here specifically to see it. Its mysteriousness is what makes it alluring, but the experience of viewing it might also benefit from some sort of explanation. Then again, the lack of one frees the viewer to create a narrative of his own.</p>
        <p>''At the Movies: Edward Hopper's 'The Sheridan Theatre,' '' Newark Museum, 49 Washington Street, Newark, through Aug. 19. Information: (973) 596-6550 or online at www.newarkmuseum.org.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
