<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Can Blogs Become A Big Source of Jobs?</title>
    <meta content="10starts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/business/yourmoney/10starts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853684"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="JOBS: FRESH STARTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blogs and Blogging (Internet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blogs and Blogging (Internet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E2D61F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="987" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Can Blogs Become A Big Source of Jobs?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Can Blogs Become a Big Source of Jobs?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA WHITAKER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEARCH ''blog,'' ''blogger'' or ''blogging'' on the Indeed.com job board and more than 13,000 jobs come up. But narrow the search to job titles containing those words and the opportunities dwindle to just over 50.</p>
        <p>The bottom line is this: while running a Web log is a skill that more and more employers seek in their employees, finding full-time work in that world is still unusual.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>While running a Web log is a skill that more and more employers seek in their employees, finding full-time work in that world is still unusual.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEARCH ''blog,'' ''blogger'' or ''blogging'' on the Indeed.com job board and more than 13,000 jobs come up. But narrow the search to job titles containing those words and the opportunities dwindle to just over 50.</p>
        <p>The bottom line is this: while running a Web log is a skill that more and more employers seek in their employees, finding full-time work in that world is still unusual.</p>
        <p>Blogs, short for Web logs, tend to be informal journals that track a subject on a regular basis. The topics are varied, and personal observations are often included. But as blogs have matured, they have also become a communications tool within companies, from the C.E.O. on down.</p>
        <p>As blogs gain in popularity, demand is growing for employees who can write them or have the technical expertise to support them. A few Web sites, including ProBlogger and Performancing, cater to bloggers and include job opportunities.</p>
        <p>''There's almost an ecosystem of jobs that have emerged around blogs,'' said Paul Forster, chief executive at Indeed.com, a job search engine with postings from more than 5,000 sources. ''It's an emerging area where there are many more opportunities related to the blog rather than being a dedicated blog writer.''</p>
        <p>For example, a posting by the search firm S4 Partners in the San Francisco Bay Area recently sought someone with an understanding of the world of blogs and the software used to support them. The goal of the company was to find a blog administrator, to establish the blog and to run it.</p>
        <p>''This was our first search of this kind,'' said Chris Shaw, president of S4 Partners, who would identify the client only as a well-known company in the high-tech sector. ''We had to do some unconventional searching. This isn't just a blogger. This is someone who knows how to set up the technology and understands the whole environment.''</p>
        <p>The person they ultimately found was Bill Lazar, a blogger and former programmer. ''This would be my first full-time job focusing on supporting the content of another blogger,'' said Mr. Lazar, noting that the job was still in negotiations. ''To get paid to work on blogs and the related technology would be great.'' He declined to discuss what the job would pay.</p>
        <p>According to information provided by Indeed, the average salary for jobs with some version of ''blog'' in the job title averages $53,000. But for writers trying to eke out an existence as a blogger for a business, pay is typically much more modest.</p>
        <p>At b5media, a global blog network out of Toronto with about 200 blogs on subjects ranging from sports and entertainment to news and technology, writers work on a contract basis. They are paid a fee of only $100 to $250 a month, based on their experience and the quality of their work. The real money can come from bonuses that are tied to the traffic their blogs receive.</p>
        <p>Including bonuses, one popular entertainment writer, who is also an editor, makes in the neighborhood of six figures a year, said Jeremy Wright, chief executive of the network. The writer's Lindsay Lohan site is consistently among the most popular, pulling in about 500,000 visitors a month.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wright said that it was far more common for full-time bloggers on the site to make $40,000 to $60,000 a year. But even that kind of pay may be hard for other bloggers to achieve.</p>
        <p>Raj Dash, a Toronto blogger who hires bloggers and posts opportunities for them on his RajDash site, has five jobs listed. For his own blog, Chameleon Integration, which covers technology and the Internet, bloggers who write two posts a day, with up to 40 posts a month of 150 to 250 words each, receive $220 a month, or $5.50 a posting.</p>
        <p>If pursuing a job as a blogger seems financially precarious, having blogging skills doesn't hurt when it comes to looking for work -- particularly in publishing, marketing, public relations and the news media.</p>
        <p>Steve Rubel, who joined Edelman, a public relations firm, in February 2006, said his blog Micro Persuasion helped him land the job. The blog, which he started in 2004, focuses on how technology is changing marketing and public relations.</p>
        <p>As part of the me2revolution group at Edelman in New York, he specializes in helping clients use new media as part of their communications. ''That blog helped me get my current job,'' he said, noting that Edelman even bought the name, which had been trademarked at his previous job. ''Through all the work and research I do writing the blog, I know where technology and people's habits are going.''</p>
        <p>He said he must be careful about what he writes on his own blog, which has about 45,000 daily readers, to ensure that he is not perceived as speaking for the firm and that he does not favor or offend any of its clients.</p>
        <p>''It's a complex relationship,'' he said. ''You have to walk that tightrope and not get hung, but since I started writing that blog, my career has taken off like a rocket ship.''</p>
        <p>Robert Scoble, whose Scobleizer technology blog is among the most well-known, said that more people -- including those at the top -- were blogging as part of their jobs with major corporations, from I.B.M. to General Motors to Southwest Airlines.</p>
        <p>''There certainly are more and more people who are doing blogging work, at least as part of their job,'' Mr. Scoble said. He noted that PodTech, an online technology and video entertainment network where he is vice president for media development and has his own show, hires bloggers, but not just because they can blog.</p>
        <p>''You need something else that comes to the table with you,'' he said. ''A good blogger is passionate and authoritative on something. If you're not passionate about what you're communicating, you're going to be missing something.''</p>
        <p>Fresh Starts is a monthly column about emerging jobs and job trends.</p>
        <p>JOBS: FRESH STARTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
