<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Clara and Leo Lost Their Spots</title>
    <meta content="10wyat" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/arts/design/10wyat.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853484"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Getty, J Paul, Museum (Los Angeles)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wyatt, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oudry, Jean-Baptiste</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Getty, J Paul, Museum</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E4DF1E30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1280" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Clara and Leo Lost Their Spots</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">How Clara and Leo Lost Their Spots</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WYATT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wyatt, Edward</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on show Oudry's Painted Menagerie at J Paul Getty Museum in Los Angeles, which features Jean-Baptiste Oudry's paintings of animals, some life-size; painstaking restoration process by Getty of three paintings that had gone unseen for 100 years described; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANYONE who has brushed the dust off a faded painting in a grandparent's attic or eyed a weather-beaten frame at a flea market has probably had the fantasy: Perhaps this is a forgotten masterpiece, neglected but immensely valuable, long hidden away and simply waiting to be uncovered.</p>
        <p>While such discoveries do occur, rarely do they happen within the walls of a museum. But in 2001, when three curators from the J. Paul Getty Museum traveled to the Staatliches Museum Schwerin, in what was formerly East Germany, they learned of three 18th-century masterpieces by the French portraitist Jean-Baptiste Oudry, paintings that had gone unseen in public for more than 100 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Getty restores to life a lion and rhino long hidden away in Germany.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANYONE who has brushed the dust off a faded painting in a grandparent's attic or eyed a weather-beaten frame at a flea market has probably had the fantasy: Perhaps this is a forgotten masterpiece, neglected but immensely valuable, long hidden away and simply waiting to be uncovered.</p>
        <p>While such discoveries do occur, rarely do they happen within the walls of a museum. But in 2001, when three curators from the J. Paul Getty Museum traveled to the Staatliches Museum Schwerin, in what was formerly East Germany, they learned of three 18th-century masterpieces by the French portraitist Jean-Baptiste Oudry, paintings that had gone unseen in public for more than 100 years.</p>
        <p>Among the treasures was ''Rhinoceros,'' a life-size portrait of an Indian rhinoceros popularly known as Clara that toured Europe for 17 years in the mid-1700s. At the height of her celebrity Clara drew thousands of spectators, mixed with royalty and inspired trends in art and fashion.</p>
        <p>Now, after five years of painstaking restoration in the Getty's conservation studios, two of the three paintings are on display through Sept. 2 at the Getty Museum as part of ''Oudry's Painted Menagerie.'' The exhibition will travel to the Museum of Fine Arts, Houston, in October and then to Schwerin, in northeast Germany, next spring. In addition to ''Rhinoceros'' (1749) and ''Lion'' (1752), a second work that had been heavily damaged and stored for more than a century in the German museum's back rooms, the exhibition includes nine other Oudry portraits of animals, most from Louis XV's menagerie at Versailles, each of them an acclaimed example of this artist's gift for realistic interpretation.</p>
        <p>Equally impressive as the works are the two restorations that have been performed by Mark Leonard, conservator of paintings, and his colleagues at the Getty, who spent years weaving threads into the canvas to repair tears, removing grimy varnish and replacing missing spots of paint.</p>
        <p>''We are extremely proud to be able to bring these paintings back to the public,'' Kornelia von Berswordt-Wallrabe, the director of the Staatliches Museum Schwerin, said in an interview here, a few days after the Getty exhibition's opening last month. ''When I came to the museum in 1993, I didn't know of these paintings. But my colleagues knew, and when I saw them, I immediately knew things were wrong.''</p>
        <p>But the ability to restore the paintings was hard to come by, even after German reunification. Not until 2001 did the opportunity come, and it arrived serendipitously.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Leonard explained it during a recent tour of Oudry's works in the Getty galleries, representatives of the museum and its parent, the J. Paul Getty Trust, had been invited by the Kulturstiftung der Länder, a Berlin conservancy organization, to tour several former East German museums to discuss possible partnerships in painting conservation.</p>
        <p>Near the end of the March 2001 visit at the museum in Schwerin, two works were mentioned almost in passing: life-size Oudry portraits of a lion and a rhinoceros, related to the museum's other animal portraits by that artist. The paintings were so deep in storage that they were not viewed that day, but the visitors were intrigued, Mr. Leonard said.</p>
        <p>Over the next several months conservators at the Schwerin museum took the paintings out, unrolled them and reported back to the Getty on their condition, along with that of a third Oudry painting, of a tiger. The Getty conservators returned in December 2001, and, Mr. Leonard said, they were awestruck by what they saw.</p>
        <p>All of the paintings were heavily damaged. The rhinoceros canvas was missing large chunks at one end and had numerous small tears in the fabric. The lion canvas was further damaged, having been folded in half along its center seam, then rolled up and crushed along one side of the roll. A result was a regular series of creases across the canvas where the paint had flaked away. The third painting, the tiger, had a large water stain, apparently resulting from a burst pipe; that canvas is still undergoing restoration at the Getty studio and is not part of the current exhibition.</p>
        <p>Both Ms. von Berswordt-Wallrabe and Mr. Leonard said that while the Schwerin and nearby museums had capable conservators, the studio space there was not large enough to allow the paintings -- which measure as much as 15 feet in width -- to be laid out for work.</p>
        <p>The lion was sent to the Getty first, in April 2002, and Mr. Leonard's crew began an intensive yearlong process of repairing tears, removing and replacing old patches and reinforcing seams. Microscopic analysis of the surface of the painting showed at least two layers of varnish; one turned out to be relatively easy to remove, significantly lightening the painting's dark overtones.</p>
        <p>Next came analysis of the paint and the primer used on the canvas, both of which were replicated as closely as possible and then applied to the appropriate spots on the canvas. For much of that work, years into the project, special easels were constructed to allow the paintings to be displayed upright, so that conservators could work on both sides at once.</p>
        <p>A year into the restoration of the lion canvas the rhinoceros painting arrived and began undergoing a similar regimen. Because the rhinoceros painting, at roughly 10 feet by 15 feet, is about one-third larger than the lion portrait, a bridge had to be constructed to allow conservators to reach the center of the canvas while it was laid out on a table.</p>
        <p>Some of the final steps in the restoration were performed last January in a public gallery at the Getty, both to make use of natural light and to allow museumgoers to see the process firsthand. A riveting description of the entire process is included in an essay by Mr. Leonard in the exhibition's catalog. The process was also filmed for a documentary by the Oscar-winning director William Friedkin, copies of which are being sold by the museum. (Mr. Leonard appeared to have kept his necktie on throughout most of the restoration process.)</p>
        <p>While the restorations were being done, other departments of the Getty were working on assembling the exhibition. Mary Morton and Scott Schaefer, associate curator and curator of paintings, led efforts to bring together not only the Schwerin museum's other Oudry portraits but also a set of drawings and studies by the painter from various collections.</p>
        <p>And then there is what Mr. Schaefer refers to as ''rhinocerotica,'' ephemera inspired by the Clara-mania that gripped much of Europe, and particularly Paris, as Clara toured the continent until her death in England in 1758. When Clara arrived in Rotterdam in 1741, a live rhinoceros had not been seen on the European continent for more than 150 years, according to the Getty's research. In some ways a rhinoceros was considered as mythical as the unicorn. (Even the well-informed were mistaken about some features: Albrecht Dürer's 1515 wood-block print of a rhino included a horn in the middle of the creature's back.)</p>
        <p>While the peripheral accouterments are amusing, they do not detract from the paintings, particularly when Ms. Morton reminds a viewer, as she did recently, ''You're the first members of the public to see these paintings since the 1870s.''</p>
        <p>Given the extreme lengths required to accomplish the restorations, the Getty officials made certain that they studied one key detail: The restored paintings will be able to fit standing up in the belly of a 747 cargo jet, meaning that when they are returned to Germany via Houston, it will not be necessary to fold or roll them up again.</p>
        <p>Oudry's Painted Menagerie  J. Paul Getty Museum  Getty Center Drive, Los Angeles; getty.edu. Through Sept. 2</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
