<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BEHIND THE WHEEL/2007 Honda CR-V; A Pop Performer Starts to Rock</title>
    <meta content="10AUTO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/automobiles/autoreviews/10AUTO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853594"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Behind the Wheel | 2007 Honda CR-V"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Honda Motor Company Limited</org>
        <org class="online_producer">J D Power &amp; Associates</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DD1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1261" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BEHIND THE WHEEL/2007 Honda CR-V; A Pop Performer Starts to Rock</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Pop Performer Starts to Rock</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHERYL JENSEN</byline>
      <dateline>EASTON, N.H.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HONDA'S original CR-V of 1997 helped to establish a new type of vehicle, the compact sport utility wagon, by combining common-sense packaging with the brand's solid reputation. The first CR-V was a huge success, even if it had all the charisma of a cinder block. Actually, it resembled a cinder block.</p>
        <p>Back then, the CR-V's competition pretty much started and ended with the Toyota RAV4, which had been introduced in 1996. Ten years later, the 2007 CR-V finds itself in a competitive free-for-all, with 20 or so cute utes wrestling for customers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The CR-V’s style has graduated from frumpy to sleek, and its handling is sharp enough that even a fussy driver can enjoy a stint at the wheel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HONDA'S original CR-V of 1997 helped to establish a new type of vehicle, the compact sport utility wagon, by combining common-sense packaging with the brand's solid reputation. The first CR-V was a huge success, even if it had all the charisma of a cinder block. Actually, it resembled a cinder block.</p>
        <p>Back then, the CR-V's competition pretty much started and ended with the Toyota RAV4, which had been introduced in 1996. Ten years later, the 2007 CR-V finds itself in a competitive free-for-all, with 20 or so cute utes wrestling for customers.</p>
        <p>This market segment, so popular now, didn't even exist 11 years ago, noted Tom Libby, automotive analyst for J. D. Power &amp; Associates. Small crossover wagons now account for 8.5 percent of the nation's light vehicle sales, and they continue to grow.</p>
        <p>This competitive pressure helps to explain the drastic changes Honda has made to its redesigned 2007 CR-V. The little wagon's style has graduated from frumpy to sleek, and its handling is now sharp enough that even a fussy driving enthusiast can enjoy a stint at the wheel. Nor has the CR-V lost the practicality that made it one of America's favorite small utilities for nearly a decade.</p>
        <p>This new approach seems to be working. So far in 2007, the CR-V has outsold all crossovers and sport utilities, regardless of size or price, according to J. D. Power.</p>
        <p>Prices start at $21,195 for the nicely equipped LX base model with two-wheel drive. (Add $1,200 for all-wheel drive.) After that comes the midlevel EX, the EX-L (with leather and XM Satellite radio) and the EX-L with a navigation system -- the first offered in a CR-V. A Honda spokesman said prices have increased around 1 percent, or just a bit more, depending on model.</p>
        <p>This year, for the first time, Honda is building CR-Vs in North America, at East Liberty, Ohio, in addition to a plant in Japan. Quality doesn't seem to have suffered; last week, J. D. Power said that the CR-V ranked highest in its class in initial quality.</p>
        <p>My CR-V test car was a top-of-the-line EX-L with all-wheel drive and a navigation system. This $28,595 model also had a rearview camera and a six-CD changer.</p>
        <p>The lens of the back-up camera tends to get easily covered by dirt, but that's not all bad: once you get out of the car to clean it off, there is no longer any mystery about what is behind you. So from that standpoint it works quite well.</p>
        <p>In addition to the more rounded body style, the larger 17-inch wheels -- now standard -- give the CR-V a little more attitude. It also has a little more punch, thanks to an additional 10 horsepower, bringing the rating up to 166 while the curb weight remains about the same. But the big improvement is in the handling, which has gone from simply competent to actually entertaining. Credit the re-engineered, stronger body; a lower center of gravity that improves stability and responsiveness; and a reworked suspension, which nicely controls body lean on turns.</p>
        <p>It isn't until we take a right turn onto Route 118, the Sawyer Highway in the White Mountain National Forest, that we discover the CR-V's unpleasant side. On that road's broken surface, the stiffness that makes the CR-V fun to drive on tight curves becomes a bit uncomfortable.</p>
        <p>The new model also represents a step back for drivers who like to shift for themselves. Last year, the midlevel CR-V EX with all-wheel drive offered a five-speed manual transmission; this year, a five-speed automatic is the only gearbox.</p>
        <p>To its credit, the automatic offers smooth upshifts and is quick to respond. Under hard acceleration, it doesn't upshift too quickly -- going well past 5,000 r.p.m. before surrendering to a higher gear. The four-cylinder engine is strong and sounds good when pushed hard. On the test vehicle, however, there was a drone and vibration around 1,500 r.p.m.</p>
        <p>Normally, the all-wheel-drive model operates in front-wheel drive until the system senses front-wheel slippage. Honda says the system has been improved so that more power shifts more quickly to the rear.</p>
        <p>The old CR-V's side-hinged swinging tailgate has been replaced by a liftgate. Because the spare is now inside under the cargo floor instead of mounted on the tailgate, the new CR-V is three inches shorter, making it fit better into cramped garages.</p>
        <p>Inside, my big gripe with the CR-V concerns the finishes. There is a lot of hard, cheap-looking plastic. So while the interior is functional, it is not very handsome. Also, the seat materials have a bargain-basement look unless you ante up for leather. The new Hyundai Santa Fe has a much richer-looking interior.</p>
        <p>On the plus side, all CR-V's come with the same high level of safety equipment. This means six air bags, including side bags for the front seats along with side curtains to protect heads in both the front and back; antilock brakes; electronic stability control to help prevent skids; and active head restraints to minimize injuries to the neck in a rear collision. The new model is a ''top safety pick'' by the Insurance Institute for Highway Safety, a recognition for vehicles that protected passengers best in front, side and rear crash tests.</p>
        <p>The CR-V is 1.4 inches wider than before, which permits more hip room. Honda says the seats are more supportive, but I found them rather hard. If you don't bring your own rear-end padding, you aren't getting any. Also the bottom cushions are short, depriving even average-sized occupants of thigh support.</p>
        <p>There is plenty of rear legroom, and because the floor under the back seat is flat, three adults really do fit there. The rear seats slide forward and back six inches to allow an easy tradeoff between cargo space and passenger legroom. The rear seat bottoms are split 60/40, and for 2007 the seatbacks are split 40/20/40, providing a center pass-through for long items like skis.</p>
        <p>Each of the three seatback sections can be individually reclined. But to do this, you must pull a plastic ring attached to a cord, and this is almost impossible to do while sitting in the seat.</p>
        <p>The CR-V can carry more than many of its rivals, including the Ford Escape and Hyundai Tucson. The rear seatbacks can be folded and the seats will tumble forward without removing the head restraints. This more than doubles cargo space to a respectable 73 cubic feet.</p>
        <p>At 65 m.p.h., there was a fair amount of wind noise, along with road noise from the rear compartment. The rather thick rearmost roof pillars seriously reduce visibility.</p>
        <p>Comparison shoppers might think the CR-V comes up short in a couple of areas. For instance, it does not offer an optional third-row seat, which is becoming common in smallish wagons. Nor can you get a V-6 in addition to the in-line 4; the RAV4, Hyundai Tucson and Ford Escape all offer a choice of 4 or V-6.</p>
        <p>But a practical analysis might suggest that neither a third row nor a V-6 is necessary. Such seats are often so cramped as to be unusable, and Honda's peppy 4-cylinder engine (which also delivers 28 m.p.g. on the highway) needs no alternative.</p>
        <p>So the CR-V is a great all-round choice, at least if you can overlook its interior. Given the sales figures, that appears not to bother a lot of people. ''They are basically selling them as soon as they come off the truck,'' said Mr. Libby of J. D. Power.</p>
        <p>INSIDE TRACK: A practical Honda gets a dose of charisma.</p>
        <p>Behind the Wheel | 2007 Honda CR-V</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
