<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From a Pandora's Box, a Spilling of Dreams</title>
    <meta content="10artsliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/10artsli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853531"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nassau County Museum of Art</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genocchio, Benjamin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Nassau County Museum of Art</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E5DF1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From a Pandora's Box, a Spilling of Dreams</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From a Pandora’s Box, a Spilling of Dreams</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN GENOCCHIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genocchio, Benjamin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Benjamin Genocchio reviews exhibit of Surrealist art at Nassau County Museum of Art; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even today, Surrealism, which is nearly a century old, captures the imagination of audiences with surprising force. This is understandable, for along with the legendary shenanigans of its leading practitioners -- which ranged from dabbling with hallucinogens to automatic writing -- it also inspired some seductive, memorable images. Rejecting reason, the artists embraced the fantasy world of dreams.</p>
        <p>The Surrealist obsession with dreams is the nominal theme of ''Surrealism: Dreams on Canvas,'' the Nassau County Museum of Art's summer exhibition. On display are 124 paintings, drawings and sculptures, along with Surrealist-inspired clothing, jewelry and even flatware. It is quite a haul, but ultimately it doesn't tell us anything about the movement that we didn't already know.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Surrealist obsession with dreams is the nominal theme of “Surrealism: Dreams on Canvas,” the Nassau County Museum of Art’s summer exhibition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even today, Surrealism, which is nearly a century old, captures the imagination of audiences with surprising force. This is understandable, for along with the legendary shenanigans of its leading practitioners -- which ranged from dabbling with hallucinogens to automatic writing -- it also inspired some seductive, memorable images. Rejecting reason, the artists embraced the fantasy world of dreams.</p>
        <p>The Surrealist obsession with dreams is the nominal theme of ''Surrealism: Dreams on Canvas,'' the Nassau County Museum of Art's summer exhibition. On display are 124 paintings, drawings and sculptures, along with Surrealist-inspired clothing, jewelry and even flatware. It is quite a haul, but ultimately it doesn't tell us anything about the movement that we didn't already know.</p>
        <p>Nor does the show really tell us much about the relationship between Surrealism and dreams; inexplicably, only a scattering of the assembled exhibits are specifically related to dreams and the unconscious. Instead, what we have is a ho-hum miscellany of Surrealist-related objects and images that are grouped by artist and loosely spun together in the exhibition catalog in essays by the curators Constance Schwartz and Charles A. Riley.</p>
        <p>Mr. Riley uses the image of Pandora's box to describe the emergence of Surrealism as a protean artistic force in Paris in the early 1920s. He is on to something there, for the subsequent rapid proliferation of Surrealist ideas and imagery remains one of the extraordinary global cultural events of the mid-20th century; in 1941, Salvador Dali and Joan Miró opened shows at the Museum of Modern Art in Manhattan, and even today Surrealism is a touchstone for many young artists.</p>
        <p>The show's strength is its diversity, with works by Surrealist-inspired artists from many parts of the world. There is a good selection of paintings by the Chilean-American Surrealist Roberto Matta, and some fine individual paintings by lesser-known Surrealist-inspired artists from England (Gordon Onslow Ford), Romania (Victor Brauner), Austria (Wolfgang Paalen), Cuba (Wifredo Lam), Mexico (Leonora Carrington) and Russia (Eugene Berman).</p>
        <p>Surrealist artists of more exalted pedigree are also on display, among them Giorgio de Chirico, Max Ernst, Pablo Picasso, René Magritte, Paul Delvaux and Miró. They are generally represented by lesser works, however; I contended with the din of a visiting school group, but under almost any circumstances the bulk of these paintings would be forgettable. The exception is a marvelous Ernst, ''Profanation of Spring'' (1945), on loan from a Long Island collection. Depicting a profusion of lush, primeval foliage, it is perfectly creepy.</p>
        <p>Another highlight is a pair of Dali landscape paintings, dazzling with their mix of classical panache and ghost-town emptiness. Dali is the kind of artist who always draws you in, no matter what you think of his work. He had an unerring sense of the decisive moment, concocting scenes in which viewers get a sense that something dramatic is about to happen. The tension is engrossing.</p>
        <p>Especially pertinent to the show's theme is a display of prints, drawings, collages and works on paper filling the back gallery and a connecting corridor. Here, among other treasures, attentive viewers will find a pencil frottage by Ernst. The Surrealists loved the chance quality of frottage (basically rubbings of textured surfaces), believing that random patterns suggested possible images. They likened the overall process to a form of unconscious or automatic drawing.</p>
        <p>Instead of working to deepen the displays of dream-inspired images by a core group of European artists, the curators chose to close the show with a selection of Surrealist-inspired paintings by Americans. This again helps to demonstrate the reach of Surrealism's influence, but the focus here is on the postwar generation of Abstract Expressionist artists who were briefly influenced by Surrealism, including Jackson Pollock, Willem de Kooning, David Smith and Robert Motherwell, rather than genuine American Surrealist acolytes.</p>
        <p>Art historical studies of Surrealism's roots in America tend to center on the efforts of a group of artists who embraced the style largely for social and political criticism, including Peter Blume, James Guy and even the early Stuart Davis. These artists are not well known to museumgoing audiences, but they were the ones who mined the subconscious for bizarre and irrational imagery. It is disappointing that they were overlooked for this exhibition.</p>
        <p>Mitigating this oversight somewhat is good artwork by other American-born or -based Surrealist painters, among them Federico Castellon, Dorothea Tanning, Kay Sage and Charles Rain. In particular, there is a great 1938 painting, ''The Dark Figure,'' on loan from the Whitney Museum of American Art in Manhattan, by Mr. Castellon, a Spanish-born painter who arrived in the United States at a young age. Reminiscent of Dali's work, it shows a faceless female figure standing in a vacant, atmospheric landscape. It is one of the show's purest manifestations of dream-infused painting.</p>
        <p>''Surrealism: Dreams on Canvas,'' Nassau County Museum of Art, 1 Museum Drive, Roslyn Harbor, through Aug. 12. Information: www.nassaumuseum.com or (516)484-9337.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
