<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beverly Ginsburg, Iles Cooper</title>
    <meta content="10Ginsburg" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/fashion/weddings/10Ginsburg.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853638"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ginsburg, Beverly R.</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Iles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E7D61F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="544" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beverly Ginsburg, Iles Cooper</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Beverly Ginsburg, Iles Cooper</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beverly R. Ginsburg and Iles Cooper are to be married this afternoon at their home in Orwigsburg, Pa. Rabbi Brian Michelson is to officiate.</p>
        <p>The bride, 56, is the senior vice president for research at the Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, a research center and outpatient center in Boston. She is also the associate director for administration at the Dana-Farber/Harvard Cancer Center, a consortium of seven Harvard institutions in Boston. She graduated summa cum laude from Adelphi University and has an M.B.A. from the University of Pennsylvania. She is the daughter of Naomi Ginsburg of Philadelphia and the late Abraham Ginsburg.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beverly R. Ginsburg and Iles Cooper are to be married this afternoon at their home in Orwigsburg, Pa. Rabbi Brian Michelson is to officiate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Beverly R. Ginsburg and Iles Cooper are to be married this afternoon at their home in Orwigsburg, Pa. Rabbi Brian Michelson is to officiate.</p>
        <p>The bride, 56, is the senior vice president for research at the Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, a research center and outpatient center in Boston. She is also the associate director for administration at the Dana-Farber/Harvard Cancer Center, a consortium of seven Harvard institutions in Boston. She graduated summa cum laude from Adelphi University and has an M.B.A. from the University of Pennsylvania. She is the daughter of Naomi Ginsburg of Philadelphia and the late Abraham Ginsburg.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, 55, is a managing member of Williamson, Friedberg &amp; Jones, a law firm in Pottsville, Pa. He graduated from the University of Wisconsin and received his law degree from Temple University. He is a son of Alice Cooper of Floral Park, N.Y., and the late Samuel Cooper.</p>
        <p>The bride's previous marriage ended in divorce, as did that of bridegroom.</p>
        <p>The couple were introduced through a dating Web site in the fall of 2004 when Ms. Ginsburg responded to an ad warily placed by Mr. Cooper, the father of four children.</p>
        <p>''We had an e-mail dialogue, but I had determined that I didn't want to start dating until after my son's bar mitzvah, a couple of weeks away,'' Mr. Cooper recalled. ''I wanted to focus on him.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Ms. Ginsburg had been struck by his Web name, ''attorneydad,'' and his sense of humor. ''By the second line of his description I was laughing,'' she recalled, ''but I had already scheduled dates with four or five other people, and I sort of lost interest in him because he wasn't writing back to me as fast as the others.''</p>
        <p>During a business trip in San Diego, she showed photographs of her online dating prospects to a member of her staff, who looked at Mr. Cooper and said: ''What are you doing? Why aren't you going out with him? He is perfect.''</p>
        <p>So Ms. Ginsburg wrote to Mr. Cooper again, and they arranged to meet at a restaurant in the King of Prussia Mall in Pennsylvania. ''I told her, 'If it is not successful, we can each go shopping, so it won't be a wasted evening,' '' Mr. Cooper said. ''She told me that she was an unusual Jewish woman in that she did not enjoy shopping. I said, 'Forget meeting, will you marry me?' ''</p>
        <p>Ten days later, at their meeting at the restaurant, neither felt the slightest impulse to shop. ''From then on, it was a fabulous romance, nothing either one of us ever expected to have in life and certainly not this late in life,'' Mr. Cooper said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ginsburg said: ''When I actually met him my immediate reaction was, 'This could be the person I have been dreaming of my whole life.' ''</p>
        <p>Eleven months later, Mr. Cooper took her back to the restaurant where they met, and he said: ''We have talked about everything -- our lives, education, children's upbringing -- but you didn't answer one of my questions. I asked you if you would marry me before we met, and you never answered.''</p>
        <p>With that he pulled out a Limoges box decorated with a heart reading, Marry Me. Inside was an engagement ring.</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
