<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cocktail's Namesake</title>
    <meta content="10shake" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/fashion/10shake.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853314"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SHAKEN AND STIRRED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/Shaken and Stirred</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E5DC163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="587" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cocktail's Namesake</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cocktail’s Namesake</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN MILES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN a teenage immigrant from Dublin named Tommy Rowles started tending bar in New York in 1958, he quickly had to learn how to make a rusty nail, pink lady and brandy Alexander. This was at Bemelmans Bar, the landmark lounge in the Carlyle, where Mr. Rowles, 67, has worked ever since.</p>
        <p>The decades brought more concoctions to learn: the Harvey Wallbanger, seabreeze, cosmopolitan and the cocktails that two of the city's boldface-name mixologists, Dale DeGroff and Audrey Saunders, introduced during their spells managing the Bemelmans. More recently, Mr. Rowles had to learn to make yet another newfangled cocktail: the Tommy Rowles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tommy Rowles has been a New York bartender since 1958, and now he has a drink named after him at the Bemelmans Bar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN a teenage immigrant from Dublin named Tommy Rowles started tending bar in New York in 1958, he quickly had to learn how to make a rusty nail, pink lady and brandy Alexander. This was at Bemelmans Bar, the landmark lounge in the Carlyle, where Mr. Rowles, 67, has worked ever since.</p>
        <p>The decades brought more concoctions to learn: the Harvey Wallbanger, seabreeze, cosmopolitan and the cocktails that two of the city's boldface-name mixologists, Dale DeGroff and Audrey Saunders, introduced during their spells managing the Bemelmans. More recently, Mr. Rowles had to learn to make yet another newfangled cocktail: the Tommy Rowles.</p>
        <p>''I'm just a bartender, not a chef,'' Mr. Rowles said. ''When I started, they had a book behind the bar, with something like 400 or 500 drinks, and that was it.'' Now Mr. Rowles is in the book.The drink, conceived as a tribute to his storied 48-year tenure, was created by Brian Van Flandern, who ended a three-year stint of mixing drinks at Per Se in February to revamp the cocktail program at Bemelmans.</p>
        <p>The bar is steeped in tradition. With its crimson-jacketed staff, Art Deco flourishes and dreamy piano music, Bemelmans evokes a black-and-white vision of bygone Manhattan in which all the men wore fedoras, all the women wore pearls, and they all blithely smoked their heads off.</p>
        <p>But none of its traditions may be more vibrant than Mr. Rowles, who captains the day shift. He is famed for his bloody mary mix -- a secret recipe of his own devising -- and for an across-the-bar exchange with Harry S. Truman during which Mr. Rowles confessed his distaste for bourbon, Mr. Truman's liquor of choice.</p>
        <p>''If you had to walk 15 blocks with those guys following you,'' the former president said of the reporters who accompanied his daily constitutional, ''you'd drink this, too.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rowles -- slender and white-haired and with a bona fide twinkle in his eyes, hoary stereotype notwithstanding -- isn't one to crow about his tribute. Modesty precludes it.</p>
        <p>''For me, having come from Ireland, it feels good,'' is the extent of his preening. ''I know my mother would be proud.''</p>
        <p>When the uninitiated order a Tommy Rowles from Mr. Rowles, he doesn't let on, even if they start carping. ''Some people, you know, they'll say it's too sweet or not sweet enough,'' he said with a shrug.</p>
        <p>Sweetly astringent is what it is. ''It's basically a Cognac and tonic, when you get down to it,'' explained Mr. Van Flandern, who rounds off that combination -- a classic in Europe, more unfamiliar here -- with simple syrup, lime juice and a whisper of rum. ''But what a great summertime drink,'' he said. ''Imagine walking off the hot sidewalk and right into that.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rowles, though, would imagine something else.</p>
        <p>''A Heineken,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Touched by the tribute, however, he couldn't help confess, ''All these new drinks drive me nuts.''</p>
        <p>TOMMY ROWLES  Adapted From Bemelmans Bar</p>
        <p>1ounce Martell Cordon Bleu Cognac</p>
        <p>1/4ounce 10 Cane rum  1ounce freshly squeezed lime juice  1 1/4ounce simple syrup  1/16teaspoon raw quinine powder or 2 dashes Angostura bitters</p>
        <p>1/2ounce club soda  Lime wedge, for garnish</p>
        <p>Mix all ingredients except club soda and lime wedge in a cocktail shaker without ice and shake vigorously. Pour into a highball glass filled with ice. Add club soda and gently roll the mixture back and forth between shaker and glass. Garnish with lime wedge and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield -- 1 serving</p>
        <p>Note -- Raw quinine powder can be bought at www.raintreenutrition.com.</p>
        <p>SHAKEN AND STIRRED</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
