<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stumble Aside, Filly Shows She Has Staying Power</title>
    <meta content="10vecsey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/sports/othersports/10vecsey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853389"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Street Sense (Race Horse)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7D8163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stumble Aside, Filly Shows She Has Staying Power</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Street Sense Has a Future Canoodling, Mostly for Profit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>She stumbled coming out of the gate, and that will be part of the legacy of Rags to Riches -- the sudden stabbing fear of danger. We have seen that all too often in the Triple Crown. Too many horses have come apart in the spring.</p>
        <p>But she regained her equilibrium quickly and caught up with the colts, and now racing has a new champion, a new story, a new hope. It happened on a lackluster day, gray and damp with a vague leftover feeling, because there was no possibility of a Triple Crown and no rematch between the Derby winner and the Preakness winner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The truth is that these great horses are worth more in the breeding shed, as soon as possible, than they are on the track.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>She stumbled coming out of the gate, and that will be part of the legacy of Rags to Riches -- the sudden stabbing fear of danger. We have seen that all too often in the Triple Crown. Too many horses have come apart in the spring.</p>
        <p>But she regained her equilibrium quickly and caught up with the colts, and now racing has a new champion, a new story, a new hope. It happened on a lackluster day, gray and damp with a vague leftover feeling, because there was no possibility of a Triple Crown and no rematch between the Derby winner and the Preakness winner.</p>
        <p>General sports fans might have gravitated to a television to watch the ancient Roger Clemens make his seemingly annual return at Yankee Stadium. Imagine that: racing could produce only seven horses for one of its most important races -- the filly was almost an afterthought, filling the void. But a few miles away, a familiar 44-year-old superstar had a comeback that was one-third competition, one-third big business, one-third soap opera.</p>
        <p>Instead, something grand happened at Belmont Park: a filly won the Belmont Stakes for the first time since 1905. In a sport dominated by breakdowns, tragedies and early retirements, with breeding rights outweighing continuity, a new star has emerged from the furious five-week Triple Crown season.</p>
        <p>The victory by Rags to Riches can be taken as a feminist statement, a victory by a gallant horse carrying five pounds less because in racing the fillies are officially considered the weaker gender. But Michael Tabor of England, an owner of Rags to Riches, says Americans make too much of a fuss over the difference between colts and fillies; it is less of an issue in European racing.</p>
        <p>At any rate, with the ghost of Ruffian's fatal injury at this same track in a 1975 match race hovering over Rags to Riches, the filly overcame her brutal stumble out of the gate and came out of the springtime as the most intriguing 3-year-old in the land.</p>
        <p>In retrospect, racing has had three superb finishes in its three most glamorous races. Street Sense romped from 19th to first in the Kentucky Derby. Curlin rebounded against Street Sense in the stretch at the Preakness. And now a filly has held off a super-horse-in-the-making, Curlin, in the Belmont. All three races were compelling, even if they left us with no clear champion.</p>
        <p>Maybe there are no clear conclusions to be drawn in a sport in which the best Triple Crown colts are ''breeding stock they let us race for a while,'' as Steve Asmussen, the trainer of Curlin, said in a radio interview Friday with Mike Francesa and Chris Russo on WFAN in New York.</p>
        <p>Thus, the enigma of racing. The champions disappear into the tricky world of breeding to produce a new wave of thoroughbreds, who race while their finicky bodies are still maturing and, if they are successful during the Triple Crown cycle, soon disappear into the sheds. It all happens so fast.</p>
        <p>But it may be a different case for the filly, who cannot be bred 40 times a year, for obvious reasons. Tabor said, ''We're here to enjoy this,'' and left open the possibility that Rags to Riches would run again next year, an increasing rarity for colts.</p>
        <p>Some of the heroes of the spring are here on a very short leash. Last week, Sheik Mohammed bin Rashid al-Maktoum bought the breeding rights for Street Sense for undisclosed millions to have him stand at stud outside Lexington, Ky., after this, his second season of racing. The sheik, the ruler of Dubai, also bought the breeding rights to Hard Spun, who finished second in the Derby and third in the Preakness and fourth yesterday.</p>
        <p>Given the frequent breakdowns in racing, it is almost hypocritical to wish that Street Sense had shown up for the Belmont yesterday. Instead, he was back home at Churchill Downs, resting up for a few races later this season and perhaps dreaming of his imminent career in the breeding shed.</p>
        <p>Street Sense was missed on the gigantic freeway of Belmont. He surely would have tested Curlin as well as their rival from those two races, Hard Spun. But if Street Sense had shown up, Rags to Riches would never have raced, according to Todd Pletcher, the trainer who won his first Triple Crown race after 28 losses.</p>
        <p>It's hard for the general public to get worked up over these instant sports celebrities, who have the competitive life of the mayfly. The short and sad life of Barbaro, the 2006 Derby champion who broke down during the Preakness and was kept alive for eight months, still weighs upon racing. So does the breakdown of Charismatic during the 1999 Belmont, but at least Charismatic lived to tell the tale to his fellow pensioners, depending on the language barrier at Shizunai stables on the island of Hokkaido, in Japan.</p>
        <p>In this new season, Curlin had his shot to dominate, but his trainer, Asmussen, had said on Friday that the grind could affect Curlin. ''I always say you get paid for what you do in racing,'' Asmussen said, adding: ''You also pay for what you do.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Rags to Riches may have been fresher in the mile-and-a-half race. Curlin has his breeding duties coming up. Rags to Riches, the filly who did not let a stumble stop her, may be around for a while. Racing needs every familiar face it can get.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
