<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Westchester School Districts Among Top Spenders</title>
    <meta content="10mainweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/10mainwe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="EDUCATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Census Bureau</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fessenden, Ford</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E5DE1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="950" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Westchester School Districts Among Top Spenders</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Westchester School Districts Among Top Spenders</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FORD FESSENDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fessenden, Ford</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US Census Bureau data show that 25 of top 100 highest-spending school districts in nation are in Westchester County, NY; experts say high salaries for teachers and administrators are driving costs, with veteran teachers earning $100,000 and more and superintendent salaries, excluding benefits, averaging more than $200,000; list; graph; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TWENTY-FIVE of the 100 highest-spending school districts in the nation are in Westchester, according to new data from the United States Census Bureau.</p>
        <p>High salaries for teachers and administrators, experts say, are driving costs, with veteran teachers in the county earning $100,000 and more, and superintendent salaries averaging more than $200,000, not including costly and generous benefits packages.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>TWENTY-FIVE of the 100 highest-spending school districts in the nation are in Westchester, according to new data from the United States Census Bureau.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TWENTY-FIVE of the 100 highest-spending school districts in the nation are in Westchester, according to new data from the United States Census Bureau.</p>
        <p>High salaries for teachers and administrators, experts say, are driving costs, with veteran teachers in the county earning $100,000 and more, and superintendent salaries averaging more than $200,000, not including costly and generous benefits packages.</p>
        <p>Among the 8,400 districts nationwide with at least 500 students that serve all grades from kindergarten to 12th, 67 of the top 100 spenders are in New York State suburbs, including 25 in Westchester. Fourteen are in northern New Jersey, and most of the rest are in Alaska and Wyoming, where sparse populations mean more teachers and higher transportation costs per pupil. Connecticut has no districts that crack that list.</p>
        <p>Leading the list in Westchester is Greenburgh Central School District, at $25,664 per student. The district's transportation costs are among the highest in the state, more than $2,300 per student, three times the county average. District officials say two large parochial schools near the district high school siphon off hundreds of students, for whom the district is required to provide buses. The district provides transportation to 1,613 private school students in addition to 1,853 public school students. The school board president, Lloyd Newland, said the district had begun a comprehensive review of operations to find ways to reduce costs.</p>
        <p>Also high on the list are Harrison, Bronxville, North Salem, Elmsford, White Plains and Tuckahoe, all of which spend more than $20,000 per student.</p>
        <p>Altogether, districts in the suburbs of New York City, including northern New Jersey, Westchester, Long Island and Fairfield County in Connecticut, spend far more money -- about 75 percent more -- educating elementary and secondary school students than the rest of the country, with an average of $14,586 per pupil versus $8,315 nationwide. Almost 40 percent of the 100 top-spending school districts are on Long Island.</p>
        <p>The suburban districts in New York are especially generous, spending nearly double the national average: $16,356 per student, according to Census data released on May 24. That is 19 percent more than those in northern New Jersey and 32 percent more than Fairfield County.</p>
        <p>And spending has only increased since 2005, when the data for this census analysis was gathered: All three states have passed or are considering legislation to add hundreds of millions of dollars in aid to local districts, and districts have added hundreds of millions more in fresh property taxes for next year. In New York, spending in the suburbs has grown by $4,000 per student since 2005, according to state figures.</p>
        <p>Among the reasons for the higher spending, experts said, is the higher cost of living in the New York area. Recent data from the Bureau of Labor Statistics show that the cost of living is 30 percent higher in New York suburbs and 15 percent higher in New Jersey suburbs than it is in the rest of the country.</p>
        <p>Also, the census data show that the number of teachers per pupil in the region is among the highest in the country, far higher than in Texas, Florida or California, for example.</p>
        <p>''Whether you go with the side that says, oh, New York just throws money at the problem or the side that says we're just investing wisely for the future, it's undeniable that people are willing to put their money where their mouth is when it comes to education,'' said David Ernst, a spokesman for the New York State School Boards Association.</p>
        <p>As affluent parents try to give their children every educational advantage, experts say, the salaries of educators have grown far faster in the region than in the rest of the country, largely erasing the stereotype of the underpaid educator that prevails elsewhere.</p>
        <p>''The data suggest that New York is outbidding its neighbors for the best teachers and administrators,'' said Bruce Baker, an associate professor at the University of Kansas School of Education.</p>
        <p>New York suburban school districts pay, on average, $10,087 per student for teacher salaries and benefits, more than twice as much as the rest of the country. Administrators cost another $1,204 per student, also about twice the national average.</p>
        <p>The suburbs of northern New Jersey and in Fairfield County, Conn., spend more than the average, but far less -- almost 25 percent -- than New York on teacher salaries and benefits, $7,629 per student. In northern New Jersey, administrators add another $1,043, and in Fairfield County, administrators cost $940 per student.</p>
        <p>New York's high teacher costs are partly attributable to smaller class sizes: The state's suburban districts, for instance, employ far more teachers than the rest of the country -- 76 per 1,000 students, compared with the national average of 60 -- but only slightly more than the New Jersey suburbs, at 74, and Fairfield, at 70.</p>
        <p>New York's suburban districts, though, pay more for each teacher, even compared with New Jersey and Connecticut -- about $133,000 in salary and benefits for each full-time teacher, compared with $94,000 in northern New Jersey and $100,000 in Fairfield, according to data from the National Center for Education Statistics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ernst said teacher salaries reflect higher costs in the state, and a more favorable legal and political atmosphere for labor in New York that makes it difficult to get concessions in years when money is tight.</p>
        <p>But Richard C. Iannuzzi, president of the New York State United Teachers, said teacher salaries were simply a further demonstration of the state's commitment to education.</p>
        <p>''We're proud that we do it well,'' Mr. Iannuzzi said. ''But I would also say in advocating for our members, we advocate for things that affect kids positively, like smaller class sizes, and drive up the cost of education.''</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
