<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN THE REGION/Long Island; Law Enforcement (Real Estate) Agents?</title>
    <meta content="10lizo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/realestate/10lizo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853597"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="In the Region | Long Island"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE0DD1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1125" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN THE REGION/Long Island; Law Enforcement (Real Estate) Agents?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Law Enforcement (Real Estate) Agents?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VALERIE COTSALAS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OFFICIALS in the town of Islip have taken measures in the past to crack down on illegal rentals in single-family homes, as have many less affluent towns on Long Island. But Islip took a more aggressive step in May when it passed a law requiring real estate agents to verify that the homes and apartments they represent are legal and compliant with building codes.</p>
        <p>The new law, an amendment to the town code, also raises fines for violations to a maximum of $5,000 from a maximum of $1,000, or 15 days in jail. This applies to a house's owner, the real estate agent or anybody else who has had a hand in enabling the code violation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Officials in the town of Islip have taken aggressive measures to crack down on illegal rentals in single-family homes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OFFICIALS in the town of Islip have taken measures in the past to crack down on illegal rentals in single-family homes, as have many less affluent towns on Long Island. But Islip took a more aggressive step in May when it passed a law requiring real estate agents to verify that the homes and apartments they represent are legal and compliant with building codes.</p>
        <p>The new law, an amendment to the town code, also raises fines for violations to a maximum of $5,000 from a maximum of $1,000, or 15 days in jail. This applies to a house's owner, the real estate agent or anybody else who has had a hand in enabling the code violation.</p>
        <p>Unsurprisingly, real estate brokers protested, gathering on the steps of Town Hall and at public hearings, claiming that the town is putting too heavy a burden on brokers.</p>
        <p>''I have no idea what the building codes are in the town of Islip,'' said Liz English, a real estate broker in West Islip. She added that New York State already prohibits licensed real estate brokers from representing illegal properties.</p>
        <p>Linda Bonarelli, the president of the Long Island Board of Realtors, said the town was using real estate brokers to enforce building codes instead of hiring more inspectors.</p>
        <p>''They have put the burden on the broker unfairly,'' Ms. Bonarelli said. ''We don't condone illegal rentals, but I think the burden should be on the town, not the Realtor.''</p>
        <p>The issue, many say, is the small stock of affordable housing in Islip and generally on Long Island ''that has forced many people into having illegal rentals,'' Ms. Bonarelli said.</p>
        <p>But the law cuts deeper than affordable housing. Opponents counter that the law is aimed at the Latino community in poor neighborhoods while town officials look the other way in more affluent areas.</p>
        <p>The highest density of illegal rentals is in the hamlets of Bay Shore, Central Islip and Brentwood, according to Steve Flotteron, an Islip town councilman who co-sponsored the new law with the town supervisor, Phil Nolan. Those neighborhoods also have a large number of Latino residents.</p>
        <p>Addressing the real estate agents' concerns, Mr. Flotteron and Mr. Nolan both said agents must simply call the town Building Department to verify that a listing has a legal rental occupancy permit.</p>
        <p>But brokers say the wording of the law is vague and seems to place greater responsibility on real estate agents than Mr. Flotteron and Mr. Nolan say. And it does not apply only to rentals.</p>
        <p>In addition to requiring that ''any person, broker or agent'' verify that there is a valid rental occupancy permit, it requires an agent to verify ''compliance with all provisions of the code of the town of Islip before listing, showing or otherwise offering for lease, rent or sale any dwelling unit in the town of Islip,'' according to the text of the law.</p>
        <p>''The law doesn't state that we only have to verify there's a legal permit,'' Ms. Bonarelli said. ''It goes on to state that the properties must be in full compliance with the code of the town of Islip.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nolan said the law was modeled after similar laws in Riverhead and Smithtown, which he said had not met with opposition.</p>
        <p>But officials in both of those towns say their laws require only that brokers verify a rental occupancy permit with the town. ''The Islip law has more to do with building codes,'' said Frank DeRubeis, the director of planning and community development in Smithtown. ''That's a little more extensive.''</p>
        <p>Beyond the law's wording as it relates to real estate agents, another section has drawn criticism: the part that allows code-enforcement officials to identify homes occupied by more than one family without actually entering them.</p>
        <p>In the past, said Mr. Nolan, the town supervisor, inspectors responding to the ''thousands of complaints'' each year about overcrowded homes and illegal rental apartments within single-family homes have needed the homeowner's permission to enter a home.</p>
        <p>The new law, referred to by officials as ''presumptive evidence,'' allows inspectors to presume that a house is occupied by more than one family if the house has any 2 of 11 features, many obvious from the street outside the house. They include more than one electric meter, more than one satellite dish or antenna, and more than one door on one side of the house.</p>
        <p>''The presumptive evidence gives us the obvious signs: there are three mailboxes, three electric meters,'' Mr. Nolan said. ''Now we can cite the homeowner, who then has to prove that they're not illegal.''</p>
        <p>The town has also hired more inspectors and streamlined the process of taking a landlord to court for violations, Mr. Nolan said.</p>
        <p>The higher fines were necessary to discourage violations, Mr. Nolan said. Until now, landlords have viewed the penalties as a ''cost of doing business,'' he said. ''Some have literally 20 or 25 people in these houses and are drawing up to $3,000 a month in profit.''</p>
        <p>Residents are paying for it with higher taxes to support overcrowded schools, Mr. Flotteron, the town councilman, said. ''Someone's paying $4,000 in taxes for a single-family house, but the house is sending 14 children to the schools,'' he said. Town officials declined to identify any house that had such severe overcrowding.</p>
        <p>Past attempts to crack down on overcrowded homes have involved the school district, according to Mr. Nolan, who has been supervisor for six months. School officials were asked to provide the town with addresses of students who lived in the same house but had different surnames. That practice was ended because of privacy concerns, he added.</p>
        <p>As for the new law, some question its timing and raise concerns that the town is victimizing Latino residents, who they say are often targets in Suffolk County towns.</p>
        <p>''There is probably minimal, if nonexistent, enforcement of mother-daughter type apartments in middle-class white neighborhoods where there are plenty of those,'' said the Rev. Allan B. Ramirez, pastor of the Brookville Reformed Church, who is also an advocate for the Latino community on Long Island. ''Why, if you're against overcrowded housing of any kind, why don't you go after those that have existed for so long?''</p>
        <p>In fact, town officials say that ''the old widow who rents out a room in her house -- that doesn't even get on our radar screen, nobody complains,'' as Mr. Nolan put it.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ramirez took issue with that approach. ''As town officials, they should realize that they are there to enforce the law,'' he said. ''If they want to call it 'the little old lady renting the apartment,' they can call it what they want, but if they are going to enforce it for one, enforce it for the other.''</p>
        <p>In the Region | Long Island</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
