<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hillary Clinton Searches For Her Inner Jock</title>
    <meta content="10healy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/weekinreview/10healy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853284"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Obama, Barack</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kennedy, John Fitzgerald</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Reagan, Ronald Wilson</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E3DD163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hillary Clinton Searches For Her Inner Jock</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hillary Clinton Searches for Her Inner Jock</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK HEALY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HILLARY RODHAM CLINTON needs a sport.</p>
        <p>Her favorite fitness activity, according to her MySpace page, is speed walking. Her hobbies include crossword puzzles, Scrabble and gardening. Organizing her closets is stress relief. Sleeping in until 7 a.m. is her idea of being naughty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the male candidate, sports equal machismo, but there is no playbook for a woman running for president.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HILLARY RODHAM CLINTON needs a sport.</p>
        <p>Her favorite fitness activity, according to her MySpace page, is speed walking. Her hobbies include crossword puzzles, Scrabble and gardening. Organizing her closets is stress relief. Sleeping in until 7 a.m. is her idea of being naughty.</p>
        <p>Her chief rival for the Democratic presidential nomination, Barack Obama, meanwhile, has already shown a touch for channeling the varsity glamour of John F. Kennedy, who radiated vigor and charisma by playing touch football and skippering boats. Mr. Obama loves to play pickup basketball, a game that is the definition of cool for a lot of men.</p>
        <p>The problem, as one of her donors put it: ''How does 59-year-old Mama run against sexy Obama?'' (The donor asked not to be named speaking critically of his candidate.)</p>
        <p>How does she show personality through leisure, particularly of the sporting kind? Voters expect their presidents to throw out the first pitch; they are used to George W. Bush clearing brush, Bill Clinton playing golf, George H.W. Bush racing speedboats, and Ronald Reagan riding horseback.But there is no playbook for a woman running for president. If Condoleezza Rice ran for president, some adviser would surely play up her love of the National Football League.</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Clinton? ''I certainly don't foresee her playing basketball,'' said Alan Patricof, a Clinton fund-raiser.</p>
        <p>The Clinton camp believes that if the presidential nomination comes down to experience, competence and gutsiness (rather than personality), Mrs. Clinton will win.</p>
        <p>''What you see is who she is,'' said her spokesman, Howard Wolfson. ''Hillary is intelligent, strong and experienced. She is also funny, warm, and compassionate. Ellen Goodman captured this well when she referred to her as a 'caring commander in chief.' ''</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Clinton also knows that she needs to win points for likeability. So she often pokes fun at herself. At a forum on faith last week, she said, ''Sometimes I say, 'Oh Lord, why can't you help me lose weight?' '' Her Web site also features a video of her mocking goofy guys as they serenade her as part of her campaign-song contest. And she often pokes fun at her atonal singing voice.</p>
        <p>Her inner jock, however, can feel forced.</p>
        <p>Last week, she teamed up with the tennis legend Billie Jean King and shared some sports stories. ''I played softball, I played pickup basketball, I played tennis,'' Mrs. Clinton said at a Women for Hillary event, recalling that she once won a trophy in an Arkansas mixed-doubles tournament.</p>
        <p>The problem for her, unlike Mr. Obama, is that if she played any sport today, she could invite ridicule. There is a delicate balance between a candidate's true self and, if voters don't buy it, a phony image. John Kerry bought a hunting license in Ohio three weeks before Election Day in 2004; his campaign also arranged for the media to photograph him with gun in hand, wearing fatigues and gesturing thumbs up after a kill. While Mr. Kerry often talked about hunting as a young man, many people found the sportsman imagery -- and him -- inauthentic.</p>
        <p>For a female candidate, double standards can also complicate their image-buffing. Last week. the Boston Herald published a column alleging that Mrs. Clinton had Botox treatments. The claim was more or less debunked, but it was a provocative moment. If the media ever confirmed that Mrs. Clinton did have a Botox treatment, she would almost certainly face an authenticity question. And the double standard would probably kick in: She would seem consumed with her looks -- as if men aren't.</p>
        <p>Hugging and crying also trigger the double standard. In 1992 Bill Clinton was saying ''I feel your pain,'' and putting his arms around grown men, sometimes tearing up over a sad story.</p>
        <p>But if Mrs. Clinton cries on the campaign trail, it will be big news -- and not in a good way, her advisers say. ''It'd be very difficult for her to cry now,'' said John Catsimatidis, another Clinton fund-raiser. ''The best she can do is listen.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton could have had a perfect feel-your-pain moment last month on a walking tour of flood-ravaged New Orleans. At his half-rebuilt home, Gerard Washington told her of being cheated by contractors. As he became more emotional, Mrs. Clinton listened with a furrowed brow and looked at him with concern. But she did not touch him. Maybe it's her nature; despite all her ''listening tours,'' she can seem rather formal. Or maybe it's the nature of her candidacy. Can a female politician go around hugging male voters?</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Kolbert, a writer for the New Yorker magazine who has spent years covering Mrs. Clinton, suggested in the latest issue that the candidate is hamstrung showing her personal side. ''When the topic was personal, it was like talking to someone through several layers of Plexiglas,'' Ms. Kolbert wrote. ''Of course, I was trying to get at the 'real' Hillary. (In the interest of full disclosure, I never even came close.)''</p>
        <p>Few reporters have. After her advisers expressed annoyance with a recent story in this newspaper about Mr. Obama's love for basketball, I volunteered to spend time reporting on Mrs. Clinton enjoying one of her hobbies.</p>
        <p>The interview request remains pending.</p>
        <p>THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
