<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the Road With History's Father</title>
    <meta content="Bissell.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/books/review/Bissell-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Kapuscinski, Ryszard</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Travels With Herodotus (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E6DD1530F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1948" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the Road With History's Father</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On the Road With History’s Father</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM BISSELL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRAVELS WITH HERODOTUS</p>
        <p>By Ryszard Kapuscinski.</p>
        <p>Translated by Klara Glowczewska.</p>
        <p>275 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Packing Herodotus, Kapuscinski set out as a young journalist. It all comes back in this posthumous memoir.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TRAVELS WITH HERODOTUS</p>
        <p>By Ryszard Kapuscinski.</p>
        <p>Translated by Klara Glowczewska.</p>
        <p>275 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
        <p>Ryszard KAPUSCINSKI disappeared in the dead of winter, January 2007, half as well known as his influence would lead one to expect. He went into the beyond Nobel-less, like Joyce and Proust and Nabokov, but to many who read him he was as exalted: ''deity'' was used, more than once, in his assorted funeral songs. While such desperate formulations as ''world literature'' conjure up bongos, beads and sitting Indian-style, the books Kapuscinski wrote may actually qualify, as evocative and singular in English as they are in their native (and what is said to be austerely fine) Polish. For many of us, the day of his death was a dark, cold day.</p>
        <p>Until 1983, most Western readers would have mistaken the man for Polish espresso. Kapuscinski's first book to appear in English, thanks to the translation of the husband-and-wife team of William R. Brand and Katarzyna Mroczkowska-Brand, was ''The Emperor'' (originally published in Polish in 1978), a spell-casting oral history of Haile Selassie's rule over Ethiopia. ''The Emperor'' was followed in 1985 by what many believe to be Kapuscinski's masterpiece, ''Shah of Shahs'' (originally published in 1982), a short, tense, fragmentary account of the 1979 Iranian revolution. In 1987 came ''Another Day of Life'' (originally published in Polish in 1976), his bizarre and shattering reportage from Angola as its former Portuguese overlords fled for their lives. These three books brought Kapuscinski acclaim in the West as perhaps the world's leading literary journalist. The acclaim was rather tardy, seeing that for the past three decades Kapuscinski had been filing dispatches from the Indian subcontinent, Asia, Latin America and, most often, Africa, initially in the service of a Polish youth journal as its first and only foreign correspondent and later for the Polish Press Agency. As his now famous about-the-author note from ''The Shadow of the Sun'' (2001) informs us, Kapuscinski ''witnessed 27 coups and revolutions'' and ''was sentenced to death four times,'' a biographical précis many nonfiction writers would do anything, short of earning it, to have.</p>
        <p>Kapuscinski's African dispatches largely made his name. Like his countryman Joseph Conrad, to whom he is often compared and to whom he bears almost no resemblance, Kapuscinski has become embedded in the continent's literary firmament. Upon Kapuscinski's death, however, the young Kenyan writer Binyavanga Wainaina attacked ''the racist writer Kapuscinski'' as being the author of some of his ''all-time classic lines about Africa,'' such as ''In Africa, the notion of abstract evil -- evil in and of itself -- does not exist.'' It is hard to blame those angered by some of Kapuscinski's more careless statements about Africa. His risky generalizations may suggest a seeming lack of recognition of Africa's varied and heterodox cultures, but that seems a minor sin in light of how deeply he attempted to understand it and how much of his life he spent there. Kapuscinski knew, of course, how complicated his subjects were. ''The European in Africa,'' he wrote in ''The Shadow of the Sun,'' ''sees only part of it'' and can only fall short when attempting to describe ''the immense realm'' of African psychology. His subject matter was local but his tone was cosmic, dislocated and sometimes surreal. His miner's light lingered deep in recesses of totalitarianism, mysticism and revolution -- places where truth begins to lose access to the photosynthesis of fact. A coloration not often noted by those in opposition to Kapuscinski is that his is the Africa of a man from a subject country who discovered it just as its nations were snapping the leashes of their colonial masters. In the end, great nonfiction writing does not necessarily require any accuracy greater than that of an honest and vividly rendered confusion. The limits of human perception cruelly bind us all.</p>
        <p>Kapuscinski's final book, ''Travels With Herodotus,'' is about the Father of History, a man so bound by his fifth-century-B.C. perception and experience as to appear by modern standards almost intellectually comatose. ''He had never heard of China,'' Kapuscinski writes, ''or Japan, he did not know of Australia or Oceania, had no inkling of the existence, much less the great flowering, of the Americas. If truth be told, he knew little of note about western and northern Europe.'' He also believed that Ethiopian men ejaculated black semen. Yet, to Kapuscinski, Herodotus was ''the first globalist'' and ''the first to argue that each culture requires acceptance and understanding.'' How much Herodotus actually traveled we cannot know, and a good deal of ''Travels With Herodotus'' is occupied with Kapuscinski's ceaseless wonderings about his early life (''Did he build sand castles at the edge of the sea?''), family history (''Might Herodotus's father have been a merchant himself?'') and personality (''Perhaps he had a naturally inquiring mind?''). The book's true nature, however, is that of an unabashed memoir, the author's first, and it opens with Ryszard, age 19, studying Greek history at Warsaw University. Although a Polish translation of Herodotus was not available until 1955, shortly after Stalin's death, Kapuscinski became a lifelong pupil of Herodotus's time, ''a world of sun and silver, warm and full of light, populated by slender heroes and dancing nymphs.'' It was also a world that seemed determined to destroy itself through internecine warfare.</p>
        <p>Kapuscinski graduated and became a journalist. After being censured, hounded, and then exonerated by the authorities for writing an exposé of a grisly Polish factory intended to be a Communist showcase -- a story curiously unmentioned here -- Kapuscinski was rewarded with his first foreign assignment. He had asked for Czechoslovakia, the strangest place he could then imagine. He was given India. His editor presented the young journalist with a gift: ''It was a thick book with a stiff cover. ... On the front, stamped in gold letters, was Herodotus, THE HISTORIES.''</p>
        <p>Kapuscinski took the book with him everywhere -- to India, to Afghanistan, to China, to Cambodia, to Rangoon. ''Sometimes,'' he writes, ''when the offices emptied in the evening and the hallways grew quiet ... I reached for The Histories of Herodotus, lying in my drawer.'' We are thus intended to believe that Herodotus served as Kapuscinski's lifelong companion and was, in some ways, his intellectual hero. Yet one will search in vain for any mention at all of Herodotus in Kapuscinski's previously published books in English. Is it all a device? If so, similar slipperiness has earned Kapuscinski no small amount of criticism from the sheriffs of nonfiction, most recently Slate's Jack Shafer, who plucked the press tag out of Kapuscinski's fedora earlier this year in a piece titled ''The Lies of Ryszard Kapuscinski.'' But calling Kapuscinski a liar is akin to one of the Pharisees investigating Jesus' story of the prodigal son and proclaiming that the young man in question never left home at all. (As for the recent revelation that in the early 1970s Kapuscinski agreed to report to the secret police -- though not on his fellow Poles -- in exchange for some freedom to travel, it is intensely disappointing, of course. Much of what Kapuscinski wrote concerned the distortive and corrupting power of totalitarianism. If the allegations are true, then his personal life gave way where his art held firm. We can lament and condemn his weakness without completely forgetting his strength.) Obviously, one should not set out to consciously deceive in a piece of writing that purports to be true. From this understanding the gradations begin.</p>
        <p>A nonfiction writer's style provides the first corresponding clue as to how we are to approach the facts at hand. The style of the plain-spoken, rigorously invisible journalist semaphores one kind of approach, that of the poetical, allusive and interactive journalist another. These are not competitive styles. One is contentedly earthbound, while the other mingles in a Milky Way where morality is not a matter of proper dates and chronology but of representational accuracy, context, language. Its mode of communication is not discursive, or even necessarily informative, but visionary. It is called poetic license for a reason: one has to earn it. As Kapuscinski once said, impartial, unopinionated fact ''is exactly what I avoid.'' He continued, ''If those are the questions you want answered, you can visit your local library.''</p>
        <p>There is distressingly little to argue over in ''Travels With Herodotus.'' The narrative floats about like an uncaptained trireme -- in the Sudan, Kapuscinski meets some questionable individuals, smokes a joint with them, goes to a Louis Armstrong concert and then ponders the Nile, which gets him thinking about Herodotus -- and the pectorals of his language have lost some definition. ''I burned the midnight oil studying up on guerrilla warfare in the jungles of Burma and Malaysia,'' he writes at one point. Whether the presumably comparable Polish phrase being approximated here by his longtime translator Klara Glowczewska is as hoary can only be guessed. It may be unreasonable to expect a writer in his 70s to strive toward the same kind of originality as he did in his relative youth. But the writer in question is Ryszard Kapuscinski. There is a reason we do not allow our superheroes to grow old.</p>
        <p>Those who know Kapuscinski's work have their favorite moments. The scene in ''Shah of Shahs'' wherein Kapuscinski imagines a moment in which a police officer threatens a man in a crowd, who for the first time in his life ''doesn't budge ... and this is precisely the beginning of the revolution.'' His description of how half of the Angolan city of Luanda was shipped away in crates during its siege, ''as if a pirate fleet had sailed into the port, seized a priceless treasure and escaped to sea with it.'' The sorcerer casts a few enchantments in ''Travels With Herodotus,'' but only one of them comes within range of either of the above. It occurs with Kapuscinski's account of the construction of the Great Wall of China, built over thousands of years with ''dedication and devotion'' and ''exemplary discipline.'' And then the classic Kapuscinskian reversal: ''This is how the world's energy is wasted.''</p>
        <p>A nameless energy gathers as one reads deeper into ''Travels With Herodotus,'' and one begins to realize that, in many ways, Kapuscinski's previous books, however brilliant, were somewhat impersonal. Here, finally, we experience the early tremors Kapuscinski underwent for the privilege to write them. Not all of it is painful; much of it, in fact, is delightful -- especially the revelation that Kapuscinski learned English from Hemingway. And one finally sees that in writing about Herodotus Kapuscinski is actually writing about himself. Herodotus tried to get the best information available, Kapuscinski notes, ''and, given the epoch, this speaks to a tremendous expenditure of effort and to great personal determination. ... And if he knows something, how does he know it? Because he heard, he saw.''</p>
        <p>Kapuscinski saw more, and more clearly, if not always perfectly, than nearly any writer one can think to name. Few have written more beautifully of unspeakable things. Few have had his courage, almost none his talent. His books changed the way many of us think about nonfiction and made many of us want to travel for ourselves and see for ourselves. Herodotus, Kapuscinski reasonably imagines, interviewed many of his subjects by campfire. ''Later, these will be called legends and myths, but in the instant when they are first being related and heard, the tellers and the listeners believe in them as the holiest of truths, absolute reality,'' he writes. And so ''the fire burns, someone adds more wood, the flames' renewed warmth quickens thought, awakens the imagination.'' When the last page of this book is turned, note how much smaller and colder the world now seems with Kapuscinski gone.</p>
        <p>Tom Bissell's most recent book is ''The Father of All Things.'' He is working on a travel book about the Twelve Apostles.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Tom Bissell's most recent book is ''The Father of All Things.'' He is working on a travel book about the Twelve Apostles.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
