<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Developers Raise Stake In Politics</title>
    <meta content="10llc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/10llc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853352"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Common Cause</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Litwin, Leonard</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1165" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Developers Raise Stake In Politics</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Developers Raise Stake in Politics</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, June 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He is a man of modest build and unassuming manner, who shuns interviews and dislikes being photographed.</p>
        <p>When Forbes magazine put him on its list of the richest 400 Americans last year, he responded with typical self-effacement. ''Calling me a billionaire is shocking,'' the man, Leonard Litwin, told the magazine. ''My wife will be surprised.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Limited liability companies are providing more cash for candidates in New York State, and no one has given more through them than Leonard Litwin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He is a man of modest build and unassuming manner, who shuns interviews and dislikes being photographed.</p>
        <p>When Forbes magazine put him on its list of the richest 400 Americans last year, he responded with typical self-effacement. ''Calling me a billionaire is shocking,'' the man, Leonard Litwin, told the magazine. ''My wife will be surprised.''</p>
        <p>But there is nothing understated about Mr. Litwin's largess to state politicians. Mr. Litwin, 92, a real estate developer, has given more than $1 million to state political candidates and parties since the beginning of 2006. The contributions were made despite a state law that limits annual donations by individuals to $150,000 and by corporations to $5,000.</p>
        <p>Mr. Litwin was able to give far more by donating almost all of the money through 15 limited liability companies, or L.L.C.'s. Under state rules, an L.L.C. can give political donations of up to $150,000 a year. That is in addition to any donations the company's owner or owners make.</p>
        <p>According to an analysis by Common Cause, a group that monitors campaign financing, L.L.C.'s are providing more and more cash for candidates in New York State, and now account for $12 million in state political donations, up from less than $600,000 in 1999. And no one has given more through L.L.C.'s than Mr. Litwin, according to Common Cause.</p>
        <p>The system allows L.L.C.'s to donate simply under the company name, making the identity of the donors hard to trace. The companies Mr. Litwin donated through include 80th Realty L.L.C. and Arwin 88th Street L.L.C., for instance.</p>
        <p>The establishment of such companies is particularly common among real estate developers. The L.L.C. structure allows a company's owners to avoid putting their own assets at risk in a business venture.</p>
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer, who raised more money from L.L.C.'s last year than any other state official, swore off them after the election and is now proposing to ban them as part of an overhaul of the state's campaign finance laws. He and others have argued that L.L.C.'s have made the state's contribution limits essentially meaningless. Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg and other city officials have moved to restrict donations though L.L.C.'s for city candidates.</p>
        <p>But the governor's proposal has met stiff resistance from Senate Republicans, who have reaped big money from limited liability companies. That is in part because real estate developers are especially generous to Republicans in Albany.</p>
        <p>Take, for instance, Mr. Litwin. Since last year, Mr. Litwin; his firm, Glenwood Management; and affiliated L.L.C.'s have given a total of $155,000 to campaign accounts maintained by the Senate Republican leadership. They also gave to 23 of the State Senate's 33 Republicans.</p>
        <p>Like most developers, Mr. Litwin has not limited his giving to one side of the aisle; he also donated to Mr. Spitzer and to Andrew M. Cuomo's campaign for attorney general last year. And he donated to their Republican opponents.</p>
        <p>He was also a prolific donor to the previous governor, George E. Pataki, contributing tens of thousands of dollars through a series of parking garages structured as limited liability companies.</p>
        <p>''This loophole allows a small elite to give massive campaign contributions, increasing the perception that they have undue influence,'' said Rachel Leon, legislative director of Common Cause New York. ''Not only is it a loophole that allows unlimited giving, but allows givers to obfuscate who the real donor is.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Litwin and Glenwood Management have shown keen interest in a number of issues under consideration in Albany, hiring lobbyists to represent their interests on land-use and environmental questions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Litwin, whose office said he would not comment, lives on Long Island and is one of New York City's largest residential developers. Almost a decade ago, The New York Times described him as ''a slim man of modest height, direct manner, vast self-assurance on a construction site, and no taste for interviews.''</p>
        <p>Steven Spinola, president of the Real Estate Board of New York, on whose board Mr. Litwin serves, said, ''He does not like to accept awards, he doesn't like to see his picture anywhere and he is just a very modest individual.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Litwin's family started in the nursery business more than seven decades ago and still owns the 200-acre Woodbourne Cultural Nurseries in Melville. He and his father, Harry, branched out to real estate in the 1950s, starting with projects on Long Island and later building the Pavilion at 500 East 77th Street. The elder Mr. Litwin died during the construction of the Pavilion, leaving the business in his son's hands.</p>
        <p>More recent Glenwood buildings include Barclay Tower, in TriBeCa, and the 45-story Liberty Plaza in Lower Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Litwin is not alone among developers who are big donors. The Common Cause analysis shows that the six largest L.L.C. donors in the state are real estate developers, though conducting such an analysis is an imperfect science because some companies are hard to trace back to the source. The list is a who's who of prominent Manhattan developers, including entities connected to the Durst Organization, led by Douglas Durst; Extell Development, led by Gary Barnett; and Vornado Realty Trust, led by Steven Roth.</p>
        <p>There is a slight paradox in Mr. Spitzer's proposing to ban contributions from L.L.C.'s; he is the son of a developer, Bernard Spitzer, whose support, including donations from his limited liability companies, made his son's political career possible.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer, who first proposed his campaign finance plan in April, is also seeking to sharply lower contribution limits across the board, and is taking aim at the unrestricted ''soft money'' that is supposed to be used for nonpolitical activities.</p>
        <p>After his proposal met a cool reception, he went to Republican districts and criticized senators personally for blocking it, accusing them of having an ''addiction to the free flow of money.'' That led the Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, to ask, ''Does this governor think he's going to get a result on campaign finance reform by -- what, by doing what -- by having a tantrum?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bruno has argued that disclosure of donations is more important than restricting donations through L.L.C.'s.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer's aggressive fund-raising, including offering people who raise money for him access to him, has struck Senate Republicans as hypocritical. The issue appeared dead until Mr. Bruno recently said he would hold hearings on the matter.</p>
        <p>The limited liability company became a recognized business structure in New York in 1994. Pointing to similar federal rules, the State Board of Elections ruled in the mid-1990s that L.L.C. donations should be treated as separate from donations made by the individuals who control them. But federal laws were tightened in 1999, and now donations on the federal level through L.L.C.'s are counted as part of the overall donations made by the individuals who control them.</p>
        <p>The state board, however, has not revisited its ruling.</p>
        <p>''It never was changed,'' said Lee Daghlian, a board spokesman. ''I can't tell you specifically why. It probably was not revisited because no one asked that it be done.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
