<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Mind of the South</title>
    <meta content="Dickey.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/books/review/Dickey-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853410"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Blount, Roy Jr</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Long Time Leaving: Dispatches From Up South (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E7DD1530F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1355" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Mind of the South</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Mind of the South</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER DICKEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LONG TIME LEAVING</p>
        <p>Dispatches From Up South.</p>
        <p>By Roy Blount Jr.</p>
        <p>383 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a collection of essays, Roy Blount Jr. considers the region where he grew up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LONG TIME LEAVING</p>
        <p>Dispatches From Up South.</p>
        <p>By Roy Blount Jr.</p>
        <p>383 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
        <p>I had to stop reading this book in public. I laughed out loud too often and too uproariously for the company in a bus or plane or cafe. What was worse, if I tried to explain myself my Southern accent, usually kept in check when I'm traveling in the North or abroad (where I live), came back like kudzu after a summer rain. ''Y'all got to read this,'' I heard myself saying to an older couple staring at me on a flight to Rome last month. (They were Americans, as I knew by their Bermuda shorts.) I don't normally say ''y'all'' except when I'm making my annual pilgrimage to South Carolina, and then only for a couple of weeks -- although I always do, it is true, feel better about myself when I'm drawing out my vowels.</p>
        <p>But enough of that, let's talk about this book of essays, ''Long Time Leaving,'' and its author, Roy Blount Jr., whose pieces sometimes read like the monologues of a stand-up comic, which is perhaps unsurprising because he calls himself a humorist, lectures a lot and appears on those few radio talk shows one might call civilized. (Blount should take Don Imus's old slot; he'd certainly be more sensitive when talking about a women's basketball team. But civilization and sensitivity probably aren't good for ratings.)</p>
        <p>Here's the real problem in writing about Blount, much as Blount discovered when he was writing about Mark Twain: ''Despair begins to creep in. How much can be said about how funny anyone's writing is? Or should be said. Introduce something by going on and on about how funny it is, and the reader may well begin to think, irritably, and quite rightly, 'Perhaps I should be the judge of that.' Laughter is so gratifying because it is autonomic. 'Nothing is so hopeless,' Dr. Johnson observed, 'as a scheme of merriment.' Merriment bubbles, or not.''</p>
        <p>The effervescence in Blount's writing depends on timing, of course. If you're going to get the jokes, you've got to get the setups, and those trickle and meander like streams in the Okefenokee. But Blount, as the word ''autonomic'' and the reference to Dr. Johnson suggest, also exhibits a literate good humor that is at least as impressive as his punch lines, and stays with you longer. If Champagne bubbles are our metaphor, Blount's best writing is the wine, not the fizz.</p>
        <p>There are many apt aphorisms, as in an essay called ''The Rapture: Lighten Up,'' where Blount takes on the public passion for the Second Coming and also the contempt for such revelations among self-satisfied secularists. ''Nothing confirms the beliefs of the credulous more than for disbelievers to tell them their beliefs are unbelievable,'' Blount warns. ''Why should the wild-eyed be insecure these days? They appeal to far bigger multitudes than the keen-eyed do.''</p>
        <p>Blount's passing observations can sum up an entire city. ''Havana was like an abandoned wedding cake that ants have moved into,'' he writes. And of the city near where he grew up: ''In the beginning, Atlanta was without form, and void; and it still is.'' His descriptions of food are invitations to carnality -- ''eating right'' is ''not letting any available good taste go unswallowed.'' His enthusiastic appreciation of music, especially blues and country, ties right into his reverence for language as a living and sometimes heavy-breathing thing.</p>
        <p>Blount hears a kid tell a couple of younger boys on the Atlanta transit system, ''Y'all like y'all never rode no bus befo','' and he turns that into a riff about iambic pentameter, the blues and Shakespeare. A discourse on the origins of the rebel yell leads to digressions within digressions, starting with the line ''Oo-ee, oo-ee baby'' in the song ''Sea Cruise'': ''Who wrote 'Sea Cruise?' Huey (Piano) Smith. I thought of Donald Duck's nephews, Huey, Dewey and Louis (that's the American language for you, three different ways of spelling ooey).''</p>
        <p>Blount has a real feel for animals -- birds, dogs, horses, fish -- but he's got a special thing for reptiles. His description of the sound a rattlesnake makes (''a shiver-inducing cross between a flutter and a sizzle'') is just about perfect. And speaking of reptilese, back in the early 1980s, before the ''new'' Ku Klux Klan had been destroyed in the courts, Blount wrote a firsthand report on a couple of cross-burnings. The Klan leadership at the time fancied itself as media-conscious and modern, so white women and kids were invited to the show along with the white-hooded men in the family. Blount catches the evil of the scene in all its hapless banality: ''I've never been to a black sabbath, but this was not what you would expect the reaction of a black sabbath's gathering to be. More like a pep rally. At a small school.''</p>
        <p>Blount says ''Long Time Leaving'' is not just about the South, but about ''the set'' of North and South that makes up the America where he lives (Massachusetts) and where he comes from (Georgia). ''Me, I hover between Southern and Northern,'' is the way he puts it. And while his running jokes are about the way the twain shall meet and misunderstand each other -- I lost count of the number of times he explains that ''y'all'' is always second-person plural -- he seems to be groping for a bigger statement. ''I always feel,'' he writes, ''that there is something I'm not quite getting at in my books.''</p>
        <p>In this collection, a whole picture does emerge that's bigger than the sum of the pieces. The South that he left behind isn't really there anymore. It started disappearing even before Blount was born in 1941, with what C. Vann Woodward called ''the bulldozer revolution'' of sprawling military bases, Interstate highways and man-made lakes. Screen porches gave way to central air-conditioning. The Bible Belt and Sun Belt merged. By the time many of these essays were being written, much of the South had become a place where ''you may doubt that you are anywhere in particular.'' That much Blount is clear on, and you can't blame him when he says, ''I just wish the South would let me decide what it should change and what it shouldn't.''</p>
        <p>But what Blount doesn't nail down, quite, is the way the rest of the United States has been infected by the kind of stubborn simple-mindedness that ''a pre-baby-boom liberal Southern Democrat'' like Blount went North to escape in the first place. He comes close in his introduction, and in the essay ''The Right Shade of Blue?,'' where he wonders how ''those who urge the country further and further toward tax-free, Deuteronomy-based world dominion'' can be put on the defensive. But the theme seems to slip away from him in the section called ''Politicking,'' where you expect him to hammer it home.</p>
        <p>Maybe Blount needs to break out of the latitudinal dialectic, and I suspect he will. One of the epigraphs for this book is from Henry Adams: ''The Southerner has no mind.'' The same line was quoted more fully in a landmark appraisal of the region's failings by W. J. Cash, published the year Blount was born. It was entitled, with apparently self-aware irony, ''The Mind of the South.''</p>
        <p>Adams was writing about a Virginia classmate at Harvard in the 1850's, Robert E. Lee's son Roony: ''Strictly, the Southerner had no mind; he had temperament. He was not a scholar; he had no intellectual training; he could not analyze an idea, and he could not even conceive of admitting two; but in life one could get along very well without ideas, if one only had the social instinct.'' Sound familiar? Those same qualities helped George W. Bush, a Connecticut-born Texan, get elected to the presidency twice -- an indication if ever there was one that the mindlessness of the South has metastasized.</p>
        <p>That doesn't strike you as funny? Well, I figure that when Blount settles down to the theme, it will be. (Y'all like y'all never seed no Bush before.) We sure could use some more good laughs.</p>
        <p>Christopher Dickey, the Paris bureau chief for Newsweek, grew up in Georgia and is the author of ''Summer of Deliverance: A Memoir of Father and Son.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Christopher Dickey, the Paris bureau chief for Newsweek, grew up in Georgia and is the author of ''Summer of Deliverance: A Memoir of Father and Son.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
