<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The City Workers' Guide To Right and Wrong</title>
    <meta content="10ethi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/thecity/10ethi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853678"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Conflicts of Interest Board (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollak, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E3D61F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="652" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The City Workers' Guide To Right and Wrong</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The City Workers’ Guide to Right and Wrong</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL POLLAK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pollak, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sampling of examples from New York City's Conflicts of Interest Board monthly column, Answers From the City Ethicist; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City government employees who wonder what they are entitled or forbidden to do on the job have their own Jiminy Cricket, in a manner of speaking: a fictional character known collectively as the City Ethicist.</p>
        <p>The city's Conflicts of Interest Board administers the conflicts law governing the city's roughly 350,000 employees, and that law can sometimes be tricky. To humanize it, the board's staff members, including its lawyers, take turns writing a monthly column, Answers From the City Ethicist. Examples of the column are on the board's Web site, www.nyc.gov/html/conflicts/html/home/home.shtml. The column is also published in The Chief-Leader, a weekly newspaper that covers New York City government and its labor unions, as Ask the City Ethicist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The city’s Conflict of Interest Board tries to spice up its work with a monthly column written by a fictional character named the City Ethicist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York City government employees who wonder what they are entitled or forbidden to do on the job have their own Jiminy Cricket, in a manner of speaking: a fictional character known collectively as the City Ethicist.</p>
        <p>The city's Conflicts of Interest Board administers the conflicts law governing the city's roughly 350,000 employees, and that law can sometimes be tricky. To humanize it, the board's staff members, including its lawyers, take turns writing a monthly column, Answers From the City Ethicist. Examples of the column are on the board's Web site, www.nyc.gov/html/conflicts/html/home/home.shtml. The column is also published in The Chief-Leader, a weekly newspaper that covers New York City government and its labor unions, as Ask the City Ethicist.</p>
        <p>While not a substitute for the detailed law, the City Ethicist offers down-to-earth advice on ethical topics, some of it wry. Here are some examples, in direct quotation and paraphrase, that are drawn from Ethicist columns on the Web site:</p>
        <p>Q. ''Can I sell Girl Scout Cookies at my city job?''</p>
        <p>A. Selling a few boxes to co-workers on your lunch break may be acceptable, but selling to the public you deal with is not. And a supervisor may not sell to a subordinate. You can sell a few boxes to your boss, however.</p>
        <p>Q. A city worker asks if she can participate with co-workers in a sou-sou, an informal system of rotating credit based on African tradition.</p>
        <p>A. City law does not prohibit it, as long as none of the participants are in a supervisor-subordinate relationship. But being in a sou-sou with your boss would violate city law.</p>
        <p>Q. ''To show his appreciation for all I've done for him, a client wants to give me $25. May I accept it?''</p>
        <p>A. No way. Accepting tips is never allowed. Tell your fan to write a nice letter to your boss instead.</p>
        <p>Q. ''My brother is considering employment at my city agency. Can I recommend him for the position?''</p>
        <p>A. ''While your brother may work for your city agency,'' the Ethicist writes, ''you may not do anything to help him get the job, nor may you supervise him if he does get the job.'' Your brother may apply for the job, but you must completely insulate yourself from the hiring process. That means no recommendations.</p>
        <p>Q. An employee's friend and co-worker who was recently promoted to supervisor needs her roof fixed. ''I used to do roofing,'' the employee writes. ''Can I do the repairs for her as long as I don't receive any payment?''</p>
        <p>A. Sorry. No financial relationships with a superior or subordinate are allowed, friends or not. ''Even if you volunteer your services, the time and labor that you donate constitutes a financial relationship,'' the Ethicist writes.</p>
        <p>Q. ''I received a $100 gift card from a lobbyist with matters before the city. May I accept it?''</p>
        <p>A. Lobbyists, their spouses or partners and their children are forbidden to offer any gift to a public servant, the Ethicist says, but notes a ''social exemption'': If a family or personal relationship, not the lobbying activity, motivated the gift, it may be allowed.</p>
        <p>Q. ''I would like to raise money for my child's soccer team. Any conflicts-of-interest problem?''</p>
        <p>A. ''That depends. If you are simply making calls from home, and are only calling, for example, other parents and a few merchants, this would be O.K.'' But don't mix the fund-raising with your city job, the Ethicist warns. For instance, don't use your title or city letterhead, or the office copier. Don't call people with whom you deal in your city job, and don't solicit from your subordinates.</p>
        <p>''So if you are the boss and you plan to ride your bike for a charity's fund-raiser, you can't ask your subordinates to pledge money for your miles.''</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
