<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Potato Diary, From Obsession to Heartache</title>
    <meta content="10RhomeCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOME WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Potatoes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hirshey, Gerri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E5DF1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1164" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Potato Diary, From Obsession to Heartache</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERRI HIRSHEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hirshey, Gerri</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gerri Hirshey Home Work essay on her love of potatoes and obsession and anguish over trying to grow them in her garden; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THIS spring, when the seed potatoes arrived at our local grain-and-feed store, I circled the barrels of dusty little tubers. I was talking to myself: Should I? Dare I plant a spud -- again? Mortified, our teenage daughter walked away from me, whispering, ''Give it up, Mom. It'll be the same as all the other times.''</p>
        <p>She has been with me in the garden, bucket at the ready, as I've gently turned over the potato mounds, anticipating a bounty below. With a child's candor, she has given voice to my suppressed anguish as she peered at my stunted and scant harvests and snorted, ''Is that it?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THIS spring, when the seed potatoes arrived at our local grain-and-feed store, I circled the barrels of dusty little tubers. I was talking to myself: Should I? Dare I plant a spud -- again? Mortified, our teenage daughter walked away from me, whispering, ''Give it up, Mom. It'll be the same as all the other times.''</p>
        <p>She has been with me in the garden, bucket at the ready, as I've gently turned over the potato mounds, anticipating a bounty below. With a child's candor, she has given voice to my suppressed anguish as she peered at my stunted and scant harvests and snorted, ''Is that it?''</p>
        <p>We gardeners know that Mother Nature can be wanton and cruel. But why, I've wondered for nearly a decade now, why won't she let me grow a humble and edible sack of potatoes, my most beloved of foods? Yellow Finn, Peruvian purple, banana fingerlings, plain old white mashers -- I've tried them all, and failed. In dutifully composted, well-drained, aerated and pesticide-free soil that grows everything from asparagus to zucchini, I have harvested only mangy, misshapen spuds. Or none at all.</p>
        <p>No one can tell me why. In my quest for a cure, I have left no potato growers' F.A.Q.s, no extension service Web site, unturned, no folksy ''tried and true'' method unexplored. I have rotated, hilled, straw-mulched and spent the equivalent of a four-star entree on pedigreed tubers, organic fungicides and insect-deterring row covers.</p>
        <p>But before I detail the disasters, I should explain the stinging irony. For me, spud worship is bred in the bone; both maternal grandmothers -- one Italian, one Polish -- grew, ate and esteemed the unlovely tubers immoderately, on both sides of the Atlantic. Apparently I got a double helix craving. As a child, I used to sneak chunks from the cutting board and eat them raw. Always, I have turned to them in periods of contentment and crisis.</p>
        <p>As a skittish, untried hostess, I could count on red potatoes -- dusted with marjoram and rosemary, roasted in olive oil until crunchy/creamy -- to take the glare off the entree failures. Feeding those ever-suspicious eaters, my children, I have looked to potatoes as a blessed fallback food -- nutritious, familiar and excellent camouflage for healthy additions, from broccoli to cheese. I reckon it was more than kismet that led me to a man who makes killer mashed potatoes emblematic of our union: rich, lumpy and good for whatever ails you.</p>
        <p>Any way you look at it, spuds are supremely accommodating. So when I finally got a decent garden in which to grow some, I was stunned to find that they were so persnickety. For years, I'd heard others boast, ''Oh, I just threw some on the hillside -- got bushels.'' Or, ''They just came up in the compost heap.'' How tough could it be?</p>
        <p>As I recall, it was some unspecified wilt that did me in that first time. Potato plagues of all sorts have found a welcome in my sunny raised beds: Nattily striped Colorado potato beetles, hitherto unseen, materialize and chow down the second a few nascent potato leaves dare unfold above ground. One year, the vilest of killers descended overnight, much as it did in the historic Irish potato famine, taking only hours to turn healthy plants into heaps of blackened slime. ''Blight? I have potato blight?'' I yawped during a consultation with a state agricultural expert. ''Yes ma'am, blight,'' came the sepulchral reply. ''I'm sorry to say that your symptoms sound like the nastiest kind -- late blight. Just when you think you've got it made.''</p>
        <p>The blight was gross, and deflating. But I soldiered on. The coup de grâce came during the Summer of the Fingerlings -- those slender, tender spudettes that carry sirloin price tags in markets. My plants, grown from the pedigreed tubers of a revered catalog house, were flourishing and pest-free when I broke my leg, badly, about a month before harvest time.</p>
        <p>During the post-op wheelchair phase, family members were tolerant about performing basic garden tasks. But as I graduated to a walker, I was left alone to fuss with row covers and keep the beetles at bay. It was an unusually dry season. The scarcity of the pretty purple blossoms limned in catalog copy worried me a tad, but, still merry with the help of time-release pain medication, I remained optimistic.</p>
        <p>When, at last, the time was right, I wired a colander to the front of my walker and clunked out to dig up my treasures. I had big plans: I was going to roast them whole with olive oil, garlic cloves and rosemary, and maybe a few shallots. I would steam some and consume them unadorned, savoring the heady bouquet of all my organic labors, a witchy chemistry of fallen apple blossoms, composted broccoli stalks and worm castings, all morphed into fragrant, golden flesh. Ah, alchemy!</p>
        <p>Oh, bitter harvest. I struggled back to the house, shredded potato vines clinging to the Velcro closings on my brace, with just a couple of dozen peanut-sized runts rattling in the colander. When I had regained a measure of composure, I got on the phone with the seed catalog's kindly troubleshooter. ''I'm hearing some genuine despair, which will not do,'' she said. ''You will try again -- I'm shipping you another batch, complimentary, next spring.''</p>
        <p>They came. They rotted -- in the shipping carton, ignored. I could brook no more heartache, would endure no more family jokes. In the freed-up garden space, I experimented with rainbow chard -- a brilliant success in magenta, yellow and green.</p>
        <p>I thought I had turned the corner. But one day, as I was handing over a wad of cash for some toothsome Peruvian blues at the farmers' market, my friend Nancy mentioned that she had tossed some spuds into a plastic bucket of dirt in her backyard and forgot about them -- until they offered up a full tub of mature specimens. Raising a trio of teenagers, she says she can best manage a sort of ''backhanded gardening.''</p>
        <p>Hmmm. It had been suggested to me, gently, that perhaps my spud failure was a simple case of loving too much. Obsession, known to kill the hottest romance, could surely K.O. tender spuds. And benign neglect was the one thing I hadn't tried. So last spring, I sliced up and buried sprouted chunks of commonplace reds in a washtub, fastened a scrap of row cover over it, pushed it to a corner of the garden and ignored it until late August. I got about three pounds' worth -- firm, tasty and dangerously encouraging.</p>
        <p>I've found a second tub and another free corner. I've spent the price of a mochachino on some unfancy seed spuds. Double or nothing, I'm taking a shot, with no expectations -- and a fallback position. An e-mail message from a local green organization brings the news that a second farmers' market is opening this month, with tons more local veggies. And no matter what the potatoes' provenance, the gratin pan awaits.</p>
        <p>HOME WORK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
