<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Prague, A World Of Stage Design</title>
    <meta content="10korn" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/theater/10korn.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853500"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prague Quadrennial (Stage Design Festival)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Prague (Czech Republic)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kornhaber, Donna</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kornhaber, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Czech Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Czech Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Czech Republic/Prague</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Prague (Czech Republic)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Czech Republic</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2DF1E30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="881" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Prague, A World Of Stage Design</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Prague, a World of Stage Design</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DONNA KORNHABER and DAVID KORNHABER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kornhaber, Donna; Kornhaber, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Prague Quadrennial, formally International Competitive Exhibition of Scenography and Theater Architecture, which celebrates fortieth anniversary this year; history of festival, especially during Cold War, described; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Arnold Aronson, a theater professor at Columbia University, received the offer several years ago to serve as general commissioner of the Prague Quadrennial, he knew it might be hard to brag about. ''Everyone knows the Oscars, the Tonys, even the Venice Biennale,'' he explained. ''I tell people all the time what I'm doing, and they say they've never heard of it.''</p>
        <p>For those who have heard of it, however, the Prague Quadrennial is, in the words of its director, Ondrej Cerny, ''the most important meeting of theater people in the whole world.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For those who have heard of it, the Prague Quadrennial is, in the words of its director, Ondrej Cerny, “the most important meeting of theater people in the whole world.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Arnold Aronson, a theater professor at Columbia University, received the offer several years ago to serve as general commissioner of the Prague Quadrennial, he knew it might be hard to brag about. ''Everyone knows the Oscars, the Tonys, even the Venice Biennale,'' he explained. ''I tell people all the time what I'm doing, and they say they've never heard of it.''</p>
        <p>For those who have heard of it, however, the Prague Quadrennial is, in the words of its director, Ondrej Cerny, ''the most important meeting of theater people in the whole world.''</p>
        <p>The event, which has taken place in Prague every four years since 1967, will celebrate its 40th anniversary this year. Based in the Industrial Palace, an 1891 Art Nouveau complex in the nearly 100-acre Vystaviste Exhibitions Grounds, the quadrennial, formally the International Competitive Exhibition of Scenography and Theater Architecture, presents displays of set, costume, lighting and sound design. This year's festival, which runs from Thursday to June 24, features exhibitions from about 60 countries spanning 6 continents and is organized into national displays.</p>
        <p>''It's like the Olympics for theater designers,'' said Alexandra Bonds, professor of costume design at the University of Oregon and commissioner of this year's United States exhibition. ''We're basically in training for it for four years.''</p>
        <p>Participating nations compete for a number of awards, including the Golden Triga, which the quadrennial's deputy director, Daniela Parizkova, describes as ''one of the most important awards in the field.''</p>
        <p>Started by the Culture Ministry at a time when, Ms. Parizkova said, ''Czechoslovakia was at the top of world theater design,'' the festival became what Mr. Aronson called ''part of the culture wars of the cold war.'' Early quadrennials were marked by elaborate spending by nations on both sides of the Iron Curtain, but especially by the Soviet Union and its satellite states. The festival became one of Eastern Europe's foremost events for artists -- and citizens -- to meet and exchange ideas. ''In the 1970s lots of people with no interest in theater came just to meet Westerners,'' Mr. Aronson said.</p>
        <p>With the fall of the Soviet Union in 1991, the festival entered what Mr. Cerny described as ''a crisis of identity.'' The Soviet Union's exhibitions were once the centerpieces of the festival; in 1991 its entry was composed entirely of corrugated cardboard and glue so that it could be thrown away after the festival to save transportation costs. It wasn't until 2003, Mr. Cerny said, that the Prague Quadrennial began to find ''a new identity in a new world.'' Mr. Aronson's appointment in 2004 as the first foreign commissioner was part of that effort. Widely acknowledged as an expert on scenographic history and theory, he has participated in the quadrennial since 1987. (Full disclosure: The authors are working acquaintances of Mr. Aronson's at Columbia.) Mr. Aronson said he was ''flabbergasted'' when he was offered the post, adding, ''It was a very gutsy decision to choose an American.'' After the initial offer the appointment required approval by the Prague Quadrennial Council, a supervisory board under the Culture Ministry. ''I had to show that I was not going to be the ugly American, taking over and changing everything. I had to show that I had a good internationalist sense.''</p>
        <p>Starting in 1967 each quadrennial has had a particular theme, like the works of Shakespeare, Chekhov or Mozart, around which countries were expected to organize their exhibitions. One of Mr. Aronson's first decisions was to eliminate the appointed concepts.</p>
        <p>''We decided the themes were not relevant to the new countries who were participating,'' he said, ''and we would have each country devise its own theme, whatever it felt was most appropriate to that country. Together we felt that multiple themes would give us the pulse of the sociopolitical world of 2007.''</p>
        <p>For the team designing the United States exhibition, this meant a focus on what Ms. Bonds called ''life today in the U.S., in the post-9/11, post-Katrina era.'' Titled ''New Voices, New Visions: Out of the Box,'' the entry also highlights ''works that explore theater beyond traditional expectations, that move beyond box sets,'' Ms. Bonds explained.</p>
        <p>The display will showcase the creations of some 95 American designers and 120 American productions, including multiple video displays and 54 production artifacts, ranging from a paper ghost puppet from Cirque du Soleil's Las Vegas production of ''Love'' to a model of George Tsypin's collapsed skyscraper for the set of an international production of ''West Side Story.''</p>
        <p>This year's festival will also have an increased focus on performance itself. One of the paradoxes of the quadrennial, Mr. Aronson said, is that ''it exhibits artifacts of process, but the event itself is missing.'' Expanding a tradition begun in 2003, this year's quadrennial will feature 500 individual performances and temporary installations at the exhibition grounds and throughout the city. The goal, said Sodja Lotker, who is coordinating the performances, is to turn Prague itself into a ''stage for designing.''</p>
        <p>Amid these changes, one constant remains: With more than 5,000 expected attendees, from students to top designers, the most important aspect of the Prague Quadrennial is still the ability to meet and exchange ideas.</p>
        <p>''For 10 days Prague becomes the center of world theater,'' Mr. Cerny said. ''Everyone makes an appointment in Prague.''</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
