<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>He Who Does Not Hesitate: Horry Is Mister Big Shot</title>
    <meta content="10horry" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853341"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803EEDA163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1072" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>He Who Does Not Hesitate: Horry Is Mister Big Shot</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <dateline>SAN ANTONIO, June 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robert Horry hit a 3-pointer late Thursday night, an act so natural, so familiar, so amusingly routine that it seemed as if every N.B.A. finals must have started this way.</p>
        <p>The degree of difficulty on the shot, from 25 feet out on the left side, was not particularly high. In the broad pantheon of Horry playoff 3-pointers, it did not rate among the most impactful, or the most memorable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Robert Horry hit a 3-pointer late Thursday night, an act so natural, so familiar, so amusingly routine that it seemed as if every N.B.A. finals must have started this way.</p>
        <p>The degree of difficulty on the shot, from 25 feet out on the left side, was not particularly high. In the broad pantheon of Horry playoff 3-pointers, it did not rate among the most impactful, or the most memorable.</p>
        <p>But it extended the San Antonio Spurs' lead to 18 points and it reminded the young Cleveland Cavaliers -- who lost the opener, 85-76 -- that their concerns go way beyond Tim Duncan's pretty bank shots and Tony Parker's whiz-bang speed.</p>
        <p>They must deal, too, with the inevitability of Horry, who may just go down as the greatest nongreat player in finals history.</p>
        <p>While the Cavaliers star LeBron James pursues his first championship and the Spurs aim for their fourth, Horry is eyeing his seventh. The mere discussion of his winning it elicits some weighty thoughts.</p>
        <p>''It would be unfortunate if he wasn't able to be a Hall of Famer,'' Cavaliers guard Damon Jones said, unprompted.</p>
        <p>It may sound like a stretch, given Horry's rather thin career scoring average (7.2 points), and his rather casual role, which has varied from third wheel to eighth man in a 15-year career.</p>
        <p>But then consider Horry's company among the career ring leaders. Only seven players have won more championships, all as members of the 1960s Boston Celtics dynasty: Bill Russell (11); Sam Jones (10); John Havlicek, Tom Heinsohn, K. C. Jones and Tom Sanders (eight each); and Frank Ramsey (seven). All but Sanders are in the Hall of Fame.</p>
        <p>Horry does not show up among the N.B.A. finals career leaders in scoring, field-goal percentage, minutes played, free throws, rebounds or assists. But he has more 3-pointers (54) than anyone in finals history, ahead of Michael Jordan (42), Michael Cooper (35) and Scottie Pippen (30). He is No. 6 in steals (49), behind Magic Johnson (102), Pippen (67), Larry Bird (63), Jordan (62) and Cooper (59).</p>
        <p>Horry, the ever-unassuming country boy from Andalusia, Ala., ponders these things and says it is a little mind-blowing.</p>
        <p>''Because you think of those guys, those elite superstar guys that you only fantasize of being like,'' Horry said. ''And then when you see your name among them in certain categories, you're kind of like, Ah, I did some things they did!''</p>
        <p>In his most modest moments, Horry thanks serendipity and his proximity to the N.B.A. legends who were kind enough to pass him the ball. He won his first two titles, in 1994 and 1995, next to Hakeem Olajuwon in Houston. He won his next three titles, from 2000 to 2002, alongside Shaquille O'Neal and Kobe Bryant in Los Angeles. When the Lakers let Horry leave in 2003, he promptly joined up with Duncan and won title No. 6 in 2005.</p>
        <p>''He was lucky,'' said the former N.B.A. coach Hubie Brown, echoing a position that Horry himself often espouses.</p>
        <p>''I always joke around'' that it is a matter of luck, Horry said, ''but I would like to think it has a little bit to do with some of my skill.''</p>
        <p>For pure visual impact, Horry's clutch 3-pointers -- which earned him the nickname Big Shot Rob -- stand out the most. The legacy began in Game 3 of the 1995 finals, when Horry hit a 3-pointer that gave Houston a 104-100 lead with 14.1 seconds left. The Rockets won and took a 3-0 series lead. In the 2001 finals, Horry hit a 3-pointer with 47 seconds left (then hit four free throws) to seal a Game 3 victory against the Philadelphia 76ers.</p>
        <p>In the 2002 Western Conference finals, Horry hit one of the most memorable shots in playoff history -- a 3-pointer from the top of the arc with 0.1 seconds left to beat the Sacramento Kings and tie the series at 2-2. In the 2005 finals, Horry hit a 3-pointer with 5.8 seconds left in overtime, giving the Spurs a 3-2 series lead over the Detroit Pistons.</p>
        <p>Horry has never been the focal point of his team -- or even the fourth option -- but his collection of clutch shots in April, May and June is as impressive as anyone's in the modern era.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people cannot take a shot at the end of a game,'' said Brown, who is in the Hall of Fame as a contributor. ''There are a lot of guys, once you get to that six-minute mark, when that clock is at 4, 3, 2, they'll make the extra pass. This guy will not do that. This guy is fearless. He'll accept the criticism if he misses. But fortunately for him, he doesn't miss very often.''</p>
        <p>Beyond the easy shrugs at the buzzer, Horry has delivered much more. In Houston, he was a dynamic, rangy small forward who routinely finished among the leaders in blocks and steals. His only single-game finals record came in 1995, with seven steals against Orlando in Game 2.</p>
        <p>Horry, who stands 6 feet 10 inches, made a seamless transition from small forward to power forward for the Lakers, then spent years guarding the likes of Duncan, Karl Malone, Chris Webber, Kevin Garnett and Rasheed Wallace.</p>
        <p>''That sounds easy to do,'' Brown said of the position change, ''but that's extremely difficult. The two positions are like night and day.''</p>
        <p>But in the end, Horry's legacy will always be defined by the big shots and the championships that always seem to follow. The run is coming to a close, however. Horry, who turns 37 in August, said that next season ''is my last year, for sure.'' His body, he says, is telling him it's time.</p>
        <p>''I can feel it coming on,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A seventh title is in reach. An eighth could come before Horry closes the book on his career. Then the folks in Springfield, Mass., will have to ponder what to do with a small-time scorer who had a big-time impact.</p>
        <p>''I try not to even think about that,'' Horry said, chuckling at the Hall of Fame suggestions. ''If it happens one day, I'll be happy then, a kid at Christmas time.''</p>
        <p>As Horry said, the Hall of Fame is filled with great scorers, great rebounders and great playmakers, ''and I don't have the points, the rebounds or the assists to get there.''</p>
        <p>All he has done is hit big shots and win championships.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
