<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why, Bitsy, Whatever Are You Reading?</title>
    <meta content="10books" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/fashion/10books.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853312"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF STYLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E7DC163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1074" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why, Bitsy, Whatever Are You Reading?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Why, Bitsy, Whatever Are You Reading?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIESL SCHILLINGER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Upper Class: A Novel  By Hobson Brown, Taylor Materne and Caroline Says.  288 pp., HarperTeen.  $8.99.</p>
        <p>A Privileged Life  Celebrating WASP Style.  By Susanna Salk.  170 pp., Assouline.  $40.</p>
        <p>AHH, the Box! That newly minted headquarters of louche on the Lower East Side -- where doormen with bowler hats and waxed mustaches admit unruly hordes to ironic burlesque shows; where Stephen Fry has been known to turn up at 2 in the morning with entourage and where Lindsay Lohan shows up whenever she's in town.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>What to read between chukkers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Upper Class: A Novel  By Hobson Brown, Taylor Materne and Caroline Says.  288 pp., HarperTeen.  $8.99.</p>
        <p>A Privileged Life  Celebrating WASP Style.  By Susanna Salk.  170 pp., Assouline.  $40.</p>
        <p>AHH, the Box! That newly minted headquarters of louche on the Lower East Side -- where doormen with bowler hats and waxed mustaches admit unruly hordes to ironic burlesque shows; where Stephen Fry has been known to turn up at 2 in the morning with entourage and where Lindsay Lohan shows up whenever she's in town.</p>
        <p>It's a place so risqué that on the last Tuesday in May it opened its doors to a book party where sporty young blondes in bateau-neck dresses and pearls reminisced about Hotchkiss with young men in khakis who looked like they'd been beamed up from Newport (or J. G. Mellon).</p>
        <p>When the guests left, they scored a bag of loot containing a copy of the book being feted, ''The Upper Class: A Novel,'' four kinds of zit gel and an issue of Teen Vogue.</p>
        <p>Stop, rewind. Book party? Pearls? Hotchkiss? Zit gel? Did someone just kill bohemia?</p>
        <p>Not quite. Ever since last summer's surprise YouTube hit, ''Tea Partay''-- Smirnoff Raw Tea's hip-hop send-up of WASP culture -- intoxicated the nation's Web surfers, a sheepish fascination with preppiness seems to have whetted the public's curiosity. The party for ''The Upper Class'' at the Box was an example of how that preppy ethos has been goosed up not only for prime time, but for after-hours, too.</p>
        <p>For instance, the socialite and Lilly Pulitzer model Amanda Hearst (recently designated one of the ''hottest billionaire heiresses'' by Forbes magazine) got down with the Heatherette impresario Richie Rich, to music performed live by a young blonde who looks like Paris Hilton.</p>
        <p>(Anyone who'd seen ''Tea Partay'' couldn't help but recall its ''New England gangsta'' lyrics: ''Straight outta Cape Cod/we're keepin' it real/we're gonna have a party/that makes the ladies squeal.'')</p>
        <p>If you can't judge a book by its cover, is it fair to judge it by its party? In this case, that wouldn't be a bad idea.</p>
        <p>''The Upper Class,'' written by three Hotchkiss graduates, is a novel about the class tensions, family pressures and vicious social jockeying that seethe in an elite boarding school in Connecticut called Wellington (oh, let's just call it Hotchkiss).</p>
        <p>But it is no lazy a roman à clef. Amazon designates its reading level as ''young adult,'' but the writing is lyrical, funny and often touching; and there's no age limit on the voyeuristic fascination the subject holds.</p>
        <p>The authors send a hot-blooded nouveau riche Long Island sexpot named Nikki (called Amy Fisher by her snotty schoolmates) to Wellington to room with Laine, a golden-skinned Greenwich blueblood who has a hard time bonding with any creature that doesn't carry a field-hockey stick or walk on four hooves.</p>
        <p>Both of them are homesick. Laine in particular remains caught in her dream of childhood: ''a ball of sun, the pollen of privet hedges  misty locker rooms at the club, lessons spent baking on the clay fields, sunk in sunny lethargy.''</p>
        <p>The complexity and difference of each girl's struggle to survive the ''Lord of the Flies'' dynamic of their enclave is admirably drawn -- and the authors make sure that neither girl is a caricature. They open the leaded windows wide onto the playing fields of privilege, then, flipping the camera around, expose the far more brutal battle within the ivy-covered walls.</p>
        <p>Taking a page from Harry Potter, they turn boarding school into a Hogwarts without magic, though not without dark arts. Reading about the different dorms -- with names like Cadwallader, Eliot, Blackstick and Thornfield -- recalls Hogwarts' Ravenclaw, Hufflepuff, Slytherin and Gryffindor houses. But there's no ''sorting hat'' for the students; they have to scramble for position on their own.</p>
        <p>The author Curtis Sittenfeld wrestled with a similar theme in her excellent novel ''Prep'' a few years ago; and last month, Andrew Trees was scorched when he published his own thinly veiled comedy of manners, ''Academy X,'' set in a private school not unlike Horace Mann (where he taught for six years, and may or may not be allowed back, come fall). What is it about the aura of the old school that so captivates the public imagination?</p>
        <p>IN ''A Privileged Life: Celebrating WASP Style,'' an unapologetically reverent scrapbook of the WASP experience and her own memories, Susanna Salk (a Milton Academy- and Vassar-educated magazine editor and playwright) offers a personal explanation: ''After I watched the World Trade Center collapse on television, I picked up an L. L. Bean catalog and gazed at its pages completely shell-shocked,'' she writes.</p>
        <p>''Could there still be a world where people sat on sunny docks with initialized totes eating Pepperidge Farm Chessmen cookies?''</p>
        <p>She longed for continuity and reassurance, she explains -- to ''wear safe, sexless clothes,'' and to sink back into the comforting preppy embrace of no-frills cocktail hours, where there would be ''Triscuits with Cracker Barrel cheese and warm white wine in plastic tumblers.''</p>
        <p>She is not afraid to make fun of WASP eccentricities, and even includes what she calls the ''only WASP joke I know.'' ''Q: What did the WASP go to the hospital for? A: The food.'' But she is serious about defending the virtues of WASP values, and their contribution to American culture. At last -- the white upper classes have a place at the table.</p>
        <p>The pages gleam with iconic photographs of über-WASPs -- William F. Buckley, George Plimpton, Jackie Onassis and members of Ms. Salk's own family -- and with people who, whatever their backgrounds, became emblems of WASP mythology: Truman Capote, F. Scott Fitzgerald, Grace Kelly and  Téa Leoni? ''There are WASP-y WASPs who are as complex and multifaceted as un-WASP-y ones,'' she argues.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the whole point of WASPdom, in her vision, is its simplicity. One caption, for a portrait of an unnamed family, says it all: ''Nothing completes a WASP family portrait like boat sneakers and dachshunds.''</p>
        <p>The book's cover bears a portrait of C. Z. Guest, taken by the elite set's photographer of choice, Slim Aarons. The book's party is at J. Crew on Fifth Avenue this Wednesday. Attendance is by invitation only. If you have yet to receive yours, it's printed, as is proper, on a monogrammed bordered correspondence card, in cursive. The dress code is ''country club chic optional.'' Gin cocktails and tea sandwiches will be served.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF STYLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
