<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hotting Up</title>
    <meta content="10wwln--safire.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/magazine/10wwln-safire-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853467"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 6-10-07: ON LANGUAGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dictionaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EFD81130F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="999" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hotting Up</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hotting Up</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Safire</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The headline on the front page of The Financial Times was a stunner: ''Murdoch denies Beijing kowtow as Dow Jones rhetoric hots up.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>And the hotties are cool.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The headline on the front page of The Financial Times was a stunner: ''Murdoch denies Beijing kowtow as Dow Jones rhetoric hots up.''</p>
        <p>Forget about whether Rupert Murdoch, the chairman of News Corporation, banged his head on the sandalwood floor in a classic kowtow to gain his television signal access to a billion-plus Chinese. Pay no attention to his run at taking over Dow Jones, parent of The Wall Street Journal, whose editorial page is the Last of the Interventionist Stalwarts.</p>
        <p>No; the stunner to the Mavenhood was the choice by Britain's global F.T. of the nonstandard verb phrase hots up to describe the rising level of controversy about the deal. Not heats up, which is what most speakers of English around the world believe happens when an argument becomes heated. Not even grows hot.</p>
        <p>Granted, brevity is a whip-bearing dominatrix in the discipline of headline writing. Heats up is one whole letter longer than hots up and might have demanded changing the column width at huge expense throughout the paper's pink pages. Not to be considered are such words as intensifies or escalates, which stretch out forever and were banned from the headlinese that keeps such short verbs as assail and decry on life support in layout's iron tongue.</p>
        <p>I put it squarely to Chrystia Freeland, U.S. managing editor of The Financial Times, a Canadian journalist at the British paper's New York office: What's up with hots up?</p>
        <p>''It's quite a normal usage in British journalism,'' she notes. ''Pops up on the BBC often. We're comfortable with it in a headline, where we use the vernacular more than in copy, especially when it fits the space.'' Freeland adds: ''We're a global paper. It's important for us to be intelligible to North American readers, and not be obviously foreign, but we don't go out of our way to change Britishisms that we think will be understandable. In our columns, writers speak in their own voices, though for our Asian edition, we take more care not to use colloquialisms. In this case, 'hots up' appeared in all four editions.''</p>
        <p>The Oxford English Dictionary backs her up: the first citation is a 1923 usage by P. G. Wodehouse, the humorist who created the character Jeeves. ''The atmosphere,'' he wrote in ''The Inimitable Jeeves,'' ''was consequently more or less hotted up when Cyril . . . breezed down center.'' (Wodehouse also liked hotsy-totsy, which made it to the U.S. back in the day, meaning ''just fine.'') Hots is still cooking along: The Times of London a couple of months ago headlined, ''Bets are hotting up about who might replace the lord chancellor under a Brown regime,'' and more to the hot point, The Mirror only a few weeks ago reported, ''Things are hotting up between Justin Timberlake and Jessica Biel.'' (That either means they're fighting or everything is hotsy-totsy; see your supermarket checkout counter for the latest.)</p>
        <p>One other bit of evidence that it is common British usage traveling to the U.S.: Sally Quinn, writing in The Washington Post soon after Reagan's inauguration in 1981, warned of scapegoats other than Nancy Reagan to be found ''as the honeymoon comes to a close and things, as the British say, begin to hot up.''</p>
        <p>What with global newspapers like The International Herald Tribune, the hotting-up pursuit of The Wall Street Journal and The F.T. -- not to mention the Internet and worldwide distribution of movies as never before -- common expressions are zipping around the world. (I just may start Mavens Without Borders.) One such American export, a kind of return present for Britain's hots up, is hottie, on which we now warm our hands:</p>
        <p>Unisexily Sexy</p>
        <p>Rarely do we come across a word that can be applied, with lust aforethought, to either sex. A physically attractive male can be called a stud, and if cuddly to boot, a stud muffin. I can retrieve, from the far reaches of my brain's hippocampus, a memory of once being called a dreamboat. An especially masculine type is called a Barney, and if tall, ''a long drink of water.'' On rare occasion, you'll hear ''Ty-guh!''</p>
        <p>Female endearments range from baby doll to arm candy, peach to fox, quail to chick -- I could go on but don't need more infuriated e-mail from people who consider any lip-smacking characterization to be an insult to the intellect.</p>
        <p>Few terms, however, are applicable to a sexually attractive person of either sex. Hottie is not spelled with a y because -ie, the lexicographer Grant Barrett informs me, ''is a classic diminutive or hypocoristic ending used for terms of endearment'' (and hypocoristic is the Greek-based word for ''called by pet names'').</p>
        <p>A hottie began as the name of the hot-water bottle, a foot-warming device of red rubber filled with leaking hot water that went out with the kowtow. Hottie is now the name of a foxy cookie or a stud muffin -- a word not unisex but duosex. The supermodel Tyra Banks has been called ''a world-class hottie''; Ontario's premier, Dalton McGuinty, has been named the ''top political hottie'' by The Guardian Weekly; and the Web site that lets students compare the teaching of college professors, male and female, has now added a ''hottie rating.''</p>
        <p>The source is probably American. It was popularized in 1987 in the song ''Go See the Doctor,'' by the hip-hop artist Kool Moe Dee. The current hip-hop star Kanye West maintains that after a year or so, when a new term is no longer in style for black people, it's O.K. for others to pick it up. ''I think white people are allowed to say bling. They are allowed to say old-skool black slang, like hottie and homie. If you say a slang word too early, it's like you're trying to be black. So as long as the slang is a little played out, you're all good.''</p>
        <p>The rise of hottie is America's way of shouting across the pond to the slangy Brits, ''Thanks for hots up!''</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 6-10-07: ON LANGUAGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
