<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Russian Airline to Buy 22 Planes From Boeing</title>
    <meta content="10boeing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/business/10boeing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853336"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boeing Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aeroflot</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kramer, Andrew E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Boeing Co</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Aeroflot</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEEDC163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="536" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Russian Airline to Buy 22 Planes From Boeing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Russian Airline to Buy 22 Planes From Boeing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW E. KRAMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kramer, Andrew E</byline>
      <dateline>ST. PETERSBURG, Russia, June 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Boeing Co announces $3.5 billion sale of 22 airplanes to Aeroflot, Russian national airline, in deal that defies souring political relations between US and Russia (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Boeing Company announced on Saturday a $3.5 billion sale of airplanes to Aeroflot, the Russian national airline, in a deal that defied the souring political relations between the United States and Russia.</p>
        <p>Boeing characterized the deal, which ended a high-stakes battle with its European rival, Airbus, as a vote of confidence in the quality of its new 787 Dreamliner airplane. The model is selling well even in countries otherwise loath to patronize American businesses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The deal between the Boeing Company and Aeroflot, the Russian national airline, defied the souring political relations between the United States and Russia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Boeing Company announced on Saturday a $3.5 billion sale of airplanes to Aeroflot, the Russian national airline, in a deal that defied the souring political relations between the United States and Russia.</p>
        <p>Boeing characterized the deal, which ended a high-stakes battle with its European rival, Airbus, as a vote of confidence in the quality of its new 787 Dreamliner airplane. The model is selling well even in countries otherwise loath to patronize American businesses.</p>
        <p>Boeing announced the sale at an economic forum that Russian officials said would show that their country remains open for business.</p>
        <p>Aeroflot is buying 22 of the airplanes, to be assembled in Everett, Wash., to renew its fleet of Boeing and Airbus planes built during the Soviet era.</p>
        <p>The sale was a victory for Boeing, based in Chicago, in one of its more politically fraught markets. Aeroflot said it would leave in place plans to also buy Airbus planes for a later delivery date.</p>
        <p>Scott E. Carson, the executive vice president of Boeing, also agreed to assist a Russian aerospace company, Sukhoi, with global marketing and after-sales support for the company's Russian-made regional aircraft, the Superjet.</p>
        <p>Boeing also signed a broad cooperation agreement with the Unified Aircraft Corporation, a state-owned holding company being formed by the Kremlin to resuscitate the domestic aircraft industry.</p>
        <p>''This underscores our long-term commitment to cooperation with Russian industry,'' Mr. Carson said in a statement.</p>
        <p>For Boeing, the offer of technical cooperation apparently revived the 787 deal with Aeroflot, which had appeared dead last year as relations between Russia and the United States soured.</p>
        <p>Talks between Aeroflot and Boeing stalled last fall after the State Department imposed sanctions on Sukhoi -- a Boeing partner even at the time, though a company better known as a maker of fighter jets -- for doing business in Iran. Sukhoi was one of seven companies in Russia, Cuba, North Korea and India sanctioned under the 2000 Iran Nonproliferation Act.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Carson played down the political crosscurrents in the deal.</p>
        <p>''It represents a business relationship between our company and Aeroflot, and I'm really proud of it,'' he said in response to a question of whether the deal should be seen as a step toward a resolution of the rift between the United States and Russia.</p>
        <p>Aeroflot also apparently suffered after the talks stalled by allowing a delivery agreement for 2010 to expire; now, the first Boeing planes will be delivered in 2014.</p>
        <p>Boeing said the catalog price, or typical sale price not reflecting modifications or delivery dates, for the 22 planes was about $3.5 billion. Neither company revealed the actual terms.</p>
        <p>The deals agreed to on Saturday continue a Boeing policy of heavy involvement in Russia that began in the early 1990s.</p>
        <p>A Boeing design center in Moscow employs about 1,400 Russian engineers who work in shifts that correspond with the downtime of Boeing engineers in Seattle, allowing the company to design planes almost around the clock.</p>
        <p>Boeing also buys parts in Russia. A onetime secret Russian military factory in the northern Ural Mountains, VSMPO-Avisma, provides Boeing with cast titanium parts under a joint venture that Boeing predicts will sell $18 billion worth of airplane parts over 30 years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
