<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amid Quaint Corners, the Billboard Blues</title>
    <meta content="10stre" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/thecity/10stre.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="STREET LEVEL/MEATPACKING DISTRICT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Outdoor Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hotel Gansevoort (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Greenwich Village Society for Historic Preservation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sign In Properties (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Achenbaum, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mindlin, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Outdoor Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Outdoor Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Greenwich Village (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E2D61F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="725" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amid Quaint Corners, the Billboard Blues</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Amid Quaint Corners, the Billboard Blues</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX MINDLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mindlin, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alex Mindlin Street Level column on two stacked freeway-style billboards that have been erected in backyard of Hotel Gansevoort in Manhattan's Meatpacking District; Greenwich Village Society for Historic Preservation has led three protests outside hotel; Michael Achenbaum, president of company that owns hotel, has apologized to public but says he cannot break long-term lease with signage company, Sign In Properties; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last week, Florent Morellet, the owner of Restaurant Florent in the meatpacking district, stood beneath the giant new billboards at the corner of Hudson and Gansevoort Streets. He considered them carefully, tucking his sunglasses into his shirt pocket.</p>
        <p>''Ah,'' Mr. Morellet finally said, in his throaty French accent. ''That lovely addition to our quaint neighborhood.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many in the meatpacking district are unhappy that the Hotel Gansevoort rented part of its property to make room for two huge billboards -- including the hotel’s owner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last week, Florent Morellet, the owner of Restaurant Florent in the meatpacking district, stood beneath the giant new billboards at the corner of Hudson and Gansevoort Streets. He considered them carefully, tucking his sunglasses into his shirt pocket.</p>
        <p>''Ah,'' Mr. Morellet finally said, in his throaty French accent. ''That lovely addition to our quaint neighborhood.''</p>
        <p>That is surely the nicest thing he has said about two stacked freeway-style billboards that recently went up in the backyard of the Hotel Gansevoort, a three-year-old boutique hotel that receives rent for the signs.</p>
        <p>The billboards loom above a low-rise background of tenements and row houses at a central intersection. The upper and larger of the two signs, advertising Volkswagen, is 20 feet tall and 60 feet wide, about 80 percent larger than a standard highway billboard. The other sign, of standard billboard size, advertises MTV.</p>
        <p>The whole assemblage, angled to face traffic coming down Hudson Street, sits on a 75-foot-tall shaft so thick that a person could eat lunch inside it. The larger billboard was erected in mid-March; the second went up on May 16, a development that was reported in Chelsea Now, a weekly newspaper.</p>
        <p>Even before the second billboard went up, some businesses and preservationists had been complaining about the signs, calling them ugly and too tall, and asking the hotel to take them down. The Greenwich Village Society for Historic Preservation has led three protests outside the Hotel Gansevoort, and 10 or so local restaurants, among them Balthazar, Pastis, 5 Ninth, One and Restaurant Florent, now refuse to accept reservations from the hotel's concierges.</p>
        <p>On a guest check pinned up behind the busy counter at Restaurant Florent, someone has scribbled a script to follow in case the hotel calls: ''I am sorry, but we have been instructed not to take reservations from your hotel, in protest against the billboard on Hudson Street.''</p>
        <p>Local sentiment seems to range from livid to blasé, depending in part on how close to the signs the speakers live.</p>
        <p>''I think it's arrogant and insensitive to the neighborhood,'' said Mary Wolf, who lives across the street from the signs and was tightly gripping her dog's leash. ''I wake up every morning looking straight at a Volkswagen ad.''</p>
        <p>But Kipton Davis, a real estate agent who lives a block away, shrugged it all off. ''Advertising is everywhere,'' she said. ''At first it was an eyesore, but I've gotten used to it.''</p>
        <p>The funny thing is this: Michael Achenbaum, president of the company that owns the hotel, said he agreed with the critics. Andrea Cohen, a spokeswoman for the hotel, referred to an ''apology to the public'' that Mr. Achenbaum issued in March, about a year after making the billboard deal.</p>
        <p>''I personally want to unequivocally apologize for having made the decision to install the billboards,'' he said in the statement. ''It was a business decision made without fully envisioning the sheer size of the signage and without understanding the emotional impact it would trigger.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Achenbaum added, however, that he could not remove the billboards because he was ''bound to a long-term lease'' with Sign In Properties, a signage company, for 20 years. Ms. Cohen added that if the hotel broke the lease, it would be contractually obligated to pay Sign In the projected lifetime revenue of the billboard, which she said would be a ''multimillion-dollar sum,'' as well as the cost of the structure. She declined to say how much rent Sign In was paying.</p>
        <p>In his statement, Mr. Achenbaum also said that to make amends, he had offered to let artists display their work on the back of the billboards in the future, and to give those artists $5,000 grants. The program has not begun yet, according to Ms. Cohen, because Mr. Achenbaum must first secure city permission to display the works.</p>
        <p>Mr. Achenbaum's apology has not been accepted in all quarters. Andrew Berman, the executive director of the preservation society, said that Mr. Achenbaum had been ''pretty unrepentant'' in private meetings with billboard opponents and could perhaps have done more to back out of the deal.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Nancy Friedman, another spokeswoman for the hotel, did not sound remorseful in describing the signs during an interview. ''The billboards aren't really that bad,'' she said. ''It's just that all the activists in the neighborhood are rallying around them.''</p>
        <p>STREET LEVEL/MEATPACKING DISTRICT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
