<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Warsaw Underground</title>
    <meta content="Welsh.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/books/review/Welsh-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853424"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Nine (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E5DD1530F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Warsaw Underground</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Warsaw Underground</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRVINE WELSH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NINE</p>
        <p>By Andrzej Stasiuk.</p>
        <p>Translated by Bill Johnston.</p>
        <p>229 pp. Harcourt. $23.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This Polish novel is set among the addicts and dealers of Warsaw’s black economy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NINE</p>
        <p>By Andrzej Stasiuk.</p>
        <p>Translated by Bill Johnston.</p>
        <p>229 pp. Harcourt. $23.</p>
        <p>The Poles, probably more than any other Europeans, must feel they deserve a little peace, freedom and prosperity. Sandwiched between the neighbors from hell (Germany, Russia), they were at the back of the line when the late 20th century dispensed its favors. But now here are democracy, economic growth and membership in the European Union; Poland's future, on the surface, appears rosier than ever.</p>
        <p>Beyond the glitzy bars of central Warsaw and their conspicuously successful clientele, however, huge swaths of Poland's capital city have been laid waste, and young people are largely noticeable by their absence. Emigration has made its presence felt, and the main beneficiaries have been the construction sites, bars and coffeehouses of Chicago, Dublin, Edinburgh, London and Berlin. The Polish diaspora has provided a low-cost army to help renew and service Western capitalism.</p>
        <p>For those who don't work for advertising agencies or in high-tech industries, or haven't been able to try their luck abroad -- the losers in the free market's crapshoot -- all the old uncertainties of the black economy beckon. It is this Warsaw underworld, with its scamming and its subsistence culture, that is so vividly evoked in Andrzej Stasiuk's new novel, ''Nine.''</p>
        <p>The publisher's blurb refers to this book as an ''existential crime novel,'' something that may incline some to proceed with trepidation. In the English language, both ''existentialism'' and ''Warsaw'' are generally prefixed by the term ''bleak,'' the way ''burger'' is followed by ''fries.'' Don't be deterred; this book reminds us how much bland fiction we publish in the English-speaking world. Our cultural hegemony has its downside; our imagination is increasingly filtered through the marketing lens of escapist genre fiction, and our so-called literary novels often feel like rehashed classics brazenly trumpeted as original work. Our novels affirm rather than challenge our sense of ourselves in the world.</p>
        <p>One measurement of a genuine writer is his or her ability to evoke a place that is instantly familiar yet outside our direct personal experience, presenting it to us as a more accurate and vivid depiction than our prejudices had previously allowed. Andrzej Stasiuk is this kind of writer. He's an accomplished stylist with an eye for the telling detail that brings characters and situations to life.</p>
        <p>The narrative of ''Nine'' follows Pawel, a young businessman who wakes up in an apartment wrecked by the loan sharks who are on his trail. He turns to Bolek, a former miner turned drug dealer, and Jacek, an addict, for help. Stasiuk understands that in the black economy we can't always choose our associates, and that as well as the need to make a living, people require some true drama in their lives. Behavior that seems self-destructive and high-risk is in some social milieus understandable, and it becomes positively fanciful to consider alternatives. Despite the harsh circumstances in which Stasiuk's protagonists find themselves, however, their humanity is never compromised.</p>
        <p>The novel is a fool's-gold chase through Warsaw -- the bus terminals, the railway stations, the shopping centers and the grubby apartments. Like the Dublin of Joyce's ''Ulysses,'' the city itself becomes a central personality of the book. The mundane and the desperate elements of urban life are skillfully intercut. Stasiuk's characters spend a great deal of time in the city's transportation system, looking for others in a comparably marginal state, hoping to beg, bully or barter improbable salvation from them.</p>
        <p>Oddly, it's the graceless Bolek who emerges as the most interesting character in ''Nine.'' The ostentatiously successful gangster has the vulgar trappings that his associates like Iron Man and ''the blond man'' aspire to emulate, but he's sinking slowly in his own ennui as in his slovenly voyages from bed to leather couch to upholstered automobile. It's Bolek's rejection of his young gold-digging girlfriend, Syl, that paradoxically feels like the book's moral center. We see before he does that in casting her aside -- and through his fantasies about the more mature Irina -- Bolek is in fact searching for a connection beyond the shallow shoes-and-shelter-for-sex exchange that underpins his association with Syl. This doomed relationship is thoughtfully and telling observed; it could have descended, in less gifted hands, into crass caricature.</p>
        <p>In this canny translation from the Polish by Bill Johnston, Stasiuk's prose soars over the city. He sees as a helicopter might, and illuminates stray lives with empathy and verve. (He's just as good at street level. Here is Pawel recalling how he and his friends, as kids, scoured the local airport for discarded packs of foreign cigarettes: ''They'd look in the trash cans or see the little colored boxes in ashtrays. Finders keepers, and they didn't care who was watching. Green-and-white Suezes, white-and-red Winstons, brown plastic Philip Morris boxes, yellow, gold and dark blue 555's, the kind that Mao smoked.'')</p>
        <p>I caught a flavor of Hamsun, Sartre, Genet and Kafka in Stasiuk's scalpel-like but evocative writing. ''Nine'' feels like a major work of modern fiction, a portrait of an uprooted and restless generation of Eastern Europeans and of a city resigned to the fact that post-Communism is not quite as advertised. This book will undoubtedly win Andrzej Stasiuk a greater following in America and, with luck, will pave the way for the translation of more vibrant literature from Eastern Europe.</p>
        <p>Irvine Welsh's most recent novel is ''The Bedroom Secrets of the Master Chefs.'' His new short-story collection, ''If You Liked School, You'll Love Work,'' will be published in July.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Irvine Welsh's most recent novel is ''The Bedroom Secrets of the Master Chefs.'' His new short-story collection, ''If You Liked School, You'll Love Work,'' will be published in July.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
