<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'My Holocaust'</title>
    <meta content="Letters.t-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853427"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07EEDF1030F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'My Holocaust'</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Below is a letter I've written in response to the review of my novel, ''My Holocaust'' (May 27). The letter is written in the voice of one of the minor characters in the novel, Lipman Krakowski, who sees himself, among other things, as a veteran letters-to-the-editor writer. I believe the review was wrongheaded and surprisingly ad hominem, reflected no understanding of either fiction or satire, was strikingly at odds with the many other very positive reviews that have appeared, and left your readers with a deeply and relentlessly distorted impression of my book.Tova Reich</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Below is a letter I've written in response to the review of my novel, ''My Holocaust'' (May 27). The letter is written in the voice of one of the minor characters in the novel, Lipman Krakowski, who sees himself, among other things, as a veteran letters-to-the-editor writer. I believe the review was wrongheaded and surprisingly ad hominem, reflected no understanding of either fiction or satire, was strikingly at odds with the many other very positive reviews that have appeared, and left your readers with a deeply and relentlessly distorted impression of my book.Tova Reich</p>
        <p>Chevy Chase, Md.</p>
        <p>Esteemed Mr. Editor:</p>
        <p>Maybe you remember from Mrs. Tova Reich's hoo-hah novel, ''My Holocaust,'' how my dear friend and fellow survivor of the Shoah, Mrs. Henny Soskis, mentioned that I'm a professional letters-to-the-editor writer, with already 3,467 published letters to my credit. The authoress Mrs. Tova Reich has turned to me because of my credentials to write this letter. Mrs. Tova Reich is not so young and beautiful anymore, so there's nothing in this for me, but that review you printed (May 27) was such schlock that I've agreed to dictate this letter of protest. The authoress herself has promised to write it down word for word.</p>
        <p>You should excuse me, Mr. Editor, but where did you find this reviewer of yours? Does he know something from fiction writing? The credits say he knows from Joe Louis -- so is he some kind of boxer maybe? I myself am an experienced weightlifter and still in very good shape, as Mrs. Tova Reich was kind enough to remark in her book, so I don't need this boxer of yours to defend me or any of my fellow survivors, thank you very much. And what's this business of saying to such a respectable lady like the authoress Mrs. Tova Reich that she has ''chutzpah'' for how she writes about us survivors? For this I came to America? To hear some little Jewish ayatollah boxer deliver a little Jewish fatwa against a writer, telling her what she can and cannot write because of how it looks to the goyim?</p>
        <p>For your information, the authoress Mrs. Tova Reich has known Shoah survivors all her life. We are not saints. We are people to whom a terrible thing happened. Excuse me, but I don't want my claim to fame to be that someone tried to exterminate me. Anyone with half a brain is sick and tired of all this ''sacred'' talk and victim idolatry at the expense of the dead. I'm sorry to inform you, Mr. Editor, but this boxer you dug up from I-don't-know-where to review my book is just another uncomprehending little knee-jerk. (My old friend Mrs. Henn'sche Soskis -- a charming lady in her own right, who, by the way, is proud of every one of her 220 pounds no matter what your boxer thinks -- tells me I shouldn't call it ''my'' book, but I feel like it's mine; I feel like it dares to tell it like it is for all of us who have been bullied and silenced by all those self-righteous machers and exploiters of the memory of the real victims, may they finally be allowed to rest in peace.)</p>
        <p>Lipman Krakowski  Wheaton, Md.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>David Margolick's review of Tova Reich's ''My Holocaust'' is breathtaking in its failure to understand the book. As Reich makes clear, the Holocaust was unique, incomparable, ultimate and it is not marketable, no matter how facile, fluent and inflated the marketing materials. Because Reich is so deeply ironic a writer, it's just barely possible for a willfully inattentive reader to miss the righteous anger at the heart of the book.</p>
        <p>Judith Plotz  Washington</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The sad thing about David Margolick's review of ''My Holocaust'' is that he gets that there is a problem. Margolick admits: ''The business of publicizing and exploiting the mass murder of European Jewry for political, financial or institutional gain is something we Jews would rather not discuss, except among ourselves.'' Still, Margolick would have us Jews stay quiet lest the goyim notice.</p>
        <p>The problem is that every time there is exploitation of the Holocaust for personal or political gain it constitutes a great desecration of the memory of the Holocaust victims. The victims were brutally massacred and now they lie dead and defenseless and open to exploitation again and again.</p>
        <p>In Jewish law the most important commandment one can do is to protect the dead. ''My Holocaust'' does this powerfully and brilliantly by shaking us to our core and commanding us to look at what we have done with the memory of the holy martyrs of the Holocaust.</p>
        <p>Margolick shrugs and writes, ''Sure, it can seem that ghoulish Holocaust commemoration has become the core of Jewish observance nowadays.'' Sure! No, it should not be so. And it cannot be so. And it is about time someone said that.</p>
        <p>Shmuel Herzfeld  Washington</p>
        <p>The writer is the rabbi of Ohev Sholom -- The National Synagogue.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
