<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pak Inspires New Generation of Countrywomen</title>
    <meta content="10pak" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/sports/golf/10pak.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853361"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ladies Professional Golf Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pak, Se Ri</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E2D9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1006" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pak Inspires New Generation of Countrywomen</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pak Inspires New Generation of Countrywomen</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <dateline>HAVRE DE GRACE, Md., June 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Darkness used to be Se Ri Pak's trusty companion on the L.P.G.A. Tour, her long days of practice fueled by a fervent belief that the last one to leave the course was destined to finish first.</p>
        <p>So it was strange to hear Pak speak about cutting out of Bulle Rock Golf Course while plenty of sunlight remained for lining up putts and launching drives. It was midafternoon on the day before she officially qualified, at age 29, for the L.P.G.A. Tour and World Golf Halls of Fame with her opening round at the L.P.G.A. Championship. Pak, the defending champion, was intent on adhering to her new routine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was not until an injury sidelined her in 2005 that South Korean golfer Se Ri Pak was able to stand back and admire her body of work, and see herself as others did, as a pioneer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Darkness used to be Se Ri Pak's trusty companion on the L.P.G.A. Tour, her long days of practice fueled by a fervent belief that the last one to leave the course was destined to finish first.</p>
        <p>So it was strange to hear Pak speak about cutting out of Bulle Rock Golf Course while plenty of sunlight remained for lining up putts and launching drives. It was midafternoon on the day before she officially qualified, at age 29, for the L.P.G.A. Tour and World Golf Halls of Fame with her opening round at the L.P.G.A. Championship. Pak, the defending champion, was intent on adhering to her new routine.</p>
        <p>''Go back to hotel,'' she said, ''have great dinner with friends and then maybe some bottles of beer.''</p>
        <p>Pak never took the time to drink in her success when she was the toast of the Tour. Between 1998 and 2004, she won 22 events, including 4 majors, and steadily grew to hate the game.</p>
        <p>''Before, I felt like I was having fun,'' Pak said in an interview here. ''But I don't think I was having fun. There was always pressure, just wanting to be really, really great and pushing myself so hard.''</p>
        <p>Then, as now, her golf swing was flawless. It was her life that was out of alignment.</p>
        <p>It was not until an injury sidelined her in 2005 that Pak was able to stand back and admire her body of work, and see herself as others did, as a pioneer.</p>
        <p>''In Korea, people who don't know golf know Se Ri,'' Pak's compatriot Birdie Kim said.</p>
        <p>When Pak joined the Tour in 1998 at age 20 after breezing through the L.P.G.A. qualifying tournament, the membership included only one other South Korean citizen, Ji Hyun Suh.</p>
        <p>Golf was considered a rich man's game in South Korea until Pak turned it into a kind of cultural revolution. In a two-month stretch during her rookie season, she won four events -- two of them majors -- and a star was born.</p>
        <p>Millions of South Koreans stayed up all night to watch the live coverage of her victory over Jenny Chuasiriporn, an amateur, in a 20-hole playoff at the 1998 United States Women's Open. At a time when South Koreans had little confidence in their economy, Pak became the gold standard for a generation.</p>
        <p>This year, 45 South Korean-born players are on the Tour, a dozen of whom started playing golf in or after 1998. Of the 84 golfers who made the cut here, 19, including Pak, were South Korean. One of them, Na On Min, is leading this tournament with 18 holes to play. Pak, 11 shots back after a 74, is the idol of most junior golfers, Min said Saturday. She added, ''So if I win this tournament, it's like no way to describe it.''</p>
        <p>Pak was a sprinter, a hurdler and a shot-putter before her father, Joon Chul Pak, steered her into golf when she was 14.</p>
        <p>He once said he made her play because he had some vague idea ''that golf would bring her money.''</p>
        <p>Under her father's watchful eye, Pak practiced on the range for hours. Sometimes in the winter, icicles would form in her hair while she hit balls. She regularly ran 15 flights of stairs, forward and backward, to build her lower-body strength.</p>
        <p>To train his daughter's mind, Joon Chul had her hit golf balls in a cemetery at night and watch pit bulls fight.</p>
        <p>Pak was trained to be a machine, but even as she was cranking out victories, she said, she felt strangely unfulfilled.</p>
        <p>''It was like, hey, I'm missing something,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In 2001 and 2002, Pak played brilliantly, posting 10 L.P.G.A. victories in that span -- five each year -- only to be overshadowed by Annika Sorenstam, who won 19 times.</p>
        <p>Pak redoubled her efforts to become No. 1, and all it got her was exhausted. By 2004, she had little left in her tank. She won only once that year, at the Michelob Ultra Open, but it was a monumental victory, giving her enough points to qualify as a Hall of Famer.</p>
        <p>Her induction would have to wait three years, until she met the 10-year Tour membership requirement. That loomed like an eternity to the burned-out Pak. Recalling those days, she said, ''I hated to be on the golf course.''</p>
        <p>At the 2005 Women's British Open, Pak injured the middle finger of her left hand while hitting out of the rough and had to take the next few months off to let it heal.</p>
        <p>Pak's friend and mentor, Nancy Lopez, called the injury ''a blessing in disguise.'' Delivered from her golfing compulsions, Pak hung out with friends and forged an identity away from the course. She returned to the Tour last year feeling like a new person and won her 23rd tournament and 5th major at the L.P.G.A. Championship. When she is inducted later this year, she will become the L.P.G.A. Tour Hall's 23rd member. (Dinah Shore is an honorary member.)</p>
        <p>One day last week, as Pak prepared to defend her title, the practice green at Bulle Rock was alive with the sound of Korean. It was music to the ears of Pak, who was the center of the conversation, literally and metaphorically.</p>
        <p>''First time it felt a little weird to hear so many players speaking Korean,'' Pak said. ''Now it just feels comfortable.'' She added: ''I'm really, really proud to see how many players have made it from my country. They're young. They have such great dreams. They're really doing well. I'm very happy to see it.''</p>
        <p>The young South Koreans are not the only ones who look up to Pak. Lorena Ochoa, the No. 1 player in the world, is one of two golfers from Mexico on the Tour. Her goal is to make her golfing dream as accessible to her countrywomen as Pak has made it to hers.</p>
        <p>''I admire her a lot,'' Ochoa said. ''She's very special. Sometimes I don't think she even realizes how big she is.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
