<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Eat; Service Compris</title>
    <meta content="10food.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="87" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/magazine/10food-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853450"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Food: The Way We Eat"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Per Se (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Randy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Keller, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Seafood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kitchens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kitchens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Central Park (NYC)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Keller, Thomas</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E1D81130F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1354" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Eat; Service Compris</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Service Compris</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Randy Kennedy</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Randy Kennedy article on meals enjoyed by staff at Per Se, Thomas Keller's restaurant overlooking Central Park; photos; recipes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The chef Thomas Keller's affection for culinary quotation marks -- ''macaroni and cheese'' made with orzo and lobster; ''bacon and eggs'' with braised pig's head and quail eggs -- is his signature, a stylistic calling card as particular as a Hemingway cadence or a Tiger Woods swing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It’s not just the rich who chow down at Per Se.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The chef Thomas Keller's affection for culinary quotation marks -- ''macaroni and cheese'' made with orzo and lobster; ''bacon and eggs'' with braised pig's head and quail eggs -- is his signature, a stylistic calling card as particular as a Hemingway cadence or a Tiger Woods swing.</p>
        <p>But the pizza made at Per Se, Keller's four-star restaurant overlooking Central Park, is not ''pizza.'' It is just pizza. As in, ''Hey, you guys wanna order a pizza?'' And yet it is pretty good, as you might expect, made all the more alluring because you will never be able to order it from the $250-per-person tasting menu, no matter how much you polish your platinum card. The 70 or so people who do get a slice or two every Friday -- apparently the great American pizza day everywhere -- were waiting for it recently with the lean, hungry look of kids in a long cafeteria line. But they had to wait a few more minutes: baking in the massive Baxter oven were loaves of bread flavored with squid ink.</p>
        <p>''When we open that door,'' warned Peter Endriss, Per Se's head baker, ''it's going to smell like low tide in here.'' (It did, courtesy of the celebrated Parisian chef, Yannick Alléno, who was borrowing part of Per Se's kitchen during a New York visit.)</p>
        <p>Endriss, a former civil engineer who got bored thinking about bridge inspections, crowds the role of pizza maker into his busy baking schedule in order to observe that hallowed restaurant tradition known as the family or staff meal. It's the time when people who make and serve food for a living finally get to take a busman's break and feed themselves. In European kitchens, such meals tend to be sit-down affairs, a final civilized huddle before the hordes arrive. In America, the meals can take wildly different forms, too often that of warmed-over takeout -- ''a lot of hot wings thrown in a pan,'' as Christopher Monaco, an expediter at Per Se, put it.</p>
        <p>There are notable exceptions, like Chanterelle in SoHo, whose staff meals are so elaborate they yielded their own cookbook. And in the empire of Keller, recently named restaurateur of the year by the James Beard Foundation, their importance takes on an almost religious intensity, a feeling that they are as integral to his restaurants' success as a preternaturally perfect brunoise.</p>
        <p>This is partly a function of biography. One of Keller's first jobs behind a stove was in a Rhode Island hotel, working for Roland Henin, a chef from Lyon. Cooking for the kitchen staff was among his duties. ''If you can make great food for these people,'' Keller wrote in the cookbook for French Laundry, his Napa Valley restaurant, where he spends much of his time, ''then someday you'll be a great chef.'' To which he appended a ''maybe.''</p>
        <p>Recently, over the course of four spring days, I ate on one side of Per Se's kitchen door, then on the other -- in the dining room -- and finally back in the kitchen again, trying to get a sense of how a humble staff meal can provide a subtext for the kind of highly choreographed dinners, nine courses, that are the restaurant's trademark.</p>
        <p>Often the fascination was simply in seeing how ingredients were alchemized, how that same English cucumber, vacuumed, compressed and barely recognizable in a Sunday-night salad, became the dice in a fine, simple yogurt sauce Monday afternoon for a North African family meal of lamb and falafel.</p>
        <p>But the real insight came in seeing the deep satisfaction, and care, the staff took in cooking for themselves, how the same spirit pervades the highest and the lowest incarnations of eating. Endriss, for example, makes sure that the pizza dough (made with the artisanal flour used for Per Se's ciabatta) is retarded overnight to improve the texture. A young chef sprinkled Hawaiian sea salt on top of the hummus with the care of a jeweler setting precious stones. These are people, of course, who have insanely high expectations for food, like Jonathan Benno, Per Se's intense chef de cuisine, who bears much of the responsibility for keeping its stars. He is not a man for whom smiling seems to come easily. And yet he grins when describing the buttermilk-soaked chicken that is the staff-meal specialty of Chico Aguilar, a sous-chef from Mexico. ''He makes arguably one of the best fried chickens in the world,'' Benno pronounced as he sliced fillets of glistening black bass for dinner.</p>
        <p>I sat down in a breezeway with the waiters and captains for the North-African feast -- the highlight of which was an intensely flavored leg of lamb, the creation of a young saucier. As I got up from the table, one of the waiters wanted to make sure I didn't miss dessert: Girl Scout cookies, the peanut-butter-sandwich kind, which someone happened to bring in.</p>
        <p>My favorite, I told him.</p>
        <p>''Yes,'' he said. ''We read minds here.''</p>
        <p>Falafel</p>
        <p>3 cups chickpeas</p>
        <p>1/2 cup plus 1 tablespoon bulgur</p>
        <p>3 medium yellow onions, roughly chopped</p>
        <p>15 cloves garlic, peeled</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons whole cumin seed</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons whole coriander seed</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon whole black peppercorns</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon kosher salt, plus more to taste</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons finely chopped mint</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons finely chopped cilantro</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons finely chopped parsley</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons white sesame seeds</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons baking soda</p>
        <p>1 to 2 quarts canola oil.</p>
        <p>1. Place the chickpeas and bulgur each in a bowl and add water to cover by 2 inches. Cover and soak overnight.</p>
        <p>2. Drain well and grind through the small dye of a meat grinder into a large bowl. Grind the onions and garlic through the meat grinder into a bowl set under a fine-mesh strainer. Press on the onions to release the excess juice. Discard the juices, then add the onion mixture to the chickpea mixture.</p>
        <p>3. In a small skillet over medium heat, toast the cumin and coriander until fragrant. Transfer to a spice grinder, add the peppercorns and grind into a powder. Transfer the spices to the chickpea mixture, along with the salt, mint, cilantro, parsley and sesame seeds. Stir to combine. Mix in the baking soda and let stand for 30 minutes. Season to taste with salt.</p>
        <p>4. Heat a medium pot filled 2 inches with canola oil to 350 degrees. Using your hands, shape the chickpea mixture into 2-inch balls. Fry in batches for 3 minutes or until dark brown and cooked through. Serve with hummus, raita and pita bread. Makes 32 pieces, serves 8.</p>
        <p>Leg of Lamb</p>
        <p>1 cup whole plain yogurt</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon smoked sweet Spanish paprika</p>
        <p>1 1/2 teaspoons ground cumin</p>
        <p>1 1/2 teaspoons ground coriander</p>
        <p>1 head garlic, peeled</p>
        <p>1/4 cup plus 1 tablespoon extra-virgin olive oil</p>
        <p>1/2 cup fresh lemon juice</p>
        <p>1/3 cup packed mint leaves</p>
        <p>1/4 cup kosher salt, plus more as needed</p>
        <p>Freshly ground black pepper</p>
        <p>1 8-to-10 pound leg of American lamb, boned and butterflied</p>
        <p>1/2 loaf French bread, cut into 1/2 -inch thick slices.</p>
        <p>1. In a food processor, combine the yogurt, paprika, cumin, coriander, garlic, olive oil, lemon juice, mint and 1/4 cup kosher salt. Pulse until the mint and garlic are finely chopped.</p>
        <p>2. Season the lamb on all sides with salt and black pepper. Lay the lamb fat-side down, roll into a tight cylinder and tie with cooking twine. Place in a container just large enough to hold it. Pour the marinade over the lamb and massage it into the meat. Dip both sides of the bread pieces into the marinade and place evenly over the meat. Cover and refrigerate overnight.</p>
        <p>3. Preheat oven to 425 degrees. Transfer the lamb to a large roasting pan, discard the bread and reserve the excess marinade. Baste the lamb with the marinade. Cook in the oven until a meat thermometer reads 130 degrees, for medium rare, about 2 to 2 1/2 hours depending on the thickness of the lamb. Baste with the marinade from time to time during the first hour of cooking. Remove from oven, tent with foil and let rest for 20 minutes before slicing. Serves 10 to 12.</p>
        <p>Food: The Way We Eat Randy Kennedy is a reporter for The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Randy Kennedy is a reporter for The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
