<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BEST SELLERS: June 10, 2007</title>
    <meta content="Hardcover.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853414"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E6DD1530F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1258" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BEST SELLERS: June 10, 2007</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended May 26, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>Editor's Choice</p>
        <p>ON CHESIL BEACH, by Ian McEwan. (Nan A. Talese/Doubleday, $22.) Consisting largely of a single sex scene played out on a couple's wedding night, this seeming novel of manners is as much a horror story as any McEwan has written. AFTER DARK, by Haruki Murakami. Translated by Jay Rubin. (Knopf, $22.95.) A tale of two sisters, one awake all night, one asleep for months.Right Livelihoods: Three Novellas, by Rick Moody. (Little, Brown, $23.99.) In the longest story here, New Yorkers react with passivity and denial after a nuclear attack in Lower Manhattan.A DAY AT THE BEACH, by Helen Schulman. (Houghton Mifflin, $24.) The events of 9/11 upend the lives of a glamorous TriBeCa couple.CONSIDERING DORIS DAY, by Tom Santopietro. (Thomas Dunne/St. Martin's, $25.95.) Avoiding sensationalism, this sympathetic biography concentrates on Day's multifaceted career.The Life of Kingsley Amis, by Zachary Leader. (Pantheon, $39.95.) The author of ''Lucky Jim'' turned drunkenness, bonhomie and lechery into the sources of serious literary pleasure.THE MINISTRY OF SPECIAL CASES, by Nathan Englander. (Knopf, $25.) A novel of a Jewish family caught up in Argentina's ''Dirty War.'' SHROOM: A Cultural History of the Magic Mushroom, by Andy Letcher. (Ecco/HarperCollins, $25.95.) Letcher's revisionist history is a delightful journalistic addition to the ''trip lit'' genre. SPY WARS: Moles, Mysteries, and Deadly Games, by Tennent H. Bagley. (Yale University, $28.) A former counterintelligence officer takes a provocative view of the case of the K.G.B. defector Yuri Nosenko, an unresolved cold-war mystery.Alias the Cat! by Kim Deitch. (Pantheon, $23.) In graphic-autobiographical mode, Deitch follows Waldo the Cat, his foul-mouthed feline muse, from one strange world to the next.Shadowland, by Kim Deitch. (Fantagraphics, paper, $18.95.) In this crazy, invigorating comic collection, Deitch charts the scoundrel's progress of the creepily clown-faced lout Al Ledicker. The full reviews of these and other recent books are on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended May 26, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>Editor's Choice</p>
        <p>ON CHESIL BEACH, by Ian McEwan. (Nan A. Talese/Doubleday, $22.) Consisting largely of a single sex scene played out on a couple's wedding night, this seeming novel of manners is as much a horror story as any McEwan has written. AFTER DARK, by Haruki Murakami. Translated by Jay Rubin. (Knopf, $22.95.) A tale of two sisters, one awake all night, one asleep for months.Right Livelihoods: Three Novellas, by Rick Moody. (Little, Brown, $23.99.) In the longest story here, New Yorkers react with passivity and denial after a nuclear attack in Lower Manhattan.A DAY AT THE BEACH, by Helen Schulman. (Houghton Mifflin, $24.) The events of 9/11 upend the lives of a glamorous TriBeCa couple.CONSIDERING DORIS DAY, by Tom Santopietro. (Thomas Dunne/St. Martin's, $25.95.) Avoiding sensationalism, this sympathetic biography concentrates on Day's multifaceted career.The Life of Kingsley Amis, by Zachary Leader. (Pantheon, $39.95.) The author of ''Lucky Jim'' turned drunkenness, bonhomie and lechery into the sources of serious literary pleasure.THE MINISTRY OF SPECIAL CASES, by Nathan Englander. (Knopf, $25.) A novel of a Jewish family caught up in Argentina's ''Dirty War.'' SHROOM: A Cultural History of the Magic Mushroom, by Andy Letcher. (Ecco/HarperCollins, $25.95.) Letcher's revisionist history is a delightful journalistic addition to the ''trip lit'' genre. SPY WARS: Moles, Mysteries, and Deadly Games, by Tennent H. Bagley. (Yale University, $28.) A former counterintelligence officer takes a provocative view of the case of the K.G.B. defector Yuri Nosenko, an unresolved cold-war mystery.Alias the Cat! by Kim Deitch. (Pantheon, $23.) In graphic-autobiographical mode, Deitch follows Waldo the Cat, his foul-mouthed feline muse, from one strange world to the next.Shadowland, by Kim Deitch. (Fantagraphics, paper, $18.95.) In this crazy, invigorating comic collection, Deitch charts the scoundrel's progress of the creepily clown-faced lout Al Ledicker. The full reviews of these and other recent books are on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>05,05,06,64</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  Last  On</p>
        <p>Week  Week  List  FICTION</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>1  A THOUSAND SPLENDID SUNS, by Khaled Hosseini. (Riverhead, $25.95.) A friendship between two women in Afghanistan against the backdrop of 30 years of war; from the author of ''The Kite Runner.''</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>1  THE OVERLOOK, by Michael Connelly. (Little, Brown, $21.99.) The Los Angeles detective Harry Bosch tangles with the F.B.I. and Homeland Security as he tries to solve the case of a murdered physicist with access to radioactive materials.</p>
        <p>3  1  3  THE 6TH TARGET, by James Patterson and Maxine Paetro. (Little, Brown, $27.99.) In San Francisco, children are disappearing, and Detective Lindsay Boxer and the Women's Murder Club investigate.</p>
        <p>4  3  2  INVISIBLE PREY, by John Sandford. (Putnam, $26.95.) The Minneapolis detective Lucas Davenport finds connections between the murder of several elderly residents and a political scandal.</p>
        <p>5  2  2  BAD LUCK AND TROUBLE, by Lee Child. (Delacorte, $26.) Jack Reacher must discover who is hunting down members of a team of former military investigators.</p>
        <p>6  6  6  THE CHILDREN OF HÃRIN, by J. R. R. Tolkien. Edited by Christopher Tolkien. Illustrated by Alan Lee. (Houghton Mifflin, $26.) In Middle-earth, an evil lord wants to destroy his rival's children.</p>
        <p>7  4  4  THE YIDDISH POLICEMEN'S UNION, by Michael Chabon. (HarperCollins, $26.95.) A detective investigates a neighbor's murder in a Jewish settlement in Alaska.</p>
        <p>8  5  5  SIMPLE GENIUS, by David Baldacci. (Warner, $26.99.) Two former Secret Service agents investigate a scientist's murder while one battles her own demons.</p>
        <p>9  8  4  RANT, by Chuck Palahniuk. (Doubleday, $24.95.) The ''oral biography'' of a serial killer.</p>
        <p>10  14  2  THE QUEST, by Wilbur Smith. (Thomas Dunne, $27.95.) In ancient Egypt, a magus searches for the cause of a series of plagues.</p>
        <p>11*  9  6  THE WOODS, by Harlan Coben. (Dutton, $26.95.) A prosecutor must confront family secrets when new evidence surfaces about a murder and disappearance at a summer camp 20 years earlier.</p>
        <p>12  10  12  NINETEEN MINUTES, by Jodi Picoult. (Atria, $26.95.) The aftermath of a high school shooting reveals the fault lines in a small New Hampshire town.</p>
        <p>13  7  2  Pearl Harbor, by Newt Gingrich and William R. Forstchen. (Thomas Dunne, $25.95.) The buildup to the historic attack, with an alternative ending.</p>
        <p>14  13  6  THE GOOD HUSBAND OF ZEBRA DRIVE, by Alexander McCall Smith. (Pantheon, $21.95.) The eighth novel in the No. 1 Ladies' Detective Agency series.</p>
        <p>15  12  5  BODY SURFING, by Anita Shreve. (Little, Brown, $25.99.) A woman takes a job as a tutor and becomes involved in a wealthy family's tensions and rivalries.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  Last  On</p>
        <p>Week  Week  List  NONFICTION</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>1  THE ASSAULT ON REASON, by Al Gore. (Penguin Press, $25.95.) How the Bush administration has degraded the political environment through secrecy, fear and the rejection of fact-based reasoning.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>1  THE REAGAN DIARIES, by Ronald Reagan. Edited by Douglas Brinkley. (HarperCollins, $35.) Selections from the 40th president's daily White House diaries.</p>
        <p>3  2  7  EINSTEIN, by Walter Isaacson. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $32.) A biography based on newly released personal letters.</p>
        <p>4  1  4  GOD IS NOT GREAT, by Christopher Hitchens. (Twelve, $24.99.) Religion as a malignant force in the world.</p>
        <p>5  7  3  PRESIDENTIAL COURAGE, by Michael Beschloss. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $28.) Profiles of nine presidents who had the courage to make unpopular decisions.</p>
        <p>6  5  15  A LONG WAY GONE, by Ishmael Beah. (Sarah Crichton/Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $22.) A former child soldier from Sierra Leone describes his drug-crazed killing spree and his return to humanity.</p>
        <p>7  6  2  JESUS OF NAZARETH, by Benedict XVI. (Doubleday, $24.95.) The pope discusses Jesus' identity as revealed in the Gospels.</p>
        <p>8  3  4  ANIMAL, VEGETABLE, MIRACLE, by Barbara Kingsolver with Steven L. Hopp and Camille Kingsolver. (HarperCollins, $26.95.) The novelist and her family spend a year eating homegrown or local food.</p>
        <p>9  9  6  WHERE HAVE ALL THE LEADERS GONE?, by Lee Iacocca. (Scribner, $25.) The former C.E.O. of Chrysler protests the lack of political and business leadership on issues like health care and energy policy.</p>
        <p>10  15  2  RICKLES' BOOK, by Don Rickles with David Ritz. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $24.) A memoir by the insult comedian.</p>
        <p>11  13  5  THE BLACK SWAN, by Nassim Nicholas Taleb. (Random House, $26.95.) The role of the unexpected.</p>
        <p>12*  8  4  AT THE CENTER OF THE STORM, by George Tenet. (HarperCollins, $30.) The former director of the Central Intelligence Agency looks back on his career.</p>
        <p>13  4  2  PLATO and A PLATYPUS WALK INTO A BAR, by Thomas Cathcart and Daniel Klein. (Abrams Image, $18.95.) A humorous tour of philosophical traditions.</p>
        <p>14  10  3  TALES FROM Q SCHOOL, by John Feinstein. (Little, Brown, $26.99.) Inside the 2005 PGA Tour Qualifying Tournament, from the author of ''A Good Walk Spoiled.''</p>
        <p>15*  11  8  PAULA DEEN: IT AIN'T ALL ABOUT THE COOKIN', by Paula Deen with Sherry Suib Cohen. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $25.) A memoir with recipes from the Southern cooking impresario.</p>
        <p>16*</p>
        <p>1  BROTHERS, by David Talbot. (Free Press, $28.) An assessment of John F. Kennedy's administration and a plea for a new effort to uncover the truth about his assassination.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
