<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seafood With a View And Breezy Informality</title>
    <meta content="10dineweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/10dinewe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853555"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/PORT CHESTER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ebb Tide Seafood (Port Chester, NY, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, M H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Seafood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907EFDF1F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="818" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seafood With a View And Breezy Informality</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Seafood With a View and Breezy Informality</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By M. H. REED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reed, M H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>M H Reed reviews Ebb Tide Seafood restaurant in Port Chester, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOME readers will soon be eating lobster rolls at Arnold's on the Cape or at LUNCH on the Montauk Highway, but until those lazy days arrive, and for diners spending the summer closer to home, Ebb Tide on the Port Chester waterfront will do nicely.</p>
        <p>On the restaurant's deck, overlooking the Byram River, a soft breeze often blows in with a touch of salty ocean air from across Long Island Sound. You may well imagine yourself on vacation at the shore as you suck down a plate of littlenecks and sip beer from plastic glasses. Plastic flatware and paper plates and napkins complete the utilitarian setting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>You may well imagine yourself on vacation at the shore as you suck down a plate of littlenecks and sip beer from plastic glasses at Ebb Tide in Port Chester.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOME readers will soon be eating lobster rolls at Arnold's on the Cape or at LUNCH on the Montauk Highway, but until those lazy days arrive, and for diners spending the summer closer to home, Ebb Tide on the Port Chester waterfront will do nicely.</p>
        <p>On the restaurant's deck, overlooking the Byram River, a soft breeze often blows in with a touch of salty ocean air from across Long Island Sound. You may well imagine yourself on vacation at the shore as you suck down a plate of littlenecks and sip beer from plastic glasses. Plastic flatware and paper plates and napkins complete the utilitarian setting.</p>
        <p>Despite its informality, Ebb Tide is not the place for some 99-cent fishwich. As in more polished spots, good fresh fish is never cheap; you get what you pay for.</p>
        <p>Salmon here is wild or organically farmed. While fish and chips or coconut shrimp with fries and coleslaw is a moderate $14, and a clam roll or a crab burger $7, if you order market-priced items, you may pay, as we did one evening at the start of crab season, as much as $30 for two gorgeous soft-shell crabs. Right now, even the lobster roll is $14. But the soft homemade Italian roll was outstanding and the filling largely fine lobster meat mingled with some crab and a bare modicum of binder.</p>
        <p>A plate of those littlenecks would be a good way to begin, although, as at the beach, ordering a conventional three-course meal isn't expected. At one table, a party of four shared a bottle of wine and a few platters of fried shrimp and fish (done in 100 percent canola oil). One nearby solo diner seemed happy with the view, a whole steamed lobster and a bottle of beer. And we were pleased with our $17 special of chowder and crab cakes.</p>
        <p>One of the delicious Italian rolls came with deep-flavored seafood chowder, which could have been a meal in itself. Wafting cilantro, this tomato-based soup was rich with big chunks of seafood. A thinner Manhattan clam chowder proved as tasty.</p>
        <p>Most entrees are garnished with one or two sides -- vegetable, rice, fries, coleslaw, tomato salad. If the tomato salad doesn't come with your entree, then order it as a side dish. It's a treat of ripe tomatoes and slivers of sweet red onion, marinated in a generous amount of oil and vinegar and served at room temperature.</p>
        <p>The sautéed entrees -- salmon, juicy scallops, crisp shrimp -- offered a choice of fragrant sauces: garlic and oil, cilantro or pesto. Like all food here, each had lots of flavor.</p>
        <p>Caramel apple pie made a pleasantly sweet ending.</p>
        <p>The people behind the ordering counter are charming, helpful and patient, but first-timers will appreciate knowing the ordering routine, especially when they're holding up a long line of hungry customers. At the counter, take a menu and step to the side until you know what you want. Check out the specials blackboard on the back kitchen wall and, if desired, the beer and wine list above the plastic cutlery and paper napkins near the self-serve coffee machine. Help yourself to a soft drink and a dessert from the refrigerated case. Then order, pay, take the portable items, along with a stand with an assigned number atop and find a seat. Your meal will be brought to you by very pleasant servers.</p>
        <p>And, a big plus, when it's time to leave, there's no waiting for the check. Simply get up and go.</p>
        <p>Ebb Tide Seafood  1 Willett Avenue  Port Chester  (914) 939-4810</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE -- A few fishing nets and shells in a simple riverside building of otherwise zero décor. A bait and tackle shop, a seafood retail store and a big kitchen share the space in the large dining room. Outside, a big popular deck next to the narrow Byram River has umbrellas and picnic tables, which can sometimes be communal. Entrance ramp.</p>
        <p>THE CROWD -- Neat shorts and flip-flops for the multigenerational customers who take the no-frills, cafeteria-style ordering in stride.</p>
        <p>THE BAR -- No bar. Sodas, juices, beers and a short list of standard red and white wines are posted on a blackboard next to the kitchen counter.</p>
        <p>THE BILL -- Lunch and dinner entrees, $12 to $18 (more for seafood at market price). Sandwiches and burgers, $7 to $9, chips or fries included. Discover, MasterCard and Visa accepted.</p>
        <p>WHAT WE LIKE -- Seafood chowder, Manhattan chowder, clams on the half shell; grilled salmon, scallops sauté, soft-shell crabs sauté, lobster roll, tomato salad, vegetable rice; caramel apple pie.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO -- Summer hours: Tuesday to Sunday, 11:45 a.m. to 4 p.m. and 5 p.m. to 9 p.m. The bait and tackle shop and the retail fish shop open at 7 a.m.</p>
        <p>Reviewed June 10, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/PORT CHESTER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
