<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A NIGHT OUT WITH -- Alison Gingeras; Follow That Motoscafo</title>
    <meta content="10nite" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/fashion/10nite.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853615"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="A Night Out With Alison Gingeras"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/A Night Out With</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Venice Biennale</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Venice Biennale</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03EED91F30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="596" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A NIGHT OUT WITH -- Alison Gingeras; Follow That Motoscafo</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Follow That Motoscafo</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIA CHAPLIN</byline>
      <dateline>VENICE</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Venice Biennale -- the art world's most decadent spectacle -- is clogged with baronesses, marquises and Forbes 500 Russian tycoons. But the person parting the velvet ropes with most ease in front of palazzos and villas on Wednesday night was Alison Gingeras, a 33-year-old curator with punkish blond hair and an Hermès scarf tied carelessly around her wrist, which, she proudly pointed out, came from a duty free airport shop in Zurich.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gingeras has put together brow-raising exhibitions at the Pompidou Center in Paris and the Guggenheim Museum in New York and written books on the photographer Guy Bourdin and the painter John Currin. But her latest act has catapulted her into art's tastemaking elite.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The latest act by the 33-year-old curator has catapulted her into art’s tastemaking elite.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Venice Biennale -- the art world's most decadent spectacle -- is clogged with baronesses, marquises and Forbes 500 Russian tycoons. But the person parting the velvet ropes with most ease in front of palazzos and villas on Wednesday night was Alison Gingeras, a 33-year-old curator with punkish blond hair and an Hermès scarf tied carelessly around her wrist, which, she proudly pointed out, came from a duty free airport shop in Zurich.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gingeras has put together brow-raising exhibitions at the Pompidou Center in Paris and the Guggenheim Museum in New York and written books on the photographer Guy Bourdin and the painter John Currin. But her latest act has catapulted her into art's tastemaking elite.</p>
        <p>Last summer, François Pinault, the French billionaire, whose empire includes Christie's auction house, hired her as chief curator for his collection and museums in Venice -- the Palazzo Grassi and Punta Della Dogana, a 17th-century customhouse.</p>
        <p>So at 7 p.m., Ms. Gingeras was working the majestic halls of the Palazzo Grassi at the opening of her exhibition ''Sequence 1.'' The supermodel Naomi Campbell sauntered past a wall painted neon-yellow by the German artist Anselm Reyle, shook hands with Ms. Gingeras and winked. (''That was cool,'' Ms. Gingeras said with a giggle.) A man from the Gagosian Gallery in New York took in a two-story tree made of 2,000 little drawings by Urs Fischer. ''Amazing,'' he said in an expensive pancontinental accent. ''He's an Austrian prince,'' Ms. Gingeras said. ''But he's also a really nice guy.''</p>
        <p>The curators, artists and ascot-wearing collectors all had the same question: what parties was she going to? (Ms. Gingeras's social selections, much like her artist picks, perk up ears like stock tips.) Just then an assistant ran up to Ms. Gingeras. ''F.P.,'' she whispered, code for Mr. Pinault, who was stepping out of his private water taxi.</p>
        <p>''It's like a dream come true,'' Ms. Gingeras said of her new life, as though it were a conceptual art performance and not reality. ''I didn't imagine such a job could exist.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Gingeras is a rare liaison between the artists and the suits. She is friendly with the young artists in her exhibitions, like Roberto Cuoghi and Kristin Baker, and her boyfriend is the Polish artist Piotr Uklanski.</p>
        <p>The crowd thinned, so it seemed a safe time to hit the dinner that Jeffrey Deitch, the New York gallery owner, was giving for Ms. Baker. Ms. Gingeras rounded up her entourage, which included Mr. Uklanski and her mother, visiting from New York to help the couple care for their 10-month-old daughter. They hopped into a motoscafo -- a private water taxi -- courtesy of Mr. Pinault, and beelined it over to the island of Giudecca. ''It's impossible to really party-hop unless you have your own boat,'' Mr. Uklanski reasoned. At Mr. Deitch's rented villa, the doorwoman wouldn't budge until she saw Ms. Gingeras. ''Oh, I didn't know they were with you,'' she said, beaming.</p>
        <p>Inside the courtyard, gangs of artists milled about, ripped T-shirts being the attire of choice for the British artists Sue Webster and Tim Noble and the members of the band Scissor Sisters. Members of Gelitin, the Austrian art collective, tossed hot wax at one another, along with bits of food.</p>
        <p>After dessert, Ms. Gingeras and her group motored along the canal for a party at a restaurant by the Rialto. But, save for a few stragglers, it had moved to the terrace at the Bauer Hotel. Ms. Gingeras pulled over, waved them aboard (a gesture of extreme kindness in Venice) and sped into the night.</p>
        <p>A Night Out With Alison Gingeras</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
