<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sprinting Stars Deliver at N.C.A.A. Meet</title>
    <meta content="10track" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/sports/othersports/10track.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853366"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TRACK AND FIELD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Amateur Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amateur Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Collegiate Athletic Assn</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Florida State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Dix, Walter</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hastings, Natasha</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E1D9163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sprinting Stars Deliver at N.C.A.A. Meet</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sprinting Stars Deliver at N.C.A.A. Meet</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY</byline>
      <dateline>SACRAMENTO, June 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the N.C.A.A. outdoor track and field championships began Wednesday, two juniors, Walter Dix of Florida State and Natasha Hastings of South Carolina, were expected to be the stars. By the time the meet ended Saturday, they had lived up to expectations.</p>
        <p>A closing-day crowd of 10,165 at Hornet Stadium watched Dix, with an uncharacteristically good start, repeat as the men's 200-meter champion, winning the race by four meters in 20.32 seconds. On Friday, he won the 100 and was part of the winning 4x100 relay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Walter Dix of Florida State again became the men’s 200-meter champion, while Natasha Hastings won the women’s 400 and was part of the South Carolina 4x400 team that finished second.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the N.C.A.A. outdoor track and field championships began Wednesday, two juniors, Walter Dix of Florida State and Natasha Hastings of South Carolina, were expected to be the stars. By the time the meet ended Saturday, they had lived up to expectations.</p>
        <p>A closing-day crowd of 10,165 at Hornet Stadium watched Dix, with an uncharacteristically good start, repeat as the men's 200-meter champion, winning the race by four meters in 20.32 seconds. On Friday, he won the 100 and was part of the winning 4x100 relay.</p>
        <p>He was the first man to win all three races in the same N.C.A.A. meet since John Carlos in 1969. He is the 22nd sprinter to win the 100 and 200 in the same N.C.A.A. meet, a group that includes Jesse Owens, Ralph Metcalfe, Hal Davis, Bobby Morrow, Carlos and Justin Gatlin.</p>
        <p>''I still have the 100-meter record to get,'' Dix said. ''It's my next thing to chase to.''</p>
        <p>In a 64-minute span, Hastings won the women's 400 and was part of the South Carolina 4x400 team that finished second. Her 400 time of 50.15 was the fastest in the world this year and a personal best. In the relay, she made up all but 2 meters of a 15-meter deficit, running the anchor leg in 50.0. Louisiana State won the race in 3 minutes 28.07 seconds, only 0.41 ahead of South Carolina.</p>
        <p>Florida State repeated as the men's team champion with 54 points, followed by L.S.U. (48) and Auburn (34). Arizona State was the women's champion with 60 points, ahead of L.S.U. (53) and Michigan (36).</p>
        <p>Several other runners were impressive during the four days:</p>
        <p>TRINDON HOLLIDAY -- As a freshman at L.S.U. last year, the 5-foot-6 Holliday finished 24th in the men's 100 at the Southeastern Conference outdoor championships, in 11.01. As a sophomore at this meet, he ran 10.02 in winning a semifinal and 10.06 in finishing second in the final. Only three men in the world have run faster this year. ''He ran great, which helped me run great,'' Dix said.</p>
        <p>TOMMY SKIPPER -- In winning the men's pole vault Friday for the second year in a row and third time over all, Skipper, a senior at Oregon, passed until the bar reached 18 feet  1/2 inch. He made that height on his first attempt and no one else cleared it. A strained calf muscle had wiped out most of his outdoor season, leaving him, he said, with ''a lot of rehab and a lot of ups and downs.''</p>
        <p>RHONDA WATKINS -- A sophomore at U.C.L.A., Watkins won the women's long jump Thursday at 22-10. She is coached by Mike Powell, who has held the men's world record since 1991. ''She's not overthinking it,'' he said. ''She's letting it all happen. She competes like she knows she's supposed to win. That's not arrogance; it's confidence.''</p>
        <p>ANDREW ELLERTON -- Ellerton, a fifth-year senior at Michigan from Sudbury, Ontario, started skating at age 2 and played hockey most of his life. But at 5-10, 135 pounds, he is designed more for running. He won the men's 800 Saturday in 1:47.48. ''It may not look it,'' he said, ''but I'm pretty strong.''</p>
        <p>KATIE ERDMAN -- A senior at Michigan, Erdman said: ''I started running in sixth grade because a lot of my friends ran. I was lousy.'' Not anymore. She finished second Saturday in an exciting women's 800, in a personal-best 1:59.35, a step behind Alysia Johnson of California (1:59.29). But they will not have a rematch at the USA outdoor championships June 21-24 in Indianapolis. ''I've got something more important,'' Erdman said. ''I will be married that weekend.''</p>
        <p>LOPEZ LOMONG -- A sophomore at Northern Arizona and a native of Sudan, Lomong took the lead in the men's 1,500 with 40 meters left Saturday and beat Leonel Manzno of Texas by less than half a second, in 3:37.07. Lomong came to the United States six years ago after he had spent 10 years in a refugee camp. He expects to become a United States citizen June 19.</p>
        <p>TRACK AND FIELD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
