<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tribute to Those Who Bear Witness</title>
    <meta content="10klaw" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/movies/10klaw.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853482"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Human Rights Watch International Film Festival</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klawans, Stuart</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Human Rights Watch</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E4DF1E30F933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1188" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tribute to Those Who Bear Witness</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tribute to Those Who Bear Witness</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART KLAWANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klawans, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Human Rights Watch International Film Festival at Lincoln Center, which will show films that both praise and challenge role of photography in human rights; several films discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FILM festival themes are like butterflies in a Rorschach blot -- or are those elephants? -- coalescing and vanishing in the blink of an eye. Watch two dozen documentaries and feature films from around the world, and let whatever patterns you like dance on your retina.</p>
        <p>But a more focused experience is available in this year's Human Rights Watch International Film Festival (Friday through June 28 at Lincoln Center's Walter Reade Theater). A verifiable theme -- a highly appropriate one too -- has come together at this festival's core, in films that both praise and challenge the role of photography in human rights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Human Rights Watch International Film Festival explores the notion that human rights might not exist without a camera nearby.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FILM festival themes are like butterflies in a Rorschach blot -- or are those elephants? -- coalescing and vanishing in the blink of an eye. Watch two dozen documentaries and feature films from around the world, and let whatever patterns you like dance on your retina.</p>
        <p>But a more focused experience is available in this year's Human Rights Watch International Film Festival (Friday through June 28 at Lincoln Center's Walter Reade Theater). A verifiable theme -- a highly appropriate one too -- has come together at this festival's core, in films that both praise and challenge the role of photography in human rights.</p>
        <p>Among the films ''The City of Photographers,'' by Sebastián Moreno Mardones, reveals how a group of brave photojournalists in 1980s Chile encouraged opposition to Gen. Augusto Pinochet's regime. ''The Devil Came on Horseback,'' by Annie Sundberg and Ricki Stern, tells the story of Brian Steidle, a former Marine Corps captain who took more than 1,000 horrific photos of the current genocide in Darfur, then used them to help raise an outcry. ''Manufactured Landscapes,'' by Jennifer Baichwal, comments and expands on the work of Edward Burtynsky, an art photographer who visits scenes of vast social and environmental disruption -- most recently in newly industrialized China -- and makes large pictures of them.</p>
        <p>Though different in setting, subject matter and method, all three films remind us that the enforcement of rights, or even the recognition of them, often begins with the click of a shutter. ''The very notion of atrocity,'' Susan Sontag wrote, ''of war crime, is associated with the expectation of photographic evidence.'' To understand how this came to be so, you could review several centuries of history (as Ms. Sontag did in her book ''Regarding the Pain of Others'') or simply jump to the critical moment. ''If there was one year when the power of photographs to define, not merely record, the most abominable realities trumped all the complex narratives,'' she wrote, ''surely it was 1945,'' when films and photographs emerged from Bergen-Belsen, Buchenwald, Dachau and Hiroshima.</p>
        <p>These pictures were crucial not only because of the terrible witness they bore but also because they circulated everywhere, a fact not lost on the photographers. In 1947 four distinguished photojournalists founded the Magnum Photos agency with the goal of working and publishing internationally. ''In Magnum's voice,'' Ms. Sontag wrote, ''photography declared itself a global enterprise.''</p>
        <p>One year later came the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, the first recognition in international law of the rights of individuals.</p>
        <p>No doubt there was as much coincidence as cause and effect in this chain of events. But if the rights first published in 1948 were to become more than ''a pious set of clichés'' (as Michael Ignatieff has put it), there had to be institutions to help enable their exercise: sets of practices and relationships ready-made for what Mr. Ignatieff called ''the advocacy revolution.'' One such institution was the new global network of photographers of conscience.</p>
        <p>The continuing importance of this network is visible every day in newspapers. It's demonstrated as well in a sidebar exhibition to this year's Human Rights Watch Film Festival. A gallery show, ''On the Frontlines,'' in the Walter Reade Theater's lobby, presents recent photographs by seven photojournalists who have been working with the festival's parent organization, Human Rights Watch. Faced with these images, the group maintains, ''no government can say 'it never happened' or 'we didn't know.' ''</p>
        <p>This may be true, as far as it goes, but the festival's movies go even further. They raise difficult questions about photojournalism and about human rights advocacy itself.</p>
        <p>When you watch Mr. Burtynsky high up on a platform in ''Manufactured Landscapes,'' directing Chinese workers like extras on a movie set, and then (in a later scene) view the resulting pictures on an art gallery's walls, you may be reminded of the persistent accusation that human rights are a parochial invention of Westerners, imposed for their authors' benefit on other people around the world. Fortunately ''Manufactured Landscapes'' incorporates something Mr. Burtynsky excludes: close-ups of people who in his photographs would be antlike or absent.</p>
        <p>In favor of Mr. Burtynsky's artworks, which are so impressive and so impersonal, you might say that they bring critical realities to light through an inherent power of photography, its ability to show what the unaided eye cannot see. In favor of Jennifer Baichwal's documentary (which, after its festival screening, will open in New York at Film Forum on June 20), you might say that it achieves its own grandeur without losing the ''human'' in human rights.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burtynsky and Ms. Baichwal do bear witness; but what's the use of testimony if no one acts on it? That's the question tormenting Brian Steidle in ''The Devil Came on Horseback.'' Still in his 20s when he left the Marines, Mr. Steidle came to Darfur in 2004 as an employee of the African Union, hired to monitor a cease-fire in Sudan's civil war. What he found was not a tenuous peace but wholesale, government-sponsored slaughter. And as an unarmed observer, he could do nothing but watch and take photographs.</p>
        <p>''The Devil Came on Horseback'' presents a sample of the awful evidence he amassed while tracing Mr. Steidle's metamorphosis from a military man to a photographer and activist. At the end of the film he remains shocked and angry that his pictures haven't changed the situation in Darfur. But it's no small thing that they've changed thousands of people, most of all himself.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Steidle has learned, the act of picturing atrocities exacts a price from photojournalists. This is also a lesson of ''The City of Photographers,'' a cinematic group portrait of Chile's extraordinary Association of Independent Photographers. That film's subjects, seen both today and in action 25 years ago, wanted to record the gathering protests against General Pinochet. So they formed the association to give themselves press credentials, then went into the streets in clusters for self-protection.</p>
        <p>In this case there was no question about the photographers' efficacy (police beatings were their testimonials), nor could any of these people have been called interlopers (though one did come from Brazil). The moral and emotional toll of their work is another matter. ''I suddenly saw us as a flock of vultures, drawn to blood,'' one photographer says. Another says: ''I came to realize that I needed the police. You become addicted to fear, and to overcoming your fear.''</p>
        <p>Today, as they look back, many of these people speak with sorrow as much as pride. But for the most resilient, the work they began with the association has never stopped. One man, who maintains an archive of the disappeared, was disturbed that he had names but not faces for many of Pinochet's victims. In one of the most moving sequences he travels around Chile, contacting family members to ask for old photos.</p>
        <p>The survivors understand. What's at stake in the request is not a mere image but the most basic of rights. As one woman says, having earned the knowledge the hard way, ''Not to have a photograph of your family is like not having a part in the history of mankind.''</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
