<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pletcher Halts Drought In Style</title>
    <meta content="10sidebar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/10/sports/othersports/10sidebar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853388"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Pletcher, Todd</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Velazquez, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E7D8163FF933A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pletcher Halts Drought In Style</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pletcher Halts Drought in Style</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After all these years and all those tries, Todd Pletcher finally figured out what it took to win a Triple Crown race: have the best horse.</p>
        <p>One of horse racing's most mystifying droughts ended yesterday. Pletcher, whose dominance over the sport had extended to everything but the Triple Crown races, finally won a classic race, ending an 0-for-28 drought when Rags to Riches won the 139th running of the Belmont Stakes. There were no particular secrets to his success; he did not do anything different in his prerace training routines. Instead, he relied on a very talented filly who was good enough to get the job done.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After all these years and all those tries, Todd Pletcher finally figured out what it took to win a Triple Crown race: have the best horse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After all these years and all those tries, Todd Pletcher finally figured out what it took to win a Triple Crown race: have the best horse.</p>
        <p>One of horse racing's most mystifying droughts ended yesterday. Pletcher, whose dominance over the sport had extended to everything but the Triple Crown races, finally won a classic race, ending an 0-for-28 drought when Rags to Riches won the 139th running of the Belmont Stakes. There were no particular secrets to his success; he did not do anything different in his prerace training routines. Instead, he relied on a very talented filly who was good enough to get the job done.</p>
        <p>''It's a real credit to how good this filly is,'' he said shortly after Rags to Riches defeated Curlin by a head to win the Belmont Stakes.</p>
        <p>Throughout the losing streak, Pletcher had never panicked or lost his composure. At times, though, he would defend his Triple Crown record, reminding anyone who cared to listen that several of the horses he had run in Triple Crown events had deficiencies and were long shots.</p>
        <p>But when Pletcher started five horses in this year's Kentucky Derby and not one seriously threatened, it began to appear that his magic was never going to work in a Triple Crown race. He did no better in this year's Preakness Stakes, where neither of his starters mounted a challenge. He came into yesterday's Belmont Stakes having gone 0 for 19 in the Derby, 0 for 3 in the Preakness and 0 for 6 in the Belmont.</p>
        <p>Pletcher has won three consecutive Eclipse Awards as the nation's outstanding trainer and has set several records, including most earnings in a year. With a massive stable loaded with quality horses, he is unquestionably the sport's top trainer.</p>
        <p>A day before this year's Kentucky Derby, Rags to Riches won the prestigious Kentucky Oaks at Churchill Downs, but Pletcher's good fortune did not last long. He did not dwell on his Derby failures and began to consider whether he could pull off a Triple Crown victory with a filly, something that rarely happens. Before yesterday, the last filly to win the Belmont was Tanya in 1905.</p>
        <p>''Maybe that was my problem,'' Pletcher joked. ''I've been looking with the wrong gender all this time.''</p>
        <p>But even on the day he won a Triple Crown race, nothing came easily. Rags to Riches had a formidable opponent in the Preakness winner, Curlin.</p>
        <p>''We couldn't do it the easy way,'' Pletcher said. ''This is pretty special when you look at the historical perspective. If you look at the statistics, no filly had won it in 102 years. That's pretty intimidating stuff.''</p>
        <p>The victory was also special for John Velazquez, Pletcher's primary rider. He also came into the race with no victories in 20 Triple Crown races. Velazquez got the mount only because Garrett Gomez had committed to ride Hard Spun before Rags to Riches was added to the field.</p>
        <p>''There's no word to describe this,'' Velazquez said. ''Obviously, I hadn't won a Triple Crown race and it was getting old. Looking back, like Todd said earlier, you have to have the right horse for the right race and the right circumstances. I think this was our best chance here today with this filly, and we got it done.''</p>
        <p>It is too early to make any predictions about the 2008 Kentucky Derby, but there is little doubt that Pletcher will be there with strength and numbers.</p>
        <p>He is given dozens of impeccably bred 2-year-olds to train each year, most of them with tremendous potential. Velazquez said there would be no more droughts.</p>
        <p>''We've stopped it,'' Velazquez said of the Triple Crown slump. ''From now on, you will see, everything turns around.''</p>
        <p>GELDING DEFEATS YOUNGER FOES -- Better Talk Now rallied up the fence yesterday to win the $400,000 Manhattan Handicap by a head in the richest race on the Belmont Stakes undercard.</p>
        <p>Better Talk Now, an 8-year-old gelding and the oldest horse in the field, split rivals in the deep stretch to earn his 14th victory in 39 starts. Better Talk Now, trained by Graham Motion, ran the one and a quarter miles on the firm course in 2 minutes 2.39 seconds.</p>
        <p>The trainer Todd Pletcher went to the bench to capture the $250,000 Acorn Stakes for 3-year-old fillies with Cotton Blossom. Cotton Blossom was the replacement for Pletcher's top filly, Rags to Riches.</p>
        <p>Teuflesberg, 17th in the Kentucky Derby, rebounded to win the $250,000 Woody Stephens Stakes for 3-year-olds. My Typhoon scored a front-running victory in the $294,000 Just A Game Stakes for fillies and mares on the turf, and Will He Shine took advantage of a horrible trip for the even-money favorite Bordonaro to win the $200,000 True North Handicap. (AP)</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
