<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Antiques</title>
    <meta content="08anti" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/arts/design/08anti.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852865"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Antiques"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Sotheby's Holdings Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Christie's</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E5DE1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1120" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Antiques</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At a London Fair, a Helping Hand, a Discerning Eye</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Wendy Moonan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At a London Fair, A Helping Hand, A Discerning Eye</p>
        <p>Because some people find the process of acquiring antiques intimidating, Clarion Arts, the organizer of the Summer Fair Olympia in London, has sought out an impartial team of experts to accompany visitors around that arts and antiques fair this week.</p>
        <p>The service is intended to help newcomers survey 300 international dealers at the fair (summerfairolympia.com), which opened yesterday and continues through June 17.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An impartial team of experts has been created to help newcomers survey 300 international dealers at the Summer Fair Olympia in London.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At a London Fair, A Helping Hand, A Discerning Eye</p>
        <p>Because some people find the process of acquiring antiques intimidating, Clarion Arts, the organizer of the Summer Fair Olympia in London, has sought out an impartial team of experts to accompany visitors around that arts and antiques fair this week.</p>
        <p>The service is intended to help newcomers survey 300 international dealers at the fair (summerfairolympia.com), which opened yesterday and continues through June 17.</p>
        <p>The experts -- in antique furniture, jewelry and 20th-century art -- are being provided by a firm founded by Tim Corfield, a second-generation antiques dealer, and his partner, Daniel Morris, a furniture specialist at Sotheby's for a decade. Corfield Morris Ltd., based in London, normally advises private banks and individual clients, many of them American. It has previously given tours to select Olympia visitors, but this year it will try to accommodate anyone who prebooks the service (by calling 011-44-77-98-88-1383).</p>
        <p>''We want to help people who have never bought antiques before,'' Mr. Corfield said about his involvement in this year's Olympia fair. ''We demystify the whole process. We take people by the hand and show them why a given piece costs what it does. We are trying to make sure people buy the right things, at every price level. We ask: 'Is this piece a good example of its kind? Is it a good value? Is it particularly rare? Is the condition original? Does it have wonderful color? An interesting provenance?' ''</p>
        <p>Or has it been stripped down, repaired in a hidden way or given a false patina?</p>
        <p>Speaking of his firm's normal business, Mr. Corfield said: ''A typical client might be someone who has just bought a house and wants to furnish it. A lot of clients don't wish their decorator to choose the actual art and antiques. Our first priority is to teach the client to become a collector rather than just a furnisher. Working with us will help him understand furniture and that if he spends his money wisely, he will end up with a collection, not a bunch of furniture.''</p>
        <p>The firm makes its money by charging commissions on purchases. ''We work on a sliding scale,'' Mr. Corfield said. ''We charge about 20 percent of the price of less expensive pieces,'' he added. ''When you get to £100,000,'' about $200,000, it's about 10 percent.</p>
        <p>The fee scale will apply to any purchases made at the fair by those using the experts' services.</p>
        <p>''We have clients looking for specific objects and collectors who want us to tell them about anything we see that's great,'' Mr. Morris said. ''We also help decorators find things.''</p>
        <p>Recently a client was looking for a fine 18th-century stool. Mr. Morris contacted his network of dealers in English antiques, attended the previews of the furniture sales at the auction houses in New York and London and scouted some antiques fairs.</p>
        <p>He was enthusiastic about Lot 20 in Christie's sale on April 20 of English furniture in New York: a George II walnut stool with cabriole legs, a seat rail with a carved shell, ball and claw feet and a padded seat covered in colorful antique needlework.</p>
        <p>In April a reporter watched as he turned it upside down, noting that the webbing underneath was 19th century, that the corner blocks and a pine rail had been replaced and that the seat rail had some long-ago worm damage that was no longer of concern. (He confirmed this by shaking the stool vigorously, to see that no new dust came out of the wormholes.)</p>
        <p>''It has a lovely, crusty old surface and a thick veneer that had been cut by hand,'' he said. ''The legs are solid, and the brackets do not appear to have been replaced. You rarely see good walnut furniture in such fine condition.''</p>
        <p>He bought the stool for his client for the hammer price of $42,000. It was estimated at $15,000 to $25,000.</p>
        <p>''Always buy the best you can,'' he said. ''It will retain its value.''</p>
        <p>He was the underbidder for a George III mahogany triple-chairback settee whose arms had scrolled, carved eagle heads. Estimated at $5,000 to $10,000, it sold for a hammer price of $65,000.</p>
        <p>''Our role is to tell people when to stop bidding,'' Mr. Corfield noted.</p>
        <p>When the firm buys a piece for a client at auction, it bases the commission on the hammer price, not the final price that includes the added buyer's premium of the auction house.</p>
        <p>''We never charge clients for our time,'' Mr. Morris said, adding that they advise people who are collecting at all price levels. ''Our bottom line is to offer value. We tell clients what they should and should not buy and where they might find other possibilities for less money.''</p>
        <p>The goal, he said, is to make the purchasing process simple and transparent. ''We have an open-book policy,'' Mr. Morris added. ''We don't take anything from the dealers, and we show all receipts.''</p>
        <p>Buying at auction, he noted, involves not only paying a buyer's premium, taxes and delivery, but also the cost of repairs and restoration.</p>
        <p>''The price at auction might be reasonable or high, depending on who else is bidding,'' Mr. Corfield said. ''If you buy from a dealer, you know the price before you decide to buy and that the piece will be in good enough condition for immediate use.''</p>
        <p>Corfield Morris is one of a handful of firms that offer such expert advice to collectors of antiques. Others include Thierry Millerand, a New York specialist in 18th-century French furniture; Bill Pallot, a Paris expert on 18th-century French furniture; and Cristina Grajales, a New York adviser and dealer in 20th-century decorative arts.</p>
        <p>Some of today's most renowned decorators employ such experts, especially when designing residences for wealthy clients who are serious collectors.</p>
        <p>''My role is to protect the client, particularly the client who wants only the best of the best,'' said Jacques Grange, a Paris designer who has done projects with Philippe Niarchos, Yves Saint-Laurent, Ronald Lauder and the financier Leon Black. ''Such experts are worthwhile, and I use them a lot,'' Mr. Grange added. ''With them we are secure.''</p>
        <p>In addition Clarion Arts and Tania Buckrell-Pos, an expert on 20th-century art at Corfield Morris, have organized a program this year for a group of Americans coming to the fair, most interior designers. It includes a private dinner with Princess Michael of Kent, president of Partridge Fine Art in London; a tour of the Wallace Collection with the curator Jeremy Warren; and a reception at Winfield House, a neo-Georgian mansion built by the American heiress Barbara Hutton that is now the residence of the United States ambassador to the Court of St. James's.</p>
        <p>Antiques</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
