<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Alaska, Bribery Investigation Looks at 'Uncle Ted'</title>
    <meta content="08alaska" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/us/08alaska.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852909"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Alaska</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Stevens, Ted</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE0DC1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Alaska, Bribery Investigation Looks at 'Uncle Ted'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bribery Investigation Looks at Senator Stevens</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM YARDLEY; David D. Kirkpatrick in Washington contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yardley, William</byline>
      <dateline>GIRDWOOD, Alaska</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The neighbors of Senator Ted Stevens occasionally catch a glimpse of him at his house in this ski resort outside Anchorage.</p>
        <p>Sometimes he is flanked by aides and security. Sometimes he is relaxing on the deck. And sometimes he can be spotted pummeling a boxing bag like a prizefighter, staying tough even at age 83. Now, after nearly 40 years of winning legislative battles and unrivaled amounts of federal financing for his home state, Mr. Stevens may be girding for a fight like no other in his career.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A corruption inquiry is examining Senator Ted Stevens’s ties to a former Alaska oil industry executive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The neighbors of Senator Ted Stevens occasionally catch a glimpse of him at his house in this ski resort outside Anchorage.</p>
        <p>Sometimes he is flanked by aides and security. Sometimes he is relaxing on the deck. And sometimes he can be spotted pummeling a boxing bag like a prizefighter, staying tough even at age 83. Now, after nearly 40 years of winning legislative battles and unrivaled amounts of federal financing for his home state, Mr. Stevens may be girding for a fight like no other in his career.</p>
        <p>Questions have arisen about the senator's ties to a former Alaska oil industry executive and about renovations to Mr. Stevens's home here as part of a wide-ranging public corruption inquiry in Alaska by the Department of Justice and the Federal Bureau of Investigation. The investigation has exposed improper links between an oil-field services company, VECO, and lawmakers in the State Legislature, including Mr. Stevens's son, Ben, the former president of the State Senate.</p>
        <p>The former executive, Bill J. Allen, who was the chief executive of VECO, pleaded guilty last month to bribery and other charges. Mr. Allen acknowledged then that the $243,250 that VECO paid to Ben Stevens from 2002 to 2006 for supposed consulting work while he was in the State Senate was instead to pay for ''giving advice, lobbying colleagues and taking official acts in matters before the Legislature,'' according to an outline of the plea.</p>
        <p>Three former state lawmakers and one current one have been indicted. Ben Stevens has not been charged with a crime, but the investigation continues and appears to be expanding. Last week, investigators asked neighbors of Senator Ted Stevens in Girdwood what they knew about a major renovation of his house in 2000. According to the contractor who did most of the work, the project was largely overseen by Mr. Allen, although the senator and his wife, Catherine, wrote checks to pay the bills.</p>
        <p>''It looks so bad,'' the contractor, Augie Paone, said of the scrutiny of the senator. ''But he just happens to be in a bad spot right now because Bill Allen is in a bad spot.''</p>
        <p>The elder Mr. Stevens, a Republican, has strong ties to Mr. Allen. Along with several other men, they jointly bought a racehorse, So Long Birdie, and they sometimes dine together at the Double Musky Inn in Girdwood, a New Orleans-style restaurant owned by another member of the horse racing group, Bob Persons.</p>
        <p>VECO has long been active in state and federal politics, and Mr. Allen was once forced to register as a lobbyist because he spent so much time at the Capitol in Juneau.</p>
        <p>It is unclear whether Mr. Stevens's actions are a central focus of the investigation or if they are under scrutiny for clues they might provide about the actions of others, including his son. A spokesman for the F.B.I. in Anchorage, Eric Gonzalez, declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stevens told The Washington Post this week that he had been told to preserve documents potentially related to the corruption inquiry, but it was not clear whether he had received those instructions from law enforcement officials or from his own lawyers. A spokesman for Mr. Stevens, Aaron Saunders, declined to comment.</p>
        <p>The fact that the investigators are asking questions about Mr. Stevens has surprised many of his longtime supporters, and it has raised questions among some Democrats about whether he might be vulnerable as he seeks a seventh full term in 2008.</p>
        <p>At a campaign kickoff event on May 30, Mr. Stevens suggested he was undaunted. ''I really do at times feel like a warrior,'' he told reporters in Fairbanks.</p>
        <p>The next day, F.B.I. agents knocked on his neighbors' doors here, according to two people who were questioned.</p>
        <p>The senator's home, his official residence in Alaska, is on a street with a mix of houses, some modest and quirky, others more substantial. The house originally had one story. In 2000, a contractor from Anchorage elevated the house on jacks so that a new first floor could be built beneath it, making the house two stories.</p>
        <p>Mr. Paone, also from Anchorage, said he was contacted by VECO executives after the house had been elevated because local contractors could not complete the finishing work before Alaska's short construction season ended.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Paone said he had completed most of the carpentry work to convert the house to two stories, including installing framing, drywall and new kitchen cabinets. The remodeled house has 2,471 square feet of living area, with a taxable value of $420,900, according to property records.</p>
        <p>Although he had been contacted by several VECO officials early on, Mr. Paone said Mr. Allen ''kind of overtook'' the project himself, largely because Mr. Stevens was usually in Washington.</p>
        <p>''The way it was presented to me was, 'I want you to help a friend of ours,' '' Mr. Paone said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Paone said he had been instructed to submit his invoices first to VECO, so they could be checked for accuracy, and then to the Stevenses in Washington. He said he had received checks from Washington on an account that had the names of the senator and his wife. He said he had charged about $100,000 for the work.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't trying to make a huge profit, but I made sure that if anything ever happened, it would be legitimate,'' Mr. Paone said in an interview in his company's offices. ''The stuff I did for him was legitimate, and he paid me for everything that he got billed for.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Paone said he had testified about his work on the house before a grand jury in the corruption case. He said his testimony had taken most of a day.</p>
        <p>The broad federal investigation surfaced nearly a year ago and has ranged from Girdwood to Juneau to commercial fishing in the Northern Pacific. Last year, investigators ordered several commercial fishing companies to submit documents relating to Ben Stevens and Trevor McCabe, a former aide to the elder Mr. Stevens. Both men were on the board of a fisheries marketing group for which the senator has helped win tens of millions of federal dollars, and Ben Stevens, a former boat captain, has been paid thousands of dollars by fishing ventures for consulting work.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stevens was appointed to office in 1968 and has won re-election ever since, usually with at least 70 percent of the vote. Some people suggest he may be keeping a low profile to avoid stirring more trouble for his son. Others say his silence is notable given his history of tangling head-on with critics who have long accused him of using Congress, and federal money, to benefit his family members and friends.</p>
        <p>''Usually, when there's an issue that's come up, he's out there fighting,'' Mayor Mark Begich of Anchorage said of the senator. ''That's not happening on this one.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Begich is a popular Democrat who said he has been contacted recently by national party leaders who want him to run against the senator next year. In a phone interview, Mr. Begich did not rule out a campaign against the senator or Representative Don Young, the state's other longtime force in Washington, who has deep ties to VECO himself.</p>
        <p>''Alaska has changed since the days they were elected,'' Mr. Begich said. ''People want very transparent, open government. The politics of pork is not the politics of the future in national politics. It's all coming to a kind of screeching halt.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Begich said scrutiny of the work on Mr. Stevens's Girdwood house, first reported by The Anchorage Daily News, raised serious questions.</p>
        <p>''In the past, usually, it was just that somebody didn't like him or something he did, but this is different,'' Mr. Begich said.</p>
        <p>Jack Roderick, a Democrat who practiced law with Mr. Stevens in the 1960s and later became mayor of Anchorage, said Mr. Stevens had showed poor judgment at times in mixing friendships and family with politics. He cited the senator's willingness to invest in the racehorse with Mr. Allen.</p>
        <p>''That's not a very good decision,'' Mr. Roderick said. ''Ted knew what Bill Allen was up to; everybody did. Everybody knew he was influencing the Legislature every chance he got. I mean, that's what lobbyists do, but Bill Allen was overstepping bounds.''</p>
        <p>VECO employees have given at least $625,000 to federal candidates and interest groups nationwide since 1990, according to the Center for Responsive Politics. They gave about $180,000 to Don Young and about $70,000 to Mr. Stevens in that period.</p>
        <p>Tim McKeever, the treasurer of the senator's 2008 campaign, said that since 2004 the campaign had received about $8,000 from Mr. Allen and another VECO executive who pleaded guilty to bribery and other charges last month, Richard L. Smith, but that the campaign was donating the money to a charity.</p>
        <p>''We're still going great guns, full steam ahead,'' Mr. McKeever said of the campaign.</p>
        <p>Several people who have been friends with the senator or followed his career for years said they were not aware of another time in which he had been touched directly by a criminal investigation. Many speculated that this one ultimately is not directed at him.</p>
        <p>''They may be onto something, but my gut tells me they're not going to find that Ted did something to benefit himself directly,'' Mr. Roderick said. ''There is a sense that something's coming down for Ben, but I don't think it's going to be the senator.''</p>
        <p>Ralph Samuels, a Republican who is the House majority leader in the State Legislature, said the questions about the work on the Girdwood house likely would raise concerns for some Alaskan voters but not enough to threaten their support for a senator who has served for all but 9 of the 48 years that Alaska has been part of the union.</p>
        <p>''Our state would not be the same without Ted Stevens. We all know that,'' Mr. Samuels said. ''So I think everybody is going to say, 'You're going to have to do a whole lot more than what I've seen so far before I start casting doubts on Ted Stevens.' ''</p>
        <p>In Girdwood, across the street from the house the senator owns with his wife, F.B.I agents knocked on the door of Wayne Fuller, a 38-year-old paramedic. Mr. Fuller said agents had asked what he knew about renovations but that he did not live in the neighborhood when the work was completed.</p>
        <p>''I told them I don't know anything,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Julie Pederson, who lives next to Mr. Fuller, said agents had asked her what she knew about the renovations, how often she saw the senator and what she knew of his habits when he was in town. In an interview later, Ms. Pederson declined to share details of what she had told the agents.</p>
        <p>Before the agents arrived, in an interview at her front door, she said Ben Stevens and his wife once spent long periods at the house in the summer. She said Mr. Stevens was a genial presence on the street, and she noted that her young children, like many other people in Alaska, refer to the senator as ''Uncle Ted.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
