<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For a Cinematic Object of Desire, a Second Act</title>
    <meta content="08bell" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/movies/08bell.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852881"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dargis, Manohla</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">De Oliveira, Manoel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Piccoli, Michel</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Belle Toujours (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Portugal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Portugal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Portugal</location>
        <person class="online_producer">de Oliveira, Manoel</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Belle Toujours (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2DE1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For a Cinematic Object of Desire, a Second Act</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For a Cinematic Object of Desire, a Second Act</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANOHLA DARGIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dargis, Manohla</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Manohla Dargis reviews film Belle Toujours, written and directed by Manoel de Oliveira; Michel Piccoli stars; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Released in 1967 to outrage and condemnation, Luis Buñuel's sublime ''Belle de Jour'' stars a frosty, breathtakingly young Catherine Deneuve as a proper bourgeois wife who, by becoming a whore, liberates herself, ruins her husband and possibly goes mad. That, at least, is one way to read the film's perverse and intentionally ambiguous finale, with its frozen teardrop, ringing bells, beatific smiles and the startling image of the paralyzed, catatonic husband rising like Lazarus from his wheelchair, as if suddenly, miraculously healed.</p>
        <p>Four decades later, having tapped into reserves of great love or shocking hubris, the Portuguese filmmaker Manoel de Oliveira revisits Buñuel's classic with ''Belle Toujours,'' a sequel of sorts starring Michel Piccoli, one of the stars of the original. Alternately fascinating and frustrating, ''Belle Toujours'' is interesting insofar as it finds one filmmaker trying to engage with a masterpiece of cinema. Mr. Oliveira frames his film as a homage to Buñuel and to the legendary screenwriter Jean-Claude Carrière, who helped adapted ''Belle de Jour'' from the Joseph Kessel novel of the same title. (Mr. Carrière also helped Buñuel write his luminously poignant memoir, ''My Last Sigh.'') But ''Belle Toujours'' is, as well, an act of critical violence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Having tapped into reserves of great love or shocking hubris, the Portuguese filmmaker Manoel de Oliveira revisits Luis Buñuel’s classic with “Belle Toujours.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Released in 1967 to outrage and condemnation, Luis Buñuel's sublime ''Belle de Jour'' stars a frosty, breathtakingly young Catherine Deneuve as a proper bourgeois wife who, by becoming a whore, liberates herself, ruins her husband and possibly goes mad. That, at least, is one way to read the film's perverse and intentionally ambiguous finale, with its frozen teardrop, ringing bells, beatific smiles and the startling image of the paralyzed, catatonic husband rising like Lazarus from his wheelchair, as if suddenly, miraculously healed.</p>
        <p>Four decades later, having tapped into reserves of great love or shocking hubris, the Portuguese filmmaker Manoel de Oliveira revisits Buñuel's classic with ''Belle Toujours,'' a sequel of sorts starring Michel Piccoli, one of the stars of the original. Alternately fascinating and frustrating, ''Belle Toujours'' is interesting insofar as it finds one filmmaker trying to engage with a masterpiece of cinema. Mr. Oliveira frames his film as a homage to Buñuel and to the legendary screenwriter Jean-Claude Carrière, who helped adapted ''Belle de Jour'' from the Joseph Kessel novel of the same title. (Mr. Carrière also helped Buñuel write his luminously poignant memoir, ''My Last Sigh.'') But ''Belle Toujours'' is, as well, an act of critical violence.</p>
        <p>This isn't the annihilating violence of criticism at its most cruel; rather, this is the act of the lover who, having long adored the object, now feels compelled somehow to possess it. Mr. Oliveira expresses his compulsion by reuniting Ms. Deneuve's character, Séverine Serizy (the Belle of both films), with the prickly Monsieur Husson (Mr. Piccoli), a sinister acquaintance of her husband, now dead. In ''Belle de Jour'' Husson furnishes the name of the brothel where Séverine takes up her furtive trade and later seeks to betray her secrets to her husband, whom he dares call friend. Years later, in ''Belle Toujours,'' Husson, now as smooth and round as a boiled dumpling, spots Séverine (the skittish Bulle Ogier) at a concert and promptly gives chase.</p>
        <p>The chase doesn't last long. Husson finds Séverine and soon wines and dines her under the dead-eyed gaze of Mr. Oliveira's camera. Their reunion booms with their awkward silences and the gentle clink of silverware. Champagne bubbles fizz; the mood fizzles. And then Husson betrays himself and Séverine, who has insisted that her past is behind her, by giving her a lacquered box like the one presented to her by a brothel client in ''Belle de Jour.'' In this justly famous exchange in the Buñuel film, a patron arrives at the brothel carrying a box that emits a disconcerting buzzing sound. The box and its secrets frighten one prostitute, who refuses to service the man, but Belle smiles as if possessed, dreamily taking the bait.</p>
        <p>Buñuel never reveals the contents of the box, though he later proposed one deliciously witty and smutty (and unprintable) answer. Much like Belle's sexual masochism, much like the woman herself and Buñuel's own film, the box remains at once a repository of mystery and a potential treasure chest, though only for those with a taste and talent for a certain kind of erotic plunder. Despite his insinuating manner, Husson shows no such talent in ''Belle de Jour,'' which is why Mr. Oliveira's decision to have him present Séverine with a buzzing box in ''Belle Toujours'' throws this fragile divertissement off course. The only way Husson could know about the box -- along with some of Séverine's other salacious secrets he's enigmatically privy to -- is if he had actually watched Buñuel's film.</p>
        <p>This slip in logic might be more interesting had Mr. Oliveira added a new kink to Buñuel's kinky classic, but this 70-minute exercise ends before it begins. Buñuel may not have been particularly sympathetic to women, but the ambiguity of ''Belle de Jour'' allows Séverine to exist outside his self-confessed parochialism. Asked if she returns to the brothel at the end of the film, he answered: ''Yes and no. It's her problem.'' This ambiguity doesn't appear to have suited Mr. Oliveira, who, like Husson, chases after this phantom of lost desire without gain. Ms. Deneuve might have given that phantom some viscera, a glimmer of mystery, but she exists here only in fond memory. The pixyish Ms. Ogier, alas, looks ready to hide under the nearest buttercup. She'll leave the buzzing to the bees.</p>
        <p>Belle Toujours  Opens today in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Written (in French, with English subtitles) and directed by Manoel de Oliveira; director of photography, Sabine Lancelin; edited by Valerie Loiseleux; production designer, Christian Marti; produced by Miguel Cadilhe; released by New Yorker Films. At the Lincoln Plaza, Broadway at 62nd Street. Running time: 70 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: Michel Piccoli (Husson), Bulle Ogier (Séverine), Ricardo Trepa (Bartender), Leonor Baldaque (Younger Prostitute) and Júlia Buisel (Older Prostitute).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
