<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Police Find Reputed Mob Figure Shot to Death in Bed in Brooklyn</title>
    <meta content="08mob" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/nyregion/08mob.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070613T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852976"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E3DA1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="836" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Police Find Reputed Mob Figure Shot to Death in Bed in Brooklyn</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Reputed Mob Figure Is Found Shot to Death in His Bed</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARA BUCKLEY and WILLIAM K. RASHBAUM; Al Baker and Daryl Khan contributed reporting.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The reputed mobster was found face up in his white striped pajamas, his mouth agape, half hanging off his bed in his Brooklyn home. He had been shot once near his ear, in the back of his head, and late last night investigators were still searching for a motive.</p>
        <p>The death of the man, Rudolph Izzi -- who the authorities said had been a soldier with the Genovese crime family -- was the second mob-related shooting in the borough in three days, and had detectives investigating whether the two attacks were related.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The death of Rudolph Izzi  who the authorities believe was tied to the Genovese crime family  was the second mob-related shooting in Brooklyn in three days.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The reputed mobster was found face up in his white striped pajamas, his mouth agape, half hanging off his bed in his Brooklyn home. He had been shot once near his ear, in the back of his head, and late last night investigators were still searching for a motive.</p>
        <p>The death of the man, Rudolph Izzi -- who the authorities said had been a soldier with the Genovese crime family -- was the second mob-related shooting in the borough in three days, and had detectives investigating whether the two attacks were related.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday morning, Robert DeCicco, whose father is a captain with the Gambino crime family, was shot in his arm and leg, and another bullet grazed his head, while he was sitting in his parked car less than a mile and a half from Mr. Izzi's home on Shore Parkway. Mr. DeCicco, who was indicted along with his father and 11 others on federal racketeering and extortion charges in January, survived the attack.</p>
        <p>Investigators are still trying to determine whether there was any connection between the shooting of Mr. Izzi, a loan shark, and Mr. DeCicco, 56, who lives on Staten Island and was said to have amassed heavy gambling debts. But both came from powerful crime families and have colorful histories of their own. There have been no arrests in either case.</p>
        <p>According to the police, Mr. Izzi's body was discovered after a friend of his, a doctor, stopped by for a visit and noticed signs of forced entry around the home's door. The friend, whose name was not released, called the police. (Another investigator said Mr. Izzi was gunned down after answering the door, though that version was not corroborated by the police.)</p>
        <p>And when investigators first saw Mr. Izzi, 74, who was declared dead in his bed, they said he seemed like a ''beat-up old man,'' a far cry from the eccentric, crisply dressed wiseguy whose nickname was ''the Cueball,'' and whose tangles with the law dated back nearly 40 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Izzi, investigators said, was a, associate of Rosario Gangi, a Genovese captain whose crew long dominated the Fulton Fish Market. Mr. Gangi is currently serving a federal prison term.</p>
        <p>In 1968, Mr. Izzi, then 35, surrendered to the Federal Bureau of Investigation after being on the lam for more than a year. The authorities charged him with stealing $2 million worth of I.B.M. stock from a New York brokerage house in 1966.</p>
        <p>In 2001, Mr. Izzi was arrested again, after the police responded to reports of gunfire at his Shore Parkway home. Mr. Izzi told the investigators that a gunman had barged into his home and pistol-whipped him, and that the intruder's gun went off after Mr. Izzi tried to wrestle him to the ground.</p>
        <p>The police did not find a gunman. But they found a pipe bomb in Mr. Izzi's garage, $60,000 in cash and a trove of loan-sharking records.</p>
        <p>Mr. Izzi's lawyer in the 2001 case, Arthur L. Aidala, said his client pleaded guilty to possession of loan-sharking records, a misdemeanor.</p>
        <p>''They found the pipe bomb in his garage that was probably from the 1950s,'' Mr. Aidala said. ''I believe they tried to ignite it and it was a dud and so those charges went by the wayside.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Aidala said Mr. Izzi was eccentric but gentlemanly, a natty and meticulous dresser with a penchant for matching clothes. ''Everything was coordinated, the shirt matched the belt matched the shoes matched the watch,'' Mr. Aidala recalled. ''I believe he wanted to pay my legal fee with a case of Cutty Sark.</p>
        <p>''He was the last of a dying breed, so to speak,'' Mr. Aidala said. ''Chivalrous.''</p>
        <p>Mr. DeCicco is the son of George DeCicco, 78, a high-ranking Gambino family member, federal authorities said. According to federal charges brought by the Brooklyn United States attorney's office in January, George DeCicco was secretly recorded telling a federal witness who owed him money, ''I'll burn your eyes out, did you ever screw me. Do you want me to burn your eyes out?''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, dozens of investigators descended on Mr. Izzi's three-story red brick home, some in white evidence collection jumpsuits, and combed the grass outside. They found a 9 millimeter shell in the house, but no gun, they said. The homicide is being investigated by detectives from the 62th Precinct. F.B.I. agents from the Organized Crime Branch were also at the scene.</p>
        <p>And neighbors were shocked by Mr. Izzi's reputed ties to the mob. They also said they were gripped by the fear that a Mafia war might be under way.</p>
        <p>''I see him almost every day, sweeping and fixing the garbage pails in front of the house,'' said Francine Romeo, who lives nearby. ''Looking at him, you'd never think anything.''</p>
        <p>But she said Mr. Izzi stopped sunbathing in his driveway after he was attacked in 2001. Ever since then, she said, he sunbathed only on his second-floor balcony.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 13, 2007, Wednesday  Because of an editing error, an article on Friday about the shooting death of Rudolph Izzi, a loan shark and reputed mobster, included an erroneous reference in some copies to his place of residence. As noted elsewhere in the article, he lived in Brooklyn, not Staten Island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 13, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article on Friday about the shooting death of Rudolph Izzi, a loan shark and reputed mobster, included an erroneous reference in some copies to his place of residence. As noted elsewhere in the article, he lived in Brooklyn, not Staten Island.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
