<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ivanovic Reaches the French Open Final With a Smile</title>
    <meta content="08tennis" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/sports/tennis/08tennis.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852993"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Sharapova, Maria</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ivanovic, Ana</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E1DA1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="912" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ivanovic Reaches the French Open Final With a Smile</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ivanovic Reaches the French Open Final With a Smile</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIET MACUR</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With eyes wide and eyebrows raised, Ana Ivanovic watched Maria Sharapova's final forehand sail past the baseline to end their semifinal match at the French Open.</p>
        <p>Ivanovic, the gentle and sweet teenager from Serbia, raised her arms and smiled, looking flabbergasted at what she had done. The scoreboard read, 6-2, 6-1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ana Ivanovic, the seventh seed, defeated Maria Sharapova, 6-2, 6-1. Ivanovic will play Justine Henin on Saturday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With eyes wide and eyebrows raised, Ana Ivanovic watched Maria Sharapova's final forehand sail past the baseline to end their semifinal match at the French Open.</p>
        <p>Ivanovic, the gentle and sweet teenager from Serbia, raised her arms and smiled, looking flabbergasted at what she had done. The scoreboard read, 6-2, 6-1.</p>
        <p>No, this was not back home in Belgrade, where she grew up playing tennis inside an Olympic-size swimming pool. ''It's true!'' Ivanovic said of her unorthodox training. Club officials had drained it, covered it with carpet, then warned the players to play down the line, lest they have an inopportune meeting with the pool's high walls.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, in one of the two women's semifinals, Ivanovic, the seventh seed, found herself not in a pool, but on Roland Garros's hallowed red clay. She had made it to her first Grand Slam final, setting up a Saturday afternoon meeting with the world's top player, Justine Henin, who defeated Jelena Jankovic, 6-2, 6-2, in the other semifinal.</p>
        <p>''Everything went so fast and it's very exciting times for me,'' the 19-year-old Ivanovic said, breathlessly. ''I won a lot of matches lately, so it's great motivation, great excitement. So it's a little bit hard to calm down. Probably later today, I'll be very tired from that.''</p>
        <p>While Henin defeated top players like No. 8 Serena Williams and the No. 4 Jankovic to make the final, Ivanovic had an easier road. She went through No. 3 Svetlana Kuznetsova and the No. 2 Sharapova, but she had beaten both women before.</p>
        <p>This time, Ivanovic had only 11 unforced errors in her semifinal match, while Sharapova seemed to do nothing right. In front of a half-empty stadium, Sharapova made 25 unforced errors, had just 9 winners and recorded 5 double faults.</p>
        <p>Sharapova chastised herself for making sloppy errors, then joked that she did not blame the fans for skipping the match to eat lunch.</p>
        <p>''I would have loved to be having lunch then, too,'' she said. ''I'd rather be having a chocolate croissant than be down, 3-0.''</p>
        <p>On the same day Sharapova packed her bags, Ivanovic, the newest female tennis star, took a huge step forward. On the court, she is subdued, compared with Sharapova's signature shrieking. She is the friendly next-door neighbor, while Sharapova has fallen into the role of a calculating diva.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the tournament, a reporter asked Ivanovic if she thought that being nice, not cutthroat, was a weakness in her game.</p>
        <p>She lit up when she heard the question: ''Thanks! I think you can never be too nice. It makes me happy that I make people happy.''</p>
        <p>But ambition is hidden inside Ivanovic. She picked up tennis when she was 5, after seeing Monica Seles on television. During that broadcast, she saw a commercial for a local tennis club, then memorized the phone number.</p>
        <p>From then on, she wanted to be a tennis player, though Serbia had no tennis tradition to speak of.</p>
        <p>''When I was a kid, I never played with the dolls, I always carried some rackets,'' she said. ''I still have videos when I was 2, with the plastic rackets and a ball. I always was kind of sporty and tennis was the thing.''</p>
        <p>Ivanovic continued to practice in her homeland even while NATO bombed Belgrade in 1999 in response to the presence of Serbian troops in Kosovo. But she moved to Switzerland when she was 14 because the facilities in Serbia were subpar.</p>
        <p>Her Serbian benefactors had gone bankrupt and her parents could not afford to bankroll her career, so Dan Holzmann, a German businessman, stepped in. He sponsored her and paid for her training, investing $500,000 in her future, according to Holzmann, who owns a successful vitamin company.</p>
        <p>She began to blossom as an athlete, working so hard she would, at times, turn white and vomit on the court, Holzmann said. At the same time, she turned into a woman of stunning beauty, swamped with requests for photo shoots and modeling jobs.</p>
        <p>''It's very flattering that people ask me to do that, but I'm really shy to do it,'' Ivanovic said. ''I don't feel as comfortable.</p>
        <p>''I prefer to say , 'Look, interview is fine, but not photos.' ''</p>
        <p>Ivanovic has had plenty of both in the past few weeks. Last month, she won a tournament in Berlin for her third tour victory. Until her success at this French Open, she had never made it past the quarterfinals of a Grand Slam event.</p>
        <p>Even with her recent success, though, Ivanovic is the newcomer in Paris, while Henin is the host. Henin, 25, has owned Roland Garros in recent years, taking home three of the past four championships. En route to the final, Henin dismantled Jankovic, beating her for the sixth time in a row. Jankovic said she could simply not keep up, saying that Henin played ''really well, flawless.''</p>
        <p>Jankovic, who is also from Belgrade, said that she thinks Henin will win this tournament, calling her the best player on clay. (Still, she made sure to wish her compatriot the best of luck.)</p>
        <p>Henin, however, is remaining humble about her chances against Ivanovic. They have played only once before, in 2005 in Warsaw, where Henin won in straight sets.</p>
        <p>''She has matured quite a lot over the last years, so this is a match I'm going to work on very seriously,'' Henin said of Ivanovic, who, even hours after making the final, was still giddy.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
