<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Steroid Investigators Requested Giambi's Cooperation</title>
    <meta content="08giambi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/sports/08giambi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852997"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Major League Baseball</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Selig, Bud</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Giambi, Jason</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mitchell, George J</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E0DA1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="597" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Steroid Investigators Requested Giambi's Cooperation</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Steroid Investigators Requested Giambi’s Cooperation</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY; Murray Chass contributed reporting.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before Commissioner Bud Selig requested that Jason Giambi of the Yankees meet with George J. Mitchell for Mitchell's investigation into the use of performance-enhancing substances in Major League Baseball, Mitchell had already sent Giambi a letter seeking his cooperation.</p>
        <p>Mitchell said last month that he sent letters to current and former players seeking their help. According to a member of the front office of an American League team, Giambi was one of the players who received a letter. Giambi testified in the Bay Area Laboratory Co-Operative steroid distribution case, so it would have been surprising if Mitchell had not tried to interview him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite sending numerous letters, investigators have not met with any players or received permission to view medical players.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before Commissioner Bud Selig requested that Jason Giambi of the Yankees meet with George J. Mitchell for Mitchell's investigation into the use of performance-enhancing substances in Major League Baseball, Mitchell had already sent Giambi a letter seeking his cooperation.</p>
        <p>Mitchell said last month that he sent letters to current and former players seeking their help. According to a member of the front office of an American League team, Giambi was one of the players who received a letter. Giambi testified in the Bay Area Laboratory Co-Operative steroid distribution case, so it would have been surprising if Mitchell had not tried to interview him.</p>
        <p>Mitchell has sent two types of letters to players, the one that Giambi received and another in which Mitchell has asked players to allow their teams to release their medical records. No players have met with Mitchell's investigators, and no one has allowed the release of medical records.</p>
        <p>The front-office person, who saw one of Mitchell's letters like the one that was sent to Giambi, said it informed players that it would be in their best interest to cooperate with the investigation. Mitchell said in the letter that using steroids was a form of cheating.</p>
        <p>Mitchell also invited Giambi and other players to speak to investigators if they had information about anyone who had used performance-enhancing drugs. There was no deadline cited for cooperating with the investigation.</p>
        <p>Mitchell said in an e-mail message that he had been in discussions with the Players' Association ''regarding the process by which the players are being asked to agree to interviews.'' Mitchell said that he hoped to ''receive responses and begin interviews in the near future,'' although he did not specify a timetable.</p>
        <p>''As I previously stated, this is one of the final phases of our investigation,'' Mitchell said. ''I expect to complete the investigation and issue my report in the coming months.''</p>
        <p>Mitchell declined to discuss specifics, saying, ''We do not comment on the details of the investigation, including any letters we may send or receive.''</p>
        <p>While Mitchell can promise players immunity from being punished by Selig for anything that is said in an interview, Mitchell does not have the authority to provide immunity from other investigations if a player is called as a witness. Even if players wanted to cooperate with Mitchell, the threat of possibly being asked to participate in other investigations could be a deterrent.</p>
        <p>In asking players to meet, Mitchell has said that he is not obligated to give any of the information to the government. But if the information is subpoenaed, he must release it.</p>
        <p>When Giambi was asked last month if he had gotten a letter from Mitchell, he said, ''You'll have to talk to Arn.''</p>
        <p>Arn Tellem, Giambi's agent, has declined comment about whether Mitchell contacted Giambi and about whether Giambi plans to meet with Mitchell.</p>
        <p>By tacitly admitting to USA Today last month that he had used steroids, Giambi created questions about his past actions. Selig issued a statement Wednesday in which he asked Giambi to cooperate with Mitchell's investigation within two weeks.</p>
        <p>Once Giambi agrees or does not agree to cooperate, Selig will make a ruling regarding Giambi's comments about steroids.</p>
        <p>Officials from the players' union communicated with Mitchell's people in person and in writing last week, and that dialogue will probably continue this week.</p>
        <p>The union is not telling players who receive letters what they should do. Players have been advised to speak to their lawyers. There are also continuing talks about clubs releasing medical records without identifying the players.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
