<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Equity Firms' Increased Bid For Biomet Is Accepted</title>
    <meta content="08biomet" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/business/08biomet.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852942"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Orthopedics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Biomet Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Institutional Shareholder Services</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Blackstone Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Texas Pacific Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Goldman Sachs Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">De La Merced, Michael J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Biomet Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Blackstone Group</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Goldman Sachs Group Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Texas Pacific Group</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E2DB1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="572" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Equity Firms' Increased Bid For Biomet Is Accepted</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Biomet Accepts Sweetened Takeover Offer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL J. de la MERCED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">De La Merced, Michael J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Group of private equity firms bidding for Biomet, maker of artificial joints, sweetens its offer to $11.4 billion after prominent shareholder adviser Institutional Shareholder Services criticized its previous offer as too low; Biomet's board accepts new offer and urges shareholders to back it; new bid represents nearly 5 percent increase over first proposal of $10.9 billion, made in December; firms involved are Blackstone Group, Kohlberg Kravis Roberts, Texas Pacific Group and unit of Goldman Sachs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A group of private equity firms bidding for Biomet, a maker of artificial joints, sweetened its offer to $11.4 billion after a prominent shareholder adviser criticized its previous bid as too low.</p>
        <p>Biomet's board said yesterday that it had accepted the new offer and urged shareholders to back it. The new bid represents a nearly 5 percent increase over the first proposal of $10.9 billion, made in December.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The artificial joint maker accepted a bid of $11.4 billion from a private equity consortium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A group of private equity firms bidding for Biomet, a maker of artificial joints, sweetened its offer to $11.4 billion after a prominent shareholder adviser criticized its previous bid as too low.</p>
        <p>Biomet's board said yesterday that it had accepted the new offer and urged shareholders to back it. The new bid represents a nearly 5 percent increase over the first proposal of $10.9 billion, made in December.</p>
        <p>Though private equity has acquired scores of companies over the last two years, shareholders recently have expressed concern that their companies were being bought too cheaply. Already, restive and vocal investors have prompted sweetened takeover offers for Clear Channel Communications, the radio network giant, and OSI Restaurant Partners, the owner of the Outback Steakhouse franchise.</p>
        <p>Under the terms of the revised offer, the buyout firms -- the Blackstone Group, Kohlberg Kravis Roberts, the Texas Pacific Group and a unit of Goldman Sachs -- will start a $46-a-share tender offer for 20 business days starting on or before June 14. After that, the firms will offer to buy out the remaining shares for the same price.</p>
        <p>''We believe the proposed price for the transaction is fair to Biomet's shareholders,'' Niles L. Noblitt, Biomet's chairman, said in a statement.</p>
        <p>As part of the new offer, Biomet canceled a vote scheduled for today. It has also agreed not to pay its annual dividend.</p>
        <p>Shares in Biomet rose to $45.61 this morning, an increase of 3.2 percent, and ended the day at $45.56.</p>
        <p>Beyond its higher price, the new offer bears another notable difference from the last one: As a tender offer, the buyout firms can now conduct a faster sale, since the company does not need to file new proxy materials. More important, the tender offer also takes away an opportunity for dissident shareholders to oppose the deal by removing the need for a shareholder vote.</p>
        <p>Under the terms of the new deal, 75 percent of Biomet shares must be tendered or sold to the bidders for the transaction to be completed. In a statement, the buyout consortium said the new offer was ''the absolute limit'' of its ability to raise its price.</p>
        <p>The use of a tender offer also removes from the equation proxy advisory firms like Institutional Shareholders Services, which criticized the earlier offer. The recommendations of such firms hold great sway over institutional investors.</p>
        <p>An I.S.S. spokeswoman said that the firm generally did not issue recommendations in tender offers, though it would provide an analysis for its clients. In a report released late last month, I.S.S. said that the December offer price had not kept pace with improvements in Biomet's operations, as well as gains in the stock prices of the company's peers.</p>
        <p>Biomet had also faced criticism for accepting the private equity offer over a higher bid by a British rival, Smith &amp; Nephew. Biomet has said that proposal was saddled with too many conditions that could have killed a deal.</p>
        <p>PSAM, an asset manager with about a 1.9 percent stake in Biomet, also said this week that it would oppose the first offer, saying it was too low. Peter Schoenfeld, the head of the firm, declined to comment yesterday.</p>
        <p>In both the Clear Channel and Biomet cases, shareholder dissatisfaction has been amplified by the laws of their home states. In Indiana, where Biomet is based, 75 percent of outstanding shares must be voted in favor of a deal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
