<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LIVING HERE | Golf Communities; Tee Time Anytime</title>
    <meta content="08live" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852969"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Coeur D'Alene (Idaho)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoyle, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gunderson, Amy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Living Here</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions/Western States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Vacation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Idaho</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E5DA1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LIVING HERE | Golf Communities; Tee Time Anytime</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">As told to Amy Gunderson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gunderson, Amy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kevin Hoyle comments on his second home in golf community in Coeur d'Alene, Idaho; photos and brief descriptions of similar properties for sale around country (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHO -- Kevin Hoyle, 55, owner of a wealth management firm, from Rancho Santa Fe, Calif.  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  WHERE -- Coeur d'Alene, Idaho.</p>
        <p>Golfing in this part of the country means golfing in a natural environment. The course here at the Club at Black Rock is absolutely gorgeous. Balls are hit over natural ponds and alongside waterfalls. A game might pause because a deer or a pheasant is on the course. And turning the corner on the back nine I can see a 180-degree view of Lake Coeur d'Alene. With scenery like this, it's actually quite easy to lose my train of thought mid-game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHO -- Kevin Hoyle, 55, owner of a wealth management firm, from Rancho Santa Fe, Calif.  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  WHERE -- Coeur d'Alene, Idaho.</p>
        <p>Golfing in this part of the country means golfing in a natural environment. The course here at the Club at Black Rock is absolutely gorgeous. Balls are hit over natural ponds and alongside waterfalls. A game might pause because a deer or a pheasant is on the course. And turning the corner on the back nine I can see a 180-degree view of Lake Coeur d'Alene. With scenery like this, it's actually quite easy to lose my train of thought mid-game.</p>
        <p>I bought a lot here and built a large house, about 7,000 square feet, with a deck and outdoor fireplace. My wife, Sandy, and I opted for lake views over golf views for this house, but we see plenty of the course when we are out playing. The course was designed by Jim Engh, but the name of the designer isn't as important to me as the layout and how much fun it is to play.</p>
        <p>My wife and I are anywhere from an 8 to 12 handicap, so a course that continues to be challenging with each round is key. Also, unlike some other private clubs, this course doesn't host professional tournaments. Bringing in a tournament shuts down the fairways for a week, for all the games and the practice rounds, and it is a pain for the residents.</p>
        <p>We spend five months of the year here starting in May. At about 100 miles from the Canadian border, the sun rises here at 5 a.m. and by the end of June it won't get dark until 10 p.m. It's possible to have a 3 p.m. tee time and wrap up a game around 7 p.m., before heading to dinner. It's the ideal summer golfing destination.</p>
        <p>As told to Amy Gunderson</p>
        <p>Information on properties was supplied by the listing companies.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Grand Junction, Colo.  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $1,235,000</p>
        <p>This 4,250-square-foot house sits alongside the ninth fairway of a Jim Engh-designed public course in the Redlands Mesa golf community. The house also has views of the Colorado National Monument, a 32-square-mile park with desert canyons and cliffs. There are three full and two half bathrooms, an island in the kitchen, a theater room, a wine cellar, 12-foot ceilings and 2,000 square feet of patio space. Grand Junction is 245 miles west of Denver. Agent: Beth Morris, Redlands Mesa, (970) 255-7400; www.redlandsmesa.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Millsboro, Del.  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $2.5 million</p>
        <p>The Peninsula on the Indian River Bay is a gated community with a private Jack Nicklaus golf course. This 4,551-square-foot house overlooks the course and has four and a half bathrooms and four screened porches. It is offered furnished. Millsboro is two and a half hours from Philadelphia. Agent: Melissa Firetti, the Peninsula on the Indian River Bay, (302) 947-4717; www.peninsuladelaware.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- St. Augustine, Fla.  WHAT -- 5-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $469,900</p>
        <p>The World Golf Village community is home to two 18-hole courses, including the King &amp; Bear, which was jointly designed by Arnold Palmer and Jack Nicklaus. Homeowners are entitled to membership at both courses. The community has several swimming pools, a fitness center and two pro golf shops. This 2,700-square-foot house was built in 2006 and has four bathrooms, granite counters in the kitchen, carpeted and tiled floors and a covered lanai. Agent: Carol von Rabenstein, Davidson Realty, (800) 940-2898; www.davidsonrealtyinc.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Bluffton, S.C.  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $1.35 million</p>
        <p>The May River Golf Club, the course at the Palmetto Bluff community, is set along the bluffs of the May River. This 2,149-square-foot house has three and a half bathrooms, a screened back porch and a carport with space for a car and a golf cart. The property is about a quarter-acre and is within walking distance of a community swimming pool, a fitness center and restaurants. It is offered furnished. Bluffton is 15 miles from Hilton Head Island. Agent: Palmetto Bluff Real Estate Company; 843- 757-3333; www.palmetto-bluff.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Hot Springs, Va.  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $2.3 million</p>
        <p>This 4,745-square-foot house is in the Homestead Preserve, which is adjacent to the Homestead Resort. Owners receive a membership in the golf and tennis club, which gives them access to the resort's three 18-hole courses, including the Old Course, which dates to 1892. The house is on 1.3 acres and has five and a half bathrooms, front and side porches, two master suites, two fireplaces and a finished basement. Hot Springs is 210 miles from Washington. Agent: Virginia Hot Springs Realty, (866) 754-5778; www.vhsrealty.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Sheridan, Wyo.  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $635,000</p>
        <p>The Powder Horn golf community in northern Wyoming has three nine-hole semi-private courses, and this house has views of the Stag Nine course. Built in 2002, this brick house is 2,900 square feet and has three bathrooms, granite counters and a two-car garage. The property is about a quarter-acre. The community has a swimming pool, walking trails, fishing ponds and tennis courts. Sheridan is a two-hour drive south of Billings, Mont. Agent: Kelly Kosine, Powder Horn Realty, (800) 329-0598; www.powderhornrealty.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
