<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Hampshire to Repeal Parental Notification Law</title>
    <meta content="08parental" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/us/08parental.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852985"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Hampshire</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E2DA1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Hampshire to Repeal Parental Notification Law</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Hampshire to Repeal Parental Notification Law</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAM BELLUCK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belluck, Pam</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, June 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Hampshire will become the first state to repeal a law requiring teenage girls to notify their parents before having an abortion, under a bill that won final passage in the State Senate on Thursday.</p>
        <p>Gov. John Lynch has said he would sign the measure. The vote in the Senate was 15 to 9. The House vote, in March, was 217 to 141.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Hampshire will become the first state to repeal a law requiring teenage girls to notify their parents before having an abortion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New Hampshire will become the first state to repeal a law requiring teenage girls to notify their parents before having an abortion, under a bill that won final passage in the State Senate on Thursday.</p>
        <p>Gov. John Lynch has said he would sign the measure. The vote in the Senate was 15 to 9. The House vote, in March, was 217 to 141.</p>
        <p>The parental notification law was the strictest in the nation when it was passed in 2003. The vote to repeal it reflects, in part, a sea change in New Hampshire politics since the 2006 elections, which swept a Democratic majority into the legislature for the first time in over a century.</p>
        <p>''Having this Democratic legislature and Democratic governor for the first time really does change the playing field,'' said Dean Spiliotes, director of research at the New Hampshire Institute of Politics at St. Anselm College. ''However, New Hampshire has always been a little bit of an outlier, somewhat libertarian and increasingly kind of moderate, with less of a focus on these social issues where you have government getting involved.''</p>
        <p>Soon after the law passed, it was challenged by Planned Parenthood of Northern New England and other groups, which argued that it was unconstitutional because it did not allow an exemption from parental notification if the girl's health was in danger. The law's supporters had intentionally omitted such a medical exception, saying that it could be used as a loophole to allow many girls to skip telling their parents.</p>
        <p>Just before the law was supposed to take effect, Judge Joseph A. DiClerico Jr. of Federal District Court in Concord, N.H., struck it down. The United States Supreme Court heard the case and ruled unanimously last year that an exception for medical emergencies had to be included. The justices sent the law back to Judge DiClerico, instructing him to see if it could be retooled to include a medical exception or if it needed to be thrown out altogether.</p>
        <p>Soon after the November election, Democrats began an effort to repeal the law, and Judge DiClerico delayed his decision. If the repeal passed, the court case would be moot; if it failed, the judge would decide the law's fate.</p>
        <p>That gave repeal advocates an edge in lobbying lawmakers -- they were able to persuade even some legislators who favored parental notification that it would be better to remove the matter from the courts.</p>
        <p>''Our opponents said, 'If you vote for repeal, you're voting against parental notification,' '' said Dawn Touzin, vice president for public policy and governmental affairs at Planned Parenthood of Northern New England. ''We said, 'No, you're not.' The issue is, do you want to leave it in the hands of the judge or shouldn't it be something that's decided by the legislature?''</p>
        <p>State Senator Joseph A. Foster, the majority leader, said he favored a law similar to those in Maine and Connecticut, which do not require parental notification, but require abortion providers to counsel girls to consider involving a parent or a trusted adult in their decision. He said he did not believe the 2003 law should be retrofitted: ''I think we ought to wipe the slate clean, start from scratch.''</p>
        <p>Repeal opponents said they would push for a notification law when the legislature reconvenes in January.</p>
        <p>''We're not going to give up on this,'' said State Representative Fran Wendelboe, a Republican. ''I've had teenagers. My kids are grown and they were boys, but I know if they did something they were ashamed of, if they could figure out a way to cover it up, they'd do it.''</p>
        <p>State Senator Robert J. Letourneau, a Republican, said: ''You can't get your daughter or son's ears pierced under the age of 17 without parental consent; you can't get a tattoo without parental consent. To me it's unconscionable that you can't give an aspirin to a child in school without parental consent, but they can have major surgery without parental notification.''</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Mr. Lynch, Colin Manning, said the governor ''would like to see parents involved if possible'' and ''is open to having a discussion'' about a law like Maine's and Connecticut's.</p>
        <p>But anything more restrictive seems unlikely to succeed, said Dante Scala, a political science professor at the University of New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>''I think it's going to take a Republican resurgence to get that put back on the front burner,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
