<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spitzer Has a New Plan for Racing Franchise</title>
    <meta content="08nyra" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/nyregion/08nyra.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852924"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Racing Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEEDC1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="586" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spitzer Has a New Plan for Racing Franchise</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spitzer Has a New Plan for Racing Franchise</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, June 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer has a proposal that would keep horse racing in the hands of the New York Racing Association, but would give one of the three private groups bidding on the state's horse racing franchise control over future casino gambling operations.</p>
        <p>The plan, according to aides to the governor, would also seek an overhaul of the troubled association's board and management. As part of the proposal, the administration is also considering shutting down thoroughbred racing at Aqueduct.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALBANY, June 7  Gov. Eliot Spitzer has a proposal that would keep horse racing in the hands of the New York Racing Association, but would give one of the three private groups bidding on the state’s horse racing franchise control over future casino gambling operations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer has a proposal that would keep horse racing in the hands of the New York Racing Association, but would give one of the three private groups bidding on the state's horse racing franchise control over future casino gambling operations.</p>
        <p>The plan, according to aides to the governor, would also seek an overhaul of the troubled association's board and management. As part of the proposal, the administration is also considering shutting down thoroughbred racing at Aqueduct.</p>
        <p>But it has by no means made a final decision and is wary of the political resistance to such a move, according to the aides, who spoke on the condition of anonymity because the negotiations are still private.</p>
        <p>The administration has already met with officials at the nonprofit racing association to discuss the proposal. On Friday, Richard Rifkin, a special counsel to the governor, is expected to meet with the three private bidders, Excelsior Racing Associates, Empire Racing and Capital Play, about the proposal.</p>
        <p>Any such plan would need the Legislature's approval. The association's current board would also have to agree.</p>
        <p>The Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, a Republican who has often clashed with the governor, will doubtless have strong views. Not only does his district include Saratoga Springs, the site of one of the tracks, but also he breeds and raises horses.</p>
        <p>''We're not going to be commenting on something that may or may not happen,'' said John McArdle, a spokesman for Mr. Bruno. ''We'll wait to be briefed. The issue of the franchise has to be determined by the Legislature as well as the governor.''</p>
        <p>Charles Carrier, a spokesman for Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, a Democrat, said, ''It sounds like a serious proposal that we have yet to be briefed on, and we look forward to learning the details.''</p>
        <p>The state's three thoroughbred tracks, Belmont, Aqueduct and Saratoga, handle more than $2.7 billion in combined racing bets a year. The 4,500 slot machines already approved for Aqueduct are projected to bring in $650 million in annual revenue. The administration is also considering bringing video gambling machines to Belmont.</p>
        <p>The franchise for the tracks expires at the end of the year. The franchise, which has been in the hands of the racing association since 1955, has had a troubled recent history. A federal monitor and a new management team were appointed in 2004 after a series of scandals. But the association has continued to struggle financially and declared bankruptcy late last year.</p>
        <p>The bidding process for the franchise has been years in the making.</p>
        <p>Last November, after a lengthy review, a commission dominated by Republicans appointed by former Governor George E. Pataki and Mr. Bruno recommended that a private bidder, Excelsior Racing Associates, take over the state's racing franchise.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Spitzer largely restarted the process after he took office.</p>
        <p>Initially, the Spitzer administration wanted to have MGM Mirage manage the thousands of video lottery terminals planned for Aqueduct, but MGM unexpectedly withdrew its bid this year. The administration then settled on a plan to leave thoroughbred racing in the hands of a restructured racing association.</p>
        <p>The most lucrative part of the franchise is expected to be the casino operation, and any private operator that took control would share revenue with the racing association, according to the aides.</p>
        <p>''Nothing here is written in stone,'' one of the governor's aides said. ''No. 1, this is part of the legislative process, we've been talking to the Legislature, but we don't have agreement at this point.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
