<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Joys of Teaching? Get Lost, Mr. Chips</title>
    <meta content="08chal" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/movies/08chal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852882"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Akel, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mass, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schremmer, Troy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haragan, Shannon</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Chalk (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Chalk (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DE1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Joys of Teaching? Get Lost, Mr. Chips</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Joys of Teaching? Get Lost, Mr. Chips</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews film Chalk, directed by Mike Akel; Chris Mass, Troy Schremmer and Shannon Haraganstar; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The gawky, overweight high school students in the fictional documentary ''Chalk'' are the antithesis of the sleek mean girls and buff junior studs of the typical Hollywood high school melodrama. Slouched glumly in their seats, they regard a new teacher with the blank gazes of bored, sullen prisoners serving out their sentences.</p>
        <p>What is an idealistic recruit to the teaching profession to do when faced with a wall of slovenly indifference? When Mr. Lowrey (Troy Schremmer), a first-year history teacher at Harrison High nervously asks his class what comes to mind when he says the word history, he is met with blank stares.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The loose-jointed ensemble comedy “Chalk” follows three teachers and one administrator over nine months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The gawky, overweight high school students in the fictional documentary ''Chalk'' are the antithesis of the sleek mean girls and buff junior studs of the typical Hollywood high school melodrama. Slouched glumly in their seats, they regard a new teacher with the blank gazes of bored, sullen prisoners serving out their sentences.</p>
        <p>What is an idealistic recruit to the teaching profession to do when faced with a wall of slovenly indifference? When Mr. Lowrey (Troy Schremmer), a first-year history teacher at Harrison High nervously asks his class what comes to mind when he says the word history, he is met with blank stares.</p>
        <p>''Chalk,'' which follows three teachers and one administrator over nine months, is so convincingly acted that if it didn't include brief interludes in which the grown-ups suddenly break into musical-comedy mode or reflect out loud in video diary segments, you might not guess it is fiction.</p>
        <p>This loose-jointed ensemble comedy is funny in a squirm-inducing way. The director, Mike Akel, and his screenwriting partner, Chris Mass, have both taught high school in Austin, Tex., and the cast includes some of their actual former students. They obviously know first-hand how unruly teenagers can gang up on a teacher and make him feel like a clueless relic.</p>
        <p>A bracing antidote to Hollywood's inspirational coach-athlete, teacher-student sob fests, this view of American high school life from a teacher's perspective feels painfully accurate. But ''Chalk'' isn't sour, even without redemption and personal transcendence. By the end of the school year progress has been made in generational communication. Still, you're not sure if anyone has really learned very much.</p>
        <p>Mostly the tone of ''Chalk'' is deadpan. No character is laugh-out-loud funny like the exhibitionist dog fanciers of ''Best in Show,'' the funniest of all recent so-called mockumentaries. The teachers may be older and more knowledgeable than their students, but as they complain, fret and bicker, they are uncomfortably similar to the adolescents under their watch.</p>
        <p>The most immature faculty member, Mr. Stroope (Mr. Mass), is an obsequious third-year history teacher obsessed with being voted teacher of the year. Not especially knowledgeable, he shamelessly begs one student to ''try not to know as much as me.''</p>
        <p>Coach Webb (Janelle Schremmer), an officious, prickly gym instructor with a crush on Mr. Lowrey, frets that people assume she is a lesbian because she has short hair and works in physical education. A stickler for the rules, she kicks up a fuss after she sees students entering a classroom a few seconds late, and she harasses her best friend, Mrs. Reddell (Shannon Haragan), a former teacher newly promoted to assistant principal, to enforce the rules strictly.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Reddell, whose marriage is suffering from her long working hours, is so snowed under by bureaucratic nonsense that she simply walks away. Her happiest days, she confesses, are those on which goes back into the classroom as a substitute.</p>
        <p>But it is Mr. Lowrey, a recently divorced former computer engineer, who is the most vulnerable and touching. After his class turns against him and steals his chalk, he goes searching for books on classroom management.</p>
        <p>The most excruciating incident he endures is a scuffle with a student over a cellphone that has not been turned off. Ejected from the classroom, the student shouts, ''You are a terrible teacher.'' When Mr. Lowrey pays a visit to the student's home, he is he is humiliated by the teenager and his mother.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lowrey's gradual development of a rapport with his students is the closest the movie comes to being upbeat. Its comic high point is a spelling bee (called a ''spelling hornet'') in which the students challenge the faculty to spell hip-hop slang words. When asked to ''spit something,'' Mr. Lowrey manages a few fumbling rhymes, and his effort is appreciated. But such small victories are not enough make him want to continue another year. His discouragement illustrates why, according to a title at the beginning of the movie, 50 percent of new teachers quit the profession within a few years.</p>
        <p>The movie is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has strong language.</p>
        <p>Chalk  Opens today in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Directed by Mike Akel; written by Mr. Akel and Chris Mass; director of photography, Steven Schaefer; edited by Bob Perkins; music by Chris Jagich; produced by Mr. Akel, Angie Alvarez and Graham Davidson; released by Virgil Films and Warrior Poets. At the Landmark's Sunshine Cinema, 139-143 East Houston Street, East Village. Running time: 105 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Troy Schremmer (Mr. Lowrey), Chris Mass (Mr. Stroope), Janelle Schremmer (Coach Webb) and Shannon Haragan (Mrs. Reddell).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
