<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Good Form Once, but Now a Dark Horse</title>
    <meta content="08thompson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/us/politics/08thompson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852918"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iowa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kifner, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thompson, Tommy G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John S (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romney, Mitt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Iowa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Iowa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Thompson, Tommy G</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EEDC1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1108" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Good Form Once, but Now a Dark Horse</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Good Form Once, but Now a Dark Horse</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN KIFNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kifner, John</byline>
      <dateline>MANCHESTER, N.H., June 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tommy G Thompson is faced with task of distinguishing himself in field of 10 Republican presidential candidates; consigned to 'lower tier' of candidates, he is scratching for headlines from press obsessed with Big Three: former Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani, Sen John McCain and former Gov Mitt Romney; Thompson's strategy is centered on winning Iowa caucuses, to establish himself as contender in later nominating contests; to that end, he is concentrating on Iowa straw poll, in which campaign puts up $30 for each of tickets that go to attendees who do the voting; poll is test of earlier fund-raising and of organization; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>How does a presidential candidate, consigned to the ''lower tier,'' distinguish himself in a field of 10 Republican hopefuls whose debates are a diorama of white male politicians in dark suits?</p>
        <p>That is the problem facing Tommy G. Thompson.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tommy G. Thompson is scratching for headlines from a press obsessed with other Republican hopefuls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>How does a presidential candidate, consigned to the ''lower tier,'' distinguish himself in a field of 10 Republican hopefuls whose debates are a diorama of white male politicians in dark suits?</p>
        <p>That is the problem facing Tommy G. Thompson.</p>
        <p>Little more than two years ago, Mr. Thompson was President Bush's secretary of health and human services, administering one of the largest budgets and departments in Washington. That job in turn followed his quite respectable 14-year run as governor of Wisconsin, where he earned praise for welfare and health care reforms.</p>
        <p>Now he is scratching for headlines from a press obsessed with the Big Three: former Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani of New York, who often gets roaring receptions; Senator John McCain of Arizona, with his ''straight talk'' message; and former Gov. Mitt Romney of Massachusetts, with his mountains of money and chiseled looks.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Thompson does manage to get headlines these days, they have not always been good. His remark at a Republican debate in May that employers should be able to fire gay workers drew a torrent of criticism, and his later explanation -- that his hearing aid had not been working and that he had urgently needed to use the bathroom -- only kept the story alive. And then there was his comment to a Jewish group that making money ''is part of the Jewish tradition.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Mr. Thompson, 65 and working on three hours' sleep, was upbeat through a grueling campaign day in New Hampshire on Wednesday. After beginning with a 6 a.m. television interview on CNN, he visited a talk radio show in Nashua, was interviewed via cellphone by two radio shows while on the road, delivered speeches at two candidate forums in Portsmouth and Concord, saw a factory that makes glass slides for microscopes and spoke at a Republican Party dinner in a style that veered from folksy to wonkish.</p>
        <p>''I'm the only one that has a plan out there,'' he kept repeating, saying he had ''detailed plans'' to solve what he described as America's two biggest crises: the war in Iraq (he suggests dividing the nation into Shiite, Sunni and Kurdish areas, where people would feel ''safe and comfortable'') and the challenges in health care, an issue that he knows something about and that the Democrats hope to ride to victory next year.</p>
        <p>On health care, he spewed statistics with zeal: ''125 million Americans have one or more chronic illnesses. 443,000 Americans die of nicotine-related diseases a year. last year there were 18 million Americans with Type 2 diabetes; this year there will be 21 million. 13 percent of people given prescriptions never fill them; 14 percent who go to pharmacists never pick them up.  just to go paperless would save 10 percent.''</p>
        <p>But the message does not always get through.</p>
        <p>At Tuesday night's two-hour Republican debate in nearby Goffstown, Mr. Thompson got to talk for only 4 minutes 21 seconds, according to unofficial but widely noted figures on a Web site affiliated with a Democratic candidate, Senator Christopher J. Dodd of Connecticut. Mr. McCain was the most voluble, clocking in at 12:44, followed closely by Mr. Giuliani at 12:35, with Mr. Romney at 11:04. Even the fringier but talkier Representative Ron Paul of Texas went on for 5 minutes 51 seconds.</p>
        <p>Nor is his situation improved by the looming possible entry of yet another candidate -- and another Thompson: former Senator Fred D. of Tennessee, who plays the gruff District Attorney Arthur Branch on television's ''Law &amp; Order,'' seen virtually round the clock.</p>
        <p>''I'm Thompson the presidential candidate, not Thompson the actor,'' the former governor has taken to growling.</p>
        <p>Obligatory American flag in his lapel, the red-haired Mr. Thompson is not afraid to employ some of his Irish charm on the trail. He told the receptionist at the microscope slide factory that she had a ''beautiful smile'' and asked if she was Irish (yes). He ends each speech with the Irish blessing that begins, ''May the road rise to meet you.''</p>
        <p>There are the small successes. Though his tart unscripted remark on how George W. Bush would be used in a Thompson administration -- ''I certainly wouldn't send him to the United Nations'' -- drew mostly nervous laughter at Tuesday night's debate, it figured in many news accounts, including notice on the front page of The Boston Globe, which circulates well in southern New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>But while Thursday's issue of The Union Leader, the only statewide paper, had long accounts of Mr. Giuliani's and Mr. Romney's activities in New Hampshire, it had none on Mr. Thompson's.</p>
        <p>Traveling on Wednesday in the four-door pickup of one of his handlers -- a gleaming hulk whose interior was soon filled with crumpled newspapers and scribbled telephone messages -- Mr. Thompson arrived at radio station WSMN in Nashua a little before 8:30 a.m. for the Allan Sprague-Woody Woodland talk show bearing a box of Dunkin' Donuts, a local ritual.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson immediately established rapport by discussing the memorable 1963 Rose Bowl game, in which his alma mater, Wisconsin, led by Ron VanderKelen at quarterback, rallied and almost beat U.S.C.</p>
        <p>But on air, the curmudgeonly Mr. Sprague demanded, ''America wants to know: will you pardon Paris Hilton?'' Mr. Thompson did not take the bait.</p>
        <p>Some hours later, he had a weightier matter to consider.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson's strategy is centered on winning the Iowa caucuses, to establish himself as a contender in later nominating contests. To that end, he has been concentrating on the strange custom known as the Iowa straw poll, scheduled for Aug. 11 in Ames, in which a campaign puts up $30 for each of the tickets that go to the attendees who do the voting. The campaign must also bus in the supporters, and feed them.</p>
        <p>The poll is thus a test of earlier fund-raising, and of organization, that in the past has served to eliminate lesser candidates. Mr. Thompson concedes that he has ''little money.'' But ''I have not missed a week in Iowa since Dec. 1,'' he said, adding that he had already visited 51 of the state's 99 counties.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson was explaining the intricacies of the straw poll when, at 2:35 on the road to Concord, he was called by his Iowa coordinator, Steve Grubbs, who said Mr. Giuliani had dropped out of it.</p>
        <p>It was a rare moment of triumph for Mr. Thompson. ''He doesn't want to be beat by me,'' he crowed.</p>
        <p>But the joy was short-lived. A second leading contender, Mr. McCain, pulled out of the poll later in the day, thus threatening to make a centerpiece of the Thompson strategy irrelevant.</p>
        <p>The big guys had done it again.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
