<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Handicapping the Tonys (I Got the Plays Right Here)</title>
    <meta content="08tony" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/theater/theaterspecial/08tony.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852898"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Tony Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06EEDE1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1669" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Handicapping the Tonys (I Got the Plays Right Here)</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Handicapping the Tonys (I Got the Plays Right Here)</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAMPBELL ROBERTSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Let's get one thing out of the way first: That 800-pound mobster in the room. Remember TiVo, people? The theater industry is counting on you to use it.</p>
        <p>Now to the business at hand.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here’s how the Tony Awards race looks, according to an unscientific survey of 22 Tony voters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Let's get one thing out of the way first: That 800-pound mobster in the room. Remember TiVo, people? The theater industry is counting on you to use it.</p>
        <p>Now to the business at hand.</p>
        <p>The 61st annual Tony Awards ceremony caps an unusual Broadway season rich for theatergoers, though not so rich for producers.</p>
        <p>Strangely, after a season so packed and so diverse, with a healthy dose of the unconventional and no runaway hit, the general feeling around Broadway this week is that the awarding of the Tonys is more or less a fait accompli: This one's a lock, that category's pretty much wrapped up, this actor can't lose.</p>
        <p>But there are more than 750 Tony voters from all over the industry -- and the country -- with their own tastes, preferences, friends, grudges and motives, ulterior or noble. So you never know for sure. Ask the producers of ''Sweeney Todd,'' one of the so-called locks last year.</p>
        <p>(O.K., about that 800-pound mobster. Sunday night pits the Tony awards ceremony, broadcast live on CBS from Radio City Music Hall, against the final episode ever of ''The Sopranos,'' or the Greatest Television Show in History, as it has come to be called. For those wondering: The organizers of the Tonys -- the American Theater Wing and the League of American Theaters and Producers -- had to choose the Tony date long before the finale of the Greatest Blah Blah was announced. But again, two words: Ti. Vo.)</p>
        <p>Here's how the race looks, according to a thoroughly unscientific survey of 22 Tony voters, a mix of producers, artists, journalists and road presenters.</p>
        <p>Yes, they say, several categories seem to be all but wrapped up: The night will probably end with the stage swarmed like a Cecil B. DeMille set with the legions of ''Spring Awakening'' producers; ''Grey Gardens'' is likely to pick up two performance awards, for leading and featured actress in a musical; Frank Langella of ''Frost/Nixon'' needs to have a speech ready.</p>
        <p>But the poll also revealed some suspense here and there. The leading-actress-in-a-play category is very much up in the air, with stage veterans pitted against newcomers; the award for leading actor in a musical appears to be in contention, contrary to the prevailing conventional wisdom; and the choreography category is anybody's game.</p>
        <p>This following list of predictions and ruminations includes the eight major categories and some semi-educated guesses about other races. Those who answered the poll did so on the condition of anonymity, for all the obvious reasons.</p>
        <p>Musical</p>
        <p>There's a chance that if you flip a coin 25 times in a row you could get heads every time. It's something like 1 in 34 million, but it's still a possibility.</p>
        <p>Likewise, according to our poll, there is a chance that ''Spring Awakening'' may lose out to ''Mary Poppins,'' ''Curtains'' or ''Grey Gardens'' for best musical of the season. Wouldn't bet on it though.</p>
        <p>Not only is ''Spring Awakening,'' the rock musical about sexually curious teenagers in 19th-century Germany, the far-and-away favorite for the top prize, it will probably pick up awards for direction (Michael Mayer), score (Duncan Sheik and Steven Sater), book (Mr. Sater) and lighting (Kevin Adams).</p>
        <p>Doug Wright's book for ''Grey Gardens,'' a musical about the eccentric relatives of Jacqueline Bouvier, will put up a serious fight. But in the end, according to the voters surveyed, the book for ''Spring Awakening'' will be carried over the top on the show's coattails.</p>
        <p>Other, less certain but possible wins for ''Spring'': featured actor (John Gallagher Jr.), orchestration (Mr. Sheik) and choreography (Bill T. Jones, though watch out for Jerry Mitchell, nominated for his work on ''Legally Blonde'').</p>
        <p>Play</p>
        <p>Of the four plays in this category, Douglas Carter Beane's satire ''The Little Dog Laughed'' doesn't have much of a chance. ''Radio Golf,'' despite its significant claim as the last in August Wilson's 10-play cycle, is also a long shot.</p>
        <p>There is a determined bunch lobbying for ''Frost/Nixon,'' Peter Morgan's re-creation of David Frost's 1977 interviews with Richard M. Nixon, and some are convinced it can win. But the Lincoln Center Theater production of Tom Stoppard's trilogy ''The Coast of Utopia,'' one of the most ambitious projects on a New York stage in years, should prevail here. Jack O'Brien, the director of ''Coast,'' is almost certain to pick up a Tony as well.</p>
        <p>The play design awards -- sets, lighting and costumes -- are likely to go to ''Coast,'' the voters in our survey said. The Tonys for best featured actor and actress in a play will probably go to ''Coast's'' Billy Crudup and Martha Plimpton, but could also go to its Ethan Hawke and Jennifer Ehle, or Billy Crudup and Jennifer Ehle, or Ethan Hawke and Martha Plimpton. You get the idea.</p>
        <p>In the end, so says the poll, ''Coast'' takes home seven awards, setting a record for the most Tonys picked up by one play.</p>
        <p>Play Revival</p>
        <p>''Journey's End,'' R. C. Sherriff's World War I drama, is the favorite, leading the Manhattan Theater Club's production of Brian Friel's ''Translations''; Eric Bogosian's ''Talk Radio''; and ''Inherit the Wind,'' by Jerome Lawrence and Robert E. Lee.</p>
        <p>The challenger is ''Inherit the Wind,'' which featured a sort of King Kong vs. Godzilla showdown between Christopher Plummer and Brian Dennehy. That probably won't be enough, though, and ''Journey's End'' will most likely take the Tony about five hours after ending its run on Broadway.</p>
        <p>Musical Revival</p>
        <p>Something seems familiar here. Last year, John Doyle's radical reimagining of ''Sweeney Todd,'' considered a safe bet, lost out to Kathleen Marshall's loving revival of ''The Pajama Game,'' considered the underdog.</p>
        <p>This year the category pits Mr. Doyle's radically reimagined ''Company'' against the faithful revival of ''A Chorus Line,'' as well as the Roundabout productions of ''110 in the Shade'' and ''The Apple Tree.''</p>
        <p>The austere revival of ''Company,'' the 1970 Stephen Sondheim and George Furth musical about marriage and/or loneliness, is limping at the box office, and ''A Chorus Line'' is a bona fide hit. But history will probably not repeat itself this year.</p>
        <p>According to the poll ''Company'' gets the Tony.</p>
        <p>Actress, Musical</p>
        <p>What a category: Audra McDonald (''110 in the Shade''), Donna Murphy (''LoveMusik''), Christine Ebersole (''Grey Gardens''), Debra Monk (''Curtains'') and Laura Bell Bundy (''Legally Blonde''). We're all winners here.</p>
        <p>Yeah, tell it to the nominees. Ms. Ebersole, who plays both Big Edith and Little Edie Beale in ''Grey Gardens'' and received radiant reviews, has been the front-runner for so long that you could be forgiven for assuming she had already won. But wait. Late in the season, when their shows opened, Ms. Murphy and Ms. McDonald arrived as real competition.</p>
        <p>And yet, in a sign of just how admired her performance is in one of the toughest categories of the night, Ms. Ebersole is still favored to win. She should still refrain from using the words ''unexpected'' or ''surprise'' in her acceptance speech.</p>
        <p>Actor, Musical</p>
        <p>The conventional wisdom says this one is going to Raúl Esparza, who has already won several awards for his starring role as Bobby in ''Company.''</p>
        <p>Michael Cerveris, playing Kurt Weill in ''LoveMusik'' has been overshadowed a little by the raves for his co-star, Donna Murphy; Gavin Lee has not stirred up much buzz for his turn as Bert in ''Mary Poppins''; and Jonathan Groff from ''Spring Awakening'' is, well, just getting started. (He'll have his chances, or so goes the logic.)</p>
        <p>But who's that lurking just outside Mr. Esparza's spotlight? Why, it's David Hyde Pierce, a man well liked around Broadway and the anchor for a show, ''Curtains,'' that got some disappointing reviews. Could the affection for Mr. Hyde Pierce and his performance be enough to earn him the Tony here?</p>
        <p>According our poll, yes it could. Mr. Hyde Pierce picked up the most votes. But it was very, very close.</p>
        <p>Actor, Play</p>
        <p>Frank Langella can go ahead and throw his hands in the air and make those double V's; his portrayal of Richard Nixon in ''Frost/Nixon'' is earning him a Tony, the poll says.</p>
        <p>As with the leading actress in a musical, just about anyone here could have been a front-runner in another season: Christopher Plummer for his turn as the speechifying Henry Drummond in ''Inherit the Wind''; Liev Schreiber as the self-destructive Barry Champlain in ''Talk Radio''; Boyd Gaines as the stoic Lieutenant Osborne in ''Journey's End''; and Brian F. O'Byrne as the, well, speechifying Alexander Herzen in ''The Coast of Utopia.''</p>
        <p>But this isn't another season.</p>
        <p>Actress, Play</p>
        <p>There are around 230 Tony voters who live outside of New York, including the 83 so-called road voters; that is, people whose main stake in the business is with non-New York theaters. (Many of the others are Broadway producers or executives who live elsewhere but put their money in New York.)</p>
        <p>That bodes well for Vanessa Redgrave (''The Year of Magical Thinking''), Angela Lansbury (''Deuce'') and Eve Best (''A Moon for the Misbegotten''), whose plays are all running and were on the boards when Tony voters suddenly saw the ceremony approaching on their calendars and started scrambling to get to the city and see the shows.</p>
        <p>That, of course, hurts Swoosie Kurtz (''Heartbreak House'') and Julie White (''The Little Dog Laughed''), whose shows closed months ago. A missed performance is missed for good.</p>
        <p>However.</p>
        <p>Ms. Redgrave and Ms. Lansbury, eminently talented and beloved actresses, are in plays that left many cold. Ms. Best was raved about and seemed to be the front-runner in this category for a time, but ''Moon'' was also poorly received, and Ms. Best is not well known.</p>
        <p>She is still probably the favorite this year, but in our limited pool of Tony voters, which includes both New Yorkers and out-of-towners, the contest wasn't even close.</p>
        <p>Survey says: Ms. White.</p>
        <p>The 61st Annual Tony Awards will be shown on CBS Sunday night at 8 p.m. Eastern time, 7 Central time. Nothing of any interest is showing on any other channel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
