<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Girl Recovers at a Hospital, but Answers and a Happy Ending Remain Elusive</title>
    <meta content="08missing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/nyregion/08missing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852990"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DA1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1090" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Girl Recovers at a Hospital, but Answers and a Happy Ending Remain Elusive</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Girl Recovers at a Hospital, but Answers and a Happy Ending Remain Elusive</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON LEIGH COWAN and NATE SCHWEBER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Unable to hold back tears, the mother of a 15-year-old Connecticut girl who was discovered in a locked crawl space at the home of three adults said yesterday that she was impatient to get her daughter back.</p>
        <p>''We love you and miss you very much and hope you come home real soon,'' the girl's stepfather added at news conference at the Bloomfield Police Department, not far from where she was found at the home in West Hartford on Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Unable to hold back tears, the mother of a 15-year-old Connecticut girl who was discovered in a locked crawl space at the home of three adults said yesterday that she was impatient to get her daughter back.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Unable to hold back tears, the mother of a 15-year-old Connecticut girl who was discovered in a locked crawl space at the home of three adults said yesterday that she was impatient to get her daughter back.</p>
        <p>''We love you and miss you very much and hope you come home real soon,'' the girl's stepfather added at news conference at the Bloomfield Police Department, not far from where she was found at the home in West Hartford on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>But as the teenager remained hospitalized, questions about the reasons for her disappearance and the circumstances under which she was living mounted as the parents, the police and lawyers for the three people charged in connection with her disappearance issued conflicting statements over the course of the day.</p>
        <p>So far, the police have not charged the three defendants -- identified by the police as Adam Gault, a 41-year-old dog trainer, and two women who also lived at the house, Ann Murphy, 40, and Kimberly Cray, 26 -- with kidnapping the girl, whom the police described as a habitual runaway who vanished last June.</p>
        <p>The three were arraigned yesterday on charges that had been reduced from those made at the initial arrests. They were charged with conspiracy to commit unlawful restraint, conspiracy to put a minor at risk of injury and interfering with the police. Mr. Gault's bail was set at $1 million. Ms. Murphy was held in $750,000 bail, and Ms. Cray's bail was set at $500,000. All three remain in custody.</p>
        <p>The authorities say they are operating under the impression that the girl may have been induced to leave her home last June, only to be abused while living with the three defendants.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, when she was discovered, one police official suggested that the girl's pallor was caused by being deprived of sunlight for a long time.</p>
        <p>But outside State Superior Court in Hartford yesterday, a lawyer for one of the defendants offered a sharply contrasting picture of the girl's year away from home.</p>
        <p>According to Michael A. Georgetti, a lawyer for Ms. Cray, the girl attended school, had a cellphone and was staying in West Hartford because she had fled a dysfunctional household.</p>
        <p>''You're going to find this is not a case of kidnapping,'' Mr. Georgetti said.</p>
        <p>Referring to Mr. Gault, he said, ''This individual was trying to protect a young girl from being sexually assaulted and physically assaulted in the home where she originally lived.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Georgetti added: ''She was not being held in captivity. She was hiding from police because she did not want to be returned to her home.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the Bloomfield police said that Mr. Gault, who had worked with the girl's stepfather, had filed two complaints on her behalf before the disappearance, one claiming that a friend of the family had abused her, the other claiming that a relative had threatened her.</p>
        <p>But Capt. Jeffrey L. Blatter of the Bloomfield Police Department said that officials could not substantiate those claims.</p>
        <p>And at the afternoon news conference, Captain Blatter said there was no evidence that the girl was enrolled in school, although Mr. Gault ''coaxed her into assuming another identity and going by another name.''</p>
        <p>Among the items seized at the home on Wednesday were three forged identification cards, according to a police report.</p>
        <p>Lt. Matthew Willauer, commanding officer for Bloomfield's detective division, said that the two female defendants had helped take care of the missing girl and were aware that she was not Mr. Gault's child.</p>
        <p>Since the girl was discovered, Captain Blatter said, the authorities had received calls ''from in and out of state'' from people claiming to have been abused by Mr. Gault.</p>
        <p>For now, the lawyer for the girl's mother and stepfather, Marc N. Needelman, said that she had been hospitalized in an effort to ease her reintegration and that his clients expected her to rejoin the family. He said the couple had been allowed to visit her.</p>
        <p>''Every parent's nightmare was mine,'' the girl's teary-eyed mother said at the news conference. ''I could never describe the horror of losing a child and having to maintain a family at the same time.''</p>
        <p>Asked about the assertion that her daughter was fleeing a dysfunctional or dangerous home, she said that, ''There's a lot of allegations out there,'' and that ''trying to filter through them'' would be a challenge.</p>
        <p>Jeanne Milstein, the state's child advocate, said that there was still much to learn about what had happened but suggested that the system could have done more.</p>
        <p>''I have very few facts, but in my office we have too often seen the plight of runaways,'' she said. ''There are far too many children who are running away, so when children run away, they run away for a reason.''</p>
        <p>Last night, the Department of Children and Families said it would be assisting the police and ''reviewing a brief involvement with the family last summer.''</p>
        <p>The police maintained yesterday that the girl's mother and stepfather were not suspects in her disappearance.</p>
        <p>Captain Blatter said that although the girl appeared to have run away from home, there were extensive telephone records suggesting that Mr. Gault may have ''had quite a bit of time to influence her decision.''</p>
        <p>Asked if she could have left Mr. Gault's home at any time, Captain Blatter said, ''Physically yes. Emotionally, we're talking about a 14-year-old under the influence of a 40-year-old.''</p>
        <p>The police had repeatedly questioned Mr. Gault over the past year in their search for the girl. They finally obtained search warrants after obtaining ''biological fluids,'' although they refused to be more specific.</p>
        <p>Armed with those warrants, a team from the Bloomfield and West Hartford Police Departments arrived at the house at 7 a.m. on Wednesday. Mr. Gault, they said, continued to insist that he knew nothing about the girl's whereabouts.</p>
        <p>But a West Hartford detective, Steven Hinckley, wrote in a report: ''As I walked into the home, I found the home to be in a state of general disarray. Every window was covered so you could not see in or out. There was trash, clothes and debris scattered throughout the house. The home also had a foul odor.''</p>
        <p>While searching the master bedroom, he spotted a small door to a crawl space behind a dresser cluttered with debris. Releasing the slide bolt on the door, he wrote, he opened the door to find the girl sitting in the crawl space.</p>
        <p>Clothed in a shirt and shorts, she immediately began crying, the detective wrote.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
