<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Familiar Royal Story, Told by a Media Queen</title>
    <meta content="08book" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/books/08book.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852884"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Diana, Princess of Wales</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Brown, Tina</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">The Diana Chronicles (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E1DE1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="942" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Familiar Royal Story, Told by a Media Queen</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Diana Chronicles</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Diana Chronicles  By Tina Brown  542 pages. Doubleday. $27.50.</p>
        <p>Like any writer examining the life and death of Diana, Princess of Wales, Tina Brown must peer into the world of British royalty with nose pressed to the glass. Unlike almost all of the others, Ms. Brown does not fog the windowpanes. In ''The Diana Chronicles'' -- which is her ''maiden foray into long-form nonfiction,'' or first book -- this celebrated editor, mover and shaker brings her own sort of privilege to the realm of aristocratic fairy tales. She knows this world much better than many who inhabit it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This is a Diana book with much more smart, snarky flair than most, told by someone who knows the world of aristocratic fairy tales much better than many who inhabit it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Diana Chronicles  By Tina Brown  542 pages. Doubleday. $27.50.</p>
        <p>Like any writer examining the life and death of Diana, Princess of Wales, Tina Brown must peer into the world of British royalty with nose pressed to the glass. Unlike almost all of the others, Ms. Brown does not fog the windowpanes. In ''The Diana Chronicles'' -- which is her ''maiden foray into long-form nonfiction,'' or first book -- this celebrated editor, mover and shaker brings her own sort of privilege to the realm of aristocratic fairy tales. She knows this world much better than many who inhabit it.</p>
        <p>It takes Ms. Brown's blend of arch journalistic savvy and social sang-froid to capture the kind of patrician women whose ''aggressive beaky look comes from years of catering to oblivious men,'' or to say of Prince Charles that ''it's the grooming that gives him liftoff.'' She appreciates that Diana had a grandfather who ''didn't see the point of ordinary people.'' And as editor of the British magazine Tatler in the Shy Di years, Ms. Brown enjoyed featuring the kinds of blue-blooded young women from whose ranks Diana came. But Diana was special, and not only because she won ''perhaps the most endearing airhead award ever: the prize for best-kept guinea pig.''</p>
        <p>''The Diana Chronicles'' is a Diana book with much more smart, snarky flair than most. But it is still a Diana book that is built on earlier ones. And the others have such varied provenance and reliability that Ms. Brown's methods raise some questions. Although she conducted many interviews of her own -- tough, in-the-trenches work with John Travolta and Mikhail Baryshnikov about dancing with Diana, for instance -- she also relies credulously on Fleet Street sources and disaffected palace functionaries.</p>
        <p>Only rarely, as with an account by the Diana-designated biographer Andrew Morton of Prince Charles's proposal of marriage (''heavily scored for cello and bass,'' according to Ms. Brown), is she skeptical about accuracy. This is true even though several of those whose material she recycles have wound up on reality TV shows, where one of them, Paul Burrell, Diana's former butler, ate the testicle of a kangaroo. So the anecdotes in ''The Diana Chronicles'' wind up varying from credible to melodramatic to weirdly sitcomlike (Diana clobbering Charles with a Bible while he kneels in prayer?), although many reveal Ms. Brown's fine ear for casual snobbery. ''We've all had our Dodi Fayeds,'' one of Diana's friends says about the ''Egyptian lounge lizard,'' in Ms. Brown's phrase, who was Diana's last Prince Charming.</p>
        <p>At its best this book combines gossip, opinion and context in ways that cast new light on Diana's cautionary tale. When Ms. Brown investigates the circumstances of a 1980 assignation aboard the royal train between Prince Charles and either his fiancée, Diana, or his old flame, Camilla Parker-Bowles, she finds reason to conclude that it was Diana who appeared there. But she is more interesting about the event's cloak of secrecy. This ''was the moment she first became a Royal,'' Ms. Brown writes of the supposedly virginal Diana, ''supported in muffling the truth by a network of polished operators who had agendas of their own.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Brown is similarly acute in parsing various Diana-Camilla chess moves. When the two finally had an emotional confrontation, she writes, Ms. Parker-Bowles's evident embarrassment was probably for Diana, not for herself.</p>
        <p>As she parses the royals' behavior, Ms. Brown is keenly attuned to its class implications. The notorious story of how Camilla first approached Charles, reminded him that their ancestors had been lovers and propositioned him is, Ms. Brown says, ridiculous. Prince Charles would already have known about the ancestors -- ''and 'How about it?' is about as upper-class a locution as 'cor blimey!' ''</p>
        <p>She suggests that ''That's a fine animal you have there, Sir'' was a likelier and better come-on, even if one of her sources about Charles and Camilla's intimacies is ''The Royals'' by Kitty Kelley. And in discussing the still-excruciating ''Camillagate'' taped conversation, she pays more attention to Camilla's skillful flattery than to Charles's bizarre longings. Although Ms. Brown's main focus is Diana, there are times when she sounds more admiring of Camilla's no-nonsense warmth than Diana's flair for drama.</p>
        <p>''The Diana Chronicles'' does its share of detective work, as when it considers the possible ways private conversations were made so public. But its more important thoughts concern the changing role of the press. As in the film ''The Queen,'' which this book resembles in its calm, credible, quietly shattering view of life inside the royal hothouse, the ability of press coverage to change history is treated seriously. And the evolution of the media's treatment of the crown, from hands-off to no-holds-barred, is all too clearly understood.</p>
        <p>If anything, Ms. Brown understates her own role as a player in this process, as when she refers almost wistfully to ''those pre-Demi Moore days, before it became routine for starlets to pose knocked up and naked for the covers of national and international magazines.'' It was on Ms. Brown's watch at Vanity Fair that the bar for celebrity privacy was lowered by that notch.</p>
        <p>She depicts Diana as someone who learned to use the new candor of the press in self-defense, only to discover that the damage she had inflicted, in exposing Buckingham Palace's steady stream of lies about her happy marriage, was irreperable. ''Diana was not a strategist,'' Ms. Brown writes. ''She was a tactician. She did not plan for the day after.'' In that regard she could not have been less like Ms. Brown, and Ms. Brown's perspective could not be more useful in spotting the Machiavellian subtext in Diana's story.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
