<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Chorus Is Dancing, And the Mother's Grim</title>
    <meta content="08alba" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/theater/reviews/08alba.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852900"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Asian American Theater Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hampton, Wilborn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yew, Chay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garcia Lorca, Federico (1898-1936)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Valdes-Aran, Ching</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">House of Bernarda Alba, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Asian-American Theater Co</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Yew, Chay</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">House of Bernarda Alba, The (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEEDE1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Chorus Is Dancing, And the Mother's Grim</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Chorus Is Dancing, and the Mother’s Grim</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILBORN HAMPTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hampton, Wilborn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wilborn Hampton reviews National Asian American Theater Company production of Chay Yew adaptation of Federico Garcia Lorca play The House of Bernarda Alba; Ching Valdes-Aran stars; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Death pervades ''The House of Bernarda Alba,'' not only the two that are knelled at the beginning and end of Federico García Lorca's last play but also the suffocating atmosphere that permeates life for the inhabitants inside. The National Asian American Theater Company has mounted a first-rate revival in an adaptation by Chay Yew that is somewhat abbreviated but maintains García Lorca's tragic claustrophobia.</p>
        <p>Certainly there was a lot of death in Spain at the time the play was written, and García Lorca himself was gunned down by Franco's Nationalists shortly after he finished it, in 1936 at the age of 38. Some critics have read a political message into the play, but while liberty is a central theme, it is for the freedom of the individual, especially women, from society's repressive mores.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The National Asian American Theater Company has mounted a first-rate revival of Federico García Lorca’s last play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Death pervades ''The House of Bernarda Alba,'' not only the two that are knelled at the beginning and end of Federico García Lorca's last play but also the suffocating atmosphere that permeates life for the inhabitants inside. The National Asian American Theater Company has mounted a first-rate revival in an adaptation by Chay Yew that is somewhat abbreviated but maintains García Lorca's tragic claustrophobia.</p>
        <p>Certainly there was a lot of death in Spain at the time the play was written, and García Lorca himself was gunned down by Franco's Nationalists shortly after he finished it, in 1936 at the age of 38. Some critics have read a political message into the play, but while liberty is a central theme, it is for the freedom of the individual, especially women, from society's repressive mores.</p>
        <p>At the outset Bernarda Alba has just buried another husband and is returning from the funeral with her five daughters. Appearances are paramount to Bernarda. If she knew of her husband's affair with the servant Blanca, she ignores it and orders eight years of mourning for him. She denies villagers the opportunity to criticize her by not letting them in her house. She locks away her own mother because she could be an embarrassment.</p>
        <p>Bernarda tries to preserve her daughters' chastity by not allowing them outside except to go to church. Even then, she admonishes them not to let their eyes wander to the men in the congregation. ''Women in church should never look at a man, except the priest, and he only because he's wearing a skirt.''</p>
        <p>But even houses with double locks have windows, and Bernarda can do little to prevent her daughters from looking out of them to watch the bare-chested field hands, or to keep Pepe el Romano, the village's young buck, from late-night visits beneath them. Pepe may end up engaged to Angustias, the oldest and ugliest of Bernarda's daughters, but it is Adela, the youngest and most beautiful of the girls, for whom he lusts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yew, who also directed, has assembled a fine cast for the production, at the Baruch Performing Arts Center. The ensemble includes a 12-member chorus that dances a flamenco at one point and provides a variety of sound effects, from clapping for castanets to slapping their thighs for galloping horses.</p>
        <p>As Bernarda Alba, Ching Valdes-Aran is a portrait of strait-laced rectitude. With her hair pulled tight in a bun and wielding her cane like a scepter, Ms. Valdes-Aran could be a cross between Madame Mao and Madame Chiang Kai-shek with a Castilian accent. Natsuko Ohama and Carmen M. Herlihy deliver excellent performances as Angustias, the eldest sister, and Martirio, the daughter who spies on her siblings. Ali Ahn flashes with youthful passion as Adela, and Kati Kuroda provides a good turn as Poncia, Bernarda's old servant.</p>
        <p>''The House of Bernarda Alba'' continues through June 23 at the Nagelberg Theater, Baruch Performing Arts Center, 55 Lexington Avenue, at 25th Street; (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
