<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES: June 8 - June 14; For Children</title>
    <meta content="08Kids" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/arts/08Kids.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852866"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E5DE1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES: June 8 - June 14; For Children</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spare Times: For Children</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAUREL GRAEBER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALL STARS HIP-HOP CABARET (Tonight) This evening of performance by and for teenagers and young adults -- with song, dance and rap about growing up in the city's poorer neighborhoods -- also offers work by seasoned artists, including an excerpt from ''Sally &amp; Tom (the American Way),'' a musical by Fred Newman about Thomas Jefferson and his slave Sally Hemings. (Through June 16.) At 7, the All Stars Project, 543 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 941-1234; $25; $10 for students.</p>
        <p>ANIMAL RHYTHMS: Two African Folktales (Sunday) The title of this show and the name of the troupe -- Treehouse Shakers -- should provide clues that this is not just a performance at which children politely sit. A dance play written by Mara McEwin and choreographed by Emily Bunning, ''Animal Rhythms'' animates the stories ''The Day It Rained'' and ''Jackal and Hare'' with lots of audience participation. At 11 a.m., Here Arts Center, 145 Avenue of the Americas, at Dominick Street, South Village, (212) 715-1914, treehouseshakers.com; $15.</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN INTERNATIONAL FILM FESTIVAL'S KIDSFILMFEST (Tomorrow) These 20 shorts are long on ideas and humor, and while they represent several countries, they are entirely in English. The fare is divided between the Peewee Program, for preschoolers through third graders, and the Tween-Time Program, for fourth through eighth graders. But there's no need to worry if your family members span the categories: The Brooklyn Children's Museum, the festival's site, has two theaters, and each program will be shown in its entirety at both 1 and 3 p.m. At 145 Brooklyn Avenue, at St. Mark's Avenue, Crown Heights, (718) 735-4400, kidsfilmfest.org. Free with museum admission: $5; free for members.</p>
        <p>CARNIVAL ON THE HUDSON (Tomorrow) Here the rides will include boat excursions on the river, courtesy of the ship Lil' Toot. The carnival will also offer music, street performers, face painters, raffles and, of course, food. All proceeds benefit the P.T.A.'s of P.S. 89 and I.S. 89. From noon to 5 p.m., World Financial Center Plaza, West Street, south of Vesey Street, Lower Manhattan, (212) 267-3623; free admission (rides require paid tickets). (In case of rain the event will move indoors to the Winter Garden.)</p>
        <p>CIRCUS SUNDAYS IN JUNE (Sunday) Brooklyn not only has a floating concert hall (Bargemusic), it also has a floating circus. This attraction, on board the Waterfront Museum and Showboat Barge, presents different entertainers every Sunday of the month. This Sunday's roster includes Acrobatic Adagio, a duo whose name says it all; Ambrose Martos, part of the clown trio Happy Hour; Kenny Kool, a young hand balancer; and the Doll, who is very much alive and does trapeze dance. At 1 and 4 p.m., Conover Street and the waterfront, Red Hook, (877) 238-5596, waterfrontmuseum.org. Tickets: in advance, $12; $6 for under 12. At the door, $15 and $8.</p>
        <p>CITYWIDE 8th GRADE SCIENCE EXPO (Tomorrow) Pioneers in research often start young, and these eager investigators will show off projects completed through Urban Advantage, a citywide science education initiative for middle schools undertaken with the American Museum of Natural History. From 1 to 4 p.m. at the museum, Milstein Hall of Ocean Life, Central Park West and 79th Street, (212) 769-5200, www.urbanadvantagenyc.org. Free with suggested museum admission: $14.50; $10.50 for students and 60+; $8 for 2 to 12; free for members.</p>
        <p>DANCEWAVE'S KIDS COMPANY SPRING CELEBRATION (Tomorrow) The choreographers are well-known artists like Twyla Tharp, Mark Morris and Trisha Brown, and the performers hope to be well known someday; they're the 12- to 18-year-old members of Dancewave's Kids Company, a preprofessional troupe chosen by audition. At 7:30 p.m., Attic Theater, Brooklyn Academy of Music, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene; $22; $12 for 18 and younger. Reservations required: (718) 522-4696, dancewave.org.</p>
        <p>FESTIVAL OF HOMEGROWN WORK (Tonight through Sunday) Oddball animation, contemporary fairy tales, a lounge-act musical of highlights from the French Revolution and a 10-minute excerpt from a one-man ''Wizard of Oz'' are all on the menu in this new festival from Downtown Art. Like its other productions, it features young artists -- ages 12 to 24 -- and that downtown state of mind. (Three programs run at different hours.) At Downtown Art, 61 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 479-0885, downtownart.org; $8; $5 for students.</p>
        <p>'THE GAZILLION BUBBLE SHOW' (Tonight through Sunday, and Wednesday and Thursday) Children love bubbles, and Fan Yang, in his interactive show, promises not just a gazillion, but also some of the largest ever blown (he holds the world record), along with light effects and lasers. (Through Sept 2.) Tonight at 7; tomorrow at 11 a.m. and 2 and 7 p.m.; Sunday at noon and 3 p.m.; Wednesday at 2 and 7 p.m.; Thursday at 7 p.m. New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200, gazillionbubbleshow.com; $40, $50 and $60.</p>
        <p>'GUSTAFER YELLOWGOLD'S WIDE WILD WORLD' (Sunday) Another space alien has landed. Hailing from the Sun and described as part cat, Gustafer Yellowgold is the creation of the illustrator and composer Morgan Taylor, who will present Gustafer's tales -- now released on DVD and CD -- with live music, slides and narration. At noon, the Bowery Poetry Club, 308 Bowery, near Bleecker Street, East Village, (212) 614-0505, bowerypoetry.com; $8.</p>
        <p>'THE JUNGLE BOOK' (Tomorrow and Sunday) This Mowgli shouldn't have any trouble swinging through the jungle; he's on strings anyway. Puppetworks has adapted Rudyard Kipling's tales into a marionette production featuring traditional Indian motifs. (Through Aug. 19.) At 12:30 and 2:30 p.m., 338 Sixth Avenue, at Fourth Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-3391, puppetworks.org; $8; $7 for 15 and under.</p>
        <p>KID ACTS! AFTERNOON PERFORMANCE AND DANCE PARTY (Sunday) This is indeed a program of child-friendly acts, including AudraRox, a rock band made up mostly of (very hip) parents; the Hover Brothers, who combine comedy and magic; and GrooveHoops, whose groove is hula hoops. They will take part in an outdoor festival that is in the annual Summer on the Hudson @ Riverside Park series. From 2 to 4 p.m., Pier 1, at 70th Street, Riverside Park South, Manhattan, nyc.gov/parks or 311. Free.</p>
        <p>'THE MILK DRAGON' (Tomorrow and Sunday) Who says children are too young for works with political import? This production inaugurates the 10th season of New Plays for Young Audiences, a series of staged readings sponsored by the Program in Educational Theater at the Steinhardt School of Culture, Education and Human Development at New York University. Written by Suzan Zeder, the show, billed as a ''political fantasy,'' follows two young people, Zack and Abra, as they encounter a forest where everything considered too dangerous or complicated has been banned. Tomorrow at 3 and 7:30 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., the Provincetown Playhouse, 133 Macdougal Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 998-5867; $5; free for high school students and children.</p>
        <p>'MODERN ARTWORKS' (Today and tomorrow) It isn't often that artists under 20 get to show in a gallery and sell their work. But each year the CUE Art Foundation sponsors the Modern ArtWorks program, which takes middle and high school students to view exhibitions at CUE, discuss the art and create projects of their own. This exhibition showcases the fruits of their labor, which are on sale for $50 each; proceeds will be split between the student and his or her school. Expect to see jazz-theme paintings, abstract art, photo collage, mixed media and more. From 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. at CUE, 511 West 25th Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-3583, cueartfoundation.org; free.</p>
        <p>'THE MUSIC IN ME' (Tomorrow) All children seem to have music in them, but not all have the means to express it. That's where Midori &amp; Friends, an organization founded by the violinist Midori, comes in. It has been offering free music-education programs in city schools for 15 years, and on Sunday the students, from elementary to high school age, will present their second annual Children's Music Festival. The storyteller David Gonzalez will be host, and world music artists like Arturo O'Farrill will perform. At 3 p.m., TriBeCa Performing Arts Center, Borough of Manhattan Community College, 199 Chambers Street, (212) 767-1300, midoriandfriends.org; free.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK FAMILY ARTS FESTIVAL (Tomorrow and Sunday) Unity in diversity is certainly possible, and it is being celebrated at this monthlong event, which focuses on the multicultural arts of the city. Tomorrow from noon to 7 p.m., the festival's ''South African Cultural Village'' will offer classes in Zulu dance, as well as craft workshops, song and drumming. On Sunday at 2 p.m., ''Salute to the Family'' includes music and dance and a tribute to social service organizations. At the Riverside Theater, Riverside Avenue at 122nd Street, Morningside Heights. Free, but reservations requested: (212) 870-6784.</p>
        <p>'PINKALICIOUS' (Tomorrow) Sometimes being in the pink can be too much of a good thing, as the pink-obsessed title character finds out in this new musical from Vital Children's Theater, which Elizabeth and Victoria Kann adapted from their children's book. (Extended through June 30.) At noon, SoHo Playhouse, 15 Van Dam Street, near Varick Street, South Village, (212) 691-1555, sohoplayhouse.com; $25 (reservations advised).</p>
        <p>SPRING CELEBRATION: A FAMILY CONCERT (Tomorrow) What better way to herald spring, a season of growth, than with the combined voices of 250 singers ages 8 to 18? That group is the Young People's Chorus of New York City, resident choir of the 92nd Street Y, which will perform a wide-ranging program, from Bach and Mussorgsky to a West African folk song and ''Sit Down, You're Rocking the Boat,'' from ''Guy and Dolls.'' At 8 p.m., the Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5500; $60, $25 and $10; $65 and $25 seats are only $10 for students and 65+.</p>
        <p>DAVID WEINSTONE AND THE MUSIC FOR AARDVARKS BAND (Tomorrow) Music for aardvarks is also music for children, as Mr. Weinstone, a former punk rocker, will demonstrate. His group specializes in tunes for urban kids, as evidenced in its new album, ''Taxi.'' At 11 a.m. (doors open at 10), the Concert Hall, New York Society for Ethical Culture, 2 West 64th Street, Manhattan, (212) 277-7179 or (212) 307-7171, theconcerthall.org; $20.</p>
        <p>LAUREL GRAEBER</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR CHILDREN.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALL STARS HIP-HOP CABARET (Tonight) This evening of performance by and for teenagers and young adults -- with song, dance and rap about growing up in the city's poorer neighborhoods -- also offers work by seasoned artists, including an excerpt from ''Sally &amp; Tom (the American Way),'' a musical by Fred Newman about Thomas Jefferson and his slave Sally Hemings. (Through June 16.) At 7, the All Stars Project, 543 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 941-1234; $25; $10 for students.</p>
        <p>ANIMAL RHYTHMS: Two African Folktales (Sunday) The title of this show and the name of the troupe -- Treehouse Shakers -- should provide clues that this is not just a performance at which children politely sit. A dance play written by Mara McEwin and choreographed by Emily Bunning, ''Animal Rhythms'' animates the stories ''The Day It Rained'' and ''Jackal and Hare'' with lots of audience participation. At 11 a.m., Here Arts Center, 145 Avenue of the Americas, at Dominick Street, South Village, (212) 715-1914, treehouseshakers.com; $15.</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN INTERNATIONAL FILM FESTIVAL'S KIDSFILMFEST (Tomorrow) These 20 shorts are long on ideas and humor, and while they represent several countries, they are entirely in English. The fare is divided between the Peewee Program, for preschoolers through third graders, and the Tween-Time Program, for fourth through eighth graders. But there's no need to worry if your family members span the categories: The Brooklyn Children's Museum, the festival's site, has two theaters, and each program will be shown in its entirety at both 1 and 3 p.m. At 145 Brooklyn Avenue, at St. Mark's Avenue, Crown Heights, (718) 735-4400, kidsfilmfest.org. Free with museum admission: $5; free for members.</p>
        <p>CARNIVAL ON THE HUDSON (Tomorrow) Here the rides will include boat excursions on the river, courtesy of the ship Lil' Toot. The carnival will also offer music, street performers, face painters, raffles and, of course, food. All proceeds benefit the P.T.A.'s of P.S. 89 and I.S. 89. From noon to 5 p.m., World Financial Center Plaza, West Street, south of Vesey Street, Lower Manhattan, (212) 267-3623; free admission (rides require paid tickets). (In case of rain the event will move indoors to the Winter Garden.)</p>
        <p>CIRCUS SUNDAYS IN JUNE (Sunday) Brooklyn not only has a floating concert hall (Bargemusic), it also has a floating circus. This attraction, on board the Waterfront Museum and Showboat Barge, presents different entertainers every Sunday of the month. This Sunday's roster includes Acrobatic Adagio, a duo whose name says it all; Ambrose Martos, part of the clown trio Happy Hour; Kenny Kool, a young hand balancer; and the Doll, who is very much alive and does trapeze dance. At 1 and 4 p.m., Conover Street and the waterfront, Red Hook, (877) 238-5596, waterfrontmuseum.org. Tickets: in advance, $12; $6 for under 12. At the door, $15 and $8.</p>
        <p>CITYWIDE 8th GRADE SCIENCE EXPO (Tomorrow) Pioneers in research often start young, and these eager investigators will show off projects completed through Urban Advantage, a citywide science education initiative for middle schools undertaken with the American Museum of Natural History. From 1 to 4 p.m. at the museum, Milstein Hall of Ocean Life, Central Park West and 79th Street, (212) 769-5200, www.urbanadvantagenyc.org. Free with suggested museum admission: $14.50; $10.50 for students and 60+; $8 for 2 to 12; free for members.</p>
        <p>DANCEWAVE'S KIDS COMPANY SPRING CELEBRATION (Tomorrow) The choreographers are well-known artists like Twyla Tharp, Mark Morris and Trisha Brown, and the performers hope to be well known someday; they're the 12- to 18-year-old members of Dancewave's Kids Company, a preprofessional troupe chosen by audition. At 7:30 p.m., Attic Theater, Brooklyn Academy of Music, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene; $22; $12 for 18 and younger. Reservations required: (718) 522-4696, dancewave.org.</p>
        <p>FESTIVAL OF HOMEGROWN WORK (Tonight through Sunday) Oddball animation, contemporary fairy tales, a lounge-act musical of highlights from the French Revolution and a 10-minute excerpt from a one-man ''Wizard of Oz'' are all on the menu in this new festival from Downtown Art. Like its other productions, it features young artists -- ages 12 to 24 -- and that downtown state of mind. (Three programs run at different hours.) At Downtown Art, 61 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 479-0885, downtownart.org; $8; $5 for students.</p>
        <p>'THE GAZILLION BUBBLE SHOW' (Tonight through Sunday, and Wednesday and Thursday) Children love bubbles, and Fan Yang, in his interactive show, promises not just a gazillion, but also some of the largest ever blown (he holds the world record), along with light effects and lasers. (Through Sept 2.) Tonight at 7; tomorrow at 11 a.m. and 2 and 7 p.m.; Sunday at noon and 3 p.m.; Wednesday at 2 and 7 p.m.; Thursday at 7 p.m. New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200, gazillionbubbleshow.com; $40, $50 and $60.</p>
        <p>'GUSTAFER YELLOWGOLD'S WIDE WILD WORLD' (Sunday) Another space alien has landed. Hailing from the Sun and described as part cat, Gustafer Yellowgold is the creation of the illustrator and composer Morgan Taylor, who will present Gustafer's tales -- now released on DVD and CD -- with live music, slides and narration. At noon, the Bowery Poetry Club, 308 Bowery, near Bleecker Street, East Village, (212) 614-0505, bowerypoetry.com; $8.</p>
        <p>'THE JUNGLE BOOK' (Tomorrow and Sunday) This Mowgli shouldn't have any trouble swinging through the jungle; he's on strings anyway. Puppetworks has adapted Rudyard Kipling's tales into a marionette production featuring traditional Indian motifs. (Through Aug. 19.) At 12:30 and 2:30 p.m., 338 Sixth Avenue, at Fourth Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-3391, puppetworks.org; $8; $7 for 15 and under.</p>
        <p>KID ACTS! AFTERNOON PERFORMANCE AND DANCE PARTY (Sunday) This is indeed a program of child-friendly acts, including AudraRox, a rock band made up mostly of (very hip) parents; the Hover Brothers, who combine comedy and magic; and GrooveHoops, whose groove is hula hoops. They will take part in an outdoor festival that is in the annual Summer on the Hudson @ Riverside Park series. From 2 to 4 p.m., Pier 1, at 70th Street, Riverside Park South, Manhattan, nyc.gov/parks or 311. Free.</p>
        <p>'THE MILK DRAGON' (Tomorrow and Sunday) Who says children are too young for works with political import? This production inaugurates the 10th season of New Plays for Young Audiences, a series of staged readings sponsored by the Program in Educational Theater at the Steinhardt School of Culture, Education and Human Development at New York University. Written by Suzan Zeder, the show, billed as a ''political fantasy,'' follows two young people, Zack and Abra, as they encounter a forest where everything considered too dangerous or complicated has been banned. Tomorrow at 3 and 7:30 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., the Provincetown Playhouse, 133 Macdougal Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 998-5867; $5; free for high school students and children.</p>
        <p>'MODERN ARTWORKS' (Today and tomorrow) It isn't often that artists under 20 get to show in a gallery and sell their work. But each year the CUE Art Foundation sponsors the Modern ArtWorks program, which takes middle and high school students to view exhibitions at CUE, discuss the art and create projects of their own. This exhibition showcases the fruits of their labor, which are on sale for $50 each; proceeds will be split between the student and his or her school. Expect to see jazz-theme paintings, abstract art, photo collage, mixed media and more. From 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. at CUE, 511 West 25th Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-3583, cueartfoundation.org; free.</p>
        <p>'THE MUSIC IN ME' (Tomorrow) All children seem to have music in them, but not all have the means to express it. That's where Midori &amp; Friends, an organization founded by the violinist Midori, comes in. It has been offering free music-education programs in city schools for 15 years, and on Sunday the students, from elementary to high school age, will present their second annual Children's Music Festival. The storyteller David Gonzalez will be host, and world music artists like Arturo O'Farrill will perform. At 3 p.m., TriBeCa Performing Arts Center, Borough of Manhattan Community College, 199 Chambers Street, (212) 767-1300, midoriandfriends.org; free.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK FAMILY ARTS FESTIVAL (Tomorrow and Sunday) Unity in diversity is certainly possible, and it is being celebrated at this monthlong event, which focuses on the multicultural arts of the city. Tomorrow from noon to 7 p.m., the festival's ''South African Cultural Village'' will offer classes in Zulu dance, as well as craft workshops, song and drumming. On Sunday at 2 p.m., ''Salute to the Family'' includes music and dance and a tribute to social service organizations. At the Riverside Theater, Riverside Avenue at 122nd Street, Morningside Heights. Free, but reservations requested: (212) 870-6784.</p>
        <p>'PINKALICIOUS' (Tomorrow) Sometimes being in the pink can be too much of a good thing, as the pink-obsessed title character finds out in this new musical from Vital Children's Theater, which Elizabeth and Victoria Kann adapted from their children's book. (Extended through June 30.) At noon, SoHo Playhouse, 15 Van Dam Street, near Varick Street, South Village, (212) 691-1555, sohoplayhouse.com; $25 (reservations advised).</p>
        <p>SPRING CELEBRATION: A FAMILY CONCERT (Tomorrow) What better way to herald spring, a season of growth, than with the combined voices of 250 singers ages 8 to 18? That group is the Young People's Chorus of New York City, resident choir of the 92nd Street Y, which will perform a wide-ranging program, from Bach and Mussorgsky to a West African folk song and ''Sit Down, You're Rocking the Boat,'' from ''Guy and Dolls.'' At 8 p.m., the Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5500; $60, $25 and $10; $65 and $25 seats are only $10 for students and 65+.</p>
        <p>DAVID WEINSTONE AND THE MUSIC FOR AARDVARKS BAND (Tomorrow) Music for aardvarks is also music for children, as Mr. Weinstone, a former punk rocker, will demonstrate. His group specializes in tunes for urban kids, as evidenced in its new album, ''Taxi.'' At 11 a.m. (doors open at 10), the Concert Hall, New York Society for Ethical Culture, 2 West 64th Street, Manhattan, (212) 277-7179 or (212) 307-7171, theconcerthall.org; $20.</p>
        <p>LAUREL GRAEBER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
