<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Something's Up, And It's Not The Surf</title>
    <meta content="08john" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/arts/television/08john.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852894"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Surfing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Surfing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surfing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Home Box Office</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905EFDE1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1175" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Something's Up, And It's Not The Surf</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Something’s Up, and It’s Not the Surf</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>None of the music in David Milch's new surfing series on HBO is by the Beach Boys. The surfing scenes are few and fleeting.</p>
        <p>Instead seedy characters spit out a lot of obscenities, and some use oddly mannered speech, giving ''John From Cincinnati'' a flavor of ''Deadwood,'' only in a contemporary beach setting -- ''Driftwood.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>HBO offers a peculiar series on surfing as unearthly pleasure and life-sapping addiction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>None of the music in David Milch's new surfing series on HBO is by the Beach Boys. The surfing scenes are few and fleeting.</p>
        <p>Instead seedy characters spit out a lot of obscenities, and some use oddly mannered speech, giving ''John From Cincinnati'' a flavor of ''Deadwood,'' only in a contemporary beach setting -- ''Driftwood.''</p>
        <p>And then there are those magical happenings in the style of Gabriel García Márquez.</p>
        <p>''John From Cincinnati,'' in other words, has many barriers to success, and the premiere episode is almost willfully strange and unlikable. But that doesn't mean that the series is bad, just peculiar, a solemn mythologization -- and mystification -- of surfing as unearthly pleasure and life-sapping addiction.</p>
        <p>Mr. Milch, who wrote for ''Hill Street Blues'' and helped create ''NYPD Blue'' before coming up with ''Deadwood,'' is back to the present. But this one is loaded with foreboding about the future. Or, as the title character repeats from time to time, ''The end is near.''</p>
        <p>John (Austin Nichols), who is not really from Cincinnati, at least not the one on this planet, wanders into a rundown surfing community in Imperial Beach, south of downtown San Diego, and into the lives of the Yosts, three generations of surfers who are a sun-bleached dynasty with a Kennedyesque curse.</p>
        <p>The stranger is amiable but slow, a cross between Chauncey Gardiner from ''Being There'' and Starman, and wherever he wanders, the paranormal follows. A grown man levitates, a dead bird returns to life.</p>
        <p>And, lest anyone miss John's otherworldliness, his surname is Monad, a word that philosophers associate with the obscure metaphysics of Leibniz, the 17th-century thinker. (Lest anyone missed the HBO bio, Mr. Milch taught literature at Yale.)</p>
        <p>Baseball inspires some writers to absurd heights of pretension and religious metaphor. Surfing, distilled into an epic battle between man and water, is even more susceptible to overreaching. And intimations of spirituality are particularly dangerous on television, where the invocation of a higher power embarrasses more than it inspires (''Ghost Whisperer'').</p>
        <p>Even on more rarefied networks, it rarely works: the battle between good and evil that veined ''Carnivàle'' sent that HBO drama straight to ratings purgatory. ''Angels in America,'' which was directed for HBO by Mike Nichols, was steadier on terra firma than with the seraphim.</p>
        <p>Mr. Milch's new show is not likely to fulfill the nation's yearning to fill the void left by ''The Sopranos,'' or, for that matter, ''Deadwood.'' It's more like ''Big Love'' or ''Carnivàle,'' smart, ambitious series that move unusual characters around an unfamiliar setting imaginatively and even with grace, but that never quite quit the surly bonds of serial drama.</p>
        <p>Mr. Milch has created engaging secondary characters who have some of the whimsical appeal of the hangers-on in ''Deadwood,'' and the family's muted melodrama is intriguing. The rare glimpses of surfing are thrilling, but the magical realism is not. It's affected, not affecting. Most of all, the story lacks a compelling antihero, like Al Swearengen on ''Deadwood'' or Tony Soprano, to center the drama and bring it to life.</p>
        <p>The surfing world may not be the most obvious milieu for eschatological musings, but Mr. Milch, who created the series with Kem Nunn, an author of novels known as ''surf noir,'' exalts the sport by placing it in a ramshackle community on the Mexican border, filled with misfits and signs of decay. In the gray predawn light, surfers talk in an empty parking lot while a few yards away, a line of Mexican illegal immigrants noiselessly sneaks across the border, like deer crossing a dewy lawn in suburban Connecticut.</p>
        <p>Mitch Yost (Bruce Greenwood) is Imperial Beach's faded local hero, a former surfing legend who was knocked off his throne by a knee injury but retains a regal hauteur. He does a lot of yoga in his hideaway but doesn't seem particularly serene: most of the time, he is a brooding, prickly defender of the purity of the sport, forever at war with the jackals who promoted, popularized, and in Mitch's mind, desecrated it.</p>
        <p>Mitch is on bad terms with his son, Butchie (Brian Van Holt), who in his day revolutionized surfing and helped make it commercial, and is now a doper squatting in a nearby abandoned motel. Mitch blames his son's addiction on the influence of a slimy surfing promoter, Linc (Luke Perry), who built his career milking Butchie's ''bad boy'' image.</p>
        <p>Butchie's 13-year-old son, Shaun, is a surfing prodigy, an innocent who has a teenager's yearning to be sponsored and win competitions, but retains a purist's love of surfing. (He is played by a real-life wundersurfer, Greyson Fletcher). Because Butchie is such a basket case, Shaun is being raised by Mitch and his wife, Cissy (Rebecca De Mornay).</p>
        <p>The Yosts are surrounded by a troupe of acolytes who revere and protect them, despite their sour moods and earthly failings, providing semi-comic relief, like the gravediggers in ''Hamlet.'' They include Bill (Ed O'Neill), a retired police detective, and Meyer Dickstein (Willie Garson, of ''Sex and the City''), who handles the family's legal affairs and belongs to the Association of Surfing Attorneys.</p>
        <p>Dayton Callie, who played Charlie Utter in ''Deadwood,'' here plays a similar role as a sentimental drug dealer who beats up deadbeat clients but alone in his car listens to Sarah Brightman singing ''Time to Say Goodbye.''</p>
        <p>John is not the only newcomer: Barry Cunningham (Matt Winston), who left Imperial Beach years ago, nursing a grievance against the Yosts, returns as the new owner of the local motel, psychosis in tow.</p>
        <p>The casting of the leads is a problem. John is essentially a cipher, so he serves more as a McGuffin than as a leading man. Ms. De Mornay is disappointing as well -- she looks great, which is nice, but that doesn't fill out her character's persona. Cissy is alternately bewildered and belligerent, but Ms. De Mornay doesn't convey why. The furtive and feral Mr. Perry is not very persuasive as a devious merchandizing mastermind -- he's more the henchman type.</p>
        <p>Only Shaun, who rarely speaks, has real charisma.</p>
        <p>''John From Cincinnati'' brings magical realism to surfing, but this surfing series is not nearly as magical as Mr. Milch's more realistic works.</p>
        <p>John From Cincinnati  HBO, Sunday night at 10, Eastern and Pacific times; 9, Central time.</p>
        <p>Directed by Mark Tinker (first episode); written and created by David Milch and Kem Nunn; Mr. Milch, Gregg Fienberg, Zvi Howard Rosenman and Mr. Tinker, executive producers; Mr. Nunn, Peter Spears and Scott Stephens, co-executive producers; Herbie and Dibi Fletcher and Bill Clark, consulting producers; Ted Mann, producer; Regina Corrado, story editor; Nichole Beattie, Steve Hark and Alix Lambert, staff writers; Junie Lowry Johnson and Libby Goldstein, casting directors. Produced by HBO Entertainment in association with David Milch's Red Board Productions.</p>
        <p>WITH: Rebecca De Mornay (Cissy Yost), Garret Dillahunt (Dr. Smith), Greyson Fletcher (Shaun Yost), Willie Garson (Meyer Dickstein), Bruce Greenwood (Mitch Yost), Luis Guzmán (Ramon), Keala Kennelly (Kai), Austin Nichols (John), Ed O'Neill (Bill), Luke Perry (Linc), Brian Van Holt (Butchie Yost), Matt Winston (Barry Cunningham).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
