<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shakespeare, Naturally</title>
    <meta content="08shak" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070609T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852895"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04EFDE1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1788" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shakespeare, Naturally</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SISARIO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALL the world's a stage, sure, but what might Shakespeare have made of the dramatic possibilities of a Lower East Side parking lot, with cars backing out right into the Capulets' masked ball? Or ''Love's Labour's Lost'' on a stroll through Central Park, as helmeted bicyclists whiz by?</p>
        <p>The outdoor summer theater season had its unofficial opening on Wednesday, when Shakespeare in the Park began previews of ''Romeo and Juliet'' at the open-air Delacorte Theater in Central Park. And for legions of New Yorkers, from theater lovers to park lovers to those who simply love anything free, no warm-weather ritual is more pleasant -- or an easier sell -- than an evening of blank verse in the Delacorte.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALL the world's a stage, sure, but what might Shakespeare have made of the dramatic possibilities of a Lower East Side parking lot, with cars backing out right into the Capulets' masked ball? Or ''Love's Labour's Lost'' on a stroll through Central Park, as helmeted bicyclists whiz by?</p>
        <p>The outdoor summer theater season had its unofficial opening on Wednesday, when Shakespeare in the Park began previews of ''Romeo and Juliet'' at the open-air Delacorte Theater in Central Park. And for legions of New Yorkers, from theater lovers to park lovers to those who simply love anything free, no warm-weather ritual is more pleasant -- or an easier sell -- than an evening of blank verse in the Delacorte.</p>
        <p>But for most others performing Shakespeare, particularly those shoestring companies where the person taking your ticket might very well turn up onstage in Act II, it takes some ingenuity to stand out and attract an audience. As a result this Shakespeare season, like every one, is a feast of strange and novel -- not to say gimmicky -- productions in unusual spaces from city parks to the tiny back rooms of bookstores.</p>
        <p>This summer there's a ''Macbeth'' without words in what is only half-jokingly called the Pretentious Festival, and a one-man ''King Lear'' at the Lincoln Center Festival whose words are all in Chinese. There's a ''Romeo and Juliet'' whose romance is interrupted by 20 minutes of a vaudevillian road show and lots of alfresco ''Romeo and Juliets'' and ''Julius Caesars'' that might very well be interrupted by stray volleyballs or honking traffic.</p>
        <p>For Jeff Lewonczyk, co-artistic director of the Brick Theater in Brooklyn, whose Pretentious Festival this month leans to the arch and self-referential (sample title: ''Every Play Ever Written: A Distillation of the Essence of Theater''), there was at least one playwright he wanted to avoid.</p>
        <p>''I'm sick to death of Shakespeare,'' Mr. Lewonczyk said in an interview on Wednesday. ''I'm sick of seeing other productions, and I'm sick of having him held up as the sole bar for quality.'' (He had also been deterred by taking on ''The Tempest'' at a premature age, he added.)</p>
        <p>But all it took was seeing a good ''Comedy of Errors'' for Shakespeare to infiltrate his creative thoughts, and soon Mr. Lewonczyk was directing a mute Macbeth and programming two other adaptations for his festival: ''Ian W. Hill's 'Hamlet' '' and ''Q1: The Bad Hamlet,'' based on the error-ridden first quarto of the play, reviled by most scholars.</p>
        <p>More than any other works in the theatrical canon, directors and actors say, Shakespeare's plays lend themselves to ambitious and unconventional interpretation, in part because they are so well known -- and so well written -- that they can survive any manner of tinkering.</p>
        <p>''You're very protected by Shakespeare in a lot of ways,'' said Bartlett Sher, whose ''Cymbeline'' with Theater for a New Audience had its premiere at the Royal Shakespeare Company in Stratford in 2001. It featured a duel between a samurai and a bullwhip-wielding cowboy. ''The writing is so strong, and the plays already have a quality to them which allows for the ability to pop them open.''</p>
        <p>And the ways to pop them open are infinite, whether they be Michael Greif's decision to make a huge pool of water spanned by a bridge the centerpiece of the stage at Shakespeare in the Park's ''Romeo and Juliet'' or the New York Classical Theater's elimination of the stage itself with a modern-dress version of ''Love's Labour's Lost'' that wanders around a pond in the northwest corner of Central Park.</p>
        <p>Though audiences might not need special enticement, the Delacorte usually features a clutch of Hollywood stars renewing their bonds to the theater (or at least making a public gesture of doing so). This year is a little short on big names; Lauren Ambrose from ''Six Feet Under'' is Juliet, and Camryn Manheim of ''The Practice'' is the Nurse. But as if to compensate, the Public is presenting two Shakespeares instead of the usual one, with ''A Midsummer Night's Dream'' directed by Daniel Sullivan beginning performances in August.</p>
        <p>New York Classical Theater has done its open-environment productions in the park for eight years, and for ''Love's Labour's Lost'' -- an atypical comedy-romance that ends with the women turning down their suitors' marriage proposals -- the company leads the audience through eight spots on the grass. When it's time to move to the next ''stage,'' the actors point the way, ad-libbing a few lines in character. At the opening performance last week Armado, the Spanish buffoon, told the audience at the end of Act I: ''I need to be alone to write my sonnet. You go that way.''</p>
        <p>The audience also winds its way through the theatrical environment in Ellen Stewart's ''dance-opera'' adaptation of ''Romeo and Juliet'' at La MaMa E.T.C. in the East Village. Instead of the greenery of the park, though, you get a sometimes confusing tour through the lower-level rooms and back stairway of the theater.</p>
        <p>Ms. Stewart's many changes to the play can test the patience of a Stratford purist. Among several added characters are Peter, an attendant to Juliet who introduces himself in conspicuously non-Shakespearean lyrics: ''My name is Peter/What could be sweeter/Than my lady Nurse/To fall in love with me.'' La MaMa's rendition has no balcony scene, though it does have an interlude with, among other entertainments, a dancing Gypsy and a man in a gorilla suit riding a tiny bicycle.</p>
        <p>But in the end it's still ''Romeo and Juliet.''</p>
        <p>Some of the most extreme interpretations are mounted with the smallest budgets, as the prohibitive costs of a full production force impecunious companies to get creative.</p>
        <p>''Shakespeare is expensive,'' said Jack O'Brien, who directed a combination of both parts of ''Henry IV'' at the Delacorte four summers ago. ''These plays were written for large companies, and you can't get away from the fact that you need resources. That does explain why people are always looking for expedient -- not to say cheap -- ways to do it.''</p>
        <p>A favorite in recent years has been Dov Weinstein's Tiny Ninja versions of the tragedies, which he has staged at the New York International Fringe Festival and Performance Space 122. Mr. Weinstein voices all the lines and, wearing black gloves, manipulates a cast of one-inch plastic ninja figurines purchased from vending machines. ''I started collecting them and realized that no one was doing classical theater with them,'' Mr. Weinstein said. ''So I decided to fill that gap.''</p>
        <p>(This summer he is taking his Tiny Ninja Theater to Washington, performing ''Macbeth'' and ''Romeo and Juliet'' at the Kennedy Center, but does not have any New York shows planned.)</p>
        <p>Hamilton Clancy's Shakespeare in the Park(ing) Lot has been running for 14 summers now in the municipal parking lot at Ludlow and Broome Streets on the Lower East Side, performing in whatever spaces are available on a given night.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes cars pull out during the performance,'' Mr. Clancy said. ''Everyone stops, moves their chairs, lets the car out, and the play will continue. It's really a sight to behold. Once people are in the context of the parking lot, they're very accepting of it.''</p>
        <p>Though the lot at Ludlow and Broome can seem an enormous distance from the Delacorte uptown, the two series are linked, by geography and perhaps by theirmissions. The first site for Joseph Papp's Shakespeare in the Park series was just blocks away in the East River Park, a narrow strip on the Lower East Side in the shadow of the Williamsburg Bridge. Papp's goal to bring free classical theater to all New Yorkers, Mr. Sher said, also set off a creative revolution by eliminating financial barriers to audiences altogether.</p>
        <p>''The really daring thing for that era was that it didn't cost any money,'' Mr. Sher said. ''That created a freedom and a context in which artists could explore and experiment, and the audiences would come in without that transaction of money going on between them.''</p>
        <p>And gimmicks, as clever and as effective a lure as they may be, have a way of vanishing once Shakespeare's language begins to cast its spell, over the actors as well as the audience.</p>
        <p>''That magic belongs to the actor,'' said Mr. O'Brien. ''You can put him in a kilt. And if he does it well you can take credit for the kilt. But Shakespeare gets the applause.''</p>
        <p>The Park's the Thing  A selection of summer Shakespeare presentations in New York. Schedule and ticket information is available from the companies.</p>
        <p>SHAKESPEARE IN THE PARK -- ''Romeo and Juliet,'' in previews; opens June 24, closes July 8. ''A Midsummer Night's Dream,'' Aug. 6-Sept. 9. Delacorte Theater, Central Park, (212) 539-8750, publictheater.org. Free; tickets required.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK CLASSICAL THEATER -- ''Love's Labour's Lost'' in Central Park, through June 24. Enter at Central Park West and 103rd Street, (212) 252-4531, newyorkclassical.org. Free.</p>
        <p>LA MAMA -- An adaptation of ''Romeo and Juliet'' by Ellen Stewart, through June 17. 66 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710, lamama.org.</p>
        <p>ARE THE FISH HAPPY? THEATER -- ''Three Kings and Their Dead,'' based on characters in ''Hamlet,'' ''Macbeth'' and ''Richard III,'' through June 16, Arthur Seelen Theater inside the Drama Book Shop, 250 West 40th Street, Manhattan, (212) 944-0595, arethefishhappy.blogspot.com.</p>
        <p>INWOOD SHAKESPEARE FESTIVAL -- ''Julius Caesar,'' through June 23. Inwood Hill Park, 218th Street and Indian Road, (917) 918-0394, moosehallisf.org. Free.</p>
        <p>PRETENTIOUS FESTIVAL -- ''Macbeth Without Words,'' ''Ian W. Hill's 'Hamlet,' '' ''Q1: The Bad Hamlet,'' Tuesday-July 1. Brick Theater, 575 Metropolitan Avenue, between Union Avenue and Lorimer Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 907-6189, bricktheater.com.</p>
        <p>HIPGNOSIS THEATER COMPANY -- ''The Taming of the Shrew,'' Thursday-July 1, Clemente Soto Velez Cultural Center, 107 Suffolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 868-4444, hipgnosistheatre.org.</p>
        <p>BOOMERANG THEATER COMPANY -- ''All's Well That Ends Well'' in Central Park, June 23-July 22. Enter at Central Park West and 69th Street, (212) 501-4069, boomerangtheatre.org. Free.</p>
        <p>THEATER OF THE EXPENDABLE -- ''Dick 2 (a k a Richard II),'' June 21-July 8. Joria Productions, 260 West 36th Street, Manhattan, (212) 352-3101, theatreoftheexpendable.org.</p>
        <p>LINCOLN CENTER FESTIVAL -- An adaptation of ''King Lear'' by Wu Hsing-Kuo, July 12. Performed in Chinese with English supertitles. Rose Theater, Broadway at 60th Street, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org.</p>
        <p>SHAKESPEARE IN THE PARK(ING) LOT -- ''Romeo and Juliet,'' July 12-28. ''Much Ado About Nothing,'' Aug. 2-18. Municipal Parking Lot at Ludlow and Broome Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 877-0099, drillingcompany.org. Free.</p>
        <p>CLASSICAL THEATER OF HARLEM -- ''Romeo and Juliet'' in city parks. July 27-28: Von King Park, Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn; Aug. 3-4, Marcus Garvey Park, Harlem; Aug. 9-10, Tompkins Square Park, East Village. Presented with the City Parks Foundation. (212) 564-9983, classicaltheatreofharlem.org or cityparksfoundation.org. Free.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 9, 2007, Saturday  An article in Weekend yesterday about Shakespeare plays being performed outdoors in New York this summer misidentified the site and misstated the date of the ''Henry IV'' directed four years ago by Jack O'Brien, who commented on theater companies' different approaches. It was the Vivian Beaumont Theater at Lincoln Center in November 2003, not the Delacorte Theater in Central Park four summers ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 9, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article in Weekend yesterday about Shakespeare plays being performed outdoors in New York this summer misidentified the site and misstated the date of the ''Henry IV'' directed four years ago by Jack O'Brien, who commented on theater companies' different approaches. It was the Vivian Beaumont Theater at Lincoln Center in November 2003, not the Delacorte Theater in Central Park four summers ago.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
