<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inside Art</title>
    <meta content="08voge" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/arts/design/08voge.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852871"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Inside Art"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Venice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Venice (Italy)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Pinault, Francois</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E4DE1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1041" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inside Art</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Venetian Customs House for Contemporary Art</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
      <dateline>Venice, June 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Venetian Customs House For Contemporary Art</p>
        <p>François Pinault, the luxury-goods magnate and art collector who owns Christie's, arrived here this week not simply to peruse the hundreds of art installations that make up this year's Venice Biennale, but also for the formal signing of an agreement on Friday between the City of Venice and his Palazzo Grassi to create a contemporary-art center in an unused customs house called Punta della Dogana, at the entrance to the Grand Canal.</p>
        <p>The agreement is for 30 years, during which Mr. Pinault is to make 141 works he has accumulated the basis of the new museum's permanent collection.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Venice’s newest museum will contain works owned by Francois Pinault, the luxury-goods magnate and art collector who owns Christie’s.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Venetian Customs House For Contemporary Art</p>
        <p>François Pinault, the luxury-goods magnate and art collector who owns Christie's, arrived here this week not simply to peruse the hundreds of art installations that make up this year's Venice Biennale, but also for the formal signing of an agreement on Friday between the City of Venice and his Palazzo Grassi to create a contemporary-art center in an unused customs house called Punta della Dogana, at the entrance to the Grand Canal.</p>
        <p>The agreement is for 30 years, during which Mr. Pinault is to make 141 works he has accumulated the basis of the new museum's permanent collection.</p>
        <p>Two years ago Mr. Pinault bought the 18th-century Palazzo Grassi as a space to present exhibitions of his contemporary-art collection as well as of shows devoted to more historical art.</p>
        <p>The Japanese architect Tadao Ando, who renovated the Palazzo Grassi, is expected to begin work on the 17th-century Dogana building this fall. The project, expected to cost $26 million, is scheduled to be completed and open in time for the 2009 Biennale.</p>
        <p>Now as many as 3,000 visitors a day flock to the Palazzo Grassi to see Mr. Pinault's collection. A new exhibition, ''Sequence 1,'' on view through Nov. 11, shows a different side of his holdings from past exhibitions.</p>
        <p>''This show was made with the Biennale in mind,'' said Alison M. Gingeras, the curator of ''Sequence 1.'' ''We have focused on 16 artists in depth.''</p>
        <p>Some works were commissioned. Franz West and Rudolf Stingel, for example, collaborated on a pavilionlike structure whose roof serves as a support for a large sculpture by Mr. West and whose interior houses a silver-paneled room and a chandelier by Mr. Stingel.</p>
        <p>The exhibition also includes works by several emerging painters, including the Milan-based Roberto Cuoghi and the New York artist Kristin Baker. ''We wanted to show some younger artists that Mr. Pinault has been collecting,'' Ms. Gingeras said.</p>
        <p>Keith Haring Mural</p>
        <p>In a warehouse in Newark the other morning, a conservator and two Chelsea dealers were taking turns on a ladder, inspecting what from the ground looked like a decaying old wall.</p>
        <p>''It's in miraculously good shape,'' Alan Farancz, the conservator, said. ''There were a few hairline cracks, but they were there to begin with.''</p>
        <p>They were scrutinizing a 40,000-pound mural created in 1987 by the Pop artist Keith Haring for the Boys' Club of New York at 135 Pitt Street on the Lower East Side. When Common Ground, a nonprofit community and housing organization, bought the building from New York City and was planning to demolish it to build low-cost housing on the site, it knew the mural was there but didn't know what to do about it.</p>
        <p>''We were told it was probably impossible to remove the mural because it was on a load-bearing wall,'' said Dave Walsh, Common Ground's director of housing development. The project manager explained the situation to his friends Alberto Magnan and Dara Metz , the husband-and-wife art dealers who own the Magnan Projects gallery in Chelsea.</p>
        <p>''It was close to being destroyed, and Common Ground was trying to save it,'' Mr. Magnan said. He and Ms. Metz volunteered to pay for a five-member crew to remove the wall before demolition, at a cost of more than $250,000, in exchange for the right to sell it.</p>
        <p>The mural could not be removed from the wall because the plaster was too thin, making the job complex and risky. ''I had to think of it like a piece of a jigsaw puzzle,'' said Pat Tarrant, a Manhattan structural engineer and master rigger who worked on the project.</p>
        <p>He first encased the front and back of the wall bearing the Haring mural with steel to protect it from collapse or other damage, and then demolished the building, leaving the decorated wall to be lifted off the site.</p>
        <p>The dealers transported it to New Jersey on a flatbed truck. It is now lying flat in a Newark warehouse so that Mr. Farancz can make sure that it is structurally sound before standing it up. ''It didn't get damaged, which is totally incredible,'' Ms. Metz said.</p>
        <p>Haring, who died in 1990 at 31, had volunteered to make the mural for the club. He decorated it with images of children involved in activities like boxing, painting, swimming and reading. ''The mural was filmed in a 'Sesame Street' episode,'' Ms. Metz said.</p>
        <p>When it is pronounced sound enough to be placed upright for viewing, the dealers hope to sell it to a museum or school. ''The Boys' Club closed in 2003, and the mural hasn't been seen since,'' Mr. Magnan said.</p>
        <p>As for determining a price, he said: ''It's hard to know. Nothing like this has been on the market before.''</p>
        <p>Experts have suggested that it could be worth $4 million to $6 million.</p>
        <p>Rembrandt at the Met</p>
        <p>Instead of celebrating the 400th anniversary of Rembrandt's birth last year, as most museums did, the Metropolitan Museum of Art is paying homage to that old master and other Dutch painters beginning this fall. For the first time, all of its 228 Dutch paintings will be on view, from Sept. 18 to Jan. 6. Usually about 100 of its Dutch paintings are hanging at one time.</p>
        <p>The show, ''The Age of Rembrandt: Dutch Paintings in the Metropolitan Museum of Art,'' has been only part of a four-year project for Walter Liedtke, a curator of European paintings. He has also been working on the first comprehensive two-volume catalog of Dutch paintings from the museum's collection.</p>
        <p>''I think of it as an installation that goes with a catalog,'' Mr. Liedtke said. ''We thought about doing this last year, but a record number of our Rembrandts were on loan to places like Amsterdam, Berlin and St. Petersburg.''</p>
        <p>The show, which will occupy 12 galleries, will feature all of the Met's 20 Rembrandts, including famous works like ''Aristotle With a Bust of Homer'' and his 1660 self-portrait. It will also include the museum's 11 paintings by Frans Hals and 5 of the 35 known paintings by Vermeer.</p>
        <p>Rather than being displayed chronologically, the works will be shown in order of acquisition, beginning with the founding purchase of 1871.</p>
        <p>Inside Art</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
