<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Teams Zero In on Pitchers In the First Round of the Draft</title>
    <meta content="08draft" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852992"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E1DA1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="590" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Teams Zero In on Pitchers In the First Round of the Draft</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It helped to be a left-handed pitcher yesterday during the first round of Major League Baseball's first-year player draft, or a pitcher of any kind.</p>
        <p>Left-handed pitchers are among baseball's most valued talents, and 7 of the 30 players chosen in the first round were left-handed pitchers, including David Price of Vanderbilt, taken No. 1 over all by Tampa Bay. Including right-handers, 17 of the 30 players selected in the first round were pitchers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It helped to be a left-handed pitcher yesterday during the first round of Major League Baseball's first-year player draft, or a pitcher of any kind.</p>
        <p>Left-handed pitchers are among baseball's most valued talents, and 7 of the 30 players chosen in the first round were left-handed pitchers, including David Price of Vanderbilt, taken No. 1 over all by Tampa Bay. Including right-handers, 17 of the 30 players selected in the first round were pitchers.</p>
        <p>Nor did it hurt to be affiliated with Scott Boras, the power agent who advises many star players and is known for eliciting top wages and bonuses for them. Five players in the first round were associated with Boras, including shortstop Michael Moustakas, a high school shortstop from California chosen by Kansas City as the second pick over all.</p>
        <p>The draft was held at Disney's Wide World of Sports in Lake Buena Vista, Fla. The first round was shown live on national television by ESPN2, the first time baseball's draft has been televised. Professional football, basketball and hockey have televised their drafts for many years.</p>
        <p>Despite speculation that an association with Boras would keep teams away from some top players, only one appeared to be drafted much lower than he was ranked. That was the right-handed pitcher Rick Porcello of Seton Hall Prep in New Jersey. He was not chosen until the 27th selection, by the Detroit Tigers.</p>
        <p>The Yankees, picking 30th and last in the first round, chose the Boras client Andrew Brackman, a right-handed pitcher. The Mets did not have a pick in the first round. Under a new rule, all teams must sign their draftees by Aug. 15 or they go back into the draft next year.</p>
        <p>The other Boras clients in the first round were Matthew Wieters, a catcher from Georgia Tech, picked fifth by Baltimore; and Matt LaPorta, a first baseman selected seventh by Milwaukee.</p>
        <p>Moustakas's teammate at Chatsworth, third baseman Matthew Dominguez, was also chosen in the first round, by Florida, which had the 12th pick.</p>
        <p>Price, according to a scouting report on the Web site mlb.com, has a fastball that reaches 95 miles an hour to go with a good slider and a change of pace that is above average. He is a 6-foot-6, 215-pound college junior who will turn 22 on Aug. 26.</p>
        <p>The Devil Rays, in their second season under new ownership, have several talented young position players but are in great need of starting pitching. The draft was held about 90 miles from their home stadium, Tropicana Field in St. Petersburg, and on the same property where they recently played a three-game home series against Texas.</p>
        <p>Many Devil Rays fans attended the draft, which was open to the public for the first time.</p>
        <p>Price is the second left-handed pitcher to be chosen out of college as the first overall choice. The first was Floyd Bannister, selected in 1976 from Arizona Sate by Houston. The left-hander Brien Taylor was selected at No. 1 out of high school by the Yankees in 1991.</p>
        <p>The first round included 17 high school players and 13 college players. The only player from outside the United States drafted in the opening round was Phillipe Aumont, a 6-7 right-handed pitcher chosen by Seattle with the 11th pick. He is from École du Versant in Gatineau, Quebec. Players from outside the United States, its territories and Canada are not subject to the draft.</p>
        <p>The San Francisco Giants were the only team with three first-round picks. They took three high school players.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
