<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Savannah, a City Close to Its Ghosts</title>
    <meta content="08kids" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/travel/escapes/08kids.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852875"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEEKEND WITH THE KIDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Savannah (Ga)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Georgia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dixon, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia/Savannah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Savannah (Ga)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E3DE1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1127" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Savannah, a City Close to Its Ghosts</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Savannah, a City Close to Its Ghosts</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS DIXON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dixon, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Weekend With the Kids column on visit to Savannah, Ga; photos; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN it comes to finding child-friendly haunts in the South, Savannah might not be the first city that comes to mind. After all, endless tours of historic mansions and myriad distinctive, though largely grown-up, galleries and stores would be enough to bore any energetic youngster. But it turns out that this vibrant 18th-century port city -- and nearby Tybee Island, with its lovely, expansive beach -- can be equal fun for young and old.</p>
        <p>Old Downtown</p>
        <p>Savannah's layout -- an inviting grid of wide streets interspersed with 24 public squares filled with oaks and statues -- makes the city a wonderful place to get around by bicycle. You can rent a bike ($20 a day) with a child's seat ($10 extra a day) or a two-child trailer ($20 extra a day) at Bicycle Link (408 Martin Luther King Jr. Boulevard, 912-233-9401; www.bicyclelinksav.com).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This vibrant 18th-century port city, where ghost tours are a mainstay, can be equal fun for young and old.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN it comes to finding child-friendly haunts in the South, Savannah might not be the first city that comes to mind. After all, endless tours of historic mansions and myriad distinctive, though largely grown-up, galleries and stores would be enough to bore any energetic youngster. But it turns out that this vibrant 18th-century port city -- and nearby Tybee Island, with its lovely, expansive beach -- can be equal fun for young and old.</p>
        <p>Old Downtown</p>
        <p>Savannah's layout -- an inviting grid of wide streets interspersed with 24 public squares filled with oaks and statues -- makes the city a wonderful place to get around by bicycle. You can rent a bike ($20 a day) with a child's seat ($10 extra a day) or a two-child trailer ($20 extra a day) at Bicycle Link (408 Martin Luther King Jr. Boulevard, 912-233-9401; www.bicyclelinksav.com).</p>
        <p>The newest downtown attraction is the 64,000-square-foot Jepson Center for the Arts (207 West York Street, 912-790-8800; www.telfair.org/buildings/jepson.asp; $10, $4 for ages 5 to 12, under 5 free), which has scores of workshops for all ages. Inside the center, the ArtZeum is a two-level space for children with a walk-through glass house and audio-visual displays. A low-tech area includes a huge doodling wall and architectural building blocks for the youngest visitors. At the Roundhouse Railroad Museum (601 West Harris Street, 912-651-6823; www.chsgeorgia.org; $4.25, $3.75 for students, under 6 free), there are passenger cars and old locomotives and a fascinating display of steam-powered and belt-driven milling machinery.</p>
        <p>Forsyth Park, at Bull and Gaston Streets, is Savannah's most sublime in-town escape. The 30 acres shaded by oaks- and magnolias hold a huge 19th-century fountain of trumpeting mermen and spouting swans, two well-equipped playgrounds -- one for little kids and one for older children -- and vast lawns.</p>
        <p>The River Street pedestrian district, with a constant stream of water taxis, riverboats, container ships and entertaining shops and restaurants, should be on any itinerary. Don't-miss shops include Village Craftsmen (223 West River Street, 912-236-7280; www.thevillagecraftsmen.com) and Gallery 209 (209 East River Street, 912-236-4583; www.gallery209.com). More than 50 vendors fill the new River Street Market Place nearby (www.riverstreetmarketplace.com), where you can find puzzle boxes from Costa Rica and carved elephants from Kenya.</p>
        <p>Tours</p>
        <p>Ghost tours are a Savannah mainstay. Shannon Scott says he has documented hundreds of Savannians' personal encounters with local ghosts and voodoo. He and Chris Soucy operate Sixth Sense Tours (888-374-4678, www.savannahghosttour.com; 7 and 9:30 p.m.; $18, $10 for ages 10 to 15, $5 under 10). Their shorter more family-friendly walk is America's Most Haunted City the Tour ($12., $8 for ages 8 to 11, $5 under 8). This 75-to-90-minute tour includes the 1797 Hampton-Lillibridge House, which was moved to its current location by Jim Williams, the protagonist of ''Midnight in the Garden of Good and Evil.'' He believed that one of the house's ghosts was an 18th-century resident of Savannah, Rene Asche Rondolier, who was said to have been lynched after being accused of murdering two girls at what is now Colonial Park Cemetery.</p>
        <p>Old Savannah Tours (912-234-8128, www.oldsavannahtours.com) offers a 90-minute Ghostly Nights tour starting at 7 p.m. ($20, $10 under age ages 6 to 11, under 6 free) aboard an open-air trolley. The company also has daytime trolley tours through town ($23, $10 for ages 5 to 12, under 5 free). You're given a map and can climb on or off throughout the historic district.</p>
        <p>The Juliette Gordon Low Center (10 East Oglethorpe Avenue, 912-233-4501; www.girlscouts.org/birthplace; $8, $7 for students, under 5 free) is a spectacular 1821 house that is the birthplace of the founder of the Girl Scouts of the USA. It has architectural fascination for adults and guides who excel at holding the attention of children.</p>
        <p>Outdoors</p>
        <p>You can channel youthful energy some 15 miles east of the city at Fort Pulaski National Monument (www.nps.gov/fopu, 912-786-5787; $3, under 16 free) and the free 6.5-mile McQueens Island bicycle and walking trail nearby (no admission fee). Pulaski is an enormous Civil War-era fort that once guarded Savannah.</p>
        <p>There are two entrances to the McQueens Island trail: just beyond the Bull Creek bridge and at the entrance to Fort Pulaski. The palm-lined trail runs along an old rail bed through marshland and along the Savannah River's south channel. Pelicans, dolphins, peregrine falcons and even bobcats can be seen.</p>
        <p>Five miles east of Savannah, endangered Florida panthers, eastern timber wolves and other wildlife can be spotted at the Oatland Island Education Center (711 Sandtown Road, 912-898-3980; www.oatlandisland.org; $3, under 4 free), an 1800s homestead. Its nature trail winds through the Lowcountry forest and marsh.</p>
        <p>Tybee Island, a 20-minute drive from Savannah, is a wonderfully eclectic beach town. Most of the action is along Tybrisa Street near the pier. This includes the oddball department store T. S. Chu's (6 Tybrisa Street, 921-786-4561; www.chusmart.com), where you'll find everything from beach rafts and sunscreen to fishing tackle and hardware.</p>
        <p>The least crowded beaches are at Tybee's southern and northern ends. At North Beach tour the fantastic Tybee Island Lighthouse (30 Meddin Drive, 912-786-5801; www.tybeeligthouse.org). A 178-step climb is rewarded with a breathtaking view and a 19th-century Fresnel lens beacon.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>For breakfast, the Firefly Cafe (321 Habersham Street, 912-234-1971) is on a quiet corner on Troup Square. Sit under the oaks and enjoy a plate of blueberry corn pancakes ($6.95) or shrimp and grits ($10.95) and let the kids explore the square.</p>
        <p>Vinnie Van Go-Go's (317 West Bryan Street, 912-233-6394) is a popular indoor-outdoor pizza joint ($11 for a large cheese).</p>
        <p>Don't miss the homemade goodies like pralines or gophers -- pecan clusters covered with caramel and chocolate, $1.50 to $2 each -- at Savannah Candy Kitchen, (318 West St. Julian Street, 912-201-9501) or Cafe Gelatohhh!'s 24 flavors of Italian-style ice cream (202 West St. Julian Street, 912-234.2344; $3.42 for a small cone).</p>
        <p>On Tybee, AJ's Dockside Restaurant (1315 Chatham Avenue, 912-786-9533) is tucked into a quiet waterfront corner on the island's south side. Try the shrimp and grits ($7.95) or artichoke dip ($6.95) appetizers, followed with a bowl of crab stew ($7.95) or scored flounder ($25.95). Arrive early for dinner.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>The Inn at Ellis Square, a Days Hotel (201 West Bay Street, 912-236-4440; www.innatellissquare.com) has a pool and is next to the market . Rates start at $179.</p>
        <p>The Westin Savannah Harbor Golf Resort and Spa (Resort Drive, 912-201-2000; www.westin.com/savannah) looks across the Savannah River at Old Downtown. Children will like the two-minute ferry ride to River Street. It has a Westin Kids Club with activities for ages 5 to 12. Rates start at $199.</p>
        <p>The Ocean Plaza Beach Resort (1401 Strand Avenue, 912-786-7777; www.oceanplaza.com) has 205 rooms and suites on the beach near Tybee Pier. Rates start at $169.</p>
        <p>WEEKEND WITH THE KIDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
