<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Selanne Takes Road Less Traveled on Way to the Stanley Cup Title</title>
    <meta content="08nhl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/sports/hockey/08nhl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852927"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Anaheim Ducks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stanley Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stanley Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Anaheim Mighty Ducks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Anaheim Mighty Ducks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Hockey League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Selanne, Teemu</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7DB1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="644" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Selanne Takes Road Less Traveled on Way to the Stanley Cup Title</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Selanne Takes Road Less Traveled on Way to the Stanley Cup Title</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEE JENKINS</byline>
      <dateline>ANAHEIM, Calif., June 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even when their logo was a cartoon, when their arena was a pond, when their name was a punch line, Teemu Selanne took them seriously.</p>
        <p>He was traded to the Anaheim Mighty Ducks in 1996, when the franchise was 3 years old, a source of amusement to some and embarrassment to others.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Teemu Selanne joined the Anaheim Mighty Ducks in 1996, the team was a source of amusement to some and embarrassment to others.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even when their logo was a cartoon, when their arena was a pond, when their name was a punch line, Teemu Selanne took them seriously.</p>
        <p>He was traded to the Anaheim Mighty Ducks in 1996, when the franchise was 3 years old, a source of amusement to some and embarrassment to others.</p>
        <p>The franchise basically asked Selanne to lead the team, embody the organization and teach Orange County the difference between a slap shot and a wrister.</p>
        <p>Whether the franchise, now known as the Ducks, knew it at the time, it chose the ideal ambassador. In interviews, Selanne answered every question, no matter how elementary. After games, Selanne signed every autograph, even if the fans could not always pronounce his name.</p>
        <p>Wayne Gretzky may have popularized hockey in Southern California when he took the Los Angeles Kings to the Stanley Cup finals in 1993. But Selanne, nicknamed the Finnish Flash, stuck around and tried to complete the job.</p>
        <p>He nearly sacrificed his career for the cause. He spent 15 seasons in the N.H.L., playing mainly for losers. He spent eight seasons in Anaheim, watching the Ducks change names, owners, logos and uniforms.</p>
        <p>In his 1,127th N.H.L. game, Wednesday night at the Honda Center, the arena formerly known as the Pond, Selanne was finally rewarded. He won his first Stanley Cup, Anaheim won its first Stanley Cup, and California won its first Stanley Cup.</p>
        <p>''I've been here a long time,'' said Selanne, who will turn 37 next month. ''I've played so many games for this dream, and there have been times I didn't know if it was ever going to happen.''</p>
        <p>This has become part of the annual Stanley Cup presentation, a veteran who has toiled in some N.H.L. outpost finally getting his first championship. But unlike many of those players, who latch on to a contender, Selanne helped build one.</p>
        <p>He spent six seasons in Anaheim, bounced to San Jose and Colorado, and realized that he missed Orange County. He was the unique star who really wanted to be a Duck. When he re-signed with Anaheim two years ago, he began to call it ''my happy place.''</p>
        <p>As Selanne skated off the ice Wednesday night after the Ducks defeated the Ottawa Senators, 6-2, he was congratulated by almost as many ushers as teammates. Selanne rattled off three reasons why he embraces this area: the weather, the growth of amateur hockey and the privacy he is afforded here.</p>
        <p>Like any veteran who wins the Stanley Cup, Selanne was asked in his postgame news conference whether he would retire. And like any veteran, he went back and forth before saying that he would need more time to decide.</p>
        <p>''I've always dreamed about retiring on top,'' Selanne said. ''And I don't know if you can go more top than this.'' He added, ''I don't want to make any decision before I'm stable and I have time to think about the future.''</p>
        <p>Selanne seems to have reached the major career milestones -- he has scored his 500th goal this season, played in his 1,000th game and won that elusive title. Even if he retires, the Ducks will still be in position for another title. The only unrestricted free agent they need to re-sign is goaltender Jean-Sébastien Giguère.</p>
        <p>As Champagne corks popped Wednesday night, N.H.L. Commissioner Gary Bettman announced to the home crowd that Anaheim was the first West Coast team to win the Stanley Cup, a declaration that provoked outrage among hardcore followers of the 1925 Victoria Cougars, the 1917 Seattle Metropolitans and the 1915 Vancouver Millionaires.</p>
        <p>It turns out that the Ducks are not the first West Coast team to win the Cup. But they are the first to win it since the league took control of the trophy, since hockey came to California, and sinec Selanne showed the locals how the game was played.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
