<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Hail of Shots Kills 3 Young Men in Brooklyn</title>
    <meta content="08murder" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/nyregion/08murder.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852962"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6DA1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Hail of Shots Kills 3 Young Men in Brooklyn</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Hail of Shots Kills 3 Young Men in Brooklyn</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRYMAINE LEE and ANN FARMER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A placid evening of socializing by a group of friends on a stoop in Brownsville, Brooklyn, turned bloody Wednesday night when a gunman walked up and opened fire, killing three young men, the police and neighbors said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Rumors of robbery and retribution were churning in the neighborhood yesterday, as relatives, friends and neighbors of the victims tried to make sense of the deaths.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Neighbors and friends of the victims speculated that the shootings could have been related to a robbery in the neighborhood earlier in the day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A placid evening of socializing by a group of friends on a stoop in Brownsville, Brooklyn, turned bloody Wednesday night when a gunman walked up and opened fire, killing three young men, the police and neighbors said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Rumors of robbery and retribution were churning in the neighborhood yesterday, as relatives, friends and neighbors of the victims tried to make sense of the deaths.</p>
        <p>The shootings were among a string of killings in an unusually violent 24-hour period in the city. In all, seven people were killed on Wednesday and early yesterday, including a couple in what the authorities described as a murder-suicide in East New York, Brooklyn, and two young men shot to death in East Harlem.</p>
        <p>The police identified the victims in the Brownsville killings as Michael Robinson, 21, of 45 Lott Avenue; Delroy Gumbs, 19, of 2275 Strauss Street; and Brandon Graves, 16, of 490 Herzl Street. All lived within a block and a half of the shootings.</p>
        <p>As an impromptu memorial grew on the concrete steps at 40 Lott Avenue, at Herzl Street, where the victims were killed, a sad chatter about ''good boys'' lost to ''nonsense'' could be heard among the many who came by to pay their respects.</p>
        <p>Before the shooting started, just before midnight, as many as eight people were sitting on the steps or standing on the sidewalk with the victims, witnesses said. Then a man with a gun strolled up and squeezed off several shots, six or eight by most witness accounts.</p>
        <p>Neighbors said the young men were innocent victims, simply in the wrong place at the wrong time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robinson, friends and family said, had custody of his infant son and was working two jobs.</p>
        <p>''The only thing he wanted to do was to go to college and take care of his family,'' said Passion Williams, 17, the mother of his son, who said she had a good relationship with him. Ms. Williams, holding the baby, said Mr. Robinson worked as a janitor for the city's Administration for Children's Services and at a Modell's sporting goods store.</p>
        <p>Agatha Anderson, 63, Mr. Gumbs's grandmother, said he was working toward his G.E.D. and held a job at a KFC restaurant.</p>
        <p>A great-aunt, Valcina Gumbs, said: ''They're very nice kids; it shocked me. It's going to take us a long time to get over this.''</p>
        <p>Friends of Mr. Graves, who was in the 10th grade, said he was quiet and reliable, and popular with the girls. His mother called him ''an angel on earth'' and said he loved music.</p>
        <p>Neighbors and friends of the victims speculated that the shootings could have been related to a robbery in the neighborhood earlier in the day, and that the gunman might have thought one of the victims had something to do with it. But the police said they had no information on any possible motive.</p>
        <p>Officers canvassed the area yesterday, talking to witnesses and handing out leaflets offering no-strings-attached cash rewards for illegal guns. A Crime Stoppers van blared a pledge from loudspeakers on its roof: $1,000 to anyone with information on the killings.</p>
        <p>A neighbor, Barbara Soto, 27, said Mr. Robinson had just come home when he saw some of his friends across the street, on the steps at 40 Lott Avenue, a neighborhood hangout. The stoop is especially popular on hotter days because it sits under a large, shady tree.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Robinson said his hellos, she said, his friends asked him to come over for a drink.</p>
        <p>''He's never on that corner,'' Ms. Soto said. ''Michael didn't have time for the streets.''</p>
        <p>A few hours later, gunshots rang out, followed by yelling and people running and diving for cover. When calm returned to the block, Mr. Robinson and Mr. Graves lay bleeding on the steps, witnesses said. Mr. Gumbs made it down the block a bit, then collapsed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Graves's head rested in Mr. Robinson's lap, witnesses said.</p>
        <p>''One was hunched over, and the other was in his arms like a mother would hold a child,'' said Bianca Rivera-Valderrama, 28. Mr. Graves ''was clenching his fist and coughing,'' she said. ''He was trying to make it.''</p>
        <p>Blood was running down the sidewalk, Ms. Rivera-Valderrama said. ''I stood over them,'' she said. ''I said a prayer to God to watch over them.''</p>
        <p>The victims were taken to Brookdale University Hospital and Medical Center, the police said, where Mr. Robinson and Mr. Graves were pronounced dead. Mr. Gumbs died later.</p>
        <p>Ms. Soto said she and Mr. Robinson had been neighbors and friends for about 10 years.</p>
        <p>''He left the streets, he had two jobs, he made everybody proud,'' she said, her eyes welling. ''My kids looked up to him. And what a good kid he was. He was the light of this block.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
