<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dow Jones Enhances the Severance Packages for Senior Managers</title>
    <meta content="08dow" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/business/media/08dow.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852943"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dow Jones &amp; Co Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">News Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dash, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murdoch, Rupert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Dow Jones &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Wall Street Journal</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Murdoch, Rupert</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bancroft Family</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E2DB1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="591" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dow Jones Enhances the Severance Packages for Senior Managers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dow Jones Enhances the Severance Packages for Senior Managers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC DASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dash, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dow Jones &amp; Co enhances severance packages for senior managers in case of takeover; amends its compensation plans so that 160 senior managers can take sizable severance payments with them if they are forced out after sale; Dow Jones is entertaining $5 billion takeover offer from Rupert Murdoch, who controls News Corp (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dow Jones &amp; Company may or may not be close to a sale, but yesterday it sweetened the pot for managers in case of a takeover.</p>
        <p>In a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission, Dow Jones said it had amended its compensation plans so that 160 senior managers could take sizable severance payments with them if they were forced out after a sale.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dow Jones said it had amended its compensation plans so that 160 senior managers could take sizable severance payments with them if they were forced out after a sale.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dow Jones &amp; Company may or may not be close to a sale, but yesterday it sweetened the pot for managers in case of a takeover.</p>
        <p>In a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission, Dow Jones said it had amended its compensation plans so that 160 senior managers could take sizable severance payments with them if they were forced out after a sale.</p>
        <p>The changes, which the S.E.C. filing said had been approved by the Dow Jones board on Monday, expanded the number of managers covered by special severance contracts to 160 from 25. And the changes could enhance the payouts for managers, who would be able to cash out all of their unvested stock options and get a portion of their 2007 bonus if they were forced out by new owners.</p>
        <p>Dow Jones, which owns The Wall Street Journal and other media properties, is entertaining a $5 billion takeover offer from Rupert Murdoch, who controls the News Corporation. The Bancroft family, which controls Dow Jones, met with Mr. Murdoch this week to discuss terms, and a few other potential suitors have stepped forward to express interest in bidding for the company.</p>
        <p>In its S.E.C. filing yesterday, Dow Jones said the changes were ''intended to enhance the company's ability to retain and attract management-level employees'' and to help them focus on their jobs.</p>
        <p>''It's not connected with any particular potential sale,'' said Linda Dunbar, a Dow Jones spokeswoman. ''Because of recent events, we wanted to aid in the retention and recruitment of talent in light of the uncertainty.''</p>
        <p>Previously, Dow Jones did not have a formal change-in-control plan in place. In its most recent proxy, the company rather ambiguously stated that it would offer change-in-control benefits that were ''superior'' to its ordinary severance plan. Clarifying those plans was left on the back burner since the company's dual-class ownership structure made a takeover seem unlikely. Only in the last few weeks did Dow Jones' board start tackling the issue.</p>
        <p>Although the company did not provide exact figures, the new arrangement spells out more clearly the potential payouts that could be awarded to top managers. But making basic assumptions about the option vesting schedule and bonus payouts could mean that some top executives might get multimillion-dollar exit packages. And the packages could be 30 percent to 40 percent higher if the company covers their taxes.</p>
        <p>Without the taxes being paid, Richard F. Zannino, who became the chief executive of Dow Jones in February 2006, could be eligible for more than $19.7 million in severance, retirement benefits and stock and option payouts based on the $60-a-share price offered by the News Corporation. L. Gordon Crovitz, The Wall Street Journal's publisher, could be eligible for more than $7.2 million.</p>
        <p>And Paul E. Steiger, who stepped down as The Wall Street Journal's managing editor in mid-May, could be entitled to more than $5 million in benefits. Mr. Steiger may not be eligible for change-in-control benefits if he leaves before the company is sold; he is required to retire from Dow Jones by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>Corporate governance experts say the board's actions suggest that the Bancroft family is preparing for a sale.</p>
        <p>''It looks to me like the handwriting is on the wall,'' said Brian Foley, an executive compensation consultant in White Plains. ''The fact that they are expanding this and taking these various actions suggests to me a distinct possibility that the board thinks this deal is going to happen. Otherwise, you don't go this far down the path.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
