<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bork v. Yale Club: Jurist Seeks Redress Over a Fall</title>
    <meta content="08bork" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/nyregion/08bork.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070614T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852979"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Supreme Court</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bork, Robert H</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E3DA1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="533" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bork v. Yale Club: Jurist Seeks Redress Over a Fall</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bork v. Yale Club: Jurist Seeks Redress Over a Fall</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN FEUER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his days as a legal scholar, Robert H. Bork, the onetime Supreme Court nominee, engaged, as many scholars do, in high-minded debates about the august issues of the law. He wrote widely -- sometimes controversially -- about antitrust issues, the right to privacy and the limitations of the First Amendment.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, however, Mr. Bork, who is 80, waded into a somewhat less majestic area of law. After a tumble at the Yale Club in Manhattan last year while ascending to the dais to deliver a speech, he filed a common everyday trip-and-fall lawsuit against the club.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robert H. Bork, the onetime Supreme Court nominee, filed a common everyday trip-and-fall lawsuit against the Yale Club in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his days as a legal scholar, Robert H. Bork, the onetime Supreme Court nominee, engaged, as many scholars do, in high-minded debates about the august issues of the law. He wrote widely -- sometimes controversially -- about antitrust issues, the right to privacy and the limitations of the First Amendment.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, however, Mr. Bork, who is 80, waded into a somewhat less majestic area of law. After a tumble at the Yale Club in Manhattan last year while ascending to the dais to deliver a speech, he filed a common everyday trip-and-fall lawsuit against the club.</p>
        <p>The tale of the suit, filed in Federal District Court in Manhattan, begins on what his court papers innocently refer to as ''the evening of June 6, 2006,'' when The New Criterion magazine held an event at the Yale Club in honor of Hilton Kramer, the magazine's co-founder. Mr. Bork, a contributor to the magazine, was among those invited to deliver remarks.</p>
        <p>The event was held in a banquet room, the suit explains, where the club's staff had erected a dais atop which a lectern had been placed for the speakers. It is the Yale Club's ''normal practice,'' the suit contends, to provide a set of stairs so that the speakers may ascend easily to their appointed perch.</p>
        <p>''At the New Criterion event, however, the Yale Club failed to provide any steps between the floor and dais,'' the suit claims. ''Nor did the Yale Club provide a handrail or any other reasonable feature to assist guests attempting to climb to the dais.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bork fell backward while ascending the dais, striking his left leg on the side of the dais and bumping his head, the suit claims. As a result of the fall, a hematoma formed on his leg and later burst. The injury required surgery, extended medical treatment and months of physical therapy, the suit contends.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Bork suffered excruciating pain as a result of this injury,'' according to the suit, ''and was largely immobile during the months in which he received physical therapy.'' Not only was he forced to use a cane, the suit maintains, but he also still walks with a limp.</p>
        <p>Tim Hill, a spokesman for the Yale Club, which is at 50 Vanderbilt Avenue, declined to comment on the suit, which seeks $1 million in damages, as well as lawyers' fees. But Cricket Farnsworth, the office manager of The New Criterion, said Mr. Bork managed to reach the dais after his spill, and delivered his speech.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bork has long had strained relations with Yale, where he served on the Law School faculty for more than 15 years before he was appointed as a judge of the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit. The faculty was generally opposed to his Supreme Court nomination, faculty members have said, although its professors testified both for and against him at his confirmation hearing in 1987. His nomination was ultimately defeated after a tumultuous Senate battle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bork has been known to chuckle during speeches when he cites a bit of popular wisdom that he says he once saw on a bumper sticker: ''Save America. Close Yale Law School.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 14, 2007, Thursday  An article on Friday about a lawsuit filed by Robert H. Bork, the onetime Supreme Court nominee, against the Yale Club in Manhattan over injuries he suffered during a fall from a dais incorrectly rendered an account of the incident by Cricket Farnsworth, the office manager for The New Criterion magazine, which had invited Mr. Bork to speak at the club. Ms. Farnsworth said that Mr. Bork went on to deliver his speech after his fall; she did not also say that he managed to make his way back to the dais first.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 14, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article on Friday about a lawsuit filed by Robert H. Bork, the onetime Supreme Court nominee, against the Yale Club in Manhattan over injuries he suffered during a fall from a dais incorrectly rendered an account of the incident by Cricket Farnsworth, the office manager for The New Criterion magazine, which had invited Mr. Bork to speak at the club. Ms. Farnsworth said that Mr. Bork went on to deliver his speech after his fall; she did not also say that he managed to make his way back to the dais first.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
