<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Let's Twist Again, Dude, as the Screws Turn</title>
    <meta content="08Dark" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/theater/reviews/08Dark.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852899"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Labute, Neil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cantor, Carolyn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krause, Louisa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Livingston, Ron</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weller, Frederick</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">In a Dark Dark House (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Lortel, Lucille, Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Labute, Neil</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Livingston, Ron</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Weller, Frederick</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cantor, Carolyn</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">In a Dark Dark House (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDE1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1172" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Let's Twist Again, Dude, as the Screws Turn</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Let’s Twist Again, Dude, as the Screws Turn</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley reviews Neil LaBute play In a Dark Dark House, directed by Carolyn Cantor; Louisa Krause, Ron Livingston and Frederick Weller star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rehab as a spectator sport has become such a girlie affair, thanks to the pink-tinged public meltdowns of Britney, Lindsay, et al., that it's kind of gratifying to watch Neil LaBute grease the road to recovery with his patented brand of testosterone.</p>
        <p>For the first scene of ''In a Dark Dark House,'' the cold-eyed, absorbing puzzle play that opened last night at the Lucille Lortel Theater, Mr. LaBute plops two of his classically brutish boys in a fancy institution for the dangerously self-medicated and watches them writhe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In this cold-eyed, absorbing puzzle play, Neil LaBute refreshingly reminds us that his talents go beyond glibly vicious storytelling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rehab as a spectator sport has become such a girlie affair, thanks to the pink-tinged public meltdowns of Britney, Lindsay, et al., that it's kind of gratifying to watch Neil LaBute grease the road to recovery with his patented brand of testosterone.</p>
        <p>For the first scene of ''In a Dark Dark House,'' the cold-eyed, absorbing puzzle play that opened last night at the Lucille Lortel Theater, Mr. LaBute plops two of his classically brutish boys in a fancy institution for the dangerously self-medicated and watches them writhe.</p>
        <p>As might be expected, these guys are not at home in a world of stand-up emotional venting and baby-sitting for grown-ups. Drew (Ron Livingston), the patient, and Terry (Frederick Weller), his older brother, fill awkward silences in the time-honored LaBute way: roughhousing, insulting each other's virility and making obscene fun of the touchy-feely stuff.</p>
        <p>But Mr. LaBute, whose judgment of his fellow men makes the Old Testament Jehovah look like a softie, has a darker purpose in mind than mere satire. The affluent Drew, a disbarred lawyer whose immediate future includes being tried for drunken driving, has enlisted the rougher-hewn Terry, a security guard, to corroborate some details of their shared past. And if you know the work of Mr. LaBute, you know that the past is never pretty.</p>
        <p>Since he made his New York stage debut a decade ago with ''bash,'' a shocker about clean-cut murderous Mormons, Mr. LaBute has become one of the most productive and formulaic of American dramatists, churning out play after play that exposes the black heart of man. (Woman, by comparison, might qualify as gray-hearted.)</p>
        <p>Nearly always driven by convoluted plots with nasty, last-minute revelations, Mr. LaBute's stage work has become the theatrical equivalent of anthology television series like ''Alfred Hitchcock Presents'' or ''The Twilight Zone.'' You're more likely to watch recent LaBute plays like ''Wrecks'' anticipating the final ''gotcha!'' twist than considering character.</p>
        <p>True to form, ''In a Dark Dark House,'' directed by Carolyn Cantor, prominently features one of those twists. Correction: make that three or four such twists, which wind up knotting the play past the point of credibility.</p>
        <p>But before the twisting takes over, Mr. LaBute refreshingly reminds us (and it's about time) that his talents go beyond glibly vicious storytelling and extend into thoughtful analyses of a world rotten with original sin. For its first three quarters, ''House'' ranks with Mr. LaBute's best work for stage (''bash,'' ''Fat Pig'') and screen (''In the Company of Men'').</p>
        <p>It is, of course, difficult for a critic to write much about Mr. LaBute's plays, given their O. Henry-ish conclusions, without receiving a flood of angry e-mail messages crying, ''Spoiler!'' But I don't think I'm being too loose-lipped in saying that ''House'' is about adolescence in American lives: how it can be warped, stolen, frozen and willfully extended. It's no coincidence that Beowulf Boritt's sylvan sets, which include a miniature golf course, have a sunny, Never-Never Land quality.</p>
        <p>This being Mr. LaBute, he explores his theme via some lurid hot-button topics, including domestic violence and child abuse. (All right, call me Spoiler, but this aspect of the plot becomes evident in the first 15 minutes.) Drew, it seems, has discovered in therapy that his self-destructive behavior stems from his encounter as a 12-year-old with a too charming man who befriended him and his brother.</p>
        <p>At its most basic, the plot of ''House'' becomes another LaButean exploration of how people use and betray one another. But there are subtler forces at work here, including Mr. LaBute's most sophisticated use of language thus far.</p>
        <p>There are three characters in ''House.'' In addition to the brothers, there's Jennifer (Louisa Krause), the 16-year-old manager of a miniature golf course, whom Terry meets in the second scene. The words these people choose, and the ways they rag one another for the way they speak, become a crucial index to who they are and why they will act as they ultimately do.</p>
        <p>It drives Terry crazy, for instance, that his successful younger brother, at 35, uses words like ''dude,'' ''bro' '' and ''whatever.''</p>
        <p>''You are not a kid, all right?'' Terry tells Drew, with what seems like excessive touchiness. He pauses uncomfortably before adding, ''You are a grown man.''</p>
        <p>On the other hand, the luscious young Jennifer is a trailer-park-type girl with an urbane, often witty mouth. Adolescence, it seems, is a relative condition. But don't make the mistake of thinking that the youngest-sounding character is the most vulnerable.</p>
        <p>Mr. LaBute's plays have become magnets for hip Hollywood dudes (oops, sorry, Terry) wanting to test their stage wings, often with very happy results. (Recent examples include Ben Stiller in ''This Is How It Goes'' and Jeremy Piven in ''Fat Pig.'')</p>
        <p>Mr. Livingston, best known for the cult favorite ''Office Space,'' is appealingly at ease onstage, turning in a sly study in instinctive manipulation. Ms. Krause, who has the bruisable-peach quality of Sandra Dee in her teen-queen glory years, is more than adequate as the vulpine Jennifer and promises to get better. Ms. Cantor lets the pace sag in Jennifer's dialogue with Terry, in a scene that demands a shivery tautness.</p>
        <p>Terry is the highest maintenance of the roles. He's the only one who's onstage for all three scenes, and he is the play's unofficial detective, elucidating sinister secrets. Mr. Weller, who has already proved his stage chops in high-profile works like ''Glengarry Glen Ross'' and ''Take Me Out,'' acquits himself with style.</p>
        <p>True, he is sometimes a prisoner of the working-class nasal accent he has affected. But his body language is eloquent throughout. Terry has the play's big, gooseflesh-making moments, and Mr. Weller nails them.</p>
        <p>Or nails them, anyway, as much as the story's continuing turns of the screw permit. In the final scene revelation follows so thickly upon revelation that you feel less like gasping than like rolling your eyes. It's not that the plot turns don't track (though I question the use of one legal ruse), but they overwhelm the play's more truly valuable accomplishments.</p>
        <p>There's a moment toward the end in which Mr. Weller, sitting on a child's swing, goes dead in the face, and in just a few seconds you learn more about his damaged life than any subsequent exposition could provide. Mr. LaBute may pride himself on speaking the unspeakable. But sometimes the unspoken says a lot more.</p>
        <p>In a Dark Dark House</p>
        <p>By Neil LaBute; directed by Carolyn Cantor; sets by Beowulf Boritt; costumes by Jenny Mannis; lighting by Ben Stanton; sound by Robert Kaplowitz; production manager, B D White; production stage manager, Joel Rosen; general manager, Barb Auld. Presented by the MCC Theater, Robert LuPone and Bernard Telsey, artistic directors; William Cantler, associate artistic director; Blake West, executive director; by special arrangement with the Lucille Lortel Theater Foundation. At the Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, West Village; (212) 279-4200. Through June 23. Running time: 1 hour 30 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Louisa Krause (Jennifer), Ron Livingston (Drew) and Frederick Weller (Terry).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
