<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A TB Patient Turns to His Inner Lawyer</title>
    <meta content="08speaker" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/us/08speaker.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852968"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Tuberculosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tuberculosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel Restrictions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tuberculosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Speaker, Andrew</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E5DA1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A TB Patient Turns to His Inner Lawyer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A TB Patient Turns to His Inner Lawyer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, June 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Until last week, Theodore and Andrew Speaker had devoted their legal skills to the workaday custody disputes and personal injury claims that clients brought to their small father-son practice here.</p>
        <p>But since Andrew, 31, was identified as the Atlanta lawyer who knowingly traveled to Europe and back with a drug-resistant strain of tuberculosis, the Speakers have been aggressively litigating a far more personal case in the worldwide court of public opinion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a weeklong stream of appearances on news programs, Theodore and Andrew Speaker have made effective use of numerous tactics from the plaintiff’s lawyer’s playbook.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Until last week, Theodore and Andrew Speaker had devoted their legal skills to the workaday custody disputes and personal injury claims that clients brought to their small father-son practice here.</p>
        <p>But since Andrew, 31, was identified as the Atlanta lawyer who knowingly traveled to Europe and back with a drug-resistant strain of tuberculosis, the Speakers have been aggressively litigating a far more personal case in the worldwide court of public opinion.</p>
        <p>In a weeklong stream of appearances on news programs, starting with last Friday's interview on ''Good Morning America'' on ABC and continuing through Wednesday night's hour on ''Larry King Live'' on CNN, the Speakers have made effective use of numerous tactics from the plaintiff's lawyer's playbook.</p>
        <p>Starting from a position of near universal condemnation, they have used persuasion, humility and the timely and selective release of bombshell evidence to portray Andrew and his family as victims of bumbling and disingenuous bureaucrats.</p>
        <p>In the CNN appearance, only hours after health officials had testified before Congress that Andrew Speaker had been advised not to travel, Theodore Speaker allowed the first broadcast of snippets of recordings from a critical meeting that he had taped surreptitiously.</p>
        <p>On the recording, which was made at a May 10 session with Fulton County health officials, the Speakers asked whether Andrew could expect to be restricted to a room once he arrived at a Denver hospital for specialized treatment.</p>
        <p>''Now, that I don't know,'' responded Dr. Eric A. Benning, director of the county health department's communicable diseases branch. ''But because of the fact that you actually are not contagious, there's no reason for you to be sequestered.''</p>
        <p>In another piece of the recording, Dr. Benning told Mr. Speaker, ''As far as we can tell you, you're not a threat to anybody right now.''</p>
        <p>Those comments, Andrew Speaker said, support his assertion that while health officials told him they preferred he not travel, they never gave him reason to believe he would be putting others at risk. The officials in the meetings, he emphasized, never wore masks.</p>
        <p>''No one ever gave the impression that I was a threat to anyone,'' he said. ''No one ever told me that anyone in my family was at risk.'' He added later, ''If they're going to say now that I was a threat, then they should have said that a long time ago so I can protect my wife and my child.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker is polished on camera, as is his wife, Sarah, a third-year law student. The newlyweds hold hands throughout interviews, addressing their hosts deferentially. Family members testify to living through a nightmare.</p>
        <p>Theodore Speaker, a Vietnam veteran who described himself as ''a little hard of hearing,'' said he taped conversations frequently and had wanted to be able to review any diagnosis offered in the meeting. Asked by Mr. King why he did not tell others in the meeting that he was taping it, Mr. Speaker said, ''I just didn't think about it.''</p>
        <p>He reiterated in an interview Thursday that he was willing to release only selected parts of the recordings. ''What was not released was privileged information about his medical condition.''</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the Fulton County health department said there would be no comment. On Wednesday, the department's director, Dr. Steven Katkowsky, told a Senate subcommittee that Mr. Speaker had been advised he was not ''highly contagious'' but was still infectious and should not travel.</p>
        <p>Theodore Speaker said that he had practiced family, personal injury and criminal law for 29 years, and that his son joined him three years ago after graduating from the University of Georgia School of Law.</p>
        <p>Only a month ago, he said, Andrew had decided to set out on his own to specialize in personal injury law.</p>
        <p>Theodore Speaker said the family had decided to mount a public campaign after concluding that Andrew's reputation was being besmirched by health officials trying to shift blame for their mistakes.</p>
        <p>Somewhat awkwardly, a primary target has been the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, where Andrew's father-in-law, Dr. Robert C. Cooksey, works as a microbiologist who researches tuberculosis. The agency is investigating Dr. Cooksey's role in the events. ''The C.D.C. needs to step up to the plate,'' Theodore Speaker said.</p>
        <p>Andrew Speaker's law school classmates recall him as a skillful advocate who led the university to honors in mock trial competitions. David M. Rich, a law school roommate who now practices in Nashville, said his friend had rejected his advice that he hire public relations professionals to control the damage.</p>
        <p>''Drew basically refused and said, 'I'm going to have to tell my own story and put my best foot forward,' '' Mr. Rich said.</p>
        <p>L. Lin Wood, an Atlanta lawyer who has guided a number of celebrity clients through legal and public relations thickets, said the Speakers had ''settled on a very aggressive strategy of getting their story out, and they have put a public face on the facts.'' Mr. Wood said they had been smart to do so.</p>
        <p>''If they had taken a wait-and-see strategy,'' he said, ''I think they would never have overcome the initial negative tone.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
