<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City Traffic Pricing Wins U.S. and Spitzer's Favor</title>
    <meta content="08congestion" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/nyregion/08congestion.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852980"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">London (Eng)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rivera, Ray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloomberg, Michael R (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peters, Mary E (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Silver, Sheldon (Speaker)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruno, Joseph L (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E3DA1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1051" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City Traffic Pricing Wins U.S. and Spitzer's Favor</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">City Traffic Pricing Wins U.S. and Spitzer’s Favor</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM and RAY RIVERA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny; Rivera, Ray</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, June 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayor Michael R Bloomberg's plan to charge people who drive into busiest parts of Manhattan is endorsed by Gov Eliot Spitzer of New York and Bush administration; if measure is approved by New York State Legislature, New York will become first city in US to impose broad system of congestion pricing, which has been credited with reducing traffic in London since it was introduced in 2003; United States Transportation Sec Mary E Peters announces that New York City is one of nine finalists for share of $1.1 billion in federal aid to fight urban traffic; warns that city's potential share could be endangered if mayor's plan does not have state approval by Aug; plan faces opposition in Legislature; Democratic Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver voices concern that congestion fees paid by drivers would go up, as it has in London, and Republican Senate majority leader Joseph L Bruno has not endorsed plan and is unclear about when issue would come up for vote; legislatie session endes on June 21, but Spitzer says he would call Legislature back into special session by Aug to consider measure; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's plan to reduce traffic by charging people who drive into the busiest parts of Manhattan received significant support on Thursday as Gov. Eliot Spitzer endorsed the idea and the Bush administration indicated that New York stood to gain hundreds of millions of dollars if the plan were enacted.</p>
        <p>If the measure is approved by the Legislature, New York will become the first city in the United States to impose a broad system of congestion pricing, which was introduced in London in 2003 and has been credited with reducing traffic there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the measure is approved, New York will become the first city in the United States to impose congestion pricing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's plan to reduce traffic by charging people who drive into the busiest parts of Manhattan received significant support on Thursday as Gov. Eliot Spitzer endorsed the idea and the Bush administration indicated that New York stood to gain hundreds of millions of dollars if the plan were enacted.</p>
        <p>If the measure is approved by the Legislature, New York will become the first city in the United States to impose a broad system of congestion pricing, which was introduced in London in 2003 and has been credited with reducing traffic there.</p>
        <p>Governor Spitzer said he would work to ensure passage of the plan, which is a major part of the mayor's blueprint for improving air quality and traffic flow for the next several decades. The Bloomberg administration has estimated that it could put the program into effect within 18 months of legislative approval.</p>
        <p>''This is a necessary investment for the future of New York City, which is to a great extent the economic engine of New York State,'' the governor said. ''And so this is not really a question of whether, it's a question of how, it's a question of making sure that we do it properly.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer appeared alongside the United States transportation secretary, Mary E. Peters, who announced that New York City was one of nine finalists for a share of $1.1 billion in federal aid to fight urban traffic. Ms. Peters warned, however, that the city's potential share could be endangered if the mayor's plan did not have state approval by August.</p>
        <p>Despite the pressure of that warning on the Legislature, the plan faces opposition in Albany. Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, a Democrat who represents Lower Manhattan, outlined a list of concerns about the plan, including questions about the several hundred cameras Mayor Bloomberg has proposed installing to track cars that enter Manhattan. Mr. Silver also said the fees paid by drivers in London rose greatly after congestion pricing began, and worried about similar increases here.</p>
        <p>In the Republican-led Senate, the majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, introduced legislation on Thursday to enact the mayor's plan but stopped short of endorsing it, and it was unclear when the issue would come up for a vote.</p>
        <p>The mayor's plan would charge $8 for cars and $21 for commercial trucks that enter Manhattan below 86th Street between 6 a.m. and 6 p.m. on weekdays, or $4 for drivers within the congestion zone, with several exceptions.</p>
        <p>The legislative session ends on June 21, but the governor said he would most likely call the Legislature back into a special session by August to consider the measure.</p>
        <p>''Part of this process is certainly to ensure that we can give the secretary the assurance that this is a plan that will happen,'' the governor said at a joint appearance Thursday morning with the mayor and Ms. Peters. He added, ''She wants that assurance, and therefore we need to create a persuasive argument that Albany is behind this.''</p>
        <p>''Obviously,'' he added, ''the governor is behind it.''</p>
        <p>Secretary Peters, who called the Bloomberg plan ''very bold,'' said that up to five of the nine cities would be selected to receive federal funds by mid-August, but she intimated that New York City was likely to be among the winners because no other city was as far along in its planning.</p>
        <p>''It cannot be easy for a politician to propose charging commuters more money to enter Manhattan, but the mayor's plan is sound, and the mayor's plan will work,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Despite his endorsement, Governor Spitzer and his aides have concerns about the fine print, including the mayor's proposal to create a public authority to take in the new revenue, estimated at $380 million a year. That would give the mayor more say over transportation spending. Mr. Spitzer would like to see the money remain in the control of existing authorities and would like to use it to ease a looming deficit at the Metropolitan Transportation Authority.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer also said he wanted to examine any ripple effects the program would have on traffic in neighborhoods outside Manhattan.</p>
        <p>That concern is shared by some Assembly members from New York City who represent districts just outside the toll zone.</p>
        <p>''One of the major problems is that districts like mine and others become possibly parking lots,'' said Assemblyman Joseph R. Lentol, a Democrat who represents the Brooklyn neighborhoods around the Williamsburg Bridge.</p>
        <p>Assemblyman Keith L. T. Wright, a Harlem Democrat, called the plan ''a great start.''</p>
        <p>''My only condition,'' he added, ''is that we have to be leery and vigilant and watchful that certain communities are not used as parking lots.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lentol said he believed that a majority of Assembly Democrats would be opposed to the mayor's plan, but added that it was hard to say for sure because many members had yet to focus on the issue.</p>
        <p>The Assembly will hold the first of a series of public hearings on congestion pricing on Friday, with the mayor as the first witness.</p>
        <p>In the State Senate, the eight Long Island Republicans, an influential bloc, are likely to oppose the bill.</p>
        <p>But the mayor's word carries considerable weight with Republicans. He is one of the largest individual donors to the Senate Republican leadership, giving them more than several hundred thousands last year.</p>
        <p>''Looking at the bill, obviously I think we owe the mayor the courtesy of a look through, but it's a difficult thing, a difficult thing to go with,'' said the Senate deputy majority leader, Dean G. Skelos.</p>
        <p>Other finalists for the federal funds are Atlanta, Dallas, Denver, Minneapolis, St. Paul, Miami, San Diego, San Francisco and Seattle. Those cities account for one-third of all highway congestion recorded among the nation's 85 largest cities, and handled about 20 percent of all vehicle travel in America, according to the Transportation Department.</p>
        <p>New York City officials hope to receive about $500 million in federal money. Secretary Peters suggested the funds could be used right away for enhancing public transit to accommodate those who previously drove to the city.</p>
        <p>As it happened, Ms. Peters said she had been delayed from reaching the Thursday morning meeting with the governor and the mayor because she was stuck in traffic on the Franklin D. Roosevelt Drive.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
