<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Jersey Senate Panel Supports Penalty for Smoking in Cars With Children Aboard</title>
    <meta content="08smoke" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/nyregion/08smoke.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852981"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Smoking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3DA1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Jersey Senate Panel Supports Penalty for Smoking in Cars With Children Aboard</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Jersey Senate Panel Supports Penalty for Smoking in Cars With Children Aboard</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, June 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Smoking in New Jersey has been banned from the workplace, public buildings, bars, restaurants and even large swaths of the casino floors in Atlantic City. The next frontier is the family car with children aboard.</p>
        <p>Under a measure passed unanimously Thursday by the Senate Health, Human Services and Senior Citizens Committee, anyone caught smoking while a passenger 16 years old or younger is in the vehicle would be charged with a disorderly offense punishable by a $100 fine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRENTON, June 7  Smoking in New Jersey has been banned from the workplace, public buildings, bars, restaurants and even large swaths of the casino floors in Atlantic City. The next frontier is the family car with children aboard.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Smoking in New Jersey has been banned from the workplace, public buildings, bars, restaurants and even large swaths of the casino floors in Atlantic City. The next frontier is the family car with children aboard.</p>
        <p>Under a measure passed unanimously Thursday by the Senate Health, Human Services and Senior Citizens Committee, anyone caught smoking while a passenger 16 years old or younger is in the vehicle would be charged with a disorderly offense punishable by a $100 fine.</p>
        <p>''There is no more important law enforcement responsibility than protecting children,'' said State Senator Raymond J. Lesniak, a Democrat of Union County who sponsored the measure. ''And there is no worse thing you can do to children's health than to have them closed up in a car where someone is smoking.''</p>
        <p>The measure would make smoking with a child in the car a primary violation of the state's traffic codes, allowing police officers to stop such drivers and give them tickets.</p>
        <p>If approved by the full Legislature and signed into law by Gov. Jon S. Corzine, the measure would make New Jersey the third state -- after Arkansas and Louisiana -- to impose such a ban. In Arkansas, however, the ban applies to those driving with children 6 and younger, and in Louisiana, 13 and younger.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, only one town, Keyport, in Monmouth County has a ban, which was approved in April.</p>
        <p>Even as legislators approved the measure, which most said was likely to be enacted, they expressed some ambivalence. Senator Barbara Buono, a Democrat from Edison, who ultimately approved the ban, wondered aloud, ''I don't know if this is the best way to deal with parental behavior.''</p>
        <p>Antismoking activists in New Jersey and nationally applauded the bill as a recognition of the harmful effects of secondhand smoke, which has driven much of the legislation aimed at banning smoking in most public places and many private ones as well.</p>
        <p>Regina Carson, president of the New Jersey Group Against Smoking Pollution, known as GASP, said that this bill addresses the needs of infants and toddlers who cannot communicate their distress at smoke and teenagers afraid to confront their parents or other adults about their discomfort.</p>
        <p>''This provides a consistent message about the dangers of second-hand smoke and smoking,'' Ms. Carson said. ''Children are taught in school, or by public service announcements, that smoking and secondhand smoke are bad for you.''</p>
        <p>Dr. John Banzhaf, executive director of Action on Smoking and Health, a 40-year-old national anti-smoking group, said that quality-of-life measures, like smoking bans when children are present, were an outgrowth of recent moves to ban smoking by foster parents, caring for children who are ultimately a state responsibility.</p>
        <p>''Six or eight months ago it would have been impossible to get such a bill through a state legislature,'' Dr. Banzhaf said. ''But the ban on foster parents has made it more likely.''</p>
        <p>But Gary Nolan, the United States regional representative for the Smoker's Club, an international group that seeks to assert private property rights in countering smoking bans, said he saw ''big brother, big pharma'' and no end to harmful social engineering behind such bills.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nolan said that the concern about secondhand smoke was ''junk science'' that cited levels of harmful substances in smoke that did not reach levels recognized as dangerous by the federal Occupational Safety and Health Administration.</p>
        <p>Among drivers, reaction mirrored the ambivalence expressed by legislators.</p>
        <p>Phil Volpe, a nonsmoker, who was seated at a Starbucks in Pennington with his 10-year-old daughter, Erin, said, ''It is a little bit big brother, but the health and safety of a child is more important than big brother.''</p>
        <p>And Erin, who said that she had just completed her school's DARE course on the prevention of alcohol, tobacco and drug use, was firmly in favor of the ban as well.</p>
        <p>''Smoking could distract someone, and they could miss a stop sign or something,'' she said.</p>
        <p>And there was a question of enforcement.</p>
        <p>Sgt. Michael F. Cseremsak of the Hopewell Township Police Department questioned whether officers would enforce the law.</p>
        <p>Using a hand-held cellphone, Sergeant Cseremsak noted, was a secondary traffic violation, meaning that officers could not stop drivers for that violation alone, but could cite them if they were stopped for some other infraction like speeding.</p>
        <p>''Does this cause hazardous or careless driving?'' said the officer, who said he occasionally smoked a cigar, though never at home or in a car. ''I don't think so. It's really borderline, and I just wonder how far we are going to go regulating people's lives.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
