<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Movers Come to Times Sq., but the Name Stays</title>
    <meta content="08nyc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/nyregion/08nyc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852938"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Times Square and 42nd Street (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Times</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DB1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Movers Come to Times Sq., but the Name Stays</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Movers Come to Times Sq., but the Name Stays</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Let's say that a company moves out of a New York neighborhood that has borne its name for more than a century. Let's also say that we are talking about the place where the ball drops every New Year's Eve. In this age of naming rights and branding strategies, some people might be eager for a change.</p>
        <p>How does Durst Square strike you?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York Times is leaving the heart of Times Square but there’s no rush to undo the name.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Let's say that a company moves out of a New York neighborhood that has borne its name for more than a century. Let's also say that we are talking about the place where the ball drops every New Year's Eve. In this age of naming rights and branding strategies, some people might be eager for a change.</p>
        <p>How does Durst Square strike you?</p>
        <p>Fine, just fine, if you're Douglas Durst.</p>
        <p>''It sounds good to me,'' said Mr. Durst, co-president of the Durst Organization, a dominant developer in the area that has been called Times Square for 103 years. But hold on, he quickly added. He was ''really just teasing.'' He is not about to petition the city for a name change. ''I think Times Square should stay Times Square,'' Mr. Durst said.</p>
        <p>And no doubt it shall. Certainly, no city official talks about undoing a name that has endured since 1904, when Long Acre Square yielded to Times Square in a nod to The New York Times, then moving to the neighborhood from its old headquarters on Park Row in Lower Manhattan. Think of the name change as an early form of branding, when that word generally meant something done by ranchers to cattle.</p>
        <p>Our curiosity now about the name is rooted in a real estate development. The Times is leaving the heart of Times Square for new digs on Eighth Avenue between 40th and 41st Streets, opposite the Port Authority Bus Terminal. This weekend, the newspaper's core, its newsroom, packs up and says farewell to its old haunt on 43rd Street between Seventh and Eighth Avenues.</p>
        <p>Technically, the new building lies within the Times Square area, at least as it is defined by the business improvement district known as the Times Square Alliance.</p>
        <p>''Our official boundaries are basically 40th to 53rd, and then just west of Sixth Avenue to the west side of Eighth Avenue, plus Restaurant Row,'' said Tim Tompkins, the alliance's president. But few people, he acknowledged, think of 40th and Eighth as truly part of Times Square.</p>
        <p>So what about the name?</p>
        <p>''You wouldn't want to go back to Long Acre, right?'' Mr. Tompkins said. ''You'd have to come up with something new. In the tradition of Times Square, it really should be auctioned off to the highest commercial bidder.''</p>
        <p>He was kidding, too. We think.</p>
        <p>The reality is that some names are forever, or as close to forever as a city of constant change can get. ''More often we create new names rather than give up old ones,'' said Kenneth T. Jackson, a Columbia University professor of history and the editor of The Encyclopedia of New York City. ''That's the way you gentrify a neighborhood: You think of something clever, Boerum Hill or something. It's fairly unusual for a name to disappear from active use.''</p>
        <p>That has surely been the case with Herald Square, another area bearing a newspaper's name. Even though The New York Herald has long gone the way of hot type and green eye shades, its memory lingers. (And that old George M. Cohan appeal endures: ''Give my regards to Broadway. Remember me to Herald Square.'')</p>
        <p>''People have great affection for the name, even those who don't know much about the history of the paper that left the scene,'' said Daniel A. Biederman, president of that neighborhood's business improvement district, the 34th Street Partnership. That was true ''even when the area was crummy,'' he said. ''It's part of New York.''</p>
        <p>No question, changing a name can be a touchy business. Look at the nastiness that has attached itself to a proposal to rename several blocks in Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, to honor Sonny Carson, who died in 2002. Mr. Carson was a black activist, community advocate and flaming bigot, having proudly pronounced himself ''anti-white.'' Given his views on race, the City Council rejected the idea last week. That has led to spasms of racially charged name-calling and threats.</p>
        <p>AT least there is no such problem with Times Square, celebrated in story and song. Actually, make that just story. Songs have been few. Broadway and 42nd Street figure in countless numbers, but not Times Square itself.</p>
        <p>We sought out the cabaret singer Steve Ross, a man with dozens of New York songs in his repertory. All he could think of was a long-ago Cohan number, ''My Town,'' which has the verse:</p>
        <p>''Times Square, how I love it! Fresh air, I'd die of it!''</p>
        <p>Those sentiments might hold up if they were set instead in Durst Square or Reuters Square or even (gasp!) Disney Square. But somehow they wouldn't sound quite the same, would they?</p>
        <p>NYC E-mail: haberman@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: haberman@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
