<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Connecticut River, Fatter Fish and Happier Fishermen</title>
    <meta content="08adventurer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/travel/escapes/08adventurer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852872"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ADVENTURER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Housatonic River (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hughes, C J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Adventurer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut River</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E4DE1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1493" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Connecticut River, Fatter Fish and Happier Fishermen</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In a Connecticut River, Fatter Fish and Happier Fishermen</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. HUGHES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hughes, C J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on fishing in Housatonic River in Connecticut, where environmentally sensitive dam-flow policies has improved river's health; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Housatonic River, which flows through western Connecticut to Long Island Sound, made local headlines earlier this spring for flooding that uprooted trees and damaged homes. The bigger story, though, at least in the eyes of fishermen, is the river's improved health.</p>
        <p>Those fishermen, as well as biologists, members of conservation groups and longtime residents, say the Housatonic's water is clearer, its plants greener and its fish fatter than in decades. As a result, 20-inch trout are being caught just two hours from Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a three-year cleanup, the water of the Housatonic River is clearer, its plants greener and its fish bigger than in decades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Housatonic River, which flows through western Connecticut to Long Island Sound, made local headlines earlier this spring for flooding that uprooted trees and damaged homes. The bigger story, though, at least in the eyes of fishermen, is the river's improved health.</p>
        <p>Those fishermen, as well as biologists, members of conservation groups and longtime residents, say the Housatonic's water is clearer, its plants greener and its fish fatter than in decades. As a result, 20-inch trout are being caught just two hours from Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The river's revived health, many sportsmen and scientists say, is the result of environmentally sensitive dam-flow policies that began three years ago. But these policies haven't been universally welcomed. Many kayakers, canoeists and rafters are unhappy with them because they have lowered water depths.</p>
        <p>The river's health is still far from fully restored. Lingering PCB contamination means that most of the fish -- brown, brook and rainbow trout, all of which are stocked, but also pike and smallmouth bass -- shouldn't be eaten.</p>
        <p>But hooking a meal is beside the point for the Housatonic's fishermen, almost all of whom release their catches and many of whom belong to that subset of purists who use only flies.</p>
        <p>They park themselves deep in the river's currents for that telltale tug on the line, the flash of silver beneath the water and that final swoop of the net. And there's evidence that the primeval battle is being played out more often.</p>
        <p>''There's a ton of excitement out there, because there are many promising signs of a comeback,'' said Robert Orciari, a fisheries biologist who oversees the region for the Connecticut Department of Environmental Protection. He has also fly-fished the Housatonic since 1981.</p>
        <p>''Fishermen see things through different eyes than scientists do,'' Mr. Orciari said. ''But both groups can really appreciate what's happening.''</p>
        <p>His agency will undertake an official head count of fishermen on the Housatonic next year, but anecdotal evidence suggests that the numbers are gradually climbing. Staff members at Housatonic River Outfitters in Cornwall Bridge estimate that although vagaries in the weather make estimates difficult, the number of fishermen in that segment of the Housatonic this year seems to be up about 25 percent over last year.</p>
        <p>Cornwall Bridge lies in the six-mile stretch of the river that runs along Route 7 in the towns of Sharon and Cornwall, in Litchfield County in the northwest corner of the state, where fishing is allowed all year. There, where the Housatonic curves under a wooden covered bridge and past Civil War-era churches, the banks are heaped with white and scoured boulders -- the kind that produce the types of eddies that trout love.</p>
        <p>The Housatonic, in fact, is comparable to the best rivers of the West in terms of its width, speed and rugged beauty, said Kirt Mayland, a regional official of Trout Unlimited, a conservation group, who has fished throughout the country.</p>
        <p>''When the water is cool and the bugs are hatching, there's no place I would rather be,'' said Mr. Mayland, who fly-fishes the Housatonic twice a week. ''It's one of the best rivers in the country.''</p>
        <p>And it's getting better, he said, thanks to a new set of rules, which went into effect in 2004 and that he helped to draft. Those rules govern how the Housatonic's hydropower plants harness river water.</p>
        <p>Before, the power plants would hold water behind huge dams, then release it in spurts through turbines. But because the water was allowed to sit in the sun for hours, its temperature would rise. The heated water, once released downstream, harmed fish, sometimes killing up to 200 a day in certain conditions, Mr. Orciari said.</p>
        <p>Now, under the terms of the licensing agreement between the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission and FirstLight Power Resources, which owns five hydropower plants on the Housatonic, dams must allow water to flow through turbines at a constant speed. This is known as a ''run of river'' approach.</p>
        <p>Because of the change, the water temperature throughout the summer hovers around a relatively chilly 65 degrees -- what it might be if the dams had never been built. That is an optimum temperature for most fish, Mr. Mayland said.</p>
        <p>This more natural flow in the long term could also stimulate trout reproduction, he added, possibly giving the river a population of native trout for the first time in a century.</p>
        <p>''It will take a while,'' Mr. Mayland said, ''but you could see a much more natural river in the next five to 10 years.''</p>
        <p>One person who is betting that more fish will beget more fishermen is Marty Iannone, who owns the Housatonic Meadows Fly Shop, which sells flies, tackle and guidebooks from a red, clapboard-sided former gas station on Route 7 across the river from Cornwall Bridge.</p>
        <p>In a bid to turn the property into a one-stop shop for anglers, in April Mr. Iannone unveiled five cabins for overnight guests, tucked against the side of a hill near the river's banks. Those cabins join an existing five-room bed-and-breakfast, whose original section dates to 1780. Next year, Mr. Iannone plans to add a restaurant to the complex -- Breadloaf Mountain Lodge and Cabins -- in a building that once housed a diner.</p>
        <p>Fishermen make up about one-fifth of his lodgers, he said, though he's hoping that percentage will rise.</p>
        <p>And there does appear to be reason for optimism. ''We are catching lots of brook trout up and down the river this spring, and we never did before,'' Mr. Iannone said.</p>
        <p>FOR now, though, most Housatonic fishermen seem to be day-trippers, if the crowd on a recent Saturday afternoon was any indication.</p>
        <p>Near Monument Hole, across the street from the fly shop, Gordon Davidson, a Danbury resident, stood in waist-deep water next to a steep bank shaded by oaks, tying a golden storm fly and lightning bug fly -- a two-for-one nymph gig -- onto his line.</p>
        <p>''Insect life has gone up'' since the run-of-river policy was put in place, Mr. Davidson said. ''There are a lot more than there used to be. It's been a very noticeable change.''</p>
        <p>But the run-of-river policy has hurt other sportsmen. Many kayakers, canoeists and rafters object to it because it results in shallower overall water depths since there's no guaranteed surge from the dams. At the height of the summer, sections of the Housatonic can dry out enough to resemble cobblestone streets.</p>
        <p>Some businesses, like River Running, a kayak- and canoe-rental service in Falls Village, have closed. And others that have depended on the Housatonic's white water since the 1970s are not sure they can survive another year.</p>
        <p>''It's so sad, we're all just still shaking our heads about it,'' said Jennifer Clarke, an owner of Clarke Outdoors on Route 7 across from West Cornwall. ''The real concern this summer is whether we can stay in business, because we're barely squeaking by as it is.''</p>
        <p>When the river is flowing heavily, as it was for much of this spring, the tension among those using it seems negligible.</p>
        <p>Indeed, on that same recent day, a flotilla of four canoes, which carried some high school friends from Massapequa, N.Y., who have made an annual journey down the Housatonic since 1979, passed close to Thomas Greiner, a resident of Trumbull, Conn., who wore a faded blue cap and net strapped to his back as he cast a line.</p>
        <p>''At certain times it can get a little hectic, like in the summer, when people are out enjoying the river more,'' Mr. Greiner said. ''But there's plenty of river to go around.''</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO</p>
        <p>Spending a Day in or on the Water</p>
        <p>FLY-FISHING lessons, guides or equipment are available from the Housatonic Meadows Fly Shop (13 Route 7, Cornwall Bridge; 860-672-6064; www.flyfishct.com). Guides also lead bird-watching trips by boat. A full-day outing for two anglers costs $275, including gear and lunch. Private lessons are $40 an hour. Three-day fishing licenses are $16 for out-of-state residents ($20 a year for state residents).</p>
        <p>The shop, on a five-acre property across the street from Housatonic Meadows State Park, also offers a five-bedroom lodge, built in 1780, at $650 a night, with a two-night minimum on weekends, as well as five cabins, each sleeping four, for $295.</p>
        <p>Housatonic River Outfitters (860-672-1010; www.dryflies.com), a full-service fly-fishing shop just south of Housatonic Meadows State Park on Route 7 in Cornwall Bridge, also offers guides, as well as instruction in casting and fly-tying.</p>
        <p>To rent kayaks, canoes or rafts, head to Clarke Outdoors (163 Route 7, West Cornwall; 860-672-63652; www.clarkeoutdoors.com). Trips typically begin in Falls Village, below the dam, and end at the Housatonic Meadows picnic area. A two-person canoe costs $54 for a weekend day, including paddles, life jackets and a ride back to the shop.</p>
        <p>Post-trip, some river rats head to the Wandering Moose Café (421 Sharon-Goshen Turnpike, West Cornwall; 860-672-0178; www.thewanderingmoosecafe.com), next to the covered bridge, where dinners include strip steak, crab cakes and, appropriately, crusted trout.</p>
        <p>ADVENTURER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
