<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Defense Team to Argue To Free Bonds's Trainer</title>
    <meta content="08bonds" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/sports/baseball/08bonds.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852996"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Bay Area Laboratory Co-Operative</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bonds, Barry</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Anderson, Greg</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E0DA1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="920" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Defense Team to Argue To Free Bonds's Trainer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Defense Team for Bonds’s Trainer Is Set to Argue for His Release</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL S. SCHMIDT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since the investigation of the Bay Area Laboratory Co-Operative began five years ago, one man has spent more time behind bars than anyone in the federal drug case: Greg Anderson, the former personal trainer of Barry Bonds.</p>
        <p>Anderson, 41, served a three-month sentence after pleading guilty in 2005 to distributing steroids and to money laundering. And since November, he has been in prison for refusing to testify about Bonds's suspected steroid use.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Greg Anderson’s legal team will file a motion arguing that the trainer’s confinement has become more of a punishment than a legitimate effort to get him to testify.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Since the investigation of the Bay Area Laboratory Co-Operative began five years ago, one man has spent more time behind bars than anyone in the federal drug case: Greg Anderson, the former personal trainer of Barry Bonds.</p>
        <p>Anderson, 41, served a three-month sentence after pleading guilty in 2005 to distributing steroids and to money laundering. And since November, he has been in prison for refusing to testify about Bonds's suspected steroid use.</p>
        <p>Those who know Anderson say he is motivated by his mistrust of the government's investigation and his friendship with Bonds. But now, with Bonds approaching baseball's career home run record, Anderson's defense team is preparing to argue for his release.</p>
        <p>The defense lawyer Mark Geragos said in a telephone interview Wednesday that he would file a so-called Grumbles motion in the next two months to argue that Anderson's confinement had become more of a punishment than a legitimate effort to persuade him to testify.</p>
        <p>Geragos said he and Anderson had delayed this step for two main reasons. The primary factor is that judges have not been sympathetic to uncooperative witnesses until they have been locked up for at least 10 months, he said. The second is more personal. Anderson wanted to give Bonds time to break the home run record.</p>
        <p>Bonds is being investigated for perjury and for some of his financial dealings, and his relationship with Anderson figures prominently in the case. An indictment of Bonds without Anderson's testimony could make the imprisonment appear unjustified.</p>
        <p>Anderson began training Bonds in 1999, two years before Bonds dominated headlines by hitting 73 home runs to set the single-season record with a performance that far exceeded anything he had done in his career. Bonds gave Anderson a ring to commemorate the feat and a $20,000 bonus, according to the book ''Game of Shadows,'' which chronicled the Balco investigation. Anderson is said to have had a tattoo done of the number 73.</p>
        <p>''Greg is a lifelong friend, and of course he wants him to break the record,'' Geragos said. ''I have always thought the government believes, and that some of those prosecutors believe, without Greg they have no case.''</p>
        <p>Bonds has 746 home runs. Hank Aaron's record is 755.</p>
        <p>''I don't think the investigation would continue if he didn't have a record to break,'' Geragos said.</p>
        <p>The current grand jury in San Francisco is set to expire in July, at which point Anderson could be released anyway. But the grand jury's term could also be extended for another six months, leaving Anderson in custody.</p>
        <p>Scott N. Schools, the interim United States attorney who is directing the Balco case in San Francisco, would not comment on Anderson's status or other aspects of the case, according to an official from his office.</p>
        <p>Several legal experts said it would be difficult to gain Anderson's freedom through a Grumbles motion. They said such situations lead to discussions between the prosecution and the defense about exchanging testimony for freedom.</p>
        <p>Martin Garbus, a First Amendment lawyer, filed a Grumbles motion in 2006 in the case of Josh Wolf, a journalist who refused to turn over a videotape of a protest to federal authorities. Garbus said it was the only way an unwilling witness could seek relief short of testifying.</p>
        <p>''It can start a negotiation and a discussion because the prosecution fears there is a chance, however slight, that the defense can win,'' Garbus said.</p>
        <p>But Geragos said Anderson would not make a deal.</p>
        <p>''He will never negotiate with the government, and I would not authorize that unless they unconditionally surrender,'' he said. ''He is never going to do that.''</p>
        <p>Paula Canny, a lawyer and close friend of Anderson's who visits him several times a month, said Anderson would not change his mind.</p>
        <p>''Greg is rock solid,'' Canny said. ''Greg is the most evolved person I know mentally and emotionally, and he is very at peace with his decision. I am not going to comment on my conversations with him, but he is at peace.''</p>
        <p>But another lawyer who has seen Anderson while visiting clients at the Federal Correctional Institution in Dublin, Calif., said Anderson did not appear to be doing well.</p>
        <p>''When I saw him, he looked depressed and down, more upset than others,'' said the lawyer, who spoke on the condition of anonymity because he said he did not want to jeopardize his relationship with Canny. ''He doesn't look good. My clients that are in the same facility say that he is not a happy camper. Jail is not a fun place, but he appears more depressed. It may just be his demeanor. He looks down, shook and depressed.''</p>
        <p>The Balco investigation has led to five convictions so far, including Anderson's. The others convicted are Balco's founder, Victor Conte Jr.; its former vice president, James Valente; Patrick Arnold, a chemist; and Remi Korchemny, a track coach. Conte served four months in prison, and Arnold was sentenced to three months in prison. Valente and Korchemny received probation.</p>
        <p>At one point last summer, it appeared that Bonds was on the verge of being indicted. That did not happen, and Anderson's silence was considered a major factor. .</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview, Bonds's criminal defense lawyer, Michael Rains, said he did not believe Anderson would testify. He said the men had not spoken since Anderson went to prison, and he advised Bonds not to write to him, either.</p>
        <p>''Barry wants Greg out, and he wants him out tomorrow,'' Rains said. ''He wanted him out yesterday.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
