<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES: June 8 - June 14; 'EXPEDITION RMA'</title>
    <meta content="08bkids" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852867"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5DE1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="425" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES: June 8 - June 14; 'EXPEDITION RMA'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAUREL GRAEBER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The highest objects in New York City are usually skyscrapers. But if Manhattan cannot have mountains, this weekend the Rubin Museum of Art will bring the mountains to Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Those peaks are the Himalayas, which will be celebrated tomorrow and Sunday in ''Expedition RMA'' not only for their region's art (the museum's focus), but also for its culture, its history and even its geography. Children can enjoy mountain-theme workshops, scavenger hunts, tours and games. And for the weekend's highlight, appropriately called ''A Peak Experience: The Ultimate Sleepover,'' the Rubin's spiral staircase will portray Mount Everest. Tomorrow those overnight campers -- 40 children ages 11 to 13 -- will ascend it, not the conventional way, but with mountaineering equipment and the guidance of seasoned climbers. (Above, participants in last year's sleepover.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The highest objects in New York City are usually skyscrapers. But if Manhattan cannot have mountains, this weekend the Rubin Museum of Art will bring the mountains to Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Those peaks are the Himalayas, which will be celebrated tomorrow and Sunday in ''Expedition RMA'' not only for their region's art (the museum's focus), but also for its culture, its history and even its geography. Children can enjoy mountain-theme workshops, scavenger hunts, tours and games. And for the weekend's highlight, appropriately called ''A Peak Experience: The Ultimate Sleepover,'' the Rubin's spiral staircase will portray Mount Everest. Tomorrow those overnight campers -- 40 children ages 11 to 13 -- will ascend it, not the conventional way, but with mountaineering equipment and the guidance of seasoned climbers. (Above, participants in last year's sleepover.)</p>
        <p>But even those not old enough for the after-hours sleepover, which has limited spaces, will experience a Himalayan atmosphere. ''We're going to have pitched in the colonnade a tent that's kitted up for base camp at Mount Everest,'' said Tim McHenry, the museum's producer. ''Kids can climb into it and try out the gear and the sleeping bags.''</p>
        <p>Children will also make their own mountains. Tomorrow they can create landscapes from flour, salt and water. On Sunday Dove Bradshaw, an artist participating in the museum's exhibition ''The Missing Peace,'' will help them design salt peaks similar to hers, which slowly dissolve from steady drips of vinegar. On Sunday the storyteller Ron Sopyla will take children on a narrative mountain journey with shadow puppets.</p>
        <p>The scavenger hunts, tomorrow only, will lead 3- to 9-year-olds to certain artworks. Both days will offer live Himalayan music, gallery tours (looking for mountains in art) and board games like bagchaal. ''Its pieces are 4 tigers and 21 goats,'' Mr. McHenry said. ''The tigers try to eat the goats, and the goats try to corner the tigers.''</p>
        <p>''Expedition RMA'' will conclude with another mountain adventure: the New York premiere of ''Team Everest: A Himalayan Journey,'' the film chronicle of the climber Gary Guller's trek for the disabled. Its goal was not the summit, but base camp. Mr. McHenry calls the documentary inspirational -- an adjective likely to describe the whole weekend. (From 11 a.m. to 6 p.m., 150 West 17th Street, Flatiron district, 212-620-5000, rmanyc.org. Activities free with museum admission except the sleepover, tomorrow at 7 p.m., $108, and the film, Sunday at 4 p.m., $15; both require reservations at Ext. 344. Their prices include museum admission: $10; $7 for students, 65+ and neighborhood residents; free for under 12.)</p>
        <p>LAUREL GRAEBER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
