<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Artificial Sweetener Rivals Renew a Heated Court Fight</title>
    <meta content="08sour" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/business/08sour.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852944"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sweeteners, Artificial</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Splenda (Sugar Substitute)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Equal (Sugar Substitute)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Slogans and Mottoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Misleading and Deceptive Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Merisant Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mcneil Nutritionals</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Browning, Lynnley</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sweetners, Artificial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sugar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Slogans and Mottoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Merisant Worldwide, Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2DB1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Artificial Sweetener Rivals Renew a Heated Court Fight</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Artificial Sweetener Rivals Renew a Heated Court Fight</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNNLEY BROWNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Browning, Lynnley</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Undisclosed settlement between makers of Equal and Splenda over Splenda's contested slogan of 'made from sugar, so it tastes like sugar' comes apart, prompting renewed fighting between two rival makers of artificial sweeteners; lawyers for Equal's maker, Merisant, file court papers accusing Splenda's maker, McNeil Nutritionals, of backing out of settlement reached May 11; Merisant asks federal judge to enforce settlement, which was reached hastily in her chambers moments after jury reached its verdict, or announce jury's decision (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sugar wars have a sour new chapter.</p>
        <p>A undisclosed settlement between the makers of Equal and Splenda over Splenda's contested slogan of ''made from sugar, so it tastes like sugar'' came apart yesterday, prompting renewed fighting between the two rival makers of artificial sweeteners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An undisclosed settlement between the makers of Equal and Splenda over Splenda’s contested slogan of “made from sugar, so it tastes like sugar” came apart Thursday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The sugar wars have a sour new chapter.</p>
        <p>A undisclosed settlement between the makers of Equal and Splenda over Splenda's contested slogan of ''made from sugar, so it tastes like sugar'' came apart yesterday, prompting renewed fighting between the two rival makers of artificial sweeteners.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for Equal's maker, Merisant, filed court papers yesterday accusing Splenda's maker, McNeil Nutritionals, of backing out of a settlement reached May 11.</p>
        <p>Merisant asked the federal district judge in Philadelphia who oversaw a five-week jury trial between the two rivals to do one of two things: enforce the settlement, which was reached hastily in her chambers moments after the jury reached its verdict, or announce the jury's decision.</p>
        <p>Because of the settlement, the verdict was never entered into the record and was not publicly disclosed.</p>
        <p>Merisant, in its court filings yesterday in Federal District Court in Philadelphia, suggested that the jury had found against Splenda's maker, McNeil, which is a unit of Johnson &amp; Johnson.</p>
        <p>''As reported in the press, that verdict found for Merisant on liability issues, concluding that McNeil's Splenda campaign was false and misleading,'' Merisant's filing yesterday said.</p>
        <p>McNeil took exception to the claim that it was backing out of the deal.</p>
        <p>''In reality, it is Merisant, not McNeil, that has violated the parties' settlement agreement,'' McNeil said in court papers filed late yesterday ''and it is Merisant, not McNeil, that refuses to comply with its terms.''</p>
        <p>The renewed fighting comes nearly four years after Merisant sued McNeil in federal court in Philadelphia in 2004, contending that McNeil had tricked millions of consumers by deliberately fostering the notion that Splenda was healthier and natural because it started out with sugar, even though the final product contained no sugar. Merisant had sought at least $176 million from McNeil.</p>
        <p>The renewal of the feud was apparently initiated by a full-page ad by Equal's maker that ran in USA Today on May 25. The ad trumpeted the undisclosed settlement and said ''Now Taste the Truth'' and offered $2 coupons for Equal products.</p>
        <p>In a sharply worded letter on May 29, lawyers for Splenda's maker told Equal's maker that they considered ''Merisant's decision to embark upon a publicity campaign concerning the settlement of the U.S. litigation to be a material breach of the parties' agreement.''</p>
        <p>In its court filings, Merisant responded by saying that ''McNeil has also denied the existence of a binding agreement between the parties.''</p>
        <p>To that, McNeil said that it was ''fully prepared to live up to the terms of the parties' settlement agreement, provided that Merisant does the same.''</p>
        <p>When asked yesterday whether McNeil was formally backing out of the settlement, a company spokeswoman, Julie Keenan, declined to elaborate. Merisant's lawyer declined to comment.</p>
        <p>When the settlement was reached on May 11, both companies released a brief joint statement saying that its details were confidential and that they would make no further comment.</p>
        <p>A lawyer specializing in false advertising claims said that it is not unusual that settlements like this fall apart. What is different in this case, the lawyer, Rochelle D. Alpert of Morgan Lewis &amp; Bockius, is that both sides seem to want the settlement enforced.</p>
        <p>''This is not a very typical situation -- more typical is when one party thinks there's a settlement and the other doesn't,'' Ms. Alpert said.</p>
        <p>Although the size of the settlement was never disclosed, Merisant appeared to indicate in a recent securities filing that the amount was in the range of $22 million to $31 million.</p>
        <p>Saying in its latest quarterly filing that it had cash and cash equivalents of $22.2 million as of March 31, Merisant said in the regulatory filing that ''we anticipate that our cash balance at June 30, 2007, will be 100 percent to 140 percent greater than the cash balance at March 31, 2007, as a result of a one-time cash payment to be received pursuant to an agreement with a third party.''</p>
        <p>The feud underscores the jockeying for leadership in the $1.5 billion artificial sweetener market.</p>
        <p>Since its mass introduction in 2000, Splenda, in the yellow packet, has overtaken the one-time industry leader Equal, in the blue packet, and now has nearly two-thirds of the artificial sweetener market in the United States. Splenda's main ingredient is a non-nutritive sweetener, sucralose, that is manufactured in laboratories.</p>
        <p>Although a sugar molecule is used in the process, sucralose is not the same thing as sucrose, the technical name for pure table sugar.</p>
        <p>Equal, also known as aspartame, has no sugar at all and has always been marketed as a wholly artificial sweetener.</p>
        <p>In its filing yesterday, Merisant also asked the judge, Gene E. K. Pratter, to award it interest and legal fees on top of the undisclosed settlement or verdict.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
