<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Key Arrest by Serbia, European Union Is to Reopen Talks</title>
    <meta content="08serbia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852916"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bosnia and Herzegovina</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wood, Nicholas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tolimir, Zdravko</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tadic, Boris (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DEFDC1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="582" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Key Arrest by Serbia, European Union Is to Reopen Talks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS WOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wood, Nicholas</byline>
      <dateline>BELGRADE, Serbia, June 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>European Union says it would resume negotiations with Serbia on agreement that is first stop toward possible membership, just one week after arrest and transfer of leading Bosnian Serb war crimes suspect Zdravko Tolimir to United Nations war crimes tribunal in The Hague; it is seen as victory for Serbia's reformist president Boris Tadic (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The European Union said Thursday that it would resume negotiations with Serbia next week on an agreement that is the first step toward possible membership in the bloc.</p>
        <p>The announcement was made a week after the arrest and transfer of a leading Bosnian Serb war crimes suspect to the United Nations war crimes tribunal in The Hague, and it was seen as a victory for Boris Tadic, Serbia's reformist president, who is supported by the United States and the European Union.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The European Union said Thursday that it would resume negotiations with Serbia next week on an agreement that is the first step toward possible membership in the bloc.</p>
        <p>The announcement was made a week after the arrest and transfer of a leading Bosnian Serb war crimes suspect to the United Nations war crimes tribunal in The Hague, and it was seen as a victory for Boris Tadic, Serbia's reformist president, who is supported by the United States and the European Union.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday the tribunal's chief prosecutor, Carla Del Ponte, said during a visit to Belgrade that she believed that the government was fully committed to cooperating, and she praised the arrest and transfer of the Bosnian Serb suspect, Gen. Zdravko Tolimir. She said Serbia would arrest General Tolimir's former boss, Ratko Mladic, the commander of the Bosnian Serb army during the 1992-95 war in Bosnia, ''within months.''</p>
        <p>The European Union has made full cooperation with the tribunal a condition for closer ties. The two senior Bosnian Serb wartime leaders are still at large and are the tribunal's most-wanted suspects: General Mladic and Radovan Karadzic, the wartime leader of the Bosnian Serb government.</p>
        <p>Just weeks ago, Serbia's hopes of resuming negotiations with the European Union seemed faint. The conservative prime minister, Vojislav Kostunica, had been accused by the Union of blocking cooperation with the tribunal. And for a brief moment in May, Mr. Kostunica's party seemed on the verge of forming a coalition with the nationalist Serbian Radical Party, which is opposed to the arrest of war crimes suspects and favors closer ties to Russia rather than to the European Union.</p>
        <p>Instead, Mr. Kostunica's party formed a coalition with President Tadic's Democratic Party. Together with the arrest of General Tolimir, the shift in Serbia's political scene helped open the door for the renewal of talks, officials said.</p>
        <p>A statement on Thursday by the European Union's expansion commissioner, Olli Rehn, said talks would resume next Wednesday on a ''stabilization and association agreement,'' the first step in the process. Such an agreement would bring ''concrete trade and economic benefits'' for Serbia, he said.</p>
        <p>In an interview on Wednesday, Ms. Del Ponte said Mr. Kostunica had told her that cooperation with the tribunal was one of his government's main priorities and that the key to tracking down General Mladic was General Tolimir's arrest.</p>
        <p>But many commentators here appear skeptical about what seemed to be Mr. Kostunica's change of heart, and say cooperation with the tribunal is more a reflection of his determination to stay in power than a new commitment to the court. In return for cooperation with the court, President Tadic's party, which wants closer ties with the European Union, agreed that Mr. Kostunica could remain as prime minister.</p>
        <p>''He is the master of the slow political game,'' Sasa Mirkovic, the general manager of B92, a television and radio network that is frequently critical of Mr. Kostunica, said of the prime minister. ''When you think he is lost, he finds a strange exit.''</p>
        <p>Media commentators also said Mr. Kostunica's priority was to ensure that Kosovo remained within Serbia and that cooperation with The Hague and the West could easily fall victim to his strategy to retain the province.</p>
        <p>The United States and the European Union support a United Nations plan under which the Union would supervise Kosovo's independence for a limited period. The issue is a central one being discussed this week at the Group of 8 meeting near Rostock, Germany.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
