<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Relying on a Rape Confession, True or False</title>
    <meta content="08abuse" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/nyregion/08abuse.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852978"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Confessions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E3DA1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="972" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Relying on a Rape Confession, True or False</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Child Rape Trial Relies on Confession, True or False</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELLEN BARRY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the videotape began to play in a Queens courtroom this week, the jurors sat spellbound. For nearly half an hour, they watched as a day care worker named Khemwatie Bedessie described the sequence of events that she said led her to have sexual intercourse with a 4-year-old boy.</p>
        <p>They had already listened to hours of testimony regarding the allegations against Ms. Bedessie, 38, but her confession stood out. In her statement, she implied that the boy had aroused her. She appeared detached, almost perplexed at her own behavior; as she finished, two male jurors covered their faces with their hands.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A woman’s confession on videotape is both the centerpiece and target in a child rape case in Queens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the videotape began to play in a Queens courtroom this week, the jurors sat spellbound. For nearly half an hour, they watched as a day care worker named Khemwatie Bedessie described the sequence of events that she said led her to have sexual intercourse with a 4-year-old boy.</p>
        <p>They had already listened to hours of testimony regarding the allegations against Ms. Bedessie, 38, but her confession stood out. In her statement, she implied that the boy had aroused her. She appeared detached, almost perplexed at her own behavior; as she finished, two male jurors covered their faces with their hands.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Ms. Bedessie's lawyer, Stephen Turano, turned to the same jury and began to make his case that the confession they had seen -- a centerpiece of the prosecutors' case -- was a false one brought about by stress and coercion.</p>
        <p>Earlier, Justice Michael B. Aloise of State Supreme Court had refused to allow testimony by a sociologist who frequently testifies about false confessions. Expert testimony of this kind is relevant, the judge said, only ''when there is little or no corroborating testimony'' pointing to the defendant's guilt.</p>
        <p>''In this case,'' Justice Aloise said, ''the court concluded that there was ample corroboration, if believed.''</p>
        <p>Whether the defense's argument could sway the jury in Ms. Bedessie's case, which could begin deliberations early next week, is not clear. But Mr. Turano's defense falls into shifting legal territory: Overturned convictions, like those of the five men convicted of rape in the 1989 Central Park jogger case, have provided ample evidence that innocent people will confess to crimes under pressure. But judges still differ on whether to present this evidence to juries.</p>
        <p>The law gives judges broad discretion over which experts to present to juries, said Yale Kamisar, a professor of law at the University of San Diego. But confessions, he added, deserve particular scrutiny because they often determine the outcome of a trial.</p>
        <p>''Many jurors are never satisfied unless there is a confession,'' he said. ''If they haven't got a confession, they're always going to wonder whether this guy did it.''</p>
        <p>The case began in February 2006 when the 4-year-old complained of an itch to his mother, who asked whether someone had touched his genitals.</p>
        <p>He then described inappropriate contact with ''Miss Anita,'' as he called Ms. Bedessie. His mother testified that she was panic-stricken, and immediately took him to Jamaica Hospital Medical Center to be examined.</p>
        <p>Ten days later, a detective approached Ms. Bedessie at Veda's Learning World in Richmond Hill, where she worked as a teacher's aide. Detective Ivan Borbon interviewed her at 10:30 that morning at the Special Victims Unit, where, he testified, she ''looked me in the eye,'' appearing ''very nervous,'' and confessed to molesting the boy. Two and a half hours later, with a prosecutor in the room, the taped confession was made.</p>
        <p>On the tape, she said that the boy had touched her breasts and that the contact had caused her to ''react emotionally.'' She described three occasions where she either fondled him or had intercourse with him. After the final episode, she told him not to tell anyone.</p>
        <p>''Yes, I felt bad about it,'' she said. ''I don't know how it came about. I felt somebody was doing it with the child, because I felt he was doing it before.''</p>
        <p>Afterward, she added, ''I couldn't sleep, because he kept coming back to me. I got my old memories back so I can't help myself when it happened.''</p>
        <p>Detective Borbon said Ms. Bedessie offered the statements readily.</p>
        <p>''She said she felt better getting it off her chest,'' he said. ''She had difficulty understanding what she had done to this child.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Turano has argued otherwise. During the three hours before the tape was made, he said, Ms. Bedessie was coerced and intimidated in various ways. He said she was told that, if she confessed, she would be given counseling and released, and that the alternative was to be imprisoned at Rikers Island, where she would be brutalized by the other inmates.</p>
        <p>Under cross-examination by Mr. Turano, Detective Borbon testified that Ms. Bedessie's statement was voluntary and spontaneous. ''You can dance with this all you want, counselor, but the bottom line is, she made a statement,'' he said. He also said, in response to Dianna Megias, an assistant district attorney, that Ms. Bedessie's confession was not false. ''Those were her words,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Turano said the expert, Richard Ofshe, a professor emeritus at the University of California, Berkeley, would help jurors accept that an innocent person might give a confession like the one that they witnessed if they were promised they would then be released.</p>
        <p>''It's very difficult to believe that someone's will can be overcome by verbal tactics, but the fact of the matter is that it occurs,'' Mr. Turano said. ''It is conduct that people do engage in, and I think it is outside the ken of a normal jury.''</p>
        <p>He said a tape of the whole three-hour interaction between the detective and Ms. Bedessie would be far more useful than the half-hour captured on videotape. ''The truth lies in the process, not the product,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bedessie is expected to testify on Monday, before the case goes to the jury. If convicted of rape and the other charges against her, she faces up to 25 years in prison.</p>
        <p>The issue of false confessions has played out differently in other New York courts. In September 2005, a Nassau County judge, Victor M. Ort, ordered a pretrial hearing to test the scientific community's acceptance of research on false confessions. He concluded, in a ruling, that ''jurors may be expected to assume that an innocent person will not confess to a crime he did not commit,'' so research on the subject should be explained to them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
