<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Small Law Firms Find Strength in Numbers</title>
    <meta content="08law" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/business/08law.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070615T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1852904"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="STREET SCENE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Network of Boutique Law Firms</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Donovan, Karen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spielvogel, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Small Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Small Business</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Sullivan &amp; Cromwell</org>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Pennsylvania</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E2DC1F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Small Law Firms Find Strength in Numbers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Some Small Law Firms Find Strength in Numbers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN DONOVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Donovan, Karen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>40-year-old Steven Spielvogel has</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Steven Spielvogel, a lanky 40-year-old lawyer who, with his angular looks and jet black hair, resembles Ric Ocasek of the 1980s band the Cars, has been on something of a tour of his own.</p>
        <p>He has been promoting a network that connects small law firms around the country and the world. The idea is to give the better small law firms a way to compete with the big national and global firms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Small boutique law firms often lack the brand name of their larger counterparts. But some hope a new network will give them additional credibility.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Steven Spielvogel, a lanky 40-year-old lawyer who, with his angular looks and jet black hair, resembles Ric Ocasek of the 1980s band the Cars, has been on something of a tour of his own.</p>
        <p>He has been promoting a network that connects small law firms around the country and the world. The idea is to give the better small law firms a way to compete with the big national and global firms.</p>
        <p>Since starting the International Network of Boutique Law Firms, in 2004, Mr. Spielvogel has been knocking on doors and setting up lunches to persuade the lawyers at small firms with prestigious résumés to start a local chapter</p>
        <p>''The network is designed to supplement pre-existing legal relationships,'' he said. ''It's not about paying a fee to get listed in a directory: the standards are very rigorous and you can feel a certain level of comfort.''</p>
        <p>The network so far has 250 law firms as members, and 16 international strategic partners, including Bolivia's oldest law firm and Mexico's oldest and largest firm.</p>
        <p>While the small boutique law firms lack the brand name of a big law firm like Cravath, Swaine &amp; Moore or Sullivan &amp; Cromwell, they hope that their membership -- at an annual fee of $1,500 -- will give them additional prominence and credibility.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spielvogel has been particular about which small firms are invited to join.</p>
        <p>''Steven is the ultimate c.v. snob when it comes to the vetting process,'' said Edward R. Gallion, a law partner with Mr. Spielvogel in New York.</p>
        <p>Charles Kagay of the law firm of Spiegel Liao &amp; Kagay in San Francisco, who is president of his city's chapter of the network, said that finding a lawyer in another city often meant ''making calls all over the nation.'' But thanks to the network, he said, Mr. Kagay has recently been hired for a litigation matter, a result of a single phone call from the president of a chapter in Texas.</p>
        <p>''On a practical level, it is very informal and very simple,'' Mr. Kagay said. ''You have somebody who you have confidence in to begin with, because they have been vetted by somebody persnickety. And chances are, I have even met them. It's something like a virtual law firm.''</p>
        <p>The effort mirrors the trend at big law firms in the last two decades to seek a broader scope and a greater national presence through mergers with other big firms. But the small boutique law firms -- those that specialize in one thing -- continue to thrive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spielvogel's venture aims to provide options to those lawyers who have decided against spending their days grinding out billable hours on a large firm's time sheet.</p>
        <p>To do that, Mr. Spielvogel, who was in a band, E-Chaos, while at the University of Pennsylvania Law School in the early 1990s, learned a valuable lesson from his time at Sullivan &amp; Cromwell, where he was a midlevel associate for two years.</p>
        <p>''When I carried a Sullivan &amp; Cromwell litigation bag and it said S.&amp; C. on it, it was a reputable presumption that you were an amazing lawyer and brilliant,'' he said. ''And I am hoping that the I.N.B.L.F. imprimatur will similarly create a reputable presumption for all I.N.B.L.F.-approved attorneys.''</p>
        <p>Typically, when a law firm seeks outside counsel, it agrees to pay a referral fee. The boutique network forbids the payment of such referral fees.</p>
        <p>The network's various chapters have a president, selected by Mr. Spielvogel. And each chapter has one firm in each of various specialties -- whether it is tax law or litigation or corporate transactions -- so that the local firms do not fight over the referral business.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spielvogel began working at a boutique operation when Mr. Gallion, once his mentor at Sullivan &amp; Cromwell, recruited him to join a firm that Mr. Gallion had founded along with another former Sullivan &amp; Cromwell lawyer.</p>
        <p>''As small-business men, we bring to bear a sense of the cost-benefit analysis to client work that a midlevel or senior level at Paul, Weiss does not,'' Mr. Gallion said.</p>
        <p>STREET SCENE</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 15, 2007, Friday  An article on the Street Scene page in Business Day last Friday about the International Network of Boutique Law Firms rendered incorrectly a word in a quotation from the founder of the organization, Steven Spielvogel, who commented on his experiences as an associate at Sullivan &amp; Cromwell. He said, ''When I carried a Sullivan &amp; Cromwell litigation bag and it said S.&amp;C. on it, it was a rebuttable presumption that you were an amazing lawyer and brilliant'' -- not a ''reputable'' presumption.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 15, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>An article on the Street Scene page in Business Day last Friday about the International Network of Boutique Law Firms rendered incorrectly a word in a quotation from the founder of the organization, Steven Spielvogel, who commented on his experiences as an associate at Sullivan &amp; Cromwell. He said, ''When I carried a Sullivan &amp; Cromwell litigation bag and it said S.&amp;C. on it, it was a rebuttable presumption that you were an amazing lawyer and brilliant'' -- not a ''reputable'' presumption.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
