<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wie Endures a Rough Week and First Round</title>
    <meta content="08lpga" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/sports/golf/08lpga.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853027"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ladies Professional Golf Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wie, Michelle</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E4D91F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="928" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wie Endures a Rough Week and First Round</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Wie Endures a Rough Week and First Round</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <dateline>HAVRE DE GRACE, Md., June 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was obvious from the start, when Michelle Wie took aim at her first fairway of this L.P.G.A. Championship with a 3-wood in her hands, that she was not the same golfer who contended for the title here last year.</p>
        <p>Wie is known for her length off the tee, but during her opening round of one-over-par 73 Thursday her driver never left her bag. It was a sure sign that Wie was intent on completing her loop around the Bulle Rock Golf Course without doing any more damage to her injured wrists or her reputation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was obvious from the start, when Michelle Wie took aim at her first fairway of this L.P.G.A. Championship, that she was not the same golfer as last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was obvious from the start, when Michelle Wie took aim at her first fairway of this L.P.G.A. Championship with a 3-wood in her hands, that she was not the same golfer who contended for the title here last year.</p>
        <p>Wie is known for her length off the tee, but during her opening round of one-over-par 73 Thursday her driver never left her bag. It was a sure sign that Wie was intent on completing her loop around the Bulle Rock Golf Course without doing any more damage to her injured wrists or her reputation.</p>
        <p>''She's definitely not firing on eight cylinders,'' said Wie's swing coach, David Leadbetter, who followed her from outside the gallery ropes, craning his neck to follow the path of some shots and chewing on his fingernails between others. ''It's like owning a Ferrari and not getting out of second gear.''</p>
        <p>The threesome featuring Wie and two South Koreans, Song-Hee Kim and Na Ri Kim, was the last one of the day to start off the No. 10 tee and commanded the largest gallery. Fans no doubt were curious to see whether Wie would spin out, as she did last week, or race ahead, the way she used to do before running out of gas last summer.</p>
        <p>There was reason to wonder. It was Wie's second tournament since returning to competitive golf after being sidelined for four months with wrist injuries and her first tournament round since withdrawing from the Ginn Tribute last week after playing the first 16 holes of her opening round in 14 over par.</p>
        <p>It had been a trying week for the 17-year-old Wie even before she left her first and second shots in the rough on the par-5 15th -- her sixth hole -- and two-putted for a double bogey that left her four over par.</p>
        <p>Her pro-am playing partners complained to Tour officials after Monday's round that she seemed uninterested in interacting with them. On Tuesday, Annika Sorenstam, a Hall of Fame member and the nearest thing the Tour has to a queen mother, chastised Wie for withdrawing with an injury from the Ginn Tribute -- for which Sorenstam happened to be host -- and then showing up here two days later to play a practice round.</p>
        <p>On top of that, Wie, who will be a freshman at Stanford in the fall, completed her college housing application and then somehow deleted the 4,000-word document when she tried to send it.</p>
        <p>''She was a little perturbed about that,'' Leadbetter said wryly, adding, ''But I think it sort of took a little from the stress she had here.''</p>
        <p>Wie wished she could have erased the 7 on No. 15 from her scorecard. It was the perfect example of how her wrist injuries have had an effect on her game. Using a driver off the tee, she normally can reach the green on the 493-yard hole in two.</p>
        <p>Opting to stay with her 3-wood, Wie hit a shot that landed 40 yards to the right of the fairway, in thick rough. It was a continuation of the same faulty swing mechanics that plagued her during her round at the Ginn, which included a 10 on one hole.</p>
        <p>She failed to clear the thick rough with her second shot. After a well- struck third shot, she summoned a rules official and asked for, and received, permission to have a Tour trainer massage her left wrist, which she fractured when she fell during a training run this past winter. (She has also been plagued by tendinitis in her right wrist.)</p>
        <p>Wie's fourth shot flew the green. Her chip landed nine feet short of the pin and she two-putted.</p>
        <p>It was a queasy moment for the golfer long ago dubbed The Big Wiesy in homage to her fluid swing. But Wie fought back, making three birdies in a four-hole stretch in the middle of her round.</p>
        <p>She finished the round six strokes behind the leaders, Kim Saiki-Maloney, Angela Park and Birdie Kim. But at least she finished.</p>
        <p>''I actually had some really good shots and built a lot of confidence off of them,'' said Wie, who tied for fifth here last year and was second in 2005.</p>
        <p>Leadbetter said there had been some discussion about whether she should play this week.</p>
        <p>He said Wie's parents, Bo and B. J., ultimately left the decision up to her.</p>
        <p>''She's a fighter,'' Leadbetter said. ''That's one thing about Michelle.'' He added: ''In theory, she probably shouldn't be playing. These tournaments have really come about a month too early, in my opinion.''</p>
        <p>Some people are wondering if Wie's success, and the celebrity that came with it, has not been a little too much, too soon.</p>
        <p>''I can't imagine being 16 and 17 and being in the spotlight that she's in right now,'' said Carolyn Bivens, the L.P.G.A. commissioner.</p>
        <p>An hour before Wie teed off Thursday Bivens was in the interview room, sitting in the chair where players routinely sit and go through their rounds, hole by hole, and she dissected Wie's week, point by point.</p>
        <p>She said nobody affiliated with the L.P.G.A. encouraged Wie to withdraw last week to avoid triggering the 88 rule, which prevents nonmembers on the Tour from receiving any sponsor exemptions for the rest of the year if they post a round of 88 or higher.</p>
        <p>''I think that leaving the tournament and coming to practice when one had pulled out with a wrist injury was not very respectful,'' Bivens said, ''and that's what Annika and what some of the other members are responding to.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
