<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Part Coach, Part Motivator And 100 Percent Welcomed</title>
    <meta content="08clemens" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/sports/08clemens.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853032"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Clemens, Roger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E3D91F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Part Coach, Part Motivator And 100 Percent Welcomed</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Part Coach, Part Motivator and 100 Percent Welcomed</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, June 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tyler Clippard had just earned his first major league victory when a call came for him on the cellphone of a Yankees staff member. Clippard, 22, was in the visitors' clubhouse at Shea Stadium, and the pitcher with more victories than anyone alive wanted to talk to him. Roger Clemens was on the line.</p>
        <p>''He called to congratulate me, which was unbelievable,'' Clippard said. ''He seemed like such a nice guy. He said he really wanted to work with the young guys, which is something I'm definitely looking forward to.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Roger Clemens is scheduled to start tomorrow, and the Yankees are looking forward to the whole package he offers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tyler Clippard had just earned his first major league victory when a call came for him on the cellphone of a Yankees staff member. Clippard, 22, was in the visitors' clubhouse at Shea Stadium, and the pitcher with more victories than anyone alive wanted to talk to him. Roger Clemens was on the line.</p>
        <p>''He called to congratulate me, which was unbelievable,'' Clippard said. ''He seemed like such a nice guy. He said he really wanted to work with the young guys, which is something I'm definitely looking forward to.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees are looking forward to the whole package Clemens offers: the outsized gunslinger who sees himself as part coach and part motivational speaker, beyond his role as a $28 million ace.</p>
        <p>Clemens is scheduled to start tomorrow against the Pittsburgh Pirates at Yankee Stadium, his first game for the Yankees since the 2003 World Series. It is an eagerly awaited debut from a performer who knows how to make a grand entrance, introducing himself to the Stadium crowd from the owner's box above home plate on May 6.</p>
        <p>''He's probably going to be sky-high on Saturday, anyway,'' Manager Joe Torre said. But with the Yankees playing better lately, Torre added, ''He can fall in line and be one of the guys as opposed to being the one guy to maybe change things and turn things around. Because I don't care how long you've been playing, it's still a lot to put on one guy.''</p>
        <p>Clemens will earn about $17.4 million from the Yankees, based on the prorated portion of his salary. He has been teammates with six current Yankees, and a curiosity to the others.</p>
        <p>Derek Jeter stayed in touch during Clemens's three seasons with the Astros and hounded him to return. Jeter came to regard Clemens as a friend, something he never expected when Clemens pitched for Boston and Toronto.</p>
        <p>''I like him,'' Jeter said. ''I didn't like him when I played against him -- not at all.''</p>
        <p>Yankees first baseman Josh Phelps knows the feeling. On Aug. 29, 2002, when Phelps was a rookie for the Toronto Blue Jays, he hit two home runs to beat Clemens at the Skydome. The next season, on opening day in Toronto, Phelps came up against Clemens in the first inning with two on and two out.</p>
        <p>''I'm coming up, thinking, all right, first at-bat of the year, runner in scoring position, great,'' Phelps said.</p>
        <p>It did not occur to Phelps that Clemens would still be thinking about those home runs from seven months before. But Clemens drilled him in the back, then struck out Eric Hinske to end the inning.</p>
        <p>''I was surprised, more than anything else,'' Phelps said. ''If he held onto it for that long, maybe it was a sign of respect. I never asked him about it. I don't get into that.''</p>
        <p>Clemens is joining a rotation that included two former teammates -- Andy Pettitte and Mike Mussina -- plus Clippard and Chien-Ming Wang, who is pitching like a No. 1 starter again, with a 4-1 record and a 2.50 earned run average over his past five starts.</p>
        <p>When Wang was growing up in Taiwan, he said, few baseball games were shown on television. But Wang was a hard-throwing right-handed pitcher, and he knew who Clemens was. He was the pitcher Wang wanted to be.</p>
        <p>Asked what he admired about Clemens, Wang thought for a bit and tried to explain. ''He trusts himself,'' said Wang, whose English is limited. He struggled to find more words, and then tapped his chest, for emphasis.</p>
        <p>Wang has never met Clemens, somehow missing his appearances at Legends Field in March and at Yankee Stadium in May. But Wang, who has been trying to diversify his repertory, said he wanted to ask Clemens how to throw a splitter.</p>
        <p>Reliever Sean Henn was with Class AAA Scranton/Wilkes-Barre when Clemens pitched there in his final minor league tuneup May 28. Around 6 p.m., Henn said, Clemens called a team meeting in the clubhouse.</p>
        <p>''He walked in and he was just drenched, like he had just got done working out for an hour,'' Henn said. ''I thought it was funny, because he had a start, and he had to be out in like 30 minutes for that. And he was just soaked.''</p>
        <p>Henn said the players expected Clemens to off-handedly apologize for causing a news media circus, and to go about his pregame routine. But Clemens was serious about sharing his wisdom with the prospects.</p>
        <p>''He told us to believe in our ability,'' Henn said. ''He said, 'Everybody in here's got the tools and the talent to be a major league ballplayer. It's just finding a routine that works and sticking with it and being more consistent.' ''</p>
        <p>One of the Yankees' coaches has seen that firsthand. Tony Peña, the first-base coach, was Clemens's catcher in Boston from 1990 through 1993, a period that included Clemens's third Cy Young award season, in 1991, and the year Clemens has said he considered the best of his career, 1990, when he went 21-6 with a 1.93 E.R.A.</p>
        <p>''He's a winner in everything he does,'' Peña said. ''When he's pitching, it's him against everybody. He's the type of guy, he promises himself that when he does bad, he needs to do extra work to correct that. He's a warrior.''</p>
        <p>Peña caught 1,950 games in his career, the fifth most in major league history. Asked if anyone else could compare to Clemens, Peña smiled and shook his head.</p>
        <p>''No,'' Peña said. ''He's one of a kind.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
