<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Phillies Rally Against Wagner, and Sweep Mets</title>
    <meta content="08mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/sports/08mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853034"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Philadelphia Phillies</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Chavez, Endy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE3D91F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Phillies Rally Against Wagner, and Sweep Mets</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Phillies Rally Against Wagner, and Sweep Mets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID PICKER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A fan seated behind the Mets' dugout held up a bright orange sign with black lettering during the top of the sixth inning yesterday that read, ''We believe.''</p>
        <p>But the faith of Mets fans may soon be tested.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets dropped their fourth consecutive game last night, a 6-3 defeat in 10 innings against the Philadelphia Phillies at Shea Stadium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A fan seated behind the Mets' dugout held up a bright orange sign with black lettering during the top of the sixth inning yesterday that read, ''We believe.''</p>
        <p>But the faith of Mets fans may soon be tested.</p>
        <p>The Mets dropped their fourth consecutive game last night, a 6-3 defeat in 10 innings against the Philadelphia Phillies at Shea Stadium. It is their longest losing streak of the season.</p>
        <p>''We didn't play well this series,'' catcher Paul Lo Duca said. ''They played well, and that's all that mattered. We had chances.''</p>
        <p>The Mets were swept in a series for the first time this season after they lost a 3-2 lead in the ninth inning when Billy Wagner allowed a bases-empty home run to Pat Burrell. The Phillies scored three runs in the 10th inning.</p>
        <p>The Mets' bullpen has been an asset throughout the season. But it struggled in this three-game series. Scott Schoeneweis allowed a run-scoring double to Chase Utley in the 10th inning, and Aaron Rowand and Burrell gave the Phillies some insurance with run-scoring hits against Joe Smith, who replaced Schoeneweis.</p>
        <p>For the fifth time in their past six games, the Mets failed to score more than three runs. They are now 17-16 at Shea.</p>
        <p>''The offense needs to do a better job scoring,'' David Wright said.</p>
        <p>But what might be most troubling for Mets fans was the array of injuries that could threaten the Mets' lead atop the National League East, which stood at three and a half games over the Atlanta Braves.</p>
        <p>Endy Chávez, who was injured while running to first base in the seventh inning of Wednesday's 4-2 loss to the Phillies, was placed on the 15-day disabled list after a magnetic resonance imaging test revealed a strained left hamstring. He was expected to miss at least four weeks.</p>
        <p>Chàvez, the Mets' top backup outfielder, had been playing every day since the Mets lost left fielder Moises Alou to a strained left quadriceps on May 12. Right fielder Shawn Green has been sidelined with a broken right foot since May 26. When Carlos Beltrán bruised his right knee last week, the Mets played with an outfield of backups.</p>
        <p>Manager Willie Randolph said that his players might be pressing at the plate to compensate for the injuries.</p>
        <p>''Overanxiousness just has to do with sometimes trying too hard,'' Randolph said. ''But we have too good of a lineup to try and take that approach. We do that sometimes.''</p>
        <p>José Valentín, who had been out since April 29 with a partially torn ligament in his right knee, was activated yesterday and started. He will play with a brace for the rest of the season, and he said that he would need surgery if he were to play next year.</p>
        <p>Valentín went 1 for 4 last night, with a single in the fifth inning. The Mets trailed, 2-0, at that point, after Jimmy Rollins's run-scoring single in the third inning and Ryan Howard's run-scoring single in the sixth. Both of those runs came against starter John Maine, who allowed six hits, struck out two and walked none over seven innings.</p>
        <p>The Mets took the lead when Carlos Delgado, Wright and Lo Duca hit successive home runs with two out in the sixth against Cole Hamels, the Phillies' starter.</p>
        <p>Wright's shot, which appeared to hit off a yellow sign just above the fence in left-center field, was not initially ruled a home run, and Wright stopped at third base. After Randolph requested that the play be overturned, the umpires had a conference and ruled it a home run. Phillies Manager Charlie Manuel then made his own protest and was ejected after arguing with the first-base umpire, Jerry Lane.</p>
        <p>It was the first time the Mets had three consecutive home runs since April 17, 1989, also against the Phillies. Those home runs were hit by Darryl Strawberry, Kevin McReynolds and Keith Hernandez.</p>
        <p>Last night the fans cheered as each player crossed home plate. But if the Mets continue to endure injuries, there will be little to cheer.</p>
        <p>The Mets have recently used Damion Easley, David Newhan, Ben Johnson and Carlos Gómez in the outfield. Johnson started in left and Gómez in right last night, and Easley was used as a pinch hitter in the seventh inning after a magnetic resonance imaging test on his sore right knee was negative.</p>
        <p>Lastings Milledge would have been an option in the outfield. But he, too, is injured. Milledge, who has been in the minors for most of the season, has been out for more than five weeks with a sprained ligament in his right foot. The Mets expect him to begin running again by next week.</p>
        <p>General Manager Omar Minaya said the Mets were not planning on trading for help in the outfield. Minaya said Green was aiming to return Sunday, when the Mets are in Detroit for a series that begins today. He could not say the same for Alou, who was frustrated by the lingering injury.</p>
        <p>After the game, the Mets who were healthy were already looking ahead.</p>
        <p>''Forget about what happened here,'' Beltrán said. ''Try to go to Detroit and win.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The Mets selected Eddie Kunz with their first selection, 42nd over all, in the 2007 first-year player draft yesterday. Kunz, a 6-foot-5 right-handed reliever, was 3-1 with 10 saves for Oregon State this season. Kunz, who throws a changeup, slider and two-seam fastball, helped the Beavers win a national championship last season. With the 47th overall pick in the draft, the Mets took Nathan Vineyard, a 6-foot-3 left-handed pitcher from Woodland High School in Cartersville, Ga. Vineyard was 8-2 with a 0.84 earned run average in 10 games this season. The Mets also selected Scott Moviel, a right-handed pitcher from St. Edward High School in Lakewood, Ohio (77th overall pick); Brant Rustich, a right-handed pitcher from U.C.L.A. (93rd); Eric Niesen, a left-handed pitcher from Wake Forest (99th); Stephen Clyne, a right-handed pitcher from Clemson (123rd); Richard Lucas, a third baseman from Wolfson Senior High School in Jacksonville, Fla. (153rd); and Zach Lutz, a third baseman from Alvernia College in Pennsylvania (183rd).</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
