<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Setback Aside, James Transcends His Generation</title>
    <meta content="08araton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853037"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E2D91F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="962" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Setback Aside, James Transcends His Generation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <dateline>SAN ANTONIO</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the promotional sake of a weighty occasion, LeBron James is supposed to be new school to Tim Duncan's old school. Except James went to no school after high school and has already proved to be adept at schooling teammates, opponents and especially his critics.</p>
        <p>There is little about James that looks his age. Facially, physically and fundamentally, he's more the recently anointed boys' dean of the Eastern Conference than the 22-year-old N.B.A. finals neophyte who could barely make a shot last night in his debut on professional basketball's grandest stage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the promotional sake of a weighty occasion, LeBron James is supposed to be new school to Tim Duncan's old school. Except James went to no school after high school and has already proved to be adept at schooling teammates, opponents and especially his critics.</p>
        <p>There is little about James that looks his age. Facially, physically and fundamentally, he's more the recently anointed boys' dean of the Eastern Conference than the 22-year-old N.B.A. finals neophyte who could barely make a shot last night in his debut on professional basketball's grandest stage.</p>
        <p>It happens to the best of them. San Antonio's Bruce Bowen is one of the premier defenders, with smart, selfless players all around to help. Behind the dominant Duncan and Tony Parker, the favored Spurs crowded James and pulled away from the Cavaliers in the third quarter, taking Game 1, 85-76.</p>
        <p>James still has plenty of time to leave his mark on the series. If the Eastern Conference final, a fourth-quarter run led by James last night and the testimony of Cavs Coach Mike Brown suggest anything, it is that James is a fast, adaptive learner who views failure as an aberration.</p>
        <p>''He's pretty patient,'' Brown said after the two defensive-minded teams slogged out of the gate and made viewers pause to reflect on the unfortunate fate of the Phoenix Suns. ''He'll read, read, read. I don't think I've ever seen him flustered or rattled after a game like this.''</p>
        <p>Seems like yesterday that we were hearing similar sentiments expressed about Duncan as he hit throwback bank shots and was the most valuable player at 23 in his first finals, against the Knicks, in 1999. Duncan had four years' experience at Wake Forest and was never a chosen one of the shoe-company subculture that has its financial benefits but can blind a young player when his eyes should be open wide. James arrived as a teenager, a virtual Nike cartoon, but astute basketball people could see past the hype and the hops, to a more Duncanesque core.</p>
        <p>''LeBron rebounds, passes, he's unselfish,'' said P. J. Carlesimo, the Spurs' assistant coach. ''He could have played 30 or 40 years ago with no problem whatsoever. If you forget that and you take the dunks out, he's really an old-school player, just like Tim, who I think is the consummate old-school player.''</p>
        <p>Let me say that I think the old-school/new-school dichotomy occasionally over-glorifies the past by people who tend to live in it. Magic Johnson and Larry Bird defined the golden 1980s, but as one who spent a fair amount of time trying to make sense of Knicks teams fronted by Ray Williams and Micheal Ray Richardson, let me vouch for the fact that the knucklehead quotient was not insignificant back then, or during the Michael Jordan-dominated 1990s.</p>
        <p>Every generation produces talented players who get it and others who don't, regardless of how many championship rings they have.</p>
        <p>Kobe Bryant has won three titles but never learned to peacefully coexist with Shaquille O'Neal or his organization at large. Kevin Garnett, like Bryant a preps-to-pros long jumper, hasn't made it to the finals in a dozen pro seasons, but his commitment to the team has always been beyond reproach.</p>
        <p>This is what you see in James's body language on court, what you hear from those on the receiving end of his brilliant passes. For that reason, how could those who roasted James for passing the ball to an open Donyell Marshall at the climax of Game 1 of the conference final against Detroit not understand that the decision, far from a dereliction of duty, was true to an overriding philosophy?</p>
        <p>Some superstars, Bryant to name one, Allen Iverson to name another, approach the game believing the outcome has to be primarily about them, and they were often right. But how far can such rigid doctrine go when the sport, more than anything, pays homage to improvisational genius?</p>
        <p>As the Lithuanian center Zydrunas Ilgauskus said of James, ''He realizes that to win the big one, he's going to need his teammates.''</p>
        <p>To pull off what would be a stunning upset against what Commissioner David Stern last night called ''the team of the decade,'' the Cavaliers will also require much more from James, who finished Game 1 with 14 points and 4 assists, and shot 4 of 16 from the field. Being matched up on Parker, who penetrated at will, didn't help. Through it all, James resisted losing control, blaming teammates or forgetting they were on the court with him.</p>
        <p>There is no question that he is a good teammate, like Duncan. ''I've watched him for five years on the bench and two years when I was doing TV here,'' Carlesimo said. ''He's the best teammate I've ever seen.''</p>
        <p>It's a process that is best observed over time. But James showed it in Game 6 of the Detroit series, not forcing the issue with the finals beckoning, giving the rookie Daniel Gibson the space to erupt for 31 points -- 48 hours after James's 48-point masterpiece in Game 5 drew Jordan comparisons from all over.</p>
        <p>Those last two Detroit games were a classic microcosm in versatility and maturity, maybe the most astonishing performance we've seen from a player so young since a 20-year-old rookie named Magic in 1980.</p>
        <p>Compared to Johnson, James, in his fourth pro season, is almost a grizzled veteran, especially on the court.</p>
        <p>''I don't feel 22 until I really get off the court,'' he said. ''And then I'm back and doing my usual video games and running around the house and stuff with my son.''</p>
        <p>He may have mastered the process of making the finals, but fatherhood, at 22? Forget old school or new school. Sounds like James is being home-schooled.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
