<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Planning To Ease Rules On Passports, Official Says</title>
    <meta content="08passport" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/us/08passport.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853018"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Passports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Identification Devices</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel Restrictions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Passports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Identification Devices</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Homeland Security Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7D91F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Planning To Ease Rules On Passports, Official Says</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Planning to Ease Rules on Passports, Official Says</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RALPH BLUMENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blumenthal, Ralph</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, June 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Responding to anguished travelers at risk of being grounded by a broken passport system, the government is expected to announce on Friday that it will ease its rules for summer travel in the Western Hemisphere, a Bush administration official said Thursday.</p>
        <p>Under the revised procedures, proof that a traveler had applied for a passport not yet received would be enough for travelers returning from Canada, Mexico, Central and South America, the Caribbean and Bermuda to present through September, said the official, who insisted on anonymity because the policy had not been formally announced.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The government is expected to announce on Friday that it will ease its rules for summer travel in the Western Hemisphere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Responding to anguished travelers at risk of being grounded by a broken passport system, the government is expected to announce on Friday that it will ease its rules for summer travel in the Western Hemisphere, a Bush administration official said Thursday.</p>
        <p>Under the revised procedures, proof that a traveler had applied for a passport not yet received would be enough for travelers returning from Canada, Mexico, Central and South America, the Caribbean and Bermuda to present through September, said the official, who insisted on anonymity because the policy had not been formally announced.</p>
        <p>''But they should expect the likelihood of additional security,'' the official said in Washington.</p>
        <p>Passport offices around the country have been struggling with a backlog of millions of applications since the Western Hemisphere Travel Initiative started in January. The program requires air travelers for the first time to show passports on returning from Canada, Mexico and elsewhere in the hemisphere, not including United States territories.</p>
        <p>The agreement, resolving differences between a beleaguered State Department and the Homeland Security Department, follows prodding by many members of Congress whose offices have been deluged with protests from their districts.</p>
        <p>Constituents who applied for passports as long ago as February -- sometimes paying $60 extra for expedited service over the regular $97 -- and with air tickets in hand had not received their documents.</p>
        <p>With toll-free phone lines overloaded, travelers have thronged the 14 passport offices, seeking scarce appointments to plead their cases in person. The agency here, among others, has created teams to expedite cases with imminent deadlines. Some travelers said they could not apply for visas without passports.</p>
        <p>Among those trying to ease the rules was Representative Thomas M. Reynolds, Republican of upstate New York, near the Canadian border. Mr. Reynolds said Thursday, before word of an accord, that White House officials had been working on concerns by the Homeland Security Department that State Department efforts to resolve the crisis could compromise border safety. The agencies, Mr. Reynolds said, had been in ''a turf war that they deny.''</p>
        <p>On Thursday, Senator George V. Voinovich, Republican of Ohio, said his office had 1,000 pleas for help in the last week and appealed to Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice to permit travelers waiting for passports to show birth certificates or alternate identification. ''I am of the opinion that the State Department has lost control of the situation,'' Mr. Voinovich wrote to Ms. Rice.</p>
        <p>The demand could accelerate with the second phase of the Western Hemisphere Travel Initiative. The program, which could begin as early as January, will require passports for ship, rail and road travelers, too.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, Representative Heather A. Wilson, Republican of New Mexico, wrote to Homeland Security Secretary Michael Chertoff, saying his department might have had a policy for the problem. A post on the Customs and Border Protection Web site, Ms. Wilson wrote, said airlines had been told that they could accept ''evidence of a good faith effort to obtain a passport in a timely fashion,'' although border officers would still decide on entry case by case.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately,'' she wrote, ''it appears airlines, the State Department passport office and local Customs and Border Patrol are not aware of this policy.''</p>
        <p>The posting, Ms. Wilson said, vanished from the Web site on Thursday. A spokeswoman here for Customs and Border Protection, Debra Zezima, said that she was not aware of a change in the site, but that the agency had long said it would accommodate travelers ''in exigent circumstances on a case-by-case basis.''</p>
        <p>Some people said they had seen scant flexibility. Tonya Elliott, of Orlando, Fla., said when she and her twin, Seana Mincy, tried to apply for a passport in April for Ms. Mincy's 3-year-old, Brendan, for a trip to Canada on June 19, a federal court clerk told them that they would not have it in time and to wait until June 5 to call for an appointment.</p>
        <p>They could not get through on the phone, Ms. Elliott said, and drove four hours on Thursday to the Miami agency, where, after a day in line, they were offered an appointment after their scheduled departure. When they protested, she said, they were threatened with arrest, adding, ''We were treated horribly.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
