<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'96 Winner Of the Tour Loses Title For Doping</title>
    <meta content="08cycling" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/sports/othersports/08cycling.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853030"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CYCLING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tour de France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tour De France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">International Cycling Union</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Riis, Bjarne</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Vandenbroucke, Frank</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Landis, Floyd</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3D91F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'96 Winner Of the Tour Loses Title For Doping</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">’96 Winner of the Tour Loses Title for Doping</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN AUSTEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The organizer of the Tour de France declared yesterday that the 1996 version of cycling's most important race no longer had a winner.</p>
        <p>The decision, announced a month before the start of this year's Tour, follows an admission by Bjarne Riis that he used performance-enhancing drugs when he won in 1996.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bjarne Riis recently admitted that he used performance-enhancing drugs when he won the 1996 Tour de France.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The organizer of the Tour de France declared yesterday that the 1996 version of cycling's most important race no longer had a winner.</p>
        <p>The decision, announced a month before the start of this year's Tour, follows an admission by Bjarne Riis that he used performance-enhancing drugs when he won in 1996.</p>
        <p>The statement from the Amaury Sport Organisation, which runs the Tour de France, came on the same day that the federal police in Belgium seized drugs in a series of cycling-related raids. It was also reported yesterday that a prominent Belgian cyclist, and convicted drug user, was admitted to a hospital after a suicide attempt.</p>
        <p>The confession from Riis, who is retired and now runs the CSC team, came after the expiration of an eight-year period in which he could have been sanctioned under International Cycling Union rules. But A.S.O. said that his drug use meant that Riis ''is no longer considered the winner of the Tour.''</p>
        <p>As a result, the official history of the race, a reference book produced mainly for journalists, will now have a blank space instead of a winner's name for 1996. That will make it the only year without a victor for the race, which has been run 93 times.</p>
        <p>That unique status may change. The statement said that if an arbitration panel sanctioned the 2006 winner, Floyd Landis, for the use of performance-enhancing drugs, he would also be stripped of his title.</p>
        <p>Richard W. Pound, the chairman of the World Anti-Doping Agency, said the elimination of Riis from the record book might discourage other riders from confessing.</p>
        <p>''If I were king of the world, I would be encouraging anyone who knows anything about doping to come forward and only then decide what sanctions to apply,'' he said. ''If you take the half-empty view of this, it could be seen as an effort to shut everyone up. On the half-full side, I'm sure they're going to say, 'We don't condone doping.' ''</p>
        <p>Cycling's drug problem has become so messy, Pound added, that it might be time to grant riders and team officials, both past and present, an amnesty in exchange for their complete testimony about doping.</p>
        <p>''It sounds like doping is just so pervasive, that may be the only practicable solution,'' Pound said.</p>
        <p>Pat McQuaid, president of the cycling union, was dismissive of the action against Riis. ''They need to be consistent and less hypocritical,'' he said. ''He's not the first winner of the Tour to admit to using drugs.''</p>
        <p>While Riis is the first rider to acknowledge using drugs to win a specific Tour, other winners have generally admitted to doping. As a result, McQuaid said that the Tour organizers should also strike out victories by such stars as Fausto Coppi and Jacques Anquetil from decades ago, even though drug testing did not exist at that time.</p>
        <p>Christophe Marchadier, a spokesman for the cycling operations of A.S.O., said that no Tour officials were available for comment.</p>
        <p>In Belgium, the state prosecutors office said at a news conference that the police had seized banned substances and detained 13 people after raiding the homes of cyclists and support workers.</p>
        <p>The government did not identify any of the people involved and no charges were filed. Much of the personnel for the Discovery Channel team are Belgian and the team's European operations are based there. But P. J. Rabice, a spokesman for the team, said that no one from the group was involved in the raids.</p>
        <p>Patrick Lefévère, manager of the top-ranked Quick Step-Innergetic team, told Belgian television that a member of its medical staff had been questioned. A spokesman for the team said the investigation did not involve any of its riders, who include Tom Boonen, a leading sprinter and former world champion.</p>
        <p>A former member of the Quick Step team, Frank Vandenbroucke, was admitted to a hospital near Milan on Wednesday after a suicide attempt. He was with Quick Step in 2002 when the police seized several performance-enhancing drugs on his property.</p>
        <p>He was suspended from cycling for six months and sentenced to 200 hours of community service. But an appeals court overturned a $336,000 fine against him, saying he should be ''judged as a drug addict, not as a doped sportsman.''</p>
        <p>Vandenbroucke was once was the third-ranked cyclist in the world, but he has not won a race since 2004 and rides for a second-tier Italian team.</p>
        <p>The team's director, Palmiro Masciarelli, told The Associated Press that Vandenbroucke had attempted to slit a vein but ended up only making ''harmless cuts'' on his arm. Vandenbroucke, who has a history of erratic behavior, was despondent because his marriage had collapsed, Masciarelli said.</p>
        <p>CYCLING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
