<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thrust Into Spotlight, Trainer Is Unable to Shake Past</title>
    <meta content="08racing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/sports/othersports/08racing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853031"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E3D91F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1141" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thrust Into Spotlight, Trainer Is Unable to Shake Past</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Thrust Into Spotlight, Trainer Is Unable to Shake Past</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Until the third Saturday in May, Steve Asmussen was mostly known in thoroughbred racing circles as a driven and ambitious second-generation horseman. He trains 200 horses in a half-dozen sites from Texas to New York. Some are relatively cheap claiming horses, others are of a much higher caliber. They help him win a lot of races.</p>
        <p>In 2004, Asmussen set a North American record with 555 victories, 53 of them in stakes races. When his colt Curlin ran down Street Sense in the Preakness Stakes, Asmussen, 41, was introduced to a far wider audience.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the wake of his biggest victory, Curlin trainer Steve Asmussen finds himself uncomfortably linked to the ongoing issue of drugs and thoroughbred racing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Until the third Saturday in May, Steve Asmussen was mostly known in thoroughbred racing circles as a driven and ambitious second-generation horseman. He trains 200 horses in a half-dozen sites from Texas to New York. Some are relatively cheap claiming horses, others are of a much higher caliber. They help him win a lot of races.</p>
        <p>In 2004, Asmussen set a North American record with 555 victories, 53 of them in stakes races. When his colt Curlin ran down Street Sense in the Preakness Stakes, Asmussen, 41, was introduced to a far wider audience.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, he found himself not only fielding questions about Curlin, who has captured four of his five lifetime starts and is the 6-5 favorite in the 139th running of the Belmont Stakes on Saturday, but also answering inquiries about a filly named No End in Sight, who won two of eight races lifetime and earned only $57,200 in her low-level career.</p>
        <p>No End in Sight tested positive for the local anesthetic mepivacaine, which can deaden pain in a horse's legs, after an eighth-place finish in a race on March 24, 2006, at Evangeline Downs in Louisiana. That test is the reason that the Louisiana Racing Commission suspended Asmussen for six months in a ruling that kept him from the nation's racetracks from July to January.</p>
        <p>He was not in Louisiana the day that No End In Sight tested 750 times over the legal limit for the anesthetic. Asmussen denies any wrongdoing, and it remains unclear who actually administered the medication and whether it was done deliberately or by accident.</p>
        <p>Still, in the wake of his biggest victory, Asmussen finds himself uncomfortably linked to the ongoing issue of drugs and thoroughbred racing.</p>
        <p>''I believe in the trainer-responsibility rule, and my name was down on the sheet as the horse's trainer,'' Asmussen said last week in an interview at his barn at Churchill Downs in Kentucky. ''I don't think the six months was justified, but I was accountable.''</p>
        <p>There is no commissioner with centralized power in thoroughbred racing, as there is in professional baseball, football, basketball and hockey. However, the industry's Racing Medication and Testing Consortium, created in 2002, has made significant progress in implementing a national drug policy, with 30 of the 38 states that conduct thoroughbred racing adopting its rules on medication, testing, prohibited practices and penalties. Nevertheless, policies can vary from jurisdiction to jurisdiction.</p>
        <p>And Asmussen is hardly the only prominent trainer to find himself linked to drug issues. Over the years, such prominent trainers as D. Wayne Lukas, Nick Zito and Bob Baffert -- all multiple Kentucky Derby winners -- have been ensnared in a drug case.</p>
        <p>In addition, backstretch rumors have trailed trainers who post impressive year-round numbers but falter in Triple Crown and Breeders Cup races, where surveillance in the barn areas is believed to be more stringent and the testing is more rigorous.</p>
        <p>The Racing Medication and Testing Consortium has funded studies and helped develop tests for a wide range of drugs that have no business in racehorses, such as the blood doping agent erythropoietin (EPO) and more exotic concoctions such as snail and cobra venom.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the drug cases that do arise have the effect of undermining public confidence in the sport.</p>
        <p>''What I can say is that with each year, we've improved the situation,'' said Dr. Scot Waterman, executive director of the consortium. ''We're closer now in having a uniformity of the rules and penalties.''</p>
        <p>Waterman said he did not know the particulars surrounding Asmussen's case and would not speak directly to it. He said that he believed most veterinarians and trainers in the sport were playing by the rules.</p>
        <p>''It's a fairly small percentage of people pushing the envelope,'' Waterman said.</p>
        <p>Asmussen insists that he is not one of them. He says the reason that he is currently second in the trainers' standing nationwide in both purse earning and victories -- $7.6 million and 182 wins through Wednesday's races -- has to do with his background and drive.</p>
        <p>He grew up on a horse farm in Laredo, Tex., where his mother and father, Keith and Marilyn, still operate a horse training center. His brother, Cash, was an outstanding jockey in the United States and a champion jockey in Europe before retiring.</p>
        <p>''I have been around horses all my life, and I have learned the right way of how you care for them and do what's best by them,'' Asmussen said.</p>
        <p>Satish Sanan, one of Curlin's five owners, has had horses with Asmussen for years and is in the vanguard of the sport's reform movement on everything from drugs to the integrity of horse sales. He did not take his horses away from Asmussen, nor did another partner in Curlin, Jess Jackson, when the trainer told him about the suspension.</p>
        <p>''I believe he's a good and honest trainer,'' said Sanan, who breeds and races under Padua Stables. ''I've seen how hard he works. I've seen how well-cared for the horses are. I don't know what happened in Louisiana, but I'm comfortable that Steve is playing fair.''</p>
        <p>Asmussen said that he was embarrassed by the Louisiana ruling and was initially crushed by the thought of spending six months away from the track. But after staying close to his home in Arlington, Tex., with his wife of 10 years, Julie, and his three sons -- Keith, 8; Darren, 6; and Erik, 4 -- he said he could take away much good from the humbling experience.</p>
        <p>In fact, he wonders if fate is at work, that Curlin might not have come into his life had he not become such a daily presence in his own family's. The colt came to his barn barely a month after Asmussen returned to the track.</p>
        <p>''I was reminded how lucky I am to have the family I do,'' said Asmussen, his voice cracking and tears filling his eyes. ''I've become much more emotional and have learned a lot about myself. I love what I do, and I'm excited about going to the racetrack every day. But before all of this happened, I may have been too wrapped up in what people who didn't know Steve Asmussen thought about me.''</p>
        <p>Now, his family travels with him at every opportunity. They were in the winners' circle at the Preakness, and are here with him for the Belmont. Asmussen still wants to win a lot of races. He is determined to continue to put in the hours to do so. Still, he believes he gained valuable perspective from his exile from racing.</p>
        <p>''Maybe the suspension had to happen for me to get Curlin and to win the Preakness,'' he said. ''Maybe I wasn't ready to win a classic like the Preakness and for that level of success. I'm not a cheater. I'm not a bad guy. The people who know me know that.''</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
