<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spurs Show That James Has Much To Learn</title>
    <meta content="08nba" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/sports/basketball/08nba.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853035"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/San Antonio Spurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">San Antonio Spurs</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Basketball Assn</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Cleveland Cavaliers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">James, LeBron</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Parker, Tony</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Duncan, Tim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D91F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="907" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spurs Show That James Has Much To Learn</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spurs Show That James Has Much to Learn</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <dateline>SAN ANTONIO, June 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The education of LeBron James, rising N.B.A. star, took on a decidedly rougher edge Thursday night, right around the time that he at last encountered the San Antonio Spurs.</p>
        <p>The finals spotlight was bright and harsh, the Spurs' defense even more so. James, who has turned the playoffs into a coronation ceremony as the league's next great hope, got lost in all the wattage and all the bodies that flew into his path.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The education of LeBron James, rising N.B.A. star, took on a decidedly rougher look Thursday night, right around the time that he encountered the San Antonio Spurs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The education of LeBron James, rising N.B.A. star, took on a decidedly rougher edge Thursday night, right around the time that he at last encountered the San Antonio Spurs.</p>
        <p>The finals spotlight was bright and harsh, the Spurs' defense even more so. James, who has turned the playoffs into a coronation ceremony as the league's next great hope, got lost in all the wattage and all the bodies that flew into his path.</p>
        <p>The Spurs began their quest for a fourth championship with an 85-76 victory at the AT&amp;T Center. James began his first finals with a nightmarish performance: no field goals in the first half and an ordinary line in the final box score. He finished with 14 points, 4 assists and 6 turnovers.</p>
        <p>When James drove, the Spurs converged. Wherever James roamed, he was met by two or three defenders. Bruce Bowen chased him and grabbed at him. Manu Ginóbili drifted into him. Tim Duncan met him near the rim.</p>
        <p>''It was definitely crowded,'' James said, although he insisted his troubles were easily resolved. ''It's not like I've never seen a double-team or triple-team before. I just have to play better.''</p>
        <p>It is true that James, 22, has seen his share of swarming defenses. He has not, however, seen much of the Spurs in his brief career, and certainly not the Spurs model that commonly dominates the month of June.</p>
        <p>Tony Parker repeatedly sped through the heart of the Cavaliers defense for layups, finishing with 27 points and 7 assists. Duncan, the three-time finals M.V.P., made the first statement of the series by stuffing a shot by James in the first quarter and finished with 24 points, 13 rebounds and 5 blocks.</p>
        <p>The Cavaliers, with a dearth of talent, can only win if James is at his passing and scoring best. He fell short on both counts, and Cleveland's offense sputtered all around. The Cavs had just nine assists in the game.</p>
        <p>After missing his first eight shots, James found a modest rhythm and converted four of his last eight attempts. But the Cavaliers were pretty much done by then, and the Spurs were merely sitting on a big lead. James only got to the foul line four times.</p>
        <p>''Stars carry teams,'' Duncan said, and the Spurs ''do a pretty good job of containing people.''</p>
        <p>It was a typical game for the Spurs, who led by as many as 18 points in the fourth quarter while James desperately tried to find his rhythm.</p>
        <p>''Some of it was me missing a lot of the shots that I usually make, and some of it was the defense that they put on me,'' James said. Looking ahead to Sunday's Game 2, James made an odd analogy for a player who went straight from high school to the N.B.A.: ''The best thing about this is it's not like the N.C.A.A. tournament, where you have one game and you're out.''</p>
        <p>Cleveland got solid, but not outstanding, production from Drew Gooden (14 points), Daniel Gibson (16 points) and Sasha Pavlovic (13 points). The starters Zydrunas Ilgauskas and Larry Hughes combined for just 4 points.</p>
        <p>James broke his shooting drought with a driving layup at the 7-minute-15-second mark of the third quarter, suggesting he might have a late breakout. Cleveland's optimism was promptly doused. Bowen and Ginóbili hit 3-pointers, Duncan and Parker hit consecutive layups, and the Spurs had a 58-47 lead, their biggest to that point.</p>
        <p>The Cavaliers called a timeout, which only gave the Spurs a chance to honor three of their former stars in attendance -- David Robinson, Sean Elliott and George Gervin -- and thus remind everyone of the chasm between these franchises.</p>
        <p>The Spurs closed the period with a 3-pointer by Bowen, a short jumper by Duncan and a 64-49 lead. Robert Horry, who is pursuing his seventh championship ring, hit a 3-pointer to open the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>This all seemed rather routine for San Antonio, performing under the comfort of three championship banners. The Spurs' three title runs all started with Game 1 victories, all at home. They are 8-2 in home games in the championship round.</p>
        <p>It was a good night to be a dynasty. It was a bad night to be a LeBron fan, or a network executive.</p>
        <p>Even Spurs Coach Gregg Popovich, who generally confines his commentary to matters of X's and O's, conceded the importance of James's ascension as an N.B.A. icon.</p>
        <p>''I think superstars are tremendously important for any of the sports leagues,'' Popovich said before the game.</p>
        <p>Popovich's team then went about ruining the N.B.A.'s mood, and perhaps its ratings.</p>
        <p>The first half ended with James having gone 0 for 7 from the field, with just 1 assist. As the half came to a close, James heaved a wild half-court shot. The buzzer spared him from another official miss.</p>
        <p>The first, eagerly anticipated shot from James in his first, eagerly anticipated finals came 3:21 after tipoff. It was an awkward-looking 14-foot fadeaway that struck the front of the rim. The crowd roared with delight. It only got louder when Duncan provided the series' first signature play, stuffing a James jumper moments later.</p>
        <p>The Cavaliers held the Spurs without a field goal for the first six minutes of second quarter, turning a 5-point deficit into a 25-22 lead. It disappeared in an instant, as the Spurs went on a 9-0 burst in the next 68 seconds and never trailed again.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
