<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Good Day for Torre, but Not Everyone's Happy</title>
    <meta content="08yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/sports/08yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1853033"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago White Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Chicago White Sox</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Abreu, Bobby</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E3D91F30F93BA35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Good Day for Torre, but Not Everyone's Happy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Good Day for Torre, but Not Everyone’s Happy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, June 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joe Torre needed six victories to reach 2,000 for his managerial career, and it seemed as if he might not make it. The Yankees were going nowhere last Wednesday, with five losses in a row, so Torre canceled batting practice and benched Bobby Abreu.</p>
        <p>The Yankees won that night in Toronto, and now they have won six of eight. Torre captured that 2,000th victory, 10-3, against the Chicago White Sox on Thursday. He was helped by a tie-breaking, eighth-inning, two-run double by Abreu, who is batting .480 in June.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees won for the sixth time in eight games Thursday night, catapulted by a two-run double by Bobby Abreu that broke a tie in the eighth inning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Joe Torre needed six victories to reach 2,000 for his managerial career, and it seemed as if he might not make it. The Yankees were going nowhere last Wednesday, with five losses in a row, so Torre canceled batting practice and benched Bobby Abreu.</p>
        <p>The Yankees won that night in Toronto, and now they have won six of eight. Torre captured that 2,000th victory, 10-3, against the Chicago White Sox on Thursday. He was helped by a tie-breaking, eighth-inning, two-run double by Abreu, who is batting .480 in June.</p>
        <p>''I usually give lineup cards out,'' Torre said in his office after the game. ''I keep this one.''</p>
        <p>Mariano Rivera gave Torre the game ball after recording the last five outs. Derek Jeter, who rested most of the game, gave Torre a hug and said that Torre seemed emotional.</p>
        <p>''I'm happy for him; he deserves it,'' Jeter said. ''He's a Hall of Fame manager, whenever he decides to call it quits. He's the best.''</p>
        <p>Torre became the 10th manager to reach 2,000 victories, and the only one who also had 2,000 hits as a player. Mike Mussina, the starting pitcher, said he hoped Torre, who is unsigned past this season, won many more games with the Yankees.</p>
        <p>But Mussina was clearly not pleased with Torre's decision to remove him. Mussina had allowed two hits in six shutout innings before an infield single and another single put runners on first and third with no outs in the seventh.</p>
        <p>Mussina said he had not even considered that the Yankees might have relievers warming up. The pitching coach, Ron Guidry, had not visited him all game, and he had thrown only 79 pitches. But Torre took him out, calling for the left-hander Mike Myers to face the left-handed-hitting A. J. Pierzynski, who singled to tie the score. Left-handers are hitting .350 against Myers this season.</p>
        <p>''Why am I upset?'' Mussina said after the game. ''Because I threw 80 pitches and I think I could have thrown 110. It was the first mess I had. I just felt like I could have kept going.''</p>
        <p>Mussina entered the game with a 2-3 record and a 6.25 earned run average. Despite low radar gun readings on his fastball, he was able to command the pitch better than he usually did, and his curveball was especially lively.</p>
        <p>''I understand his thinking, but seventh inning with 79 pitches?'' Mussina said. ''I know I haven't been pitching that well, but oh well. Gotta earn it back, I guess. Gotta earn it back.''</p>
        <p>While Mussina stewed, he also recognized how much better the Yankees have played lately. Although first baseman Josh Phelps misplayed the infield hit in the seventh -- retreating to the bag instead of taking the ball and flipping to Mussina -- the defense has been crisper, the offense has been strong and the pitching has been solid.</p>
        <p>The result is consecutive series victories for the first time this season. The Yankees won two of three in Boston and three of four here.</p>
        <p>''We've actually looked like a baseball team now for the last part of this trip,'' Mussina said. ''We've played the game right, energy, except for the first game of this trip when we were still asleep -- getting in at 5 -- other than that, we've played really well.''</p>
        <p>Abreu hit .208 in May, the worst average in any calendar month of his 12-year career (minimum 10 at-bats). Resting for the last game of May, he said, made a big difference. ''Fresher mind, fresher body, everything,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Since then, Abreu is 12 for 25, with eight walks in seven games. He singled and scored the Yankees' first run, in the fourth, and doubled in two against the left-hander Matt Thornton to break a 1-1 tie in the eighth.</p>
        <p>In the ninth, Abreu walked with two outs to load the bases for Alex Rodriguez, who ripped a grand slam to left for his 22nd home run. In the ninth inning this season, Rodriguez is batting .529 (9 for 17) with 6 homers and 16 runs batted in.</p>
        <p>As Abreu improves, it stands to reason that Rodriguez improves along with him. Johnny Damon and Robinson Canó have come alive, too, but Abreu has helped Rodriguez more than any other hitter.</p>
        <p>''I know I enjoy hitting behind him a lot,'' Rodriguez said. ''Johnny's been better and Robby's been better, but Abreu, he's an awesome guy to hit behind, because he sees so many pitches.''</p>
        <p>When Abreu is on base, pitchers are more likely to challenge Rodriguez. But Rodriguez often has a better idea of their repertory because of how many pitches Abreu sees. He is back to being himself.</p>
        <p>''The last two weeks, I was pretty much lost at the plate, swinging at bad pitches,'' Abreu said. ''I didn't do my job. I was working so hard to get out of my slump. Finally, I feel a lot better at the plate. Back to normal.''</p>
        <p>He is back to normal, and the Yankees (27-31) are nearly back to .500.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
