<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where the Beach Books Are</title>
    <meta content="01summ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/books/01summ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851223"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Geist, Bill</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Leonard, Elmore</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Berg, Elizabeth</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Deford, Frank</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E4DC1530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1514" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where the Beach Books Are</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Where the Beach Books Are</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If a computer were programmed to create summer reading, it might outdo Hilma Wolitzer's new novel. Maybe.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wolitzer has named a book ''Summer Reading,'' set it in Amagansett and centered it on a book club, the Page Turners, whose members look like sun-streaked Clairol models and take tea and sandwiches with their literature. When it comes to packaging, this novel is prettily wrapped in a blue and green cover that depicts books on a lawn chair and might be called ''Still Life of Summer Vacation.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The best of escapist summer reading isn’t really a matter of geography. It takes you anywhere it wants to go.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If a computer were programmed to create summer reading, it might outdo Hilma Wolitzer's new novel. Maybe.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wolitzer has named a book ''Summer Reading,'' set it in Amagansett and centered it on a book club, the Page Turners, whose members look like sun-streaked Clairol models and take tea and sandwiches with their literature. When it comes to packaging, this novel is prettily wrapped in a blue and green cover that depicts books on a lawn chair and might be called ''Still Life of Summer Vacation.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Wolitzer understands the clientele for summer books. While the Page Turners struggle through Trollope and ask apt questions (''If novels are all, like, about morality, why are there so many descriptions of rooms and gardens and gowns?''), it's clear that ''winter reading,'' or ''that endless blizzard of pages flecked with the blown soot of words,'' isn't really what they're after. Summer reading has more to do with charmed lives, blue skies and location, location, location.</p>
        <p>Just put a chef on a yacht on the Riviera and you have a 327-page book-sized vacation. With the culinary travel memoir ''Mediterranean Summer: A Season on France's Côte d'Azur and Italy's Costa Bella,'' the reader shares the adventures of David Shalleck (a k a ''The One Without the Tan''), whose mission is to keep things festive aboard a newly renovated 124-foot schooner. Whether he is out buying vegetables at dawn, worrying about why the fish on ice have cloudy eyes or catering to the wishes of his employers, known as La Signora and Il Dottore, Mr. Shalleck (with his co-writer, Erol Munuz) tells an escapist story that comes with recipes and practically generates its own sea breeze.</p>
        <p>Part of the fine art of telling picturesque stories is getting their central characters to the desired summer setting in a hurry. Some books manage this more gracefully than others.</p>
        <p>In his novel ''The Prince of Nantucket,'' Jan Goldstein describes Teddy Mathison, a hot senatorial candidate (''Men wanted to be around him; women wanted to have his baby'') whose California campaign is interrupted by an abrupt summons. Just when his poll numbers on family values are flagging, Teddy learns that his mother is on Nantucket with a worsening case of Alzheimer's. And a telltale ''Z'' on his calendar turns out to mean that he must also contend with his teenage daughter, Zoe. Though he hates to return to Nantucket -- where, as the title indicates, things will go nicely for him -- he has no choice. The future Prince of Nantucket is glimpsing cranberry bogs and lighthouses by Page 21.</p>
        <p>''The Savage Garden,'' by Mark Mills (who has already written a novel called ''Amagansett''), is a much better book. But it's every bit as manipulative in its early stages. Adam Strickland, a Cambridge University student, is minding his own business when a professor tempts him with an offer too touristy to refuse. How about a summer at a large villa in Tuscany? It may be ''an impressive, if somewhat pedestrian, example of High Renaissance Tuscan vernacular,'' but it also has a garden full of ''Da Vinci Code''-flavored clues for Adam to unearth. This alluring, mysterious novel has other flavors -- like fennel salami -- too.</p>
        <p>Not all forms of summer-book wanderlust are this upscale. In the midst of hilariously picaresque travels through small-town America in ''Way Off the Road,'' the CBS News correspondent Bill Geist makes culinary distinctions on a less grand scale. ''Barbecue is -- unofficially, of course -- the official food of rural America,'' he writes. ''Probably not the official cuisine. That would be meat loaf.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Geist, who has collected a book-length array of rustic wonders like the world's largest paint ball, also equips his book with a warning indicative of its excitement level. ''If you experience an erection lasting more than four hours while using this product,'' he writes, ''I'd be really surprised.''</p>
        <p>In ''Michael Tolliver Lives,'' due June 12, Armistead Maupin makes no such claim. ''Here in our beloved Gayberry,'' as Mr. Maupin puts it, Michael, a character from Mr. Maupin's ''Tales of the City'' series, is friskier than ever, a 55-year-old gardener fully engaged with life despite his H.I.V.-positive diagnosis. With AIDS drugs for some of his needs and Viagra for others, Michael is happily ensconced with a much younger man and very much a part of the riotous San Francisco gay culture that ''Tales of the City'' made so endearing.</p>
        <p>Anyone who enjoyed those earlier books will welcome the opportunity for a return trip to its setting. Mr. Maupin maintains that this is a stand-alone novel and not a sequel. But it's familiar enough to have the warmth of a reunion long overdue.</p>
        <p>Any encounter with Elmore Leonard is a reunion of sorts -- even if his destination in ''Up in Honey's Room'' is World War II Detroit. For proof of how seductive the right writer can make even the most unexpected destination, consider Mr. Leonard's follow-up to ''The Hot Kid,'' in which that title character -- Carl Webster of the United States Marshals Service -- finds himself in the midst of bizarre German spies, who are living in the Midwest and trying to go native. Perhaps these enemy agents shouldn't be funny, but when you read Mr. Leonard, you enter Mr. Leonard's world. A trip like that is its own kind of vacation.</p>
        <p>So one of this book's characters proudly claims the title of Heinrich Himmler's separated-at-birth twin. Another ''heel-clicker,'' as Mr. Leonard calls his Nazis, is named for the renowned mystery editor and bookseller Otto Penzler, and his Ms. Right turns out to be a Jewish girlfriend. As for Honey Deal, the vamp of the title, she lives up to her name. And she tries every conceivable tactic to turn the Hot Kid even hotter.</p>
        <p>Wartime Chicago has much less appeal in Elizabeth Berg's current beach book, which has the bright look and sky-blue cover art of a sure thing. (''That pure blue,'' writes Ms. Berg, as a character looks upward. ''Those white, white clouds.'') But ''Dream When You're Feeling Blue,'' about the three Heaney sisters and their romances with men in uniform, has a bobby-pin level of period detail that becomes humdrum much too quickly. ''We collected for rubber today?'' the family's kid brother exclaims. ''And guess what? Old lady Clooney gave us her girdle!'' Fine -- but did Ms. Berg really need to give that girdle to her readers?</p>
        <p>Ms. Berg's view of Chicago is frankly feminine; Frank Deford's Cleveland is a guy's kind of town. That's because ''The Entitled,'' Mr. Deford's new novel, is a baseball book with the Cleveland Indians at its center and the team's road-weary manager, Howie Traveler, as its central figure. Howie is tested by the sight of his superstar outfielder, Jay Alcazar, dragging a woman into a hotel room against her will, so the book has a chance to examine the mores of contemporary sports. But it also transports the reader to a world of athletes whose constant traveling leaves them in true limbo. Howie has more than one player who doesn't understand why the Kansas City airport and stadium aren't in Kansas.</p>
        <p>There's a more glamorous, hard-boiled worldliness to Anthony Gagliano's ''Straits of Fortune,'' set in Miami and trumpeted by a spectacular piece of beach-book cover art. With a colorful sunset in the background, the cover depicts a babe in a neon-green bikini holding a gun as she lies on the deck of a boat in a glamorous harbor; surely these are all the food groups the genre requires. In this memorably crisp debut Mr. Gagliano tough-talks his way through a plausibly noir narrative rich with the requisite heat and duplicity. He favors lines like ''He was about as sentimental as a gangplank on a busy day.''</p>
        <p>One final beach-book destination: Los Angeles, under a cloud of acrid smoke. No, this doesn't automatically make for a picturesque getaway, but it belongs on the list anyhow. That's because Robert Ellis's ''City of Fire'' is a gripping, spooky crime novel whose heroine, Detective Lena Gamble, watches her city burn while a serial killer is on the prowl. And at its best escapist summer reading isn't really a matter of geography. It takes you anywhere it wants to go.</p>
        <p>The Hot List  These are the books mentioned in this article:</p>
        <p>CITY OF FIRE by Robert Ellis (St. Martin's Minotaur); 357 pages; $24.95.  DREAM WHEN YOU'RE FEELING BLUE by Elizabeth Berg (Random House); 276 pages; $24.95.  THE ENTITLED by Frank Deford (Sourcebooks); 318 pages; $24.95.  MEDITERRANEAN SUMMER by David Shalleck with Erol Munuz (Broadway Books); 332 pages; $23.95.  MICHAEL TOLLIVER LIVES by Armistead Maupin (HarperCollins); 277 pages; $25.95.  THE PRINCE OF NANTUCKET by Jan Goldstein (Shaye Ayreheart Books); 239 pages; $24.  THE SAVAGE GARDEN by Mark Mills (G. P. Putnam's Sons); 324 pages; $24.95.  STRAITS OF FORTUNE by Anthony Gagliano (William Morrow); 240 pages; $23.95.  SUMMER READING by Hilma Wolitzer (Ballantine Books); 251 pages; $24.95.  UP IN HONEY'S ROOM by Elmore Leonard (William Morrow); 292 pages; $25.95.  WAY OFF THE ROAD by Bill Geist (Broadway Books); 240 pages; $23.95.</p>
        <p>BOOKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
