<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>James Puts on Scoring Clinic in Overtime</title>
    <meta content="01pistons" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/sports/basketball/01pistons.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851378"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Cavaliers 109, Pistons 107"/>
      <identified-content>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, LeBron</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Detroit Pistons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Detroit Pistons</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Cleveland Cavaliers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">James, LeBron</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E5D91030F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1150" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>James Puts on Scoring Clinic in Overtime</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">James Puts on Scoring Clinic in Overtime</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <dateline>AUBURN HILLS, Mich., May 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Minute after hypnotic minute, LeBron James lifted into the air, suspended in a stratosphere from where only he could see the basket. Every time his feet hit the ground a split second before his improbable jumpers hit the bottom of the net, despite Detroit Pistons defenders all over him, the Palace of Auburn Hills gasped and fell into stunned silence.</p>
        <p>It was as close to reverence as the home fans could show, after seeing James take over the game and the Eastern Conference finals Thursday night by piling in 29 of his team's final 30 points through the thrilling fourth quarter and two overtimes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>LeBron James scored 29 of the Cavs’ last 30 points in a double overtime victory that put his team one win away from its first trip to the N.B.A. finals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Minute after hypnotic minute, LeBron James lifted into the air, suspended in a stratosphere from where only he could see the basket. Every time his feet hit the ground a split second before his improbable jumpers hit the bottom of the net, despite Detroit Pistons defenders all over him, the Palace of Auburn Hills gasped and fell into stunned silence.</p>
        <p>It was as close to reverence as the home fans could show, after seeing James take over the game and the Eastern Conference finals Thursday night by piling in 29 of his team's final 30 points through the thrilling fourth quarter and two overtimes.</p>
        <p>If there were other players on the Cleveland Cavaliers, nobody saw them. And if there was any way to stop James, the Pistons could not find it. It was only fitting that James, in the final 2.2 seconds of the second overtime, won Game 5 of this career-defining series when he muscled his way to the basket. His driving layup, when he pushed past three Pistons, lifted the Cavaliers to a 109-107 victory over the Pistons and gave Cleveland a 3-2 lead in the series.</p>
        <p>James' 48 points -- a franchise playoff record -- put his team one victory from reaching its first N.B.A. finals. Game 6 is in Cleveland Saturday, where the Cavaliers have not lost in this series.</p>
        <p>The zone James locked into this night was as effortless for him as it was dazzling to observers. What, exactly, did it feel like?</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to miss,'' James said with a weary smile, walking out of the interview room 20 minutes after the buzzer sounded. ''Not everybody gets the opportunity to be in a zone like that. I just wanted to will my team to victory and do the best job possible.'' There was no denying this night was another step toward a coronation for James, the player dubbed the Chosen One and King James when he starred in high school in Akron, Ohio. James wears 23 in obvious homage to Michael Jordan and on this night the comparisons -- from the performance, to the team he beat were inevitable.</p>
        <p>''It was very Jordanesque,'' the Pistons' Chauncey Billups said. ''That kid was on fire, it was crazy. He put on an unbelievable display out there. It's probably the best I have seen against us ever in the playoffs.''</p>
        <p>When Billups missed a 13-foot jumper with one second remaining in the 58-minute contest, the Pistons walked off their court blinking.</p>
        <p>They are the conference finalists for five straight years and now, for the second straight season, they are in danger of taking an early vacation because of one star player. Last season it was Miami's Dwyane Wade.</p>
        <p>''We've been in a hole before,'' the Pistons' Rasheed Wallace said. Last year in the conference semifinals, the Cavaliers won Game 5 to take a 3-2 series lead but then lost two in a row. But James was not playing at this level.</p>
        <p>''If I did everything I did tonight and we lost, it means nothing,'' James said. ''So the win is the most important thing for us and we are one more win from getting to our goal.''</p>
        <p>All night, James carved up the Pistons defense. When they tried to trap James, he dribbled out of the double-coverage and to the basket. He scored 25 points in a row. Drew Gooden's free throw with 2 minutes 49 seconds left in regulation was the only point James did not score in the final 16 minutes of basketball.</p>
        <p>''My words don't give it justice for what he did,'' Cavaliers Coach Mike Brown said. ''He was awesome and at 22 years old, wow.''</p>
        <p>James was asked if he were surprised he could score on three driving dunks -- in the fourth quarter and overtime. ''Why do I have to be surprised? I made a lot of good moves and I was able to finish,'' he said.</p>
        <p>James' sublime finish in overtime -- when he scored all 9 points in each of the two periods -- capped a game of momentum swings that had 16 ties and 22 lead changes. No exchange in the game was as thrilling as the one in the final 31 seconds of regulation between James and Billups.</p>
        <p>First, James took the ball at the top of the arc and with his cross-over dribble left Jason Maxiell flat-footed. Then, with the Pistons' Tayshaun Prince getting out of the way, he soared to throw down a vicious dunk that gave the Cavaliers an 89-88 lead. But Billups, who finished with 21 points, would not be denied. He drained a 3-pointer with 22.9 seconds left that gave the Pistons a tenuous 91-89 lead. James was not finished. With 9.5 seconds left, he drove the middle of the lane for a dunk, tying the score, 91-91.</p>
        <p>When Billups's 3-pointer missed at the buzzer, the game went to overtime. James will never have to wonder ''what might have been'' had he made three free throws in regulation. And he will never have to think about the jumper he missed with 7.9 seconds left, with the Cavaliers leading by 2 points in the first overtime. Billups hit two free throws to force the second overtime.</p>
        <p>The drama began early in the game. After the first four games of the series were decided in the final minute of regulation, it was no wonder the action between the teams turned from chippy to contentious with 28.7 seconds left in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>The Pistons were leading, 28-22, when Detroit's Antonio McDyess fouled Anderson Varejao hard going to the basket, raking him across the shoulders. Following form, Varejao fell on his back and grimaced, his tight curls mopping the floor. James charged from the corner in front of his bench and hurdled over his fallen teammate, searching for McDyess. Instead, James found Pistons forward Jason Maxiell, who held him back as the two exchanged words. James was assessed a technical foul. The normally soft-spoken McDyess was given a flagrant 2 foul, an immediate ejection, and walked to the locker room in disbelief.</p>
        <p>Chris Webber, the veteran Pistons center, played his best game of the series with the extra minutes, scoring 20 points. His 3-point play with 1:28 remaining in the second overtime, gave the Pistons a 107-104 lead.</p>
        <p>But James, of course, answered right back. He hit a fade-away 3-pointer to tie the game with 1:14 to play. ''I thought the shot he had in front of our bench to tie it up when we were up three, off to the left and going up, he was in an unbelievable zone,'' Pistons Coach Flip Saunders said.</p>
        <p>The zone took its toll after the game. When asked how he felt, James replied: ''Terrible.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''I'm everything -- I'm banged up, I'm winded, I'm fatigued. I've got all day tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>His night, however, will linger far longer in playoff memory.</p>
        <p>Cavaliers 109, Pistons 107</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
