<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Children</title>
    <meta content="01kids" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/arts/01kids.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851194"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPARE TIMES | JUNE 1 - JUNE 7"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E3DD1530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Children</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spare Times: For Children</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAUREL GRAEBER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALL STARS HIP-HOP CABARET (Tonight and tomorrow) This evening of performance by and for teenagers and young adults -- with song, dance and rap about growing up in the city's poorer neighborhoods -- also offers work by seasoned artists, including an excerpt from ''Sally &amp; Tom (the American Way),'' a musical by Fred Newman about Thomas Jefferson and his slave Sally Hemings. (Through June 16.) At 7 p.m., the All Stars Project, 543 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 941-1234; $25; $10 for students.</p>
        <p>'BUG BOY BLUES' (Tomorrow and Sunday) Kafka for kids? That's the idea behind this show by Lisa Railsback, which explores the mind of young Gregor Samsa, subject of ''The Metamorphosis.'' It has a more hopeful ending and some whimsical elements, like a jam band and dancing insects, but still manages to be surprisingly, well, Kafkaesque. For ages 8 and older. Tomorrow at noon and 2 p.m., Sunday at 2 and 4 p.m., the Looking Glass Theater, 422 West 57th Street, Clinton, (212) 352-3101; $12; $10 for 12 and under.</p>
        <p>CIRCUS SUNDAYS IN JUNE (Sunday) Brooklyn not only has a floating concert hall (Bargemusic), it also has a floating circus. This attraction, on board the Waterfront Museum and Showboat Barge, presents different entertainers every Sunday of the month. This Sunday's roster includes Billy Bones the Good Pirate and the trapeze act the Mermaidens. At 1 and 4 p.m., Conover Street and the waterfront, Red Hook, (877) 238-5596, waterfrontmuseum.org. Tickets: in advance, $12; $6 for under 12. At the door, $15 and $8.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY UNITY PICNIC (Tomorrow) Unity in diversity is certainly possible, and it will be celebrated at this event, which opens the annual monthlong New York Family Arts Festival presented by the Riverside Theater. The focus will be on the multicultural arts of the city, with steel-pan rhythms, Zulu dance, gospel, storytelling and old-fashioned sack and egg-and-spoon races. Not to mention free food. From noon to 5 p.m., Sakura Park, 122nd Street and Riverside Drive, Morningside Heights, (212) 870-6784; free.</p>
        <p>'CUT &amp; PASTE' (Tomorrow) Today cutting and pasting can involve computers as much as scissors and glue. Children 5 to 10 can use either in the latest ''Saturday in the Galleries'' program from ARTime, which combines a 90-minute gallery tour with a workshop on the first Saturday of each month. Tomorrow the subject is the large-scale work of the photographer Andreas Gursky; children will take their own digital photos to create a collage at home. At 11 a.m.; $25 for one adult with one child; $5 for each additional child. If possible, families should take digital cameras. Reservations and meeting place: (718) 797-1573 or artimeny@nyc.rr.com.</p>
        <p>FESTIVAL OF HOMEGROWN WORK (Tonight through Sunday) Oddball animation, contemporary fairy tales, a lounge-act musical of highlights from the French Revolution and a 10-minute excerpt from a one-man ''Wizard of Oz'' are all on the menu in this brand-new festival from Downtown Art. Like other Downtown Art productions, it features young artists -- ages 12 to 24 -- and that downtown state of mind. (Through June 10; three programs run at different hours.) At Downtown Art, 61 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 479-0885, downtownart.org; $8; $5 for students.</p>
        <p>GOVERNORS ISLAND FAMILY FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) Governors Island played an important role in American military history, but these days it's devoted to peacetime fun. Its summer season opens tomorrow with a celebration of music, crafts and theater, including, at 12:30 p.m., ''Amazing Aesop,'' a production of six fables from Literally Alive Children's Theater. From 12:30 to 4 p.m., www.govisland.com; free.</p>
        <p>'LOVE'S LABOUR'S LOST' (Tonight through Sunday) Where else can you find a Shakespearean theater that welcomes infants, children and dogs? This one is Central Park, where New York Classical Theater presents outdoor productions at which the actors change location with each scene. Take a picnic, and sneakers. At 7 p.m., in the park at West 103rd Street and Central Park West, (212) 252-4531; free.</p>
        <p>A MAD HATTER'S TEA PARTY (Today) Wonderland is now in SoHo, at least through Sunday, while the Children's Museum of the Arts presents an exhibition devoted to the work of Lewis Carroll. In this annual family benefit children will be invited to step into Alice's shoes and play croquet at the Queen's, interview a caterpillar, swim in a ''pool of tears'' and make Cheshire Cat masks. And have a tea party of course. From 4 to 8 p.m., 182 Lafayette Street, near Broome Street, (212) 274-0986, Ext. 113, or ephelan@cmany.org; $75; $25 for children.</p>
        <p>MADISON SQUARE PARK CONSERVANCY SPRING PLAYGROUND FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) Playgrounds are always fun, but the one in Madison Square Park promises to offer more than usual at this annual festival, which will include games, snacks, crafts and live music by the groups the Deedle Deedle Dees and Bubble Does the Beatles for Kids. From 10 a.m. to 2 p.m., Fifth Avenue and 25th Street, madisonsquarepark.org; free.</p>
        <p>'THE MUSIC IN ME' (Sunday) All children seem to have music in them, but not all have the means to express it. That's where Midori &amp; Friends, an organization founded by the violinist Midori, comes in. It has been offering free music education programs in city schools for 15 years, and on Sunday the programs' students, who range from elementary to high school age, will present their second annual Children's Music Festival. The storyteller David Gonzalez will be host, and world music artists like Arturo O'Farrill will also perform. (The concert will be repeated on June 9 at another location.) At 3 p.m., Hostos Center for the Arts &amp; Culture, 450 Grand Concourse, at 149th Street, Mott Haven, the Bronx, (212) 767-1300, midoriandfriends.org; free.</p>
        <p>'MICROCOSMOS' AND 'THE NATURAL HISTORY OF THE CHICKEN' (Tomorrow and Sunday) No, they didn't shrink the kids, but they did amplify the insects -- with extremely high-power photography -- in ''Microcosmos,'' a documentary about bugs' lives that unfolds at their level. The ''Natural History'' film, for ages 10 and older, is tongue in cheek, billed as ''the 'Spinal Tap' '' of chicken documentaries. Both are being shown by the New York International Children's Film Festival. At 11 a.m., 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 349-0330, gkids.com; $11; $7.50 for 12 and under and 65+.</p>
        <p>P.S. 183 SPRING ARTS FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) There will be dancing in the streets, or close to it, at this daylong event supporting the school. Indian dance activities, a program from the National Dance Institute, a student variety show and art exhibits will complement the antiques and farmers' market held outdoors in the schoolyard. From 8 a.m. to 5 p.m., 66th and 67th Streets, between York and First Avenues, Manhattan, (877) 436-7658; free.</p>
        <p>RED HOOK WATERFRONT ARTS FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) The Pirates of the Caribbean may not dock here, but it seems as if everyone else will: circus performers, hula-hoop teachers, face painters, youth dance troupes, hip-hop artists, bands and D.J.'s. Activities for children include knot-tying workshops, a coloring contest and free canoe and kayak rides. (Rain date, Sunday.) From 10 a.m. to 7 p.m., Louis J. Valentino Jr. Park &amp; Pier, Coffey and Ferris Streets, Red Hook, Brooklyn, (718) 643-6790, Ext. 411, dancetheatreetcetera.org; free.</p>
        <p>'THE SECRET LIVES OF STREETS' (Thursday) New York streets are more than numbers; many have names and entire histories behind those names. What they reveal about Brooklyn is the subject of this exhibition, organized by 10 teenagers in an after-school program who worked with the authors of ''Brooklyn by Name,'' Leonard Benardo and Jennifer Weiss. Interested neighborhood sleuths can meet the students and hear the authors talk at this opening reception. From 5:30 to 7:30 p.m., Brooklyn Historical Society, 128 Pierrepont Street, at Clinton Street, Brooklyn Heights, (718) 222-4111, brooklynhistory.org; free.</p>
        <p>SOLAR ONE FAMILY DAY (Tomorrow) It really is easy being green, according to Solar One, a nonprofit Manhattan center devoted to promoting environmental education and ecologically safe design. On the first of its summer family days, to be held on the first Saturday of every month through September, the center offers a workshop with undeniable child appeal: creating solar-powered toys, including race cars and drums. From 10 a.m. to 1 p.m., Solar One, Stuyvesant Cove Park, 23rd Street and the East River, (212) 505-6050, solar1.org. Free, but e-mail reservations are requested: sarah@solar1.org.</p>
        <p>SPRING FAMILY DAY AT THE GUGGENHEIM (Sunday) This is an afternoon of art: looking at it, making it and sometimes even being a part of it. Planned activities include exploring interactive installations like Piotr Uklanski's, which turns the museum space into a pulsing, hot-colored disco, and joining the illustrator Jeff Hopkins in an interactive storytelling session. From 1 to 4 p.m., the Guggenheim Museum, 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3788, guggenheim.org/education; $15 a family; $10 for members and free for family members.</p>
        <p>SUMMER READING KICKOFF (Thursday) Reading is one pleasurable summer activity that doesn't depend on good weather, and libraries are promoting it with the annual Summer Reading Program for children and teenagers. Those who register can participate in free activities, including author talks, reading contests and writing book reviews online. It all begins with a free outdoor celebration, with live music, at noon at the Bronx Library Center, 310 East Kingsbridge Road, at Briggs Avenue, Fordham. From 2 to 4 p.m. Brooklyn Public Library branches will provide refreshments, activities and gifts for all who sign up. Information: summerreading.org.</p>
        <p>'THOMAS SAVES THE DAY' (Today through Sunday) Thomas the Tank Engine, many preschoolers' favorite locomotive, is chugging his way into Manhattan, not to Grand Central Terminal or Pennsylvania Station but to the Beacon Theater. The occasion is a 90-minute musical featuring this literary and TV star, his fellow trains Percy and Diesel and other residents of the Island of Sodor. At 11 a.m. and 2 and 5 p.m., 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 307-7171; $25 to $69.</p>
        <p>UPTOWN COUNTY FAIR (Tomorrow) A county fair sounds rural, but this is strictly a city event: on 93rd Street, between Columbus and Amsterdam Avenues, where P.S. 333 Manhattan School for Children is sponsoring a benefit, with a petting zoo, an obstacle course, face painting, arcade games, crafts and more. From 11 a.m. to 5 p.m., (212) 222-1450; free.</p>
        <p>LAUREL GRAEBER</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR CHILDREN.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALL STARS HIP-HOP CABARET (Tonight and tomorrow) This evening of performance by and for teenagers and young adults -- with song, dance and rap about growing up in the city's poorer neighborhoods -- also offers work by seasoned artists, including an excerpt from ''Sally &amp; Tom (the American Way),'' a musical by Fred Newman about Thomas Jefferson and his slave Sally Hemings. (Through June 16.) At 7 p.m., the All Stars Project, 543 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 941-1234; $25; $10 for students.</p>
        <p>'BUG BOY BLUES' (Tomorrow and Sunday) Kafka for kids? That's the idea behind this show by Lisa Railsback, which explores the mind of young Gregor Samsa, subject of ''The Metamorphosis.'' It has a more hopeful ending and some whimsical elements, like a jam band and dancing insects, but still manages to be surprisingly, well, Kafkaesque. For ages 8 and older. Tomorrow at noon and 2 p.m., Sunday at 2 and 4 p.m., the Looking Glass Theater, 422 West 57th Street, Clinton, (212) 352-3101; $12; $10 for 12 and under.</p>
        <p>CIRCUS SUNDAYS IN JUNE (Sunday) Brooklyn not only has a floating concert hall (Bargemusic), it also has a floating circus. This attraction, on board the Waterfront Museum and Showboat Barge, presents different entertainers every Sunday of the month. This Sunday's roster includes Billy Bones the Good Pirate and the trapeze act the Mermaidens. At 1 and 4 p.m., Conover Street and the waterfront, Red Hook, (877) 238-5596, waterfrontmuseum.org. Tickets: in advance, $12; $6 for under 12. At the door, $15 and $8.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY UNITY PICNIC (Tomorrow) Unity in diversity is certainly possible, and it will be celebrated at this event, which opens the annual monthlong New York Family Arts Festival presented by the Riverside Theater. The focus will be on the multicultural arts of the city, with steel-pan rhythms, Zulu dance, gospel, storytelling and old-fashioned sack and egg-and-spoon races. Not to mention free food. From noon to 5 p.m., Sakura Park, 122nd Street and Riverside Drive, Morningside Heights, (212) 870-6784; free.</p>
        <p>'CUT &amp; PASTE' (Tomorrow) Today cutting and pasting can involve computers as much as scissors and glue. Children 5 to 10 can use either in the latest ''Saturday in the Galleries'' program from ARTime, which combines a 90-minute gallery tour with a workshop on the first Saturday of each month. Tomorrow the subject is the large-scale work of the photographer Andreas Gursky; children will take their own digital photos to create a collage at home. At 11 a.m.; $25 for one adult with one child; $5 for each additional child. If possible, families should take digital cameras. Reservations and meeting place: (718) 797-1573 or artimeny@nyc.rr.com.</p>
        <p>FESTIVAL OF HOMEGROWN WORK (Tonight through Sunday) Oddball animation, contemporary fairy tales, a lounge-act musical of highlights from the French Revolution and a 10-minute excerpt from a one-man ''Wizard of Oz'' are all on the menu in this brand-new festival from Downtown Art. Like other Downtown Art productions, it features young artists -- ages 12 to 24 -- and that downtown state of mind. (Through June 10; three programs run at different hours.) At Downtown Art, 61 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 479-0885, downtownart.org; $8; $5 for students.</p>
        <p>GOVERNORS ISLAND FAMILY FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) Governors Island played an important role in American military history, but these days it's devoted to peacetime fun. Its summer season opens tomorrow with a celebration of music, crafts and theater, including, at 12:30 p.m., ''Amazing Aesop,'' a production of six fables from Literally Alive Children's Theater. From 12:30 to 4 p.m., www.govisland.com; free.</p>
        <p>'LOVE'S LABOUR'S LOST' (Tonight through Sunday) Where else can you find a Shakespearean theater that welcomes infants, children and dogs? This one is Central Park, where New York Classical Theater presents outdoor productions at which the actors change location with each scene. Take a picnic, and sneakers. At 7 p.m., in the park at West 103rd Street and Central Park West, (212) 252-4531; free.</p>
        <p>A MAD HATTER'S TEA PARTY (Today) Wonderland is now in SoHo, at least through Sunday, while the Children's Museum of the Arts presents an exhibition devoted to the work of Lewis Carroll. In this annual family benefit children will be invited to step into Alice's shoes and play croquet at the Queen's, interview a caterpillar, swim in a ''pool of tears'' and make Cheshire Cat masks. And have a tea party of course. From 4 to 8 p.m., 182 Lafayette Street, near Broome Street, (212) 274-0986, Ext. 113, or ephelan@cmany.org; $75; $25 for children.</p>
        <p>MADISON SQUARE PARK CONSERVANCY SPRING PLAYGROUND FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) Playgrounds are always fun, but the one in Madison Square Park promises to offer more than usual at this annual festival, which will include games, snacks, crafts and live music by the groups the Deedle Deedle Dees and Bubble Does the Beatles for Kids. From 10 a.m. to 2 p.m., Fifth Avenue and 25th Street, madisonsquarepark.org; free.</p>
        <p>'THE MUSIC IN ME' (Sunday) All children seem to have music in them, but not all have the means to express it. That's where Midori &amp; Friends, an organization founded by the violinist Midori, comes in. It has been offering free music education programs in city schools for 15 years, and on Sunday the programs' students, who range from elementary to high school age, will present their second annual Children's Music Festival. The storyteller David Gonzalez will be host, and world music artists like Arturo O'Farrill will also perform. (The concert will be repeated on June 9 at another location.) At 3 p.m., Hostos Center for the Arts &amp; Culture, 450 Grand Concourse, at 149th Street, Mott Haven, the Bronx, (212) 767-1300, midoriandfriends.org; free.</p>
        <p>'MICROCOSMOS' AND 'THE NATURAL HISTORY OF THE CHICKEN' (Tomorrow and Sunday) No, they didn't shrink the kids, but they did amplify the insects -- with extremely high-power photography -- in ''Microcosmos,'' a documentary about bugs' lives that unfolds at their level. The ''Natural History'' film, for ages 10 and older, is tongue in cheek, billed as ''the 'Spinal Tap' '' of chicken documentaries. Both are being shown by the New York International Children's Film Festival. At 11 a.m., 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 349-0330, gkids.com; $11; $7.50 for 12 and under and 65+.</p>
        <p>P.S. 183 SPRING ARTS FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) There will be dancing in the streets, or close to it, at this daylong event supporting the school. Indian dance activities, a program from the National Dance Institute, a student variety show and art exhibits will complement the antiques and farmers' market held outdoors in the schoolyard. From 8 a.m. to 5 p.m., 66th and 67th Streets, between York and First Avenues, Manhattan, (877) 436-7658; free.</p>
        <p>RED HOOK WATERFRONT ARTS FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) The Pirates of the Caribbean may not dock here, but it seems as if everyone else will: circus performers, hula-hoop teachers, face painters, youth dance troupes, hip-hop artists, bands and D.J.'s. Activities for children include knot-tying workshops, a coloring contest and free canoe and kayak rides. (Rain date, Sunday.) From 10 a.m. to 7 p.m., Louis J. Valentino Jr. Park &amp; Pier, Coffey and Ferris Streets, Red Hook, Brooklyn, (718) 643-6790, Ext. 411, dancetheatreetcetera.org; free.</p>
        <p>'THE SECRET LIVES OF STREETS' (Thursday) New York streets are more than numbers; many have names and entire histories behind those names. What they reveal about Brooklyn is the subject of this exhibition, organized by 10 teenagers in an after-school program who worked with the authors of ''Brooklyn by Name,'' Leonard Benardo and Jennifer Weiss. Interested neighborhood sleuths can meet the students and hear the authors talk at this opening reception. From 5:30 to 7:30 p.m., Brooklyn Historical Society, 128 Pierrepont Street, at Clinton Street, Brooklyn Heights, (718) 222-4111, brooklynhistory.org; free.</p>
        <p>SOLAR ONE FAMILY DAY (Tomorrow) It really is easy being green, according to Solar One, a nonprofit Manhattan center devoted to promoting environmental education and ecologically safe design. On the first of its summer family days, to be held on the first Saturday of every month through September, the center offers a workshop with undeniable child appeal: creating solar-powered toys, including race cars and drums. From 10 a.m. to 1 p.m., Solar One, Stuyvesant Cove Park, 23rd Street and the East River, (212) 505-6050, solar1.org. Free, but e-mail reservations are requested: sarah@solar1.org.</p>
        <p>SPRING FAMILY DAY AT THE GUGGENHEIM (Sunday) This is an afternoon of art: looking at it, making it and sometimes even being a part of it. Planned activities include exploring interactive installations like Piotr Uklanski's, which turns the museum space into a pulsing, hot-colored disco, and joining the illustrator Jeff Hopkins in an interactive storytelling session. From 1 to 4 p.m., the Guggenheim Museum, 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3788, guggenheim.org/education; $15 a family; $10 for members and free for family members.</p>
        <p>SUMMER READING KICKOFF (Thursday) Reading is one pleasurable summer activity that doesn't depend on good weather, and libraries are promoting it with the annual Summer Reading Program for children and teenagers. Those who register can participate in free activities, including author talks, reading contests and writing book reviews online. It all begins with a free outdoor celebration, with live music, at noon at the Bronx Library Center, 310 East Kingsbridge Road, at Briggs Avenue, Fordham. From 2 to 4 p.m. Brooklyn Public Library branches will provide refreshments, activities and gifts for all who sign up. Information: summerreading.org.</p>
        <p>'THOMAS SAVES THE DAY' (Today through Sunday) Thomas the Tank Engine, many preschoolers' favorite locomotive, is chugging his way into Manhattan, not to Grand Central Terminal or Pennsylvania Station but to the Beacon Theater. The occasion is a 90-minute musical featuring this literary and TV star, his fellow trains Percy and Diesel and other residents of the Island of Sodor. At 11 a.m. and 2 and 5 p.m., 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 307-7171; $25 to $69.</p>
        <p>UPTOWN COUNTY FAIR (Tomorrow) A county fair sounds rural, but this is strictly a city event: on 93rd Street, between Columbus and Amsterdam Avenues, where P.S. 333 Manhattan School for Children is sponsoring a benefit, with a petting zoo, an obstacle course, face painting, arcade games, crafts and more. From 11 a.m. to 5 p.m., (212) 222-1450; free.</p>
        <p>LAUREL GRAEBER</p>
        <p>SPARE TIMES | JUNE 1 - JUNE 7</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
