<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Athletes Acting Cadly</title>
    <meta content="01araton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/sports/basketball/01araton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851353"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bryant, Kobe</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Araton, Harvey</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E2D71530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Athletes Acting Cadly</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Athletes Acting Cadly</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On my car radio yesterday morning, a baseball reporter for ESPN was lamenting the disconnect between the news media and celebrity athletes as a result of salacious reporting, such as the latest tabloid frenzy in New York over Alex Rodriguez's personal life. Contemporary stars, the reporter contended, are more distrustful than ever of mainstream outlets and, given their wealth, increasingly indifferent to the benefits of making themselves available.</p>
        <p>Made perfect sense to me until the next topic of discussion: Kobe Bryant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Having long established himself as a serial newsmaker, for better or worse, Kobe Bryant again demonstrated a fondness and dexterity for self-promotion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On my car radio yesterday morning, a baseball reporter for ESPN was lamenting the disconnect between the news media and celebrity athletes as a result of salacious reporting, such as the latest tabloid frenzy in New York over Alex Rodriguez's personal life. Contemporary stars, the reporter contended, are more distrustful than ever of mainstream outlets and, given their wealth, increasingly indifferent to the benefits of making themselves available.</p>
        <p>Made perfect sense to me until the next topic of discussion: Kobe Bryant.</p>
        <p>Having long established himself as a serial newsmaker, for better or worse, Bryant demonstrated a profound fondness and dexterity for the traditional promotional blitz Wednesday. In a calculated burst of wacky loquacity, he made the rounds when a simple telephone call to his employer, the Los Angeles Lakers, might have delivered the same message.</p>
        <p>In summary: Whaaaa!</p>
        <p>Poor baby Bryant, sitting home this month while basketball fans pay attention to LeBron James, decided the Lakers weren't rebuilding fast enough the three-championship dynasty he fallaciously claims he had no role in dismantling.</p>
        <p>It was all the fault of the Lakers' front office, which wasn't nice to him, which lied to him, and that was why, though it pained him so, he was stating his unequivocal desire to be traded, to go elsewhere, as far away as Pluto, if need be.</p>
        <p>Before Bryant takes his killer jumper to the perimeter of the solar system, he may want to check on how restrictive a salary cap the Plutonian Basketball Association has, if he hasn't changed his mind and realized he would better fit on Uranus.</p>
        <p>Wednesday, Bryant couldn't keep his story straight from one radio show to another, telling one host there is ''no other alternative'' to a trade before crossing over on two others, saying that he wanted to spend the rest of his career with the Lakers.</p>
        <p>When The Los Angeles Times caught up with him, Bryant had refined his persecution complex, back to preferring a trade but adding, ''I don't have much of a choice.''</p>
        <p>He certainly did have one as a free agent three years ago, when he could have fled the Lakers at the same time the owner Jerry Buss was trading Shaquille O'Neal to Miami without any protest from Bryant.</p>
        <p>He could have remained in Los Angeles, aligned himself with Elton Brand and the upstart Clippers, or taken a more promising road back to playoff prominence, from the weaker Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>He had to have recognized the difficulty of approximating what he had with O'Neal in a league financial system that smartly protects small-market teams from being Steinbrennered into submission. Unfortunately, performance ideology has always been an issue, an unnecessary distraction, for No. 8-turned-24, or Michael Jordan's number plus one.</p>
        <p>''I'm tired of being a sidekick,'' Bryant was quoted as saying in a book by Lakers Coach Phil Jackson, oblivious to the probability that O'Neal would have become his consigliere, as he has with Dwyane Wade in Miami, as the big man moved into his mid-30s.</p>
        <p>Now Bryant knows what it means to be his team's lone star, lord and savior. Bounced from the first round of the playoffs by Phoenix for the second straight season, he has run out of patience, along with loyalty for an organization that chose him over the popular O'Neal, paid him every cent the salary cap would allow, hired back Jackson at $10 million a year as he asked, not exactly scrimped with a $77 million payroll and stood firmly behind him when he was charged with raping a Colorado woman in 2003. (The case was eventually dismissed.)</p>
        <p>To put Bryant's suffering into proper context, consider Kevin Garnett, 12 years in snowy Minneapolis, once past the first round of the playoffs, yet to make himself the kind of public spectacle that plays well with rebellious teenagers but turns ticket-buying and television-watching adults off to the N.B.A.</p>
        <p>Bryant can't give the Lakers two more years to provide better supporting talent, the worst-case scenario allowing him to opt out of his contract before his 31st birthday, still in prime playing and earning years.</p>
        <p>He couldn't have shown consideration for James and Tim Duncan and colleagues still at work, waited a few more weeks to clench his fists and jump up and down?</p>
        <p>Perhaps not, as some athletes are predisposed, genetically hard-wired, to draw attention, one way or another.</p>
        <p>Considered by many to be baseball's Bryant, the game's best pound-for-pound player, Rodriguez has established a similar it's-always-something niche during his three-plus seasons in New York.</p>
        <p>A headline-grabbing magazine interview clumsily timed last year to challenge the Yankees' postseason karma and increase the prodigious personal pressure on A-Rod. A postplayoff lunch in Manhattan that just happened to be around the corner from where reporters were staking out George Steinbrenner after reports that Joe Torre might be fired.</p>
        <p>It would be a presumptuous and a psychological leap to suggest that A-Rod was looking to land on the front page of The New York Post this week after being photographed outside a hotel elevator with a woman who is not his wife.</p>
        <p>But how can discretion be the better part of valor when he apparently doesn't know that a citizen journalist these days can be anyone holding a cellphone? When he doesn't have the good sense to lie low during trying times for himself and the Yankees, drawing charges of gamesmanship from the Blue Jays in Toronto on the same day the photos appeared?</p>
        <p>Some just have the knack, can't stop themselves from crying out and, yes, occasionally reaping the desired reward. In Bryant's case, Buss snapped to attention and issued a calming statement, Jackson and Magic Johnson called to sweet-talk him and his self-serving tantrum obliterated San Antonio's claiming of the Western Conference title.</p>
        <p>Go find that kind of attention, such dependable press service, on Pluto.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
