<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Healthy Abreu Tries to Get Swing Back in Shape</title>
    <meta content="01yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/sports/01yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851319"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Abreu, Bobby</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EFD81530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1015" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Healthy Abreu Tries to Get Swing Back in Shape</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Healthy Abreu Tries to Get Swing Back in Shape</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a subtle but symbolic move at the end of a rout. With the Yankees ahead by five runs in Toronto on Wednesday, Manager Joe Torre removed Johnny Damon from the outfield and inserted Bobby Abreu. It was one 33-year-old outfielder in a hitting slump replacing another in a physical slump.</p>
        <p>Abreu, who is hitting .228, did not start the game because Torre wanted to give him a two-day mental break from his struggles. Damon smashed a leadoff homer and later added his 2,000th career hit, but it is anybody's guess how his legs will feel tonight at Fenway Park.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bobby Abreu’s is in good health, but he is still in a slump, and the Yankees can’t quite figure out why.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was a subtle but symbolic move at the end of a rout. With the Yankees ahead by five runs in Toronto on Wednesday, Manager Joe Torre removed Johnny Damon from the outfield and inserted Bobby Abreu. It was one 33-year-old outfielder in a hitting slump replacing another in a physical slump.</p>
        <p>Abreu, who is hitting .228, did not start the game because Torre wanted to give him a two-day mental break from his struggles. Damon smashed a leadoff homer and later added his 2,000th career hit, but it is anybody's guess how his legs will feel tonight at Fenway Park.</p>
        <p>''Just show up every day, and hopefully there's some life behind the legs'' Damon said.</p>
        <p>Damon is batting .264 with three home runs and a .362 on-base percentage that is slightly better last year's. Yet he has been in and out of the lineup since his calves cramped up on opening day, calling his durability into question with more than two and a half seasons left on his four-year, $52 million contract.</p>
        <p>Torre said he thought Damon could become a first baseman, if only because he throws left-handed, adding that Damon's years of all-out play had probably worn down his body.</p>
        <p>''But I still think he can be an offensive force,'' Torre said. ''His health has to be there for his ability to show. But I certainly think there's a lot of energy still left there.''</p>
        <p>Abreu has not dealt with any physical problems since a spring training injury to his rib cage. His good health makes his slide more perplexing.</p>
        <p>''You don't all of a sudden not know how to hit, not at his age,'' said the Yankees' third-base coach, Larry Bowa, who managed Abreu in Philadelphia. ''He's not 40 years old. You don't all of a sudden say, 'God, I forgot how to hit.' But one thing about him, if you watch him when he hits a ground ball, he's running hard. He's playing hard. He's just not getting it done.''</p>
        <p>When Abreu slumped in Philadelphia, Bowa said, he would break out within 10 days or so, and during that stretch he might draw 12 walks. The difference now is that Abreu is not walking as often. He recently went a career-long 61 plate appearances without a walk.</p>
        <p>''I've never seen him swing at as many bad pitches as I've seen during this period of time,'' Bowa said. ''I don't know if he's trying to force the action. I mean, he still knows his strike zone, but now he starts expanding it, which he's never done.</p>
        <p>''I'm down there at third and the count will be 2-0, and I'm saying to myself, 'Let it go, man.' He takes that strike. I'm going to say something, but I think right now everybody's trying to give their input and sometimes it's an overload. He respects the coaches and he knows guys are trying to help, but sometimes it's too much.''</p>
        <p>Kevin Long, the hitting coach, said he had talked with Abreu about his stride and urged him to let the ball travel deeper. But there is only so much he can do. When Long asked last year's hitting coach, Don Mattingly, about how to approach Abreu, Mattingly essentially told him to simply trust that Abreu would come around.</p>
        <p>''Your M.O. with him,'' Long said, quoting Mattingly, ''is that he's going to hit.''</p>
        <p>Abreu led the majors in walks last season, with 124, but this year he is tied for third on the Yankees, with 24, and his on-base percentage is .313, compared with .419 for the Yankees last season. Long said Abreu's walks were down because pitchers did not fear him as much and were throwing him more strikes. Abreu disagreed.</p>
        <p>''I'm just struggling,'' he said. ''I've been getting a lot of good pitches to hit. I haven't hit them well.''</p>
        <p>Some players give the appearance of indifference, a tag that Torre said stuck to his brother Frank, a first baseman in the 1950s, and sticks to Abreu now. But it is a false label, said Torre, who believes that Abreu feels burdened that he has let the team down.</p>
        <p>''When you don't really hit and you're losing, you feel bad,'' Abreu said. ''You feel like you don't do your part, you don't contribute to get the team wins, and you feel like you're not helping at all. It's awful to go through.''</p>
        <p>Abreu seemed to be a perfect fit in the Yankees' lineup last season, another patient hitter who stroked doubles even as his home run rate declined. Abreu still rarely homers -- he has hit only one in his last 177 at-bats -- but he has also hit only six doubles.</p>
        <p>Abreu has a $16 million option for next season that the Yankees seem unlikely to exercise if his slump continues. Bowa said the uncertainty may be weighing on Abreu.</p>
        <p>''I think he likes it here,'' Bowa said. ''That started it. I think he wanted to impress people -- 'I want my option picked up' and all that. Now it's snowballed and he's probably thinking, 'Now what?' ''</p>
        <p>Abreu said he had enough to worry about without thinking too far ahead. As for Damon, with three elite center fielders on the free-agent market this winter -- Torii Hunter, Andruw Jones and Ichiro Suzuki -- he knows the Yankees will have options and the outfield could look different next season.</p>
        <p>''It could be,'' said Damon, who has a limited no-trade clause. ''That's how baseball is.''</p>
        <p>For now, Damon just wants his legs to feel strong all the time, because he relies on them so much. He would like to break out his zany personality more often, too.</p>
        <p>''But it's tough,'' Damon said. ''You can't really goof around in the clubhouse when your team's not winning.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Chien-Ming Wang (3-4) will start for the Yankees in tonight's series opener against the Red Sox. He will be opposed by Tim Wakefield (5-5). Mike Mussina (2-3) will face Curt Schilling (5-2) tomorrow afternoon and Andy Pettitte (3-4) will be matched against Josh Beckett (8-0) on Sunday.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
