<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Casting for President, Will Actor Rate a Callback?</title>
    <meta content="01watch" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/us/politics/01watch.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070606T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851248"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE TV WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Thompson, Fred Dalton</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E6D91530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Casting for President, Will Actor Rate a Callback?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Casting for President, Will Actor Rate a Callback?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stanley, Alessandra</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the movie mogul Jack Warner heard that Ronald Reagan was running for governor of California in 1966, he was dismayed. ''Jimmy Stewart for governor,'' he said. ''Ronald Reagan for best friend.''</p>
        <p>The 2008 Republican nomination is turning into a Dick Wolf production -- politics ripped from TV Guide. The casting is once again upside down. Rudy Giuliani for front-runner? Maybe. But the Fred Thompson of ''Law &amp; Order'' fame is better suited as chief of staff.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 2008 Republican nomination is turning into a Dick Wolf production  politics ripped from TV Guide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the movie mogul Jack Warner heard that Ronald Reagan was running for governor of California in 1966, he was dismayed. ''Jimmy Stewart for governor,'' he said. ''Ronald Reagan for best friend.''</p>
        <p>The 2008 Republican nomination is turning into a Dick Wolf production -- politics ripped from TV Guide. The casting is once again upside down. Rudy Giuliani for front-runner? Maybe. But the Fred Thompson of ''Law &amp; Order'' fame is better suited as chief of staff.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson, a former senator from Tennessee, had a solidly conservative voting record in Washington, but most Americans know him best as the fictional Manhattan district attorney Arthur Branch. Arthur is not so much an inspiring leader as he is a crafty consigliere: a bluntly pragmatic D.A. who has colorfully phrased views and a wily ability to bend them -- and those of his staff -- to meet the political needs of his office.</p>
        <p>Arthur is a conservative, wears a flag pin in his lapel and is particularly deft at pressing Assistant D.A. Jack McCoy to ask for the death penalty. ''It's not just you, Jack,'' he says in his bourbon-and-branch-water drawl. ''It's the law.'' (In that particular TNT rerun, he held up a copy of a book titled ''Penal Code,'' to make his point.)</p>
        <p>Now that he is creating a committee to raise money from contributors unhappy with the existing field of candidates, Mr. Thompson can apply his powers of persuasion in a different way. It's not just you, Rudy, it's the ''Law &amp; Order.''</p>
        <p>Maybe it's only fair that Mr. Thompson rides on the coattails of a fictional prosecutor invented by Mr. Wolf. Mr. Wolf based the first Manhattan district attorney on the show, Adam Schiff, on Robert M. Morgenthau, who has been Manhattan district attorney since 1975.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson's fame as an actor -- and the popularity of the character he has played since he left the Senate in 2002 -- could compensate for his late entry into the money-raising race. But he won't necessarily persuade voters that he should be in the Oval Office.</p>
        <p>Americans want their presidents to be loyal and steadfast. This week, Mr. Thompson said he asked Mr. Wolf to release him from his ''Law &amp; Order'' contract -- at a time when the 17-year-old series is struggling to survive. (Earlier this month, NBC came close to canceling it.)</p>
        <p>Women may harbor doubts about his character's character. Arthur has a weakness for the young, tall, gorgeous prosecutors in his office and for mentoring them through their cases.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson hopes voters will see him as a successor to Ronald Reagan, but the ''Great Communicator'' is not really so apt a model. Howard H. Baker Jr., the former Senate majority leader from Tennessee who tapped Mr. Thompson as minority counsel during the 1974 Watergate hearings, is a closer match.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baker, who was known on Capitol Hill as the ''Great Conciliator,'' ran for the Republican presidential nomination in 1980, but lost the New Hampshire primary to Reagan. When the Reagan White House ran into trouble in the second term, Mr. Baker was brought in as chief of staff to clean up after the pugnacious Donald T. Regan, a former chairman of Merrill Lynch, who was skittish about sharing credit and clashed with Nancy Reagan.</p>
        <p>Arthur was elected to replace the unpugnacious Nora Lewin (Dianne Wiest), a liberal law professor who was skittish about capital punishment and clashed with more aggressive prosecutors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson may see himself as a commander in chief, but Hollywood has preferred to cast him as a senior White House aide or adviser. He played a White House chief of staff in the 1993 film ''In the Line of Fire,'' and the director of central intelligence in the 1987 thriller ''No Way Out.'' He wasn't picked to play a president until 2005, in the HBO film ''Last Best Chance,'' which was more of a public-service film made with support from the Nuclear Threat Initiative and other foundations.</p>
        <p>Once candidates declare, their pasts are scoured for personal, often embarrassing details. Mr. Thompson has not only his own bachelor days in Washington; voters may also hold him accountable for Arthur's past.</p>
        <p>That stately, Southern gentleman has a few peccadilloes of his own. On one episode, he confided to Jack that he once dressed up in a clown suit to serenade a girl who loved opera with snatches from Pagliacci. ''She laughed, then she slammed the door in my face,'' Arthur says ruefully. ''My point is, guys do goofy things for girls whether they want them to or not.''</p>
        <p>THE TV WATCH</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 6, 2007, Wednesday  The TV Watch column on Friday, about Fred D. Thompson, the former senator and actor on ''Law &amp; Order,'' who has taken steps to run for president, misstated the year of the Senate Watergate hearings, when he was named minority counsel for the committee investigating the scandal. It was 1973, not 1974.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 6, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>The TV Watch column on Friday, about Fred D. Thompson, the former senator and actor on ''Law &amp; Order,'' who has taken steps to run for president, misstated the year of the Senate Watergate hearings, when he was named minority counsel for the committee investigating the scandal. It was 1973, not 1974.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
