<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HAVENS | Lake Superior's North Shore; Minnesota's 'Freshwater Ocean' Attracts a New Generation</title>
    <meta content="01havens" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/travel/escapes/01havens.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851231"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Havens | Lake Superiors North Shore"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Minnesota</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lake Superior</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Finn-Olaf</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Great Homes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Vacation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Minnesota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Minnesota</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Lake Superior</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1DC1530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HAVENS | Lake Superior's North Shore; Minnesota's 'Freshwater Ocean' Attracts a New Generation</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Minnesota’s ‘Freshwater Ocean’ Attracts a New Generation</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FINN-OLAF JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Finn-Olaf</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on north shore of Lake Superior, Minnesota, as place to live or visit; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Shore,'' for most Minnesotans, is the North Shore of Lake Superior. Before Highway 61 -- which is more than just a road in Bob Dylan's mythology -- was extended from Duluth to the Canadian border in the 1920s, local Scandinavian fisherman took in summer guests who traveled from the railhead in Duluth north on the postal boat.</p>
        <p>Four generations of vacationers have now been regaled with tales of the larger-than-life figures of the north, from American Indians to fishermen and trappers to lumbermen. This is, after all, Paul Bunyan country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four generations of vacationers have now been regaled with tales of the larger-than-life figures of the north, from American Indians to fishermen and trappers to lumbermen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Shore,'' for most Minnesotans, is the North Shore of Lake Superior. Before Highway 61 -- which is more than just a road in Bob Dylan's mythology -- was extended from Duluth to the Canadian border in the 1920s, local Scandinavian fisherman took in summer guests who traveled from the railhead in Duluth north on the postal boat.</p>
        <p>Four generations of vacationers have now been regaled with tales of the larger-than-life figures of the north, from American Indians to fishermen and trappers to lumbermen. This is, after all, Paul Bunyan country.</p>
        <p>Lake Superior's granite coves and sheer cliffs, backed by deep pine, birch and fern forests, are reminiscent of the coast of Maine, right down to the vast expanse of lead-gray water that disappears into a shoreless horizon -- the higher parts of the Michigan coast on the other side can only be glimpsed on clear days.</p>
        <p>''Lake Superior is like a freshwater ocean where the light is always changing,'' said Ron Ankeny, a Minneapolis architect who has a Scandinavian-style cabin perched on the edge of the granite shoreline. ''Sometimes the waves go up to 15 feet.''</p>
        <p>The North Shore is a year-round destination. In summer, it's a haven for climbing, hiking and swimming, though some prefer the inland lakes and streams to Lake Superior's often frigid waters. In fall, the spectacular foliage turns the shore into a 100-mile-long Technicolor tie-dye ribbon made double-wide by the reflection in the water. In winter, cross-country skiing, snowmobiling and downhill skiing at Lutsen take over.</p>
        <p>''Coming from Switzerland, you would think that the shore would pale in comparison, but it doesn't,'' said Annie Cleveland, who lives in Zurich with her husband and two sons but still makes the pilgrimage each summer to her family's cabin near Two Harbors. ''My kids do exactly what I did when I was kid: build forts in the woods, count bald eagles, throw rocks endlessly into the lake, skinny-dip in the river, fish off the shore and gather pine cones and driftwood for the evening bonfire.''</p>
        <p>Private, multigenerational cabin enclaves along the coast still attract weekend warriors making the two-and-a-half-hour drive from Minneapolis-St. Paul, arguing along the way about which roadside shop has the best smoked fish or the cheapest wild rice. But amid the old-money log constructions, new arrivals have given rise to steel pavilions, curvy modernist lumber homes and even New York-style loft constructions that overlook the granite coast.</p>
        <p>And over the last decade, gleaming resorts, restaurants and condo developments have turned this once exclusive shore into one of the most popular second-home regions in the Upper Midwest.</p>
        <p>The Scene</p>
        <p>The North Shore, which some wags have dubbed the ''Norwegian Riviera,'' is a kind of Lake Wobegon with panache.</p>
        <p>It is a place where you will find business titans from the Twin Cities and local wool-shirted bohemians rubbing elbows with mineworkers and sailors in the coffeehouses, bars and cafes of Grand Marais, an intimate and colorful harbor village 110 miles north of Duluth, midway up the shore.</p>
        <p>Lumberjack fashion prevails: worn overalls, thick plaid shirts and leather hiking boots have been the uniform of choice for decades. ''My cabin fashion only looks good up there,'' Mrs. Cleveland said. ''I wear the same clothes for days, which is probably not something I could get away with in places like Lake Tahoe or Aspen.''</p>
        <p>The North Shore's predominant ''Scandihoovian'' look was defined by Edwin Lundie, a Minneapolis architect, who, during the first six decades of the 20th century built more than a dozen notable cabins along the shore, including the giant red main lodge at the Lutsen Resort. ''He set the tone for the North Shore,'' said Mr. Ankeny, who owns Lundie's former cabin near Taconite Harbor. ''His Scandinavian carvings, stone fireplaces and timber framing set the standard by emphasizing great craftsmanship.''</p>
        <p>This tradition continues in the North House Folk School, which sits in a group of brightly painted wood shacks on the Grand Marais waterfront, where you can sign up for courses on everything from how to build your own birch-bark canoe to carving traditional Norwegian ale bowls</p>
        <p>Most people come to the shore to play in the great outdoors. For hikers, there is the Superior Hiking Trail, which follows the lake's scenic ridge line for 205 miles past Gooseberry Falls and other sights. For bikers and in-line skaters, there is Gitchi-Gami State Trail, a planned 86-mile of paved trail between Two Harbors and Grand Marais that is still under construction.</p>
        <p>Several segments have already been completed, notably an eight-mile stretch along the beautiful cliffside setting between Cascade River and Grand Marais.</p>
        <p>Pros</p>
        <p>There aren't many places in America where your lake view is shared with what sounds like the cast of a Disney movie: ''We see timberwolves, bear, moose and even the occasional red fox,'' Mr. Ankeny said. ''There's always something moving amidst the trees.''</p>
        <p>New arrivals mean new amenities -- from the expanded Lutsen Mountains ski area to new restaurants that venture beyond such traditional North Shore fare as fried walleye and wild rice. ''You can eat well in Grand Marais and other new culinary hot spots along the shore, or you can still go to the ma-and-pa cafes for simpler fare,'' said Rob Buntz, the developer of the Bluefin Bay resort in Tofte, who recently opened the Bluefin Grille restaurant there.</p>
        <p>Cons</p>
        <p>On one recent weekend, the major noise on the shore was not the waves or the birds but the constant roar of cars on Highway 61. At nights, the big diesel rigs take over.</p>
        <p>The rigorous physical life of the north coupled with an underlying Lutheran mind-your-own-business ethic means that ''Minnesota nice'' is often replaced with ''Minnesota stoic.'' ''This is not a place where locals are going to be asking you many questions,'' said Nate Morris, who owns a condo at Bluefin Bay. ''People here are usually very polite, but keep to themselves.''</p>
        <p>During the off-season and even on weekdays the solitude can be overwhelming for some. ''It was too isolated for my wife,'' said Tom Kailor of the decision to sell his recently completed ''dream house'' on a hill high above Silver Bay.</p>
        <p>Oh, and this is Northern Minnesota; ever heard that it sometimes gets cold up here?</p>
        <p>The Real Estate Market</p>
        <p>Yes, the North Shore has been discovered. ''There's been quite a surge in prices here over the past five years, not just because we're mirroring the real estate market all over the country but also because more and more out-of-state buyers have discovered the North Shore,'' said Tom Fiero, a real estate agent based in Tofte.</p>
        <p>Real estate prices on Lake Superior have soared in the past decade, but the region is still relatively cheap compared to Northern California or coastal Maine. Real estate agents say the rule of thumb is a cost of $2,000 to $3,000 per foot of shoreline on the lake. Just 10 years ago, it was less than $1,000 per foot.</p>
        <p>''It used to be big news when a property sold for more than a million,'' said John F. Costello, a real estate agent in Lutsen. Now, at least a half-dozen North Shore properties are for sale for more than a million.</p>
        <p>LAY OF THE LAND</p>
        <p>POPULATION -- 16,295 for Cook and Lake Counties, according to a 2006 Census Bureau estimate.</p>
        <p>SIZE -- The distance is 118 miles from Two Harbors, where the wilderness shoreline begins, to Grand Portage on the Canadian border. Lake County and Cook County make up 3,583 square miles of the North Shore.</p>
        <p>LOCATION -- Northern Minnesota along Lake Superior, 154 miles north of Minneapolis-St. Paul and just north of Duluth.</p>
        <p>WHO'S BUYING -- Real estate agents say that most cabins and condos are being sold mainly to young professionals and empty nesters, mostly from Minneapolis-St. Paul, although some Chicagoans and others from the Upper Midwest are buying.</p>
        <p>GETTING THERE -- Duluth International Airport is a 10-minute drive from Lake Superior and is served by regular 50-minute flights from Minneapolis-St. Paul International Airport, which is a two-and-a-half-hour drive from Duluth.</p>
        <p>WHILE YOU'RE LOOKING -- Bluefin Bay (7192 West Highway 61, Tofte, 800-258-3346; www.bluefinbay.com) has modern cottages, outdoor pools, a scenic river trail and daily activities that range from hikes to campfires. Rates start at $89 a night. Lutsen Resort (5,700 West Highway 61, Lutsen, 800-258-8736; www.lutsenresort.com) has rooms starting at $59 a night.</p>
        <p>THREE FOR SALE</p>
        <p>Perched Above the Chilly Waters With a Shoreless Horizon</p>
        <p>Information on properties was supplied by the listing companies.</p>
        <p>WHAT -- 1-bedroom cabin  HOW MUCH -- $375,000</p>
        <p>This year-round cabin is near Two Harbors and overlooks Lake Superior. There are one bathroom, a sauna and a private cove with a sand and pebble beach. Broker: David Parsons, Parsons Realty, (800) 338-3340; www.parsonsrealty.net.</p>
        <p>WHAT -- 3-bedroom condo  HOW MUCH -- $425,000</p>
        <p>This two-level unit has a large Jacuzzi and a balcony a fishing pole's length from Lake Superior at the Bluefin Bay resort. The condo has access to the resort's pools and other amenities and is next to the Superior Hiking Trail. It is also a 10-minute drive from the Lutsen Mountains ski area. Broker: Rob Buntz, Bluefin Bay, (612) 599-2757; www.bluefinbay.com.</p>
        <p>WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $1.95 million</p>
        <p>This 6.7-acre property is on a hilltop 800 feet above Lake Superior near Silver Bay and has expansive views. Designed by the architect David Salmela, the house is 4,000 square feet and has four bathrooms and floor-to-ceiling windows. Agents: John Oberholtzer and Tom Fiero, Cascade Property Sales, (800) 381-1319; www.cascadepropertysales.com.</p>
        <p>Havens | Lake Superiors North Shore</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
