<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Attorney General Is Called Corzine's Pick for Top Judge</title>
    <meta content="01justice" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851323"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04EED81530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="837" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Attorney General Is Called Corzine's Pick for Top Judge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN; Alison Leigh Cowan and Ronald Smothers contributed reporting.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine plans to nominate Attorney General Stuart Rabner to be the next chief justice of the New Jersey Supreme Court, potentially leaving his imprint on the state's legal landscape for the next two decades, administration officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Rabner, who turns 47 on June 30, is confirmed by the State Senate and serves until the mandatory retirement age of 70, he will break by six years the record for the longest tenure of a New Jersey chief justice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine plans to nominate Attorney General Stuart Rabner to be the next chief justice of the New Jersey Supreme Court, potentially leaving his imprint on the state's legal landscape for the next two decades, administration officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Rabner, who turns 47 on June 30, is confirmed by the State Senate and serves until the mandatory retirement age of 70, he will break by six years the record for the longest tenure of a New Jersey chief justice.</p>
        <p>Anthony Coley, Mr. Corzine's communications director, said the administration would not comment on the issue. But other administration officials, speaking on the condition of anonymity because they did not want to upstage the governor, said that Mr. Rabner would be introduced at a news conference on Monday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine is also expected to nominate Anne Milgram, Mr. Rabner's first assistant, as the next attorney general. If confirmed, Ms. Milgram, 36, would become one of the youngest attorneys general in state history.</p>
        <p>The selection of Mr. Rabner had been widely expected for months by the Trenton establishment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine was asked in a recent interview whether he wanted to nominate someone who would serve a long time and leave an imprint on the Court, much as the 52-year-old chief justice of the United States Supreme Court, John G. Roberts Jr., is expected to do, or to make a short-term appointment, like that of the state's current chief justice, James R. Zazzali, who will be 70 on June 17. The governor replied, ''Let me put you out of your misery: longer term.''</p>
        <p>Since he took office in January 2006, Mr. Corzine, a liberal Democrat, has talked frequently about how the State Supreme Court -- historically regarded as one of the most progressive in the United States -- was inextricably linked to the state's budget because of landmark decisions on education, housing and other issues.</p>
        <p>The position may also be the most powerful state judgeship in America, because the chief justice is responsible for assigning all 453 judges of the Superior Court, Appellate Division and Tax Court, and for overseeing a statewide staff of about 9,000.</p>
        <p>''Stuart Rabner's tenure is potentially so long that he could touch every major issue imaginable: school funding, Mount Laurel housing, bonded indebtedness, death penalty and so on,'' said Peter G. Verniero, a former Supreme Court justice. ''It's a near endless list. It's not an exaggeration to say that this is potentially the most significant gubernatorial appointment since Robert Wilentz was appointed in 1979. From what I know of Stuart, he's up to the task.''</p>
        <p>If confirmed, an outcome that is considered likely, Mr. Rabner would follow a career arc similar to that of Mr. Zazzali's predecessor, Chief Justice Deborah T. Poritz, who was appointed by Gov. Christie Whitman after posts as a governor's chief counsel, then attorney general, and finally, chief justice.</p>
        <p>He would serve an initial seven-year term before being considered for a lifetime appointment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rabner, who grew up in Passaic and graduated from Princeton University and Harvard Law School, was head of the criminal division and terrorism unit of the United States attorney's office in Newark. He is highly regarded by Republicans and Democrats alike for his intellect, integrity and calm demeanor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine did not know Mr. Rabner well before becoming governor. But after working closely with him during the shutdown of the state government last July because of a budget impasse, and amid the furor surrounding Attorney General Zulima V. Farber, who resigned under an ethical cloud, Mr. Rabner has become one of the governor's most trusted confidants.</p>
        <p>If Ms. Milgram is nominated for attorney general, she, too, is expected to face little, if any, opposition. She was Mr. Corzine's counsel while he was in the United States Senate, and before that, was a lawyer in the civil rights division of the federal Department of Justice, successfully prosecuting cases of international human trafficking. An avid backpacker, Ms. Milgram graduated from Rutgers and New York University Law School, and tried her hand as a pastry apprentice at the restaurants Le Cirque and Osteria del Circo.</p>
        <p>State Senator John Adler, a Democrat of Camden County and chairman of the Judiciary Committee, said yesterday that he did not have direct knowledge of the appointments. But he noted that Mr. Corzine had invited committee members to Drumthwacket, the governor's mansion in Princeton, this morning.</p>
        <p>Senator Adler, who graduated from Harvard Law School a year before Mr. Rabner, said of his qualifications: ''I have a very high regard for Stuart Rabner as an attorney, as a public servant and as a person. And in whatever capacity he serves New Jersey, New Jersey is better off.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rabner is expected to return to Princeton this weekend for his 25th reunion, said Maria Gardner, a co-chairwoman of the reunion, and he is scheduled to take part in the discussion of an issue that is likely to resonate in a Rabner court: same-sex marriage.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
