<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Florida's Donovan Is Leaving for the Magic</title>
    <meta content="01donovan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851350"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Orlando Magic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE3D71530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Florida's Donovan Is Leaving for the Magic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETE THAMEL; Liz Robbins and Thayer Evans contributed reporting.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After leading Florida to consecutive men's national basketball titles, Coach Billy Donovan will accept an offer to become head coach of the Orlando Magic today.</p>
        <p>Donovan was expected to accept an offer for five years worth more than $5 million a year. A news conference is scheduled for 11 a.m. today in Orlando; Florida will hold a news conference at 4 p.m. A spokesman for the Magic declined to comment, saying the team would have nothing to say until its search for a coach was complete.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After leading Florida to consecutive men's national basketball titles, Coach Billy Donovan will accept an offer to become head coach of the Orlando Magic today.</p>
        <p>Donovan was expected to accept an offer for five years worth more than $5 million a year. A news conference is scheduled for 11 a.m. today in Orlando; Florida will hold a news conference at 4 p.m. A spokesman for the Magic declined to comment, saying the team would have nothing to say until its search for a coach was complete.</p>
        <p>The Florida athletic director, Jeremy Foley, was quoted at the Southeastern Conference meetings this week as saying that the university was very close to signing Donovan to a long-term deal. Donovan was expected to make about $3 million a year, making him one of the highest-paid coaches in college basketball. But Foley conceded last night.</p>
        <p>''We certainly wish this run could have gone on forever, it's been an incredible privilege to be a part of,'' Foley said.</p>
        <p>While Donovan, 42, had maintained that he was happy at Florida, he never ruled out going to the N.B.A. He said in an interview with The New York Times in February 2006 that he would like to become an N.B.A. assistant for a year to learn the nuances of the professional game before becoming a head coach. But Donovan has since won consecutive titles at Florida, increasing his value to N.B.A. teams.</p>
        <p>Many successful college coaches have failed recently in the N.B.A., including Donovan's friend and mentor Rick Pitino. But a big attraction to the Orlando job is that Donovan can build his team around Dwight Howard, one of the game's best young big men. Orlando also has $14 million available under the salary cap, which would enable the Magic to pursue both Vince Carter, who is expected to opt out of his contract with the Nets, and Rashard Lewis of Seattle in free agency.</p>
        <p>Donovan's legacy at Florida will be a strong one, having transformed the Gators from a basketball afterthought to an elite program in 11 seasons. He compiled a 261-103 record, prying SEC dominance from Kentucky with savvy recruiting and a relentless style of play.</p>
        <p>The move to the Magic would seem to make sense for Donovan, who lives 90 minutes from Orlando and whose family likes the area. The Magic made the playoffs this year after a three-year absence and have committed $146 million to building an arena.</p>
        <p>The likely favorite to succeed Donovan would be Anthony Grant, the Virginia Commonwealth coach. After serving as an assistant under Donovan for 10 years, Grant took over at Virginia Commonwealth last year and led the Rams to the N.C.A.A. tournament as a No. 11 seed. V.C.U. defeated sixth-seeded Duke in the first round before losing to No. 3 Pittsburgh in overtime.</p>
        <p>A message left for Grant was not immediately returned, but his wife said he might be reluctant to leave Virginia Commonwealth.</p>
        <p>''I am just so excited about what we were doing here,'' Christina Grant said in a telephone interview. ''To move, it just wouldn't  '' She paused. ''I feel tight right now. We have so much to do here.''</p>
        <p>The hiring of Grant could help Florida keep its highly regarded recruiting class. The small forward Adam Allen said he would still probably enroll at Florida, in part because Grant had recruited him before he left for V.C.U. ''He's a great coach and I have a lot of respect for him,'' Allen said in a telephone interview. One member of Florida's recruiting class, forward Alex Tyus, said he spoke to Donovan last night for about 15 minutes.</p>
        <p>Tyus said that Donovan wanted Grant to be his replacement.</p>
        <p>''He said that right now they are trying to hire Coach Grant to see if he will come back to Florida,'' Tyus said. ''He said that he wanted to try and get him.''</p>
        <p>Tyus also said he was not surprised that Donovan would move.</p>
        <p>''He said it always intrigued him to coach in the N.B.A,'' Tyus said. ''He wanted everyone to understand that and that it was a good situation where Orlando was close to him. It just came at a good time for him.''</p>
        <p>PACERS HIRE O'BRIEN -- Jim O'Brien was hired yesterday as coach of the Indiana Pacers, who turned to an N.B.A. veteran in hopes of reviving a team that missed the playoffs for the first time in a decade.</p>
        <p>The announcement ended a five-week search that began with the firing of Rick Carlisle.</p>
        <p>O'Brien has coached in Boston and Philadelphia, compiling a 182-158 record in five seasons. He has been out of coaching since he was fired by the 76ers after the 2005 season. (AP)</p>
        <p>GRIZZLIES TAKE IAVARONI -- Marc Iavaroni, an assistant with the Phoenix Suns for the past five years, was hired yesterday as coach of the Memphis Grizzlies, who went 22-60 last season after three consecutive trips to the N.B.A. playoffs. (AP)</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
