<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The, Uh, Joy of Digging Ditches</title>
    <meta content="01ritual" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/travel/escapes/01ritual.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851232"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="RITUALS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Irrigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pipe</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rinehart, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Irrigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Irrigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E0DC1530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="992" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The, Uh, Joy of Digging Ditches</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The, Uh, Joy of Digging Ditches</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN RINEHART</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rinehart, Steven</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Steven Rinehart Rituals column on joys of digging ditches in his yard for underground drainage pipe, plastic irrigation lines and electrical conduit; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MY neighbor in Ulster County, N.Y., is a great gardener who can toss off the Latin name for most everything on his 10-acre spread without a moment's hesitation. Another friend of mine is a terrific gardener, too -- ''a guy gave me this,'' he's always saying, ''and I just stuck it in the ground and now look at it go.'' The carpenter down the road effortlessly coaxes stone into beautiful snaking walls rivaling those that have stood there for 200 years. Tourists stop and take pictures of them.</p>
        <p>My garden may resemble a 7-year-old who's just given himself a haircut, and the stone wall on our property may look a bit disgruntled (my wife built it when she was eight months pregnant). But I am good at something outdoorsy and rural -- although perhaps unfortunately for me, it's practically invisible.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>To dig a suitable irrigation ditch, whether it be buried pipe or, say, a French drain, there are essentially four steps, each with its own tool.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MY neighbor in Ulster County, N.Y., is a great gardener who can toss off the Latin name for most everything on his 10-acre spread without a moment's hesitation. Another friend of mine is a terrific gardener, too -- ''a guy gave me this,'' he's always saying, ''and I just stuck it in the ground and now look at it go.'' The carpenter down the road effortlessly coaxes stone into beautiful snaking walls rivaling those that have stood there for 200 years. Tourists stop and take pictures of them.</p>
        <p>My garden may resemble a 7-year-old who's just given himself a haircut, and the stone wall on our property may look a bit disgruntled (my wife built it when she was eight months pregnant). But I am good at something outdoorsy and rural -- although perhaps unfortunately for me, it's practically invisible.</p>
        <p>I'm a crackerjack ditch digger. Buried in my two-acre parcel are no fewer than 300 feet of perforated drainage pipe, plastic irrigation lines and electrical conduit.</p>
        <p>I've got underground pipe leading from each of my gutter downspouts at least 20 feet out into the yard. I've got two wells, an old dug well and a newer drilled one, and I'm contemplating putting in a third just for the chance to run the service connections out to it. It's not that I need a third well; my elaborate underground irrigation system has so many branches a schematic of it would resemble the genealogy of the Windsors. Whatever ails my garden, it's not the lack of readily available moisture.</p>
        <p>Fascination with ditches, digging and drainage seems to be part of my DNA. My grandfather dug ditches for the W.P.A. during the Depression. My father carved countless trenches out of the Korean countryside; I still have his handy little fold-up entrenching tool.</p>
        <p>My own contribution to the family obsession, however, is less History Channel and more HGTV. The only real drama in my version is the habit of impulsively purchasing pipe from Lowe's, racing home and then burying it in the ground before buyer's remorse sets in.</p>
        <p>Perhaps because of his own father, my dad had a thorough respect for the craft of ditch digging, even though he had a master's degree. There are, he taught me, a right way and a wrong way to dig a ditch. The wrong way includes using anything hydraulic, gas-powered or pneumatic. A real ditch is an agreement among an individual and his or her own hands, back and knees. It makes no difference if the ditch is in the middle of a wilderness or one's own suburban backyard -- the essentials are the same.</p>
        <p>To dig a suitable irrigation ditch, whether it be buried pipe or, say, a French drain (two grades of gravel buried along a course and left uncovered), there are essentially four steps, each with its own tool.</p>
        <p>First you use a spade to mark out and set aside sod. Next you remove soil by alternating between a pick and long-handled shovel, with the occasional tamping iron to prize out fieldstone. This is the longest step -- dig, toss, dig, toss.</p>
        <p>Then comes crumbing and shaving; crumbing is the careful removal of loose stone and dirt, usually with a flat-bottomed shovel like a coal scoop, and shaving is the flattening of the ditch floor to create an even bed for the pipe.</p>
        <p>Shaving is done with a gardener's hoe and the aforementioned spade, this time used nearly parallel to the ground -- ''like a pool player lining up a shot,'' my father used to say. A poor drainage ditch viewed in cross-section resembles a U; a proper ditch is box-shaped. A proper ditch is something in which it is a pleasure to lay a length of pipe.</p>
        <p>For the ditch-digging enthusiast, however, there isn't a more unfortunate place to work than the Catskills. My property is essentially a slightly slanted rock formation onto which a retreating glacier reluctantly dribbled some topsoil and, a few thousand years later, some incurable optimist built a farmhouse. The soil itself is a sandy and acidic stew of scalloped bluestone, fieldstones the size of microwave ovens, and the sort of strong and tenacious roots that keep hardwood trees from toppling over in such inhospitable terrain.</p>
        <p>And that's not the end of it. My house is situated in a marshy spot of Ulster County known as the Vly, from the Dutch word for valley, but better translated as ''Seattle.'' Like a thousand-acre version of Al Capp's Joe Btfsplk, the Vly seems to always sport a mantle of gray clouds and its accompanying sad drizzle.</p>
        <p>My father loved ditch digging, but he was a realist. When it started to rain, he climbed out of the trench. I'm a weekend-home owner, so I take what little time I have to dig as it comes, regardless of the weather.</p>
        <p>Crumbing in the driving rain is what panning for gold must have been like, except instead of precious metals lurking in the soupy trench there are drowning earthworms and hibernating grubs the size and complexion of uncooked shrimp. I have no idea why I love it so.</p>
        <p>Luckily for them, none of my children seem to have inherited the family fascination. They watch my ditch digging with their own individual expressions of incomprehension and pity. Each has visited me during a project, brought me a beverage or a bandage, but none has ever stayed. They're content to lie on the hammock, ride their bikes and swing on the swing set. They know how to take it easy. When it rains, they watch videos and play Scrabble.</p>
        <p>THAT was true, anyway, until one weekend not too long ago, when it finally happened -- one of the children snapped. My younger daughter, age 8, without the slightest coaxing, walked out into a steady drizzle and steadfastly and against all my entreaties -- and with nothing but her bare hands -- began to construct a bluestone wall.</p>
        <p>She gets it from her mother.</p>
        <p>RITUALS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
