<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who Likes the Immigration Bill?; The Two-Year Solution</title>
    <meta content="01lind" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/opinion/01lind.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851304"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Immigrants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Citizenship</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Residence Requirements</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lind, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Citizenship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Citizenship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E4D81530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="418" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who Likes the Immigration Bill?; The Two-Year Solution</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Two-Year Solution</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michael Lind</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lind, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Lind Op-Ed article proposes lowering residency requirement for legal immigrants who seek to become US citizens from five years to two; holds that making law-abiding immigrants citizens more quickly would clear way for enforceable amnesty later; argues that all Americans would benefit from faster naturalization process because it would shrink number of non-citizens living in US and would prevent two-tier labor market (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH the new immigration package already beginning to unravel, it would be wonderful if we could find one element of reform that everyone involved in the immigration debate can agree on.</p>
        <p>Here's my candidate: lower the residency requirement for legal immigrants who seek to become citizens from five years to two.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>All Americans would benefit from a speeded-up naturalization process that rapidly shrinks the number of non-citizens living and working on American soil.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH the new immigration package already beginning to unravel, it would be wonderful if we could find one element of reform that everyone involved in the immigration debate can agree on.</p>
        <p>Here's my candidate: lower the residency requirement for legal immigrants who seek to become citizens from five years to two.</p>
        <p>This is not a new idea. In fact, it's 217 years old. In 1790, Congress passed the first naturalization act, which imposed a two-year residency requirement for legal immigrants. Alarmed by the French Revolution, Congress subsequently changed the residency requirement to five years with the Naturalization Act of 1795. Growing fear of foreign infiltration during the wars of the French Revolution inspired Congress to enact the Naturalization Act of 1798, which increased the residency requirement to 14 years and permitted the president to deport dangerous aliens.</p>
        <p>In addition to worrying about subversive Frenchmen, Federalist Party lawmakers wanted to deny suffrage to Irish immigrants, who tended to vote for their rivals, the Jeffersonian Republicans. After Thomas Jefferson was elected president, his allies in Congress in 1802 reduced the residency requirement. And that's why, 200 years later, legal immigrants cannot become naturalized citizens unless they reside for five years in the United States, with at least half of that time spent physically on United States soil.</p>
        <p>Why, one might ask, should we shorten the residency requirement now? Think of it this way. There are roughly 10 million foreign-born legal permanent residents in the United States today -- nearly as many as the estimated number of illegal immigrants. Shortening the residency requirement would accelerate their naturalization.</p>
        <p>This, in turn, would make amnesty or earned citizenship for most of the illegal immigrants already living here easier down the road. It would be unfair suddenly to grant citizenship to those who have broken the rules, allowing them to leapfrog over those who have waited patiently in line to become citizens. Solution: make the law-abiding immigrants citizens more quickly, in order to clear the way for an enforceable amnesty later.</p>
        <p>This wouldn't be a boon just for legal immigrants and many illegal immigrants -- all Americans would benefit from a speeded-up naturalization process that rapidly shrinks the number of non-citizens living and working on American soil. We don't want a two-tier labor market in this country, with non-citizen workers with limited rights pitted against citizen-workers with full rights.</p>
        <p>The Congress of 1790, which included many of the founders, got it right. We can, too -- especially now that the French Revolution is over.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Michael Lind is a fellow at the New America Foundation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Michael Lind is a fellow at the New America Foundation.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
