<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Book the Met Wasn't Ready for, It Seems</title>
    <meta content="01nyc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/nyregion/01nyc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851244"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Metropolitan Museum of Art</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Weber, Nicholas Fox</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E7D91530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="771" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Book the Met Wasn't Ready for, It Seems</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Book the Met Wasn’t Ready for, It Seems</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nicholas Fox Weber believed a deal had been struck, but we will get to that in a moment.</p>
        <p>First, let's establish that Mr. Weber has written a new book, ''The Clarks of Cooperstown,'' about a New York family of great wealth with roots in the upstate town that is home to the Baseball Hall of Fame. The Clarks are an intriguing bunch. Some of them surely qualify as eccentric. (If you're poor and act funny, you're nuts. Rich people are eccentric.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An author suggests the Metropolitan Museum of Art practiced censorship when it decided not to sell copies of his book that had undercurrents of gay behavior.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nicholas Fox Weber believed a deal had been struck, but we will get to that in a moment.</p>
        <p>First, let's establish that Mr. Weber has written a new book, ''The Clarks of Cooperstown,'' about a New York family of great wealth with roots in the upstate town that is home to the Baseball Hall of Fame. The Clarks are an intriguing bunch. Some of them surely qualify as eccentric. (If you're poor and act funny, you're nuts. Rich people are eccentric.)</p>
        <p>The family patriarch, Edward Cabot Clark, made bundles in the mid-19th century by having the wit to partner with Isaac Merritt Singer, as in Singer sewing machine. Clark also invested in real estate in Cooperstown and in Manhattan, including a brooding structure on Central Park West that came to be called the Dakota.</p>
        <p>Edward's son, Alfred Corning Clark, married and had four sons. But he wasn't captivated by sewing machines or, it seems, his marriage. He preferred life in Europe, Paris in particular, where he lavished money and considerable attention on artists who, apparently by no coincidence, were young men.</p>
        <p>Two of Alfred's sons, Sterling and Stephen, had a falling-out and didn't speak to each other for decades. But both inherited their father's aesthetic impulse and became prodigious collectors of art: Cézanne, Renoir, Picasso, Hopper, Matisse, van Gogh, Seurat -- the impressive list goes on.</p>
        <p>Sterling was a piece of work. In the 1930s he was accused of plotting a coup with Wall Street types, the idea being to replace President Franklin D. Roosevelt with a figure more to their liking, someone on the order of Mussolini. To make sure that neither the government nor his brothers got their hands on his art collection, Sterling built the Sterling and Francine Clark Art Institute in Williamstown, Mass.</p>
        <p>For his part, Stephen was a trustee of both the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Museum of Modern Art in New York.</p>
        <p>Last week, the Met opened an exhibition of paintings collected by the rivalrous brothers. This is where Mr. Weber and his 420-page book on the Clarks enter the frame.</p>
        <p>He had, in his words, knocked himself out to finish writing in time for the exhibition because, he said, the museum had agreed to carry his book in its store. That was the deal. His editor at Alfred A. Knopf, Victoria Wilson, said, ''There was no question that book would be sold at the Met.''</p>
        <p>AFTER the exhibition opened, Mr. Weber went to the museum. No book, nowhere. Contrary to his expectations, ''I was told at the main bookstore that it was policy not to sell it,'' said Mr. Weber, who is executive director of the Josef and Anni Albers Foundation, an institution dedicated to the visual arts, in Bethany, Conn.</p>
        <p>His discovery struck his editor as strange. In fact, ''she was outraged,'' Mr. Weber said. Ms. Wilson nosed around and learned, she said, that some eyebrows at the museum had been raised by the book's undercurrents of gay behavior.</p>
        <p>That was a turn that she and Mr. Weber found more than strange. It's not as if hints of 19th-century homosexuality are bound to give many New Yorkers the vapors.</p>
        <p>''Why the Met in 2007 would be so put off by this element of the book is astonishing,'' Mr. Weber said.</p>
        <p>In any event, he said, he was told by a Met employee that the word going around the museum was that his book, once judged to be worthy, had now been deemed sub-par. And should museum-goers ask about it, the correct response was to ''feign ignorance.''</p>
        <p>''To me, it qualifies completely as censorship,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Strong words, strong enough to ask the Met what gives.</p>
        <p>''There's not much of a story here,'' and certainly no censorship, said a spokesman, Harold Holzer. The Weber book, he said, was held back merely as a ''marketing strategy'' to help sales of the catalog for the Clark show. Copies of the book have been ordered, Mr. Holzer said, and should be in the museum store next week.</p>
        <p>So that should be that: Another controversy with an ''only in New York'' flavor, brought to light and resolved.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Weber found himself ''still appalled'' yesterday, convinced that the Met's sudden change of heart was ''simply an attempt to avoid bad publicity.''</p>
        <p>Of course, we felt obliged to note that publicity, good or bad, happens to be in his own book-selling interest. A fair point, Mr. Weber acknowledged, but not the issue. ''I have a slightly self-righteous side,'' he said, ''and when I feel there is an element of wrongdoing, it really gets to me.''</p>
        <p>NYC E-mail: haberman@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: haberman@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
