<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wachovia in a $6.8 Billion Deal to Acquire A.G. Edwards</title>
    <meta content="01broker" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/business/01broker.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851263"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="STREET SCENE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Edwards, A G, &amp; Sons</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wachovia Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Merrill Lynch &amp; Co Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dash, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Wachovia Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E4D91530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="805" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wachovia in a $6.8 Billion Deal to Acquire A.G. Edwards</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Wachovia in Deal to Acquire A.G. Edwards</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC DASH; Peter Edmonston contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dash, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wachovia Corp acquires A G Edwards in $6.8 billion cash and stock deal that highlights continued consolidation of retail brokerage sector; move aims to expand Wachovia's reach in securities business as it faces more difficult times in other parts of banking industry; deal will make Wachovia Securities country's second-largest retail broker after Merrill Lynch; graph; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the brokerage business was populated by dozens of small companies, three firms in St. Louis made the city the industry's biggest center west of Wall Street. Now, only two remain independent.</p>
        <p>The Wachovia Corporation swallowed up A. G. Edwards yesterday in a $6.8 billion cash and stock deal that highlights the continued consolidation of the retail brokerage sector.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The deal will form the second-largest retail stock brokerage firm in the U.S. after Merrill Lynch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the brokerage business was populated by dozens of small companies, three firms in St. Louis made the city the industry's biggest center west of Wall Street. Now, only two remain independent.</p>
        <p>The Wachovia Corporation swallowed up A. G. Edwards yesterday in a $6.8 billion cash and stock deal that highlights the continued consolidation of the retail brokerage sector.</p>
        <p>Bringing together more than $1.1 trillion in client assets and nearly 15,000 advisers, the move aims to expand Wachovia's reach in the securities business as it faces more difficult times in other parts of the banking industry.</p>
        <p>The deal will make Wachovia Securities the country's second-largest retail broker after Merrill Lynch, allowing it to take advantage of the cost efficiencies that come with size and to sell bank products to a bigger base of affluent clients. It also could enhance the capabilities of its fledgling investment bank, giving clients access to a broader network of retail investors for distributing new securities offerings.</p>
        <p>''This is an end game for us,'' G. Kennedy Thompson, Wachovia's chairman and chief executive, said on a conference call with investors. ''We have everything that we need to grow this business organically.''</p>
        <p>For A. G. Edwards, the deal is the end of an era. Ever since a friend of Abraham Lincoln founded the securities firm more than 120 years ago, it remained fiercely independent. Until the last several years, it was run by a member of the Edwards family.</p>
        <p>It was also among the last of the brokerage firms to focus mainly on distributing, not manufacturing, investment products. And over the years, it developed a reputation for standing by its brokers during market downturns even when rivals cut their ranks.</p>
        <p>But the industry's underlying economics have changed. Investors are increasingly turning to bigger firms like UBS and Morgan Stanley, which offer more attractive prices and a broader set of investment products. Others are heading to online and discount brokerage firms, where they pay even lower commission fees to execute trades.</p>
        <p>''We knew we needed scale, we knew we needed additional products as financial services continues to migrate toward a global platform,'' said Robert L. Bagby, the company's chief executive, during the conference call. ''We could not provide that at A. G. Edwards. We didn't have the capital base.''</p>
        <p>They may not be the only ones. Among the major regional brokerage houses, only firms like Edward Jones, its privately held crosstown rival, and Raymond James, a Florida-based broker, are left. Shares of Raymond James rose more than 7 percent yesterday on speculation that it could be taken over next.</p>
        <p>Wachovia's offer yesterday involves a significant outlay of cash and stock. It calls for shareholders of A. G. Edwards to get 0.9844 Wachovia shares and $35.80 in cash for every A. G. Edwards share, giving shareholders a 16 percent premium over Wednesday's closing price. The deal is expected to close in early October, executives said.</p>
        <p>The combined retail brokerage business will operate out of St. Louis, while A. G. Edwards's other lines of business, including stock research and investment banking, will be folded into the bank's current operations.</p>
        <p>Wachovia, formed through a series of mergers over the years, has earned a reputation as an acquisition machine. Last year, it bought Golden West Financial, one of the last major independent banks on the West Coast, in a $26 billion deal. And it has steadily built its securities business by piecing together smaller firms.</p>
        <p>The deal for A. G. Edwards is the latest big grab for the Wachovia brokerage unit, which nearly doubled in size through a 2003 joint venture with Prudential Financial.</p>
        <p>Still the latest deal also presents integration challenges. Bank executives say that they expect to eliminate as many as 4,000 employees, or about a quarter of the combined total work force, and close about 230 branches over a three-year period.</p>
        <p>But the biggest hurdle, analysts say, may be holding on to its advisers. Competitors are already on the prowl, and turnover is typically rampant during transitions.</p>
        <p>Wachovia said that it planned to offer large retention packages to the A. G. Edwards brokers and keep top managers from both companies. While Daniel J. Ludeman, currently president and chief executive of Wachovia Securities, will continue in those roles at the combined brokerage firm, Mr. Bagby, 65, will be chairman.</p>
        <p>Although A. G. Edwards executives are not entitled to any change-in-control payouts, the deal will allow its managers and directors to cash out millions of dollars in stock and options. At $89.50, Mr. Bagby has shares worth $14.5 million.</p>
        <p>One of the big winners in the deal appears to be a former University of Maryland finance professor and a longtime A. G. Edwards director, E. Eugene Carter, who holds more than 230,000 shares. That stake could be worth $20.6 million.</p>
        <p>STREET SCENE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
