<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pentagon Files Offer Details On Detainee In Suicide</title>
    <meta content="01gitmo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/us/01gitmo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851300"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hunger Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hunger Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Guantanamo Bay Naval Base (Cuba)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E5D81530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pentagon Files Offer Details On Detainee In Suicide</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pentagon Files Offer Details on Detainee in Suicide</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GLABERSON and MARGOT WILLIAMS; Tim Golden contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Golden, Tim; Williams, Margot; Glaberson, William</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Guantánamo detainee who apparently committed suicide on Wednesday was a persistent hunger striker, at one point dropping his weight to 88.5 pounds, government documents indicate.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the Pentagon identified the man as a 34-year-old former member of the Saudi armed forces, Abdul Rahman Ma'ath Thafir al-Amri, and suggested that officials had held him in one of stricter areas at Guantánamo Bay, Cuba, Camp 5, because of a need to control him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Guantánamo detainee who apparently committed suicide on Wednesday was a persistent hunger striker, government documents indicate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Guantánamo detainee who apparently committed suicide on Wednesday was a persistent hunger striker, at one point dropping his weight to 88.5 pounds, government documents indicate.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the Pentagon identified the man as a 34-year-old former member of the Saudi armed forces, Abdul Rahman Ma'ath Thafir al-Amri, and suggested that officials had held him in one of stricter areas at Guantánamo Bay, Cuba, Camp 5, because of a need to control him.</p>
        <p>Fragmentary documents in the public Guantánamo files have a sketchy picture of the man whose death, after three suicides in June, has became a flashpoint in the debate over the detention policies.</p>
        <p>Military officials said yesterday that Mr. Amri had been a midlevel Qaeda operative with direct ties to higher-level members, including meeting Osama bin Laden, and had fought United States forces in the Tora Bora mountains.</p>
        <p>Beyond acknowledging that he had died of an ''apparent suicide,'' the officials did not give details of Mr. Amri's death, saying an autopsy would be performed. The documents suggest that he was part of a chronic struggle between the military jailers at Guantánamo and an unknown number of detainees who have challenged that control with long-running hunger strikes.</p>
        <p>The hunger strikes and other resistance in the camps have brought periodic crackdowns by the military, especially over the last year, including the use of feeding chairs. Persistent hunger strikers are strapped in so they can be fed a nutrient formula through a plastic tube inserted in a nostril.</p>
        <p>In April, the military said 12 detainees were being force fed. Some detainees' lawyers have said the total number of hunger strikers might be much higher. It is not know whether Mr. Amri was force fed.</p>
        <p>As his history began to emerge, it brought a predictable exchange between the government and critics. The American Civil Liberties Union, Amnesty International and the Center for Constitutional Rights were among the groups condemning the loss of life, blaming detention policies and calling for investigations.</p>
        <p>''The sad truth is we can guarantee there will be more deaths,'' said Clive Stafford Smith, legal director of Reprieve, an international group that provides legal representation to 35 detainees, including several Saudis.</p>
        <p>Jose Ruiz, a spokesman for the United States Southern Command in Miami, which controls the joint task force at Guantánamo, said, ''The men and women of Joint Task Force Guantánamo conduct their mission professionally and humanely.''</p>
        <p>The death seemed to challenge an image promoted by military officials that Guantánamo had entered a relatively calm period. Despite criticism from human rights groups and others of the steps that the military has taken to clamp down on security, the military leadership at Guantánamo has appeared confident that their approach had not increased the risk of prisoner suicides.</p>
        <p>''I think it's simply better conditions of detention for the detainees, and less communication between the camps themselves, '' Rear Adm. Harry B. Harris Jr. said last month, as he stepped down as commander at Guantánamo.</p>
        <p>In an interview with The New York Times on May 21, Admiral Harris said the number of hunger strikers, discipline cases and ''self-harm gestures'' was declining.</p>
        <p>Mr. Amri is not believed to have had a lawyer. So much about his time at Guantánamo is unknown.</p>
        <p>Some details are apparent from documents. Detainee weight charts released by the Pentagon this year because of a lawsuit show that when he arrived in February 2002, Mr. Amri weighed 150 pounds. A downward spiral in 2005 included a November weigh-in at 88 1/2 pounds. Last February, another detainee, in a letter to his lawyer, listed Mr. Amri as a hunger striker in Camp 5.</p>
        <p>The public record of the accusations against Mr. Amri show contradictory and inconclusive elements like many of the detainees' cases.</p>
        <p>An American officer who was appointed his personal representative said at a hearing that Mr. Amri was a jihadist. The officer added that Mr. Amri believed that the military was making a mistake in detaining him, an undated summary of the representative's statement shows.</p>
        <p>Mr. Amri said Americans had trained him while he was in the Saudi army for nine years. As a result, he said, it made no sense that he would have gone to Afghanistan to kill Americans.</p>
        <p>''He could have done that while he was side by side with them in Saudi Arabia,'' the officer said.</p>
        <p>He acknowledged that he had seen Mr. bin Laden, but said it was ''from a distance,'' the representative reported.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
