<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mauresmo Rallies and Carries the Flag to the Third Round</title>
    <meta content="01tennis" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/sports/tennis/01tennis.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851345"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Mauresmo, Amelie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hewitt, Lleyton</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Dechy, Nathalie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E4D71530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mauresmo Rallies and Carries the Flag to the Third Round</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mauresmo Rallies and Carries the Flag to the Third Round</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIET MACUR</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, May 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the middle of Amélie Mauresmo's match here Thursday, a spectator yelled ''Vive la France!'' and laughter rippled through the packed Court Philippe Chatrier.</p>
        <p>Evidently, that fan was not picky about which player won the second-round match. Mauresmo, the fifth seed, and her competitor, Nathalie Dechy, are both French.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Amélie Mauresmo beat Nathalie Dechy in a close, three-set match that was completed only after a two-hour rain delay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the middle of Amélie Mauresmo's match here Thursday, a spectator yelled ''Vive la France!'' and laughter rippled through the packed Court Philippe Chatrier.</p>
        <p>Evidently, that fan was not picky about which player won the second-round match. Mauresmo, the fifth seed, and her competitor, Nathalie Dechy, are both French.</p>
        <p>On the streets of Paris, though, there has definitely been a favorite. In the weeks leading to the French Open, Mauresmo said she heard encouragement from her compatriots who passed her around town. They shouted ''Roland Garros is yours this year!'' and ''We are counting on you!''</p>
        <p>In the past, before Mauresmo had won two Grand Slam tournaments, those words piled pressure upon her.</p>
        <p>''I had a lot of trouble with people saying those things to me, when it was earlier in my career,'' she said. ''Now I just say: 'Thank you, I'll try to win for you. I'll do my best.' Things are very different now.''</p>
        <p>Mauresmo is much more relaxed after winning two majors last year. On Thursday, it took her only two sets to reach that state of mind against Dechy, whom she has known for nearly 20 years.</p>
        <p>After a close, three-set match that was completed after a two-hour rain delay, Mauresmo won, 6-3, 6-7 (3), 6-1. The French still have hope that one of their own will win the women's title this year.</p>
        <p>Mauresmo is one of three Frenchwomen -- and one of eight French singles players -- to advance to the third round. The best she has done here has been to reach the quarterfinals, twice.</p>
        <p>The last Frenchwoman to win this tournament was Mary Pierce in 2000, when she became the first to do so in 33 years. Yannick Noah was the last Frenchman to win, in 1983. Before that, Marcel Bernard won in 1946.</p>
        <p>So fans were ready, and hungry, for Mauresmo's match against Dechy. They chanted ''Am-é-lie! then ''Nat-a-lie!'' as the two began to play in the sunshine that has been rare here this week.</p>
        <p>Mauresmo, 27, and Dechy, 28, grew up playing junior tennis against each other, and they remain close friends. Mauresmo said Dechy would regularly win when they were young. But now, she said, ''That is no longer the case.''</p>
        <p>It came close to tipping Dechy's way on Thursday, particularly in the second set. After the rain delay, Dechy won three quick points of a tie breaker to win the second set. But Dechy struggled in the third set, later saying she had problems with the conditions. It was also complicated, she said, to play such a good friend in such a fierce match. The two had played five times before as professionals. Mauresmo now leads, 4-2.</p>
        <p>''It's never easy, because most of the time we used to more practice together than to play matches,'' said Dechy, still frowning because of the loss. ''But I just try to forget it, and as I said before the match, do my best.''</p>
        <p>Last year, in her 12th year of playing Grand Slams, Mauresmo finally became a champion of not one, but two majors, winning the Australian Open and Wimbledon. In between, she sputtered here, reaching only the fourth round. She is now set to play Lucie Safarova, the No. 25 seed, in the third round, which will give her time to rest after her two-and-a-half hour match against Dechy.</p>
        <p>Lleyton Hewitt, however, may need more time to rebound from his match on Thursday. About an hour afterward, his face was still glowing red from the sun and the exertion of his three-and-a-half hour match against Gaston Gaudio, the 2004 French Open champion.</p>
        <p>But Hewitt did not mind the marathon match. He needed the extra time.</p>
        <p>Hewitt, the No. 14 seed, recovered from a two-set deficit to beat Gaudio and advanced to the third round, 4-6, 3-6, 6-2, 6-4, 6-2. Only three other times in his nine years on the Tour has he accomplished a similar feat. Afterward, he walked through the players' restaurant with his year-old daughter, Mia, in his arms, both of them smiling wide.</p>
        <p>''He's got to be one of the toughest second-round players to play,'' Hewitt said. ''You just don't really know what you're going to get from him. So at first, he played fantastically.''</p>
        <p>Hewitt, 26, has won the United States Open and Wimbledon, but has made it to the quarterfinals of the French Open only twice.</p>
        <p>Even though he missed two months this year because of a back injury, Hewitt was able to hang on. After losing the first two sets, he looked across the net and saw the stoic Gaudio become slower and slower. At the same time, Hewitt began to feel better, his energy rising.</p>
        <p>''At the end, I couldn't control the match anymore,'' said Gaudio, who went from No. 5 in the world two years ago to No. 72 now. ''It is true that I fought very hard. Even in the fifth set, I can tell you that I pulled out all the stops to get out of this tricky situation.''</p>
        <p>Although Hewitt and Gaudio's match seemed to last forever, it still managed to beat the rain that postponed several matches until later in the day.</p>
        <p>By nightfall, after play had resumed, several top-seeded players won: the two-time defending champion Rafael Nadal defeated Flavio Cipolla; No. 3 Svetlana Kuznetsova beat Meghann Shaughnessy; and No. 2 Maria Sharapova defeated Jill Craybas. No. 8 Serena Williams was dominant against Milagros Sequera in the first set and went on to win, 6-0, 7-6 (3).</p>
        <p>On Friday, though rain is expected, the matches will continue, including that of Mauresmo and Dechy, who will play doubles together.</p>
        <p>Though opponents for an afternoon, they returned everything to normal once their singles match had ended. At the net, they kissed each other on both cheeks.</p>
        <p>''It's a hard thing to play a good friend,'' Mauresmo said. ''But I just told her to check the schedule for doubles. After that, life went on.''</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
