<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Teacher's Novel, and His Departure, Stir Up a Bronx School</title>
    <meta content="01teacher" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/nyregion/01teacher.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851340"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E5D71530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="682" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Teacher's Novel, and His Departure, Stir Up a Bronx School</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Teacher’s Novel, and Its Aftermath, Stir Up a Bronx School</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SEWELL CHAN; David M. Herszenhorn contributed reporting.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A furor has erupted at a New York City private high school over a history teacher's satirical novel, his impending departure and, now, accusations that administrators barred the student newspaper from publishing a letter by prominent historians and scholars who had come to the teacher's defense.</p>
        <p>The controversy, which has divided teachers, parents and students at the Horace Mann School, a private school in the Riverdale section of the Bronx, erupted this week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A furor has erupted at private high school over a history teacher’s satirical novel and accusations that the school barred the student newspaper from publishing a letter defending the teacher.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A furor has erupted at a New York City private high school over a history teacher's satirical novel, his impending departure and, now, accusations that administrators barred the student newspaper from publishing a letter by prominent historians and scholars who had come to the teacher's defense.</p>
        <p>The controversy, which has divided teachers, parents and students at the Horace Mann School, a private school in the Riverdale section of the Bronx, erupted this week.</p>
        <p>The Record, the student newspaper, published an editors' note on Wednesday stating that the head of the school, Thomas M. Kelly, had forbidden the editors from publishing two letters and an opinion essay concerning the case of the history teacher, Andrew S. Trees.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kelly did not respond to telephone messages left at his office late yesterday, and Dr. Trees did not respond to messages left at his home and with his parents.</p>
        <p>Dr. Trees had published a novel last year, ''Academy X,'' that poked fun at the mores and foibles of affluent children and their overbearing parents at a fictional elite school. His narrator, a teacher named John Spencer, calls the school an ''ethical wonderland'' and laments the antics of Caitlyn Brie, a pampered student at the school.</p>
        <p>(Reviewing the novel in The New York Times last year, Michiko Kakutani wrote, ''In the early pages of this novel Mr. Trees demonstrates inklings of a Kingsley Amis-like ability to extract humor from the travails of his hapless hero, but any hopes that the book might become a 'Lucky Jim'-ish romp are soon squashed by his preposterous plot and John's tedious class rage at Caitlyn's parents and their ilk.'')</p>
        <p>Dr. Trees's annual contract to teach at the school was not renewed for the next school year, prompting an outcry from some teachers and students.</p>
        <p>In a letter to the student newspaper last week, a fellow history teacher, Peter P. Sheehy, wrote that the novel ''has angered some because the themes and issues he explores correspond very closely to issues with which we struggle.'' While some believe ''the novel reflects poor taste,'' he added, ''such critiques do not warrant the punishment of an author or artist who says something unpopular or controversial.''</p>
        <p>Last week, according to The Record, some 150 students signed a petition in defense of Dr. Trees. In an editors' note this week, The Record stated that it had received two letters and an opinion essay in response to Dr. Sheehy's letter, but that Dr. Kelly had prohibited their publication because '' 'personnel issues' should not be 'vetted' in the paper.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Gawker, a gossipy blog that often pokes fun at the Manhattan elite, published a copy of one of the allegedly censored letters. (The blog noted that The Record's incoming editor in chief, Elyssa Spitzer, is a daughter of Gov. Eliot Spitzer.)</p>
        <p>The Times also obtained a copy of the letter, which was signed by dozens of prominent historians, including Eric Foner of Columbia University, William H. Chafe of Duke University and Julian Bond of the University of Virginia, who is a former chairman of the N.A.A.C.P.</p>
        <p>''We were shocked and disappointed that the Horace Mann School would dismiss a faculty member for writing a novel, and we applaud the many Horace Mann students who courageously and thoughtfully protested this action,'' the letter stated.</p>
        <p>Dr. Trees graduated from Princeton in 1990 and received a doctorate in history from the University of Virginia in 1999. His dissertation adviser there, Peter S. Onuf, is among those who signed the letter.</p>
        <p>Andrew B. Lewis, a visiting assistant professor of history at Hamilton College in Clinton, N.Y., and a friend of Dr. Trees's from graduate school, said he was not surprised that so many would come to Dr. Trees's defense. ''Even if, on the surface, he's only a teacher at a prep school, people in the profession know and respect Andy Trees and are willing to sign onto this,'' Dr. Lewis said. ''Many of these are civil rights historians who are appalled at the notion that an institution would fire somebody for writing satire.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
