<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Congress Wants to Define Exactly What Abusive Tax Shelters Are</title>
    <meta content="01shelter" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/business/01shelter.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070602T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851265"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="STREET SCENE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Shelters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baucus, Max (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rangel, Charles B (Rep)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Browning, Lynnley</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tax Shelters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ernst &amp; Young</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <org class="online_producer">House of Representatives</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E4D91530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1298" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Congress Wants to Define Exactly What Abusive Tax Shelters Are</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Congress Wants to Define Exactly What Abusive Tax Shelters Are</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNNLEY BROWNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Browning, Lynnley</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Congress want to define exactly what abusive tax shelters are; efforts are aimed at reining in questionable tax shelters that have deprived government of hundreds of billions of dollars in taxes in recent years; proposal to define tax shelter abuse would go to Senate Finance Committee, led by Max Baucus and House Ways and Means, led by Charles B Rangel; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tax shelter business is under attack.</p>
        <p>And it is not just because of the three-year federal investigation into tax shelter fraud that resulted in the indictment of four current and former partners of the accounting firm Ernst &amp; Young this week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Efforts to raise the legal hurdle that determines whether a shelter is legitimate are again gaining traction in Congress.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The tax shelter business is under attack.</p>
        <p>And it is not just because of the three-year federal investigation into tax shelter fraud that resulted in the indictment of four current and former partners of the accounting firm Ernst &amp; Young this week.</p>
        <p>Efforts to raise the legal hurdle that determines whether a shelter is legitimate are again gaining traction in Congress after years of failed attempts, say senior tax lawyers and lobbyists. The efforts are aimed at reining in questionable tax shelters that have deprived the government of hundreds of billions of dollars in taxes in recent years.</p>
        <p>The hurdle is the doctrine of economic substance, a topic usually debated only in academic papers and arcane court rulings.</p>
        <p>The economic substance doctrine holds that a transaction must have genuine economic substance, as well as a legitimate business purpose other than tax savings, in order to reap a legitimate tax benefit.</p>
        <p>In other words, if a tax shelter does fancy footwork to follow, or appear to follow, the letter of the tax code but violates its spirit by existing mainly to generate tax deductions, then it is a sham shelter in the eyes of the Internal Revenue Service.</p>
        <p>Senate and House proponents argue that making the doctrine into a law, rather than keeping it a common sense principle and leaving its interpretation up to the courts, will make it easier to crack down on abusive shelters and raise billions of dollars, through proposals for stiff penalties.</p>
        <p>But critics, including most tax lawyers and tax professors, argue that the doctrine has worked well enough as it is, as evidenced by a string of high-profile I.R.S. victories in tax and federal courts on the issue.</p>
        <p>''Codifying it into law creates rigidity that defeats the function that the doctrine has played over the years,'' said Prof. Bernard Wolfman, a tax specialist at Harvard Law School. ''Codifying will cause us to look to the words and letters, rather than underlying spirit. Tax lawyers have no limits in their imagination, and once there's a rigid statement of it, people will seek to get around it, and there will be an 'it' to get around.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the move to write the standard into law is not supported by the I.R.S. and the Treasury Department.</p>
        <p>Donald L. Korb, chief counsel at the I.R.S., said in a brief telephone interview that converting the flexibility of the doctrine into the rigidity of law could provide a road map of sorts to questionable tax planners. ''I'm worried taxpayers would go right up to the edge; they will structure around the statutory rule,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That view is echoed by the Treasury Department. A spokesman said that ''this is something that should be used only in the courts, and codifying could pose some serious administrative and enforcement problems. Right now it is used case by case in the court, and we need to have it nuanced enough not to be a blanket provision.''</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, Christopher S. Rizek, a tax lawyer at Caplin &amp; Drysdale in Washington and a former senior tax policy official at the Treasury Department, said, ''I think it's pretty likely that a provision codifying economic substance will be enacted in this Congress, notwithstanding the doubts many practitioners and tax policy experts have expressed about it.''</p>
        <p>The push to crack down on questionable tax shelters has ramifications not only for the accounting firms, law firms and banks that have built a huge business in creating tax shelters for wealthy individuals, but also for large corporations, which increasingly rely on smart tax planning to bolster their profits.</p>
        <p>In recent years, a number of companies, including Coltec Industries, United Parcel Service and Black &amp; Decker, have had their tax shelters ruled invalid by courts because they did not meet the economic substance doctrine.</p>
        <p>The most recent example came last week, when H. J. Heinz lost its bid for a $42.6 million tax refund in the United States Court of Federal Claims, after the judge in the case ruled that the tax shelter used by the company to generate the claimed loss was a sham.</p>
        <p>The Heinz deal involved transfers of stock from Heinz to a subsidiary, HCC, in the mid-1990s, but the judge, Francis M. Allegra, wrote in his opinion that the shifts were intended to create artificial losses with tax benefits, and thus lacked economic substance.</p>
        <p>''This court will not don blinders to the realities of the transaction before it,'' Judge Allegra wrote in his opinion. ''Stripped of its veneer, the acquisition by HCC of the Heinz stock had one purpose, and one purpose alone -- producing capital losses that could be carried back to wipe out prior capital gains. There was no other genuine business purpose. As such, under the prevailing standard, the transaction in question must be viewed as a sham -- a transaction imbued with no significant tax-independent considerations, but rather characterized, at least in terms of HCC's participation, solely by tax-avoidance features.''</p>
        <p>Heinz has not yet decided whether it will appeal.</p>
        <p>What perhaps most upsets tax lawyers, policy analysts and officials are proposals in the current Senate and House versions to impose definitions of ''profit'' and ''risk'' when defining whether a transaction is legitimate. In a world of increasingly dizzying financial transactions involving complex derivatives and the like, such concepts can become tricky.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately, there's a lot of transactions that would now become suspect,'' said Robert Willens, an analyst with Lehman Brothers who covers corporate accounting and tax policies. He said that such legitimate and common transactions as liquidating a controlled subsidiary, conducting a spinoff for antitrust reasons, and stock repurchases through surplus funds could be deemed illegitimate if the economic substance doctrine were turned into a law with profit requirements. ''It would be a mess,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Tax practitioners are also upset about proposals to impose a 40 percent penalty on users of shelters or transactions found to violate the proposed economic substance laws -- an amount they consider draconian.</p>
        <p>Pressure to make economic substance a law is building in particular because a Joint Committee on Taxation has estimated that doing so could raise nearly $17 billion a year in unpaid taxes. With new ''pay as you go'' rules that now compel lawmakers not to increase the federal deficit with any new spending or tax proposals, lawmakers are looking for any money sources that can be directed to unrelated bills in education, for example.</p>
        <p>The Senate has passed several versions of an economic substance bill in recent years, and the Senate Finance Committee, which deals with tax legislation and whose chairman is Max Baucus, Democrat of Montana, indicated recently that it may soon try to stuff the bill into larger spending provisions. As for which provision and when, a committee spokeswoman, Carol Guthrie, said that ''everything is on the table.''</p>
        <p>The House has considered but not passed similar bills proposed by, among others, Representative Lloyd Doggett, Democrat of Texas, but that may change.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the House Ways and Means Committee, whose chairman is Charles B. Rangel, Democrat of New York, and which deals with tax legislation, said that ''it could certainly come up again in the context of paygo. But there's nothing on the immediate radar screen.''</p>
        <p>So the government's fight against abusive tax shelters may be influenced by factors not directly, or only, related to a desire to curb abusive shelters.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration opposes codification.</p>
        <p>But Lee Sheppard, a writer on tax issues for taxnotes.com, an influential trade publication, predicted that ''Congress will enact economic substance codification because a large revenue estimate has been attached to it.''</p>
        <p>She continued: ''In lots of bills, there are things the Bush administration doesn't like, and it signs them anyway. The question is, is this a deal breaker -- and I don't think it is.''</p>
        <p>STREET SCENE</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 2, 2007, Saturday  An article on the Street Scene page of Business Day yesterday about Congressional efforts to rein in tax shelters referred incompletely to a tax shelter case involving United Parcel Service. Although a federal court did indeed rule that U.P.S. engaged in sham transactions to avoid hundreds of millions of dollars in corporate income taxes, that ruling was rejected in 2001 by the United States Court of Appeals for the 11th Circuit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 2, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on the Street Scene page of Business Day yesterday about Congressional efforts to rein in tax shelters referred incompletely to a tax shelter case involving United Parcel Service. Although a federal court did indeed rule that U.P.S. engaged in sham transactions to avoid hundreds of millions of dollars in corporate income taxes, that ruling was rejected in 2001 by the United States Court of Appeals for the 11th Circuit.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
