<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dell to Lay Off 10% of Its Work Force</title>
    <meta content="01dell" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/technology/01dell.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851258"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Idc (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dell Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flynn, Laurie J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Dell Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5D91530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="767" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dell to Lay Off 10% of Its Work Force</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dell Reports Better-Than-Expected Profit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE J. FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flynn, Laurie J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dell will lay off 10 percent of its 88,100 employees over next 12 months as it tries to increase profit; also says that lower component costs and higher selling prices helped it produce stronger-than-expected earnings in its first quarter; net income was $759 million on $14.6 billion in revenue for its first quarter ended May 4; IDC says Dell's share of worldwide PC market dropped to 15.2 percent in first quarter from 18.2 percent last year; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dell said yesterday that it would lay off 10 percent of its 88,100 employees over the next 12 months as it tries to increase profit. The computer maker also said that lower component costs and higher selling prices helped it produce stronger-than-expected earnings in its first quarter.</p>
        <p>Dell surprised investors by reporting net income of $759 million, or 34 cents a share, on $14.6 billion in revenue for its first quarter that ended May 4. In the quarter last year Dell reported net income of $762 million, or 33 cents a share, on revenue of $14.2 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dell also announced that it would lay off 10 percent of its work force over the next year in order to reduce costs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dell said yesterday that it would lay off 10 percent of its 88,100 employees over the next 12 months as it tries to increase profit. The computer maker also said that lower component costs and higher selling prices helped it produce stronger-than-expected earnings in its first quarter.</p>
        <p>Dell surprised investors by reporting net income of $759 million, or 34 cents a share, on $14.6 billion in revenue for its first quarter that ended May 4. In the quarter last year Dell reported net income of $762 million, or 33 cents a share, on revenue of $14.2 billion.</p>
        <p>Wall Street analysts had been expecting Dell to report earnings of 26 cents a share on revenue of $13.95 billion, according to a survey by Thomson Financial. As a result, shares of Dell rose 5.9 percent in after-hours trading, to $28.49. It had closed at $26.91, up 2.6 percent in regular trading before Dell's earnings announcement.</p>
        <p>Although Dell has been losing market share to it competitors worldwide, the company said that the average selling price of its computers increased 14 percent during the quarter. It was also helped by particularly strong sales of computer servers, it said. Dell's server revenue grew 19 percent, to $1.6 billion.</p>
        <p>''It was a very strong performance, but there are still questions,'' said A. M. Sacconaghi, a securities analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein. ''Dell is not off to the races quite yet.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sacconaghi, like other analysts, is still waiting for Dell to disclose the nature of its accounting problems that are under investigation by the Securities and Exchange Commission. Dell has said it might have to restate earnings from prior quarters. The company said it incurred approximately $46 million, or two cents a share, in costs associated with the ongoing investigations during the quarter.</p>
        <p>Some Wall Street analysts noted that the benefit Dell received from lower component prices in the first quarter might not prove sustainable. ''The key surprise here is the upside in average selling price,'' said William Shope, an analyst with JPMorgan. ''But this is a quarter where there are so many anomalies.''</p>
        <p>This was also the first full quarter that Michael S. Dell, the company's founder, had been back in charge. The Dell chairman took back the title of chief executive in late January and began orchestrating a turnaround strategy that has included a shake-up of Dell's executive team, an increased openness to customer suggestions and, most recently, a shift in Dell's direct-sales model.</p>
        <p>''Our strategic intent is to simplify information technology for our customers by removing cost and complexity,'' Mr. Dell said in a prepared statement.</p>
        <p>Dell has been rapidly losing market share, particularly to Hewlett-Packard, now the world's largest maker of personal computers. During the first three months of the year, Dell's share of the worldwide PC market dropped to 15.2 percent from 18.2 percent last year, according to IDC, a market analysis firm. Dell's decline came in sharp contrast to the overall PC market, which grew 10.9 percent.</p>
        <p>To start growing again, Dell has said it would depart from the direct sales business model that helped it achieve phenomenal growth in the 1990s. Dell executives said last week that the company would sell a limited selection of its computers at Wal-Mart Stores, the world's largest retailer.</p>
        <p>Dell executives suggested that the deal with Wal-Mart was just the start of its plan to overhaul its sales strategy. In a further departure from the direct model, Dell has also been working more closely with value-added resellers who sell systems to small businesses and corporations.</p>
        <p>Dell has been counting on growth in overseas markets like China and India to help it compensate for weakening sales growth in the United States. Dell's international shipments exceeded domestic shipments during the first quarter, for the second consecutive quarter.</p>
        <p>Dell announced in August that the S.E.C. was conducting an investigation into its financial practices over the last few years. Dell executives said in March that they had uncovered ''evidence of misconduct'' through an internal investigation of its financial operations, involving accruals, reserves and other balance-sheet items.</p>
        <p>The company released no new information about that investigation. Since the start of the S.E.C. investigation, Dell executives have not held their customary conference call with Wall Street analysts and reporters.</p>
        <p>In a statement, Dell executives cautioned that the first-quarter earnings statement was preliminary and subject to possible change. Earnings from the second, third and fourth quarters of 2006 remain preliminary pending the outcome of the S.E.C. inquiry.</p>
        <p>The company has also delayed both the filing of its annual report and its annual shareholders meeting.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
