<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Father With Two Careers, In Business and in Murder</title>
    <meta content="01broo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/movies/01broo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851230"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Evans, Bruce A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Costner, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moore, Demi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cook, Dane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hurt, William</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Mr Brooks (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Serial Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Serial Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Costner, Kevin</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Helgenberger, Marg</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hurt, William</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Moore, Demi</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Mr. Brooks (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE2DC1530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="801" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Father With Two Careers, In Business and in Murder</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Father With Two Careers, in Business and in Murder</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews film Mr Brooks, directed by Bruce A Evans; Kevin Costner, Demi Moore, Dane Cook and William Hurt star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Who knew that serial killing is an addiction that sufferers hope to overcome by attending A.A. meetings and murmuring the serenity prayer? That, at least, is how the buttoned-up title character of ''Mr. Brooks,'' a nutty variation of ''Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde,'' deals with such inconvenient urges. ''I'm an addict,'' he announces at a 12-step meeting while withholding the true nature of his cravings.</p>
        <p>This preposterous character, played by Kevin Costner, is one of several afflicted with thrill-killing compulsions in a movie in which half the population of Portland, Ore., seems to suffer from homicidal dementia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In “Mr. Brooks,” serial killing is an addiction that sufferers hope to overcome by attending 12-step meetings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Who knew that serial killing is an addiction that sufferers hope to overcome by attending A.A. meetings and murmuring the serenity prayer? That, at least, is how the buttoned-up title character of ''Mr. Brooks,'' a nutty variation of ''Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde,'' deals with such inconvenient urges. ''I'm an addict,'' he announces at a 12-step meeting while withholding the true nature of his cravings.</p>
        <p>This preposterous character, played by Kevin Costner, is one of several afflicted with thrill-killing compulsions in a movie in which half the population of Portland, Ore., seems to suffer from homicidal dementia.</p>
        <p>Earl Brooks, a successful box manufacturer, is the Portland Chamber of Commerce's man of the year. A model citizen, ideal husband to his wife, Emma (Marg Helgenberger), and devoted father to his daughter, Jane (Danielle Panabaker), Earl leads a lurid double life.</p>
        <p>As the notorious Thumbprint Killer, he is also a maniac whose specialty is slaughtering young lovers, arranging their bodies into amorous poses, meticulously vacuuming the crime scene and signing it with the victims' thumbprints. Earl's fiendish alter ego, Marshall (William Hurt) -- an imaginary figure who leans over Earl's shoulder while he's driving -- flashes an evil grin and tempts him with descriptions of the fun they could have if only Earl would give in to his darkest impulses.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Brooks,'' alas, is not a comedy. A werewolf movie masquerading as a thriller, it looks like a canny attempt by Bruce A. Evans, its director and screenwriter (with Raynold Gideon), to establish a ''Saw''-like franchise using the names of fading '80s stars to lend the project a semblance of respectability. If it is not as sadistic as the ''Saw'' and ''Hostel'' movies, it is as malignant in its insistence on the omnipresence of evil.</p>
        <p>Another would-be killer is a peeping-Tom photographer calling himself Mr. Smith (the comedian Dane Cook), who observes Earl's double murder of a couple who amuse their neighbors by having sex with the lights on and the shades open. Days after the crime he confronts Earl with his evidence and demands to be let in on the fun. He won't go to the police if Earl takes him along on his next homicidal spree.</p>
        <p>Also on the rampage is Thornton Meeks (Matt Schulze), a convicted serial killer known as the Hangman, who strings up his victims in public places and scrawls mocking graffiti on their corpses. Newly escaped from prison, this standard-issue monster makes a vengeful beeline for Tracy Atwood (Demi Moore), the humorless police detective who sent him to jail. Because Tracy has also been assigned to the case of the Thumbprint Killer, she obviously has her hands full.</p>
        <p>Finally there is Earl's baby-faced daughter, who drops out of college in her freshman year claiming she is pregnant. When the police visit the Brooks home to question Jane about a classmate's murder, Daddy instinctively senses the unbearable truth. ''She has what I have,'' he declares to Marshall, wringing his hands.</p>
        <p>Now we know: Serial killing is in the blood, a curse passed down from generation to generation.</p>
        <p>This tightly plotted movie throws in an extra subplot involving Tracy's ugly divorce from a younger, cheating gigolo (Jason Lewis) whom she married on the rebound and who now demands millions. (The screenplay goes through elaborate contortions to try to explain why a wealthy heiress like Tracy would work as a policewoman, but the explanation doesn't wash.)</p>
        <p>Tracy is the most wooden screen performance of Ms. Moore's career. Looking exhausted and tense, the actress is as expressive as a wax museum effigy. That is not the case with Mr. Costner and Mr. Hurt, who pull out the stops to play a horror-movie tag team. In their scenes together Mr. Costner's sinister but tortured Earl and Mr. Hurt's gleefully sociopathic Marshall do a sadomasochistic soft shoe of psychological bullying and whining.</p>
        <p>Marshall is a creepy flesh-and-blood extrapolation of the inner voice inside anyone who has considered raising hell for the sheer thrill of it. In the world of ''Mr. Brooks,'' there's no greater kick than acting like a really bad boy and getting away with it.</p>
        <p>The movie is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual situations, profanity and gory violence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brooks  Opens today nationwide.</p>
        <p>Directed by Bruce A. Evans; written by Mr. Evans and Raynold Gideon; director of photography, John Lindley; edited by Miklos Wright; music by Ramin Djawadi; production designer, Jeffrey Beecroft; produced by Jim Wilson, Kevin Costner and Mr. Gideon; released by Metro Goldwyn Mayer. Running time: 120 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Kevin Costner (Earl Brooks), Demi Moore (Tracy Atwood), Dane Cook (Mr. Smith), William Hurt (Marshall), Marg Helgenberger (Emma Brooks), Ruben Santiago-Hudson (Hawkins), Danielle Panabaker (Jane Brooks), Matt Schulze (Thornton Meeks) and Jason Lewis (Jesse Vialo).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
