<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Columbia to Pay $1.1 Million To State Fund in Loan Scandal</title>
    <meta content="01loans" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851246"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E7D91530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Columbia to Pay $1.1 Million To State Fund in Loan Scandal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN W. ARENSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Columbia University will pay $1.1 million to a fund to educate students about loans and has agreed to have its financial aid office monitored by state officials for five years, under a settlement that New York State Attorney General Andrew M. Cuomo announced yesterday.</p>
        <p>The settlement, the most stringent Mr. Cuomo has reached with any university so far in his investigation of the $85 billion student loan industry, grew out of his finding that David Charlow, the financial aid director for Columbia's undergraduate college and its engineering school, was promoting a lending company in which he had a financial stake.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Columbia University will pay $1.1 million to a fund to educate students about loans and has agreed to have its financial aid office monitored by state officials for five years, under a settlement that New York State Attorney General Andrew M. Cuomo announced yesterday.</p>
        <p>The settlement, the most stringent Mr. Cuomo has reached with any university so far in his investigation of the $85 billion student loan industry, grew out of his finding that David Charlow, the financial aid director for Columbia's undergraduate college and its engineering school, was promoting a lending company in which he had a financial stake.</p>
        <p>Columbia put Mr. Charlow on paid leave in April, when it was disclosed that he held $100,000 or more in shares of Education Lending Group, the parent company of Student Loan Xpress, and it dismissed him last week.</p>
        <p>The Columbia settlement came on a day of developments in the student loan scandal. The Federal Trade Commission said in a letter to Congress that it was ''actively assessing whether lenders are making deceptive claims'' in marketing student loans. Mr. Cuomo also announced that the National Association of Student Financial Aid Administrators, a trade group of college financial aid officials, had agreed to monitoring by his office.</p>
        <p>And the University of Southern California said that its financial aid director, Catherine C. Thomas, who also owned shares in Education Lending Group, would retire effective today. The university said in a statement that Ms. Thomas' actions were ''inconsistent with USC's conflict of interest policy'' and that it was continuing to investigate.</p>
        <p>Michael W. Fitzgerald, a lawyer representing Ms. Thomas, confirmed her retirement and would not comment further.</p>
        <p>Columbia is the only university so far that has agreed to make annual reports on its financial aid office to Mr. Cuomo, and it is also the only one to make a substantial payment to the education fund he set up.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo said at a news conference yesterday that while he had reached settlements with about 25 colleges, Columbia was different because it ''was not properly policing its employee'' and he thought the agreement could serve as a benchmark for more to come.</p>
        <p>He added that he believed that Mr. Charlow had been ''acting illegally'' in his efforts to promote Student Loan Xpress and that a criminal prosecution was possible. He declined to comment further, saying the investigation was continuing.</p>
        <p>Asked about the possibility of criminal charges, Harvey Kurzweil, a lawyer for Mr. Charlow, said, ''I don't believe there is a basis for that.''</p>
        <p>Columbia said in a statement that a ''longtime, well-regarded employee failed to uphold the trust that had been placed in him by the University'' and that it was making changes to ''make this kind of conduct a thing of the past.''</p>
        <p>The university added that its agreement with the attorney general ''specifically states that Columbia University does not admit, and expressly denies, that it has violated any law in connection with its student loan practices.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo's office found that Mr. Charlow had put Student Loan Xpress on Columbia's list of preferred lenders after acquiring the stock. He also advised the company on marketing strategy, pushed its loans and helped draft talking points for its sales force.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo said Columbia had agreed to centralize the oversight of all of its financial aid operations at its various schools and to provide reports on the operations to the attorney general for five years.</p>
        <p>While Columbia is the only university so far that is being put under such scrutiny, Mr. Cuomo said that there were ''other schools in similar situations,'' and that he was beginning to negotiate with them.</p>
        <p>In addition to Mr. Charlow and Ms. Thomas, Lawrence W. Burt, the financial aid director at the University of Texas at Austin, also held stock in Education Lending Group. At Johns Hopkins University, the financial aid director, Ellen Frishberg, received about $65,000 in consulting fees and tuition payments from Student Loan Xpress and more from other companies. All four university officials have left or been dismissed.</p>
        <p>The attorney general's office has reached agreements in which more than a dozen other colleges and universities have agreed to pay back students the amounts the colleges had received from lenders in return for generating loan volume among students. The University of Pennsylvania, for example, will be returning $1.6 million, and New York University will be paying out $1.4 million. Columbia did not have such a revenue-sharing arrangement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo said the agreement to have Columbia contribute more than $1 million anyway -- to a fund run by his office to educate students and parents about financial aid -- was an effort to estimate a sum ''commensurate with their relative liability.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo also had a public reconciliation with the National Association of Student Financial Aid Administrators.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Cuomo first started investigating student lending problems, Dallas Martin, the group's president, accused him of ''character assassination.''</p>
        <p>But yesterday, Mr. Martin said that he had been wrong, and that his association had expanded its own code of ethics. ''I want to apologize,'' he said. ''We did not have all the facts. We do not condone individuals taking kickbacks.''</p>
        <p>Appearing next to Mr. Cuomo, Mr. Martin said the association would stop relying on lenders to sponsor its conferences and allowing them to use the meetings to court its members. For five years, the attorney general's office will have representatives at the conferences to ensure compliance.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
