<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Enough Space for Me and My Sailboard</title>
    <meta content="01Hood" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/travel/escapes/01Hood.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851207"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Windsurfing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hood River (Ore)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Preusch, Matthew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions/Western States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Vacation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oregon/Mount Hood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oregon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oregon/Hood River</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Mount Hood (Ore)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EEDD1530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1341" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Enough Space for Me and My Sailboard</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Enough Space for Me and My Sailboard</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW PREUSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Preusch, Matthew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on second-home market for windsurfers in Hood River, Ore, whose population of 6,500 doubles in summer; new town houses and old downtown bungalows have garages that accommodate boards and paraphernalia of windsurfing rather than cars; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JUST off Oak Street, the main drag of Hood River, Ore., there's a block of multistory town houses, each with an ordinary-looking garage door at street level. But look close, and you'll notice something odd. There are no accompanying curb cuts -- no breaks in the concrete at the street to allow driving in.</p>
        <p>Cars are parked on the street. The garages are filled with sports equipment -- in particular, the boards, sails, masts and attendant paraphernalia of windsurfing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For weekenders bearing sails and bikes in Hood River, Ore., storage means more than a walk-in closet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JUST off Oak Street, the main drag of Hood River, Ore., there's a block of multistory town houses, each with an ordinary-looking garage door at street level. But look close, and you'll notice something odd. There are no accompanying curb cuts -- no breaks in the concrete at the street to allow driving in.</p>
        <p>Cars are parked on the street. The garages are filled with sports equipment -- in particular, the boards, sails, masts and attendant paraphernalia of windsurfing.</p>
        <p>''These were built with second-home owners in mind,'' said Greg Colt, a local real estate agent. And in Hood River, second homes are owned by windsurfers.</p>
        <p>Hood River, in the Columbia River Gorge on the border of Oregon and Washington, is a windsurfer's paradise. Steady winds funnel up through the Cascade Mountains from cooler climes on the Pacific coast toward the warm inland desert to the east, whipping the wide Columbia River into a froth of wind-driven waves.</p>
        <p>Between Memorial Day and Labor Day, Hood River's usual population of 6,500 doubles as the windsurfers crowd into town. And as the gorge area's second-home market has grown, builders have figured out that luring buyers is easier if they are given a place to keep their sailboards and other stuff.</p>
        <p>Whether vacation homes are new town houses, old downtown bungalows, or McMansions marching up the ordered pear orchards of the Hood River Valley -- the garage ''is a key component to every house,'' said Steve Gates, a local builder who also owns a windsurfing shop. ''And it's not for cars.''</p>
        <p>Even in condominium buildings where there are no personal garages, some place for the gear has to be found, as Frank Bosl and Pam Sheets can tell you. They live primarily in Seattle but are longtime Hood River windsurfers, and bought a condo in a four-story building in downtown Hood River in 2005. It has two bedrooms and two bathrooms, black granite countertops or a view of the Columbia through the floor-to-ceiling windows.</p>
        <p>But ask them what sold them on it, and Mr. Bosl won't point to the cherry floors or the awe-inspiring views. Instead he will grab his keys, pull you into the elevator and press ''P'' for parking. Down in the bowels of the building, he'll walk by his 1979 Ford pickup, loaded with windsurfing gear, and open the door to a nearby locker large enough to swallow not only all of their windsurfing boards, sails and wetsuits, but also their bicycles.</p>
        <p>''We wouldn't have bought this unless we had the storage locker,'' Mr. Bosl said.</p>
        <p>Sean Aiken, a former professional windsurfer who now sells homes to other windsurfers, agrees. ''Storage is key around here, for sure,'' he said, because vacation residents don't want to haul heavy boards, masts and sails every time they visit.</p>
        <p>Solutions to the problem have become easier in recent years as the development of two-piece masts and the popularity of smaller boards have made windsurfing equipment easier to store. In the past, some attempts to satisfy gear-laden residents resulted in structures that were not only large but ungainly.</p>
        <p>In one of Hood River's older second-home developments, the Timbercrest condominiums, built in 1990, stands what looks like a tight grouping of four octagonal grain silos. Inside these strange-looking contrivances, tall masts and boards can be stored upright.</p>
        <p>Another condo development, the Lodge, has rows of skinny, two-story gear lockers that could double as changing rooms for Yao Ming.</p>
        <p>The locker that belongs to Mr. Bosl and Dr. Sheets is not much taller than head-high, but it has 550 cubic feet of storage. Their living space, meanwhile, is a compact 1,000 square feet.</p>
        <p>Downsized homes and upsized storage areas aren't unique to second homes in the Columbia gorge. According to a study completed in January by the National Association of Home Builders, ''The Home of the Future,'' future buyers will want more storage of all kinds, from linen closets to mud rooms.</p>
        <p>''Across the U.S., developers and builders are becoming more cognizant of and including all kinds of storage,'' said Margaret Wylde, president of ProMatura, a market research company.</p>
        <p>For physically active baby boomers now driving much of the condo market, many of them downsizing from large homes where they raised families, storage also means places for their gear -- frequently for water sports. One nationwide survey found that more than half of the owners cited an interest in water sports as one reason they bought their second homes.</p>
        <p>IN the Columbia River Gorge, whose vistas are protected by the 85-mile-long Columbia River Gorge National Scenic Area, water is the main attraction.</p>
        <p>When the region first became synonymous with American windsurfing in the 1980s, trucks bearing logs from the nearby Mount Hood National Forest were still common on the roads. Discover Bicycles, a road and mountain biking shop on Oak Street, was still a hardware store. And there were no gas stations off Interstate 84 advertising sail repairs in their windows.</p>
        <p>Vacation accommodations were scant. Many a longtime visitor has stories about sleeping in a van in a pullout by the river or pitching a tent at the Wind Ranch, a rowdy private campground that was on the Washington side of the Columbia.</p>
        <p>The ratty vans are still around, but accommodations have gone upscale. A 2005 survey of the 25 agents at Don Nunamaker Realtors in Hood River found that almost a fourth of 177 buyers from the previous 16 months had bought second homes rather than primary residences.</p>
        <p>In the off season, Hood River neighborhoods are dotted with closed-up vacation properties, which locals call ghost houses.</p>
        <p>Mr. Aiken estimates that he sells about 25 second homes a year. ''And every one of them probably windsurfs or kiteboards,'' he said.</p>
        <p>THREE years ago, Jim Adams, 48, a chiropractor from Santa Barbara, Calif., bought a house in Hood River in part because of its large garage. He lives in an attached studio when he comes to town to windsurf, and he rents out the main residence.</p>
        <p>He plans to subdivide the garage to share the storage space with his tenants.</p>
        <p>''That's the baby boomer generation,'' he said. ''We don't need as much room to be living in because we live outside. We just use our houses to sleep in.''</p>
        <p>Corbin Shays, a developer, tucked 800-square-foot garages under a row of 1,500-square-foot town homes just west of downtown that he finished this winter.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to build something where people have their stuff stacked up outside for everybody to look at because we didn't provide enough storage,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Joe Alexander and Gail Karvonen of Portland, Ore., bought one of the units to rent out in the summer, keeping in mind their potential tenants' likely reason for coming to the area. ''We thought it would be helpful for them to keep their kiteboarding equipment inside,'' Mr. Alexander said.</p>
        <p>The gear-friendly mindset along the Columbia isn't confined to Hood River. Across the Columbia in Washington, a lumber company wants to turn a derelict waterfront mill into a 60-acre destination resort marketed specifically to windsurfers. The resort, Broughton Landing, is expected to sell about a third of the planned 255 homes and condos as seasonal residences.</p>
        <p>The project faces several permitting hurdles, but if built, it will have a private beach on the Columbia with storage lockers for guests and residents, said Mike Usen, the project's designer.</p>
        <p>Speaking of windsurfers, he said, ''Instead of having to drive your rig down to a launch site somewhere, you can just walk across this pedestrian bridge and your rig will be ready to go.''</p>
        <p>But new winds are also blowing in the Columbia Gorge. Woe to the builderwho considers only the wind riders.</p>
        <p>Hood River now attracts mountain bikers interested in the free riding terrain at Post Canyon and whitewater kayakers drawn to the drops of the White Salmon River, a tributary that enters the Columbia across from Hood River.</p>
        <p>Now, said Mr. Gates, the builder who doubles as a windsurf shop owner, ''we really have to provide space for windsurf boards, kayaks and bikes.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
