<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cloistered in the Castle and Dreaming of His Empire</title>
    <meta content="01fift" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/movies/01fift.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851218"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seitz, Matt Zoller</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">De Oliveira, Manoel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trepa, Ricardo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cintra, Luis Miguel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">de Matos, Gloria</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Fifth Empire, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">de Oliveira, Manoel</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Fifth Empire, The (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE6DC1530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="492" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cloistered in the Castle and Dreaming of His Empire</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cloistered in the Castle and Dreaming of His Empire</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT ZOLLER SEITZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seitz, Matt Zoller</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matt Zoller Seitz reviews film The Fifth Empire, directed by Manoel de Oliveira; Ricardo Trepa, Luis Miguel Cintra and Gloria de Matos star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With ''The Fifth Empire,'' a drama about a young Portuguese king hoping to unite his troubled nation by embarking on a foreign adventure, the prolific 98-year-old director Manoel de Oliveira pushes his minimalist style as far as it can go.</p>
        <p>The result is an obstinately static, talky film that doesn't merely acknowledge the story's roots as a stage play -- ''El Rei Sebastião,'' by José Régio -- but foregrounds them. Mr. Oliveira lets conversations go on in long takes until a topic has been picked over from every conceivable angle. When he breaks to watch characters traverse staircases while Carlos Paredes's score twangs like the music from ''The Third Man,'' you may laugh, because what you're seeing is Mr. Oliveira's idea of an action scene.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With “The Fifth Empire,” the prolific 98-year-old director Manoel de Oliveira pushes his minimalist style as far as it can go.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With ''The Fifth Empire,'' a drama about a young Portuguese king hoping to unite his troubled nation by embarking on a foreign adventure, the prolific 98-year-old director Manoel de Oliveira pushes his minimalist style as far as it can go.</p>
        <p>The result is an obstinately static, talky film that doesn't merely acknowledge the story's roots as a stage play -- ''El Rei Sebastião,'' by José Régio -- but foregrounds them. Mr. Oliveira lets conversations go on in long takes until a topic has been picked over from every conceivable angle. When he breaks to watch characters traverse staircases while Carlos Paredes's score twangs like the music from ''The Third Man,'' you may laugh, because what you're seeing is Mr. Oliveira's idea of an action scene.</p>
        <p>At the same time, though, ''The Fifth Empire'' is hypnotic. Mr. Oliveira's aesthetic syncs up with his main interest: capturing characters' words and gestures in real time as they work through philosophical and political conundrums while remaining largely oblivious to the physical world around them.</p>
        <p>That world consists of the enormous, ornate castle where the story of ''The Fifth Empire'' takes place. Masterly photographed by the cinematographer Sabine Lancelin, who pinpoints as many shades of darkness as Charles Darwin did species of animal, it's not just a building but a psychological space that abstracts and amplifies themes brought up in Mr. Oliveira's script.</p>
        <p>The plot is really a series of dialogues between the passionate but wishy-washy King Sebastião (Ricardo Trepa, who oversells the character's torment) and his advisors and subjects. Their ranks include his aged mother (Glória de Matos), his Holy Cobbler (Luís Miguel Cintra) and assorted noblemen and leering, Fellini-esque jesters.</p>
        <p>The hero is based on the real-life King Sebastião, a boy ruler who was believed to have been killed in 1578 battling the Moors in Morocco. In Mr. Oliveira's film, he makes a messianic return and devises an absurd plan to return to Africa and create a Christian ''Fifth Empire.'' As he frets, rivals and underlings watch him for signs of political weakness or insanity.</p>
        <p>A political world riddled with unknowns, contradictions and reversals deserves a comparably formidable setting, and Mr. Oliveira provides it. Staircases rise into gloom and fall into torchlight; schemes are hatched in near-total darkness, lighted only by stars glimpsed through a barred window. Mr. Oliveira's script talks itself hoarse, but his images sing.</p>
        <p>The Fifth Empire  Opens today in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Directed by Manoel de Oliveira; written (in Portuguese, with English subtitles) by Mr. Oliveira, based on the play ''Rei Sebastião'' by José Régio; director of photography, Sabine Lancelin; edited by Valérie Loiseleux; music by Carlos Paredes; produced by Paulo Branco; released by Lusomundo Audiovisuais. At the Anthology Film Archives, 32 Second Avenue, at Second Street, East Village. Running time: 127 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: Ricardo Trepa (King Sebastião), Luís Miguel Cintra (Simão, Holy Cobbler) and Glória de Matos (Queen Catarina).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
