<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Poise in His Performance, Surprises Up His Sleeve</title>
    <meta content="01hutc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/arts/music/01hutc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Hutcherson, Bobby</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E6DC1530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="499" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Poise in His Performance, Surprises Up His Sleeve</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Poise in His Performance, Surprises Up His Sleeve</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATE CHINEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Something funny happened during Bobby Hutcherson's second set at the Blue Note on Wednesday night. He was halfway through a vibraphone solo, just gaining momentum, when he had the impulse to pound furiously at a single note -- plonk! plonk! plonk! -- as if hammering nails into a board. This intemperate act seemed to take even Mr. Hutcherson by surprise: he staggered a couple of steps back from his instrument, and there was a flicker of mild astonishment on his face before he convulsed with laughter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hutcherson, 66, is no stranger to bold, improvisational behavior. Forty years ago he was well known for his brilliant work on a wave of left-of-center Blue Note albums, by figures like the alto saxophonists Eric Dolphy and Jackie McLean; his definitive effort as a leader, ''Stick-Up!,'' was issued in 1966.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mr. Hutcherson found ways to undercut his own judiciousness by breaking up his performances with bold, improvisational behavior at the Blue Note on Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Something funny happened during Bobby Hutcherson's second set at the Blue Note on Wednesday night. He was halfway through a vibraphone solo, just gaining momentum, when he had the impulse to pound furiously at a single note -- plonk! plonk! plonk! -- as if hammering nails into a board. This intemperate act seemed to take even Mr. Hutcherson by surprise: he staggered a couple of steps back from his instrument, and there was a flicker of mild astonishment on his face before he convulsed with laughter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hutcherson, 66, is no stranger to bold, improvisational behavior. Forty years ago he was well known for his brilliant work on a wave of left-of-center Blue Note albums, by figures like the alto saxophonists Eric Dolphy and Jackie McLean; his definitive effort as a leader, ''Stick-Up!,'' was issued in 1966.</p>
        <p>Recently Mr. Hutcherson has favored a tighter range of expression, focusing on melody and phrasing with the precision of a good singer. His new album, ''For Sentimental Reasons'' (Kind of Blue), features love songs played with an articulate rhythm section of Renee Rosnes on piano, Dwayne Burno on bass and Al Foster on drums.</p>
        <p>That lineup has been augmented at the Blue Note by the guitarist Russell Malone, who seems to have had a bracing effect on the music. On Wednesday he took the first solo, on Fats Waller's ''Jitterbug Waltz,'' in a style that felt strategically terse, with eighth notes bitten off at the ends. Mr. Malone, who is capable of a much more fluid approach, seemed to be setting up Mr. Hutcherson for a stylistic contrast. It worked: the vibraphone solo that followed was a round of legato cascades.</p>
        <p>The combination of vibraphone, guitar and piano hasn't been commonly heard since the midcentury heyday of the George Shearing Quintet. There are reasons for this, mostly having to do with the issue of overcrowding a similar register.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Hutcherson and Mr. Malone managed to use this overlap to their advantage on ''Ode to Angela,'' a near-bossa by Harold Land that begins with an ascending Eastern scale. Ms. Rosnes joined them in playing the melody, but took care to avoid weighing it down.</p>
        <p>On ''Ode to Angela'' and a pair of standards, ''Old Devil Moon'' and ''I Thought About You,'' Mr. Hutcherson demonstrated a measured sort of poise. Occasionally he would pause midphrase, as if reconsidering his options, and then branch out in another direction.</p>
        <p>But as he often does with the SFJazz Collective, which also counts Ms. Rosnes as a member, Mr. Hutcherson found ways to undercut his own judiciousness. On ''Old Devil Moon'' that meant straying outside the tonal center and straining against the tempo.</p>
        <p>And when the solo ended with a metallic whack on the lowest key, Mr. Hutcherson rolled his eyes back in his head. He wasn't laughing that time, and nobody else was, either.</p>
        <p>The Bobby Hutcherson Quintet continues through Sunday at the Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village; (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
