<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lawsuit Accuses G.E. of Bias Against Women</title>
    <meta content="01bias" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/business/01bias.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851235"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Electric Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Deutsch, Claudia H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schaefer, Lorene F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Diversity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">General Electric Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E3DA1530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="741" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lawsuit Accuses G.E. of Bias Against Women</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lawyer Files Bias Suit Against G.E.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA H. DEUTSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Deutsch, Claudia H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lorene F Schaefer, who made it as far as general counsel for GE Transportation, files lawsuit, accusing General Electric of systematically discriminating against women in both pay and promotions; she is seeking to have suit certified as class action; David Sanford, one of Schaefer's lawyers, says he expects as many as 1,700 women to join suit and that he is asking for back pay, raises and compensatory damages totaling about $500 million to be distributed among plaintiffs; GE disputes Schaefer's claims (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lorene F. Schaefer says she moved steadily up General Electric's in-house legal ladder for 13 years, getting praise and stock grants each step along the way. She made it as far as general counsel for GE Transportation.</p>
        <p>But this year, she said in an interview, ''I bumped up against an absolute glass ceiling into the executive ranks.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lorene F. Schaefer has accused G.E. of systematically discriminating against women in both pay and promotions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lorene F. Schaefer says she moved steadily up General Electric's in-house legal ladder for 13 years, getting praise and stock grants each step along the way. She made it as far as general counsel for GE Transportation.</p>
        <p>But this year, she said in an interview, ''I bumped up against an absolute glass ceiling into the executive ranks.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday Ms. Schaefer, 43, filed a lawsuit in Federal District Court in Connecticut, accusing G.E. of systematically discriminating against women in both pay and promotions. She is seeking to have the suit certified as a class action.</p>
        <p>David Sanford, one of her lawyers, said he expected as many as 1,700 women to join the suit and that he was asking for back pay, raises and compensatory damages totaling about $500 million to be distributed among the plaintiffs.</p>
        <p>Ms. Schaefer is not sure that many women will sign on. ''The women at G.E. are scared to death, so this is the loneliest thing I've ever done,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Schaefer maintains that G.E. has done a stellar job of helping women migrate up through management. But she said that only 13 percent of G.E.'s officers were women, about the same percentage as six years ago. Moreover, she said that many male general counsels were part of G.E.'s ''senior executive band,'' the job level just below corporate officer. She said that most female general counsels, including herself, were ranked lower.</p>
        <p>''There are women at all levels throughout that corporation who are ready to be promoted, so G.E. can no longer say that it does not have a good feeder pool to tap,'' she said.</p>
        <p>G.E. disputes her facts as well as her contentions. Gary Sheffer, a G.E. spokesman, said that about $40 billion -- about a quarter of G.E.'s annual revenue -- came from business units run by women.</p>
        <p>He also said that in 2001, when Jeffrey R. Immelt took the helm as G.E. chairman, 17, or 9.3 percent, of G.E.'s 182 corporate officers were women; today, 27, or 14.5 percent, of 186 officers are women. Mr. Immelt is among those named in the suit.</p>
        <p>''Her claim that these numbers have remained flat is demonstrably untrue,'' Mr. Sheffer said, adding that G.E. will fight the suit.</p>
        <p>G.E. has faced discrimination charges before. Two years ago, Marcel T. Thomas, then the chief executive of GE Aviation Materials, sued G.E. after he received a negative evaluation and a negligible raise. Mr. Thomas, who is black, charged racial discrimination, and sought to have his suit certified as a class action. He never received the certification, and Mr. Thomas and G.E. quietly settled.</p>
        <p>Ms. Schaefer was recently demoted from her post as general counsel of GE Transportation because, the suit says, John Dineen, the group's chief executive, wanted a ''big-time G.C.'' She was not asked to leave -- ''they actually said I wasn't considered a throwaway employee,'' she said in the interview -- but she was not offered a specific new job.</p>
        <p>''They clearly hoped I'd ask for a severance package,'' she said. ''There was no rational explanation other than the fact I was a woman.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Schaefer has been on paid administrative leave since May 10, shortly after her lawyers alerted G.E. of the pending suit. She said she would like to return to G.E. -- but with a higher title and higher pay.</p>
        <p>''The purpose of this lawsuit is systemic change at G.E.,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Judge Approves Sprint-Nextel Plan</p>
        <p>KANSAS CITY, Mo., May 31 (AP) -- A judge in Kansas has given preliminary approval to Sprint Nextel's proposal to settle a class-action age bias lawsuit for $57 million.</p>
        <p>Judge John W. Lungstrum of Federal District Court said on Wednesday that the agreement was ''reasonable, adequate, fair and consistent'' and scheduled a final approval hearing in Kansas City, Kan., on Sept. 10.</p>
        <p>Filed in 2003, the lawsuit claims the company that was then called Sprint illegally moved employees 40 or older to positions that were then eliminated.</p>
        <p>The settlement, announced May 18, covers 1,697 former employees who were laid off from Oct. 1, 2001, to March 31, 2003.</p>
        <p>Under the newest agreement, 11 people who have served as lead plaintiffs in the case will receive an average of $155,000 each. The plaintiff's lawyers will receive $19.4 million in fees, plus an additional $1.65 million to cover the process of confirming the settlement. The remaining 1,686 plaintiffs will split the leftover $34.3 million, for an average payment of $20,332 each.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
