<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Jersey Says Its Pension Fund Is Being Examined by the S.E.C.</title>
    <meta content="01pension" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/nyregion/01pension.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851311"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E1D81530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="942" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Jersey Says Its Pension Fund Is Being Examined by the S.E.C.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pension Fund in New Jersey Faces Scrutiny From S.E.C.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARY WILLIAMS WALSH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Securities and Exchange Commission has begun an inquiry into New Jersey's handling of its pension fund for public employees, a move that suggests federal regulators are concerned that the state did not properly disclose its contributions to the fund.</p>
        <p>In a statement issued yesterday, the New Jersey state treasury said it was cooperating with the S.E.C., which was also sharing information with the United States attorney's office.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The move suggests that federal regulators are concerned that the state did not properly disclose its contributions to the fund.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Securities and Exchange Commission has begun an inquiry into New Jersey's handling of its pension fund for public employees, a move that suggests federal regulators are concerned that the state did not properly disclose its contributions to the fund.</p>
        <p>In a statement issued yesterday, the New Jersey state treasury said it was cooperating with the S.E.C., which was also sharing information with the United States attorney's office.</p>
        <p>The inquiry follows a report in The New York Times in April about accounting maneuvers that made it look as if New Jersey was putting more cash into the pension fund than it actually did over many years. Some of the offering statements for New Jersey's bonds, for example, incorrectly described money spent on health insurance as pension contributions. The S.E.C. has the authority to make sure the state makes full and correct financial disclosures to the municipal bond markets.</p>
        <p>The state treasury did not say why the United States attorney's office was involved in the investigation. One possible area of inquiry, however, is whether any officials were improperly rewarded in connection with pension transactions, as may have happened in a recent pension fund scandal in San Diego. Five officials have been indicted there.</p>
        <p>New Jersey did not provide details about the scope of the inquiry or how many years it covered.</p>
        <p>The inquiry was reported yesterday in The Star-Ledger of Newark.</p>
        <p>State officials acknowledge that the pension fund has a serious deficit of billions of dollars and needs big contributions that will require cuts in other programs, higher taxes or another source. But dealing with thorny accounting questions to the satisfaction of regulators could take years and require even more contributions than officials now expect. It could also affect New Jersey's creditworthiness. With reported assets of about $80 billion, the fund is the nation's ninth-largest public fund.</p>
        <p>Shortly after The Times reported on the state's pension accounting maneuvers, Gov. Jon S. Corzine said he wanted to investigate the matter because he believed the state had been letting the pension fund lapse ''for the better part of a decade'' and needed to address the resulting shortfall.</p>
        <p>''I consider it one of our greatest challenges,'' Governor Corzine said in early April, adding that he would ask the state attorney general, Stuart Rabner, to conduct an investigation with the help of an outside actuary because he did not believe the state had adequate technical expertise in house.</p>
        <p>But now the state appears to be letting federal regulators lead the investigation. A spokesman for the attorney general said it had hired a former S.E.C. official, Carmen J. Lawrence, to represent the state before the S.E.C. Ms. Lawrence, who was the director of the S.E.C.'s Northeast regional office from 1996 to 2000, is now a leader of the securities regulation and enforcement practice at the law firm of Fried, Frank, Harris, Shriver &amp; Jacobson.</p>
        <p>State Senator Leonard Lance, a longtime critic of the state's financial management, said he was writing a letter to the state treasurer, Bradley Abelow, demanding more information about the commission's inquiry and asking whether any other federal agencies were involved.</p>
        <p>Senator Lance recalled that he had asked the treasurer at a hearing in April whether the Internal Revenue Service was investigating the pension fund -- the treasurer said no -- and now wished he had been told about the S.E.C. inquiry, which started in late April.</p>
        <p>Officials at the S.E.C. and the United States attorney's office said confidentiality rules barred them from discussing investigations or even confirming that an inquiry was in progress.</p>
        <p>The commission does not currently receive or review governmental financial statements, focusing instead on making sure corporate accounting is truthful. But Christopher Cox, the S.E.C. chairman, has recently expressed a strong interest in policing disclosures to investors in municipal bonds, which are issued by states as well as by municipalities.</p>
        <p>In addition to the S.E.C. and the United States attorney, the Internal Revenue Service has jurisdiction over certain parts of the federal pension law. Tax officials said yesterday that they could not comment on New Jersey or any other individual governments that operate pension funds. But they echoed Mr. Cox's general sentiment that there appeared to be a need for more monitoring of public pension plans.</p>
        <p>''We sense that perhaps compliance is not as good as it should be in this area,'' said Joseph Grant, the I.R.S.'s director of employee plans. ''We are looking at what our authority allows us to do, and where we can best use that authority to have the most salutary effect on participants.''</p>
        <p>He said that in general, the I.R.S. had legal authority to make sure pension money was not used to pay for other things, like health insurance, and to make sure it was prudently invested. New Jersey's records suggest that it might not have properly separated pension money from health insurance money. The state has also embarked on a program to invest part of the pension fund in new asset classes, such as private equity and hedge funds, angering some employee groups.</p>
        <p>Steven T. Miller, an I.R.S. commissioner, said in a speech to lawyers last month that the agency should include government pension plans in its enforcement. ''How could it not, with one in five Americans employed by governments?'' he said. ''Coverage and asset protection are of vital importance here, as recent headlines indicate.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cox has said that the recent scandal over the pension fund in San Diego exposed problems with government disclosures. The S.E.C. found that the city had shortchanged its pension fund for many years and deliberately covered up the resulting financial problems, in what amounted to securities fraud.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
