<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Faith, Reason and a G.O.P. Hopeful</title>
    <meta content="l01evolution" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851291"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EFD91530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1133" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Faith, Reason and a G.O.P. Hopeful</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''What I Think About Evolution,'' by Sam Brownback (Op-Ed, May 31):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''What I Think About Evolution,'' by Sam Brownback (Op-Ed, May 31):</p>
        <p>Senator Brownback stated that he is willing to accept any part of evolutionary theory that does not conflict with his faith.</p>
        <p>As a person of science who does not believe that sound reason must be ''purified,'' I find his pick-and-choose approach to science very worrisome, as he might one day be responsible for making the most important decisions for this country.</p>
        <p>We can only hope that he chooses to believe the facts when it comes to decisions about our health, national security, economic policy and education.</p>
        <p>As science has yet to prove or disprove the existence of a divine power, and probably never will, I will use my gift of reason, be it from God or evolutionary serendipity, to inform my beliefs and decisions.</p>
        <p>Claire Knezevic  Lake Bluff, Ill., May 31, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>There is much to agree with in Senator Sam Brownback's article, particularly when he writes that we should not ''drive a wedge between faith and reason.'' Unfortunately, he also urges us to ''firmly reject'' aspects of science when they are inconsistent with religious beliefs. That doesn't work.</p>
        <p>The purpose of science is to tell us about the nature of the natural world, whether we like the answer or not. To thrive in our science and technology-based society, people really can't pick and choose which scientific facts to accept.</p>
        <p>Evolution is a core, well-tested scientific concept that explains how Earth's life forms gradually arose from common ancestors billions of years ago.</p>
        <p>Believing in a god and accepting evolution are not inconsistent for many people. But religion should not be substituted for science, nor the reverse, since they deal with different domains.</p>
        <p>Alan I. Leshner  Washington, May 31, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is chief executive of the American Association for the Advancement of Science and executive publisher of Science.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Senator Sam Brownback says there cannot be any contradiction between faith and reason. He makes an excellent point that an appreciation of biological evolution does not necessitate a completely materialistic and deterministic worldview.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, he also makes some very specific statements about the limits of evolution that are clearly not supported by observation or experiment. For example, the suggestion that evolution occurs only by small changes within a species is not consistent with the many observations of rapid speciation.</p>
        <p>Not only can we study rapid speciation in nature, but we can also directly observe it and examine its causes in the lab.</p>
        <p>By restricting the scope of science to explain only some aspects of the natural world, Senator Brownback forces there to be a contradiction between faith and reason.</p>
        <p>Michael Travisano  St. Paul, May 31, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is an associate professor in the department of ecology, evolution and behavior at the University of Minnesota and an associate editor of the journal Evolution.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Much to my surprise, I agree with much of what Senator Sam Brownback has to say about the false choice between faith in God and acceptance of evolutionary theory.</p>
        <p>But I can't help but feel that he did not truthfully answer the question posed in the first Republican presidential candidates' debate given his assertion that these are not mutually exclusive positions.</p>
        <p>At the very least, he should have challenged the premise of the question if he felt, as his article implies, that the question was intended to force the candidates to elevate faith over reason or vice versa. Doing so in a well-publicized public forum would have established that the senator is able to reject attempts to limit the range of ideas and options that he would consider in exercising the duties of the office of president.</p>
        <p>That is a strength that seems lacking in most politicians today, including the current crop of presidential hopefuls.</p>
        <p>George Reynolds  Nashville, May 31, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I wonder if Sam Brownback understands that the purpose of science is to answer a question in the most objective way possible. Whether studying the origins of life or a new drug, scientists use the scientific method to override preconceived notions and beliefs by gathering and analyzing evidence or data.</p>
        <p>Science cannot do its job unless the dichotomy between faith and science is recognized. Beliefs are not a substitute for hard evidence, but they can determine how societies use the answers science provides.</p>
        <p>Rhoda Newell  San Antonio, May 31, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Senator Sam Brownback says ''the heart of the issue is that we cannot drive a wedge between faith and reason.'' He thus tries to commingle the two by asserting that those facets of evolution that do not contradict what he calls the ''fundamental truth'' of man's creation and divine causality should be accepted while those that do not should be rejected as ''atheistic theology posing as science.''</p>
        <p>By subjecting scientific observation to a theological litmus test, he drives the very wedge between faith and reason that he purports to avoid.</p>
        <p>As a scientist, I would say that God is much more subtle than to force us to close our eyes to what we see in deference to what another may choose to believe is his guiding hand.</p>
        <p>James Mechalakos  Cold Spring, N.Y., May 31, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Senator Sam Brownback's calm, dispassionate article about faith and science is proof that intelligent life does exist in Congress.</p>
        <p>He brings the most robustly rational argument to this unfortunately emotional debate. He rises above the sound-bite histrionics and illuminates the key point in the debate: the independence of the empirical sciences within their specific fields must be safeguarded, but we must also recover the perennial wisdoms of philosophy and theology to safeguard humanity from science-based ethical systems.</p>
        <p>While Al Gore is lamenting the loss of reason in American life, his former colleague in the Senate is doing an admirable job of trying to recover it.</p>
        <p>John L. Stehn  Port Washington, N.Y.  May 31, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Apparently Senator Sam Brownback is in favor of scientific inquiry as long as it does not speak to questions of ultimate meaning.</p>
        <p>It has never been science's purview to speak to theological questions of meaning or faith. Which faith would it speak to? I'm sure that Senator Brownback prefers his own brand of Christianity, but where does that leave everyone else?</p>
        <p>The beauty of science is that it is a universal human endeavor to arrive at answers completely independent of, and uninfluenced by, any specific religion or faith. Notably, Christians, Muslims, Buddhists, Hindus and atheists all work as scientists, and all speak the same universal human language of reason.</p>
        <p>Thilo Weissflog  San Antonio, May 31, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
