<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LIVING HERE | Waterfront Town; Where the Boats Dance</title>
    <meta content="01live" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851205"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Wisconsin</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Fish Creek (Wis)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">McCullagh, Ann</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyttle, Bethany</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Living Here</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Vacation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EEDD1530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="861" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LIVING HERE | Waterfront Town; Where the Boats Dance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">As told to Bethany Lyttle</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyttle, Bethany</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ann McCullagh comments on her family's vacation cottage in Fish Creek, Wis; photos and brief descriptions of other waterfront properties available in US and Canada (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I was pregnant with my daughter -- very pregnant -- when my sister called and said: ''Ann, you have to get up to Door County because there are these 1890s holiday cottages going up for sale.'' They were these dumpy little places that had gone into disrepair. There were four of them, all built around a funny fish-shaped swimming pool.</p>
        <p>Today, they are all privately owned; there's a homeowners association, and it's all very charming. Our cottage is teeny -- about 700 square feet -- but it's fully equipped, and frankly, we don't think twice about having four adults and the kids with their friends. There's a screened porch with wicker chairs for reading and we have a back deck, too.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I was pregnant with my daughter -- very pregnant -- when my sister called and said: ''Ann, you have to get up to Door County because there are these 1890s holiday cottages going up for sale.'' They were these dumpy little places that had gone into disrepair. There were four of them, all built around a funny fish-shaped swimming pool.</p>
        <p>Today, they are all privately owned; there's a homeowners association, and it's all very charming. Our cottage is teeny -- about 700 square feet -- but it's fully equipped, and frankly, we don't think twice about having four adults and the kids with their friends. There's a screened porch with wicker chairs for reading and we have a back deck, too.</p>
        <p>They call this area the Cape Cod of the Midwest. The town is quaint. And there are always boats dancing on the water. When we arrive, the kids drop their bags and within minutes, they're jumping off the town pier. There are white clapboard cottages, ice cream shops and candy shops, and aside from the fact that in July it's so crowded you may as well be in Chicago, it's perfect.</p>
        <p>The nautical theme at the cottage and the water all around us is such a contrast to our home in Elgin. Just up at the corner, there's this little clearing called Sunset Point and people gather there each night. At the shoreline, kids skip stones as the sky changes from one spectacular color to another. When the sun finally disappears, people clap. And then we all walk away.</p>
        <p>As told to Bethany Lyttle</p>
        <p>Information on properties was supplied by the listing companies.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Salem, Mass.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $499,900</p>
        <p>This 1,428-square-foot Victorian house is in the Salem Willows district near a park and beach. The house has a large front porch with ocean views. The house has been fully renovated with a new heating system and granite countertops in the kitchen. There are two and a half bathrooms and wide-pine and hardwood floors throughout. From the master bedroom, a spiral staircase leads up to a third-floor turret with ocean views. Agent: Kathleen Sullivan, ReMax Advantage Real Estate, (978) 927-9199; www.sullivanteam.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Stonington, Me.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $650,000</p>
        <p>This house is roughly 1,500 square feet and has a covered porch with views of the harbor at Stonington, the Deer Isle fishing and lobstering town a 60-mile drive from Bar Harbor. The house, which dates from the 1880s, has been fully renovated; a rear addition can serve as a fourth bedroom. There are two and a half bathrooms. Agent: Richard Lord, Shepard's Select Properties, (207) 367-2790; www.shepardselect.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Southport, N.C.  WHAT -- 2-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $475,000</p>
        <p>This house was built in 1948 and is in the old downtown area on the Cape Fear River. It is 1,300 square feet and has established gardens surrounded by a picket fence. Interior details include original 1940s kitchen cabinets, plantation blinds and hardwood floors. The house is within walking distance of the town's many restaurants and shops. There are water views of the river from the back porch and yard. The house has one bathroom. Broker and owner: David Burn, Cape Fear Coast Real Estate, (910) 278-5523; www.cfcoast.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Montauk, N.Y.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $950,000</p>
        <p>This house was moved from the village to this half-acre lot in 1942 and is the only Dutch Colonial in Montauk. It has 275 feet of frontage on Fort Pond and has a small private dock. The house, which has been in the same family since it was built, is perched on a hill with water views. It is 1,500 square feet and has one bathroom. The house has been used as a seasonal property and is not heated. Montauk is about 115 miles from Manhattan. Broker: Kathleen Beckmann, Kathleen G. Beckmann Real Estate, 631-668-5325; www.kathleenbeckmann.com</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Fish Creek, Wis.  WHAT -- 2-bedroom condominium  HOW MUCH -- $325,900</p>
        <p>Located on a peninsula with Green Bay on one side and Lake Michigan on the other, this condominum is within walking distance of the beach, town shops and restaurants. It has a patio off the dining room, and the condominium complex has an outdoor pool. The apartment has ceramic tile floors, an open floor plan, a gas log fireplace, maple cabinets in the kitchen and a wall-mounted flat-screen television. Each bedroom has a full bathroom. Agent: Jill Schram-Dickson, Realty Executives, (920) 469-4639; www.jilldickson.com</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Lunenburg, Nova Scotia  WHAT -- 5-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $373,738</p>
        <p>This approximately 100-year-old house was built by a ship captain for his wife. It has a sweeping stairway, an arched front door, bay windows, three bathrooms and established gardens. The house is approximately 3,000 square feet and has southerly views of the bay and is within walking distance of Old Town Lunenburg, which is on Unesco's World Heritage list. The asking price is 399,000 Canadian dollars. Lunenburg is about 60 miles from Halifax. Agent: Michael Wilson, Tradewinds Realty, (902) 634-1250; www.tradewindsrealty.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
