<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Accolades, Some Tearful, In Pastor's Twilight Years</title>
    <meta content="01graham" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/us/01graham.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851316"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina/Charlotte</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evangelical Movement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Graham, Billy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0D81530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1113" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Accolades, Some Tearful, In Pastor's Twilight Years</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Accolades, Some Tearful, for a Preacher in His Twilight Years</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEELA BANERJEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Banerjee, Neela</byline>
      <dateline>CHARLOTTE, N.C., May 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a man who has welcomed crowds his whole life, the evangelist Billy Graham appeared humbled and a bit embarrassed to be before this one Thursday in a parking lot near the Charlotte airport.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of friends, family members, ministers and politicians had gathered to dedicate a library celebrating the ministry of Mr. Graham, whose vast popularity lent him the title ''America's pastor.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hundreds of friends, family members, ministers and politicians gathered to dedicate a library commemorating the ministry of the evangelist Billy Graham.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For a man who has welcomed crowds his whole life, the evangelist Billy Graham appeared humbled and a bit embarrassed to be before this one Thursday in a parking lot near the Charlotte airport.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of friends, family members, ministers and politicians had gathered to dedicate a library celebrating the ministry of Mr. Graham, whose vast popularity lent him the title ''America's pastor.''</p>
        <p>Standing on a platform before the Billy Graham Library, former President George Bush delivered the keynote address, his voice cracking into a sob as he said Mr. Graham was ''the man, the preacher, the humble farmer's son who changed the world.'' Former Presidents Jimmy Carter and Bill Clinton also spoke of how Mr. Graham had transformed their lives.</p>
        <p>Infirm and rarely appearing in public now, Mr. Graham approached the dais using a walker and noted the sense of completion and twilight that marked the speeches before his.</p>
        <p>''I feel like I've been attending my own funeral, listening to all these speeches,'' he said to the crowd's nervous laughter. ''I've been here at the library once, and my one comment when I toured it was that it is too much Billy Graham. My whole life has been to please the Lord and honor Jesus, not to see me and think of me.''</p>
        <p>Initiated by the Rev. Franklin Graham, Mr. Graham's older son, and board members of the Billy Graham Evangelistic Association, the library is to serve as a tribute to the 60 years of Mr. Graham's ministry around the world.</p>
        <p>The $27 million, 40,000-square-foot library is to open on Tuesday. It holds childhood photos of Mr. Graham; his college yearbook, in which he said he wanted to be an evangelist; the tiny engagement ring he gave his wife, Ruth; and footage of his rousing sermons over the decades, from Los Angeles to Moscow, in which he urged people to open their hearts to Christ.</p>
        <p>''My father is 88 years old, and he still wants to preach, but his body is just worn out,'' Franklin Graham said on a tour of the library before the ceremony. ''I hope this library can be an extension of his life. I hope it can be of use long after he's in heaven.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Graham's crusades filled stadiums even into his old age because of his simple, passionate call to Christianity. He has befriended presidents since Eisenhower, as well as Queen Elizabeth II and Pope John Paul II, and he helped fuel the surge in Christianity in the developing world in the last generation.</p>
        <p>''Every president, truth be told, is mostly grateful to him for that personal kindness,'' Mr. Clinton said. ''When he prays with you in the Oval Office, or upstairs in the White House, you feel like he is praying for you, not the president.''</p>
        <p>No one among contemporary evangelical leaders approaches Mr. Graham's stature, scholars said. ''Nobody is going to be next the Billy Graham,'' said Randall Balmer, professor of American religion at Barnard College. ''What we are looking at in the future of evangelism is niche evangelism, based on ethnicity, language, worship style. Graham was no doubt the last of the mass evangelists.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Graham rejected the sectarianism that evangelicals had been known for earlier in the 20th century, religion scholars said, without diluting his Christian message. He exploited radio and television early to spread the Gospel. Most significantly, he helped reorient Christians in the postwar era once more toward evangelizing.</p>
        <p>''Billy Graham stayed extremely focused on what he saw as his calling in life: conversion of people to Christianity,'' said David Key, director of the Baptist Studies Program at Emory University. ''Billy Graham didn't veer to the left or the right during his ministry -- and both those on left and the right have criticized him for that.''</p>
        <p>Over the years, Mr. Graham largely eschewed the social justice activism of mainline Christianity, although he integrated his crusades in the mid-1950s and spoke out against nuclear proliferation and apartheid. Mr. Clinton and Mr. Carter recalled how moved they had been to attend his integrated crusades in the segregated South.</p>
        <p>''He was constantly broadminded, forgiving, humble in his treatment of others,'' Mr. Carter said. ''He has reached out equally to all people, black or white, man or woman. I am one of the tens of millions of people whose spiritual lives have been shaped by Billy Graham.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Graham cautioned other evangelical Christians that they aligned themselves with politicians at their peril, religion scholars said.</p>
        <p>''When the religious right arose, he warned preachers about getting involved, that it was too easy to get manipulated,'' said William Martin, professor emeritus of sociology at Rice University and author of ''A Prophet With Honor: The Billy Graham Story.''</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Graham is still chairman of the Billy Graham Evangelistic Association, Franklin Graham has succeeded him as chief executive, his priorities and style sharply differing from his father's. Franklin Graham has made comments critical of Islam, while his father took great care not to offend. The younger Mr. Graham is heavily involved in international relief work, while his father focused mainly on preaching.</p>
        <p>The library will house Billy Graham's personal papers and memorabilia after his death. Individual donors and organizations financed construction of the library, including the Pew Charitable Trust, which gave $3 million. It also has a $27 million endowment.</p>
        <p>The project has been tinged with controversy, stemming largely from a family disagreement about whether the library should be the Grahams' burial site. Franklin Graham and others had hoped to persuade their parents to be buried at the library, The Washington Post reported last year.</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Graham has long insisted that she and her husband be buried at the Cove, a retreat run by the evangelistic association near Asheville, N.C. Franklin Graham said his parents had made a decision, which they have so far kept private.</p>
        <p>Other supporters of Mr. Graham have complained about the theme-park aspects of the library.</p>
        <p>The main entrance is a stylized barn, meant to suggest the Charlotte dairy farm where Mr. Graham grew up, and its entrance is a 40-foot glass cross. A mechanical cow named Bessie welcomes visitors at the entrance with reminiscences of the boy ''Billy Frank'' practicing his oratory on tree stumps and cows.</p>
        <p>But farther inside, the darkened rooms with display cases and video screens crackle with Mr. Graham's preaching. He says in one sermon that he never knew a man to accept Christ and then regret it.</p>
        <p>At the end, a video message from his followers urges visitors not to leave without a decision to accept Christ. The exit doors stay closed on an automatic timer and let the visitor ponder the plea.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
