<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>James Puts On Scoring Clinic In Overtime</title>
    <meta content="01pistons" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851354"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2D71530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1071" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>James Puts On Scoring Clinic In Overtime</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <dateline>AUBURN HILLS, Mich., May 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Minute after hypnotic minute, LeBron James lifted into the air, suspended in a stratosphere where only he could breathe and only he could see the basket.</p>
        <p>Every time his feet hit the ground a split second before his improbable jumpers hit the bottom of the net with Detroit Pistons all over him, the Palace of Auburn Hills fell into stunned silence. It was as close to reverence as a home team could show, after seeing James take over the game and the series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Minute after hypnotic minute, LeBron James lifted into the air, suspended in a stratosphere where only he could breathe and only he could see the basket.</p>
        <p>Every time his feet hit the ground a split second before his improbable jumpers hit the bottom of the net with Detroit Pistons all over him, the Palace of Auburn Hills fell into stunned silence. It was as close to reverence as a home team could show, after seeing James take over the game and the series.</p>
        <p>If there were other players on the Cleveland Cavaliers, nobody saw them. And if there was any way to stop James, the Pistons could not find it.</p>
        <p>It was only fitting that James, in the final 2.2 seconds of the second overtime, won Game 5 of this memorable Eastern Conference final series when he muscled his way to the basket. His driving layup past three more Pistons lifted the Cavaliers to a 109-107 victory over the Pistons, giving Cleveland a 3-2 series lead.</p>
        <p>James not only scored 48 points, he scored 29 of his team's last 30 points, putting himself and the Cavaliers one game from reaching their first N.B.A. finals. Game 6 is in Cleveland Saturday, where the Cavaliers have not lost in this series.</p>
        <p>What did it feel like to be in the zone?</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to miss,'' James said with a weary smile. ''Not everybody gets the opportunity to be in a zone like that. I just wanted to will my team to victory and do the best job possible.''</p>
        <p>There was no denying this night was anything less than a coronation for James, the player dubbed the Chosen One and King James when he starred in high school in Akron, Ohio.</p>
        <p>James wears 23 in homage to Michael Jordan and on this night the comparisons were inevitable.</p>
        <p>''It was very Jordanesque,'' the Pistons' Chauncey Billups said. ''There was nothing we could do.''</p>
        <p>When Billups missed a driving layup at the buzzer, Pistons walked off this court blinking. Billups traded baskets like dares with James at the end of the fourth quarter, and Billups sank the free throws that sent the game into the second overtime.</p>
        <p>But he and his team faltered at the feet of 22-year-old James.</p>
        <p>James scored all 9 of the Cavaliers points in the first overtime and all 9 of their points in the second overtime.</p>
        <p>Last year in the conference semifinals, the Cavaliers won Game 5 to take a 3-2 series lead but then lost two in a row. But James was not playing on this level then.</p>
        <p>The Pistons and Cavaliers traded momentum and baskets seemingly all game, with 16 ties and 22 lead changes. But until James's sublime performance in overtime, no exchange in the game was as thrilling as the one in the final 31 seconds of regulation between James and Billups.</p>
        <p>First, James made the most-eye popping play of the game to that point. He took the ball at the top of the arc and with his cross-over dribble left Jason Maxiell flat-footed. Then, with the Pistons' Tayshaun Prince getting out of the way, he soared to throw down a vicious dunk that gave the Cavaliers an 89-88 lead.</p>
        <p>But Billups, who finished with 21 points, would not be denied. He drained a 3-pointer with 22.9 seconds left that gave the Pistons a tenuous 91-89 lead.</p>
        <p>James was not finished. With 9.5 seconds left, he drove the middle of the lane for a dunk, tying the score, 91-91. When Billups's 3-pointer missed at the buzzer, the game went to overtime, only the second time that has happened in playoffs this season.</p>
        <p>James may be wondering what might have been if he had made his shots at the foul line in regulation. James had hit a 3-pointer to pull the Cavaliers within a point, 88-87. But when he went to the line with 1 minute 52 seconds left, he missed both shots. On his previous trip to the line he missed a free throw that would have completed a 3-point play.</p>
        <p>Cavaliers Coach Mike Brown was asked Monday to describe what was happening in the Cavaliers' dreadful third quarters, in which the Pistons had outscored them in all three games to that point. ''Pistons basketball,'' Brown said. ''They're aggressive on both sides of the floor and we have more turnovers in that third quarter.''</p>
        <p>Sure enough, Billups started the scoring 10 seconds into the second half Thursday with a 3-pointer and Prince took it from there. After going scoreless in the first half, Prince personally outscored the Cavaliers, 8-4, helping the Pistons open a 10-point lead.</p>
        <p>The Pistons had taken a lead at halftime, 52-51, for the first time in the series, but after 13 first-half lead changes, it was not without a struggle. The Pistons' lead swelled to as many as 8 points just four minutes into the second quarter.</p>
        <p>Billups was steady, leading the Pistons with 13 first-half points. The veteran center Chris Webber had 11. Before the game, Webber tried to control his frustration over his diminished playing time.</p>
        <p>When Antonio McDyess was ejected Thursday for committing a flagrant foul against Anderson Varejao, Webber knew he would be playing more minutes. He had been averaging just 9 points in 22.8 minutes coming into Game 5.</p>
        <p>''It would be easy for me to force shots, but we all have to sacrifice for the greater good,'' Webber said before the game. Webber played 12:33 in the first half and sparked the Pistons in the paint. He finished 20 points.</p>
        <p>It had taken four games decided in the final minute before to action between the teams turned from chippy to contentious with 28.7 seconds left in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>The Pistons were leading, 28-22, when McDyess fouled Varejao hard going to the basket, raking him across the neck. Following form, Varejao on his back and grimaced, his curls mopping the floor.</p>
        <p>James charged from the corner in front of his bench and hurdled at full-speed over his fallen teammate, searching for McDyess. Instead, James found Pistons forward Jason Maxiell, who held him back as the two exchanged a spit-filled conversation. James was assessed a technical foul.</p>
        <p>James was fuming, the emotion of the incident apparently unsettling him so much that he shot an airball on a 3-point attempt on the next possession. But he soon channeled that passion, sensing the opportunity at stake.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
