<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Past and Present: Imperfect, Tense</title>
    <meta content="01book" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/books/01book.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851224"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">McEwan, Ian</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E4DC1530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="943" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Past and Present: Imperfect, Tense</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Past and Present: Imperfect, Tense</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Chesil Beach  By Ian McEwan  203 pages. Nan A. Talese/Doubleday. $22.</p>
        <p>After two big, ambitious novels -- ''Atonement'' and ''Saturday'' -- Ian McEwan has inexplicably produced a small, sullen, unsatisfying story that possesses none of those earlier books' emotional wisdom, narrative scope or lovely specificity of detail.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ian McEwan has inexplicably produced a small, sullen, unsatisfying story that possesses none of those earlier books’ emotional wisdom, narrative scope or lovely specificity of detail.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Chesil Beach  By Ian McEwan  203 pages. Nan A. Talese/Doubleday. $22.</p>
        <p>After two big, ambitious novels -- ''Atonement'' and ''Saturday'' -- Ian McEwan has inexplicably produced a small, sullen, unsatisfying story that possesses none of those earlier books' emotional wisdom, narrative scope or lovely specificity of detail.</p>
        <p>Although ''On Chesil Beach'' grapples with some of Mr. McEwan's perennial themes -- the hazards of innocence, the sudden mutation of the ordinary into the awful, the inexorable grip of time past over time present -- it does so in a mechanical and highly arbitrary fashion. It also focuses closely on one couple's romantic and sexual relationship without opening a window, as his earlier novels have done, onto larger social and moral issues, and without giving the reader any genuine psychological insights into its two main characters.</p>
        <p>The central event of this novel concerns the disastrous wedding night of Edward and Florence, naïve young things, who have come, one evening in July of 1962, to a hotel on the Dorset coast for their honeymoon. Both are virgins, and both are nervous about their first time in bed together. In fact Florence is beyond nervous: She's terrified, for she regards the prospect of sex with ''a visceral dread, a helpless disgust as palpable as seasickness.'' The couple's attempt to consummate their marriage, predictably enough, ends in an embarrassing encounter that will snowball into a far more dire emotional exchange, all of which is depicted by Mr. McEwan in unsavory, voyeuristic terms that are as cringemaking as they are graphic.</p>
        <p>Mr. McEwan vaguely suggests that Florence's problem stems from some sort of incestuous relationship with her father, but his depiction of her past is sketchy and stilted, and he never succeeds in making her emotional life remotely palpable -- or plausible -- to the reader. Whereas he has often used his gifts as a writer in previous books to put across the point of view of decidedly unappealing people (sinister children, predatory con men, cagey opportunists willing to use virtually any means to achieve their ends), he fails here to make this seemingly pleasant, well-to-do English woman remotely sympathetic or understandable. Florence comes across as a narcissistic hysteric, who has manipulated Edward into marriage without confiding any of her neuroses or fears or expectations. As for Edward, he too emerges as a bizarrely opaque character: volatile, self-absorbed and incurious, a myopic twit who never seems to think it odd that Florence dislikes kissing him or making out.</p>
        <p>Mr. McEwan attributes the lack of communication between the newlyweds to the era and its repressive mores: ''They lived in a time when a conversation about sexual difficulties was plainly impossible.'' But while his choice of a time frame for the novel might be some sort of allusion to Philip Larkin's famous lines that ''sexual intercourse began/In nineteen sixty-three'' sometime ''between the end of the Chatterley ban/ And the Beatles' first LP,'' he acts as though 1962 were the early Victorian era, not a time when the Rolling Stones were starting to rock 'n' roll, and ''Who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf?'' was playing on Broadway.</p>
        <p>Worse, he never makes the reader understand what brought Florence and Edward together in the first place, save a mutual desire to escape their parents and start new lives of their own. Florence is a dedicated classical musician, a violinist, who practices five hours a day and attends as many as five chamber recitals a week; Edward regards classical music as something ''best heard in the background at low volume, a stream of undifferentiated mewling, scraping and tooting generally taken to signify seriousness and maturity and respect for the past, and entirely devoid of interest or excitement.'' She hangs out at concert halls and tearooms in her London neighborhood; he haunts the pubs of Fitzrovia and Soho.</p>
        <p>Florence comes from a snooty, upper-class family that wanted to give her skiing, tennis and flying lessons as a girl; Edward grew up in a hard-scrabble, chaotic household where ''the beds were never made, the sheets rarely changed,'' the bathroom never cleaned. When Edward goes to visit Florence's family, he finds the food served there -- things like muesli, cheese that was not cheddar, ratatouille and bouillabaisse -- ''faintly repellent.'' Sometimes, Mr. McEwan writes, ''if he ate too fast, he came close to gagging.''</p>
        <p>As for emotional and physical chemistry, Edward finds himself incredibly attracted to Florence, but Florence finds his attentions repellent. When he tries to put the moves on her during a screening of ''A Taste of Honey,'' she ''leaped out of her seat and into the aisle like a startled gazelle.'' For some reason this episode doesn't discourage Edward or prompt him to talk to her about their relationship. In the course of a year's courtship Florence never tells him about the extreme revulsion she feels for any sort of physical contact, just as Edward never tells her about his ugly temper and his youthful proclivity for getting into fights. In short, neither of them has the faintest idea who the other person really is.</p>
        <p>Perhaps Mr. McEwan means, in recounting the sad ballad of Edward and Florence, to create a sort of Chekhovian fable about missed connections and the failure to communicate. Perhaps he means to re-examine his favorite theme of innocence gone awry, explicated with far greater resonance in his 1990 novel, ''The Innocent.'' Perhaps he means to explore, as he did so beautifully in ''Saturday'' and ''Atonement,'' the precariousness of daily life and the difficulty of achieving -- and holding onto -- ordinary happiness. Unfortunately for the reader he has done none of these things. Instead he's given us a smarmy portrait of two incomprehensible and unlikable people.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
