<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mixed Reaction in Lebanon to U.N. Assassination Tribunal</title>
    <meta content="01lebanon" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/world/middleeast/01lebanon.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851267"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Lebanon</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Security Council</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hariri, Rafik</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E4D91530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mixed Reaction in Lebanon to U.N. Assassination Tribunal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mixed Reaction in Lebanon to U.N. Assassination Tribunal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HASSAN M. FATTAH; Nada Bakri contributed from Beirut, Lebanon, and Hugh Naylor from Damascus, Syria.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Naylor, Hugh; Bakri, Nada; Fattah, Hassan</byline>
      <dateline>DUBAI, United Arab Emirates, May 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After two and a half years of protests, Lebanese who have demanded an international tribunal to try suspects in the 2005 assassination of former Prime Minister Rafik Hariri and in several other politically inspired killings finally got what they wished for.</p>
        <p>But even within Lebanon, the reaction was mixed. And with Syrian intelligence and officials close to President Bashar al-Assad among those already accused of involvement in the Hariri killing, the greatest fear expressed by many in the region on Thursday was that the tribunal approved by the United Nations Security Council on Wednesday would only result in further turmoil.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The greatest fear expressed by many in the region was that the tribunal approved by the United Nations Security Council would only result in further turmoil.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After two and a half years of protests, Lebanese who have demanded an international tribunal to try suspects in the 2005 assassination of former Prime Minister Rafik Hariri and in several other politically inspired killings finally got what they wished for.</p>
        <p>But even within Lebanon, the reaction was mixed. And with Syrian intelligence and officials close to President Bashar al-Assad among those already accused of involvement in the Hariri killing, the greatest fear expressed by many in the region on Thursday was that the tribunal approved by the United Nations Security Council on Wednesday would only result in further turmoil.</p>
        <p>''This is not the Nuremburg trials, where the whole world was in agreement, or a trial over a massacre in Rawanda, where millions were killed,'' said Riad Kahwaji, director of the Institute for Near East and Gulf Military Analyses in Dubai. ''This is a trial for the political murder of several individuals, and what is at stake is the stability and security of the whole region.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hariri, 60, a powerful prime minister who had helped lead Lebanon's reconstruction after 15 years of civil war, was killed with 22 other people in a February 2005 bombing. The ensuing public outcry forced Syria to end its 29-year domination of Lebanon. But it also set off a series of political crises that culminated in a six-month-long sit-in outside the seat of government, bringing much of it to a virtual standstill.</p>
        <p>Supporters of the tribunal hailed it as a major step forward. Late Wednesday, Mr. Hariri's supporters celebrated with fireworks and a visit to Mr. Hariri's grave.</p>
        <p>''We will not fear for our future and that of our children anymore; we can relax at last,'' said Rana Ramadan, 24, a member of the Future Movement, led by Saad Hariri, Rafik Hariri's son and political heir, speaking on Thursday. ''The court was the simplest thing that we could do to honor the martyr Hariri for all the accomplishments he did. It is the beginning of Lebanon's freedom.''</p>
        <p>Critics, however, say they fear it will undermine Lebanon's sovereignty and worsen the country's political instability. Syria, which has been fingered in preliminary investigations, says that senior members of the regime will be forced to testify or be indicted, threatening the very core of its government. Others, like the militant group Hezbollah, say the court will be used by the United States and other Security Council members that oppose its growing political role in Lebanon to weaken it.</p>
        <p>''The resolution is a violation of the sovereignty of Lebanon and an aggressive interference in its internal affairs,'' said a statement issued by Hezbollah on Thursday. ''This is a blatant violation that makes the resolution illegal and illegitimate, both nationally and internationally. The ruling coalition has presented a great gift to the American administration as they put between its hands a political card that it can use for political pressure.''</p>
        <p>The Security Council passed the resolution by a vote of 10 to 0, with China, Qatar, Indonesia, Russia, and South Africa abstaining. The resolution, under Chapter VII of the United Nations charter, makes the court's rulings binding and provides it with powers to indict and interrogate officials who may not have been held accountable before.</p>
        <p>Chapter VII allows the Security Council to take military and nonmilitary action to ''restore international peace and security'' against any threat to peace or act of aggression. Abstaining countries contended that establishing the tribunal under Chapter VII was inappropriate and that a trial can only go ahead if there is a political consensus for it in the country.</p>
        <p>The resolution gives the Lebanones Parliament until June 10 to vote on the existing legislation. If it does not, and few expect that it will, a United Nations tribunal consisting of a majority of international judges and an international prosecutor would be organized in a foreign location.</p>
        <p>In downtown Beirut on Thursday night, many bristled at the idea that the Security Council could impose such a court in the first place, despite the will of the opposition, which is estimated to account for almost half of Lebanon.</p>
        <p>''Lebanon will be turned into a battlefield after this,'' said Hussein Jammoul, 27, a protester who has camped in the tent city in downtown Beirut since December. ''Every foreign country will be able to interfere in Lebanon's affairs.''</p>
        <p>In Damascus on Thursday, many said they feared the implications of the tribunal on a country that has already borne the burden of economic sanctions and international isolation.</p>
        <p>''Why would Syria want to stir so much trouble by killing just one man,'' said Mahmoud Hinawi, a store owner. ''It doesn't make sense that we're blamed for this.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
