<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Now Batting For the Yankees, Lindsay Lohan</title>
    <meta content="01sandomir" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851318"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EFD81530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Now Batting For the Yankees, Lindsay Lohan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Now Alex Rodriguez knows what is like to be Lindsay Lohan, a serial mainstay of celebrity culture. There he was Wednesday on the front page of The New York Post, pictured in a Toronto hotel with a woman, who, as the tabloid noted, was not his wife. ''STRAY-ROD,'' read the perfect headline.</p>
        <p>A day earlier, the Post's front page featured a stark image of Lohan, apparently unconscious in her car. ''SMASHED,'' the headline said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Now Alex Rodriguez knows what is like to be Lindsay Lohan, a serial mainstay of celebrity culture. There he was Wednesday on the front page of The New York Post, pictured in a Toronto hotel with a woman, who, as the tabloid noted, was not his wife. ''STRAY-ROD,'' read the perfect headline.</p>
        <p>A day earlier, the Post's front page featured a stark image of Lohan, apparently unconscious in her car. ''SMASHED,'' the headline said.</p>
        <p>Sports superstars are a different type of celebrity than those in Hollywood, and their species rarely cross-pollinate. Athletes benefit from a media culture in which the beat reporters do not view the reporting of players' off-the-field dalliances as their job -- a compact that dates to newspapers not chronicling Babe Ruth's sexual peccadillos.</p>
        <p>So while the unmarried Derek Jeter might be seen canoodling with a hottie in a Manhattan club, photographers are not staking him out en masse as they do Lohan, Paris Hilton or Britney Spears, or driving him off a road.</p>
        <p>There are no sports couples as delicious to follow as Brad Pitt and Angelina Jolie. But it is tempting to wonder how Joe DiMaggio and Marilyn Monroe would be treated if ''Access Hollywood'' existed in the 1950s.</p>
        <p>''Sports figures in this era, David Beckham aside, do not generate the attention of paparazzi,'' said Larry Hackett, the managing editor of People magazine. There is no regular sports equivalent of 40 photographers camped out at the Ivy Restaurant in Los Angeles waiting for Nicole Richie, he said.</p>
        <p>Criminal cases, court fights and domestic disputes can make athletes into entertainment subjects, no more so than O. J. Simpson, who was retired by the time of the murder of his ex-wife and her friend. Kobe Bryant's sexual-assault case could not be avoided by the celebrity media given his Q rating.</p>
        <p>The divorce filing by the wife of Mets catcher Paul Lo Duca last year led to tabloid stories about Lo Duca's self-described teenage lovers. Michael Jordan transcended sports into entertainment and business, and he got a taste of the tabloid treatment amid reports of his heavy gambling.</p>
        <p>But not one of them had a saga like Anna Nicole Smith's -- although the 1980s love affair of Wade Boggs and Margo Adams was a beauty.</p>
        <p>Hackett and Janice Min, the editor-in-chief of US, said they did not believe that the Rodriguez incident would lead to an accelerated emphasis on sports stars to fill Web sites, pages and airwaves, even though every fan with a cellphone can be a paparazzo. Athletes in their seasons work nearly every day, while actors and celebrities with indefinable talents provide opportunities for paparazzi by shopping, lunching and dining and sunning themselves (the latter a pursuit that a shirtless Rodriguez engaged in last year in Central Park) in New York and Los Angeles, the bicoastal ground zero of their world.</p>
        <p>''In Hollywood, people go out a lot more,'' said Min, who turned down an offer to publish the Rodriguez photos, ''and not a lot of journalists and paparazzi are camped out in a hotel in Cincinnati waiting for ballplayers.''</p>
        <p>Hackett said: ''It's a needle in a haystack to wait for athletes to misbehave, but celebrities go out with other celebrities. There's a hunger to see them.''</p>
        <p>There is virtually no market, Min said, to buy photos of athletes' newborns, as there is in the hard-core celebrity market.</p>
        <p>Athletes raise their celebrity quotient if they date Hollywood stars. Tom Brady dated Bridget Moynahan, who is pregnant with their child, then hooked up with the model Giselle Bündchen, Leonardo DiCaprio's ex-lover.</p>
        <p>Would the entertainment audience know of San Antonio Spurs guard Tony Parker if he were not seeing Eva Longoria? Min said, ''Sports figures are celebrities to men, but celebrities are a female sport.''</p>
        <p>Will Leitch, the editor of Deadspin.com, a sports Web site, said he is fascinated that the lives and affairs of athletes have not been poked and prodded the way they are in entertainment and politics. Political coverage has not been the same since The National Enquirer published photographs of Donna Rice in the former Senator Gary Hart's lap 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>''Athletes have gotten a free ride,'' Leitch said. ''If you're not at the level of an A-Rod, you probably still will. I don't think there's a market for that kind of news unless you have a transcendent level of popularity.''</p>
        <p>Recalling Randy Johnson's attempt to bat away a local news camera in 2005 on his way to his Yankees physical, Leitch said: ''One guy follows him in New York and he freaks out. Even Sean Penn could have handled that.''</p>
        <p>A certain sign that athlete gossip is usually a lightweight pursuit was last year's cancellation, after a brief run, of ''ESPN Hollywood,'' a daily 30-minute series that purported to be the ''Entertainment Tonight'' of sports.</p>
        <p>''It wasn't the best opportunity to cover athletes and entertainment,'' said David Berson, an ESPN executive vice president. ''I think fans want information about athletes in the context of sports coverage.''</p>
        <p>Except now, with the continuing A-Rod news cycle. The mystery woman is surely being pursued, with gobs of cash to be thrown at her to tell her tale. Other players are advised to stay in their hotel rooms. Alone.</p>
        <p>SPORTS BUSINESS E-mail: sportsbiz@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: sportsbiz@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
