<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ancient Aboriginal Tales, Parallel Across Epochs</title>
    <meta content="01cano" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/movies/01cano.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851217"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">De Heer, Rolf</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kurddal, Crusoe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dalaithngu, Jamie Dayindi Gulpilil</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ten Canoes (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Aborigines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aborigines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Ten Canoes (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6DC1530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="987" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ancient Aboriginal Tales, Parallel Across Epochs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ancient Aboriginal Tales, Parallel Across Epochs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews film Ten Canoes, directed by Rolf de Heer; Crusoe Kurddal and Jamie Dayindi Gulpilil Dalaithngu star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''I came from a water hole,'' declares the wise, slyly humorous Storyteller, who narrates ''Ten Canoes,'' Rolf de Heer's mesmerizing film of Australian Aboriginal life many centuries ago. As he muses on birth, death and reincarnation in tribal mythology, and goes on to relate an ancient, rambling fable in which a young man learns patience, the cycle of human life is indivisible from the rhythms of the natural world.</p>
        <p>''Ten Canoes,'' the 10th feature by Mr. de Heer, a Dutch-born Australian filmmaker, is a close collaboration between him and the Ramingining Aboriginal people, many of whom appear in the movie. The first feature made in an Australian indigenous language (there are several different dialects), it swept the 2006 Australian Academy Awards. For the director it was the next logical step into ethnographic territory after his 2002 film, ''The Tracker.'' In its immersion in a primitive culture, it recalls Zacharias Kunuk's comparably impressive 2002 film, ''Atanarjuat'' (''The Fast Runner''), the first Canadian Inuit feature.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is nothing more enthralling than a good yarn, and “Ten Canoes” interweaves two versions of the same story.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''I came from a water hole,'' declares the wise, slyly humorous Storyteller, who narrates ''Ten Canoes,'' Rolf de Heer's mesmerizing film of Australian Aboriginal life many centuries ago. As he muses on birth, death and reincarnation in tribal mythology, and goes on to relate an ancient, rambling fable in which a young man learns patience, the cycle of human life is indivisible from the rhythms of the natural world.</p>
        <p>''Ten Canoes,'' the 10th feature by Mr. de Heer, a Dutch-born Australian filmmaker, is a close collaboration between him and the Ramingining Aboriginal people, many of whom appear in the movie. The first feature made in an Australian indigenous language (there are several different dialects), it swept the 2006 Australian Academy Awards. For the director it was the next logical step into ethnographic territory after his 2002 film, ''The Tracker.'' In its immersion in a primitive culture, it recalls Zacharias Kunuk's comparably impressive 2002 film, ''Atanarjuat'' (''The Fast Runner''), the first Canadian Inuit feature.</p>
        <p>The Storyteller, portrayed by the veteran Aborigine actor David Gulpilil Ridjimiraril Dalaithngu (''Walkabout,'' ''The Last Wave'' and ''Rabbit-Proof Fence,'' billed simply as David Gulpilil), is the only character who speaks English. Almost everyone else in the 90-minute film, set in the Arnhem Land in Australia's Northern Territory, east of Darwin, speaks the Ganalbingu language, which is translated into colloquial, occasionally racy subtitles.</p>
        <p>Once you become accustomed to the mystical vocabulary describing a world without modern science and technology, it amounts to using different terms to describe universal experience. Both the Storyteller's tale and the movie that contains it transport you out of time and leave you wondering if sorcery, religion and psychotherapy are different forms of magic.</p>
        <p>Everything begins and ends with the water hole, where people are fish who ask to be born and where they eventually return, only to repeat the cycle. Evil spirits bring on calamity, and sorcery is the not always reliable solution of last resort.</p>
        <p>There is nothing more enthralling than a good yarn, and ''Ten Canoes'' interweaves two versions of the same story, one filmed in black and white and set a thousand years ago, and an even older one, filmed in color and set in a mythic, prehistoric past.</p>
        <p>The newer narrative begins when the tribal chief, Minygululu (Peter Minygululu), leads 10 warriors on a journey deep into the forest to gather bark to make canoes, which they paddle into a crocodile-infested swamp in search of goose eggs. Making the trip for the first time is Minygululu's impatient younger brother, Dayindi (Jamie Dayindi Gulpilil Dalaithngu, David Gulpilil Ridjimiraril Dalaithngu's son), who vents his frustration at having no wife. He pines for the youngest of Minygululu's three wives, though to pursue her would be to violate tribal law.</p>
        <p>As their journey continues, Minygululu pacifies Dayindi by regaling him with an ancient story that addresses his plight. Its message can be boiled down to the phrase ''All in good time.''</p>
        <p>There is a lot of playful wit in the story. The men laugh and tease each other about sexual prowess and endowment, while back in camp the women squabble and complain about their husbands.</p>
        <p>The look of these black-and-white scenes was inspired by a photo of 10 canoeists taken by the anthropologist Donald Thomson, who worked in the area in the mid-1930s and lived for months among the original inhabitants, the Yolngu. Thomson left behind 4,000 black-and-white photographs of the Yolngu culture.</p>
        <p>The ancient story Minygululu tells to his younger brother is a loose-jointed fable whose solemnity is continually undercut by joking asides and tangents that propose alternative directions the tale might take. Its central character, Minygululu's ancient ancestor, Ridjimiraril (Crusoe Kurddal), is also a tribal chief who lives with three wives, one wise, one jealous and one (the youngest) beautiful.</p>
        <p>Like Dayindi, Ridjimiraril's younger brother, Yeeralparil (played by the same actor), pines for the youngest and prettiest of his older brother's wives. Shortly after a stranger visits the tribe, Ridjimiraril's middle wife disappears, and her husband imagines that she has been kidnapped by the stranger.</p>
        <p>Months later another visitor reports that the wife has been spotted living with the stranger in a distant camp. Ridjimiraril leads a war party to retrieve her, but she is not there. Yeeralparil is forbidden to join the party because if his older brother is killed, he must take over his wives. There is much more to come, including murder and revenge and threat of war. But you can see where this is headed as a fable.</p>
        <p>Contemplating a film like ''Ten Canoes'' or ''Atanarjuat,'' you confront inevitable questions about the depiction of primitive peoples in feature films and documentaries. Where does detached observation end and emotional identification begin? At what point does admiration for the noble savage become condescending and sentimental? If the humor of ''Ten Canoes'' largely liberates it from ethnographic solemnity, it feels suspiciously contemporary.</p>
        <p>The cinematographer Ian Jones's ravishing vision of an unspoiled paradise seduces you as powerfully as John Toll's photography did in Terrence Malick's ''Thin Red Line.'' In the Malick film, set on Guadalcanal, paradise is despoiled almost from the moment it is discovered and soldiers tramp across its sacred ground. In ''Ten Canoes'' that paradise is an eternal past.</p>
        <p>Ten Canoes  Opens today in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Directed by Rolf de Heer; written (in various Yolngu Aboriginal dialects, with English subtitles) by Mr. de Heer and the people of Ramingining; director of photography, Ian Jones; edited by Tania Nehme; traditional music performed by Richard Birrinbirrin, Peter Minygululu, Billy Black, John Nudumul and Mark Muruwirri; produced by Mr. de Heer and Julie Ryan; released by Palm Pictures. At the Cinema Village, 22 East 12th Street, Greenwich Village. Running time: 90 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: Crusoe Kurddal (Ridjimiraril), Jamie Dayindi Gulpilil Dalaithngu (Dayindi/Yeeralparil), Richard Birrinbirrin (Birrinbirrin), Peter Minygululu (Minygululu), Frances Djulibing (Nowalingu) and David Gulpilil Ridjimiraril Dalaithngu (the Storyteller).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
