<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hard-Won Garbage Plan Runs Into Trouble in Albany</title>
    <meta content="01garbage" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/nyregion/01garbage.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851336"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6D71530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="956" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hard-Won Garbage Plan Runs Into Trouble in Albany</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hard-Won Garbage Plan Runs Into Trouble in Albany</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAY RIVERA; Danny Hakim contributed reporting.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It seemed like a political milestone of sorts. After two years of squabbling, the City Council and Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg reached an agreement last year to overhaul the way the city disposes of garbage.</p>
        <p>Compromises had been made and constituencies had been mollified. The system seemed workable. And then the plan went to Albany.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the heart of the fight are questions about the city’s plans to place a garbage recycling station on the Gansevoort Peninsula just south of West 14th Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It seemed like a political milestone of sorts. After two years of squabbling, the City Council and Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg reached an agreement last year to overhaul the way the city disposes of garbage.</p>
        <p>Compromises had been made and constituencies had been mollified. The system seemed workable. And then the plan went to Albany.</p>
        <p>The plan is intended to expand recycling and reduce the number of garbage trucks on city streets by increasing the use of barges and trains. Now the hard-fought agreement is in trouble because state legislators from the West Side of Manhattan oppose a key element.</p>
        <p>At the heart of the fight are questions about the city's plans to place a garbage recycling station on the Gansevoort Peninsula just south of West 14th Street. Mr. Bloomberg says that the station is critical to the 20-year plan, and that without it all the other pieces will fall apart.</p>
        <p>But three Assembly members whose districts either include or are near the Gansevoort site say the city has never adequately studied alternative locations, and they are threatening to use their clout with Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, a Democrat who is also from Lower Manhattan, to kill it.</p>
        <p>''My position is that particular location is an illegal location,'' said Assemblywoman Deborah J. Glick, a Democrat whose district abuts the site. ''There are better alternatives that can be implemented quickly and that would have greater carrying capacity.''</p>
        <p>The mayor and the City Council speaker, Christine C. Quinn, say the legislators' objections are steeped in the kind of parochial politics that the Council, led by Ms. Quinn, fought hard to overcome in passing this plan. It calls for each borough to handle its own waste, and in the spirit of promoting that idea, Ms. Quinn agreed to the Gansevoort station, which is in her district.</p>
        <p>At a news conference at the site yesterday, Mayor Bloomberg said, ''We simply can't let this element of our solid waste management strategy fall prey to a shortsighted not-in-my-backyard mindset.'' The site currently houses a city Sanitation Department garage, a road salt warehouse and the remains of a waste transfer station that operated there until the early 1990s.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloomberg was flanked by Ms. Quinn and a handful of council members, environmentalists and community advocates from the other boroughs who say that Manhattan should start handling its own waste instead of trucking it to poorer neighborhoods around the city.</p>
        <p>At the urging of city officials, the Republican leadership of the State Senate has introduced a bill that would amend the Hudson River Park Act, which is required to place the facility at the Gansevoort site. City officials say the amendment is the final hurdle to implementing the full plan.</p>
        <p>But in the Assembly, the city has been forced to turn for help to Assemblyman Adriano Espaillat of Upper Manhattan. He is expected to introduce a similar measure next week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Espaillat's involvement in a matter outside his district has drawn the ire of Ms. Glick and the two other Assembly members most opposed to the Gansevoort site: Richard N. Gottfried and Linda B. Rosenthal.</p>
        <p>Just two weeks ago Mr. Espaillat signed a letter along with two dozen other Assembly members raising concerns about the site. But he said he changed his mind after concluding that the new plan would reduce the burden of neighborhoods in the Bronx and Brooklyn that currently handle much of Manhattan's waste.</p>
        <p>Ms. Glick insists this fight is not about parochialism. She says she wants to protect Hudson River Park, which was created in 1998 by the Legislature.</p>
        <p>Ms. Glick, who said that creating the park was a ''very, very, long, complicated political process,'' asserted that she would prefer that the Gansevoort site be turned into parkland instead of a recycling station. ''It is unacceptable for the city to within a few short years seek to undo one of the lynchpins to that agreement,'' Ms. Glick said.</p>
        <p>The three Assembly members say there are better alternatives in their districts, including converting Pier 76 from a tow pound to a transfer station. ''The city has attacked these proposals but has never studied them,'' Mr. Gottfried said. ''It's a pretty typical City Hall response to attack an alternative that you have never studied.''</p>
        <p>Administration officials say the alternatives are fraught with problems that make them unworkable.</p>
        <p>Without the Gansevoort station, they say, recyclable metal, glass and plastic from Manhattan would continue to be moved by truck to facilities in the Bronx, Brooklyn and New Jersey, leaving residents of those areas to contend with traffic congestion and air quality problems.</p>
        <p>In addition to easing those burdens, city officials say the Gansevoort site would also free up capacity at an existing paper recycling facility at 59th Street on the Hudson River to handle Manhattan's commercial waste, which the Assembly members also object to.</p>
        <p>Ms. Glick and Mr. Gottfried are senior Democrats who lead two of the most prominent committees in the Assembly: Higher Education and Health Care, respectively. More important, they both have strong ties to Mr. Silver, who has the power to block the transfer station and who has not hesitated in the past to stop major projects that had strong support from city officials.</p>
        <p>Most notably, his opposition to the development of a West Side stadium for the New York Jets doomed the project, one that Mr. Bloomberg had sought for nearly four years.</p>
        <p>Asked about the transfer station, Charles Carrier, a spokesman for Mr. Silver, said a bill on the issue had not been introduced in the Assembly.</p>
        <p>''We have no bill,'' he said. ''Until we have a bill, we would have to wait to see what they are asking us to do.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
