<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Search for Abducted Britons Continues Across Baghdad</title>
    <meta content="01iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/world/middleeast/01iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E5D91530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="964" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Search for Abducted Britons Continues Across Baghdad</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Search for Abducted Britons Continues Across Baghdad</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMIEN CAVE; Muhanad Seloom and Iraqi employees of The New York Times contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cave, Damien; seloom, muhanad</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, May 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The search for five British civilians kidnapped from an Iraqi government building intensified Thursday with American troops conducting raids in Sadr City and the Iraqi government pledging its support for an investigation.</p>
        <p>Several residents in Sadr City, the sprawling Shiite stronghold, said American airstrikes killed two brothers in the neighborhood overnight, an assertion the American military denied.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The search for five British civilians kidnapped from an Iraqi government building intensified and the Iraqi government pledged its support for an investigation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The search for five British civilians kidnapped from an Iraqi government building intensified Thursday with American troops conducting raids in Sadr City and the Iraqi government pledging its support for an investigation.</p>
        <p>Several residents in Sadr City, the sprawling Shiite stronghold, said American airstrikes killed two brothers in the neighborhood overnight, an assertion the American military denied.</p>
        <p>Iraq's Shiite-led government, in an effort to distance itself from the abduction, said Thursday that it was working closely with the British authorities to find the kidnapped civilians and their captors.</p>
        <p>''The Iraqi government has undertaken urgent measures to determine the facts and locate the kidnappers,'' said a statement from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs. It added that ''the government condemns this crime and is doing all it can to ensure the immediate release of the kidnapped Britons.''</p>
        <p>The gunmen who abducted the Britons -- a business consultant and his four bodyguards -- were seen speeding toward Sadr City after the attack. The gunmen, wearing police commando uniforms and driving official sport utility vehicles, are believed to be members of the Mahdi Army, a militia loyal to the populist Shiite cleric Moktada al-Sadr.</p>
        <p>The fact that the kidnappers completed the abduction without firing a shot has led some Iraqi and Western officials to suspect that they were militants who had infiltrated the national police and received assistance from employees at the Finance Ministry complex, where the abductions occurred.</p>
        <p>The finance minister, Bayan Jabr, is a Shiite and a former interior minister who oversaw the rapid growth of Iraq's security forces at a time when Sunni and American officials accused the ministry of allowing its ranks to be infiltrated by militiamen. Mr. Jabr has made no public comment on the attack.</p>
        <p>Also on Thursday, the United States military announced that two American soldiers were killed and two wounded by a roadside bomb in southwestern Baghdad on Wednesday and that a third died Tuesday as a result of a roadside bomb on Monday in northwestern Baghdad.</p>
        <p>The announcements bring the American military death toll for May to 123, according to Iraq Coalition Casualty Count http://icasualties.org/oif/, a Web site that tracks military and civilian casualties. The figure could rise. The military said eight American soldiers were wounded Thursday in a suicide car bomb attack at a checkpoint in a Sunni area of eastern Baghdad.</p>
        <p>According to data on the Web site, May has become the third-deadliest month of the war for American troops. In November 2004, 137 American service members died in Iraq. In April 2004, 135 died.</p>
        <p>The troops nonetheless continued with their mission. In Kadhimiya, a center of power for Shiite politicians and militias, Iraqi and American troops detained a commander from the Mahdi Army suspected of murdering and intimidating Iraqis and ordering attacks on American troops.</p>
        <p>And violence here continued. In Anbar Province, a suicide truck bomb exploded in Ramadi, killing five people, including three policemen, said Tariq Yousif, an Iraqi security official.</p>
        <p>A suicide bomber who exploded at a police recruitment center in Falluja killed one policeman and wounded eight people, according to American military officials. News agencies reported that 20 people were killed.</p>
        <p>The authorities found 29 bodies throughout Baghdad.</p>
        <p>The police in Diyala Province said they found a grave with five bodies in Baquba.</p>
        <p>An Associated Press Television News cameraman was shot and killed in Baghdad on Thursday while walking to a mosque near his home, according to the news agency.</p>
        <p>American officials also said that an Iraqi husband and wife who work for the United States Embassy in Baghdad appear to have been kidnapped, news agencies reported. In Amiriya, a Sunni area of western Baghdad, fighting erupted for at least four hours between two Sunni militant groups, Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia and a group known as the Islamic Army, witnesses said.</p>
        <p>Yassir, a 26-year-old witness who would give only his first name, said that he saw at least four bodies in the main commercial street.</p>
        <p>Witnesses and an Interior Ministry official said the battle reflected a fight for control that began three weeks ago after the two groups met and could not agree on a strategy for resistance to American troops.</p>
        <p>The fighting started at 3:30 p.m., they said; four hours later, Americans soldiers intervened, but gunfire could still be heard after 11 p.m.</p>
        <p>''We heard a lot of booms,'' Yassir said. He added that some rocket-propelled grenades had been fired, ''and even some houses have been destroyed.''</p>
        <p>Gates Weighs U.S. Presence in Iraq  By The New York Times</p>
        <p>HONOLULU May 31 -- Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates did not rule out that the Bush administration might need time beyond September to make a full assessment of the troop buildup in Iraq. But he said that no firm decision had been made to delay such an assessment until the end of the year or early next year.</p>
        <p>''I don't think the goalposts have changed really at all,'' Mr. Gates said to reporters in Hawaii after he received briefings at the United States Pacific Command.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates said that political dynamics in Washington would no doubt increase pressure in the coming months for the Bush administration to publicly measure the success or failure of the so-called surge, but that he did not want commanders in Iraq to be influenced by that.</p>
        <p>''Our military commanders should not have to worry about the Washington clock,'' he said. ''That's for us to worry about.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates spoke of an ''enduring'' American military commitment to Iraq, unlike the American troop withdrawal from Vietnam, where he said the United States ''left lock, stock and barrel.'' He said that the American presence in Iraq could be modeled after the long American commitment to South Korea and Japan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
