<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wie's Day Ends With Wrong Kind of Buzz</title>
    <meta content="01golf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/sports/golf/01golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851343"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Wie, Michelle</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E4D71530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="941" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wie's Day Ends With Wrong Kind of Buzz</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Wie’s Day Ends With Wrong Kind of Buzz</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <dateline>MOUNT PLEASANT, S.C., May 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michelle Wie winced as she watched her tee shot soar out of bounds on an uncomplicated par 5 at the Ginn Tribute on Thursday morning. She was trying to salvage a disastrous round, her first in a tournament since January. She had already sprayed shots into the woods, fished others out of the tall swooping grass that grows in the swamp here and annoyed her playing partners when her father spoke to her during a previous calamitous hole.</p>
        <p>This, though, became Wie's most spectacularly awful shot of the day. Wie, who started on the back nine, hit her drive so far right on the par-5 No. 3 that it hit a car parked along Palmetto Isle Drive. Her ball bounced back toward the course, only to roll down a storm drain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michelle Wie sent balls flying all over the course and annoyed her playing partners before withdrawing from the Ginn Tribute on Thursday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Michelle Wie winced as she watched her tee shot soar out of bounds on an uncomplicated par 5 at the Ginn Tribute on Thursday morning. She was trying to salvage a disastrous round, her first in a tournament since January. She had already sprayed shots into the woods, fished others out of the tall swooping grass that grows in the swamp here and annoyed her playing partners when her father spoke to her during a previous calamitous hole.</p>
        <p>This, though, became Wie's most spectacularly awful shot of the day. Wie, who started on the back nine, hit her drive so far right on the par-5 No. 3 that it hit a car parked along Palmetto Isle Drive. Her ball bounced back toward the course, only to roll down a storm drain.</p>
        <p>Wie hit another tee shot, which she hooked left into a swamp, and finished with a 10. She withdrew from the tournament after 16 holes when she was 14 over par.</p>
        <p>''It was actually quite funny,'' Wie said of her adventures at No. 3. ''I was going to crawl down the drain and prove it was inbounds, but I couldn't fit into the drain.''</p>
        <p>Wie, 17, was still trying to make the best of her day when her manager, Greg Nared, approached her as she walked to the tee at No. 8. Nared had spent the previous two holes talking on his cellphone and conferring with Wie's parents. She listened to Nared, signed her opponents' scorecards and was whisked away in a cart.</p>
        <p>Wie said she withdrew because she ''tweaked'' one of her wrists, the injury that had kept her out of competition for the past four months. But Wie was also in danger of shooting an 88, and if she did, she would be disqualified from playing in another L.P.G.A. event this year. Tour rules say that non-Tour members cannot play again if they fail to break 88 in a round. Wie, who is not a Tour member, was playing on a sponsor's exemption.</p>
        <p>When she left, Wie may have faced a two-shot penalty if her playing partners had pressed their complaint about B. J. Wie making a comment after his daughter hit her tee shot into the woods on No. 14. He said something about her returning to the tee for her next shot instead of taking a drop.</p>
        <p>At the time, Janice Moodie, one of her playing partners, spoke to the Wies. After the round, when Wie's withdrawal made the point moot, Moodie said she did not believe the conversation qualified as ''outside coaching,'' which is against the rules.</p>
        <p>''He was very close to her and that's what I questioned,'' Moodie said.</p>
        <p>Wie has faced complaints about her father's behavior and etiquette when he was her caddie early in her career, and she was disqualified from her first tournament as a professional two years ago after taking a bad drop.</p>
        <p>Wie's parents and manager left the course without comment Thursday.</p>
        <p>Although Wie did answer questions, she skirted the issue of what her father said and evaded saying whether the 88-strokes rule prompted her withdrawal. ''I don't think about shooting 88,'' she said. ''That's not what I do.''</p>
        <p>Alena Sharp, Wie's other playing partner, said she did not see Wie struggling with her wrist. She had made no outward signs, other than her terrible round, that she was hurting.</p>
        <p>The day's events will clearly not further Wie's tenuous acceptance by the other members of the L.P.G.A. Tour. There have been numerous complaints about her lack of commitment to women's golf and there is resentment about the attention she gets despite never having won a pro tournament.</p>
        <p>Thursday, however, most of the players were cautious about commenting on Wie's withdrawal.</p>
        <p>''I don't understand exactly what is going on, but hopefully she is O.K.,'' said Lorena Ochoa, the world's No. 1 female player who shot a four-under-par 68 and was two shots behind the leader, Angela Park.</p>
        <p>''That's a bummer,'' said Annika Sorenstam, who is the official host of this tournament and is playing in her first tournament after recovering from a back injury. ''I know what it's like to be injured. I guess mine healed better than hers.''</p>
        <p>Sorenstam shot an even-par 72 in her return, which helped to give her tournament a shot of encouraging news to counter Wie's fiasco.</p>
        <p>Wie's round continued a string of poor performances that stretch back to last season, before her wrist injuries became an issue. She has not broken par in a women's event since last summer. Her last several appearances in men's events have left her nowhere close to making the cut. In her last one, the Sony Open in January, she missed the cut by 14 strokes.</p>
        <p>Still, Wie said she hoped to play next week at the McDonald's L.P.G.A. Championship despite her injury.</p>
        <p>''The last thing I want to do is not play next week,'' Wie said. ''I'm really excited to get back in the game and play in tournaments again. I'm going to reanalyze it and kind of try to be smart about it. But I definitely want to play next week.''</p>
        <p>Wie had tried to stay cheerful during her round, even throwing her arms up in celebration after she hit a terrific approach shot to within a foot of the pin for her only birdie on No. 18. She tried to coax other shots back in play as they were heading astray.</p>
        <p>''The only way to go from here is up,'' Wie said.</p>
        <p>She might have said that on the No. 3 tee as well, only to find that things could indeed get worse.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
