<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Defense Team Asks Leniency From Judge In Libby Case</title>
    <meta content="01libby." name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/washington/01libby-.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851281"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News Sources, Confidential Status of</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Libby, I Lewis Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Plame, Valerie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Fitzgerald, Patrick J</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1D91530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="555" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Defense Team Asks Leniency From Judge In Libby Case</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Defense Team Asks Leniency From Judge in Libby Case</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL A. LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Neil A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawyers for I. Lewis Libby Jr. urged a federal judge on Thursday to consider his long record of public service and spare him from prison on his felony conviction for his role in a C.I.A. leak investigation.</p>
        <p>The lawyers recommended that Mr. Libby, the former chief of staff to Vice President Dick Cheney, be given probation, possibly with community service, when he is sentenced on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawyers for I. Lewis Libby Jr. urged a federal judge to consider his long record of public service and spare him from prison on his felony conviction for his role in a C.I.A. leak investigation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lawyers for I. Lewis Libby Jr. urged a federal judge on Thursday to consider his long record of public service and spare him from prison on his felony conviction for his role in a C.I.A. leak investigation.</p>
        <p>The lawyers recommended that Mr. Libby, the former chief of staff to Vice President Dick Cheney, be given probation, possibly with community service, when he is sentenced on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Libby was convicted in March of lying to a grand jury and F.B.I. agents investigating the leak of the identity of a Central Intelligence Agency operative, Valerie Wilson.</p>
        <p>The prosecutor, Patrick J. Fitzgerald, asked last week that Mr. Libby be sentenced to 30 to 37 months for his conviction for perjury and obstruction of justice.</p>
        <p>Judge Reggie B. Walton, who presided over the trial, has great leeway in fixing a sentence because federal guidelines are no longer as binding as they once were. But they still provide a recommended time range that is reached by a complicated calculation. The probation office calculated the range as 15 to 21 months, Mr. Libby's lawyers said.</p>
        <p>''Distinguished public servant. Generous mentor. Selfless friend,'' begins the court filing in which Mr. Libby's lawyers asked that he be spared prison. ''This is the rich portrait of Mr. Libby that emerges from the description of him in more than 160 heartfelt letters submitted to the court on his behalf.''</p>
        <p>''There is no denying the seriousness of the crimes of which Mr. Libby was convicted,'' the lawyers wrote. ''At the same time, there is no denying the kind of person Mr. Libby is and the contributions he has made to his country.''</p>
        <p>While the two sides have offered starkly different proposals for Mr. Libby's sentence, another question to be decided by Judge Walton may be equally important. If he sentences Mr. Libby to prison, he has to decide whether he should begin serving his time immediately or be allowed to remain free pending his appeal. The issue could bear on whether Mr. Libby receives a presidential pardon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Libby's lawyers and other supporters have said President Bush should issue a pardon, and if Mr. Libby is sent to jail on Tuesday, that decision would have to be put immediately in front of the president if a pardon were to have any value. The White House has not commented on the possibility of a pardon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fitzgerald argued against leniency, saying Mr. Libby had not shown any remorse for his crimes. And the punishment should be greater, he argued, because the crimes were serious and Mr. Libby's refusal to tell the truth cost the government money. Prosecutors were obliged to engage in a difficult and costly effort to persuade reporters to testify before the grand jury.</p>
        <p>Mr. Libby, known by the nickname Scooter, was not charged with leaking Ms. Wilson's name but with lying about his conversations with reporters about her to the authorities investigating the leak.</p>
        <p>The letters written to the judge on behalf of Mr. Libby came from family friends and senior military officers, among others, according to Thursday's filing. It did not mention whether Mr. Bush or Mr. Cheney had sent letters of support, and their press officials would not say whether they had written any.</p>
        <p>Judge Walton ruled that all the letters would be made public after sentencing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
