<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suspect in Ex-Agent's Poisoning Insists He Was Framed</title>
    <meta content="01poison" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/world/europe/01poison.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851249"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poisoning and Poisons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Intelligence Services</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kgb (Soviet Security Police)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chivers, C J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lugovoi, Andrei K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berezovsky, Boris A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Poisoning and Poisions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Intelligence Services</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poisoning and Poisons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Intelligence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Litvinenko, Alexander V</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lugovoi, Andrei K</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Berezovsky, Boris A</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E6D91530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1110" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suspect in Ex-Agent's Poisoning Insists He Was Framed</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Suspect in Ex-Agent’s Poisoning Insists He Was Framed</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J CHIVERS and ALAN COWELL; C. J. Chivers reported from Moscow, and Alan Cowell from London.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan; Chivers, C J</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, May 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russian businessman Andrei K Lugovoi, suspect in fatal poisoning of former KGB officer Alexander V Litvinenko, claims he is being framed by those responsible for killing, Britain's foreign intelligence agency and self-exiled Russian tycoon Boris A Berezovsky; holds that British intelligence officers tried to recruit him to collect compromising material about Russian Pres Vladimir V Putin; makes his claims at news conference in Moscow, during which he gives sensational but unverifiable descriptions of supposed actions of spies and their agents among Russians living in London; British government and Berezovsky promptly deny plotting killing of Litvinenko, who died last year in Britain; conflicting allegations exploit and underscore deepening suspicions between Russia and West; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The suspect in the fatal poisoning of Alexander V. Litvinenko, the former K.G.B. officer and Kremlin critic who died last year in Britain, said Thursday that Britain's foreign intelligence agency and a self-exiled Russian tycoon had organized the killing and framed him to create a political scandal.</p>
        <p>The suspect, the Russian businessman Andrei K. Lugovoi, also contended that British intelligence officers had tried to recruit him to collect compromising material about President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Andrei K. Lugovoi said that Britain’s foreign intelligence agency and a self-exiled Russian tycoon had organized the killing and framed him to create a political scandal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The suspect in the fatal poisoning of Alexander V. Litvinenko, the former K.G.B. officer and Kremlin critic who died last year in Britain, said Thursday that Britain's foreign intelligence agency and a self-exiled Russian tycoon had organized the killing and framed him to create a political scandal.</p>
        <p>The suspect, the Russian businessman Andrei K. Lugovoi, also contended that British intelligence officers had tried to recruit him to collect compromising material about President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia.</p>
        <p>''The poisoning of Litvinenko could not have been but under the control of the British special service,'' Mr. Lugovoi said at a packed news conference here, during which he gave sensational but unverifiable descriptions of the supposed actions of spies and their agents among Russians living in London.</p>
        <p>He said he had evidence supporting ''this dark political story in which British special services play the main role.'' He refused to disclose it, saying he would provide his information only to the Russian government.</p>
        <p>The British government and Boris A. Berezovsky, the tycoon, promptly denied plotting the killing. ''This is a criminal not an intelligence matter,'' said a British official who spoke on condition of anonymity under civil service rules. Mr. Berezovsky, a bitter enemy of Mr. Putin, described Mr. Lugovoi's appearance as a publicity stunt organized by the Kremlin.</p>
        <p>The conflicting allegations exploited and underscored the deepening suspicions between Russia and the West, even as they brought new twists to a case that has fascinated the public on each side of the old cold war divide. They also elevated the case to a new level of public theater, combining elements of a bungled espionage thriller with claims of innocence reminiscent of the O. J. Simpson case.</p>
        <p>''They have found a Russian James Bond, who penetrated nuclear centers and poisoned his friend in cold blood and along with this contaminated himself, his children and his wife,'' Mr. Lugovoi said. ''And all of it has been done by the lone terrorist, Lugovoi.''</p>
        <p>''They thought I would be silent,'' he added. ''But this is not going to happen.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Litvinenko died an excruciating death on Nov. 23, 2006, after being poisoned by polonium 210, a rare radioactive isotope that investigators said had been slipped into his drink during a meeting with Mr. Lugovoi at a bar in a London hotel three weeks earlier. From his deathbed, he accused Mr. Putin of having a hand in the crime.</p>
        <p>The Kremlin has denied playing any role, and condemned suggestions that Mr. Putin was involved as intended to discredit Russia.</p>
        <p>Last week, Britain's Crown Prosecution Service accused Mr. Lugovoi of murder, saying it had evidence that he had poisoned Mr. Litvinenko. The two men had worked for the K.G.B., although in different departments. This week, Britain asked Russia to extradite Mr. Lugovoi to stand trial. Russia has not formally replied to the request but has made clear that it will refuse.</p>
        <p>At the briefing on Thursday, Mr. Lugovoi, whose travels through London last fall left a trail of polomium 210 traces in offices, hotel rooms, restaurants and bars, jabbed his finger at the crowd and declared himself a victim.</p>
        <p>He spoke swiftly and often excitedly. At times his allegations contradicted one another, as when he suggested that Mr. Litvinenko had been killed by a Spanish arm of the Russian mafia, or on orders from Mr. Berezovsky in revenge for a failed blackmail attempt.</p>
        <p>He was consistent on one matter: his claims of innocence. He said he could not even remember whether Mr. Litvinenko had ordered a drink at the time he was suspected of being poisoned, because he and another associate from former Soviet intelligence circles, Dmitri V, Kovtun, ''were going to football and had a good dose of alcohol.''</p>
        <p>''What kind of idiot poisoner one would be, to act so primitively,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lugovoi also described the supposed advances of British intelligence officers and agents, saying that through Mr. Berezovsky and Mr. Litvinenko he was lured to meetings in 2005 with RISC Management Ltd. of London.</p>
        <p>After the meetings, he said, he was suspiciously overpaid through a company in Cyprus to gather information about business risks in Russia. Later, he said, ''The Brits became interested in everything: my connections, financial potential, existence of direct access to the president of Russia as well as contacts with employees'' of Russian intelligence agencies.</p>
        <p>He called the escalation a ''banal recruitment'' that contained ''specific political and intelligence tasks dealing with Russia and its president.''</p>
        <p>RISC Management is a private consultancy that says it offers clients risk assessment, corporate intelligence and security services. Traces of polonium were found in its offices after Mr. Litvinenko died.</p>
        <p>Cliff Knuckey, the company's managing director, said it would not comment on Mr. Lugovoi's allegation but had cooperated with the British police in the case. ''We have provided evidence to Scotland Yard, and we are not going to compromise any investigations they are pursuing,'' he said in a brief telephone interview.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lugovoi also said that Mr. Litvinenko, who made his name in part by stridently criticizing Mr. Putin and Russia's intelligence services, had proposed a racket to secure asylum for Russians who would publicly criticize Russian authorities.</p>
        <p>This allegation aligned neatly with assertions in recent years by the Kremlin and the Federal Security Service, a successor of the K.G.B., that domestic political opponents in Russia received foreign support, including from intelligence agents.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lugovoi also said Mr. Litvinenko and Mr. Berezovsky worked for the British foreign intelligence agency, MI6, and accused the British government of spreading traces of polonium along his and Mr. Kovtun's routes to try to frame them. ''We were marked by polonium on purpose for the future use in a political scandal,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berezovsky issued a statement describing Mr. Lugovoi's appearance as a spectacle choreographed by the Kremlin. ''It is now clearer than ever that the Kremlin is behind the murder of Alexander Litvinenko,'' it read. ''Everything about Mr. Lugovoi's words and presentation made it obvious that he is acting on Kremlin instruction.''</p>
        <p>He challenged Mr. Lugovoi to demonstrate his innocence in British court. Mr. Lugovoi said that he would not go to Britain, but that he had retained British lawyers.</p>
        <p>The British government, which avoids comment on operational intelligence matters, did not respond to Mr. Lugovoi's accusations that Mr. Litvinenko and Mr. Berezovsky had worked for MI6. It suggested that by accusing the secret service, Mr. Lugovoi sought to distract attention from a central issue -- its demand for his appearance in court. ''We are still seeking his extradition,'' the British official said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
