<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-Governor Says Affidavit Shows Politics In Bribe Case</title>
    <meta content="01prosecute" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/us/01prosecute.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851275"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Alabama</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Siegelman, Don E</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E2D91530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="659" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-Governor Says Affidavit Shows Politics In Bribe Case</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ex-Governor Says Affidavit Shows Politics in Bribe Case</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>BIRMINGHAM, Ala., May 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alabama has a tradition of savage political warfare, but Don E. Siegelman's fight to stay out of prison is reverberating all the way back to Washington.</p>
        <p>Federal prosecutors here are seeking 30 years in prison for Mr. Siegelman, who was the Democratic governor of Alabama from 1999 to 2003 and was convicted last year of accepting $500,000 in bribes from the chairman of the HealthSouth Corporation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal prosecutors are seeking 30 years in prison for Don E. Siegelman, former governor of Alabama who was convicted of accepting $500,000 in bribes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Alabama has a tradition of savage political warfare, but Don E. Siegelman's fight to stay out of prison is reverberating all the way back to Washington.</p>
        <p>Federal prosecutors here are seeking 30 years in prison for Mr. Siegelman, who was the Democratic governor of Alabama from 1999 to 2003 and was convicted last year of accepting $500,000 in bribes from the chairman of the HealthSouth Corporation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Siegelman, who is scheduled for sentencing on June 26, says he was singled out by prosecutors with close personal ties to Alabama Republican leaders and to the Bush White House.</p>
        <p>Mr. Siegelman's defenders have tied his plight to the uproar in Washington over the Bush administration's decision to dismiss eight United States attorneys, but they have produced no firm evidence of political interference.</p>
        <p>Now they have an affidavit from a lawyer who says she heard a top Republican operative in Alabama boast in 2002 that the United States attorneys in Alabama would ''take care'' of Mr. Siegelman. The operative, William Canary, is married to the United States attorney in Montgomery, Leura G. Canary. Mr. Canary, who heads the Business Council of Alabama, was an informal adviser to Bob Riley, a Republican, who defeated Mr. Siegelman in 2002.</p>
        <p>Earlier, Mr. Canary worked in the White House under President Bush's father and has close ties to Karl Rove, Mr. Bush's top political strategist.</p>
        <p>In the affidavit, the lawyer, Jill Simpson, said Mr. Canary's remark was made in a conference call with her and Rob Riley, Governor Riley's son and campaign manager.</p>
        <p>Ms. Simpson said Mr. Canary assured the younger Mr. Riley that ''his girls would take care of'' Mr. Siegelman before he had a chance to run for the governor's seat in 2006 and identified ''his girls'' as Leura Canary and Alice Martin, the United States attorney in Birmingham.</p>
        <p>Neither Mr. Canary nor Mr. Riley responded to requests for comment about Ms. Simpson's affidavit.</p>
        <p>In 2003, Ms. Canary recused herself from the investigation, after Mr. Siegelman's lawyer accused her of conflicts of interest. She turned the case over to Louis Franklin, a career prosecutor who had served under Republicans and Democrats.</p>
        <p>After a nine-week trial last year, a jury acquitted Mr. Siegelman on 25 counts and convicted him on 7, almost all tied to accepting money from Richard Scrushy, the former chairman of HealthSouth. Mr. Siegelman was not convicted of pocketing any money himself. Rather, a jury convicted him of persuading Mr. Scrushy to pay $500,000 to retire the debt of a political group that had campaigned to win voter approval for a state lottery.</p>
        <p>Mr. Siegelman had championed the lottery as a way to raise money for education, and he had co-signed a loan to the group that tried to win voter support for it. ''The only act I did was to try to get kids a free college education,'' Mr. Siegelman said this week.</p>
        <p>But Justice Department officials dismiss Mr. Siegelman's protests, saying in a sentencing memorandum to the court that he ran the state government ''like a grocery store.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Franklin, who led the prosecution, said his team of investigators methodically uncovered evidence that Mr. Siegelman and other top officials received thousands of dollars in money and gifts from businessmen who sought contracts, tax breaks and other help from the state government.</p>
        <p>''He traded on his office, and that is a very significant crime,'' Mr. Franklin said Thursday in an interview.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franklin, who said he had not seen the affidavit, said he had gone to great lengths to prevent Ms. Canary from seeing information about the case.</p>
        <p>''I get deeply offended when Siegelman says I didn't control this case,'' he said. ''If he wants to put this on anybody, it should be me. I made the decision.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Franklin said he had faced resistance from some in the Justice Department and said he had to work hard to win approval for indicting the former governor.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
