<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hernández Rolls As Mets' Outfield Shrinks Again</title>
    <meta content="01mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/sports/baseball/01mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851348"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">San Francisco Giants</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E4D71530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="934" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hernández Rolls As Mets' Outfield Shrinks Again</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hernández Rolls as Mets’ Outfield Shrinks Again</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every time Paul Lo Duca catches for Orlando Hernández, he settles into his crouch, puts down two fingers -- the sign for a curveball -- and prepares for a surprise. The ball may come in slow, fast or somewhere in the middle, and from any of Hernández's 58 arm angles.</p>
        <p>''Just throw it, and I'll catch it,'' Lo Duca said he tells Hernández.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Orlando Hernández’s curveball kept the Giants at bay, but Carlos Beltrán left the game after the first inning with a bruised right knee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every time Paul Lo Duca catches for Orlando Hernández, he settles into his crouch, puts down two fingers -- the sign for a curveball -- and prepares for a surprise. The ball may come in slow, fast or somewhere in the middle, and from any of Hernández's 58 arm angles.</p>
        <p>''Just throw it, and I'll catch it,'' Lo Duca said he tells Hernández.</p>
        <p>This revelation may offer some comfort to the San Francisco Giants, who also did not seem to know what was coming from Hernández's right arm last night. In the Mets' 4-2 victory at Shea Stadium, Hernández allowed hits to the first two batters, with each scoring to end his 19-inning shutout streak. He then retired 20 of the next 21 batters. Only a leadoff walk to pitcher Matt Cain in the third inning spoiled the streak, and he was promptly erased on a double play.</p>
        <p>''I did nothing different,'' Hernández said. ''I felt good.''</p>
        <p>Joe Smith threw a scoreless eighth, and Billy Wagner finished off Hernández's splendid night by recording his 13th save, striking out the final hitter, Rich Aurilia, with Barry Bonds on deck.</p>
        <p>Bonds went 1 for 6 in the series and was hitless in three at-bats against Hernández in what could have been his final game in New York. If Bonds, as expected, sets the career home run record this season (he has 746 homers, 9 behind the leader, Hank Aaron), he may consider retiring. Judging by the fan reaction throughout the series, he will not be missed.</p>
        <p>''We were able to hold him for three games without doing something to us,'' Wagner said. ''You don't want to tempt fate and be put in that situation.''</p>
        <p>One person who certainly may be missed, however, is Carlos Beltrán, who left the game after the first inning with a bruised right knee. Beltrán sustained the injury after colliding with Aurilia at first base. In his haste to avoid contact, Beltrán slammed into Aurilia's upper body, and the collision knocked him off stride and caused him to land awkwardly on the knee. He will have a magnetic resonance imaging test this morning but said that he did not expect to miss more than a few days.</p>
        <p>''I'm not worried,'' Beltrán said. ''If I'm walking right now, I'm not worried. I just felt weak.''</p>
        <p>If Beltrán winds up being out for an extended period, the Mets, down to only three bona-fide outfielders, will probably have to plumb the depths of Class AAA New Orleans for a replacement. Ricky Ledee, anyone?</p>
        <p>Since last Friday, the Mets lost Shawn Green (broken foot) to the disabled list and Carlos Gómez (hamstring strain) for two games, and that does not even count Moises Alou, who has been sidelined since May 13 with a strained left quadriceps. Maybe the outfielder's glove Lo Duca was playing with before the game was an omen. Pretty soon, Manager Willie Randolph may have to take Lo Duca up on his offer.</p>
        <p>''We'll find someone,'' Randolph said, with a hint of a laugh, of his incredible shrinking outfield. ''We'll be O.K.''</p>
        <p>The Mets' lineup is far less imposing without Beltrán, Green or Alou, and they did not score again after tagging Cain for two runs in each of the first two innings. But Hernández did not need much help, anyway, as he dismantled the Giants' middling lineup, and he even added an offensive contribution, bunting over Damion Easley and Ben Johnson with no outs in the second. Both runners eventually scored.</p>
        <p>Coming off throwing six scoreless innings last Friday in Florida, his first start since being sidelined for a month with shoulder bursitis, Hernández was not on a pitch count. But the Mets are still being cautious with him. After retiring Bengie Molina to end the seventh, on his 95th pitch, Hernández told Randolph that he could not go any longer.</p>
        <p>''I guess he's still feeling like he wants to get back into the type of stamina that he wants to be in,'' Randolph said.</p>
        <p>Hernández said, ''I'm not feeling the same yet as before the injury.''</p>
        <p>That was little consolation to the Giants, who scored in the first inning for the third consecutive game but never threatened again. Randy Winn lined a single and Omar Vizquel followed by pounding a hanging breaking ball into the right-center field gap for a run-scoring triple. Aurilia then hit a sacrifice fly, and the Mets trailed, 2-0.</p>
        <p>The game-time temperature was 75 degrees, but it dropped rapidly, and the cooler weather made it hard for Hernández to get a good grip on the ball early. Like many pitchers, he prefers humidity, when the moisture helps him to keep the ball on his fingers longer.</p>
        <p>''In his last three starts, he's thrown his breaking ball wherever he's wanted,'' Lo Duca said.</p>
        <p>Lo Duca added that Hernández seemed to settle in shortly after facing Bonds, who popped out after Aurilia, but Hernández did not have a theory of his own.</p>
        <p>''Better location, maybe,'' said Hernández, who has allowed three earned runs in his past 27 innings. ''But I don't know.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The Giants traded closer Armando Benítez to the Florida Marlins for reliever Randy Messenger last night. Benítez, 34, was 0-3 with 9 saves in 11 chances and a 4.67 earned run average. His final game for San Francisco was Tuesday night, when he balked twice and gave up a game-ending home run to Carlos Delgado in the 12th inning of a 5-4 loss to the Mets. Benítez had 47 saves for the Marlins in 2004. Messenger, 25, is 1-1 with a 2.66 E.R.A.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
