<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Largest Labor Union in Britain May Consider a Boycott of Israel</title>
    <meta content="01britain" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/world/europe/01britain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070605T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851333"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D71530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="509" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Largest Labor Union in Britain May Consider a Boycott of Israel</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Largest Labor Union in Britain May Consider a Boycott of Israel</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, May 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A movement in Britain to boycott Israel economically and culturally gathered speed on Thursday as the country's biggest labor union said it would follow the union of university instructors in weighing punitive measures against Israel.</p>
        <p>Mary McGuire, a spokeswoman for Unison, a union of public service employees with 1.3 million members, said a resolution calling for a boycott had been placed on the agenda for the group's annual national conference starting June 19. Word of the proposal emerged one day after the University and College Union, representing 120,000 instructors, voted to urge its members to consider their future relationships and exchanges with Israeli academics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A resolution calling for a boycott has been placed on the agenda for the union’s annual national conference next month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A movement in Britain to boycott Israel economically and culturally gathered speed on Thursday as the country's biggest labor union said it would follow the union of university instructors in weighing punitive measures against Israel.</p>
        <p>Mary McGuire, a spokeswoman for Unison, a union of public service employees with 1.3 million members, said a resolution calling for a boycott had been placed on the agenda for the group's annual national conference starting June 19. Word of the proposal emerged one day after the University and College Union, representing 120,000 instructors, voted to urge its members to consider their future relationships and exchanges with Israeli academics.</p>
        <p>The instructors' vote -- which did not impose an immediate boycott -- drew protests from academics in the United States and Israel. In Britain, senior figures at some of the country's top universities, including Cambridge and Oxford, distanced themselves from the resolution, saying that they ''strongly condemned'' it and that they ''reject outright the call for an academic boycott.''</p>
        <p>The chairman of the group, Prof. Malcolm Grant of University College London, said, ''It is a contradiction in terms and in direct conflict with the mission of a university.''</p>
        <p>Politicians from the major political parties also condemned the vote by the instructors' union.</p>
        <p>Asked if the Unison congress would also consider a boycott of some form, Ms. McGuire said, ''There is a motion down on our agenda that is to that effect.'' However, she said, with around 150 motions from the union's 1,500 branches to debate, it was not clear whether the boycott call would be discussed. According to the Unison Web site, www.unison.org.uk, the proposal to be debated at the conference says, ''Unison believes the appropriate response is to support the growing international moves towards a union-based campaign of boycott and sanctions against Israeli institutions, in line with the call from over 170 Palestinian civil society organizations including the Palestine General Federation of Trade Unions and individual unions and labor collectives.''</p>
        <p>In a preamble, the motion ''notes that, during 2006, Israel invaded Lebanon and Gaza, withheld tax revenues form the Palestine Authority and refused dialogue with the elected Authority following the democratic elections of January 2006, resealed the borders of Gaza, expanded illegal settlements in the West Bank, and continued the construction of the illegal Apartheid Wall.''</p>
        <p>It accused the government of Prime Minister Tony Blair of adopting ''a consistent stand in support of the Israeli government throughout the shameful events of 2006, even joining the U.S. in failing to call for a cease-fire amidst worldwide condemnation of the Israeli invasion of Lebanon.''</p>
        <p>The motion suggested that the union discuss the kinds of economic ties its members have with Israel and Israeli companies, and highlight the scope of a potential consumer boycott. The Israeli newspaper Haaretz said Thursday that officials from Histadrut, the largest union in Israel, had seen a copy of the Unison motion.</p>
        <p>Histadrut was reported to have urged the British union to withdraw the motion. But Ms. McGuire said the union leadership had no authority do so before the national conference.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 5, 2007, Tuesday  A headline on Friday about a growing movement in Britain to boycott Israel economically and culturally referred incorrectly in some copies to a decision reached by the union of public service employees, the largest British labor union. The union said a resolution that would call for a boycott of Israel would be considered at its upcoming annual meeting. The union did not call for such a boycott.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 5, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A headline on Friday about a growing movement in Britain to boycott Israel economically and culturally referred incorrectly in some copies to a decision reached by the union of public service employees, the largest British labor union. The union said a resolution that would call for a boycott of Israel would be considered at its upcoming annual meeting. The union did not call for such a boycott.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
