<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge Criticizes Police Dept. For Illegal Loitering Arrests</title>
    <meta content="01beg" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/nyregion/01beg.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851320"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beggars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beggars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402EFD81530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge Criticizes Police Dept. For Illegal Loitering Arrests</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Judge Criticizes Police Dept. for Illegal Loitering Arrests</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARA BUCKLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal judge sharply criticized the New York Police Department yesterday for failing to follow repeated court orders by arresting hundreds of panhandlers and beggars, but still denied a request to hold the city in contempt of court.</p>
        <p>The judge, Shira A. Scheindlin of United States District Court in Manhattan, admonished the department for continuing to enforce a law that was declared unconstitutional in 1992 -- resulting in a court order to halt enforcement -- and for ignoring a second order to stop enforcing the law in June 2005.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The judge admonished the department for enforcing a law that was declared unconstitutional in 1992 but still denied a request to hold the city in contempt of court.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal judge sharply criticized the New York Police Department yesterday for failing to follow repeated court orders by arresting hundreds of panhandlers and beggars, but still denied a request to hold the city in contempt of court.</p>
        <p>The judge, Shira A. Scheindlin of United States District Court in Manhattan, admonished the department for continuing to enforce a law that was declared unconstitutional in 1992 -- resulting in a court order to halt enforcement -- and for ignoring a second order to stop enforcing the law in June 2005.</p>
        <p>Still, Judge Scheindlin said the department had recently taken several steps to correct its behavior. The measures included mailing 40,000 reminders out with officers' pay stubs, sending warning letters to offending officers and providing additional training stressing that the statute was unlawful, she said.</p>
        <p>It was only after the plaintiffs -- half a dozen people who were unlawfully arrested or charged for panhandling or loitering -- asked in December that the department be held in contempt that the Police Department ''turned their behavior around,'' Judge Scheindlin wrote.</p>
        <p>(An original plaintiff in the case, a longtime panhandler named Eddie Wise, accepted a $100,000 settlement from the city last year, after repeated illegal arrests.)</p>
        <p>Before December, the judge wrote, the department had effectively been in contempt: It went through the motions of correcting the pattern of unlawful arrests but had a ''flippant attitude'' about its continuing violation of the 2005 order.</p>
        <p>''Until December 2006, defendants' failure to comply was unreasonable and harmful,'' she wrote. ''Defendants' longstanding apathy towards this problem was offensive.''</p>
        <p>Judge Scheindlin also said the court would start monitoring the department's efforts, and their effectiveness, every two months.</p>
        <p>Matthew D. Brinckerhoff, the plaintiffs' lawyer, said the department willfully ignored the 2005 order because it protected people often regarded as public nuisances. ''It's one of those purposeful neglect situations,'' he said. He also said the department started making significant changes only in March, when it mailed out reminders with paychecks and began warning offending officers.</p>
        <p>''I think they have taken reasonable steps over the last two months but did nothing for 15 years,'' Mr. Brinckerhoff said.</p>
        <p>There is also a class-action suit in the works, Mr. Brinckerhoff said, on behalf of thousands of others unlawfully arrested statewide.</p>
        <p>The chief department spokesman, Paul J. Browne, faulted the State Legislature for failing to remove the statute from the state's penal code. He also said the department had gone to ''extraordinary lengths'' to make sure its officers' mistakes were not repeated.</p>
        <p>The statute in question banned loitering ''for the purpose of begging,'' and a federal judge ruled in 1992 that it was unconstitutional to enforce it in New York City. In 1993, that ruling was upheld on appeal.</p>
        <p>Yet 12 years later, another federal judge found that the Police Department was nonetheless arresting or issuing summonses to hundreds of people citywide, and that the district attorney's office was still prosecuting many of the cases. The judge ordered law enforcement authorities to stop enforcing the statute once and for all.</p>
        <p>But, Judge Scheindlin noted yesterday, ''enforcement continues to this day.''</p>
        <p>According to statistics that the Police Department has not disputed, officers issued 772 summonses and made 51 arrests under the statute from June 2005, when the judge's order was issued, to January of this year. Many of the summonses were issued in the 75th Precinct, which includes East New York in Brooklyn. Four summonses were issued in Queens and Staten Island as recently as Feb. 21.</p>
        <p>The judge noted that the statistics gave an incomplete picture of the psychological toll of the arrests.</p>
        <p>In December 2005, a new Police Department computer program eliminated the unlawful statute from a drop-down menu that officers use to select the appropriate charges for people who are arrested. As a result, it is impossible to know how many people are unlawfully arrested under the statute, brought to a station house and released, the judge said. According to the original complaint, some people hid in their homes, afraid that they would be picked up on outstanding bench warrants based on the original unlawful arrest.</p>
        <p>Still, Judge Scheindlin said she was satisfied that the Police Department was finally responding to the court orders. ''Granted,'' she wrote, throwing in a few wry italics, ''this came approximately 17 months late.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
