<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TODAY IN BUSINESS</title>
    <meta content="01biztoday" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E3D81530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="889" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TODAY IN BUSINESS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TALKS OVER SELLING DOW JONES -- The Bancroft family, which controls Dow Jones &amp; Company, the publisher of The Wall Street Journal, agreed to meet with Rupert Murdoch just weeks after the family rejected an initial $5 billion takeover offer from Mr. Murdoch's News Corporation. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>LERACH MAY LEAVE LAW FIRM -- William S. Lerach, one of the most powerful securities class-action lawyers in the nation, is considering plans to leave the law firm he founded three years ago. His possible departure suggests that a long-running criminal investigation into accusations of kickbacks paid to class-action plaintiffs has gained momentum. [C1.]</p>
        <p>SEEING OPPORTUNITY IN DEFAULTS  -- The subprime mortgage business is in tatters, but that hasn't stopped some private equity companies, hedge funds and investment banks from swooping in and taking over those battered businesses, seeing opportunity amid the wreckage. [C1.]</p>
        <p>WIND POWER'S TAX BREAKS -- The nation's investment in wind energy continues to grow. But there is uncertainty over whether lawmakers in Congress will extend the tax benefits that encourage companies to invest in wind power. [C1.]</p>
        <p>PICTURES, FOLLOWED BY WORDS -- A new online feature of Google Maps that offers panoramic ground-level photographs of miles of streets around San Francisco, New York, Las Vegas, Miami and Denver is stirring up a debate over privacy concerns on the Web. [C1.]</p>
        <p>PUBLISHERS SEEKING BLOCKBUSTER -- In the absence of a new Harry Potter book or a blockbuster by Dan Brown, the publishing industry struggled to sell more copies last year than it did the year before, according to a report to be released today by the Book Industry Study Group, a publishing trade association. [C3.]</p>
        <p>QUESTIONS OVER MAN WITH TB -- The man with a dangerous form of tuberculosis who flew to Europe for his wedding and honeymoon was identified as Andrew Speaker, 31, a lawyer in Atlanta, who homeland security officials said entered the country when a customs agent who knew Mr. Speaker was being sought by health authorities let him pass. Congress plans to hold hearings on the way the case has been handled. [A1.]</p>
        <p>DELL TO LAY OFF 10% OF WORKERS -- Dell said that it would lay off 10 percent of its 88,100 employees over the next 12 months as it tries to increase profit. [C3.]</p>
        <p>WACHOVIA BUYS A. G. EDWARDS -- The Wachovia Corporation swallowed up A. G. Edwards in a $6.8 billion cash and stock deal that highlights the continued consolidation of the retail brokerage sector. [C5.]</p>
        <p>FINES PAID IN BACKDATING CASES -- Two technology companies, Brocade Communications Systems and Mercury Interactive, became the first two companies to pay fines to settle federal accusations of civil fraud in connection with backdated stock options. Brocade has agreed to pay $7 million and Mercury is paying $28 million. [C8.]</p>
        <p>WELLPOINT OUSTS FINANCIAL CHIEF -- WellPoint, the biggest American health insurer, ousted its chief financial officer after an external investigation revealed he violated its code of conduct. The board named its chief accounting officer, Wayne S. DeVeydt, to replace the finance chief, David C. Colby, effective immediately. [C6.]</p>
        <p>GREEN ISSUES AND AUTOMAKERS -- Labor and management in the auto industry are often at odds, but they have agreed on something critics have been telling them for years: Detroit must act to reduce its vehicles' impact on the environment. [C3.]</p>
        <p>N.J. COURT RULES ON WAL-MART SUIT -- In a setback for Wal-Mart, the New Jersey Supreme Court ruled that a lawsuit claiming that the company refused to allow workers to take rest breaks and meal breaks could proceed as a class action on behalf of nearly 80,000 current and former Wal-Mart employees. [C7.]</p>
        <p>CONGRESS TAKING UP TAX SHELTERS -- Congress is taking another close look at reining in questionable tax shelters that have deprived the government of hundreds of billions of dollars in taxes in recent years. [C5.]</p>
        <p>ECONOMIC GROWTH RATE IS CUT -- The Commerce Department revised the broadest indicator of economic strength, measuring all goods and services produced in the United States, to show a 0.6 percent advance over the first three months of the year. [C3.]</p>
        <p>'MISCONDUCT' BY 2 CHINESE FIRMS -- Chinese regulators acknowledged that two Chinese companies had ''engaged in some misconduct'' in the way they labeled and sold a poisonous ingredient that ended up in cold medicine, killing at least 100 people in Panama last year. But the regulators said primary responsibility for the deaths rested with traders in Spain and Panama. [A6.]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>RETIREMENT -- As life spans lengthen, experts on aging say it is more important than ever to prepare for the physical and psychological aspects of retirement. A special section is at nytimes.com/retirement.</p>
        <p>BUSINESS OF GREEN -- Consumer products are beginning to carry details about their environmental impact, and restaurant owners are finding ways to handle garbage with less affect on the environment. Those articles and more are in a special section at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>Business Briefing  Articles on these developments are available at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>The Justice Department approved Monsanto's $1.5 billion acquisition of the cotton company Delta and Pine Land, but required both companies to sell assets related to cottonseed production. (AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TALKS OVER SELLING DOW JONES -- The Bancroft family, which controls Dow Jones &amp; Company, the publisher of The Wall Street Journal, agreed to meet with Rupert Murdoch just weeks after the family rejected an initial $5 billion takeover offer from Mr. Murdoch's News Corporation. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>LERACH MAY LEAVE LAW FIRM -- William S. Lerach, one of the most powerful securities class-action lawyers in the nation, is considering plans to leave the law firm he founded three years ago. His possible departure suggests that a long-running criminal investigation into accusations of kickbacks paid to class-action plaintiffs has gained momentum. [C1.]</p>
        <p>SEEING OPPORTUNITY IN DEFAULTS  -- The subprime mortgage business is in tatters, but that hasn't stopped some private equity companies, hedge funds and investment banks from swooping in and taking over those battered businesses, seeing opportunity amid the wreckage. [C1.]</p>
        <p>WIND POWER'S TAX BREAKS -- The nation's investment in wind energy continues to grow. But there is uncertainty over whether lawmakers in Congress will extend the tax benefits that encourage companies to invest in wind power. [C1.]</p>
        <p>PICTURES, FOLLOWED BY WORDS -- A new online feature of Google Maps that offers panoramic ground-level photographs of miles of streets around San Francisco, New York, Las Vegas, Miami and Denver is stirring up a debate over privacy concerns on the Web. [C1.]</p>
        <p>PUBLISHERS SEEKING BLOCKBUSTER -- In the absence of a new Harry Potter book or a blockbuster by Dan Brown, the publishing industry struggled to sell more copies last year than it did the year before, according to a report to be released today by the Book Industry Study Group, a publishing trade association. [C3.]</p>
        <p>QUESTIONS OVER MAN WITH TB -- The man with a dangerous form of tuberculosis who flew to Europe for his wedding and honeymoon was identified as Andrew Speaker, 31, a lawyer in Atlanta, who homeland security officials said entered the country when a customs agent who knew Mr. Speaker was being sought by health authorities let him pass. Congress plans to hold hearings on the way the case has been handled. [A1.]</p>
        <p>DELL TO LAY OFF 10% OF WORKERS -- Dell said that it would lay off 10 percent of its 88,100 employees over the next 12 months as it tries to increase profit. [C3.]</p>
        <p>WACHOVIA BUYS A. G. EDWARDS -- The Wachovia Corporation swallowed up A. G. Edwards in a $6.8 billion cash and stock deal that highlights the continued consolidation of the retail brokerage sector. [C5.]</p>
        <p>FINES PAID IN BACKDATING CASES -- Two technology companies, Brocade Communications Systems and Mercury Interactive, became the first two companies to pay fines to settle federal accusations of civil fraud in connection with backdated stock options. Brocade has agreed to pay $7 million and Mercury is paying $28 million. [C8.]</p>
        <p>WELLPOINT OUSTS FINANCIAL CHIEF -- WellPoint, the biggest American health insurer, ousted its chief financial officer after an external investigation revealed he violated its code of conduct. The board named its chief accounting officer, Wayne S. DeVeydt, to replace the finance chief, David C. Colby, effective immediately. [C6.]</p>
        <p>GREEN ISSUES AND AUTOMAKERS -- Labor and management in the auto industry are often at odds, but they have agreed on something critics have been telling them for years: Detroit must act to reduce its vehicles' impact on the environment. [C3.]</p>
        <p>N.J. COURT RULES ON WAL-MART SUIT -- In a setback for Wal-Mart, the New Jersey Supreme Court ruled that a lawsuit claiming that the company refused to allow workers to take rest breaks and meal breaks could proceed as a class action on behalf of nearly 80,000 current and former Wal-Mart employees. [C7.]</p>
        <p>CONGRESS TAKING UP TAX SHELTERS -- Congress is taking another close look at reining in questionable tax shelters that have deprived the government of hundreds of billions of dollars in taxes in recent years. [C5.]</p>
        <p>ECONOMIC GROWTH RATE IS CUT -- The Commerce Department revised the broadest indicator of economic strength, measuring all goods and services produced in the United States, to show a 0.6 percent advance over the first three months of the year. [C3.]</p>
        <p>'MISCONDUCT' BY 2 CHINESE FIRMS -- Chinese regulators acknowledged that two Chinese companies had ''engaged in some misconduct'' in the way they labeled and sold a poisonous ingredient that ended up in cold medicine, killing at least 100 people in Panama last year. But the regulators said primary responsibility for the deaths rested with traders in Spain and Panama. [A6.]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>RETIREMENT -- As life spans lengthen, experts on aging say it is more important than ever to prepare for the physical and psychological aspects of retirement. A special section is at nytimes.com/retirement.</p>
        <p>BUSINESS OF GREEN -- Consumer products are beginning to carry details about their environmental impact, and restaurant owners are finding ways to handle garbage with less affect on the environment. Those articles and more are in a special section at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>Business Briefing  Articles on these developments are available at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>The Justice Department approved Monsanto's $1.5 billion acquisition of the cotton company Delta and Pine Land, but required both companies to sell assets related to cottonseed production. (AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
