<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INSIDE ART</title>
    <meta content="01voge" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/arts/design/01voge.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851202"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Inside Art"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Sotheby's Holdings Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Getty, J Paul, Museum</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Los Angeles County Museum of Art</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E0DD1530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INSIDE ART</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Auction Houses Banking on Buoyant London Market</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Auction Houses Banking On Buoyant London Market</p>
        <p>After the record prices at last month's auctions in New York, Sotheby's and Christie's are bracing for an encore in London this month. But what will distinguish these sales, starting on June 18, from any that have taken place there in a generation is the increase of artwork from the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>London auctions this month will include a fair amount of American merchandise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Auction Houses Banking On Buoyant London Market</p>
        <p>After the record prices at last month's auctions in New York, Sotheby's and Christie's are bracing for an encore in London this month. But what will distinguish these sales, starting on June 18, from any that have taken place there in a generation is the increase of artwork from the United States.</p>
        <p>''It used to be the other way around,'' said Marc Porter, president of Christie's. ''But this summer half what we are selling in our postwar and contemporary art auction is from the United States, and a third of the consignments for our Impressionist and modern art sale are from America too.''</p>
        <p>Sellers continue to want to cash in on a buoyant market, and the weak dollar makes selling in Europe advantageous. ''London used to be a main export center, but not anymore,'' said Cheyenne Westphal, chairwoman of contemporary art for Sotheby's in Europe, who is based in London. ''American clients love to get a lot of dollars for the pound. There's also a new community of international collectors who have London as their base, and they feel comfortable buying here.''</p>
        <p>In addition to collectors working in the London financial markets, scores of Russians and Asians with homes there have become big buyers.</p>
        <p>Brett Gorvy, a co-head of postwar and contemporary art for Christie's worldwide, said that the auction house was sending three collections from the United States to its London sale, and that half of that auction's estimated value has come from America.</p>
        <p>Hoping that scores of disappointed bidders will try their luck again, both Sotheby's and Christie's have packed their sales with works by artists who performed well last month. Among the top works in each sale are works by Damien Hirst, Francis Bacon, Lucian Freud and Mark Rothko.</p>
        <p>As in May, the auction houses gave sellers guarantees: undisclosed minimum sums promised regardless of the outcome of the sales. But executives do not seem nervous about their financial investments. Although both auction houses generally considered London a stepsister to the more glamorous New York, Mr. Gorvy said that was no longer true. ''We see London as being equal to New York,'' he said. ''There's no real difference in perception.''</p>
        <p>Getty Buys 'Bestiary'</p>
        <p>The J. Paul Getty Museum in Los Angeles has bought the ''Northumberland Bestiary,'' a 13th-century English Gothic illuminated manuscript.</p>
        <p>''If you're going to tell the story of medieval manuscripts, this is the key work,'' said Thomas Kren, curator of the manuscript department at the Getty. ''It is the greatest English manuscript still in private hands.''</p>
        <p>Considered an outstanding example of medieval art, the encyclopedia of animals, both real and imaginary, is richly illustrated in 112 colored ink drawings that includes a full-page miniature depicting Adam naming the beasts, from hawks and monkeys to griffins and dragons.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Kren declined to say who sold it to the Getty or what the institution paid, Sotheby's had auctioned the manuscript in London in 1990. The seller then was the 11th Duke of Northumberland, whose family had owned it since the 18th century.</p>
        <p>Nicholas Poole-Wilson of Bernard Quaritch, a London gallery, bought the manuscript at Sotheby's for $5.8 million. At the time Mr. Poole-Wilson would not say for whom he was bidding, but manuscript experts said they believed his client was Ladislas von Hoffman, a Washington collector. Experts say the Getty must have paid around $20 million.</p>
        <p>The manuscript will go on view at the Getty today (through July 29) as part of ''Medieval Beasts,'' an exhibition of animal images.</p>
        <p>Another Broad Museum</p>
        <p>Four years ago Eli Broad, the Los Angeles collector, philanthropist and chairman of SunAmerica, the financial company he founded, gave $50 million to the Los Angeles County Museum of Art to build a contemporary-art center, opening next year. It is to be called the Broad Contemporary Art Museum.</p>
        <p>It won't be the only museum bearing the Broad name. This week Michigan State University, from which Mr. Broad graduated in 1954, announced that he and his wife, Edythe, had given the university $26 million for a new art museum. To be called the Eli and Edythe Broad Art Museum, it will house the university's current collection, which ranges from antiquities to contemporary art.</p>
        <p>''I hope besides a museum they get a great piece of architecture too,'' Mr. Broad said.</p>
        <p>The university is in the process of choosing an architect. The finalists include Coop Himmelblau from Vienna, Thom Mayne from Los Angeles, Zaha Hadid from London, Randall Stout from Los Angeles and William Pedersen from New York.</p>
        <p>New Fitzwilliam Director</p>
        <p>Exactly a week after Timothy Potts resigned as director of the Kimbell Art Museum in Fort Worth, he was appointed director of the Fitzwilliam Museum in Cambridge, England. In January Mr. Potts replaces Duncan Robinson, who is retiring.</p>
        <p>The Fitzwilliam boasts world-famous collections of paintings, drawings, antiquities, decorative objects and metals. ''They call the Fitzwilliam the finest small museum in Europe, which is not so different from the Kimbell,'' Mr. Potts said.</p>
        <p>Inside Art</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
