<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Street Sense Will Pass Up the Belmont</title>
    <meta content="01racing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/sports/othersports/01racing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851299"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Street Sense (Race Horse)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Nafzger, Carl</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6D81530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="557" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Street Sense Will Pass Up the Belmont</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Street Sense Will Pass Up the Belmont</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Street Sense, the Kentucky Derby winner, is skipping the 139th running of the Belmont Stakes, leaving Curlin, the Preakness champion, the likely favorite in what now is a compact field of five for the third leg of the Triple Crown.</p>
        <p>Street Sense's owner, Jim Tafel, and the trainer Carl Nafzger said they agonized for two hours Wednesday night over whether to seek a rematch with Curlin at Belmont on June 9 or to wait for the Travers Stakes in August at Saratoga Race Course.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Kentucky Derby winner will skip the Belmont Stakes and a rematch with Curlin, the colt who ran him down in the Preakness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Street Sense, the Kentucky Derby winner, is skipping the 139th running of the Belmont Stakes, leaving Curlin, the Preakness champion, the likely favorite in what now is a compact field of five for the third leg of the Triple Crown.</p>
        <p>Street Sense's owner, Jim Tafel, and the trainer Carl Nafzger said they agonized for two hours Wednesday night over whether to seek a rematch with Curlin at Belmont on June 9 or to wait for the Travers Stakes in August at Saratoga Race Course.</p>
        <p>''The competitive side said go; the logical side said no, no, no,'' Nafzger said yesterday at a news conference at Churchill Downs. ''We went over a lot of situations last night. The decision was made. There were a lot of reasons to run and a lot of reasons not to run. Mr. Tafel wanted the Triple Crown like you can't believe.''</p>
        <p>But when Curlin ran down Street Sense in the stretch at Pimlico Race Course on May 19 to win the Preakness by a head, their dreams of becoming the 12th Triple Crown champion, and the first since Affirmed in 1978, were crushed.</p>
        <p>So Tafel and Nafzger will forgo a rematch in a grueling mile-and-a-half race in June in favor of a potential championship campaign in the late summer and fall. Street Sense, after all, was awarded the Eclipse Award as the best 2-year-old after winning the Breeders' Cup Juvenile last fall at Churchill Downs.</p>
        <p>''We want the Travers and we want the Breeders' Cup Classic,'' said Nafzger, referring to the $5 million race that is the marquee event of thoroughbred racing's season-ending championships. The Classic will be run in October at Monmouth Park.</p>
        <p>''We could be the first horse to win the Juvenile, the Derby, the Travers, and the Classic,'' Nafzger said. ''Mr. Tafel said these are worthy goals, let's go after it. Let's don't chase spilled water. We spilled the water in the Preakness.''</p>
        <p>The defection of Street Sense means that the Belmont may attract its smallest field since 1978, when only three horses took on Affirmed and his rival Alydar. The most dangerous challenger to Curlin is Hard Spun, who finished second in the Derby and third in the Preakness.</p>
        <p>Still, Curlin's trainer, Steve Asmussen, was not predicting an easy victory. Curlin has dazzled racing enthusiasts by winning four of five races, his only blemish a third-place finish in the Derby.</p>
        <p>''That's Mr. Nafzger's decision and I'm sure he's doing what was right by the horse,'' Asmussen said. ''My position is be careful what you wish for. Right now is the first I heard that he wasn't coming. I was fully prepared to run against him and Hard Spun.''</p>
        <p>Instead, at this point Curlin will meet Hard Spun; Imawildandcrazyguy, the Derby's fourth-place finisher; Tiago, its seventh-place finisher; and Slew's Tizzy, who has won the Lexington Stakes and Lone Star Derby in his last two starts.</p>
        <p>Nafzger conceded that economics played a part in the decision not to run Street Sense in the Belmont. As the 2-year-old champion and Derby winner, the colt is already worth $30 million as a stallion prospect.</p>
        <p>''As a sportsman, you want to come back and challenge Curlin now,'' Nafzger said. ''I can't believe we got beat, but we got beat. We got outrun. That's behind us. The decision now is to regroup.''</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
