<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the 21st Century, the Persistence of Tradition</title>
    <meta content="01annu" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/01/arts/design/01annu.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070630T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1851203"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sculpture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sculpture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Academy of Design</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFDD1530F932A35755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="954" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the 21st Century, the Persistence of Tradition</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In the 21st Century, the Persistence of Tradition</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARTHA SCHWENDENER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You could say that contemporary art became academic art in the 1960s, when experimental and subversive artists started teaching in art schools. Most of the art now in galleries, biennials and fairs is produced by artists coming out of this educational system. But there is ''academic'' in this sense, and then there are academicians, professional artists elected by their peers to be members of the National Academy.</p>
        <p>Founded in 1825 as the National Academy of Design and modeled on the Royal Academy of Arts in London, this organization was considered somewhat progressive in the 19th century because its annual exhibitions showcased living American artists (rather than dead Europeans). But as Annette Blaugrund, director of the National Academy Museum and School of Fine Arts (as it is now known), points out in the catalog for its 182nd annual show, the 20th-century academicians were unwilling to accept avant-garde artists into their ranks. This led to ''gaps'' in the museum's collection, which is made up of works donated by each new member.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Traditional mediums reign at the National Academy of Design: the annual isn’t just heavy on painting, sculpture and architecture; it also consists almost exclusively of these categories.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You could say that contemporary art became academic art in the 1960s, when experimental and subversive artists started teaching in art schools. Most of the art now in galleries, biennials and fairs is produced by artists coming out of this educational system. But there is ''academic'' in this sense, and then there are academicians, professional artists elected by their peers to be members of the National Academy.</p>
        <p>Founded in 1825 as the National Academy of Design and modeled on the Royal Academy of Arts in London, this organization was considered somewhat progressive in the 19th century because its annual exhibitions showcased living American artists (rather than dead Europeans). But as Annette Blaugrund, director of the National Academy Museum and School of Fine Arts (as it is now known), points out in the catalog for its 182nd annual show, the 20th-century academicians were unwilling to accept avant-garde artists into their ranks. This led to ''gaps'' in the museum's collection, which is made up of works donated by each new member.</p>
        <p>Such gaps extend to the academy's current makeup and are most evident in the members-only exhibitions that are held every other year, alternating with invitational shows.</p>
        <p>A quick glance at the ''182nd Annual'' will tell you which year this is. If there is such a thing as academic art in the 21st century, here's where you'll find it. Traditional mediums reign. The annual isn't just heavy on painting, sculpture and architecture; it also consists almost exclusively of these categories.</p>
        <p>Scores of competent figurative paintings and Expressionist- or Impressionist-inspired still lifes and landscapes hang on the walls. William Bailey delivers a characteristically stark tableau of vessels lined up on a table. Philip Pearlstein's ''Model With Two Cement Flamingos'' features a dour nude, her head truncated by the top of the picture plane. Tradition gets a bit of a jolt -- although a gentle one -- with photorealist works by Robert Cottingham and Richard Estes.</p>
        <p>Fifty years later, the once-reviled Abstract Expressionism has been absorbed thoroughly into the academy. It makes a strong showing here, downsized from its heroic mural scale to comfortable easel-size works by James Bohary, William Clutz, Robert Goodnough, Paul Jenkins, Harry Kramer and Ben Frank Moss.</p>
        <p>Geometric abstraction, popular in recent years with younger artists, who combine it with everything from architecture to digital circuitry, turns up too: Vincent Longo's tight pink and orange composition, ''Lattice: Plane Site''; Richard Sloat's ''Hester Street Hip Hop,'' which updates Mondrian's ''Broadway Boogie Woogie''; an untitled painting by Diana Horowitz that looks like a Rothko redux; and Paul Russotto's ''Rubberneck,'' a gestural painting overlaid with a web of geometric forms.</p>
        <p>Will Barnet's elegant geometric composition ''Enclosure/Enveloping Forms,'' with a light purple spiral against a dark ground, is a particularly good example. Mr. Barnet, who was born in 1911, describes himself in a gallery handout as ''possibly the last living artist to be trained in the classic French Academy tradition,'' although he points out that part of his development as an artist came from rebelling against this background.</p>
        <p>The show is weighted toward painting. Sculpture is represented mostly by kitschy figuration or classic modern abstraction. Melvin Edwards is an exception, although his mangled, welded-steel composition, ''East Texas Algebra,'' suffers from being wedged into a corner in a nook between two galleries.</p>
        <p>Although there is little here that will surprise you, some works gain interest when read against the grain. Paintings like Thomas Cornell's demented pastoral filled with smiling figures, ''The Birth of Nature and Dance of Love''; Frank Mason's antiquated religious painting, ''Gloria in Excelsis Deo''; and Don Perlis's creepy ''Polyphemus, the Escape of Odysseus'' would register as quirky-cool if moved to a different context (say, further downtown). Here they're merely among the stranger works.</p>
        <p>There is just one photographic work: Frances Myers's intermittently graphic and heavy-handed series of digital prints on canvas, taken from a video depicting a ''Dead Deer.''</p>
        <p>Walking through this show, you may notice the breach between this vision of contemporary American art and others -- the Whitney Biennial is the oft-cited example -- but there is also a gap between participants and abstainers. Of the roughly 350 members of the academy, 194 took part this year.</p>
        <p>You sense that the annual show may not rank very high on the ''To Do'' lists of abstaining academicians like Elizabeth Murray, Nancy Spero, Frank Stella, Claes Oldenburg, Helen Frankenthaler, Eric Fischl, Bill Jensen, Jasper Johns, Frank Gehry, Lee Bontecou or Chuck Close. (In the early years, if members failed to contribute work for two years, they were demoted to associate status.)</p>
        <p>The academy, with its school as well as its museum, in recent years has tried to reposition itself by mounting several shows to emphasize its relevance. ''Surrealism USA'' in 2005 used works from the collection to demonstrate American contributions to Surrealism. ''The Photorealist Project'' in 2004 looked back at a 1970s American movement that hasn't fared as well as others from that period, despite the obsession with the relationship between painting and photography.</p>
        <p>This year's ''High Times, Hard Times: New York Painting 1967-1975,'' organized by a guest curator, Katy Siegel, with the painter David Reed, offered a new look at a decade when painting flourished on the margins, in the shadow of new mediums like performance art and photography.</p>
        <p>Some of this spirit has made its way into the ''182nd Annual.'' Space constraints were the reason that in 2000 the work of academicians was separated from that of nonmembers. Mixing these groups once again would perhaps fill all the gaps -- of the last century and this one as well.</p>
        <p>''182nd Annual: An Exhibition of Contemporary American Art'' continues through July 24 at the National Academy Museum, 1083 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street; (212) 369-4880.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 30, 2007, Saturday  An art review in Weekend on June 1 about ''182nd Annual: An Exhibition of Contemporary American Art,'' at the National Academy Museum on Fifth Avenue at 89th Street, referred incompletely to a show at the museum earlier this year, which was cited as an example of shows the academy has been mounting to emphasize its relevance. Although the show, ''High Times, Hard Times: New York Painting 1967-1975,'' was exhibited at the academy, it was a traveling exhibition organized by Independent Curators International.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 30, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>An art review in Weekend on June 1 about ''182nd Annual: An Exhibition of Contemporary American Art,'' at the National Academy Museum on Fifth Avenue at 89th Street, referred incompletely to a show at the museum earlier this year, which was cited as an example of shows the academy has been mounting to emphasize its relevance. Although the show, ''High Times, Hard Times: New York Painting 1967-1975,'' was exhibited at the academy, it was a traveling exhibition organized by Independent Curators International.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
