<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What if You Met the Enemy and It Really Was You, and Then It Happened Again</title>
    <meta content="14game" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/technology/14game.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GAME THEORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Irem (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Agetec (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Crystal Dynamics</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Eidos Plc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Zoe Mode</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sega Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herold, Charles</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Raw Danger (Video Game)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Lara Croft Tomb Raider: Anniversary (Video Game)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Crush (Video Game)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Game Theory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E7DA143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1091" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What if You Met the Enemy and It Really Was You, and Then It Happened Again</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What if You Met the Enemy and It Really Was You, and Then It Happened Again</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES HEROLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herold, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Herold reviews video games Raw Danger, developed by Irem and published by Agetec, Lara Croft Tomb Raider: Anniversary, developed by Crystal Dynamics and published by Eidos and Crush, developed by Zoe Mode and published by Sega; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It isn't often you walk around a corner and run into yourself, but it happens occasionally in Raw Danger, a survival game in which the player lives through the aftermath of a tsunami as several characters.</p>
        <p>In this game, each character's actions affect the journey of at least one other character. If a man asks for your help and you refuse, you may find yourself later playing that man and having to solve a problem on your own. Choose a path that causes something to collapse and another character will have one avenue of escape cut off. Raw Danger illustrates that every decision can have consequences for others.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Raw Danger is a survival game in which a player lives through the aftermath of a tsunami as several characters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It isn't often you walk around a corner and run into yourself, but it happens occasionally in Raw Danger, a survival game in which the player lives through the aftermath of a tsunami as several characters.</p>
        <p>In this game, each character's actions affect the journey of at least one other character. If a man asks for your help and you refuse, you may find yourself later playing that man and having to solve a problem on your own. Choose a path that causes something to collapse and another character will have one avenue of escape cut off. Raw Danger illustrates that every decision can have consequences for others.</p>
        <p>Raw Danger begins when the levees of a new city collapse. Raw Danger, a sequel to the 2003 earthquake-themed Disaster Report and developed by Irem, works hard to repurpose the original game's components. In the earthquake game, players had to deal with heat and dehydration, locating water and scavenging clothes to ward off the sun. During Raw Danger's flood, players must scavenge clothes to stay warm and find heat sources to dry out. Both games even have forgettable, generic titles seemingly designed to deter anyone from noticing them.</p>
        <p>Raw Danger is difficult to categorize. You explore your environment and use found objects to bypass obstacles as in an adventure game; you find and use clothing with various degrees of protection as in a role-playing game; and you also climb and hop as in an old-fashioned platform-jumping game. At times the game also adds brief action elements.</p>
        <p>The first story relates a waiter's efforts to escape a city as he deals with torrential rains, flooded streets and collapsing floors. Eventually the waiter escapes the city, but that is only the beginning. The player goes on to experience the flood as a cabby, a bitter high school student and an escaped convict.</p>
        <p>Characters can be affected in small ways. During conversations you are sometimes offered a choice of sentences. When playing the student you can call a man a pervert. If you do, in the next section when you play as that man, who turns out to have amnesia, he will respond by thinking, ''Is that what I am, a pervert?''</p>
        <p>This is pretty cool, and there's a certain thrill in living through a moment you witnessed earlier as someone else. But the structure is problematic if you want to experience all the game's subplots and variations. The second time I played the game I found about 80 percent was the same, even with all the variations. Once you know where to go and what to do, the game is not nearly as enthralling.</p>
        <p>Raw Danger is full of brilliant ideas and original gameplay, but it is constantly bumping up against the limits of its small budget. One wishes the designers had created an open city along the lines of Grand Theft Auto III and made character interactions more varied, frequent and unpredictable, but that would be a far more expensive game to make.</p>
        <p>The developers, alas, could not even afford polished graphics. While the game is somewhat impressive when a tidal wave topples a building, the visuals are generally lackluster and characters are stiff and lifeless.</p>
        <p>These are mainly cosmetic issues that don't substantially affect the gameplay, but they will put off a lot of players used to slicker games. That's a shame, because Raw Danger offers a fascinating experience.</p>
        <p>Once upon a time, all games were ugly and awkward, but people still loved them; in 1996, gamers considered Lara Croft of Tomb Raider a sex symbol even though she looked like a crash test dummy with a painted-on face. Now, Crystal Dynamics has remade Tomb Raider as Tomb Raider: Anniversary, a game that combines the original's smart design and clever puzzles with the slick game engine used for last year's Tomb Raider: Legend.</p>
        <p>Anniversary shows how far games have come in a decade. While the original was entertaining, the controls made even simple tasks like picking up an object a chore. When the original Lara had to jump over a chasm or dodge a booby trap, she was killed more often by the clumsiness of the controls than the incompetence of the player. In Anniversary, Lara handles well when you need to leap to a ledge, pull a switch or dodge a dinosaur. If she breaks her neck, it is usually your fault.</p>
        <p>The visuals are grander and Lara has some new tricks up her sleeve, but no effort has been made to flesh out the negligible story. Someone tells Lara to go to Peru. She explores some underground caverns, runs into someone a few hours later for another insignificant conversation and then explores some more. The game represents 1996 action-game design theory: if the storyline sags, you can put a dinosaur in just because, well, dinosaurs are cool.</p>
        <p>Great gameplay can compensate for halfhearted storytelling. This is good news for Crush, a puzzle game from Zoë Mode, since the minimal story is as forgettable as its puzzles are ingenious.</p>
        <p>Crush is about a psychiatric patient hooked up to a machine that allows him to explore his own mind. The premise seems arbitrary. The game's glittering lights and abstract towers could as easily be set in cyberspace or an alternate dimension.</p>
        <p>Crush has one central gimmick: you can crush three-dimensional space into two dimensions to create new pathways. Pale bricks set into a wall become platforms, and dark walls disappear. Flattening an east side view might cause towers of different heights to coalesce into a staircase, while flattening from the west could reveal a passageway. Crush a top-down view and a high platform will suddenly merge with the floor so you can step onto it. Puzzles are fiendishly intricate, and it is a thrill when you finish a circuitous, mind-bending route to the exit.</p>
        <p>Whether you are looking at a problem from every angle, looking at a disaster from every point of view or just looking at a game and thinking, wow, that's a nice looking game, keep looking. If you see yourself coming around the corner, try not to get in your own way.</p>
        <p>RAW DANGER  Developed by Irem and published by Agetec for PlayStation 2; for ages 13 and up; $14.99.</p>
        <p>LARA CROFT TOMB RAIDER: ANNIVERSARY  Developed by Crystal Dynamics and published by Eidos Interactive for PlayStation 2 and Windows 2000 and up; for all ages; $29.95.</p>
        <p>CRUSH  Developed by Zoë Mode and published by Sega for PlayStation Portable; for ages 10 and up; $29.99.</p>
        <p>GAME THEORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
