<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oscar Rules Regarding Producing Are Relaxed</title>
    <meta content="14acad" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/movies/14acad.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854321"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Awards/Academy Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Academy Awards (Oscars)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Academy Awards (Oscars)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Academy Awards (Oscars)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E2DB143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oscar Rules Regarding Producing Are Relaxed</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Oscar Rules Regarding Producing Are Relaxed</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL CIEPLY</byline>
      <dateline>BEVERLY HILLS, Calif., June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Producers take heart: It just got a little easier to put your hands on an Oscar.</p>
        <p>But just a little.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences said it will now, “in a rare and extraordinary circumstance,” consider crediting more than three producers as nominees for Oscars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Producers take heart: It just got a little easier to put your hands on an Oscar.</p>
        <p>But just a little.</p>
        <p>Bruised by disputes over which of a film's producers are entitled to a best-picture award, the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences, which awards the Oscars, said it would now, ''in a rare and extraordinary circumstance,'' consider crediting more than three producers as nominees. An eight-year-old policy had limited the number of qualifying producers to three.</p>
        <p>The new rule was adopted by the film academy's 43-member board of governors on Tuesday night, along with revisions that will permit two production designers to be nominated for their work on a given film, among other minor changes.</p>
        <p>The agreement to consider exceptions to the three-producer rule, though a small change, was welcomed by some of those who had been slighted by the old limitation, which at this year's Oscar ceremony excluded two producers, Albert Berger and Ron Yerxa, from awards consideration for the best-picture nominee ''Little Miss Sunshine.''</p>
        <p>''My immediate thought would be that it's a good move,'' Mr. Yerxa said. ''Quotas are almost always inherently unfair.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Yerxa, with Mr. Berger, his longtime producing partner, had played a major role in assembling the team that made ''Little Miss Sunshine,'' only to see three producers who were more involved in the project's latter stages qualify for the Academy Award.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berger and Mr. Yerxa said they had since become wary of financing movies under any deal that required them to add producers. Such arrangements have become common as wealthy investors and individuals, hungry for involvement in the moviemaking process, have embraced the independent film world.</p>
        <p>The academy's rule of three had been intended to avoid the sort of spectacle that occurred in 1999, when Harvey Weinstein, then the Miramax co-chairman, joined a gaggle of others in accepting the best-picture Oscar for ''Shakespeare in Love.'' That movie had five credited producers.</p>
        <p>In announcing the change Sidney Ganis, the film academy's president, said officials wanted to preserve a limit on the number of credits. But, he added, ''a truly unique situation could arise, and we want to have just enough flexibility to allow for that rare occurrence.''</p>
        <p>In 2005 the academy in effect tried to farm out its credits headaches by declaring that it would rely on a vetting process used by the Producers Guild of America. The producers guild presents its own awards and conducts an elaborate annual assessment of the actual role of the various producers who claim credit in a movie.</p>
        <p>But the arrangement between the groups was strained during this past Oscar season. The producers guild, normally sparing with credits, honored all five producers of ''Little Miss Sunshine'' with its Golden Laurel, the equivalent of best picture, leaving the academy to reduce the field on its own.</p>
        <p>This year's Oscar winner, ''The Departed,'' had credit problems as well. The academy honored just Graham King, though both the actor Brad Pitt and the studio executive Brad Grey were credited as producers. Mr. Grey had been instrumental in getting the film under way at Warner Brothers before becoming chairman of Paramount.</p>
        <p>Left unchanged by the academy was the bias of both it and the guild against recognizing a producer's credit for those who finance a film but are not fully involved in its production. The two groups have so far prevailed against a lawsuit by the financier Bob Yari, who last year was excluded from honors for ''Crash,'' the best-picture winner, of which he was a credited producer. Mr. Yari challenged that snub in court.</p>
        <p>The case was dismissed by a judge in Los Angeles, though Mr. Yari has filed notice that he intends to appeal, a spokesman said.</p>
        <p>The push to limit producers has been couched as an attempt to protect the purity of a craft that has sometimes been tainted by meaningless credits. But some new-wave producers argue that arbitrary definitions will inevitably break down as the lines between finance, marketing and production continue to blur.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
