<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Panel Says Liberian Ex-Leader's Wealth Hasn't Vanished</title>
    <meta content="14taylor" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/world/africa/14taylor.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854340"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Liberia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nigeria</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Security Council (Un)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Polgreen, Lydia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simons, Marlise</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taylor, Charles G</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Liberia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Nigeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Nigeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Liberia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Liberia</location>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Security Council</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Taylor, Charles G</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E6DA143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Panel Says Liberian Ex-Leader's Wealth Hasn't Vanished</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Panel Says Liberian Ex-Leader’s Wealth Hasn’t Vanished</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYDIA POLGREEN and MARLISE SIMONS; Lydia Polgreen reported from Dakar, and Marlise Simons from Paris.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Polgreen, Lydia; Simons, Marlise</byline>
      <dateline>DAKAR, Senegal, June 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Report by experts advising United Nations Security Council suggests that Charles G Taylor may still have access to considerable wealth, hidden in investments in Nigeria and Liberia; Taylor upended his long-awaited war crimes trial on June 4 by refusing to appear, saying he is too poor to afford his own defense and is dissatisfied with one provided by court, despite having amassed estimated half a billion dollars while in power in Liberia; experts say efforts to trace his fortune have met with resistance in Nigeria and Liberia; two countries have not frozen assets believed to be connect to Taylor (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Charles G. Taylor's long-awaited trial on 11 war crimes and crimes against humanity opened in The Hague on June 4, Mr. Taylor upended the proceedings by refusing to appear, saying he was too poor to afford his own defense and unhappy with the one provided by the court, despite having amassed a personal fortune estimated at half a billion dollars while in power in Liberia.</p>
        <p>But a confidential report by a panel of experts advising the United Nations Security Council suggests that Mr. Taylor may still have access to considerable wealth, salted away in investments in Nigeria and Liberia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Charles G. Taylor may still have access to considerable wealth amassed during his presidency, despite claiming penury at his war crimes trial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Charles G. Taylor's long-awaited trial on 11 war crimes and crimes against humanity opened in The Hague on June 4, Mr. Taylor upended the proceedings by refusing to appear, saying he was too poor to afford his own defense and unhappy with the one provided by the court, despite having amassed a personal fortune estimated at half a billion dollars while in power in Liberia.</p>
        <p>But a confidential report by a panel of experts advising the United Nations Security Council suggests that Mr. Taylor may still have access to considerable wealth, salted away in investments in Nigeria and Liberia.</p>
        <p>The Nigerian government refused to allow the panel, a group of financial analysts and specialists in the timber and diamond trades, to travel to Nigeria to investigate Mr. Taylor's finances, according to the report. Nor have Nigeria and Liberia frozen assets believed to be connected to Mr. Taylor, in part because they have not done so for several other prominent local officials whose assets the United Nations has said should be frozen as well.</p>
        <p>The report, which was sent to the Security Council on Wednesday, found evidence documenting payments Mr. Taylor received during his presidency from a timber company that was connected to an arms dealer convicted last year in a Dutch court of smuggling weapons for Mr. Taylor. There was also evidence suggesting that Mr. Taylor retained links to one of Liberia's biggest cellphone companies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor's claims of penury are a surprising turn of events for a man believed to have stolen hundreds of millions of dollars from Liberia and neighboring Sierra Leone, which he dragged into a civil war that lasted more than a decade. Mr. Taylor built a fortune in kickbacks from sales of the rich array of natural resources from both countries.</p>
        <p>A court spokesman said that Mr. Taylor still had a court-appointed lawyer, Karim Khan, and that although Mr. Taylor said in a letter to the court on June 4 that he was firing Mr. Khan, he cannot. Only the court can make that change, the spokesman said. Mr. Taylor also said in his letter that he wanted to defend himself. But for that he will have to ask the court's permission, and it may not be given, the spokesman said.</p>
        <p>The court spokesman also said that a second defense lawyer was expected to join Mr. Khan. The Taylor defense team, paid by the court, at present includes two legal assistants and two researchers.</p>
        <p>No one knows what happened to Mr. Taylor's money. In the Nigerian city of Calabar, where Mr. Taylor lived in exile for three years under a deal in which he gave up power in 2003, he lived in style with a handful of luxurious villas for himself and his entourage.</p>
        <p>In an earlier report last year, the United Nations panel of experts said evidence suggested that Mr. Taylor had ''made significant investments in Nigeria, such as in real estate,'' the report said.</p>
        <p>But efforts to trace his fortune have bumped up against resistance in Nigeria, where the panel of experts says he has made a number of investments, and Liberia, where he is connected, through intermediaries, to one of the country's biggest cellphone networks.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Taylor was arrested as he tried to flee Nigeria last March, he had with him a large amount of cash, but that money has also disappeared, the report said.</p>
        <p>In his time as a warlord and later as president of Liberia, Mr. Taylor extracted millions in exchange for tax breaks and a wide range of other favors for businessmen who hauled off billions' worth of treasure from Sierra Leone and Liberia in the nearly two decades they spent embroiled in interconnected civil wars.</p>
        <p>He built his first fortune as a government official in the 1980s, pocketing close to $1 million before fleeing an embezzling charge. He ended up in the United States, where he was arrested for extradition to Liberia but mysteriously escaped a Massachusetts prison.</p>
        <p>After several years of wandering around Africa, including a spell in a Libyan militia training camp, he launched his offensive on Liberia from Ivory Coast in 1989. By wresting control of the most mineral- and timber-rich regions of the country, he gained, by some estimates, $100 million a year in the early 1990s.</p>
        <p>The report details of one such deal between Mr. Taylor and Natura Holding, which hauled thousands of tons of hardwoods from Liberia during the civil war. According to a 2001 statement of account from the Ministry of Finance of Liberia unearthed by researchers, a subsidiary of the timber company, Natura, was credited for paying $2 million in taxes on July 17, 2000. The next day, a deposit from Natura for almost the same amount appeared in Mr. Taylor's personal account, according to a bank statement.</p>
        <p>''Millions more may have been deposited into Taylor's accounts, but definitive information on the ownership of these bank accounts has been difficult to obtain,'' the report said.</p>
        <p>He is believed to have entered into similar deals with the Oriental Timber Company, which was partly owned by Guus van Kouwenhoven, a Dutch businessman who was convicted in a Dutch court in 2006 of smuggling arms for Mr. Taylor. He was but one of a number of businessmen suspected of helping funnel arms for Mr. Taylor's insurgents and later his army to fuel the civil wars in Liberia and Sierra Leone.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
