<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Teaching Policy Chief Takes Top School Job in Baltimore, and Klein Taps Brooklyn Educator</title>
    <meta content="14school" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/nyregion/14school.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070724T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854418"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Klein, Joel I</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E7D8143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Teaching Policy Chief Takes Top School Job in Baltimore, and Klein Taps Brooklyn Educator</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Teaching Policy Chief Takes Top School Job in Baltimore, and Klein Taps Brooklyn Educator</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE BOSMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After one year, Andrés Alonso, the senior instructional official in the New York City public schools, is resigning as Chancellor Joel I. Klein's top deputy to become chief executive of the Baltimore public schools.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klein announced yesterday that Mr. Alonso would step down at the end of the school year and be succeeded on July 1 by Marcia V. Lyles, a veteran superintendent from Brooklyn who has worked in the city school system for three decades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chancellor Joel I. Klein announced that Marcia V. Lyles, a veteran superintendent from Brooklyn who has worked in the city school system for three decades, will come his new top deputy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After one year, Andrés Alonso, the senior instructional official in the New York City public schools, is resigning as Chancellor Joel I. Klein's top deputy to become chief executive of the Baltimore public schools.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klein announced yesterday that Mr. Alonso would step down at the end of the school year and be succeeded on July 1 by Marcia V. Lyles, a veteran superintendent from Brooklyn who has worked in the city school system for three decades.</p>
        <p>In picking Ms. Lyles to be deputy chancellor for teaching and learning, the chancellor broke his recent pattern of promoting aides from outside the traditional school bureaucracy. Her selection comes at a time when the efforts to free principals from oversight are expected to change the nature of the job.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klein praised Ms. Lyles's experience as an educator, first as a high school English teacher and then as a principal and superintendent.</p>
        <p>''She has been an extraordinary asset to my senior leadership team and an extraordinary leader for teaching and learning,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lyles drew instant support from the teachers' and principals' unions. But her promotion surprised some superintendents because, as the superintendent of Region 8 in Brooklyn since 2004, her region's gains in test scores in reading and math, while solid, have been behind those in many other regions over the past three years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klein, however, said at a news conference to announce Ms. Lyles's appointment that in 2007 her students' test score gains had been the strongest in the city and that test scores alone were not the basis of his decision. Among the 10 regional superintendents, Ms. Lyles had the second-highest gains in the four-year graduation rate between 2004 and 2006, bested only by Kathleen M. Cashin in Region 5 in Brooklyn and Queens.</p>
        <p>''I am delighted,'' Ms. Lyles, 58, said at the news conference. She added that though the city schools had made ''tremendous'' gains, ''there is still much work to be done.''</p>
        <p>The deputy chancellor for teaching and learning is responsible for curriculum and teaching policies with direct impact on what students experience in the classrooms. The job has had rapid turnover in recent years. Ms. Lyles will be the fourth person to hold the job under Mr. Klein since he took office in 2002.</p>
        <p>Meryl Tisch, a member of the New York State Board of Regents, said, ''I worry about this constant rotation.'' She cited the departure of Mr. Alonso's predecessor, Carmen Fariña, who resigned in April 2006 after two years. ''I don't want to start from ground zero again.'' Ms. Tisch said. ''I worry that this constant rotation in key personnel puts them at risk to not be able to maximize the achievement they're building toward.''</p>
        <p>Aminda Gentile, a vice president at the United Federation of Teachers, called Mr. Alonso's resignation ''bittersweet,'' but extended her union's congratulations to Ms. Lyles.</p>
        <p>Ernest Logan, president of the Council of School Supervisors and Administrators, said he looked forward to working with Ms. Lyles. One test of Ms. Lyles's authority came last month, when all of the city's principals chose to affiliate with ''school support organizations,'' which will provide resources to schools beginning next year.</p>
        <p>Principals had three options to choose from: to operate an ''empowerment school,'' which is organized in nontraditional ways; to work with a private nonprofit group; or to choose one of four ''learning support organizations'' being headed by former superintendents from the old regional system. Ms. Lyles was to be one of the superintendents.</p>
        <p>Of those 750 principals who chose learning support organizations, roughly 165 wanted to work with her.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alonso, 50, has been deputy chancellor for less than a year. He is a former lawyer and graduate of Harvard Law School who taught special education and bilingual education in Newark for 11 years. He obtained his doctorate in education from Harvard in June 2006.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview from Baltimore, Mr. Alonso said that he looked forward to running the district. ''It seemed like a great fit in terms of an opportunity to influence a system,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klein, who has sought to make New York a model for how to reshape a troubled urban school system, expressed little dismay at having one of his top executives hired by another big-city school district.</p>
        <p>''I'm pretty cool with that,'' he said. ''People want top leadership, and they recruit them.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 24, 2007, Tuesday  An article on June 14 about the resignation of the senior instructional official in the New York City public schools misspelled the given name of a member of the New York State Board of Regents who said she was concerned about rapid turnover in this position. (The error was repeated in an article on July 18 about the release of data showing how the city schools would use an influx of state money.) The regent is Merryl H. Tisch, not Meryl.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 24, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article on June 14 about the resignation of the senior instructional official in the New York City public schools misspelled the given name of a member of the New York State Board of Regents who said she was concerned about rapid turnover in this position. (The error was repeated in an article on July 18 about the release of data showing how the city schools would use an influx of state money.) The regent is Merryl H. Tisch, not Meryl.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
