<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gonzales and the Senate Vote</title>
    <meta content="l14gonzales" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854373"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E1DA143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gonzales and the Senate Vote</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''In Senate Vote, G.O.P. Fights Off Gonzales Rebuke'' (front page, June 12):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''In Senate Vote, G.O.P. Fights Off Gonzales Rebuke'' (front page, June 12):</p>
        <p>It is now clear that most Republicans in the Senate place protection of one of their most incompetent party members over the good of the country. The once Grand Old Party is exposed once again as a travesty of what it once was.</p>
        <p>We, the voters, will remember that fact next Election Day even if Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales can't seem to remember anything. Unfortunately, until the end of President Bush's term, the country will have to endure a dysfunctional Justice Department at a time when the demands of national security remain critical. It is a sad day for the Republican Party and yet another disgrace for America.</p>
        <p>William B. Spillman Jr.  Floyd, Va., June 12, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I congratulate the seven Republicans who joined Democrats in voting to end debate and move to a no-confidence vote against Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales.</p>
        <p>I find it repulsive that this administration stands behind a man who abused his power and lied to Congress and to the people.</p>
        <p>But again, President Bush's support for Mr. Gonzales is a reflection of his own doing. I am wondering when and if I will ever see justice applied before 2008.</p>
        <p>Monique Frugier  Ardmore, Pa., June 12, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I was troubled to learn that the attorney general is ''not focusing on what the Senate is doing'' but rather ''focusing on what the American people expect'' of him. We the American people elected senators to represent us, and we expect Alberto R. Gonzales to focus on what they do.</p>
        <p>Edwin Everhart  Chapel Hill, N.C., June 12, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>President Bush is quoted as saying, ''They can have their votes of no confidence, but it's not going to make the determination about who serves in my government.''</p>
        <p>It appears that President Abraham Lincoln's fervent hope for government of the people, by the people and for the people is not happening in George W. Bush's ''this is my government'' world.</p>
        <p>Janice L. Winchester  Seattle, June 12, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Silence in the Senate'' (editorial, June 13):</p>
        <p>It took one individual to lead us into war in Iraq, but as our ''democracy'' has evolved, a simple majority is insufficient to express the will of the people. The new math is now 60. Will this theory of evolution eventually require unanimity before anything useful can be accomplished?</p>
        <p>This silence seems to be getting louder and louder as our elected representatives have abandoned their constitutional responsibilities.</p>
        <p>Morris Roth  Fort Lee, N.J., June 13, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>While I believe that Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales made some egregious errors in explaining the rationale behind firing the nine United States attorneys, Congress was only hurting itself by trying to stage this no-confidence vote.</p>
        <p>Did the Democrats honestly believe that if they won this political battle, President Bush would have abruptly decided to fire the attorney general? I think not.</p>
        <p>Simply put, this is partisanship at its finest, and the ordinary citizen is tired of this Beltway bickering. This nonsense over the symbolic no-confidence vote gives the voter an impression that all the Democratic-controlled Congress wants to do is heap more misery on a terribly unpopular president at the expense of real issues like immigration.</p>
        <p>If legislators would focus on passing at least some substantive piece of legislation, perhaps this Congress would not be so reviled.</p>
        <p>Adam Hyams  Jericho, N.Y., June 13, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
