<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seeing Manhattan From Sea Level</title>
    <meta content="14swim" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/sports/othersports/14swim.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854378"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SWIMMING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E0DA143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seeing Manhattan From Sea Level</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Seeing Manhattan From Sea Level</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE TORGOVNICK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The visibility in some of the waterways surrounding Manhattan is so poor that a swimmer can barely see his own hands. The water is cold, the currents are powerful and debris can include plastic bags and dead fish.</p>
        <p>Despite those conditions, demand far outstrips the number of spots available in the annual Manhattan Island Marathon Swim, which on Saturday morning will send freestyle swimmers on a 28.5-mile course around the island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite poor conditions in some of the waterways surrounding Manhattan, demand far outstrips the number of spots available in the annual Manhattan Island Marathon Swim.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The visibility in some of the waterways surrounding Manhattan is so poor that a swimmer can barely see his own hands. The water is cold, the currents are powerful and debris can include plastic bags and dead fish.</p>
        <p>Despite those conditions, demand far outstrips the number of spots available in the annual Manhattan Island Marathon Swim, which on Saturday morning will send freestyle swimmers on a 28.5-mile course around the island.</p>
        <p>So many swimmers want to participate, in fact, that the race's organizers added three more events to the calendar.</p>
        <p>When the marathon swim began in 1982 (a revival of an event popular in the 1920s), it had only 12 swimmers. Nearly 90 are registered this year, and they range in age from 18 to 76. Many live in the New York area, but others arrive from throughout the country and the world -- including participants from Italy, Guatemala, Australia and Japan.</p>
        <p>''It's like applying to college,'' said Morty Berger, the founder of the Manhattan Island Foundation, which organizes the annual race. Manhattan Island Marathon Swim hopefuls must complete an online application, submit an essay about why they want to be part of the race and pay a fee of $1,285. Because the race can last more than nine hours, contenders must also complete a qualifying swim to show they have the stamina. Still, Berger said, ''We'll never be able to satisfy the demand.''</p>
        <p>When registration began Dec. 1, the slots filled in 1 hour 40 minutes. A long waiting list compelled the foundation to offer ''quiet swims'' in which a small number of people would have a chance to circumnavigate Manhattan. They gave priority to swimmers on the waiting list who had applied in previous years.</p>
        <p>The field for the main swim Saturday is composed of 25 solo swimmers and 15 relay teams of two, four or six members. For each of the quiet swims -- scheduled for July 14, Aug. 3 and Sept. 1 -- three individuals or teams will participate.</p>
        <p>Berger said another reason for a limit on the number of swimmers is the difficulty in coordinating with the boat traffic in New York Harbor.</p>
        <p>''For each swimmer or team, there needs to be a powerboat and a kayak escort, and we can't get the O.K. to have more boats out there,'' Lisa Gilson, a member of the event's advisory board, said.</p>
        <p>Most of the entry fee goes toward hiring the escort boats, which guide the swimmers through the race, ensure their safety and hold their crew.</p>
        <p>Kathy Jaeger, captain of Team Barbie, a four-person relay team, said she was disappointed when her team landed far down on the waiting list for the main event. But her team eagerly accepted an invitation to participate in a quiet swim.</p>
        <p>''It gives you a totally different view of Manhattan,'' Jaeger said about swimming around the island. ''When I went under the Brooklyn Bridge, I did backstroke so I could look up. When you swim past Yankee Stadium, nothing can beat it.''</p>
        <p>Rendy Lynn Opdycke, a graduate student from California, was among the first 25 solo swimmers accepted for the main event Saturday. She won the race last year and is a favorite again this year.</p>
        <p>''I would see Manhattan in movies and think, 'I could swim around that,' '' Opdycke said. ''The swim goes counterclockwise and I breathe to the right, so I don't see Manhattan at all as I swim. But when you're coming down the Hudson River, the Statue of Liberty gets bigger. I tear up because my grandparents came through Ellis Island.''</p>
        <p>Berger said that first-time participants would be surprised to see how clean the water is. ''The rivers and beaches around New York have come a long way -- federal and state regulations have put us in a good place,'' he said. ''The whole ecosystem here has dramatically improved.''</p>
        <p>But rain can create problems.</p>
        <p>''A drizzle or a short, 10-minute burst is fine, but if you have a sustained rain, we surpass the capacity constraints of the sewage system,'' Berger said. ''Everything goes straight into the river because of the way the system was built at the turn of the century.''</p>
        <p>The race was called off in 2003 and 2005 because of poor water quality and inclement weather.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Farber, a landscape architect from Brooklyn, will compete as a solo swimmer on Saturday for the first time, though he has competed in shorter races in the city's rivers. He said he has spent the past several months trying to figure out the best feeding schedule.</p>
        <p>''The rules are that you can't touch anyone on the boat,'' he said. ''Your crew has a fishing line with a bunch of Tupperware containers attached to it and they throw it out to you.''</p>
        <p>The water conditions can rob swimmers of their appetites. ''The Harlem River is brown and viscous,'' Farber said. ''Trying to hold down food is not easy there.''</p>
        <p>Because the water is salty, it can make swimmers' tongues feel swollen -- some rinse their mouths with Listerine periodically to diminish this effect. Wet suits are not permitted, and traditional bathing suits can rub against a swimmer's skin, creating what are known as swimsuit hickeys. To prevent this, swimmers coat their bodies in lanolin or Vaseline.</p>
        <p>But they swim on. The field is full, and the waiting list for the Manhattan Island Marathon Swim remains long. ''How many people get to say they swam around Manhattan?'' said Susie Hunter, another member of Team Barbie.</p>
        <p>SWIMMING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
