<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Immigration Bill Stalled, Advocates Push Forward</title>
    <meta content="14support" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/washington/14support.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854352"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE5DA143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1124" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Immigration Bill Stalled, Advocates Push Forward</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Immigration Bill Stalled, Advocates Push Forward</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Archibold, Randal C</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As officials in Washington discussed ways to revive an immigration bill stalled in the Senate, immigrant advocates moved forward on Wednesday with a new round of lobbying that they hope will lead illegal immigrants out of the shadows.</p>
        <p>Two nationwide caravans supporting immigrant rights are on their way to Washington, including members of a ''Dreams Across America'' campaign that left Wednesday on a train here to tell their stories at several stops and through a multimedia Web site. It is one of three Dreams Across America trains carrying 100 immigrants through different parts of the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Immigrant advocates moved forward on Wednesday with a new round of lobbying that they hope will lead illegal immigrants out of the shadows.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As officials in Washington discussed ways to revive an immigration bill stalled in the Senate, immigrant advocates moved forward on Wednesday with a new round of lobbying that they hope will lead illegal immigrants out of the shadows.</p>
        <p>Two nationwide caravans supporting immigrant rights are on their way to Washington, including members of a ''Dreams Across America'' campaign that left Wednesday on a train here to tell their stories at several stops and through a multimedia Web site. It is one of three Dreams Across America trains carrying 100 immigrants through different parts of the country.</p>
        <p>The campaign is organized by many of the groups -- including labor unions and the Roman Catholic Church -- that last year brought hundreds of thousands of people into the streets in support of immigration changes. The campaign is intended to counter concerns about border security and amnesty for illegal immigrants that have dominated the debate in Washington.</p>
        <p>''We want to create a dialogue with the public,'' said Fermin Vasquez, 20, a college student from El Salvador who recently became a legal resident. ''We know there are a lot of misconceptions about what an immigrant is and isn't. Anti-immigrant people ignore the civil wars and disasters and economic conditions that cause people to immigrate.''</p>
        <p>Cardinal Roger M. Mahony, the archbishop of Los Angeles, attended the send-off. He said there was a need to draw attention to recent public opinion polls that have shown a majority of Americans in favor of comprehensive changes to immigration law.</p>
        <p>''Because a few have raised negative voices, strident voices, it is easy to forget the majority of Americans are for immigration reform,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The other caravan plans to deliver one million letters Thursday to a group of senators in Washington from citizens and legal residents supporting passage of the comprehensive bill.</p>
        <p>But unlike the largely cohesive front lined up against the Senate bill, there is some division among immigrant advocates about whether the legislation is worth fighting for.</p>
        <p>Some are pressing to get the bill approved by the Senate in hopes of making changes when it goes before the House. Others denounce that strategy and call for a process that would make it easier than the bill envisions for large numbers of illegal immigrants in the United States to get legal status.</p>
        <p>''Nothing will be worse in terms of the millions of individuals and families that will be criminalized in perpetuity by the proposed Senate legislation,'' said lawyers for the Center for Human Rights and Constitutional Law, an advocacy group, in a statement.</p>
        <p>Frank Sharry, executive director of the National Immigration Forum, one of the groups in a broad coalition backing the bill, said many supporters had problems with aspects of the bill but supported the measure as a first step after years of failure to get any overhaul.</p>
        <p>That approach has left supporters of the bill in the awkward position of at once holding their noses while beating the drums for it.</p>
        <p>The Dreams Across America train reflects the changing tactics of some supporters, deliberately shifting their energies away from another round of demonstrations to lobby Congress. The cross-country public relations campaign offered a softer note to the large, loud demonstrations that some of the people behind the new move had backed last year.</p>
        <p>Behind the scenes, pro-immigration lobbyists are peppering legislators with calls and meetings, and everyone is operating with a sense that the next few weeks are critical.</p>
        <p>The bill ''is certainly not what we wanted,'' said Richard H. White, president of the Arizona Interfaith Network, which promotes the legalization of illegal immigrants. ''But our point is, because we have differences, that does not mean that should stop the debate. There is just too much cost being borne inordinately by Arizona and other border states.''</p>
        <p>But other advocates disagree, saying supporters of an overhaul have given too much ground. The bill, they argue, would do little to advance their goal of granting citizenship or legal status to all 12 million illegal immigrants and would not make it easier to unite divided families.</p>
        <p>Antonio Gonzalez, a veteran immigrants' rights advocate who leads a coalition of groups opposing the bill, said it would create an ''apartheid system'' of open doors for the affluent and skilled and closed ones for less fortunate but much-needed low-skilled workers.</p>
        <p>''It does not legalize 12 million undocumented people because there are an infinite number of obstacles in the legalization program that preclude 80 to 90 percent from making it through the system to permanent residency,'' he said. ''It does not solve future labor needs because of built-in deficiencies like requiring temporary workers to go back for a year after two years. Nobody is going to do that.''</p>
        <p>He said it was misguided to think the House was the body to soften provisions so that illegal immigrants and their families could get legal status quicker or easier.</p>
        <p>''The anti-immigrant right is driving this process, and the House is more susceptible to their pressure than the Senate,'' said Mr. Gonzalez, president of the William C. Velasquez Institute, an immigration policy center here.</p>
        <p>Such splits were reflected here in California, where Senator Dianne Feinstein, a backer of the bill, voted to cut off debate while a fellow Democrat, Senator Barbara Boxer, considered more liberal, joined 11 other Democrats in voting not to.</p>
        <p>As the presidential primaries gets closer, senators will be less inclined to make waves with an immigration bill, Mr. Sharry said, noting the minefield of procedural tactics, horse-trading and political posturing that can kill legislation.</p>
        <p>''Immigration legislation in the Congress has the feel of an Indiana Jones flick,'' Mr. Sharry said. ''It is so unpredictable and there are so many trapdoors and bad guys and slithering snakes and huge boulders you don't see until they are on you. To get to the 'grand bargain' was extremely time consuming, extremely painful and extremely difficult.''</p>
        <p>Still left in the lurch are millions of illegal immigrants. A group of church leaders have begun a New Sanctuary Movement to house illegal immigrants facing deportation in churches across the country. Law enforcement officers generally do not enter church grounds to make arrests unless lives are at stake.</p>
        <p>Last Friday, Liliana, who refused to give her last name, took up residence at St. Luke's Episcopal Church in Long Beach, near Los Angeles. She has three small children who were born in the United States and are citizens, but she has been told she is ineligible for legal status because she entered the country with a fraudulent birth certificate from her native Mexico several years ago.</p>
        <p>''We are not criminals or bad people,'' she said in a recent interview. ''We just want a way to work here and provide for our children.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
