<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>YouTube Passes Debates to a New Generation</title>
    <meta content="14youtube" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE1D8143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="821" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>YouTube Passes Debates to a New Generation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The quadrennial ritual of presidential debates has long followed a tried and true format.</p>
        <p>A guy in a suit asks mostly predictable questions of other people in suits. The voter is a fixture in the audience, motionless until he or she gets to address the candidate, respectfully. Everything is choreographed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The quadrennial ritual of presidential debates has long followed a tried and true format.</p>
        <p>A guy in a suit asks mostly predictable questions of other people in suits. The voter is a fixture in the audience, motionless until he or she gets to address the candidate, respectfully. Everything is choreographed.</p>
        <p>Now imagine a college student in jeans and a T-shirt asking a question, less reverentially, more pointedly and using powerful visual images to underscore the point. Maybe he or she will ask about the war in Iraq -- and show clips from a soldier's funeral. Or a mushroom cloud. The question might come as a rap song or through spliced images of a candidate's contradictory statements.</p>
        <p>The presidential debates are about to enter the world of YouTube, the anything-goes home-video-sharing Web site that puts the power in the hands of the camera holder. YouTube, which is owned by Google, and CNN are co-sponsoring a debate among the eight Democratic presidential candidates on July 23 in South Carolina, an event that could define the next phase of what has already been called the YouTube election, in which anyone with a video camera might alter the political debate.</p>
        <p>More than 100 million video clips are viewed on the site every day.</p>
        <p>The candidates are to assemble in Charleston, S.C., at the Citadel. The questions will come via video submitted by ordinary people through YouTube. Anderson Cooper, the CNN anchor, is to be the moderator.</p>
        <p>The video format opens the door for originality and spontaneity, elements usually foreign to the scripted environment of presidential image-making.</p>
        <p>The effect of freelance video on the political landscape is already evident. Senator George Allen, Republican of Virginia, lost his bid for re-election last year after a video showing him using the word ''macaca'' to describe a Democratic campaign worker of Indian descent spread across the Web and broke through to the mainstream media.</p>
        <p>''It's one of the biggest innovations we've seen in politics,'' said Mike Gehrke, director of research for the Democratic National Committee, which coordinated the YouTube/CNN event.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cooper has already made an appeal on CNN to viewers to make their videos ''creative,'' but no one knows quite what to expect.</p>
        <p>They are likely to reflect the irreverence inherent on YouTube. But how far will CNN go in showing the site's often-subversive attitude, as expressed in the ''1984'' video portraying Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton, Democrat of New York, as a Big Brother figure? And what to make of videos like one now racing around the Internet in which a young woman sings a salacious song about having a crush on Senator Barack Obama, Democrat of Illinois?</p>
        <p>Candidates are trying to counter with their own videos. ''Candidates are starting to recognize that the only way to fight the potential of the tsunami of voter-generated video is to produce lots of video themselves,'' said Andrew Rasiej, a co-founder of the nonpartisan Web site techPresident.com, which tracks the candidates' use of technology.</p>
        <p>The political videos on YouTube, especially those offered by the campaigns, are almost always less popular than clips on random topics. The most-viewed video in YouTube's 28-month history is a humorous look at dance steps, and has been viewed more than 50 million times over the last year. One of the most-watched political videos, the ''1984'' clip, has been watched about 3.4 million times in the three months it has been up.</p>
        <p>But the ones shown during the debate may get more attention. The scenes will be available on the Web for anyone to mash up new videos. The viral nature of the Web, and the pickup by the mainstream media, could spread the clips further.</p>
        <p>The debate sponsors hope YouTube involvement will increase ratings for the debates by bringing in a new audience; the question is whether that audience will go to the polls.</p>
        <p>''The impact of the YouTube debate can't be overestimated'' in reaching young voters, said Michael Bassik, a Democratic consultant with MSHC Partners, which specializes in online political advertising and is not affiliated with a campaign. In the five televised debates, most viewers were older than 55.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bassik said one downside for the candidates would be if a negative video were tagged to show up when someone searched for a campaign's own video. Still, he said, ''the campaigns are so risk-averse, they would be reluctant to engage in a YouTube debate if it weren't perceived over all as a positive experience.''</p>
        <p>YouTube said it would hold a similar debate for Republicans in Florida on Sept. 17. Matt Lewis, director of operations at townhall.com, a conservative site, said he liked the idea.</p>
        <p>''Yes, there's definitely opportunities for abuse here, for things to be shown out of context,'' Mr. Lewis said. ''But then you come back with your own video and show the full thing. Technology will happen, and the question is whether it will happen for you or to you.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
