<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Small Rebound in the 2nd Quarter</title>
    <meta content="14econ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/business/14econ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854386"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventories (Economic Indicator)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve System</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Commerce Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Labor Department (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peters, Jeremy W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leading Economic Indicators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Reserve System</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E6D9143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Small Rebound in the 2nd Quarter</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Small Rebound in the 2nd Quarter</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEREMY W. PETERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Peters, Jeremy W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Reserve's 'beige book' report shows economy was lusterless overall from mid-April through first few days of June but quickening in some regions; also finds inflation was muted in recent weeks; says labor costs were tame in period; finds strain on residential housing market showed few signs of abating, though commercial construction was growing; one bright spot for housing was market in and around New York City, which strengthened recently; prices climbed, sales 'remained brisk' and housing inventories shrunk; New York district is only Fed district to report increase in residential mortgage lending; Commerce Department reports retail sales in May rose 1.4 percent compared with 0.1 percent decline in April; says business inventories rose 0.4 percent in April; Labor Department reports measure of import prices rose at slower pace in May; graphs (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Words like ''modest,'' ''moderate'' and ''somewhat faster'' do not typically describe the type of economy that sends Wall Street on a tear.</p>
        <p>But that is exactly what happened yesterday when the Federal Reserve released its regular snapshot of economic conditions in the United States. The report found that the economy was lusterless overall but quickening in some regions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Federal Reserve report found that the economy was lusterless over all but quickening in some regions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Words like ''modest,'' ''moderate'' and ''somewhat faster'' do not typically describe the type of economy that sends Wall Street on a tear.</p>
        <p>But that is exactly what happened yesterday when the Federal Reserve released its regular snapshot of economic conditions in the United States. The report found that the economy was lusterless overall but quickening in some regions.</p>
        <p>The report also found that inflation was muted in recent weeks, a soothing observation for investors who have been unnerved lately by concerns that rising prices could prompt an interest rate increase by the Fed.</p>
        <p>Stock prices, which had been gaining all day, surged shortly after the report was released at 2 p.m. and finished the trading day with the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index, the broadest of the major stock indexes, posting its biggest leap since March.</p>
        <p>Shares were already on the rise as bond yields, which rose to a five-year high on Tuesday, began to ease in the morning, and a new batch of economic data suggested that consumers were showing few signs of fatigue. With rising gas prices and falling property values in many parts of the country, the wherewithal of the American consumer has been in doubt.</p>
        <p>The Fed's beige book, which surveyed economic activity in the central bank's 12 regions from mid-April through the first few days of June, supported a report yesterday from the Commerce Department that said retail sales last month rose by the largest margin in nearly a year and a half. The 1.4 percent jump in May was far more than Wall Street was expecting, and it came after a 0.1 percent decline in April.</p>
        <p>The upswing in spending was widespread, with auto dealers, construction supply companies and clothing stores all reporting stronger sales, according to the Commerce Department.</p>
        <p>Another government report released yesterday suggested that American businesses were expecting this firm level of growth to continue in the second half of the year. The Commerce Department said that business inventories -- the stockpiles of unsold goods that companies accumulate -- rose 0.4 percent in April, the fastest pace since last September. Monthly inventory growth has not risen more than 0.2 percent since last fall.</p>
        <p>Economists said that a rebound in growth was to be expected after such a slow first quarter. The gross domestic product advanced just 0.6 percent from January through March, the slowest in more than four years.</p>
        <p>''It confirms for most of us the notion that the 0.6 percent first-quarter G.D.P. was more statistical artifact than dangerously close to recession,'' said Robert J. Barbera, chief economist of ITG, an investment advisory firm. ''For those who thought the 0.6 percent G.D.P. number was a precursor to things going forward, that's a dead-on-arrival story.''</p>
        <p>Consumer spending has slowed from the lofty levels of last year. But economic growth in the second quarter is now starting to look stronger than many economists had predicted.</p>
        <p>''It's going to be a very solid quarter,'' said Joshua Shapiro, chief United States economist with MFR, an economic research firm. ''You have the consumer slowing down, but not precipitously in the second quarter; capital spending is O.K.; and it all nets out to what can be a pretty fancy second-quarter number.''</p>
        <p>The concern, he said, is if growth accelerates too quickly and prompts the Fed to raise rates. ''What will be much more important is what type of momentum we have in the end of the second quarter and in the third quarter. If it doesn't slow, I think people will start to worry about Fed tightening.''</p>
        <p>But in the wake of the latest numbers, any interest rate change up or down by the Fed seems far off. A measure of import prices, which the central bank monitors for signs of inflation, rose at a slower pace in May, according to a Labor Department report released yesterday.</p>
        <p>And the beige book noted that price increases were benign in recent weeks. ''District reports generally did not indicate an increase in overall price pressures,'' the report said.</p>
        <p>And labor costs, which have been a source of concern for Fed officials who worry that businesses could pass the cost of rising wages along to consumers, were tame.</p>
        <p>The strain on the residential housing market showed few signs of abating, though commercial construction was growing, according to the Fed report. No district reported an increase in new home construction, and real estate agents across the country said they expected the slump to continue for ''several more months at least.''</p>
        <p>The one bright spot for housing, according to the report, was the market in and around New York City, which strengthened recently. Prices climbed, sales ''remained brisk'' and housing inventories shrunk. The New York district was the only Fed district to report an increase in residential mortgage lending.</p>
        <p>The pattern in the Cleveland district, where builders said that ''residential construction has yet to bottom out,'' was more the norm.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
