<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As the Rich Get Richer, The Nascar Field Tilts</title>
    <meta content="14nascar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/sports/othersports/14nascar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854463"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Hendrick Motorsports Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Earnhardt, Dale Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hendrick, Rick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D8143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="944" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As the Rich Get Richer, The Nascar Field Tilts</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">As the Rich Get Richer, the Nascar Field Tilts</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIV BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <dateline>MOORESVILLE, N.C., June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dale Earnhardt Jr. flashed a broad smile as he stood next to the race-team owner Rick Hendrick with cameras clicking away, capturing the moment that marked the beginning of a new era in Nascar.</p>
        <p>Earnhardt, the most popular driver in the sport, announced Wednesday at his JR Motorsports headquarters that he would join Hendrick Motorsports, the most dominant team in the Nextel Cup. Earnhardt has agreed to a five-year contract starting in 2008. His addition will create an all-star lineup at Hendrick next year with the four-time Cup winner Jeff Gordon and the defending Cup champion Jimmie Johnson.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dale Earnhardt Jr., the most popular driver in Nascar, announced Wednesday that he will race for Hendrick Motorsports beginning in 2008.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dale Earnhardt Jr. flashed a broad smile as he stood next to the race-team owner Rick Hendrick with cameras clicking away, capturing the moment that marked the beginning of a new era in Nascar.</p>
        <p>Earnhardt, the most popular driver in the sport, announced Wednesday at his JR Motorsports headquarters that he would join Hendrick Motorsports, the most dominant team in the Nextel Cup. Earnhardt has agreed to a five-year contract starting in 2008. His addition will create an all-star lineup at Hendrick next year with the four-time Cup winner Jeff Gordon and the defending Cup champion Jimmie Johnson.</p>
        <p>Terms of his contract were not disclosed, but Hendrick said that Earnhardt would not be the highest-paid driver on his team.</p>
        <p>''It's akin to the Yankees signing the best free agent out there,'' Marc Ganis, a sports marketing consultant, said in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>The comparison is apt. Hendrick Motorsports was already a dynasty, winning four consecutive Cup titles in the 1990s on the way to six championships over all. Last year, Johnson delivered title No. 6, and the organization has been even stronger this season. It has won 10 of 14 races, including four victories apiece by Gordon and Johnson and one each by Casey Mears and Kyle Busch. Busch was let out of his contract and will depart after this season to keep Hendrick under Nascar's cap of four drivers per team.</p>
        <p>Soon, Hendrick will have Earnhardt, too. And that could change the sport.</p>
        <p>''It's going to make a formidable team indomitable,'' Geoff Smith, the president of the Roush Fenway Racing team, said in a telephone interview. ''Between Jeff Gordon and Dale Jr., I think they already have 60 to 70 percent of all the licensed goods.</p>
        <p>''They're going to have a lot more money than everybody else,'' Smith said. ''And that usually makes the competition tougher. It makes the weak weaker, and so forth.''</p>
        <p>In the economics of Nascar, the top teams are the ones that can spend the most to take advantage of engineering and technological advances. Earnhardt -- who accounts for 35 percent of the merchandise sales in Nascar, according to his sister and chief negotiator, Kelley Earnhardt Elledge -- will create a windfall for Hendrick, depending on their split of merchandise sales and what sponsors are attracted to the team. That will allow the team to spend more to find speed.</p>
        <p>But not all buy the theory that Hendrick will raise the cost of competition.</p>
        <p>''The Hendrick organization is well thought out,'' Don Miller, the president of Penske Racing, said in a telephone interview. ''Now it's going to be a little more effective than it was before. But it's not going to turn the sport upside down at all.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps not, but it could raise the profile of Nascar, and that might have an impact on everyone in the sport.</p>
        <p>Earnhardt, the son of the seven-time points champion Dale Earnhardt, has been voted the most popular driver in the sport by fans for the past four years. Earnhardt Jr. is the sentimental image of Nascar, after his father died in a crash on the final lap of the 2001 Daytona 500.</p>
        <p>Every race is a sea of red in large part because of the many Earnhardt Jr. fans who show up in Budweiser red gear with the No. 8 prominently displayed. It has not been determined if Budweiser will join Earnhardt at Hendrick or if Earnhardt will continue using the No. 8. But that will not matter if Earnhardt can find victory lane again. He has won 17 races with his current team, Dale Earnhardt Inc., but is winless in 2007 and has gone more than a year since his last victory, which came in May 2006. Earnhardt announced May 10 that he would leave D.E.I. after a year of sometimes contentious negotiations with his stepmother, Teresa Earnhardt.</p>
        <p>''I think that I'll have a good opportunity to succeed and win a lot of races,'' he said of the move to Hendrick. ''I think personally I will cherish a championship on my mantle when it's all said and done.''</p>
        <p>If Earnhardt starts winning regularly, many in Nascar could benefit.</p>
        <p>''Historically, in the United States, when you have a dominant team or a dominant player, TV ratings go up, newsprint covering your sport goes up and fan interest goes up,'' said Ganis, the marketing consultant. ''That has happened with Tiger Woods in golf, it happened in football with the Cowboys, 49ers, the Patriots. It has happened in basketball with the Lakers.''</p>
        <p>And perhaps that was why Nascar officials felt no compulsion to even the Nextel Cup's suddenly lopsided playing field.</p>
        <p>''In a way, I guess, they want him taken care of and I think they know me well enough that I'm going to take care of him,'' Hendrick said. ''I think that Nascar needs Junior to be successful and they need him to be happy and, I mean, I hope you guys could see today, he's pretty happy.''</p>
        <p>It remains to be seen if Earnhardt's many fans will feel the same way. Gordon has always been the archenemy of Junior Nation. Now fans will have to adjust to the two as teammates.</p>
        <p>''He's got what he needs and I think he's just going to show the world now what he really can do when he's got the equipment to do it with,'' said Sharon Weddington, 49, of Mooresville, a fan who went to JR Motorsports for the announcement Wednesday morning even though it was not open to the public.</p>
        <p>''Honestly, a true fan is going to follow him,'' she said. ''They're going to be there. Our blood is red. Budweiser red.''</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
