<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Only Thing Missing Is Bananarama</title>
    <meta content="14CODES" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/fashion/14CODES.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854297"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DRESS CODES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05EFDE143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="699" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Only Thing Missing Is Bananarama</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Only Thing Missing Is Bananarama</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Colman</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AH, cruel summer.</p>
        <p>A glance at the thermometer will tell you that the mercury is once again creeping into the 80s. And a perusal of the air-conditioned sale racks at Jeffrey New York will tell you that designers are doing the same.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some guys who may not remember the 80s are dressing like they do.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AH, cruel summer.</p>
        <p>A glance at the thermometer will tell you that the mercury is once again creeping into the 80s. And a perusal of the air-conditioned sale racks at Jeffrey New York will tell you that designers are doing the same.</p>
        <p>If this season's ahead-of-the-curve men's wear -- the clothes that flew off the rack as well as the lingerers -- is any indication, the fashion-o-meter that tracks whichever decade is influencing edge-of-fashion designers has finally clicked over, from the 1970s to the '80s. The shift has been coming for a few years, with designers like Hedi Slimane and Alexandre Plokhov referencing the style of bands from the late '70s and early '80s like Blondie, the Ramones, Elvis Costello and the Attractions, and the Clash. But now the waffling is over.</p>
        <p>This spring, fashion enthusiastically revisited the '80s with neon-bright colors, abstract and ethnic prints, blousy silhouettes, crazy asymmetrical graphics, impractically high-tech fabrics and New Wave accessories. Designers like Kim Jones, stores like Seven New York, European fashion magazines like Numero and Hercules, and New York hipsters like Geordon Nicol of the MisShapes are all waving, as Yaz sang in 1982, ''Goodbye Seventies.''</p>
        <p>If it all sounds a little much, that's the point. At a time when so much men's wear is relatively safe, and so many of the same looks can be found at Barneys New York and H&amp;M, some guys are itching for a style, or even a T-shirt, that unequivocally pushes the envelope instead of being quietly, stylishly ironic. At the same time, many 20-year-olds, having missed much of the Us decade the first time around, have a highly romanticized view of the early '80s, and are, as Devo sang in 1981, ''Through Being Cool.''</p>
        <p>''I'm a huge fan of Day-Glo,'' said Will Granlund, 26, an artist in Manhattan. ''I wear something fluorescent every day. The '90s, they were such angst-ridden, drab times. I think it is time for something a little more lighthearted.''</p>
        <p>''Eighties fashion wasn't necessarily flattering,'' he added, ''but it didn't matter. It was done in this spirit of not really caring.''</p>
        <p>That spirit is alive at Seven New York in SoHo, where '80s graphic experimentation pervades lines like Cassette Playa, Kenzo Minami, House of Holland, not to mention Kim Jones and Raf Simons. And the trend is hardly limited to the fringe. The spring lines of Prada, Martin Margiela and Marc Jacobs featured colors and prints of the '80s.</p>
        <p>And Italo Zucchelli, the Calvin Klein men's wear designer, really went there, with gray plastic-y fabrics, shirts in acid yellows and belts in electric blues, black-and-white grid patterns and high-tech textures.</p>
        <p>''I'm a child of the '80s, and part of my DNA was built in that period, mostly because I love that music so much,'' said Mr. Zucchelli, 42. ''The '80s were really a golden era of fashion. Men were more daring -- they wore skirts, they were not afraid. You'd go to a club and see all kinds of things.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Zucchelli and others, the fashion exuberance of the '80s (so perfectly exemplified by those skyward-tilting hairstyles held in place by a strange substance called mousse) stands in pointed contrast to today's distressed, faded understated looks (of which your is-it-or-isn't-it-vintage T-shirt is the ultimate example). He is trying to push his own collections toward a similar edge, he said. The sky-blue leggings he offered this season are a far cry from the slouchy cargo pants so omnipresent at Abercrombie &amp; Fitch.</p>
        <p>''It's fashion,'' he said of his collection.</p>
        <p>Whether men figure out that fashion is not a four-letter word remains to be seen. Most are perfectly content with today's upgraded style landscape where you can buy good-looking stylish clothes for as much or as little as you want to spend. Certainly high-'80s looks are not for everyone -- nor were they the first time around.</p>
        <p>Even so, Mr. Zucchelli expressed surprise at how well some of the oddest stuff sold this year. But if you find some outré bit of '80s style on the sale rack and are feeling bold, wear it with pride -- and claim you paid full price. As the Go-Go's sang back in 1981, ''Our Lips Are Sealed.''</p>
        <p>DRESS CODES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
