<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vintage Performance From Mussina</title>
    <meta content="14yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/sports/baseball/14yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854472"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Arizona Diamondbacks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Mussina, Mike</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Matsui, Hideki</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01EED8143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vintage Performance From Mussina</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Vintage Performance From Mussina</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Their seats are in the front row of Section 616, in the upper deck behind home plate at Yankee Stadium, a convenient spot for paying homage to the Yankees' starting pitcher. Gary DeSpirito and his son, Anthony, from Hawthorne, N.J., attend eight games a year in those seats, and most of the time the pitcher is Mike Mussina.</p>
        <p>Before their last game, the DeSpiritos searched Google for a picture of a moose and printed a bunch to tape to the awning in front of them after each strikeout. But Mussina pitched badly, as he often has this season. The father and son hung just two moose that night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Spotting his fastball and curve with uncanny precision, Mike Mussina struck out seven over seven and two-thirds innings, leading the Yankees to their eighth straight victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Their seats are in the front row of Section 616, in the upper deck behind home plate at Yankee Stadium, a convenient spot for paying homage to the Yankees' starting pitcher. Gary DeSpirito and his son, Anthony, from Hawthorne, N.J., attend eight games a year in those seats, and most of the time the pitcher is Mike Mussina.</p>
        <p>Before their last game, the DeSpiritos searched Google for a picture of a moose and printed a bunch to tape to the awning in front of them after each strikeout. But Mussina pitched badly, as he often has this season. The father and son hung just two moose that night.</p>
        <p>''He lost that game,'' Anthony said, ''so we're trying something different.''</p>
        <p>This time, they brought 10 copies of an image of Bullwinkle, the cartoon moose. At the end of each inning from the third through the seventh, Mussina put them to work. Spotting his fastball and curve with uncanny precision, Mussina struck out seven over seven and two-thirds innings, leading the Yankees to a 7-2 victory over the Arizona Diamondbacks.</p>
        <p>Mussina allowed six hits and no walks, and he left to a standing ovation from the crowd of 53,891. He waved twice on his way to the dugout -- once to the fans, he said, and once to his family.</p>
        <p>''The crowds here at Yankee Stadium now, they're into the games, and they like the way we're playing now,'' Mussina said. ''There's some excitement. It's nothing like it was four weeks ago.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees nudged their record over .500, at 32-31, ran their winning streak to eight and gained ground in two races. The Yankees trail Boston by eight and a half games in the American League East, and trail Detroit by four and a half for the wild card.</p>
        <p>It was Mussina's first victory in five weeks, but he pitched well for the third time in four starts. He also lasted five outs longer than he did in Chicago last Thursday, when Manager Joe Torre pulled him before the first out of the seventh inning, to Mussina's chagrin.</p>
        <p>At the mound last night, Torre said he told Mussina, ''I got you tired this time.'' Mussina smiled, though he said later he could not hear what Torre said amid all the cheers.</p>
        <p>''I think it meant a lot,'' Torre said. ''Moose doesn't show much emotion, but just the fact that he acknowledged them the way he did, everybody was happy for him, and I'm sure he appreciates that.''</p>
        <p>Torre wanted Wil Nieves to continue catching Mussina, a pairing that has had good results. In six starts with Nieves, Mussina has a 3.25 earned run average. In four starts with Jorge Posada, his E.R.A. was 9.00.</p>
        <p>Torre kept Posada in the lineup, as the designated hitter, and the move paid off when Posada pulled the first pitch of the bottom of the second for a homer. It erased the run Arizona had scored in the top of the inning, and the Diamondbacks never led again.</p>
        <p>Liv치n Hern치ndez walked three in the third inning -- by the end of his night, he would have five walks and a share of the National League lead, with 43 -- and the Yankees scored twice. The runs came on a mammoth homer by Alex Rodriguez, who swatted a flat breaking ball off the facing of the third deck in left field.</p>
        <p>''You never had to look twice,'' Torre said. ''He killed that ball.''</p>
        <p>It was Rodriguez's 25th homer, and he knew it as soon as he hit it, flipping the bat toward the dugout and beginning his trot around the bases.</p>
        <p>Trailing by 3-1, Hern치ndez retired the first two hitters of the fourth, but struggled thereafter. Bobby Abreu singled, stole second and scored on a single by Rodriguez. After Posada's second walk, Hern치ndez left a pitch high to Hideki Matsui, who crunched it to right field for a three-run homer.</p>
        <p>That made the score 7-1, and with the way Mussina was pitching, the Diamondbacks were overmatched. Mussina's fastball looked crisper than usual, near 90 miles an hour with life, and his curveballs were sharp.</p>
        <p>''I can pitch at 87, 88, 89,'' Mussina said. ''I can pitch there, as long as I've got the other stuff that I feel like I can do some things with. If I've got good command of the fastball with a little bit on it, they have to take it at least a little bit seriously. And if I can get the breaking ball over in any count, that really helps.''</p>
        <p>Each inning from the third through the seventh, Mussina sent the Diamondbacks back to the field with a strikeout. He caught Conor Jackson looking at a curveball to end the third, and threw an 87-mile-an-hour fastball past Mark Reynolds to finish the fourth.</p>
        <p>The fifth ended with Miguel Montero staring at an 88 m.p.h. fastball, and a curveball fooled Chad Tracy to end the sixth. Mussina used the curveball again to get Chris Young before the seventh-inning stretch.</p>
        <p>If the 38-year-old Mussina is past his prime, the Diamondbacks were not aware of it.</p>
        <p>''His stuff seemed real similar to what I've seen in the past,'' said Eric Byrnes, who was 1 for 4. ''People talk about how his stuff's declined, but obviously it didn't look like that tonight. He comes right at you and throws strikes. He made us get ourselves out, and we continued to do that all night.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
