<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Unexpected Odd Couple: Free Markets and Freedom</title>
    <meta content="14democracy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/world/14democracy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854341"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICAL MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Patricia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Fukuyama, Francis</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Stiglitz, Joseph E</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mandelbaum, Michael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E6DA143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1092" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Unexpected Odd Couple: Free Markets and Freedom</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Unexpected Odd Couple: Free Markets and Freedom</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Patricia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Academics back away from century-old theory that democracy and capitalism need each other to survive; examples like China, where economic boom continues despite Communist Party rule, and Russia, where Pres Vladimir V Putin has squelched opposition, challenge theory; some scholars say spread of democracy may still happen but it will take longer; some argue that capitalism preceded democracy in almost every country except United States where they arose at same time; China is considered ultimate test of theory; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When President Bush declared last week that political openness naturally accompanied economic openness, his counterparts in Beijing and Moscow were not the only ones to object. Liberal and conservative intellectuals, even once ardent supporters, have backed away from the century-old theory that democracy and capitalism, like Paris Hilton and paparazzi, need each other to survive.</p>
        <p>From China, where astounding economic growth persists despite Communist Party rule, to Russia, where President Vladimir V. Putin has squelched opposition, to Venezuela, where dissent is silenced, developments around the world have been tearing jawbreaker-size holes in what has been a remarkably powerful idea, not only in academic circles but also in both Republican and Democratic administrations -- that capitalism and democracy are two sides of a coin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The success of free market autocracies is leading intellectuals to back away from the notion that capitalism and democracy need each other to survive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When President Bush declared last week that political openness naturally accompanied economic openness, his counterparts in Beijing and Moscow were not the only ones to object. Liberal and conservative intellectuals, even once ardent supporters, have backed away from the century-old theory that democracy and capitalism, like Paris Hilton and paparazzi, need each other to survive.</p>
        <p>From China, where astounding economic growth persists despite Communist Party rule, to Russia, where President Vladimir V. Putin has squelched opposition, to Venezuela, where dissent is silenced, developments around the world have been tearing jawbreaker-size holes in what has been a remarkably powerful idea, not only in academic circles but also in both Republican and Democratic administrations -- that capitalism and democracy are two sides of a coin.</p>
        <p>''People, including myself, still have reasons to think it will eventually happen,'' Francis Fukuyama, a political economist at the Johns Hopkins School of Advanced International Studies, said of China's evolution to democracy. ''But the time frame has to be a lot longer.'' At least in the next couple of decades, he said, it is likely that ''the authoritarian system will keep going and get stronger.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fukuyama, perhaps more than anyone else, has been associated with the idea that capitalism and democracy are inextricably linked. In his famous essay, ''The End of History,'' written in 1989 as the Soviet Union was in decline, he declared that all nations would ultimately develop into Western-style liberal democracies.</p>
        <p>''There was great hope in the early 1990s,'' said Michael Mandelbaum, the author of the forthcoming book ''Democracy's Good Name: The Rise and Risks of the World's Most Popular Form of Government.'' The belief was that rising incomes would create a middle class that would agitate for personal liberty and political power. The tipping point seemed to occur when per capita income reached somewhere between $6,000 and $8,000. True, there were exceptions like tiny Singapore with its growing wealth and one-party state, but they were often dismissed as too small or transitional to really put a dent in the theory.</p>
        <p>Yet, as the free market and autocrats gained power in the Caucasus, Central Asia, Latin America and Russia, the initial optimism about democracy's sure-footed march faltered. Some scholars pointed out that the American experience, where democracy and capitalism arose at the same time, was not so much a model for the rest of the world as an anomaly. ''Capitalism came before democracy essentially everywhere, except in this country, where they started at the same time,'' said Bruce R. Scott, an economist at Harvard Business School who is finishing a book titled ''Capitalism, Democracy and Development.''</p>
        <p>''In the rest of the world, it took 100, 200, 300 years before they got to where they could manage a democracy,'' Mr. Scott said. A big mistake, he said, was assuming that ''all you had to have was a constitution and an election and you had a democracy; that was really stupid.''</p>
        <p>Joseph E. Stiglitz, a Nobel laureate now at Columbia University, agrees that one of the biggest changes since the early 1990s is an appreciation of the complexity and limits of democracy.</p>
        <p>As more fledgling democracies fail, various theories have surfaced to explain the appearance of democracy and elections without real freedom. Fareed Zakaria, a columnist and author of a book on the development of democracy, suggested that some countries -- Singapore, Peru and Russia, for example -- went through a stage of ''illiberal democracy,'' where there was robust economic growth but few political liberties like a free press, the rule of law and personal liberty until liberal habits and institutions had a chance to develop.</p>
        <p>Then, just after the start of the Iraq war, ''There was a miniburst of optimism'' that capitalism was leading to democracy after all, Mr. Mandelbaum said, with three popular uprisings in Ukraine, Georgia and Kyrgyzstan and elections in Gaza, Lebanon and Egypt in 2005. The burst quickly fizzled though, when the democratic ''revolutions'' proved short-lived and prone to violence and corruption. Now some scholars argue that a free market can even end up undermining democracy. ''Capitalism doesn't necessarily lead toward democracy at all,'' Mr. Scott said. ''The one thing that you can say is that capitalism is going to relentlessly produce inequality of income, and eventually that is going to become incompatible with democracy.'' That is where political leadership and institutions come in.</p>
        <p>Another problem, said Lord Dahrendorf, a research professor at the Social Science Research Center Berlin, is that when democracy fails to deliver the economic goods, people begin to doubt its value. ''Few things seem more difficult and yet few things are more important for sustainable liberty,'' he wrote recently, ''than to separate capitalism and democracy in people's minds.'' Otherwise, instead of mutually reinforcing each other, the two spiral into disenchantment.</p>
        <p>Even if capitalism does not assure democracy's existence, many economists and political scientists say it creates a hospitable atmosphere and helps democratic systems withstand turmoil. Nor should we forget, Mr. Stiglitz counsels, that ''the movement from closed to open society is a very big change.'' To compete economically, a nation has to be plugged into the global information network, which exposes its citizens to other political systems and cultures. Reinforcing that trend, Mr. Mandelbaum said, is that the ''habits and values of a market economy, when transferred to the political sphere, make for a democracy.''</p>
        <p>But China, he acknowledges, is ''the big enchilada, the big test.'' Even with its growing middle class, it still has a billion poor people. Pressure for democracy will increase, but so will push back from China's leaders. So far they have been successful. ''The Chinese government is pretty good at buying off intellectuals and the middle class who fear disorder much more than they want political participation,'' Mr. Fukuyama said.</p>
        <p>He added that he would not be surprised if China and even Russia were to come up with a ''new type of authoritarian ideology that tries to justify'' their non-Western systems. He has already heard the outlines of such arguments -- which echo the ''Asian values'' idea of non-Western cultural norms that lead to different development paths -- from Chinese intellectuals and Russian policy makers.</p>
        <p>Where the theorizing spills out of the classroom, though, is around the question of what can be done to influence the process. This is where stark differences appear, not between liberals and conservatives, but between the professors and policy makers. As Mr. Fukuyama said, one point on which he has differed from neoconservatives in the Bush administration is that, ''I think, in general, the United States can't do very much.''</p>
        <p>POLITICAL MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
