<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="14forsumms" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854405"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E2D9143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-19</p>
        <p>Shiite Holy Shrine in Iraq Is Bombed a Second Time  Two explosions apparently set by Sunni extremists toppled the minarets that remained atop one of Iraq's most revered Shiite shrines after a devastating bombing last year. Appeals for calm by Shiite leaders seemed to head off a sectarian convulsion like the wave of killings that pushed Iraq toward civil war following the 2006 bombing.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Hamas Seizes Most of Gaza  Hamas forces consolidated control over much of Gaza, taking command of the main north-south road and blowing up a Fatah headquarters in Khan Yunis, in the south.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Liberian's Finances Questioned  A confidential report by a panel of experts advising the United Nations Security Council suggests that Charles G. Taylor, the former president of Liberia on trial on war crimes who said he was too poor to afford his defense, may still have access to considerable wealth.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Gates Suggests Iran-Taliban Tie  The flow of illicit weapons from Iran to Taliban fighters in Afghanistan has rincreased so much that it suggests the shipments are taking place with the knowledge of the government in Tehran, Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates said.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Beirut Bombing Kills Lawmaker  A powerful bomb exploded at a popular seaside club in Beirut, killing a prominent lawmaker and nine other people. The bombing was the deadliest of five explosions that have rattled the Beirut area in a month.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Barak Returns to Israeli Politics  Ehud Barak, the former prime minister of Israel, returned to the political scene as the new leader of the Labor Party, and the deputy prime minister, Shimon Peres of the ruling Kadima Party, was elected by Parliament to the largely ceremonial post of president.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Clue to Dinosaur in China  Scientists uncovered a surprise in northern China: the fossil skeleton of abirdlike dinosaur that lived 70 million years ago.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A20-28</p>
        <p>New Changes Are Planned For Bill on Immigration  The White House and senators from both parties mapped out possible changes in a comprehensive immigration bill to better portray it as a way to bolster national security rather than to grant amnesty to millions of illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>As officials discussed ways to revive the immigration bill stalled in the Senate, immigrant advocates moved forward with a new round of lobbying that they hope will lead illegal immigrants out of the shadows.  A24</p>
        <p>House Votes on Gun Law  The House voted to close a loophole in gun control laws that allowed the Virginia Tech gunman, who in April killed 32 people and himself, to buy firearms even though he had been committed to a mental hospital. The Senate is likely to follow suit, in what would be the first time since 1996 that Congress has approved a measure strengthening gun control.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Panels Issue Subpoenas  The Senate and House Judiciary committees issued subpoenas to Harriet E. Miers, the former White House counsel, and Sara M. Taylor, the former political director, ratcheting up the pressure on the White House to cooperate with the Congressional inquiry into last year's firings of federal prosecutors.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Hmong Split After Arrest  The arrest of Gen. Vang Pao, the most recognized leader of Hmong people in the United States, has revealed a split in the Hmong population that has sprung up in this country: between old and young, between those who fled Laos and those who grew up here.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Testimony on Duke Case  The prosecutor in the Duke University lacrosse case, Michael B. Nifong, had nothing to do with a private laboratory's decision to not disclose that tests had found DNA from at least four unknown men on the body and underwear of a stripper who accused the students of gang rape, the laboratory director said. A28</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION B1-7</p>
        <p>Bank to Build Tower Near Ground Zero Site  After months of sharp bargaining and threats to relocate, JPMorgan Chase is expected to announce that it has struck a deal to build a skyscraper near ground zero and move its investment banking headquarters from Midtown. The bank's planned 42-story tower would rise at the site of the soon-to-be demolished former Deutsche Bank building. B1</p>
        <p>Reversal on Surveillance  In a startling legal reversal, a federal judge in Manhattan decided to vacate his own order that greatly limited the New York police from videotaping people at public gatherings because he had received new information in the case.  B1</p>
        <p>SPORTSTHURSDAY D1-7</p>
        <p>Blogger Stirs Legal Debate  The eviction of a newspaper reporter from a press box for blogging about a N.C.A.A. baseball game on the Internet while the event was still in progress has stirred a complex debate over legal questions surrounding First Amendment rights and contract law.  D5</p>
        <p>ARTS E1-10</p>
        <p>Oscar Producing Rules Relaxed  The Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences, which awards the Oscars, said it would now consider crediting more than three producers as nominees.  E1</p>
        <p>Waterfront on Endangered List  The National Trust for Historic Preservation plans to declare Brooklyn's industrial waterfront one of America's 11 most endangered historic places.  E1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES A29</p>
        <p>Baron Guy de Rothschild  The patriarch of the French branch of the famous banking dynasty, he was 98. A29</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY C1-15</p>
        <p>Buying Quality Health Care  In a Pennsylvania survey of the state's 60 hospitals that perform heart bypass surgery, the best-paid hospital received $100,000 for the operation while the least-paid got less than $20,000. At both hospitals patients had comparable lengths of stay and death rates.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Business Digest C2</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL A30-31</p>
        <p>Editorials: A failure to protect our troops; another sorry ascension; keeper of the Saudi secrets; Bork v. Bork.</p>
        <p>Columns: Timothy Egan and Nicholas D. Kristof.</p>
        <p>Bridge E6  TV Listings E9  Crossword E4  Weather B8</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-19</p>
        <p>Shiite Holy Shrine in Iraq Is Bombed a Second Time  Two explosions apparently set by Sunni extremists toppled the minarets that remained atop one of Iraq's most revered Shiite shrines after a devastating bombing last year. Appeals for calm by Shiite leaders seemed to head off a sectarian convulsion like the wave of killings that pushed Iraq toward civil war following the 2006 bombing.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Hamas Seizes Most of Gaza  Hamas forces consolidated control over much of Gaza, taking command of the main north-south road and blowing up a Fatah headquarters in Khan Yunis, in the south.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Liberian's Finances Questioned  A confidential report by a panel of experts advising the United Nations Security Council suggests that Charles G. Taylor, the former president of Liberia on trial on war crimes who said he was too poor to afford his defense, may still have access to considerable wealth.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Gates Suggests Iran-Taliban Tie  The flow of illicit weapons from Iran to Taliban fighters in Afghanistan has rincreased so much that it suggests the shipments are taking place with the knowledge of the government in Tehran, Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates said.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Beirut Bombing Kills Lawmaker  A powerful bomb exploded at a popular seaside club in Beirut, killing a prominent lawmaker and nine other people. The bombing was the deadliest of five explosions that have rattled the Beirut area in a month.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Barak Returns to Israeli Politics  Ehud Barak, the former prime minister of Israel, returned to the political scene as the new leader of the Labor Party, and the deputy prime minister, Shimon Peres of the ruling Kadima Party, was elected by Parliament to the largely ceremonial post of president.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Clue to Dinosaur in China  Scientists uncovered a surprise in northern China: the fossil skeleton of abirdlike dinosaur that lived 70 million years ago.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A20-28</p>
        <p>New Changes Are Planned For Bill on Immigration  The White House and senators from both parties mapped out possible changes in a comprehensive immigration bill to better portray it as a way to bolster national security rather than to grant amnesty to millions of illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>As officials discussed ways to revive the immigration bill stalled in the Senate, immigrant advocates moved forward with a new round of lobbying that they hope will lead illegal immigrants out of the shadows.  A24</p>
        <p>House Votes on Gun Law  The House voted to close a loophole in gun control laws that allowed the Virginia Tech gunman, who in April killed 32 people and himself, to buy firearms even though he had been committed to a mental hospital. The Senate is likely to follow suit, in what would be the first time since 1996 that Congress has approved a measure strengthening gun control.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Panels Issue Subpoenas  The Senate and House Judiciary committees issued subpoenas to Harriet E. Miers, the former White House counsel, and Sara M. Taylor, the former political director, ratcheting up the pressure on the White House to cooperate with the Congressional inquiry into last year's firings of federal prosecutors.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Hmong Split After Arrest  The arrest of Gen. Vang Pao, the most recognized leader of Hmong people in the United States, has revealed a split in the Hmong population that has sprung up in this country: between old and young, between those who fled Laos and those who grew up here.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Testimony on Duke Case  The prosecutor in the Duke University lacrosse case, Michael B. Nifong, had nothing to do with a private laboratory's decision to not disclose that tests had found DNA from at least four unknown men on the body and underwear of a stripper who accused the students of gang rape, the laboratory director said. A28</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION B1-7</p>
        <p>Bank to Build Tower Near Ground Zero Site  After months of sharp bargaining and threats to relocate, JPMorgan Chase is expected to announce that it has struck a deal to build a skyscraper near ground zero and move its investment banking headquarters from Midtown. The bank's planned 42-story tower would rise at the site of the soon-to-be demolished former Deutsche Bank building. B1</p>
        <p>Reversal on Surveillance  In a startling legal reversal, a federal judge in Manhattan decided to vacate his own order that greatly limited the New York police from videotaping people at public gatherings because he had received new information in the case.  B1</p>
        <p>SPORTSTHURSDAY D1-7</p>
        <p>Blogger Stirs Legal Debate  The eviction of a newspaper reporter from a press box for blogging about a N.C.A.A. baseball game on the Internet while the event was still in progress has stirred a complex debate over legal questions surrounding First Amendment rights and contract law.  D5</p>
        <p>ARTS E1-10</p>
        <p>Oscar Producing Rules Relaxed  The Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences, which awards the Oscars, said it would now consider crediting more than three producers as nominees.  E1</p>
        <p>Waterfront on Endangered List  The National Trust for Historic Preservation plans to declare Brooklyn's industrial waterfront one of America's 11 most endangered historic places.  E1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES A29</p>
        <p>Baron Guy de Rothschild  The patriarch of the French branch of the famous banking dynasty, he was 98. A29</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY C1-15</p>
        <p>Buying Quality Health Care  In a Pennsylvania survey of the state's 60 hospitals that perform heart bypass surgery, the best-paid hospital received $100,000 for the operation while the least-paid got less than $20,000. At both hospitals patients had comparable lengths of stay and death rates.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Business Digest C2</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL A30-31</p>
        <p>Editorials: A failure to protect our troops; another sorry ascension; keeper of the Saudi secrets; Bork v. Bork.</p>
        <p>Columns: Timothy Egan and Nicholas D. Kristof.</p>
        <p>Bridge E6  TV Listings E9  Crossword E4  Weather B8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
