<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Georgia Aquarium Mourns Another of Its Whale Sharks</title>
    <meta content="14shark" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/us/14shark.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854354"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia/Atlanta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sharks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Aquariums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aquariums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlanta (Ga)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Georgia Aquarium</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E4DA143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="507" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Georgia Aquarium Mourns Another of Its Whale Sharks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Georgia Aquarium Mourns Another of Its Whale Sharks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRENDA GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodman, Brenda</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the second time in five months, the Georgia Aquarium is mourning one of its stars, a young whale shark named Norton who was euthanized by veterinarians early Wednesday morning after he stopped swimming and slipped to the bottom of his tank.</p>
        <p>The exact cause of his illness is not yet known, said Ray Davis, the senior vice president for zoological operations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the second time in five months, a whale shark at the aquarium was euthanized, raising questions about the viability of the species in captivity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the second time in five months, the Georgia Aquarium is mourning one of its stars, a young whale shark named Norton who was euthanized by veterinarians early Wednesday morning after he stopped swimming and slipped to the bottom of his tank.</p>
        <p>The exact cause of his illness is not yet known, said Ray Davis, the senior vice president for zoological operations.</p>
        <p>The shark had been swimming and eating poorly for months, a change in his health that seemed to coincide with the use of a chemical pesticide to treat his tank for an infestation of parasitic leeches, Mr. Davis said.</p>
        <p>Another young whale shark named Ralph, who was also exposed to the treatments, died in January after he stopped swimming and could not be revived.</p>
        <p>That shark had also stopped eating shortly before his death, and biologists who participated in the necropsy said a hole in the lining in his stomach had probably caused an infection that led to his death.</p>
        <p>Ralph was being force-fed with a length of PVC pipe, and caretakers modified the tube after learning the results of the necropsy. Norton was also being force-fed, Mr. Davis said, but he had seemed to show interest in his food recently and caretakers took that to be a sign he might recover.</p>
        <p>''We've been very aggressive in our care, as you would be with a loved one or a pet,'' Mr. Davis said.</p>
        <p>In June 2005, Bernie Marcus, the founder of Home Depot, thrilled this city and raised the eyebrows of marine biologists with the news that he had bought the biggest fish in the world to swim in the biggest tank in the world -- a facility he had designed specifically to accommodate whale sharks, bus-size swimmers that would be on display for the first time outside Asia.</p>
        <p>But very little is known about these fish, a species that is considered to be endangered by many countries, and critics warned that whale sharks, which may live for decades in the wild, tend to fare much worse in captivity. A study of 16 whale sharks kept at the Okinawa Expo Aquarium from 1980 to 1998 found they survived, on average, 502 days in captivity. That facility has kept at least one whale shark for more than 10 years since that study ended.</p>
        <p>Ignoring naysayers, the Georgia Aquarium has already replaced the two dead sharks with two new males, Taroko and Yushan, flown in from Taiwan on June 1. Those two fish, along with Alice and Trixie, the two females that joined the exhibit in 2006, are all eating on their own and behaving normally, Mr. Davis said.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, after news of the shark's death, some marine biologists criticized the aquarium.</p>
        <p>''It's appalling, of course,'' said Lori Marino, a biologist who studies whale biology and behavior at Emory University in Atlanta. ''We all knew something like this was going to happen.</p>
        <p>''I wonder how many more animals have to die before they realize that this is not a viable exhibit for these animals.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
