<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>4 in Senate Seek Penalty For China</title>
    <meta content="14trade" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/business/worldbusiness/14trade.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854438"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baucus, Max (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grassley, Charles E (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schumer, Charles E (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graham, Lindsey (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Paulson, Henry M Jr (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weisman, Steven R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4D8143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1292" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>4 in Senate Seek Penalty For China</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">4 in Senate Seek Penalty for China</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN R. WEISMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weisman, Steven R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sens Max Baucus, Charles E Grassley, Charles E Schumer and Lindsey Graham propose legislation aimed at penalizing China over its export practices and predict that they will have votes to pass it in Congress this year even if it is vetoed by Pres Bush; administration says it will oppose bill, which appears certain to aggravate tensions with China at time when Treasury Sec Henry M Paulson Jr has sought to use negotiations to change Chinese economic policies, particularly those keeping value of its currency, the yuan, low; such low Chinese currency rates are spur to exports by making them cheaper for foreign consumers; US trade deficit with China last year was $232 billion, about one third of total American deficit with its trading partners; Chinese are sitting on estimated $1.4 trillion in foreign exchange, and have started to use some of that vast reserve to purchase American companies; administration, in issuing separate, semiannual report to Congress on exchange rate policies of American trading partners, says China does not meet 'technical requirements' of being labeled currency 'manipulator,' label that could bring sanctions; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four leading Democratic and Republican senators proposed legislation Wednesday aimed at penalizing China over its export practices and predicted that they would have the votes to pass it in Congress this year even if it was vetoed by President Bush.</p>
        <p>The administration indicated it would oppose the bill, which appeared certain to aggravate tensions with China at a time when Treasury Secretary Henry M. Paulson Jr. has sought to use negotiations to change Chinese economic policies, particularly those keeping the value of its currency low in relation to the dollar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four leading Democratic and Republican senators proposed legislation aimed at penalizing China over its export practices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Four leading Democratic and Republican senators proposed legislation Wednesday aimed at penalizing China over its export practices and predicted that they would have the votes to pass it in Congress this year even if it was vetoed by President Bush.</p>
        <p>The administration indicated it would oppose the bill, which appeared certain to aggravate tensions with China at a time when Treasury Secretary Henry M. Paulson Jr. has sought to use negotiations to change Chinese economic policies, particularly those keeping the value of its currency low in relation to the dollar.</p>
        <p>The legislation would set up an elaborate mechanism to punish China if it did not change its policy of intervening in currency markets to keep the exchange value of the currency, the yuan, low. Such low Chinese currency rates are a spur to exports by making them cheaper for foreign consumers..</p>
        <p>One of the four senators, Max Baucus, Democrat of Montana and chairman of the Finance Committee, said, ''This bill requires the Treasury Department to take firm but fair action when other nations play games with the U.S. dollar.'' He said the bill would pass by ''a veto-proof majority in the House and Senate.''</p>
        <p>Senator Charles E. Grassley of Iowa, the ranking Republican on the Finance Committee, said that the bill was not intended to start a fight with China and that he hoped it would persuade the Chinese to voluntarily change their practices before any penalties were imposed.</p>
        <p>Senators Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York, and Lindsey Graham, Republican of South Carolina, were also co-sponsors. They had sponsored a tougher version of the bill last year, calling for tariff increases of 27 percent on Chinese goods if the authorities in Beijing did not raise the value of their currency.</p>
        <p>That legislation was withdrawn under pressure from the administration, and Mr. Schumer and Mr. Graham acknowledged that its mechanism for imposing duties on Chinese goods would have violated international trade rules. They said the new bill would lead to penalties while complying with the rules.</p>
        <p>Mr. Paulson was briefed on the bill but issued no comment. Clay Lowery, the Treasury Department's acting under secretary for international affairs, indicated that the administration would resist it as likely to increase tensions with Beijing.</p>
        <p>''We believe that the best way to engage China on these issues is through dialogue and negotiations, and not necessarily through legislation,'' Mr. Lowery told reporters at a briefing accompanying a separate Treasury action on China, a report released Wednesday assessing its currency practices.</p>
        <p>The new legislation is one of several bills aimed at Beijing and introduced in the House and the Senate at a time of mounting criticism over Chinese economic policies that have promoted exports and restricted Chinese markets for foreign investment and goods.</p>
        <p>The United States trade deficit with China last year was $232 billion, about a third of the total American deficit with its trading partners. After years of accumulating trade surpluses, the Chinese are sitting on an estimated $1.4 trillion in foreign exchange, and have started to use some of that vast reserve to purchase American companies, including a stake in the Blackstone Group last month.</p>
        <p>Administration officials say that Mr. Paulson, a former Goldman Sachs executive who for years conducted business deals in China, has repeatedly warned the Beijing authorities to expect anti-China legislation if they did not open their economy more to outside investment and imports, and make more progress in letting the currency float more freely.</p>
        <p>''We have told the Chinese that there will be legislation on China,'' an administration official said, declining to be further identified. ''Our hope is to work with Congress to make sure it does not damage relations with China.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Paulson helped persuade Mr. Schumer and Mr. Grassley last year, arguing that the cabinet-level ''strategic economic dialogue'' with the Chinese he and colleagues recently conducted was a better way of bringing about change.</p>
        <p>Chinese and American officials met in Beijing in December and last month in Washington to move the process along, but with limited results.</p>
        <p>The bill announced on Wednesday reflected a widespread feeling in Congress that Mr. Paulson's approach had failed, especially on the currency matter. Mr. Paulson said last month that the dialogue was aimed at achieving long-term reforms in China, though he praised the Chinese for taking some limited steps in the short term.</p>
        <p>In issuing a separate, semiannual report to Congress on exchange rate policies of American trading partners, the administration took the same position it had in the past -- that China did not meet the ''technical requirements'' of being labeled a currency ''manipulator,'' a label that could bring sanctions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lowery said that it had been hard to assign motives to Chinese currency practices and therefore impossible to label China a manipulator. But the Treasury's report said it had forcefully raised the question of currency values ''at every available opportunity and will continue to do so.''</p>
        <p>It repeated accusations by Mr. Paulson and others that China's rapid economic growth reflected a ''severely unbalanced'' economy driven by exports and policies that discouraged domestic consumption.</p>
        <p>The currency report, which the law requires every six months, contained no surprises, nor was it a surprise that Democrats and Republicans denounced the administration for not labeling China a manipulator. The same criticism came from manufacturers' groups critical of Chinese trade and investment barriers.</p>
        <p>China critics cite a range of impediments to trade and investment, but the main focus of Congressional anger has been on the value of the yuan. Beijing has acknowledged that it must change its currency practices, but has appealed for patience.</p>
        <p>The yuan's value has appreciated by about 8 percent in relation to the dollar since July 2005. But many economists say that if it were allowed to float in the open market, it would appreciate by at least 20 percent to 30 percent. Instead, China uses its export revenue to buy dollars so that the value of the yuan is seen as artificially low.</p>
        <p>European leaders have also begun warning China over its trade and currency practices. Peter Mandelson, the European Union's trade commissioner, said last week that China was ''at a crossroads'' in its economic relations with the West.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration, while trying mostly to use persuasion in getting China to change its economic practices, has moved toward a harder line in the last six months. Early in the year, the administration threatened new tariffs, arguing that China was illegally subsidizing some exports.</p>
        <p>It has also taken China to court proceedings at the World Trade Organization, contending that its policies on subsidies and on the protection of copyrights and trademarks are illegal.</p>
        <p>These actions have drawn a reaction from Chinese officials, who warn that they would only strengthen the hand of hard-line elements.</p>
        <p>World Trade Organization rules bar protectionist measures except under some limited circumstances. The legislation proposed by Senators Baucus, Grassley, Schumer and Graham was intended to let the United States define currency practices as a form of ''dumping,'' or selling goods below cost.</p>
        <p>Countries belonging to the trade organization may impose duties on imports if they are dumped, but it was not clear whether the legislation would meet the W.T.O.'s definition.</p>
        <p>The legislation would require the Treasury Department to report on ''fundamentally misaligned currencies'' that would require ''priority action'' leading to consultations with the International Monetary Fund and the World Trade Organization. If these talks failed, certain penalties would kick in.</p>
        <p>Among these would be curbing China's voting rights at the I.M.F., limiting federal procurement of Chinese goods and services, and opposing United States government-backed loans or World Bank lending for China. The president could waive these penalties on carefully defined national security grounds, but Congress could register its disapproval of any such waiver.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
