<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coughlin Wants Less Talk, More Wins</title>
    <meta content="14giants" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/sports/football/14giants.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854377"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Coughlin, Tom</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Shockey, Jeremy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Strahan, Michael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Barber, Tiki</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0DA143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="656" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coughlin Wants Less Talk, More Wins</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Coughlin Wants Less Talk, More Wins</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tom Coughlin wants to coach a Giants team that does more winning and less bickering.</p>
        <p>Facing a pivotal year in his coaching career, Coughlin delivered a message when the team opened its three-day minicamp Wednesday. Simply put, Coughlin wants better performance and less talk. The Giants, who started 6-2 last season, lost 7 of their last 9 games, including their playoff loss to the Philadelphia Eagles. Along the way, several players criticized the coaching staff, there was division in the locker room, and the team never regained its momentum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>During the Giants’ late season struggles last year, several players criticized the coaching staff, there was division in the locker room, and the team never regained its momentum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tom Coughlin wants to coach a Giants team that does more winning and less bickering.</p>
        <p>Facing a pivotal year in his coaching career, Coughlin delivered a message when the team opened its three-day minicamp Wednesday. Simply put, Coughlin wants better performance and less talk. The Giants, who started 6-2 last season, lost 7 of their last 9 games, including their playoff loss to the Philadelphia Eagles. Along the way, several players criticized the coaching staff, there was division in the locker room, and the team never regained its momentum.</p>
        <p>A similar season could cost Coughlin his job. So, on the first day of minicamp, he was determined to set a different tone.</p>
        <p>''What we would really like to do, and I've talked to our team about it, is do our playing on the field and let our play do the talking,'' Coughlin said. ''Not spend so much time trying to explain who we are, where we are. Let's just play the game. Talk is cheap.''</p>
        <p>Asked why he felt compelled to convey that message to the team, Coughlin said: ''Because I think basically we talked too much. We need to play the game, and let our performance do our talking for us. We are in the media capital of the world, I understand that. But by the same token, performance is the key here. We need to get back to playing the game.''</p>
        <p>How well Coughlin's message resonates will play a part in the team's chemistry. One of the most outspoken Giants during Coughlin's tenure, Tiki Barber, has retired. Barber criticized the Giants' coaching strategy on several occasions during his career. But the Giants still have strong veteran personalities, including tight end Jeremy Shockey, defensive end Michael Strahan and wide receiver Plaxico Burress.</p>
        <p>If the Giants win consistently, it will be much easier for Coughlin to keep a lid on the locker room. But griping usually comes with losing, and several players said Wednesday that dissension hurt the team last season.</p>
        <p>''The distractions we had last year kind of affected us a little bit,'' linebacker Antonio Pierce said. ''We need to get back to having fun. Last year, it was fun when we were 6-2. After that, it wasn't fun for me.</p>
        <p>''We don't need to feed into the negativity. I don't want to worry about coming in here saying: 'Why is this teammate fighting? Why did he say that?' This ain't high school. This is professional football.''</p>
        <p>Asked about Barber's outspokenness last season, Pierce smiled and said: ''Tiki's not here no more. He's part of the media. He's a great Giant, we wish him the best in the media. But that was his comments and his views.''</p>
        <p>Strahan said the Giants would have fewer internal problems because Coughlin established a looser atmosphere.</p>
        <p>''Coach just has a lot easier demeanor about him,'' Strahan said. ''When you look at him, you don't get tense. Before, he just was a very intense fellow. But you look at him, you feel like you can go talk to him. He's going to come over and joke with you.</p>
        <p>''Before, we just didn't have that rapport. As the years have gone by, the better the rapport has gotten. Guys enjoy playing for him. I can't always say that, but now guys enjoy playing for him.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Fullback Jim Finn, who had shoulder surgery this week, has been placed on injured reserved and will miss the 2007 season.  Linebacker Jessie Armstead officially retired after signing a one-day contract with the Giants. In nine years with the team, Armstead made five Pro Bowls.  Michael Strahan, who did not participate in drills, said that he was recovering nicely from his right foot injury and that he expected to remain an elite defensive end at age 35. ''I feel like I can have my best year this year,'' Strahan said. ''I feel great. I've been running, no problem.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
