<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When They're 44</title>
    <meta content="14wells" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/sports/baseball/14wells.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854465"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Diego Padres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">San Diego Padres</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Clemens, Roger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wells, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E0D8143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1071" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When They're 44</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At 44, Wells Is the Anti-Clemens</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEE JENKINS</byline>
      <dateline>SAN DIEGO, June 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The reunions happened to be scheduled for the same day, one at Yankee Stadium, the other at All Souls Episcopal Church in San Diego.</p>
        <p>The Roger Clemens reunion, at Yankee Stadium last Saturday afternoon, was in honor of his latest comeback. It included four standing ovations and the playing of Elton John's ''Rocket Man.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Among 44-year-old starting pitchers in the major leagues, the Yankees’ Roger Clemens clearly gets the most love, but the Padres’ David Wells inspires the most awe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The reunions happened to be scheduled for the same day, one at Yankee Stadium, the other at All Souls Episcopal Church in San Diego.</p>
        <p>The Roger Clemens reunion, at Yankee Stadium last Saturday afternoon, was in honor of his latest comeback. It included four standing ovations and the playing of Elton John's ''Rocket Man.''</p>
        <p>The David Wells reunion, at All Souls last Saturday night, was in honor of his high school baseball team, which won a city championship 25 years ago. Players took part in a panel discussion and ate dinner at a nearby seafood restaurant.</p>
        <p>''Clemens had a big Yankee love-fest,'' said Susan Graham, president of the baseball booster club at Point Loma (Calif.) High School, Wells's alma mater. ''We had more of a community thing.''</p>
        <p>Among 44-year-old starting pitchers in the major leagues, Clemens clearly gets the most love, but Wells inspires the most awe. With one look at Clemens, it is easy to understand why he is still pitching. With one look at Wells, it is nearly impossible.</p>
        <p>Clemens is robust; Wells is round. Clemens still throws 90-mile-an-hour fastballs; Wells lives off lollipop curves. Clemens's biggest health problem is a fatigued groin muscle; Wells's health problems have included Type 2 diabetes, gout and high cholesterol.</p>
        <p>And yet, Clemens is the one who skipped the first two months of the season, saying he wanted to keep his body fresh. Wells, meanwhile, was around from the beginning of spring training, trying to discover the benefits of fish, salad and chicken.</p>
        <p>''I went two and a half months without a beer,'' Wells said. ''But I'm still the same old me.''</p>
        <p>Wells is so old, in fact, that his current pitching coach, Darren Balsley, was his counterpart in a city championship game in 1981. Balsley beat Wells for the '81 title and then watched Wells come back to win it in '82.</p>
        <p>While Clemens has been hailed this season for his one start, last Saturday against Pittsburgh, Wells has made 12. His earned run average, 4.76, is hardly All-Star material, but his smooth delivery and uncanny control still keep him in business.</p>
        <p>He has the benefit of lowered expectations. Clemens, in his second turn with the Yankees, is being asked to help win the World Series. Wells, in his second turn with the Padres, is being asked only to solidify the back end of the rotation.</p>
        <p>Wells makes contributions in other, more subtle ways. While Clemens is not obligated to spend time with the team between starts, Wells savors the four hours before games and the four days before outings.</p>
        <p>''I try to bring a lot of chaos to the clubhouse,'' Wells said. ''Cutting up, having fun, talking smack -- it's the fellowship with the guys. It's being at the park, talking baseball, having fun -- being a 25-year-old kid or a 44-year-old kid.''</p>
        <p>If Wells looks 44 and acts 25, Clemens looks 25 and acts 44. Despite the similar arc to their careers -- stops in New York, Boston and Toronto, along with stints in their respective hometowns -- Clemens and Wells have never had much in common.</p>
        <p>From the beginning, Clemens was a fireballer, Wells more of a junkballer. Clemens was one of the stars, Wells one of the guys. Clemens was the pitcher everybody wanted to work out with. Wells was the pitcher everybody wanted to hang out with.</p>
        <p>''A lot of guys in modern baseball like to show up, play the game and then go home,'' Padres catcher Josh Bard said. ''Boomer doesn't need the money. He comes here because he really and truly likes to be here.''</p>
        <p>On off-days, Wells has handed down his old Versace suits to reliever Heath Bell, introduced the lead singer of Creed to infielder Geoff Blum, taught a sharper curveball to starter Chris Young and gone over game plans with the staff ace Jake Peavy.</p>
        <p>Since receiving a diagnosis of diabetes in March, Wells has tried to improve his diet and limit his alcohol intake. But when he starts telling stories after games, he is still liable to pop open a beer and hold court.</p>
        <p>''The guy is larger than life in every way,'' Blum said.</p>
        <p>The Padres' clubhouse has taken on Wells's outsized personality. The team dog -- Bubba, a bulldog owned by Trevor Hoffman -- runs around the room before games. The team dad -- Bill Giles, father of the brothers Marcus and Brian Giles -- lounges on the sofa.</p>
        <p>Although the Yankees have more resources than the Padres and a far more powerful lineup, Wells may have a better shot at the playoffs than Clemens. San Diego, with the stingiest pitching staff in baseball, entered Wednesday night tied for first place in the National League West. The Yankees, despite a weeklong winning streak, remain far behind the Boston Red Sox in the American League East.</p>
        <p>Clemens and Wells both started Saturday, working six innings and giving up three runs. Clemens was rewarded with a victory and hundreds of congratulations. Wells got a no-decision and apologies from the Padres' relief corps, which blew a four-run lead.</p>
        <p>The Yankees are familiar with the juxtaposition between these pitchers. When Clemens gave up a run in the top of the first inning Saturday, he barely reacted. When Wells gave up a run in the top of the first, he rolled his eyes and shrugged his shoulders.</p>
        <p>''Our players know that Boomer is all in, all the time,'' Padres Manager Bud Black said. ''They know that he is in the trenches and will leave it all out there on the field. Players respect a guy like that. They see how much he loves the game.''</p>
        <p>Clemens and Wells cannot seem to get out of each other's way. They have been teammates and adversaries. They have been traded for each other.</p>
        <p>Now, they are on the same turn in the rotation. While Clemens is scheduled to pitch Friday night against the Mets at Shea Stadium, Wells is scheduled to pitch against the Chicago Cubs at Wrigley Field.</p>
        <p>After their last dual starts, on opposite coasts last Saturday, Clemens conducted a news conference at Yankee Stadium, flanked by his two youngest sons.</p>
        <p>Wells left Petco Park quickly and headed to The Brigantine, the seafood restaurant where his former high school teammates had gathered to reminisce. Wells missed the panel discussion at the church and the beginning of dinner.</p>
        <p>But he had all night to hang with the guys and talk baseball.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
