<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Pangs of Family Mealtime Guilt</title>
    <meta content="14work" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/fashion/14work.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854303"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="LIFE'S WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E0DC143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1166" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Pangs of Family Mealtime Guilt</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Pangs of Family Mealtime Guilt</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lisa Belkin</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON a recent weeknight at my house, my 16-year-old gobbled leftover pasta and a protein bar at 5:15, then raced off to baby-sit at 5:30. My 13-year-old left for Hebrew school at 6, where dinner is served in the form of pizza and salad (though I can't swear that he ever eats the salad). My husband, whose usual commute brings him home at about 7, drove directly to pay a condolence call at 7:30, where he snacked on a cookie. I ate low-carb cereal standing at the kitchen sink.</p>
        <p>On this particular night, I started to read ''Dinner With Dad,'' Cameron Stracher's chronicle of his vow to be home with his wife and young children for a sit-down meal (half of which he would cook himself) five nights a week. As a lawyer who spent four hours on a train each day, this was no easy feat. His book is charming and insightful. And it made me more than a little cranky.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Is life without dinner together really the equivalent of child abuse?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON a recent weeknight at my house, my 16-year-old gobbled leftover pasta and a protein bar at 5:15, then raced off to baby-sit at 5:30. My 13-year-old left for Hebrew school at 6, where dinner is served in the form of pizza and salad (though I can't swear that he ever eats the salad). My husband, whose usual commute brings him home at about 7, drove directly to pay a condolence call at 7:30, where he snacked on a cookie. I ate low-carb cereal standing at the kitchen sink.</p>
        <p>On this particular night, I started to read ''Dinner With Dad,'' Cameron Stracher's chronicle of his vow to be home with his wife and young children for a sit-down meal (half of which he would cook himself) five nights a week. As a lawyer who spent four hours on a train each day, this was no easy feat. His book is charming and insightful. And it made me more than a little cranky.</p>
        <p>It's not really Mr. Stracher's fault. I have been touchy on this subject for years, ever since the National Center on Addiction and Substance Abuse at Columbia University began releasing studies equating life without family dinner to something akin to child abuse.</p>
        <p>Its most recent report compares teenagers who have two or fewer family dinners per week with those who have five or more, and finds that the group that rarely eats en famille is twice as likely to have tried cigarettes, one and a half times more likely to have tried alcohol, and twice as likely to have tried marijuana. It goes on to link all this with academic performance, saying the greater the incidence of family dinners, the more A's and B's on report cards.</p>
        <p>I like having dinner with my family. When I was growing up, it happened every night. But that was when my father saw his last orthodontic patient at 5 o'clock, and my mother worked school district hours, and my brother, sister and I were not frantically running a gantlet of activities as we raced toward college. So to tell me that my reward for juggling a heavy workload, and my husband's 12-hour workdays, and my children's chock-full lives is the specter of juvenile delinquency just feels like one more layer of guilt to pile onto working parents.</p>
        <p>Because the fact is, failing to sit around the table as a family every weeknight hardly condemns your children to substance abuse and failing grades. The study by the center on addiction, while widely cited in simple shorthand, actually shows a complicated correlation, not a straightforward causation. ''The question isn't really do you eat dinner together, the question is are you involved in your family's life,'' says Dr. Harold Koplewicz, director of the New York University Child Study Center. ''Dinner is something we can count, so it becomes shorthand for much more. But it's not the food that's important as much as the time and connection.''</p>
        <p>So the hours I spend sprawled on the couch with the boys, arms and legs entangled, critiquing our favorite TV shows? That counts? Or the time spent in the car driving to all the activities that make dinner an impossible goal? That counts, too?</p>
        <p>''Absolutely,'' Dr. Koplewicz says. He is careful to point out that there is a difference between simply staring indiscriminately at the set and having a conversation that starts with the plot of ''Lost'' and branches out to ethics and history and literature. The latter can be better ''than a rushed family meal where the kids sulk and the parents lecture and then everyone storms away from the table.''</p>
        <p>Ah, yes. Those kinds of dinners. The ones that are less ''Father Knows Best'' and more ''All in the Family.'' The kind where you race home because it is your turn to cook, and then you spend hours making macaroni and cheese from scratch, only to have the children refuse to eat it because the pasta isn't shaped like bunnies and the cheese is the wrong color. So you throw it all in the trash and sulk like a child yourself at all the wasted effort. (That happened at Mr. Stracher's house at the start of his grand experiment.)</p>
        <p>Or the kind where you sit down to a Rockwellian tableau, and the one who is a situational vegetarian runs screaming from the table because he saw something that looked like blood on a drumstick. (That happened at our house. More than once.)</p>
        <p>A blog I visit periodically is ''Make Your Own Damn Dinner'' by a mother in West Texas who calls herself Badger and who got tired of making three different meals every night -- one for the parents and one for each of her two children. So she made a rule last summer, when her children were 8 and 10, that if they did not like what was served they could fend for themselves. ''It has to include a protein and a veggie,'' she writes, ''but other than that they're on their own.''</p>
        <p>I admire Badger's blog for its straight talk, and when I confessed my guilt to her in an e-mail message that I was somehow failing my children every time dinner passed uncelebrated, she did not disappoint.</p>
        <p>''I really enjoy having the family together, but that's not when I do the majority of my parenting,'' she wrote back. ''We parent all day long, not just between 5 and 7 p.m.''</p>
        <p>Of course I know that. We all do. Why then the looming mythology of dinner, so ingrained that a study that proves only a potential correlation can take such firm hold? Why the feeling of loss when there are empty chairs at the table? Mr. Stracher's book holds a clue. To keep his vow, he had to quit one of the two jobs he was working, one that required regular overnight trips out of town. That, in turn, brought financial worries, but also time -- to coach his children's sports teams (they are now 11 and 7) and teach them how to tie their shoes, and help with math.</p>
        <p>He did all this, he comes to see, not for them as much as for himself. ''It was a form of selfishness,'' he explained in an interview. ''I didn't do it because of data, or because I feared for their future, but because I realized that wasn't the way I wanted to be living my life. Yes, it's better for kids to have a dad around, but it's also better for me to be around. To not be eating fast food on a train in the dark.''</p>
        <p>Seen through that lens, family dinner is in fact a warning sign. Not that we are failing our children, but that we are failing ourselves. Working too hard. Relaxing too little. Letting life get a bit too out of control. And with that as the lesson, I am off to make fajitas for dinner. They all like fajitas. Most of the time.</p>
        <p>LIFE'S WORK E-mail: Belkin@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: Belkin@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
