<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mixing, Matching and Mirth For Oakmont's First 36 Holes</title>
    <meta content="14pairings" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/sports/golf/14pairings.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854471"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Davis, Mike</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hall, Jeff</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Crouse, Karen</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EED8143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mixing, Matching and Mirth For Oakmont's First 36 Holes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mixing, Matching and Mirth for Oakmont’s First 36 Holes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crouse, Karen</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa., June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The course at Oakmont Country Club has greens that slope like a funhouse floor and about as much breathing room as polyester knit pants. If the weather this week is hot and dry, the world's best golfers are liable to stagger through the United States Open with faces longer than the 667-yard 12th hole.</p>
        <p>The Open, one of golf's stiffest tests, leaves little room for levity, but the officials who put on the event for the United States Golf Association are not humorless. The proof is in the pairings for the first two rounds, which appear to have been compiled with a wink and a smile.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The officials who put on the United States Open are not humorless. The proof is in the pairings for the first two rounds, which appear to have been compiled with a wink and a smile.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The course at Oakmont Country Club has greens that slope like a funhouse floor and about as much breathing room as polyester knit pants. If the weather this week is hot and dry, the world's best golfers are liable to stagger through the United States Open with faces longer than the 667-yard 12th hole.</p>
        <p>The Open, one of golf's stiffest tests, leaves little room for levity, but the officials who put on the event for the United States Golf Association are not humorless. The proof is in the pairings for the first two rounds, which appear to have been compiled with a wink and a smile.</p>
        <p>This year the job fell to Mike Davis, the director of rules and competitions, and Jeff Hall, the director of rules/competition standards. Sequestered in a room, they channeled their inner Willy Wonka.</p>
        <p>The 52 threesomes are where tradition intersects with tongue in cheek. You have the reigning titleholders from the British Open (Tiger Woods), the United States Amateur (Richie Ramsay) and the United States Open (Geoff Ogilvy) playing together.</p>
        <p>There is the PGA Tour's twin piqued, Pat Perez and Woody Austin, who have a history of acting out on the course. Pérez made an obscene gesture at his golf ball at a tournament in Florida two years ago, and Austin once bent the shaft of his putter when he banged himself on the head with it.</p>
        <p>The Australian Matthew Goggin, who rounds out the group, laughed at the suggestion that he was the calm center of this stormy pairing. ''I'm not going to pass judgment on anyone throwing clubs and going off,'' Goggin said with a laugh, ''because it's just as likely to be me as anyone else.''</p>
        <p>The pairings include a bow to excellence, with No. 2-ranked Phil Mickelson, No. 3 Jim Furyk and No. 4 Adam Scott making up one group. ''We thought those are three guys playing great golf,'' the U.S.G.A.'s Davis said, ''So wouldn't it be fun to have them together.''</p>
        <p>There is also a bow to fashion in the form of the peacock pairing of Ian Poulter, Ryan Moore and Shingo Katayama, all of whom are distinctive dressers. That threesome stands out even on the black-and-white page of a pairing sheet.</p>
        <p>''Three guys that like to dress a little different than everybody else,'' said Bubba Watson, who is participating in his second United States Open. ''When I saw the pairings, that one caught my eye.''</p>
        <p>There is the group of bridesmaids: Colin Montgomerie, Tim Clark and Chris DiMarco, all of whom have been runners-up in majors.</p>
        <p>And the pride of Milton High: Watson is paired with his good friend Boo Weekley, who graduated from the same school in the small Florida panhandle town where they grew up.</p>
        <p>''My wife called me last week, after she saw the pairings on the Internet,'' said Watson, who was playing in the P.G.A. Tour event in Memphis. ''I saw Boo on the range right afterwards and said, 'Hey, we're playing together at the Open,' and he was like, 'Man, that will be fun.' ''</p>
        <p>The 28-year-old Watson had to agree. ''I don't know how they came up with it, but it's good for me,'' he said. ''Playing with someone I know that well, it lightens up the day.''</p>
        <p>Nobuhiro Masuda, a mainstay on the Japan Tour, rounds out the threesome. ''Nobody's going to understand anybody in that pairing,'' Watson said. ''If he can't speak English, we're not going to understand him, and he might not understand our Southern twang.''</p>
        <p>There is a Spanish pairing for the ages, featuring three eras with one tee time: José María Olazábal, Sergio García and Pablo Martín.</p>
        <p>And a nod to a British Open of yesteryear in a pairing that includes Thomas Bjorn and Ben Curtis, who won the title at Royal St. George's in England in 2003 after Bjorn, who was leading, played the last four holes in four over par.</p>
        <p>One of the Tour's faster players, Rory Sabbatini, is paired with one of the more fastidious, Justin Leonard.</p>
        <p>In a recent poll of Tour players taken by Sports Illustrated, Sabbatini was identified by 25 percent of the respondents as their least favorite playing partner. Jerry Kelly, the third member of the group, said he considered Sabbatini a friend and did not sound at all bothered to be playing with him.</p>
        <p>''I like to get paired with some of the friends that I know because you know you're going to have a good time in between shots,'' Kelly said.</p>
        <p>It took Davis and Hall the better part of a day to complete this year's pairings. ''It's probably the funnest day of the year,'' Davis said Wednesday, ''just because we get to laughing so hard about some of the pairings.''</p>
        <p>Once they were done, they handed their list to the U.S.G.A.'s executive director, David Fay, to review.</p>
        <p>Fay once had their job but relinquished it when he decided he was becoming a little carried away. Or as he put it, ''making it a game for a game's sake.''</p>
        <p>As he perused Davis and Hall's handiwork, he laughed at the inside jokes.</p>
        <p>''Not a sinister chuckle,'' he said, ''but a 'Ha.' ''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
