<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trial Ordered in Italy for 4 Big Banks in Parmalat's Failure</title>
    <meta content="14parmalat" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/business/worldbusiness/14parmalat.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854392"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Parmalat</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Citigroup Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Deutsche Bank Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Morgan Stanley</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ubs Ag</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sylvers, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greco, Francesco</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tanzi, Calisto</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Italy</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Parmalat SpA</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Citigroup Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Deutsche Bank AG</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Morgan Stanley</org>
        <org class="online_producer">UBS AG</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E6D9143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="646" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trial Ordered in Italy for 4 Big Banks in Parmalat's Failure</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trial Ordered in Italy for 4 Big Banks in Parmalat’s Failure</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SYLVERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sylvers, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>MILAN, June 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Italian judge orders Citigroup, Deutsche Bank, Morgan Stanley and UBS, as well as 13 employees of four banks, to stand trial on charges of market manipulation in events that led to multibillion-dollar bankruptcy filing of Italy's Parmalat in 2003; indictments represent success for Milan prosecutors, led by Francesco Greco, who has been working on case for more than three years; trial is not scheduled to start until January and proceedings could last several years; case is one of several under way as prosecutors try to unravel series of events that led to Parmalat's collapse with debt of 14.3 billion euros, or about $19 billion; all four banks deny wrongdoing; photo of Parmalat's founder and former chairman Calisto Tanzi (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An Italian judge on Wednesday ordered Citigroup, Deutsche Bank, Morgan Stanley and UBS, as well as 13 employees of the four banks, to stand trial on charges of market manipulation in the events that led to the multibillion-dollar bankruptcy filing of the Italian dairy company Parmalat in 2003.</p>
        <p>Though the trial is not scheduled to start until January, and the proceedings could last several years, the indictments represent a success for the Milan prosecutors, led by Francesco Greco, who have been working on the case for more than three years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Citigroup, Deutsche Bank, Morgan Stanley and UBS have been ordered to stand trial on charges of market manipulation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An Italian judge on Wednesday ordered Citigroup, Deutsche Bank, Morgan Stanley and UBS, as well as 13 employees of the four banks, to stand trial on charges of market manipulation in the events that led to the multibillion-dollar bankruptcy filing of the Italian dairy company Parmalat in 2003.</p>
        <p>Though the trial is not scheduled to start until January, and the proceedings could last several years, the indictments represent a success for the Milan prosecutors, led by Francesco Greco, who have been working on the case for more than three years.</p>
        <p>The case is one of several under way as the prosecutors try to unravel a series of events that led to Parmalat's collapse with a debt of 14.3 billion euros, or about $19 billion, the largest bankruptcy in Europe.</p>
        <p>The banks and their employees are accused of lining up financing for Parmalat through the sale of bonds and other financial instruments while knowing that the company had been falsifying its accounts and was in financial difficulty. In some cases, the banks secured funds for Parmalat through bond sales just months before its collapse.</p>
        <p>All four banks denied wrongdoing on Wednesday, saying that like the investors who bought Parmalat bonds and shares, they had not known that the company was teetering near collapse and doctoring its financial results.</p>
        <p>UBS said in a statement: ''Parmalat was rated by independent agencies as a financially sound company. This position was confirmed by external auditors. UBS has absolutely no evidence that any of its employees were aware of the true state of Parmalat's finances. UBS is mounting a vigorous defense against the various claims.''</p>
        <p>The other banks released similar statements, and all declined to elaborate.</p>
        <p>Parmalat's finances disintegrated in December 2003 when it was disclosed that a bank account, in which the company said it had 3.9 billion euros, did not exist. Calisto Tanzi, Parmalat's founder and former chairman, and more than a dozen other former employees and advisers were jailed in the weeks after the collapse.</p>
        <p>An independent auditor later found that Parmalat had been falsifying its accounts for more than a decade and had a debt of 14.3 billion euros, eight times more than it acknowledged. Mr. Tanzi later said that Parmalat began falsifying its accounts in the 1980s.</p>
        <p>For the banks to be convicted, the prosecutors will have to prove that they did not have organizations and policies aimed specifically at preventing their employees from committing the crimes.</p>
        <p>The 13 employees are mainly senior managers of the banks' Italian operations, who in most cases are still in place.</p>
        <p>The statute of limitations on market manipulation in Italy is seven and a half years from the time the crime was committed, meaning that in most cases, the trial will have to be concluded by the end of 2010 or the charges will be dropped. With the trial not scheduled until January, and with a long appeals process likely if there are convictions, several legal experts said that the statute of limitations might come into play.</p>
        <p>There are two other court proceedings connected to the Parmalat collapse, in Milan and in Parma, Parmalat's hometown.</p>
        <p>More than 50 former employees and advisers face charges of fraudulent bankruptcy in Parma, which can be punished with prison sentences as long as 15 years.</p>
        <p>In the other Milan trial, Mr. Tanzi and others are accused of market manipulation, obstructing an investigation by Italy's market regulator and falsifying audits. Mr. Tanzi has said in that trial, which began last year, that the banks led him astray and provided financing even when they knew the company was in dire financial condition.</p>
        <p>Parmalat's new management, led by Enrico Bondi as chief executive, is suing Italian and international banks as well as former auditors over the financial collapse. Mr. Bondi has reached out-of-court settlements with several banks and with a former auditor, Deloitte Touche Tohmatsu.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
