<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Skateboarding in Olympics: Rad or Bad?</title>
    <meta content="14olympics" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/sports/othersports/14olympics.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854379"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ACTION SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Snowboarding</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Skateboards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snowboarding</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skateboards</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Higgins, Matt</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EEDA143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Skateboarding in Olympics: Rad or Bad?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Skateboarding in Olympics: Rad or Bad?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT HIGGINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Higgins, Matt</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is definitely not cycling. Some say it is not a sport at all. Still, skateboarding -- with creative assistance from cycling's international governing body -- appears headed for the Olympics in a bid to make the 111-year-old Games more attractive to a younger audience.</p>
        <p>Reaction in the skateboarding community has ranged from joy to skepticism to downright contempt, and stirred memories of the Olympic debut of snowboarding nearly 10 years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Skateboarding  with creative assistance from cycling’s international governing body  appears headed for the Olympics in a bid to make the 111-year-old Games more attractive to a younger audience.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is definitely not cycling. Some say it is not a sport at all. Still, skateboarding -- with creative assistance from cycling's international governing body -- appears headed for the Olympics in a bid to make the 111-year-old Games more attractive to a younger audience.</p>
        <p>Reaction in the skateboarding community has ranged from joy to skepticism to downright contempt, and stirred memories of the Olympic debut of snowboarding nearly 10 years ago.</p>
        <p>Last week in Lausanne, Switzerland, members of the International Olympic Committee and the International Cycling Union discussed adding skateboarding as a discipline at the 2012 Games in London.</p>
        <p>And in two weeks the management board of the cycling union is expected to adopt skateboarding, starting a two-year process that would make it part of the Olympic program. A final decision would be made in 2009 by the executive committee of the I.O.C.</p>
        <p>If skateboarding is accepted -- and signs are it will be -- it will become the third action sport in the Olympics, joining snowboarding and BMX racing, which debuts at the 2008 Games in Beijing.</p>
        <p>''From our side we are committed to help the development of skateboarding,'' said Enrico Carpani, a spokesman for the cycling union.</p>
        <p>So, too, is the I.O.C.</p>
        <p>Carpani said that at a meeting in 2006, Jacques Rogge, the I.O.C. president, asked the cycling body to assist skateboarding with entry to the Olympics.</p>
        <p>''There's a real wish within the I.O.C. to engage with the youth and make a program that's very appealing to them,'' the I.O.C. spokeswoman Emmanuelle Moreau said.</p>
        <p>It is about time, according to the skateboarding icon Tony Hawk, who has helped organize the sport worldwide.</p>
        <p>''I believe the chances are good'' skateboarding will appear at the 2012 Games, Hawk wrote in an e-mail message. ''The Olympics desperately need a cool factor for their Summer Games. They finally figured out that snowboarding is more popular than curling during the winter. Now they need to make the same realization for summer sports.''</p>
        <p>Snowboarding was a highly rated event on NBC at the 2006 Winter Games. But its debut as a skiing discipline at the 1998 Winter Games in Nagano, Japan, was dogged by controversy.</p>
        <p>In 1994, snowboarding was brought under the auspices of the International Ski Federation. As a result, many snowboarders felt that skiing had hijacked their sport and several of the world's top riders boycotted the Games. Even afterward, competitors complained that the ski federation's judging criteria emphasized amplitude (height) over creativity, effectively stifling the sport's most sacrosanct element -- style.</p>
        <p>Although those problems have since mostly been resolved, the episode looms in the minds of many skaters.</p>
        <p>Danny Way is a top professional skater who has won gold medals at the X Games. He said he could foresee international judging becoming controversial.</p>
        <p>Gary Ream has been leading Olympic efforts on behalf of skateboarding. He is also president of the International Skateboarding Federation, a coalition of skateboarders representing more than 30 countries.</p>
        <p>''If you ask any skateboarder on the street, 'Do you want to be in the Olympic Games,' especially in this country, they would probably say, 'No,' '' Ream said. ''Because right off the bat, that's the coolest, easiest thing to say. And I would probably say that's the attitude of skateboarding in general.''</p>
        <p>But Ream believes skateboarding will wind up in the Olympics with or without the support of most skaters.</p>
        <p>Still, skateboarding in the Olympics is unlikely to sit well with the sport's more hard-core elements.</p>
        <p>''At the X Games they have Slim Jims and the Marines and stuff like that,'' said Jake Phelps, editor of the skateboarding magazine Thrasher. ''That is hogwash. I know the Olympics is going straight down that alley because they want some of that X Games cash.''</p>
        <p>A major boycott by skaters in 2012 seems unlikely, however.</p>
        <p>Olympic skateboarding would most likely feature the sport's vertical discipline, performed on massive halfpipe ramps like those featured in the X Games.</p>
        <p>''There are plenty of successful skaters that have made their careers almost exclusively by competing,'' Hawk wrote. ''These are the ones that will rise to the occasion when offered a chance to be Olympic athletes. The irony is that the naysayers whose livelihoods are based in the skateboard industry will end up benefiting from the newfound global interest.''</p>
        <p>ACTION SPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
