<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Summer of Love (and Rivalry, Too)</title>
    <meta content="l14frisco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854372"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/San Francisco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E1DA143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="524" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Summer of Love (and Rivalry, Too)</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In ''(Don't Go Back to) San Francisco'' (Op-Ed, June 9), Michael Walker contends that the San Francisco bands of the Summer of Love are remembered today, if at all, for their few hit singles, and that the Los Angeles neighborhood Laurel Canyon ''was the more evolved and influential destination that summer.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In ''(Don't Go Back to) San Francisco'' (Op-Ed, June 9), Michael Walker contends that the San Francisco bands of the Summer of Love are remembered today, if at all, for their few hit singles, and that the Los Angeles neighborhood Laurel Canyon ''was the more evolved and influential destination that summer.''</p>
        <p>But influence can't always be measured in commercial terms. San Francisco was the glorious laboratory out of which exploded psychedelic art, light shows and, of course, the very kind of communal concert experience that became the blueprint for Woodstock, which Mr. Walker himself calls a ''pop cultural landmark.''</p>
        <p>And who played at Woodstock, after all? San Francisco acts like the Jefferson Airplane, the Grateful Dead, Country Joe and the Fish, Santana and Janis Joplin did. Tellingly, Joni Mitchell, Laurel Canyon's resident queen, was urged to stay home by her agent, David Geffen. She would later write the hit song about the festival, but her disappointment has been well documented. In the end, as she knew, you had to be there.</p>
        <p>Laurel Canyon may have been a ''legendary neighborhood,'' but San Francisco was a whole other world.</p>
        <p>Andy Bart  Tarrytown, N.Y., June 10, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Of course Laurel Canyon was filled with talented musicians churning out No. 1 hits. The San Francisco sound was about ethos and sensibility, and its two root sources were the Beats and jazz (especially the post-bop modal variety). Mix these with early rock 'n' roll, a stirring, often shrouded and foggy landscape perched on the earth's edge, and a deep desire for the new, and you have something Los Angeles never had.</p>
        <p>Mitchell Wilson  Berkeley, Calif., June 10, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Michael Walker argues that bands from Laurel Canyon were more ''evolved and influential'' than San Francisco bands during the Summer of Love. Los Angeles did produce some great music during this period, but no city was home to more innovative musicians and promoters than San Francisco during the late 1960s.</p>
        <p>As a cultural icon who redefined the role of women in rock, can a person be more important than Janis Joplin? San Francisco's own Sly &amp; the Family Stone, who released their first album in 1967, became one of the most influential bands in music history. And one of the ''show-business novices'' who Mr. Walker says ran the San Francisco music scene was none other than Bill Graham.</p>
        <p>Michael Jenner  Vancouver, British Columbia  June 9, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Michael Walker cites Scott McKenzie's Summer of Love anthem ''San Francisco (Be Sure to Wear Flowers in Your Hair)'' as evidence that ''the real music'' of the era was produced in Los Angeles. When the song hit the airwaves in the spring of 1967, I and my fellow Haight-Ashbury hippies immediately recognized it for what it was: a syrupy, commercial, L.A. (indeed) exploitation of our precarious little psychedelic utopia.</p>
        <p>Of course the Haight was doomed, but McKenzie's song, ostensibly a celebration, was its expedited death knell. I still can't hear the thing without cringing.</p>
        <p>Dean Sluyter  Plainfield, N.J., June 9, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
