<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Winning Is Best Change That Els Can Make</title>
    <meta content="14golf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/sports/golf/14golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854470"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Els, Ernie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907EED8143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Winning Is Best Change That Els Can Make</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Winning Is Best Change That Els Can Make</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa., June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There have been small scars and deeper bruises in the career of Ernie Els, whether from a surgeon's blade or the heartbreak of 18 holes gone wrong.</p>
        <p>Three years ago, while in contention to win each of the four major championships, Els instead came away with nicks to his psyche. Two years ago, while on a sailing holiday in the Mediterranean, he tore the anterior cruciate ligament in his left knee while riding an inner tube.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the site where he won his first major tournament 13 years ago, Ernie Els is trying to come to terms with the dings to his mind and body.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There have been small scars and deeper bruises in the career of Ernie Els, whether from a surgeon's blade or the heartbreak of 18 holes gone wrong.</p>
        <p>Three years ago, while in contention to win each of the four major championships, Els instead came away with nicks to his psyche. Two years ago, while on a sailing holiday in the Mediterranean, he tore the anterior cruciate ligament in his left knee while riding an inner tube.</p>
        <p>''I've had it all, mate,'' Els, 37, said Tuesday. ''Legs, knees, fingers, wrists, nose, everything.''</p>
        <p>On the eve of the United States Open at Oakmont Country Club, where he won his first major 13 years ago, Els is trying to come to terms with the dings to his mind and body.</p>
        <p>Once a fixture among the best players in the world -- a fraternity that includes Tiger Woods, Phil Mickelson and Vijay Singh -- Els has been the first of the group to show signs of slipping. While Mickelson will begin Thursday's first round playing with an injured left wrist, Els is fighting through a slump that has left him without a victory on the PGA Tour for three years.</p>
        <p>Els has changed club manufacturers, agents and putting styles -- from the traditional grip to cross-handed. He has lived in Orlando, Fla., Wentworth, England, and Johannesburg, where he was born.</p>
        <p>But since rupturing his knee in July 2005, he has seen a downturn in his game that has been largely uninterrupted.</p>
        <p>Woods, who overcame his own left knee injury, though not as serious, after the 2002 season, said Tuesday: ''I think Ernie is probably one to admit that the injury is pretty significant. It happened on probably the wrong leg. If it happened on the right leg, he could get away with it. But the left leg is your impact leg, and a lot of torque goes through that area. It's pretty significant.''</p>
        <p>Woods, who has a friendly rivalry with Els, has kept tabs on Els's recovery -- and his struggles.</p>
        <p>''You've seen signs of Ernie starting to play a little bit better,'' Woods said. ''I know he switched his putting grip, and he's been putting better. Over all, you see the talent that he has, and I think anyone will admit that once he gets it going, that he can pretty much win any tournament.''</p>
        <p>If there is a course anywhere that could stir Els from his malaise, Oakmont might be it. He was 24 years old when he arrived here for the 1994 United States Open, a talented golfer from South Africa with an unhurried swing. In the searing heat, Els announced his presence on the world stage by defeating Colin Montgomerie and Loren Roberts in a playoff.</p>
        <p>Although Oakmont has lost about 5,000 trees since the 1994 championship, the spirit and sightlines of the course are unchanged, Els said. Late afternoon thunderstorms fell for a half-hour Wednesday, softening the 7,230-yard course.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't play any different, I would say, from '94,'' Els said. ''With the length they have put into the course, with new technology, we are basically playing the same shots from the tees and same irons into the greens.''</p>
        <p>Els's victory at Oakmont came three years before Woods won the Masters for his first major, four years before Singh won the P.G.A. Championship for his first major, and 10 years before Mickelson won the Masters for his first major. Els was among the first of the long hitters of the 1990s, a player that Johnny Miller on Tuesday recalled as being a ''power player at the top of his game with a great short game'' when he won at Oakmont.</p>
        <p>Although Els again displayed both traits in winning the United States Open at Congressional in 1997 and the British Open at Muirfield in 2002, the victories have mostly dried up.</p>
        <p>During his preparation for this year's championship at Oakmont, Els admitted to catching television highlights of his 1994 triumph on these same fairways and greens.</p>
        <p>He said he was surprised how much he had changed in 13 years -- he guessed that he had gained 25 pounds -- but he still recognized the golfer and wondered if the older version might be even better than the younger one.</p>
        <p>''I would say, through the years, I've improved a lot,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But whether he can shake loose another major championship is uncertain. Although he has several trophies and good memories, there are also tangible scars and those less visible.</p>
        <p>''It's amazing what a little bit of talent and a little bit of belief does,'' Els said. ''It was kind of funny looking at yourself then and where you think you are right now.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
