<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parade Officials Criticize Police Over Arrest Total</title>
    <meta content="14parade" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/nyregion/14parade.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854383"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Latin Kings</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Puerto Rican Coalition</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E7D9143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parade Officials Criticize Police Over Arrest Total</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Parade Officials Criticize Police Over Arrest Total</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The organizers of the Puerto Rican Day Parade criticized the police yesterday for arresting more than 200 people Sunday, many of them on charges of unlawful assembly.</p>
        <p>The organizers said that although they had not wanted gang members to march in the parade, they were concerned now that innocent bystanders might have been arrested as part of a police anti-gang effort.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The organizers of the Puerto Rican Day Parade criticized the police for arresting more than 200 people Sunday, many of them on charges of unlawful assembly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The organizers of the Puerto Rican Day Parade criticized the police yesterday for arresting more than 200 people Sunday, many of them on charges of unlawful assembly.</p>
        <p>The organizers said that although they had not wanted gang members to march in the parade, they were concerned now that innocent bystanders might have been arrested as part of a police anti-gang effort.</p>
        <p>''Something went terribly wrong on Sunday,'' Madelyn Lugo, chairwoman of the parade organization, said at a Midtown news conference. ''Dozens of lawfully assembled paradegoers were arrested, manhandled, denied their rights and forced to endure a night in jail.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Lugo said she had sent a letter to Raymond W. Kelly, the police commissioner, asking for a meeting to discuss what precautions the police had taken against wrongful arrests.</p>
        <p>She said that parade organizers had barred members of the Latin Kings gang from marching this year, though they had marched in past parades, and that the organizers had agreed that the police should arrest gang members who tried to jump over barricades and join the parade without authorization.</p>
        <p>Still, she said, the organizers were shocked by the outcome.</p>
        <p>Paul J. Browne, a spokesman for the Police Department, said yesterday that the commissioner had not yet received Ms. Lugo's letter, so he could not comment on whether there would be a meeting.</p>
        <p>''I'll look to see if there's any validity to the complaints, but the notion that the police were engaged in wholesale arrests of innocent bystanders is just false,'' Mr. Browne said.</p>
        <p>At the news conference, the parade organizers introduced Thomas Scull, 18, a high school senior who wore sneakers at the parade in black and yellow, the Latin Kings colors, and was arrested. The police complaint accused him of making hand signals associated with the Latin Kings. He said that he was not a gang member, and that the police had focused on him because of his sneakers.</p>
        <p>''Now I can't wear them because they are gang colors,'' said Mr. Scull, a student at West Side High School in Manhattan. He was arrested on Sunday at 2:30 p.m., and said he spent the night in jail and was released at about 8:30 p.m. on Monday. He complained that his wrist was still sore from being handcuffed.</p>
        <p>Manuel Mirabal, president of the National Puerto Rican Coalition, said pointedly at the news conference that although he ''wore a yellow tie at the parade,'' he was not arrested.</p>
        <p>Mr. Browne provided information suggesting that at least one arrested paradegoer was not as innocent as he had claimed. He said officials believe that a man who had identified himself to a reporter on Monday as a 55-year-old postal worker from New Jersey who was wrongfully arrested near 47th Street and Fifth Avenue was actually 52 and was charged with lewd behavior at 54th Street.</p>
        <p>No one answered the telephone yesterday at the home of the man Mr. Browne named, so he could not be asked about the police complaint.</p>
        <p>Norman Siegel, a civil liberties lawyer, said yesterday that he had been contacted by the Justice Committee, a Latin civil rights group, that said it was representing more than 150 of those arrested.</p>
        <p>Mr. Siegel said he doubted that arresting people for unlawful assembly would stand up in court.</p>
        <p>''It's not applicable,'' he said. ''In fact, people were gathering for a lawful assembly because there was a parade. I think it will be extremely difficult for the Police Department to prove unlawful assembly given the facts that have been made public at this point.''</p>
        <p>Barbara Thompson, a spokeswoman for the Manhattan district attorney, Robert M. Morgenthau, said her office had drafted 161 complaints, primarily for unlawful assembly.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Scull's case, the criminal complaint charges him with unlawful assembly and disorderly conduct. It says that Police Officer Eric Andreoli, of the gang unit in Manhattan, observed him with 16 other people ''yelling, screaming, obstructing pedestrian traffic.''</p>
        <p>The complaint continues, ''Deponent observed the defendants and said others displaying hand signals, which deponent knows from deponent's training and experience to be known gang signs for the Latin Kings.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
