<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kitchen Tales</title>
    <meta content="14kitchen.intro" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854326"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E1DB143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="3340" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kitchen Tales</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PENELOPE GREEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE American kitchen has been an aspirational space ever since electricity and post-World War I prosperity commingled in a nifty new appliance called the refrigerator. ''There are scads of ads from the 1920s showing people in tuxedos and evening gowns literally adoring their fridge,'' said Victoria Matranga, a historian of industrial design and the design programs coordinator at the International Housewares Association near Chicago. Then as now, Ms. Matranga said, owning the right appliance flagged your social status by showing off your understanding of technology and progress, not to mention your prowess as a breadwinner. The kitchen has also long been a very personal space, not just a place where we tell stories about who we are, but a highly functional theater for those stories (even if the stories have nothing to do with the preparation of food).</p>
        <p>Highly attuned to these fundamentals, the makers of appliances are well aware of how much the kitchen means to their customers, and so pour money and manpower into ethnographic, human science and brand identity research in an effort to learn more. (Money well spent, it seems: Americans forked over more than $15 billion on kitchen appliances last year, a 21 percent increase over the year before, according to the NPD Group, a market research firm.) This observational research is how LG learned that people were trying to jam their sports water bottles into fridge-door water dispensers and finding the standard cavity too small, leading the company to make dispensers in its new refrigerators more than 11 inches tall, the largest in the industry. And the same kind of research explains why Amana makes an oven with indented racks: its researchers noted a disturbing tendency of some bakers to scald their forearms when reaching deep in an oven to retrieve pans set at the back. Observing the human animal in its native habitat (as well as in company labs carefully constructed to look like home), corporate researchers study not only how many times these humans open their refrigerators (55 times a day, according to General Electric) and what might be the most intuitive and comfortable shape for their dishwasher handle, but how that dishwasher or refrigerator supports their idea of themselves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE American kitchen has been an aspirational space ever since electricity and post-World War I prosperity commingled in a nifty new appliance called the refrigerator. ''There are scads of ads from the 1920s showing people in tuxedos and evening gowns literally adoring their fridge,'' said Victoria Matranga, a historian of industrial design and the design programs coordinator at the International Housewares Association near Chicago. Then as now, Ms. Matranga said, owning the right appliance flagged your social status by showing off your understanding of technology and progress, not to mention your prowess as a breadwinner. The kitchen has also long been a very personal space, not just a place where we tell stories about who we are, but a highly functional theater for those stories (even if the stories have nothing to do with the preparation of food).</p>
        <p>Highly attuned to these fundamentals, the makers of appliances are well aware of how much the kitchen means to their customers, and so pour money and manpower into ethnographic, human science and brand identity research in an effort to learn more. (Money well spent, it seems: Americans forked over more than $15 billion on kitchen appliances last year, a 21 percent increase over the year before, according to the NPD Group, a market research firm.) This observational research is how LG learned that people were trying to jam their sports water bottles into fridge-door water dispensers and finding the standard cavity too small, leading the company to make dispensers in its new refrigerators more than 11 inches tall, the largest in the industry. And the same kind of research explains why Amana makes an oven with indented racks: its researchers noted a disturbing tendency of some bakers to scald their forearms when reaching deep in an oven to retrieve pans set at the back. Observing the human animal in its native habitat (as well as in company labs carefully constructed to look like home), corporate researchers study not only how many times these humans open their refrigerators (55 times a day, according to General Electric) and what might be the most intuitive and comfortable shape for their dishwasher handle, but how that dishwasher or refrigerator supports their idea of themselves.</p>
        <p>Of course, from all this energy and effort what finally accrues to a company is just an average: a guess at what the largest number of folks have in common when it comes to kitchen behaviors, quibbles and desires. The truth is that every kitchen has its own particular lesson, its own story, and its own author. Following are the stories of six of them, in neighborhoods from Chelsea to Crown Heights, Red Hook to Westchester. What corporate anthropologist would have envisioned a setup as complicated as three generations of women running a household of six from a suburban kitchen where curried goat is a specialty? Or as arcane as a bright white research lab for a food historian investigating ancient Roman cuisine? Or as visually toothsome as an artist's kitchen crafted from found objects?</p>
        <p>What does it all mean? The food historian pondered the question for himself. ''That's a bit like asking a man to subject himself to his own Freudian analysis,'' he said, and then ventured this answer: ''I guess I am Lear and the kitchen is my heath, wherein I strive to outscorn the to-and-fro conflicting wind and rain.''</p>
        <p>When the Real Estate Market Sizzles, the Oven Stays Cold</p>
        <p>THE Wolf oven in this open kitchen with cherry wood veneer cabinets still has the plastic wrapping on its shelves, though its owner, Dennis Mangone, 47, has lived here for two years. But the kitchen has uses besides cooking.</p>
        <p>Standing at a black Corian island, Mr. Mangone, a senior vice president at the Corcoran Group, can spread out offering plans; field offers on his BlackBerry, laptop and two cellphones (one for European calls, one for domestic ones); and, for refreshment, glance up Fourth Avenue to the MetLife Building.</p>
        <p>It's a power perch, stage left of the living room of his 2,000-square-foot condo on the eighth floor of the green glass tower at Astor Place designed by Gwathmey Siegel &amp; Associates Architects. Mr. Mangone never turned on the oven in his last two kitchens either, at the Trump World Tower at United Nations Plaza and at the Mandarin Oriental at the Time Warner Center. The latter came with room service. ''Boy, do I miss that,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''It's not that I'm antifood or against preparing it,'' he said, ''or that I don't know how. It's that this part of my life is all about working.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mangone said he had 14 exclusive listings in buildings from Central Park to SoHo, 30 (multimillion-dollar) apartments in contract, and an expectation of bringing in $200 million in gross commissions by the end of the year. What this kitchen gives Mr. Mangone, who has a taste for Prada suits and Armani furniture, is aesthetic pleasure and surfaces on which to work. ''The counter is very easy to write on,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Next month Mr. Mangone will move into yet another trophy condo -- at 40 Bond, Ian Schrager's latest brand extension, designed by Herzog &amp; de Meuron -- with another trophy kitchen, designed by John Pawson, the English minimalist. Mr. Pawson has made the place handle- and object-free. The kitchen is hidden behind sliding panels of oiled maple. ''You need a search team to find out what's behind any of the doors,'' Mr. Mangone said. ''Actually, you need a search team to find the doors.''</p>
        <p>The Only Heat Is From Hot Sauce</p>
        <p>JILL PETTIJOHN, a raw-food cook and advocate, has earned a bit of fame in the fashion world, both as Donna Karan's personal chef and as the purveyor of five-day juice fasts, the juices for which are delivered daily to winter-swollen fashion editors from her raw-food restaurant in Red Hook, Brooklyn. She may have been responsible for a rash of public non-eating this spring, reckoned Kate Betts, editor of Time Style &amp; Design magazine. Ms. Betts and her husband spent a week sipping Ms. Pettijohn's juices and then pretending to eat at her many meal-centered business and social functions. ''I even saw men pushing their food around their plates,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The kitchen in Ms. Pettijohn's new loft, in a converted cotton warehouse overlooking New York Harbor, will see plenty of food preparation, but very little cooking. Her meals -- hijiki salad, barely steamed haricots verts, lots of smoothies -- are constructed (or deconstructed in a blender) rather than sautéed, boiled or braised. Although the developer of this property added typical flourishes, including a set of G.E. Monogram stainless steel appliances, a kitchen island and lots of cabinet space, Ms. Pettijohn will be using little of it. She relies on knives, a blender and an array of pots for brief steaming. ''My last oven I used for storage,'' she said, ''but I don't need any more storage here. The microwave, well, it's good for warming up heating pads.''</p>
        <p>Gentle and laconic, like many born below the 10th parallel -- she is from New Zealand -- Ms. Pettijohn, 50, seems an unlikely diet guru. But she has convictions, and if pressed to deliver a manifesto, she said, it would describe her method of food preparation as ''making living food'' -- food that isn't processed -- as well as ''kindly cooked food, which means I cook it just enough to bring out the flavors and the best nutritional benefit without destroying the enzymes.'' Her cabinets are stocked with myriad powders and extracts, packaged in jars, bags and little dropper-top bottles, suggesting medicine more than food.</p>
        <p>Spirulina (a k a green algae) and three kinds of salt live in a cabinet to the left of the stove. There's pink Himalayan salt, Celtic sea salt and salt with kelp in it. Also a mortar and pestle for grinding down large chunks. As for seating, there are no bar stools, nor are there dining chairs or a table anywhere in the apartment. Instead, Ms. Pettijohn and her guests might sit on a wicker ''pouf'' at a table that's about dachshund height, or forego even the pouf to sit cross-legged on the floor.</p>
        <p>The Artist's Kitchen, Recycled and Curated</p>
        <p>SIMONE LEIGH, 46, lives in Crown Heights, Brooklyn, on the second floor of a squat brick building that was once a garage for Ebbets Field. Ms. Leigh is an artist who makes swollen and lovely ceramic objects -- eggs, breasts, missiles, plantains -- that she assembles into large installations about race, history and gender.</p>
        <p>Her kitchen is something of an installation, too, which she put together using found and bought objects with shapes and surfaces that pleased her. She said she likes patinas that build up over time, old objects that look new and anything from the 1920s or the 1950s, because the shapes of those eras remind her of both African vessels and the Jetsons.</p>
        <p>Roughly 8 by 8 feet, the kitchen takes its shape from the way Ms. Leigh places its furniture. ''It's a flexible space,'' she said. ''I'm constantly reassembling and unassembling it.''</p>
        <p>Last week, two of her Wedgwood-blue clay plantains were tucked between a rocket-shape ice bucket and a green and blue plastic teapot from Senegal on the 1950s ceramic hutch that is her kitchen counter, which she bought at Moon River Chattel, a vintage store in Williamsburg.</p>
        <p>The double porcelain sink from the 1920s was free, from a building going co-op in Sunset Park. So was the enamel Royal Rose stove, which she found on the street one day and had recalibrated. ''Isn't it an elegant little object?'' she said, gazing fondly at it. ''The kitchen looks this way by necessity,'' she added, ''because I could never afford to buy all these things.''</p>
        <p>The stove is missing all its burner knobs. Ms. Leigh can't find the distinctive red replacements, so she turns it on with pliers to cook ''basic things like chicken or asparagus,'' she said, describing herself as a ''noncook.'' She added: ''I don't embellish food.''</p>
        <p>Next to the sink, there's a little glass-and-wood curio cabinet upon which sits a huge glass jar shaped like an acorn squash, filled with dog food. Inside, the cabinet is filled with small mirrored disco balls, hundreds of fake fingernails, tile samples, glass bottles shaped like breasts, silver ponytail holders and four jars of mica, all of which will find their way into sculptures, Ms. Leigh said.</p>
        <p>The dog food is for Kafka, a 4-year-old Tibetan terrier named by Ms. Leigh's 10-year-old daughter, Zenobia. ''He is completely un-Kafka-esque, and Zenobia has never heard of Kafka,'' Ms. Leigh said. ''It was just on the list of doggy names. Her other choice was Skippy, and I couldn't live with that.''</p>
        <p>Multigenerational Cooking</p>
        <p>TEN years ago, right after the birth of Paulette Mullings-Bradnock's son Reginald, her mother came to visit from Kingston, Jamaica.</p>
        <p>''She saw our lifestyle, the going to work at 7 a.m. and not coming home until 8 at night,'' said Ms. Mullings-Bradnock, 46, who was born in Jamaica and is an audit director at AIG, the financial services company in Manhattan; her husband, Howard, is a gastroenterologist with a practice in Queens.</p>
        <p>''She said, 'This is no way to raise your kids.' She said, 'I'm staying, are you O.K. with that?' We were living in a really small house in Yonkers then, but I said yes. It's our Caribbean culture, that your elders live with you and care for the kids. It's how we were brought up.''</p>
        <p>And it is in the family's kitchen that this dynamic finds its fullest expression. Ms. Mullings-Bradnock was raised and fed by her great-grandmother in Kingston, she said, while her mother, Edith Crooks, now 66, worked. ''And the deal is, mom fully expects me to do the same for my kids,'' Ms. Mullings-Bradnock said.</p>
        <p>In 2001, the family, including Ms. Crooks, moved into a huge, custom-built brick house in a new development in Ardsley, N.Y., near Dobbs Ferry. There are six bedrooms, a living room, a dining room and a swimming pool, but the hub -- the house's white-hot center -- is the kitchen-family room. This female-ruled kingdom, with its cherry cabinets and black granite, was designed by Mr. Bradnock; Ms. Mullings-Bradnock was traveling at the time. ''Howard has been known to use it,'' she said. ''He has cleaned a dish or two.'' His only mistake, said Ms. Mullings-Bradnock, who is 5 feet 8 inches tall, was the height of the range hood. ''It's too low and I always hit my head on it.''</p>
        <p>In any case, Ms. Crooks broke in with a grin, ''I'm mostly in charge. But Paulette has an iron hand on weekends.''</p>
        <p>The kitchen has a square center island, a skylight and other familiar suburban luxuries like vast amounts of counter and cabinet space and a walk-in pantry, but its flavor is particularly Jamaican. There is a nest of Dutch ovens under the range, brought from the island to stew oxtail and curried goat. Ms. Crooks keeps frozen goat meat, curried goat and spare ribs in the freezer of the Sub-Zero, along with chopped callaloo greens, which Ms. Crooks grows in the backyard, and red snapper and oxtail, which she buys at a Korean market in the Bronx every two weeks. (Ms. Mullings-Bradnock said a friend likes to tease: ''What? You can't get goat meat in Westchester?'') The kitchen is big enough to accommodate the whole family, which now includes Gwendolyn Martin, 82, Ms. Mullings-Bradnock's great-aunt, who moved in a few months ago and is the designated salad maker.</p>
        <p>Each weekday, starting at about 2 p.m., Ms. Crooks makes a dinner that embraces everyone's tastes -- catering to Reginald's preference for barbecued chicken, for example, and his sister, Taylor's, for macaroni and cheese -- and that can stay warm on the stove top for hours. One night last week, five Pyrex dishes waited for the onslaught. Mrs. Martin is the first shift, eating at about 5:30 p.m., followed by Taylor and Reginald, who come home from sports at 6, and the final shift might find Mr. Bradnock trailing in for his meal at 11 p.m. ''It's not so tidy,'' said Ms. Crooks, sweeping her hands over spotless counters and orderly cabinets. ''But it's a human kitchen. When I cook, it comes from the heart.''</p>
        <p>A Classico-Minimalist</p>
        <p>THERE were no turtle rumps, dormice or sows' vulvas in the freezer of Jesse Browner's Chelsea kitchen recently, but there was boar meat, and his pantry -- a swell pullout number hidden in a cabinet -- held a whiffy bottle of garum, a fish-infused oil that smells something like a restaurant's Dumpster on a really hot day.</p>
        <p>Mr. Browner is the author of ''The Uncertain Hour,'' a new novel about the last meal of the Roman satirist Petronius, which -- as Mr. Browner imagines it -- included all of the above ingredients and then some. For some time now, Mr. Browner, 46, a food historian and translator, has been investigating ancient Roman haute cuisine, which was marked, he said, by the use of strange body parts, sharp seasonings like coriander and cumin, and spices like rue, pennyroyal and lovage, as well as garum, which he described cheerfully as ''salted and fermented fish guts'' while brandishing the little bottle of tobacco-colored oil.</p>
        <p>Accused of a plot to murder the Emperor Nero, Petronius, Nero's adviser on all things luxurious and the writer of the ''Satyricon,'' was allowed to be the architect of his own punishment (death by suicide) and the author of his last meal. This idea -- the attempt at a perfectly crafted event -- is one that fascinates Mr. Browner, who sees all ''these unbelievable neuroses at work'' in the preparation of food, at least the passionate form that he practices.</p>
        <p>''It's complicated,'' he said, ''and quite pessimistic and tied to all sorts of character flaws and childhood traumas.'' Mr. Browner likes to say that next to writing, cooking is as close as one can get to creating a perfect world. ''Everything in a meal is here because I brought it here,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He designed his all-white kitchen, with the help of an architect friend, Laura Kurgan, in support of that idea of perfection. It is the main event of the West 15th Street loft where Mr. Browner lives with his wife, Judith Clain, a book editor, and their two daughters, and the first thing you see when you walk in the door.</p>
        <p>What you won't see is a dish rack, overhead cabinets, Mr. Browner's extensive armory of tools or much of anything on the counters, even when he is presenting, as he did a few weeks ago, a four-course Roman banquet for 12. He prefers not to cook in front of guests, he said: ''I want to maintain the sense of magic.''</p>
        <p>Above the Store, a Little R&amp;D</p>
        <p>ROMANA RAFFETTO met her husband, Gino, at a cafe on West Fourth Street just a few weeks after she arrived in New York in 1957; she had come by ship, having traveled from her hometown of Asolo, just outside Venice.</p>
        <p>Gino Raffetto was a son of Marcello Raffetto, originally from Genoa, who had been running his pasta business from a storefront in a small brick building he owned on Houston Street near Macdougal since 1906.</p>
        <p>After they were married, the younger Mr. Raffetto and his wife moved to a railroad-style apartment above his father's store. (Gino, who had been a banker, took over the shop with a cousin in the mid-1970s.)</p>
        <p>The apartment was ''just terrible,'' Mrs. Raffetto said recently, and they renovated it in 1974, adding a bedroom for their son Richard, now 46, and updating the kitchen. They carved out a tiny space that today still seems to represent an ergonomic ideal for Mrs. Raffetto, 74, who can pivot from stove to sink to fridge without taking a step.</p>
        <p>''When we did this, I was very happy,'' she said. ''Today, it is still perfect, my little kitchen. I don't like anybody to come in when I'm cooking, and look, I can reach everything. I wouldn't change a thing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Raffetto put up the cabinets himself. Mrs. Raffetto used her shoulders to steady them -- she demonstrated, bending down and inclining one shoulder -- while he screwed each one to the wall.</p>
        <p>Custom touches include a deep sink that can hold a night's worth of dishes and pots. There is no dishwasher. ''Who needs them?'' Mrs. Raffetto said, flicking a hand dismissively. ''It's like washing dishes twice, and then putting them away twice.''</p>
        <p>When Gino's cousin died in 1978, Mrs. Raffetto took her place alongside her husband at the store. She's still working downstairs, most days. Their son Andrew, who, with his brother, Richard, is also in the family business, calls the kitchen upstairs ''our R and D department.''</p>
        <p>Gino Raffetto died last year. His picture has pride of place on a broad, dark-stained wood cabinet that is set perpendicular to the kitchen and holds liquor, the ''good'' dishes and a television set. These days, in the evenings, Mrs. Raffetto said, she likes to light the candle that sits next to her husband's picture. ''It keeps me company,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Last week, Mrs. Raffetto opened her freezer door (on the outside is a photo gallery of grandchildren) to reveal herbs and sliced vegetables in plastic bags and tubs of Parmesan. In the fridge below was a cook's delight: shelves stuffed to overflowing with mushrooms; golden raisins; candied flowers, citron and candied cherries; bags of nuts; milk; cream; butter; and more.</p>
        <p>''With Gino gone, I don't cook like I used to,'' she said apologetically. ''There's not much here.''</p>
        <p>A corner outside the kitchen is a ''pantry,'' with a large wooden cutting board tucked behind the cereal boxes. Mrs. Raffetto uses it to roll dough for pies and pasta, she said, by pulling it out onto the round dining table.</p>
        <p>Above the ''pantry'' is a black-and-white photograph of a dandelion gone to seed. It was a gift from ''what's-his-name, the fashion photographer,'' she said, meaning Irving Penn (whose secretary, she said, is a loyal Raffetto's customer).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
