<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stormy Weather for Soloists As Battles Rage All Around</title>
    <meta content="14reed" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/arts/music/14reed.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854318"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Dizzy's</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Reed, Eric</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Tyner, McCoy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E2DB143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="550" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stormy Weather for Soloists As Battles Rage All Around</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Stormy Weather for Soloists as Battles Rage All Around</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN RATLIFF</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When a jazz club audience completely rolls over for a band and gives it full license, the band can do extraordinary things -- instinctive, daring, almost unreasonable things.</p>
        <p>This is what happened with the pianist Eric Reed's new group at Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola on Tuesday night: The crowd was already feeling excitable, and the band fed off that feeling, shooting back with force.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When a jazz club audience completely rolls over for a band and gives it full license, the band can do extraordinary things  instinctive, daring, almost unreasonable things.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When a jazz club audience completely rolls over for a band and gives it full license, the band can do extraordinary things -- instinctive, daring, almost unreasonable things.</p>
        <p>This is what happened with the pianist Eric Reed's new group at Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola on Tuesday night: The crowd was already feeling excitable, and the band fed off that feeling, shooting back with force.</p>
        <p>The set was, in one sense, your basic, modern small-group post-bop, strings-of-solos and all. But form doesn't determine everything. Mr. Reed is an intensely upbeat presence. Where most jazz pianists after McCoy Tyner and Herbie Hancock grew introspective, he has gone the other way, toward harder work with the right hand and bright harmonies.</p>
        <p>His latest band is a quintet with two tenor saxophones, a setup with some pedigree but perhaps not enough respect. You think of Sonny Rollins and John Coltrane in ''Tenor Madness'' from 1956 or Johnny Griffin and Eddie Lockjaw Davis's stormy pair-ups from the early '60s, and you think of battles. If anyone can create a platform for benign competition, it's Mr. Reed. But there are other things going on here too.</p>
        <p>The two saxophonists are Seamus Blake and Stacy Dillard. Mr. Blake has been around New York since the early '90s, working with the drummer Victor Lewis and figuring out his own kind of jazz-rock with his band, the Bloomdaddies; his playing has cheer, momentum and a kind of happy bluster.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dillard arrived much more recently, and he sounds like the next step forward. On Tuesday his playing was fast and technically advanced, with a sure tone and modest projection (he was the quieter of the two players); he could make a long, fast phrase with a lot of well-placed notes sweep along like a single breath. He sounds natural, self-possessed even at high speeds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dillard and Mr. Blake were working off each other's energy, one following the other, and it worked well enough. But at the peak of one piece (Blue Mitchell's calypso ''Fungii Mama''), they improvised simultaneously, soloing in the same pitch area to make a dense mash of sound. It was a simple enough idea that didn't go on for very long -- no solo went on for very long, all through the set -- but an extremely powerful one.</p>
        <p>At the same time, though, Mr. Reed and his drummer, Willie Jones, were locking in furiously, threatening to take the focus off the saxophonists. People tend to think that the solos are the meat of a jazz gig, where the real ideas arrive, but here there was a fantastic tension between the power of the front line and the power of the rhythm section. (Marco Panascia was the bassist.)</p>
        <p>Working in fast tempos (especially in Pat Metheny's ''Elucidation,'' with chord changes every other beat), the pianist and drummer cranked up their energy almost perversely high, adding tiny phrases and fills but never releasing control of the hard swing.</p>
        <p>And they didn't let up. Through the last piece, Herbie Hancock's ''Eye of the Hurricane,'' the set didn't reach a peak and then sag; it just kept getting more tense.</p>
        <p>The Eric Reed Quintet performs through Sunday at Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway; (212) 258-9595 or jalc.org.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
