<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Showcasing His Growth, Parker Quiets His Critics</title>
    <meta content="14nba" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/sports/basketball/14nba.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854440"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/San Antonio Spurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">San Antonio Spurs</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Cleveland Cavaliers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Parker, Tony</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E4D8143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="851" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Showcasing His Growth, Parker Quiets His Critics</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Showcasing His Growth, Parker Quiets His Critics</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <dateline>CLEVELAND, June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Tony Parker talked about growing pains with a vindicated grin Wednesday, he was not talking about the agony that has been LeBron James's first N.B.A. finals.</p>
        <p>Nor was Parker referring to the reaction that the few television viewers might have had from the Spurs' hard-to-watch 75-72 victory against the Cleveland Cavaliers on Tuesday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In six seasons, Tony Parker has overcome the doubts of his coach, of the team’s franchise player and of the front office and brought the Spurs within one victory of a third N.B.A. title in five years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Tony Parker talked about growing pains with a vindicated grin Wednesday, he was not talking about the agony that has been LeBron James's first N.B.A. finals.</p>
        <p>Nor was Parker referring to the reaction that the few television viewers might have had from the Spurs' hard-to-watch 75-72 victory against the Cleveland Cavaliers on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>Instead, Parker, the San Antonio Spurs' 25-year-old point guard from France, was acknowledging his own story. In six seasons, Parker has overcome the doubts of his coach, of the team's franchise player and of the front office and brought the Spurs within one victory of a third N.B.A. title in five years. He also has emerged as the leading contender for the series' most valuable player award.</p>
        <p>No longer known just for the company he keeps -- fiancée Eva Longoria or the three-time finals M.V.P. Tim Duncan -- Parker has become the most improved player on a team that celebrates consistency above all.</p>
        <p>''His graph is like this,'' P. J. Carlesimo, a Spurs assistant coach, said Wednesday, pointing diagonally into the rafters of the Quicken Loans Arena where no championship banners hung. ''It's not easy to get better when you're already an All-Star. He gets better every year. He's better now than a month ago.''</p>
        <p>So, too, are the Spurs.</p>
        <p>Despite the eyesore of Game 3, the Spurs snuffed the Cavaliers because of Bruce Bowen's continued defensive tyranny against James and because Parker led his team in scoring for the third consecutive game. He also sank a clutch 3-pointer, as if he were Robert Horry.</p>
        <p>Parker knew that Coach Gregg Popovich was screaming for him not to take such a shot. Parker could joke about it a day later because he made the 3-pointer. Four years ago, though, Parker wondered when the vein-popping criticism from his coach would ever stop.</p>
        <p>''Coach Pop was really, really hard on me, always trying to push me and looking for perfection,'' Parker said. ''I thought I was doing pretty good, being 21, but it was never enough. Sometimes I felt like it wasn't fair, all the criticism.''</p>
        <p>After Parker won his first title in his second season (2003), the Spurs fiercely recruited the Nets' Jason Kidd. ''It's hard to accept because I felt like I was the best point guard for that team,'' Parker said.</p>
        <p>Parker expressed his displeasure publicly in July 2003, which did not please Spurs officials but drew their respect. Resilient to the physical and mental pressure Popovich and his teammates applied in his first three years, Parker won another title in 2005, in the shadows of Duncan and Manu Ginóbili.</p>
        <p>Last season, Parker reconstructed his mid-range jumper with the assistant coach Chip Engellend, displaying the work ethic and results that earned Popovich's respect.</p>
        <p>''I think the most telling thing is the trust that Pop has in Tony and has developed in him,'' R. C. Buford, the Spurs' general manager, said Wednesday. ''At one point, that was a relationship dominated by Pop, and now there is a mutual respect, a synergy that doesn't require domination as much.''</p>
        <p>Parker calls it a ''father-son relationship,'' adding, ''Sometimes I thought he was crazy, but it made me a great player.''</p>
        <p>As for his being crazy, Popovich smiled and said: ''He's very accurate, he's honest and he's wonderful. He's done a great job.''</p>
        <p>Popovich called Parker the greatest guard finisher since Rod Strickland. But by adding that jumper to his tear-drop runner and his blinding speed, Parker has become an all-around offensive threat, averaging 24.6 points in the finals.</p>
        <p>These Spurs are known for their workaday success, embodied by the elegant, fundamental play of Duncan and the gritty defense of the formerly-undrafted Bowen. With five seconds remaining in Game 3, James attempted a game-tying 3-pointer. Replays showed Bowen grabbing James from behind before the shot. No foul was called.</p>
        <p>''I don't know. Did the official blow the whistle?'' Bowen said with a sly grin.</p>
        <p>''Definitely I thought there was contact,'' James said Wednesday. ''But we don't want to make that as an excuse of why we lost the game. We had opportunities where we could have made shots before that.''</p>
        <p>James could only marvel at the dominance of the Spurs, who are seeking their fourth title in nine seasons. ''They don't have the greatest athletes in the world, they don't have the greatest shooters in the world, but they have probably the greatest team in the world and that's what this sport is all about,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Spurs have their own focus as Popovich reminded his players Wednesday. Parker was surrounded by French reporters when Popovich walked out of his news conference and shouted playfully to Parker to stop talking.</p>
        <p>''Hey, we've still got another game to play!'' Popovich said. ''And then, if we lose, another game after that. And maybe another game after that.''</p>
        <p>''I know, I know,'' Parker shouted back, shaking him off as he did those early growing pains.</p>
        <p>''I think I will never be at that point today if I didn't go through all of that,'' Parker said. ''Now, I'm very happy where I'm at.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
