<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Mrs. Giuliani, Not the Usual Campaign Trail for a Candidate's Wife</title>
    <meta content="14judith" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/us/politics/14judith.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854450"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E2D8143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Mrs. Giuliani, Not the Usual Campaign Trail for a Candidate's Wife</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Mrs. Giuliani, Not the Usual Campaign Trail for a Candidate’s Wife</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC SANTORA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Santora, Marc</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three months ago, as Rudolph W. Giuliani was starting his quest for the Republican nomination, his campaign sought to introduce the political world to his third wife, Judith, having her speak at a fund-raiser in New York, while Mr. Giuliani suggested on national television that his wife might someday even sit in on cabinet meetings.</p>
        <p>Then came a flood of negative press: that she was responsible for Mr. Giuliani's estrangement from his children, that she had been married twice before and that a company she once worked for killed puppies while conducting research. That led Mr. Giuliani, who once said his wife would play a forward role in his political life, to plead with reporters to ''show a little decency'' with regards to Mrs. Giuliani.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rudolph W. Giuliani’s wife, Judith, has mainly been out of the glare of the press, focusing on fund-raising and other private functions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three months ago, as Rudolph W. Giuliani was starting his quest for the Republican nomination, his campaign sought to introduce the political world to his third wife, Judith, having her speak at a fund-raiser in New York, while Mr. Giuliani suggested on national television that his wife might someday even sit in on cabinet meetings.</p>
        <p>Then came a flood of negative press: that she was responsible for Mr. Giuliani's estrangement from his children, that she had been married twice before and that a company she once worked for killed puppies while conducting research. That led Mr. Giuliani, who once said his wife would play a forward role in his political life, to plead with reporters to ''show a little decency'' with regards to Mrs. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>Since then, Mrs. Giuliani has kept a low profile on the campaign trail even as her husband has been stepping up his appearances around the nation. When she is traveling with Mr. Giuliani around the country, she is rarely seen with him at campaign events, even as his opponents highlight their families.</p>
        <p>At the Lincoln Day dinner in Iowa this April, for instance, Mitt Romney tightly gripped the hand of his wife, Ann, as they mingled with the crowd, never letting go even as he shook the hands of supporters with his free hand. When he spoke that night, he talked about his grandchildren and brought his wife and one son on stage to join him.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Giuliani was not there.</p>
        <p>Associates say that Mrs. Giuliani, after initially being stung by the harshness of the attacks, is only now regaining her confidence and has been increasingly working on her husband's behalf. Her role has mainly been out of the glare of the press, focusing on fund-raising and other private functions.</p>
        <p>The campaign maintains that there is no grand plan to reintroduce her. The hope is that, after the rough start, the public can become familiar with her gradually.</p>
        <p>Paul Costello, who worked as Kitty Dukakis's press secretary and has advised first ladies, said that the campaign had been too defensive in introducing Mrs. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>''I think the most important thing they can do is introduce her in a natural way,'' Mr. Costello said. ''The way she was introduced last time was sort of unusual and kind of odd.''</p>
        <p>He said that the tabloid newspaper environment of New York posed particular risks but that Mr. Giuliani did not help matters when he suggested to Barbara Walters that his wife could sit in on cabinet meetings.</p>
        <p>''It is not the first message that a campaign wants to get out there,'' Mr. Costello said.</p>
        <p>Associates of Mrs. Giuliani say she has recently been gingerly stepping back into the limelight, pointing to her appearance at a charity event Sunday night in New York for Laniado Hospital in Netanya, Israel.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Yitzchok Waldman, executive vice president of the American Friends of Laniado Hospital, said that organizers of the event had originally invited Mr. Giuliani, but that when he could not come, they extended the invitation to his wife.</p>
        <p>''A big percentage of the people there did not know her,'' Rabbi Waldman said.</p>
        <p>Many of those who had heard of her, he said, knew only the negative things they had read.</p>
        <p>Some people were so concerned before the event that they approached Rabbi Waldman to tell him they might want another speaker.</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Giuliani, he said, put the crowd at ease from the moment she arrived at their gathering, at the Marriott Marquis.</p>
        <p>''She changed the impression of everyone in that room,'' he said, relating how she told an emotional story -- choking back tears -- about comforting a suicide bomb survivor in Jerusalem. ''She was not this mean-spirited woman she had been made out to be.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Giuliani, who gained experience in fund-raising while working for Changing Our World, which raises money for nonprofit groups, is also playing an increasingly active role in helping the campaign raise cash. She helped Candace Stark, a longtime player in the New York political scene, organize a fund-raiser, which was held on Monday night.</p>
        <p>Michael McKeon, a campaign spokesman, said Mrs. Giuliani understood that politics could be rough but was ready to play an active role in the campaign.</p>
        <p>''We are comfortable with the balance that we have struck,'' Mr. McKeon said.</p>
        <p>In the future, he said, Mrs. Giuliani will be with her husband on the campaign trail when it seems as if she can be a help and at other times she will be behind the scenes.</p>
        <p>''Her primary role,'' he said, ''is to be supportive to the mayor.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
