<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Battle Over Math in New Jersey Drives Off a New Schools Chief</title>
    <meta content="14math" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/nyregion/14math.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854421"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D8143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1426" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Battle Over Math in New Jersey Drives Off a New Schools Chief</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Battle Over Math in New Jersey Drives Off a New Schools Chief</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WINNIE HU</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Parents, some involved in a campaign against the math teaching in the highly regarded Ridgewood, N.J., school district, were to have met the new superintendent at a reception last Monday night.</p>
        <p>But the reception was abruptly canceled, leaving the school board president to explain that the superintendent, scheduled to begin on July 1 after a nine-month search costing more than $20,000, had backed out, largely because of the escalating math fight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A superintendent on Long Island is the latest casualty in the math wars, felled by parents who complain that their children have failed to learn basic skills in one of the top-performing school districts in New Jersey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Parents, some involved in a campaign against the math teaching in the highly regarded Ridgewood, N.J., school district, were to have met the new superintendent at a reception last Monday night.</p>
        <p>But the reception was abruptly canceled, leaving the school board president to explain that the superintendent, scheduled to begin on July 1 after a nine-month search costing more than $20,000, had backed out, largely because of the escalating math fight.</p>
        <p>In a statement expressing disappointment, the five-member school board said the recruit, Martin Brooks, had been made to feel unwelcome by ''anonymous phone calls, e-mail messages, blogs and Web postings by some community members'' that ''questioned his integrity, ethics and educational philosophy.''</p>
        <p>''You have to question how much further they'd be willing to go to advance their cause,'' Mark Bombace, the school board president, said in an interview. ''And that is very disturbing to someone who has spent his life trying to do the right thing for children.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Brooks, a superintendent on Long Island, is the latest casualty in the math wars, felled by parents who complain that their children have failed to learn basic skills in one of the top-performing school districts in New Jersey. After consulting math professors and hiring private tutors, the parents flooded the Internet -- and the local newspaper, The Ridgewood News -- with concerns about what is known as reform math, collecting more than 175 signatures on a petition calling for an overhaul of math instruction in six of the district's nine schools.</p>
        <p>These schools -- four elementary schools and the district's only two middle schools -- use reform math, an approach that typically allows students to explore their own solutions to problems, writing and drawing pictures, and to use tools like the calculator while they learn mathematical methods and skills. Reform math grew out of an effort to instill in students a deeper understanding of what they are doing rather than memorizing facts and repeating answers.</p>
        <p>But parents like Linda Moran, a former math teacher, say the approach has left their children lacking. Mrs. Moran said she became upset last year when one daughter, 10 at the time, had no idea how much she was owed after shoveling snow for an hour and 15 minutes, at $7.50 per hour, and the other, at 13, asked for a calculator option on her cellphone to figure out restaurant tips.</p>
        <p>''She had started to view herself as a non-math person, and I was not going to allow that,'' said Mrs. Moran, who, along with her husband, an engineer, now spends seven hours a week tutoring three of their four children in math.</p>
        <p>Reform math has been used for more than a decade in schools nationwide, including some public schools in New York City and its suburbs, but some have moved away from it recently amid concern that it leaves students with a shaky grasp of the basics. The opposition accelerated after a September 2006 report by the National Council of Teachers of Mathematics, the nation's leading group of math teachers, that recommended a tighter focus on basic math skills and narrower state standards.</p>
        <p>In Ridgewood, about 25 miles northwest of Midtown Manhattan, the math debate has created an unusual level of friction in a 5,600-student district where the excellence of the schools is taken for granted. The district's test scores are consistently among the highest in New Jersey. Ninety-four to 100 percent of the fourth graders in each Ridgewood elementary school passed the state math test in 2006, compared with 82.3 percent across the state.</p>
        <p>The parents who oppose reform math say it is confusing, moves too slowly and allows students to get by without mastering basic skills, partly because they can rely on calculators. ''It's like math for English majors,'' said Frances Edwards, a public relations consultant. ''It was never equations. It was patterns, drawing circles, writing down numbers and explaining what you did.''</p>
        <p>Reform math has been used in Ridgewood elementary schools since at least 2000. School officials say it spread largely because teachers embraced it. The approach was introduced in the middle schools this year. School officials said it is often supplemented with more traditional instruction.</p>
        <p>''I believe that 80 percent of the parents in this community feel comfortable with the math instructional program in kindergarten through eighth grade,'' said Paul Arilotta, who has served as interim superintendent for the past year. (The school board is meeting on Monday to decide what to do in Dr. Brooks's absence.)</p>
        <p>But Dr. Arilotta said the dispute had dampened teacher morale and taken up time. In response to the concerns, he said he planned to hire an independent consultant this month to convene groups of parents and teachers and start a dialogue on the issue. ''We're trying to move this to a problem-solving process rather than having a fight or a battle,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Joseph G. Rosenstein, a math professor at Rutgers University who supports reform math, said that it is often the more educated parents who grow angry and frustrated at the approach because they do not understand it. ''They want their children's education to resemble their education because they are successful,'' he explained. ''They say, 'It worked for me, why won't it work for them?' ''</p>
        <p>Few in Ridgewood knew much about reform math until several parents started to mobilize in the past year, stepping up their efforts after the hiring of Dr. Brooks. He has spent the last seven years as superintendent of Plainview-Old Bethpage, on Long Island, which put a reform math program in effect during his tenure.</p>
        <p>An anti-reform math movement has sprung up there as well. More than 900 residents have signed a petition asking for reform math to be removed from the schools, and the approach became an issue in school board elections this spring, when three of the seven board members were ousted.</p>
        <p>In Ridgewood, e-mail messages circulated by parents and items posted on an online forum, The Ridgewood Blog, contended that Dr. Brooks and his wife, who is a Hofstra University education professor, were ardent supporters of reform math and that she had received grants from the National Science Foundation to promote it.</p>
        <p>Dr. Brooks said in an interview that his wife's science foundation grants had nothing to do with reform math, and that while he supported the approach, neither he nor his wife had ever worked to promote it.</p>
        <p>Dr. Brooks said he had received several e-mail messages from Ridgewood parents and several anonymous phone calls saying not to come, or questioning his position on reform math.</p>
        <p>''I was tremendously offended by some of the blogs; they were just baldfaced lies,'' he said. ''I had heard so many wonderful things about the Ridgewood community in the past, it would be surprising if these voices spoke for that community. I'm hoping that Ridgewood is able to recapture its real voice in the future.''</p>
        <p>He said he did not know what he would do next after turning down the $212,000-a-year job in Ridgewood. His last day in the Plainview-Old Bethpage district is June 30.</p>
        <p>Liz Gnall, 40, a former engineer and software developer who started a Web site in Ridgewood (vormath.info) that includes the petition against reform math, said that she had not contacted Dr. Brooks and that her sole concern was to address the inadequacies of reform math.</p>
        <p>Much of the parental opposition has centered on Travell Elementary School, one of two schools in Ridgewood that use a program called Investigations in Number, Data and Space. The Travell principal, Margy Leininger, gave a presentation about it to parents this spring, and sent home surveys for parents to evaluate a new math workbook. ''We've been listening to parents and reflecting on our practices,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In Narrie Gavares's fifth-grade classroom at Travell on Friday, the students sat on the rug watching their teacher draw brightly colored stacks of squares on a sketch pad to illustrate the concept of exponential functions. The students then worked on activity books as Ms. Gavares passed out bins full of plastic tiles.</p>
        <p>''They really understand the value of numbers,'' Ms. Gavares said. ''And their sense becomes so keen that they're able to be flexible with numbers and manipulate them more efficiently.''</p>
        <p>Dorothy Koski, president of Travell's Home and School Association, said that while she had some concerns about the reform approach, her 10-year-old daughter had benefited from it.</p>
        <p>''I think it should stay for the time being,'' she said. ''We've invested a lot of time and energy into the program, and we have to give it a chance.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
