<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Shift, Judge Eases Limits On Surveillance By the Police</title>
    <meta content="14ruling" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/nyregion/14ruling.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854422"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Surveillance of Citizens by Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveillance of Citizens by Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE7D8143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Shift, Judge Eases Limits On Surveillance By the Police</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Shift, Judge Eases Limits on Surveillance by the Police</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN FEUER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a startling legal reversal, a federal judge in Manhattan decided yesterday to vacate his own order that had greatly limited the New York police in videotaping people at public gatherings. He said the reversal was based partly on new information.</p>
        <p>In February, the judge, Charles S. Haight Jr., issued what seemed an ironclad, somewhat scathing rebuke of the police, ruling that its surveillance teams could videotape protesters only if there was an indication that unlawful activity might be under way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The judge said he had received fresh accounts of two demonstrations that were videotaped by police, and that the police were justified in recording them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a startling legal reversal, a federal judge in Manhattan decided yesterday to vacate his own order that had greatly limited the New York police in videotaping people at public gatherings. He said the reversal was based partly on new information.</p>
        <p>In February, the judge, Charles S. Haight Jr., issued what seemed an ironclad, somewhat scathing rebuke of the police, ruling that its surveillance teams could videotape protesters only if there was an indication that unlawful activity might be under way.</p>
        <p>Citing two events in 2005 -- an antiwar march in Harlem and a protest by homeless people in front of Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's town house -- the judge ruled in February that the police had broken their own guidelines for political surveillance by videotaping people who were lawfully exercising their right to free speech.</p>
        <p>But in yesterday's ruling, Judge Haight, of United States District Court, somewhat reluctantly set that order aside, saying he had received fresh accounts of the demonstrations from city lawyers that directly contradicted accounts provided by lawyers for the plaintiffs. The new accounts suggested that unlawful activity might indeed have been occurring, with protesters becoming unruly. ''Given these conflicting accounts, the descriptions of these events in the court's 02/07 order cannot be regarded as findings of fact by the court in areas where the facts are disputed,'' he wrote.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's ruling came in the context of what is known as the Handschu case, a class-action lawsuit filed in 1971 that is among the most important (and certainly longest-lived) federal disputes that have sought to balance the citizenry's right to political expression with the state's interest in keeping public order. The case has resulted, most importantly, in the establishment of guidelines in 1985 that forbid the police to investigate political groups unless a crime is being -- or is about to be -- committed.</p>
        <p>The current dispute arises from the fact that after the Sept. 11 attack, the city asked the judge to relax the guidelines and allow more leeway to conduct investigations of political groups. Judge Haight agreed to a somewhat milder set of guidelines, but gave them teeth by later ruling that his own court would hold in contempt any police official who violated the rules.</p>
        <p>In yesterday's ruling, however, Judge Haight reversed himself, saying that he lacked the power to enforce the guidelines alone: The police could be liable for punishment only if they violated the United States Constitution, not his order.</p>
        <p>At a hearing in April, Gail Donoghue, special counsel for the city's Law Department, argued that if Judge Haight remained the sole authority to enforce the guidelines, his court would soon be inundated with ''minitrial after minitrial.'' The judge himself agreed with this assessment, writing in yesterday's decision, ''It would be unduly burdensome for this court to police every alleged violation of the N.Y.P.D. guidelines no matter how slight.''</p>
        <p>The judge, however, used the authority of contract law to ensure that the police did abide by the guidelines.</p>
        <p>''In the language of contracts'' he wrote, ''the N.Y.P.D. promised to enact (and impliedly to follow) the N.Y.P.D. guidelines in exchange for the court's promise to grant modifications.''</p>
        <p>He later wrote: ''If the N.Y.P.D. should break its promise to the court, I am not required to sit idly by with my hands tied.''</p>
        <p>From the start of the recent arguments, lawyers for the plaintiffs have said that the protests in Harlem and at the mayor's house were legal and peaceable. Until a few months ago, the city did not dispute that portrayal, for reasons, the judge wrote, that ''passeth all understanding.''</p>
        <p>When the city did file its accounts of the marches, they contradicted those of the plaintiffs in key ways: A city lawyer said the march at Mayor Bloomberg's house, for instance, was ''unruly and disobedient'' with the crowd blocking traffic and forcing a woman with a baby carriage into the street.</p>
        <p>Jethro M. Eisenstein, a lawyer for the plaintiffs, said that he and his partners would return to Judge Haight's court and prove that the marches were, in fact, calm and lawful, and seek to prove that the department engages in political surveillance against its own guidelines.</p>
        <p>Ms. Donoghue, the city lawyer, said through a spokeswoman that the city was ''continuing to study the decision's full import.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
