<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Committees Subpoena Ex-Officials on Dismissals</title>
    <meta content="14attorneys" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/us/14attorneys.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854347"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <org class="online_producer">House of Representatives</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Miers, Harriet E</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gonzales, Alberto R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5DA143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Committees Subpoena Ex-Officials on Dismissals</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">2 Committees Subpoena Ex-Officials on Dismissals</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID JOHNSTON; Eric Lipton contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, David</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Senate and House Judiciary Committees issued subpoenas on Wednesday to Harriet E. Miers, the former White House counsel, and Sara M. Taylor, the former political director, ratcheting up the pressure on the White House to cooperate with the Congressional inquiry into last year's firings of federal prosecutors.</p>
        <p>The White House has rejected previous Congressional requests to interview presidential aides, offering to let them be interviewed in private if no transcript is kept.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The subpoenas from Congress intensify pressure on the White House over the dismissals of U.S. attorneys.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Senate and House Judiciary Committees issued subpoenas on Wednesday to Harriet E. Miers, the former White House counsel, and Sara M. Taylor, the former political director, ratcheting up the pressure on the White House to cooperate with the Congressional inquiry into last year's firings of federal prosecutors.</p>
        <p>The White House has rejected previous Congressional requests to interview presidential aides, offering to let them be interviewed in private if no transcript is kept.</p>
        <p>The judiciary panels, acting two days after Republicans blocked an effort to hold a no-confidence vote on Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales, also sought White House documents about its involvement in the dismissals and efforts to respond to Congressional inquiries into whether as many as nine United States attorneys were removed for political reasons.</p>
        <p>A White House spokesman, Tony Fratto, said in a statement that ''committees can easily obtain the facts they want without this confrontational approach by simply accepting our offer.'' The committees' Democratic leaders ''are more interested in creating media drama than getting the facts,'' Mr. Fratto said.</p>
        <p>In a statement issued jointly by the two committees, Representative John Conyers Jr., Democrat of Michigan and chairman of the House panel, said, ''This subpoena is not a request, it is a demand on behalf of the American people for the White House to make available the documents or individuals we are requesting to help us answer the questions that remain.''</p>
        <p>The Senate Judiciary Committee had previously voted to authorize subpoenas for the two former officials, but had not issued them, hoping to obtain the voluntary cooperation of the White House, which did not respond to several written requests.</p>
        <p>Senator Patrick J. Leahy of Vermont, expressing the Democrats' frustration, said in a statement, ''The White House cannot have it both ways: it cannot stonewall Congressional investigations by refusing to provide documents and witnesses, while claiming nothing improper occurred.''</p>
        <p>Congressional investigators have largely completed their interviews of Justice Department officials and assembled thousands of pages of departmental documents. Yet they still cannot definitively answer such basic questions as who initiated the effort to oust the nine prosecutors, how the nine were selected and whether their dismissals were motivated by a desire to push a political agenda, like accelerating investigations of Democrats or protecting Republican elected officials from scrutiny, as some members of Congress have asserted.</p>
        <p>The inquiry has at least made clear that Ms. Miers and Ms. Taylor, among others at the White House, helped orchestrate the effort, despite an early statement by the Bush administration denying such a role.</p>
        <p>Ms. Miers, starting as early as March 2005, was exchanging e-mail with D. Kyle Sampson, the attorney general's former chief of staff, discussing prosecutors who could be removed. The consultations continued through this January, when she resigned, as she conferred then with her deputy, William K. Kelley, and Justice Department officials, over the backlash from the dismissals, questioning whether the administration should cite poor performance as a motivation.</p>
        <p>''The individuals aren't saying anything public. Senators are,'' Ms. Miers wrote. ''Then we are going to go out and say negative things about the people?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelley wrote back, ''F.Y.I. -- maybe we can consider briefing the interested senators in private without going negative in public?''</p>
        <p>Ms. Taylor, the e-mail has shown, played an important role in the appointment of J. Timothy Griffin, a former aide to Karl Rove, President Bush's chief political adviser, as the interim United States attorney in Arkansas. He replaced H. E. Cummins III, one of the prosecutors removed.</p>
        <p>Ms. Taylor expressed outrage, in one exchange released this week, that a Justice Department official had said Mr. Cummins was not removed for performance reasons. ''Bud is lazy -- which is why we got rid of him in the first place,'' she wrote in a February e-mail message to Mr. Sampson, rebutting accusations that a job was being created at the request of Ms. Miers and Mr. Rove. Ms. Taylor, speaking through her lawyer, W. Neil Eggleston, indicated she was willing to testify if the White House and Congress came to an agreement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
