<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TODAY IN BUSINESS</title>
    <meta content="14biztoday" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854403"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E3D9143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="940" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TODAY IN BUSINESS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOSPITAL CARE CHARGES -- Stark evidence that high medical payments do not necessarily buy high-quality patient care is presented in a Pennsylvania hospital study. Of the hospitals that perform heart bypass surgery, the best-paid hospital received nearly $100,000 for the operation while the least-paid got less than $20,000. Both facilities had comparable lengths of stay and death rates. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>SCALPING GOES PRO -- Some sports teams no longer provide paper tickets to their season-ticket holders, who instead simply swipe a credit card or driver's license to enter the arena. The electronic ticket systems have an important side benefit: they allow the team to control, and get a fee from, any reselling of a ticket. [C1.]</p>
        <p>KELLOGG TO CURB SOME ADS -- The Kellogg Company said that it would phase out advertising its products to children under age 12 unless the foods meet specific nutrition guidelines for calories, sugar, fat and sodium. Kellogg also announced that it would stop using licensed characters or branded toys to promote foods unless the products meet the nutrition guidelines. [C1.]</p>
        <p>SENATORS SEEK TO PENALIZE CHINA -- Four leading Democratic and Republican senators proposed legislation aimed at imposing penalties on China over its export practices and predicted that they would have the votes to pass it in Congress this year even if it was vetoed by President Bush. The Bush administration indicated it would oppose the bill, which appeared certain to aggravate tensions with China at a time when Treasury Secretary Henry M. Paulson Jr., above, has sought to use negotiation to change Chinese economic policies. [C1.]</p>
        <p>TEXT MESSAGES ON WALL STREET -- Wall Street's two self-policing groups are expected to release proposed guidelines for the regulation of written electronic communications, including internal and external exchanges, in rules that will probably cover text messages carried over cellphones, BlackBerrys and other devices. [C3.]</p>
        <p>PANEL REJECTS ANTI-OBESITY DRUG -- A drug made by Sanofi-Aventis that was once viewed as a possible magic bullet against obesity was rejected by a federal advisory panel because of worries that it causes neurological and psychiatric problems and increases the risk of suicide. [C3.]</p>
        <p>BANKS INDICTED IN PARMALAT CASE -- An Italian judge ordered Citigroup, Deutsche Bank, Morgan Stanley and UBS to stand trial on charges of market manipulation in the events that led to the multibillion-dollar bankruptcy filing of the Italian dairy company Parmalat in 2003. [C8.]</p>
        <p>THE GENUINE ARTICLE ON eBAY -- The online auction giant eBay says new rules to curb fraud have resulted in a 60 percent decline in the number of complaints from luxury goods makers that counterfeits of their products are being sold on the site. It also says that in the last four months it has banished tens of thousands of sellers who did not meet new, elevated standards. But other companies still complain about piracy on eBay. [C9.]</p>
        <p>Google and eBay got into a tussle at eBay's convention in Boston this week, when Google invited the auction site's sellers to a party to promote Google Checkout, a service that competes with eBay's PayPal. [C9.]</p>
        <p>TALKS TO SELL BARNEYS -- The Jones Apparel Group is close to an agreement to sell Barneys New York, the fashionable clothing retailer, for about $825 million to the investment arm of the Dubai government, people involved in the talks said. [C1.]</p>
        <p>STARS AND STRIPES AND G.M. -- ''Buy American'' has always been an undercurrent in General Motors' advertising, but the theme has been showing up more forcefully of late, as G.M. uses the one adjective that competitors like Toyota and Honda cannot use. Advertising. [C5.]</p>
        <p>A VIDEO SITE IN THE POLITICAL ARENA -- YouTube, which is owned by Google, and CNN are co-sponsoring a debate among the eight Democratic presidential candidates next month, with questions asked via videos submitted by people through YouTube. The debate is a reflection of YouTube's impact on politics. [A26.]</p>
        <p>DEBATE OVER BLOGGING AT A GAME -- The eviction of a newspaper reporter from a baseball press box for blogging about a game while it was in progress has stirred a debate over legal questions surrounding First Amendment rights, intellectual property rights and contract law. [D5.]</p>
        <p>NBC IN HIGH SCHOOL -- NBC News will announce an online educational venture, intended as a supplement to high school courses in American history, government and English, that draws heavily on its film archives, as well as on its journalists. [E3.]</p>
        <p>PRIVATE FORESTS AT RISK -- Conservationists are concerned that large tracts of the nation's private forests are at risk of falling into mismanagement, being subdivided or being sold for development as aging landowners pass the land to heirs or buyers. Small Business. [C6.]</p>
        <p>RETAIL REPORT BOLSTERS SHARES -- Stocks surged, pushing the Dow Jones industrial average to its biggest gain in almost 11 months, after the bond market rallied and a report on retail sales exceeded economists' estimates. [C15.]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>Business Briefing</p>
        <p>Articles on these developments are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>A HOUSE COMMITTEE CHAIRMAN said at a hearing that he would seek legislation to curb lending abuses if the central bank did not act quickly to do so. (AP)</p>
        <p>LEHMAN BROTHERS HOLDINGS said it would merge two residential mortgage units, BNC Mortgage and Aurora Loan Services, and cut 400 jobs. (REUTERS)</p>
        <p>THE CERIDIAN CORPORATION, the human resources company whose biggest shareholder, William A. Ackman, regards a $5.3 billion takeover bid as too low, said it would be prepared to consider other plans to sell itself. (REUTERS)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOSPITAL CARE CHARGES -- Stark evidence that high medical payments do not necessarily buy high-quality patient care is presented in a Pennsylvania hospital study. Of the hospitals that perform heart bypass surgery, the best-paid hospital received nearly $100,000 for the operation while the least-paid got less than $20,000. Both facilities had comparable lengths of stay and death rates. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>SCALPING GOES PRO -- Some sports teams no longer provide paper tickets to their season-ticket holders, who instead simply swipe a credit card or driver's license to enter the arena. The electronic ticket systems have an important side benefit: they allow the team to control, and get a fee from, any reselling of a ticket. [C1.]</p>
        <p>KELLOGG TO CURB SOME ADS -- The Kellogg Company said that it would phase out advertising its products to children under age 12 unless the foods meet specific nutrition guidelines for calories, sugar, fat and sodium. Kellogg also announced that it would stop using licensed characters or branded toys to promote foods unless the products meet the nutrition guidelines. [C1.]</p>
        <p>SENATORS SEEK TO PENALIZE CHINA -- Four leading Democratic and Republican senators proposed legislation aimed at imposing penalties on China over its export practices and predicted that they would have the votes to pass it in Congress this year even if it was vetoed by President Bush. The Bush administration indicated it would oppose the bill, which appeared certain to aggravate tensions with China at a time when Treasury Secretary Henry M. Paulson Jr., above, has sought to use negotiation to change Chinese economic policies. [C1.]</p>
        <p>TEXT MESSAGES ON WALL STREET -- Wall Street's two self-policing groups are expected to release proposed guidelines for the regulation of written electronic communications, including internal and external exchanges, in rules that will probably cover text messages carried over cellphones, BlackBerrys and other devices. [C3.]</p>
        <p>PANEL REJECTS ANTI-OBESITY DRUG -- A drug made by Sanofi-Aventis that was once viewed as a possible magic bullet against obesity was rejected by a federal advisory panel because of worries that it causes neurological and psychiatric problems and increases the risk of suicide. [C3.]</p>
        <p>BANKS INDICTED IN PARMALAT CASE -- An Italian judge ordered Citigroup, Deutsche Bank, Morgan Stanley and UBS to stand trial on charges of market manipulation in the events that led to the multibillion-dollar bankruptcy filing of the Italian dairy company Parmalat in 2003. [C8.]</p>
        <p>THE GENUINE ARTICLE ON eBAY -- The online auction giant eBay says new rules to curb fraud have resulted in a 60 percent decline in the number of complaints from luxury goods makers that counterfeits of their products are being sold on the site. It also says that in the last four months it has banished tens of thousands of sellers who did not meet new, elevated standards. But other companies still complain about piracy on eBay. [C9.]</p>
        <p>Google and eBay got into a tussle at eBay's convention in Boston this week, when Google invited the auction site's sellers to a party to promote Google Checkout, a service that competes with eBay's PayPal. [C9.]</p>
        <p>TALKS TO SELL BARNEYS -- The Jones Apparel Group is close to an agreement to sell Barneys New York, the fashionable clothing retailer, for about $825 million to the investment arm of the Dubai government, people involved in the talks said. [C1.]</p>
        <p>STARS AND STRIPES AND G.M. -- ''Buy American'' has always been an undercurrent in General Motors' advertising, but the theme has been showing up more forcefully of late, as G.M. uses the one adjective that competitors like Toyota and Honda cannot use. Advertising. [C5.]</p>
        <p>A VIDEO SITE IN THE POLITICAL ARENA -- YouTube, which is owned by Google, and CNN are co-sponsoring a debate among the eight Democratic presidential candidates next month, with questions asked via videos submitted by people through YouTube. The debate is a reflection of YouTube's impact on politics. [A26.]</p>
        <p>DEBATE OVER BLOGGING AT A GAME -- The eviction of a newspaper reporter from a baseball press box for blogging about a game while it was in progress has stirred a debate over legal questions surrounding First Amendment rights, intellectual property rights and contract law. [D5.]</p>
        <p>NBC IN HIGH SCHOOL -- NBC News will announce an online educational venture, intended as a supplement to high school courses in American history, government and English, that draws heavily on its film archives, as well as on its journalists. [E3.]</p>
        <p>PRIVATE FORESTS AT RISK -- Conservationists are concerned that large tracts of the nation's private forests are at risk of falling into mismanagement, being subdivided or being sold for development as aging landowners pass the land to heirs or buyers. Small Business. [C6.]</p>
        <p>RETAIL REPORT BOLSTERS SHARES -- Stocks surged, pushing the Dow Jones industrial average to its biggest gain in almost 11 months, after the bond market rallied and a report on retail sales exceeded economists' estimates. [C15.]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>Business Briefing</p>
        <p>Articles on these developments are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>A HOUSE COMMITTEE CHAIRMAN said at a hearing that he would seek legislation to curb lending abuses if the central bank did not act quickly to do so. (AP)</p>
        <p>LEHMAN BROTHERS HOLDINGS said it would merge two residential mortgage units, BNC Mortgage and Aurora Loan Services, and cut 400 jobs. (REUTERS)</p>
        <p>THE CERIDIAN CORPORATION, the human resources company whose biggest shareholder, William A. Ackman, regards a $5.3 billion takeover bid as too low, said it would be prepared to consider other plans to sell itself. (REUTERS)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
