<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Losses Are Taking a Toll On the Frustrated Mets</title>
    <meta content="14mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854480"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7D7143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="874" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Losses Are Taking a Toll On the Frustrated Mets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets are not panicking. They are not scared. Yet the losses are stacking up in staggering fashion, 9 in 10 games with their 9-1 drubbing to the Los Angeles Dodgers on Wednesday night, and in small but distinct ways this dreadful stretch is starting to wear on them.</p>
        <p>Only the coaches watched the final few innings from the dugout steps. The players stayed inside the dugout, as if they were resigned to another loss and eager to leave this place as soon as they could. Who could blame them? The last time the Mets were at Dodger Stadium, back in October, they swept the Dodgers in the division series. They have not won here since. The Dodgers outscored them, 18-5, in sweeping the three-game series, and they bashed the previously indestructible Jorge Sosa, who had started the Mets' only two victories this month, for six runs and eight hits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Mets are not panicking. They are not scared. Yet the losses are stacking up in staggering fashion, 9 in 10 games with their 9-1 drubbing to the Los Angeles Dodgers on Wednesday night, and in small but distinct ways this dreadful stretch is starting to wear on them.</p>
        <p>Only the coaches watched the final few innings from the dugout steps. The players stayed inside the dugout, as if they were resigned to another loss and eager to leave this place as soon as they could. Who could blame them? The last time the Mets were at Dodger Stadium, back in October, they swept the Dodgers in the division series. They have not won here since. The Dodgers outscored them, 18-5, in sweeping the three-game series, and they bashed the previously indestructible Jorge Sosa, who had started the Mets' only two victories this month, for six runs and eight hits.</p>
        <p>The Mets are still in first place, but their lead is down to two games in front of Atlanta and the mercurial Phillies, who swept the Chicago White Sox, with a series against the hottest team in baseball up next. At least the Mets get Thursday off before facing the Yankees, who have won eight in a row. If they do not play, they cannot lose.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it's confidence that we're lacking,'' said Billy Wagner, the Mets' closer. ''It's more along the lines of frustration. That's the best word because it's not a lack of effort, it's a lack of focus. For things to go your way, we need to make our own breaks.''</p>
        <p>For the sixth consecutive game, the Mets scored first, but that temporary piece of good news only served to reinforce another discouraging pattern. After each time the Dodgers took the lead for good in this series, including in the fifth inning Wednesday, when they scored three off Sosa, the Mets did not score in any of the 14 successive innings.</p>
        <p>Unlike the first two games, when they did not reach base after the sixth inning, they managed three hits that led nowhere. Ricky Ledee stranded runners at second and third in the seventh.</p>
        <p>Perhaps this is all a coincidence. Perhaps the Dodgers' relief pitchers are just that good (their 3.43 earned run average is the second best in the National League). Perhaps the Mets' late-game lethargy is a byproduct of their trying too hard.</p>
        <p>Manager Willie Randolph said it is human nature for players to press during slides like this. ''It's not like we're playing the Bad News Bears here,'' Carlos Delgado said. ''You're not just going to throw out your gloves and give up.''</p>
        <p>Sosa was coming off throwing eight scoreless innings last Friday in Detroit, but word of his success apparently had not reached the West Coast. He allowed only one hit through the first four innings before unraveling in the fifth.</p>
        <p>Wilson Betemit belted a hanging 0-2 changeup just out of the reach of Carlos Beltrán in left-center field to even the score at 1-1 and end Sosa's consecutive scoreless-inning streak at 15. The next hitter, Matt Kemp, reached on an infield single, and with two outs he scored when Rafael Furcal ripped a triple past Carlos Delgado and into the right-field corner. Juan Pierre followed with a run-scoring single, and the Dodgers led, 3-1.</p>
        <p>They added three more off Sosa in the sixth, all with two outs. Consecutive singles by Betemit and Kemp extended the Dodgers' lead to 5-1, chasing Sosa, and Tony Abreu greeted Pedro Feliciano by lining a run-scoring double to left.</p>
        <p>From the outset, the matchup seemed to favor the Mets, and not just because Sosa was pitching. Although Dodgers ace Brad Penny entered the game 7-1 with the second-lowest earned run average in the National League (2.26), he has never fared well against the Mets (3-10, 6.16), whose eight starting position players were hitting a combined .358 off him.</p>
        <p>True to form, the Mets hit him early. Shawn Green grounded a double inside the third-base line and scored on David Wright's two-out single, putting the Mets ahead, 1-0. As the Dodgers pounded away, that 1 stayed on the scoreboard the rest of the game.</p>
        <p>This is the stretch that will test the Mets' patience. After the Yankees series comes the Twins, then the A's, then the Cardinals, then the Phillies.</p>
        <p>Asked whether he felt it necessary to remind his players to stay calm, Randolph deadpanned: ''No, I threaten them. Fear is a big motivator. I go a little crazy before the game so I can set them straight. Maybe go all Billy Martin on them and knock over the food table.''</p>
        <p>He was only kidding. But the Mets need something to shake them from these doldrums.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Joe Smith thought he was the victim of another rookie joke when he was left out of the photograph for the cover story on Omar Minaya in this week's issue of Sports Illustrated. With four players, Willie Randolph and Minaya in the shot, Smith was told to lie down in a ''swimsuit pose,'' but he was cropped out. ''I think it was just so they could easily say that this kid doesn't belong,'' Smith said, smiling. ''Oh, well.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
