<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reading the Cards Well Enough to Collect Them All</title>
    <meta content="14card" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/crosswords/bridge/14card.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854301"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Bridge"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cards and Card Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cards and Card Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E4DD143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="656" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reading the Cards Well Enough to Collect Them All</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Reading the Cards Well Enough to Collect Them All</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Phillip Alder</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The final of the trial to select the U.S.A.-2 team for this year's Bermuda Bowl world championship ended Sunday night in Schaumburg, Ill., with Nick Nickell, Dick Freeman, Bob Hamman, Paul Soloway, Jeff Meckstroth and Eric Rodwell winning the 120-board match. They defeated Russ Ekeblad, Ron Rubin, Fred Gitelman, Brad Moss, Chip Martel and Lew Stansby by 271 international match points to 225.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the best piece of card reading during the trial was in the diagramed deal, Board 112 of the semifinals. It was brought to my notice by Chris Willenken.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The final of the trial to select the U.S.A.-2 team for this year’s Bermuda Bowl world championship ended Sunday night in Schaumburg, Ill., with Nick Nickell, Dick Freeman, Bob Hamman, Paul Soloway, Jeff Meckstroth and Eric Rodwell winning the 120-board match.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The final of the trial to select the U.S.A.-2 team for this year's Bermuda Bowl world championship ended Sunday night in Schaumburg, Ill., with Nick Nickell, Dick Freeman, Bob Hamman, Paul Soloway, Jeff Meckstroth and Eric Rodwell winning the 120-board match. They defeated Russ Ekeblad, Ron Rubin, Fred Gitelman, Brad Moss, Chip Martel and Lew Stansby by 271 international match points to 225.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the best piece of card reading during the trial was in the diagramed deal, Board 112 of the semifinals. It was brought to my notice by Chris Willenken.</p>
        <p>In the match between Ekeblad and a team led by Richard Schwartz, both Souths made six hearts exactly.</p>
        <p>In the other semifinal between Nickell and Seymon Deutsch's team, there was more action.</p>
        <p>At the first table Soloway opened the North hand with one club, strong and artificial. Bart Bramley (East) passed, and Hamman (South) responded one no-trump, showing 12 or more points with five-plus hearts. Now Sidney Lazard (West) pre-empted with four clubs. When North rebid four hearts, South continued with four spades, which was Roman Key Card Blackwood in hearts. West was still there with four no-trump, announcing a secondary diamond suit. North passed to show three key cards (two aces and the trump king, or three aces), East competed with five diamonds, and South's double ended the auction.</p>
        <p>The defense took the maximum. It is normally best to start with a trump when the opponents have sacrificed at a high level, trying to cut down their ruffing tricks. Hamman did that, leading his diamond deuce. Declarer rose with West's king, then played a club, which was ducked to South's king.</p>
        <p>Hamman continued with another low trump, declarer winning with West's eight and North pitching a spade. East ruffed a club with his diamond seven, but South overruffed with his jack, cashed the diamond ace and shifted to the heart deuce. North won with his ace and returned a heart to South's jack, declarer throwing dummy's spade. Declarer ruffed the heart king with the board's diamond queen and called for the club jack. North won with his queen and led a sneaky low spade, but East went up with his queen, so went down ''only'' seven.</p>
        <p>The auction at the other table is given, four no-trump being Roman Key Card Blackwood in hearts and five spades showing two key cards (one ace and the trump king, or two aces) and the trump queen.</p>
        <p>Against seven hearts, if Rodwell (West) had led anything but a club, Gary Cohler (South) would have ruffed two diamonds on the board and got home without difficulty. But the club lead disrupted declarer's communications.</p>
        <p>Cohler was confident that West was 1-1-4-7. Since West had jumped to four clubs on a jack-high suit, he surely had a very distributional hand. Playing on that basis, South won with his club king, cashed the diamond ace, ruffed a diamond in the dummy and took the spade ace. If the spade queen had dropped, declarer would have drawn trumps. But when it did not, South called for the club ace.</p>
        <p>If Meckstroth (East) had ruffed, the contract would have been defeated. But that was not clear. Perhaps ruffing would cost a natural trump trick. So on the club ace East and South pitched diamonds. And on the club queen East threw his last diamond and South a spade to give this end position:</p>
        <p>Now declarer could have ruffed the last club in his hand, cashed the heart king, played his remaining spade to dummy's king and crossruffed home. But Cohler knew East had not ruffed because he was hoping to score a trump trick. Backing his judgment, South ran dummy's heart nine.</p>
        <p>When it held, declarer took dummy's spade king, ruffed a club in his hand, ruffed the diamond jack on the board and claimed.</p>
        <p>Minus 1,700 and plus 2,210 gave the Deutsch team 11 imps in a losing cause.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
