<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blogger's Ejection May Mean Suit for N.C.A.A.</title>
    <meta content="14blogs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E3D8143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="982" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blogger's Ejection May Mean Suit for N.C.A.A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The eviction of a newspaper reporter from a baseball press box for blogging about a game while it was in progress has stirred a debate about First Amendment rights, intellectual property rights and contract law.</p>
        <p>The National Collegiate Athletic Association, which on Sunday ejected Brian Bennett of The Courier-Journal of Louisville, Ky., during the Louisville-Oklahoma State game at Jim Patterson Stadium in Louisville, contends it is merely enforcing long-established principles as they apply to a new technology.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The eviction of a newspaper reporter from a baseball press box for blogging about a game while it was in progress has stirred a debate about First Amendment rights, intellectual property rights and contract law.</p>
        <p>The National Collegiate Athletic Association, which on Sunday ejected Brian Bennett of The Courier-Journal of Louisville, Ky., during the Louisville-Oklahoma State game at Jim Patterson Stadium in Louisville, contends it is merely enforcing long-established principles as they apply to a new technology.</p>
        <p>But the newspaper is weighing a legal challenge on First Amendment grounds -- the right to free speech as it applies to reporting news in a public place.</p>
        <p>Jon Fleischaker, a lawyer representing The Courier-Journal, said yesterday that such a challenge might be made, within the next 10 days, because the event took place at a public facility and because the eviction was enforced by the University of Louisville, a public institution that was the host university.</p>
        <p>''We're just not sure whether there is enough official state action to properly be able to say there's a First Amendment claim,'' Fleischaker said in a telephone interview. ''We're doing some work to see who's on first.''</p>
        <p>Scott Bearby, associate general counsel for the N.C.A.A., said in a telephone interview yesterday that the dispute ''doesn't really have a First Amendment angle to it'' and that the N.C.A.A. had a right to protect the contracts it establishes with television networks and its own Internet providers.</p>
        <p>''It's a logical extension of the rights that have been around for years and years,'' Bearby said. Furthermore, Bearby said, the N.C.A.A. can revoke credentials to events from news organizations that post Internet accounts of their events even by other employees who sit outside the press box or watch it on television outside the stadium.</p>
        <p>In a statement sent via e-mail, the N.C.A.A. said: ''Reporters covering our championships may blog about the atmosphere, crowd and other details during a game but may not mention anything about game action. Any reference to game action in a blog or other type of coverage could result in revocation of credentials.''</p>
        <p>Rich Gordon, an associate professor of journalism at Northwestern University and a director of its new media journalism program, said that ''this is just the latest skirmish in a longer-term war'' that will get more contentious.</p>
        <p>''The law, as happens in many cases, has not kept up with the technology,'' Gordon said. ''As a journalist, you're inclined to wave the First Amendment flag. This is going to get messier before it gets figured out. The media trends are at odds with the leagues' goal of controlling distribution and extracting a ransom.''</p>
        <p>The N.C.A.A. action is occurring against a rapidly changing backdrop of how athletes, teams and leagues reach fans through different and new technologies and often bypass traditional news media.</p>
        <p>Many newspapers have started or expanded their Internet coverage of sports events with reports before, during and after games. On the other side, players like Red Sox pitcher Curt Schilling and Giants outfielder Barry Bonds have their own Web sites, and teams like the Chicago White Sox and the University of Missouri have relegated reporters covering their games to less desirable seating areas.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the Islanders addressed the growing influence of sports blogs by announcing the creation of the NYI Blog Box, a separate press area for home games at Nassau Coliseum. The team is allowing approved bloggers, and those who want to become bloggers, access to game notes and providing an area to interview coaches and players.</p>
        <p>But, in addressing the issue that came up in Louisville, the Islanders said they had not yet decided whether bloggers would be allowed to transmit live during games.</p>
        <p>The N.C.A.A. decision at the baseball tournament was ostensibly to protect the broadcasting rights that were sold to ESPN, which was telecasting the game, and CBS Sportsline.com, the official Internet provider of detailed descriptions for N.C.A.A. baseball tournament games.</p>
        <p>An ESPN spokesman, Mike Humes, said: ''To be honest, we didn't ask for it. They didn't consult us.'' Bearby, the N.C.A.A. lawyer, said the N.C.A.A. initiated the action because ''the entertainment event or sporting event has the ability to limit access to who gets that firsthand account.''</p>
        <p>Bearby also said any challenge based on use of a public facility would be irrelevant because the N.C.A.A. rents the facilities for a private event. ''To portray this as a First Amendment right is a little bit misleading,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Lisa Dolak, a professor of law at Syracuse University who specializes in intellectual property rights, said the N.C.A.A. might be within its rights under contract law to issue a press credential that said, as she put it, ''Thou shalt not blog'' and expect its rule to be obeyed.</p>
        <p>But, Dolak said, the N.C.A.A. may have difficulty proving under intellectual property law that a live blog account of its games reduces the ticket value of its event or its transmission rights. ''That would seem kind of weak,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Bennie Ivory, the executive editor of The Courier-Journal, said in a telephone interview Tuesday that the ban was a free-speech issue. ''How can anybody control it?'' Ivory said. ''A blog is opinion and observation with some facts thrown in.''</p>
        <p>Ivory and others asked whether it was in the best interests of sports promoters to discourage what amounts to free publicity for their live events and telecasts. One of them was James Speta, a professor of law at Northwestern who specializes in Internet law.</p>
        <p>Speta also expressed doubt as to how such rules could be applied to bloggers at the games but outside the press box or to bloggers outside of the stadium.</p>
        <p>''Somebody's trying to set precedent here,'' Speta said. ''There is value in the immediacy of the distribution of the facts. But, once the hotness of the news is gone, there's no protection for the value that comes from the distribution of the facts.''</p>
        <p>SPORTS MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
