<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Legislators' Pet Spending Projects, Exposed</title>
    <meta content="14tree" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/nyregion/14tree.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854424"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E6D8143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="809" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Legislators' Pet Spending Projects, Exposed</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">N.J. Legislators’ Pet Spending Projects, Exposed</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, June 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As part of the effort to bring greater transparency to the state's budget process and reduce the potential for corruption, the Legislature on Wednesday released for the first time a list of special projects and other changes to the $33.5 billion budget being requested by individual lawmakers.</p>
        <p>The list of what have long been known as Christmas tree items -- so named because they were strung onto the budget like so many lights and ornaments -- include local pet projects like $75,000 for the Boys and Girls Club of Newark and $82,000 for the meals program of the UJA Federation of Northern New Jersey. Some reflected municipalities' priorities, like $1 million for the North Hudson Fire District and $750,000 for landfill closings in North Arlington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Aiming to increase transparency and reduce corruption, the New Jersey Legislature released a list of budget changes requested by individual lawmakers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As part of the effort to bring greater transparency to the state's budget process and reduce the potential for corruption, the Legislature on Wednesday released for the first time a list of special projects and other changes to the $33.5 billion budget being requested by individual lawmakers.</p>
        <p>The list of what have long been known as Christmas tree items -- so named because they were strung onto the budget like so many lights and ornaments -- include local pet projects like $75,000 for the Boys and Girls Club of Newark and $82,000 for the meals program of the UJA Federation of Northern New Jersey. Some reflected municipalities' priorities, like $1 million for the North Hudson Fire District and $750,000 for landfill closings in North Arlington.</p>
        <p>Others were sponsored by large groups of lawmakers and reflected broad policy: a $129 million increase in aid to hospitals that treat uninsured patients, $3 million to legal services for the poor, and cost-of-living increases for workers at health programs receiving state funds.</p>
        <p>In all, the Legislature posted online 404 requested changes to the budget proposed by Gov. Jon S. Corzine. (It is at www.njleg.state.nj.us/changebudgetproposal/budgetresolutions.asp). Each change lists its legislative backers, along with a disclosure form detailing any personal or business relationship the lawmaker has to the recipient of the money.</p>
        <p>The list came the day after the legislative leaders and Governor Corzine announced they had reached agreement on the budget, well in advance of the June 30 deadline.</p>
        <p>Later Wednesday, they released the blueprint of that agreement, which includes a total of $189 million more in spending than Mr. Corzine proposed in February. By far the largest single change that lawmakers made in the governor's proposal was the $129 million increase in aid to hospitals for serving the uninsured. And only about 50 of the members' requested changes were included in the two houses' appropriation measure. Hearings on the measure are scheduled to begin Friday.</p>
        <p>The Christmas tree list is, in part, the legislative leaders' attempt to defuse the public's suspicion about the items, which often find their way into the state spending plan at the last minute without much discussion and are suspected of benefiting politically connected interests.</p>
        <p>The practice of adding last-minute items flourished in varying degrees under both Democratic and Republican regimes in the Legislature, and has in the last year attracted the attention of federal investigators, who have subpoenaed budget records concerning Christmas tree items back to 2004.</p>
        <p>In March a former budget committee chairman, Sen. Wayne R. Bryant, a Democrat from Camden, was indicted on corruption charges, accused of pushing for such budget enhancements for a state medical school that employed him as a consultant.</p>
        <p>The new openness in New Jersey comes amid outrage over similar budget items, known as earmarks in the United States Congress, that have also figured prominently in corruption scandals. Congress as well has moved in the last year to shed light on the process of earmarks.</p>
        <p>''This is open, and there is nothing that is going to be happening behind a closed door at 4 in the morning,'' said Senate President Richard J. Codey, a Democrat.</p>
        <p>Mr. Codey noted that in recent weeks he had been discouraging some members from seeking certain changes or additions to the budget, warning that Governor Corzine, who has the authority to make line-item vetoes, would never approve it. He said that over the next eight months, before next year's budget negotiations begin, the lawmakers would refine the new, more transparent process to pool changes under broad program areas and eliminate narrowly focused items without cutting funding of local projects altogether.</p>
        <p>''There are plenty of programs that are worthwhile and should be included in the budget,'' Mr. Codey said. ''I disagree that these are all questionable Christmas tree items.''</p>
        <p>Sen. Leonard Lance, the Republican leader, said his party's members had not requested any additions to the budget.</p>
        <p>''We believe that the state is in a precarious fiscal situation with a $2.5 billion structural deficit,'' he said. ''We just hope they vote on each item individually so that there can be discussion.''</p>
        <p>But such individual votes are unlikely. Instead, Assembly and Senate Democrats were caucusing late on Wednesday to winnow the list of changes. In the Assembly, according to Joseph Donnelly, the spokesman for Speaker Joseph R. Roberts Jr., there were 245 specific budget changes requested from 45 of the 50 Democrats. Those changes included 223 requests for increased spending and 22 requests for reduced outlays in such areas as fuel, reductions based on updated economic projections since the original budget was drawn up.</p>
        <p>Mr. Donnelly said this amounted to $495 million in increased spending and $194 million in reductions for a net increase of $300 million -- the figure in place before legislators and the governor then cut the requests to achieve the final increase of $189 million.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
