<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Southeast Asian Terrorist Leader Is Under Arrest, Indonesian Police Confirm</title>
    <meta content="14indo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/world/asia/14indo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854344"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jemaah Islamiyah (Terrorist Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gelling, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dujana, Abu</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Indonesia</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Jemaah Islamiyah</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E5DA143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Southeast Asian Terrorist Leader Is Under Arrest, Indonesian Police Confirm</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Southeast Asian Terrorist Leader Is Under Arrest</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER GELLING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gelling, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>JAKARTA, Indonesia, June 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Indonesian police confirm that Abu Dujana, major Southeast Asian terrorist leader, has been arrested; police say he leads military arm of Jemaah Islamiyah, Southeast Asian Islamist group; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After several days of uncertainty, the Indonesian police confirmed Wednesday that Abu Dujana, a major Southeast Asian terrorist leader and a most-wanted fugitive in Indonesia, had been arrested and was in custody in central Java.</p>
        <p>Sisno Adiwinoto, the national police spokesman, told reporters that Mr. Dujana, described by Indonesian security officials as an Afghan-trained militant who had relationships with Qaeda leaders, was arrested last weekend with six other terrorism suspects.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Indonesian police said Abu Dujana led the military arm of Jemaah Islamiyah, blamed for the 2002 Bali bombings, and had connections with al Qaeda leaders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After several days of uncertainty, the Indonesian police confirmed Wednesday that Abu Dujana, a major Southeast Asian terrorist leader and a most-wanted fugitive in Indonesia, had been arrested and was in custody in central Java.</p>
        <p>Sisno Adiwinoto, the national police spokesman, told reporters that Mr. Dujana, described by Indonesian security officials as an Afghan-trained militant who had relationships with Qaeda leaders, was arrested last weekend with six other terrorism suspects.</p>
        <p>Mr. Adiwinoto said it had taken several days to confirm Mr. Dujana's identity because he had many aliases. The police had thought the suspect was one of his top aides.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dujana, 37, leads the military arm of Jemaah Islamiyah, the Southeast Asia Islamist group, the police said. He was captured after raids across central Java last weekend by Indonesia's Detachment 88.</p>
        <p>Jemaah Islamiyah has been blamed for a number of major bombings in Indonesia, including the 2002 bombing in Bali that killed more than 200 people. The police said that Mr. Dujana was wanted specifically for his role in the 2004 bombing of the Australian Embassy in Jakarta, but that he had long been involved with Jemaah Islamiyah.</p>
        <p>The militant wing of Jemaah Islamiyah has been seriously weakened in recent years after the capture or death of several of its leaders, including the master bomb maker Azhari Husin, who was killed in 2005.</p>
        <p>But raids in March by Detachment 88 uncovered detailed plans of Jemaah Islamiyah's new command structure, suggesting it was beginning to rebuild.</p>
        <p>''The arrest of Dujana substantially improves the security situation in Indonesia,'' said Sidney Jones, an analyst with the Brussels-based International Crisis Group who works in Jakarta and is knowledgeable about Jemaah Islamiyah. ''But it is important to remember that this isn't just a military operation, it is a social and economic organization, it is resilient enough to withstand the arrest of a small number of individuals.''</p>
        <p>Another of Indonesia's most-wanted terrorists, a Malaysian-born militant, Noordin Top, is at large. The police said they believed that Mr. Dujana was involved in protecting Mr. Top, since the latter was nearly captured in 2005, and other significant Southeast Asian militants.</p>
        <p>Indonesia's success in capturing militants and dismantling the militant arm of Jemaah Islamiyah has won the country recognition and prompted the United States to begin normalizing military ties in 2005.</p>
        <p>Ansyaad Mbai, the top antiterrorism official at the Coordinating Ministry for Security and Political Affairs, said part of the reason for the success was the ability of the police to draw information from previously arrested militants.</p>
        <p>But despite the capture of Jemaah Islamiyah's more violent members, the group's ideological roots run deep throughout Indonesia.</p>
        <p>''Many of these individuals are often living in one place, involved in local religious studies,'' Ms. Jones said. ''How do you move from really good police work in catching criminals responsible for violent activity to combating the ideological recruitment more generally when no criminal activity is being committed?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
