<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Another Spin for 'Buy American'</title>
    <meta content="14adco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/business/media/14adco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854388"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chevrolet Division of General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Saturn Division of General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Deutsch (Ad Agency)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Campbell-Ewald</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bunkley, Nick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mellencamp, John</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Slogans and Mottoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Slogans and Mottoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6D9143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Another Spin for 'Buy American'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Another Spin for ‘Buy American’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICK BUNKLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bunkley, Nick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>'Buy American' has been showing up more forcefully in General Motors advertising; Deutsch advertising developed slogan 'Rethink American' for Saturn campaign; some Saturn vehicles are not particularly American; they are largely based on Opel models that are designed and sold in Europe, and some of cars sold in US are manufactured abroad; Saturn has been enjoying significantly higher sales thanks to its new lineup; GM's redesigned full-size pickup truck, Chevrolet Silverado, is featured in patriotic spots set to John Mellencamp's song Our Country; ads, created by Campbell-Ewald, tie into Chevrolet's tagline 'An American revolution'; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GENERAL MOTORS has clearly been hurt by consumers who simply refuse to buy an American brand of vehicle. But the automaker has decided to use its heritage as a competitive advantage rather than a weakness, since it is one adjective that competitors like Toyota and Honda cannot use.</p>
        <p>''Buy American'' has always been an undercurrent in G.M.'s advertising, but the theme has been showing up more forcefully of late. This spring General Motors has run three marketing campaigns centered on its American roots.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>General Motors has decided to use its heritage as a competitive advantage in its advertising, rather than a weakness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GENERAL MOTORS has clearly been hurt by consumers who simply refuse to buy an American brand of vehicle. But the automaker has decided to use its heritage as a competitive advantage rather than a weakness, since it is one adjective that competitors like Toyota and Honda cannot use.</p>
        <p>''Buy American'' has always been an undercurrent in G.M.'s advertising, but the theme has been showing up more forcefully of late. This spring General Motors has run three marketing campaigns centered on its American roots.</p>
        <p>''Even the staunchest American- car rejecter is rooting for American cars,'' said Eric Hirshberg, president of Deutsch Los Angeles, the advertising agency behind the current campaign for G.M.'s Saturn brand. ''They just don't think they're good enough quality, or they're set against them for whatever reason. But everybody in this country has an affinity for American cars and wants to get behind them.''</p>
        <p>Deutsch, part of the Interpublic Group of Companies, developed the slogan ''Rethink American'' for Saturn; the campaign, which began running about a month ago, includes television, print, online and billboard components. Saturn itself was introduced by G.M. in 1990 to lure buyers who were considering an import brand.</p>
        <p>These days, however, some Saturn vehicles are not particularly American. They are largely based on Opel models that are designed and sold in Europe, and some of the cars sold in the United States are manufactured abroad. Yet Saturn has been enjoying significantly higher sales thanks to its new lineup.</p>
        <p>In addition, G.M.'s redesigned full-size pickup truck, the Chevrolet Silverado, is featured in patriotic spots set to the John Mellencamp ballad ''Our Country.'' The ads, created by Campbell-Ewald, a unit of Interpublic, tie into Chevrolet's tagline, ''An American revolution.''</p>
        <p>In May, G.M. drew attention to a Memorial Day sale at Buick, Pontiac and G.M.C. dealerships with ads thanking American soldiers and offering to collect letters for the troops overseas. And last fall, G.M. signed on the conservative radio host Sean Hannity for a promotion called the Great American Car Giveaway.</p>
        <p>Despite these patriotic appeals, a G.M. spokeswoman, Ryndee Carney, said the company is trying to play up its vehicles' amenities more than their heritage.</p>
        <p>''You see more of our advertising talking specifically about the product and the brand as opposed to 'We're American,' '' Ms. Carney said.</p>
        <p>Saturn's ads highlight safety features, fuel economy and critical acclaim. Still, each spot ensures that consumers know that the brand is American.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hirshberg of Deutsch described the campaign as ''the opposite of a buy-American campaign,'' noting that a newspaper ad for the Aura sedan begins: ''Don't buy it because it's American. Buy it because it's amazing.''</p>
        <p>The ads are meant to persuade consumers that Saturn has improved considerably since it began selling entry-level vehicles and that the brand should prompt people with low opinions of American vehicles to take another look.</p>
        <p>'' 'Rethink American' is not a patriotism campaign,'' Mr. Hirshberg said. ''It's a 'rethink your rejection of American' campaign.''</p>
        <p>Although Saturn's sales have been rising, G.M. will have difficulty persuading people who have spurned American vehicles that they have improved, said Jim Hossack, a consultant with AutoPacific in Tustin, Calif.</p>
        <p>''The stigma is still there. Is the reality still there? I'm not really sure,'' Mr. Hossack said. ''There's still a negative connotation coming from decades of products that proved in the end to have quality, reliability and durability less than the leading Japanese imports'.''</p>
        <p>G.M. is not the only American automaker that has been playing up its roots. Ford Motor tries to rally its employees around the slogan ''Red, White and Bold,'' and Ford executives talk of the company's goal to ''embody the American spirit'' and to become ''America's car company.''</p>
        <p>In addition, Ford is a prominent sponsor of the ''American Idol'' singing competition on the Fox network.</p>
        <p>Even as At Ford and G.M. are waving the flag, so, too are some of the foreign automakers that have plants in the United States. Mark Fields, the president of Ford's Americas division, has criticized Toyota for ''desperately trying to cast itself as an American brand'' to appeal to patriotic shoppers. At last year's Los Angeles auto show, Mr. Fields said, ''Americans really do want to buy American brands -- as long as we're competitive with the imports.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hossack said patriotism alone was not enough for G.M. and Ford to regain any of the market share that they have lost to Toyota, Honda and others. Still, that they are American companies could work in their favor, he said.</p>
        <p>''I don't see a whole lot of patriotism, but I do see a sort of rooting for the underdog,'' Mr. Hossack said. ''For decades G.M., Ford and Chrysler had such a dominant position that the underdog was the imports. But they may have inverted their position. Detroit may now be the underdog.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
