<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Never Mind the Name: Balanchine's '60s Hit Seeks to Sparkle Again</title>
    <meta content="14jewe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/arts/dance/14jewe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854333"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York City Ballet</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bouder, Ashley</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Stafford, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kowroski, Maria</person>
        <person class="online_producer">de Luz, Joaquin</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Fairchild, Megan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Suozzi, Sean</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EFDB143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="492" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Never Mind the Name: Balanchine's '60s Hit Seeks to Sparkle Again</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Never Mind the Name: Balanchine’s ’60s Hit Seeks to Sparkle Again</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>George Balanchine's ''Jewels'' was said to have been inspired by a visit to Van Cleef &amp; Arpels, though he made sure to say publicly that the ballet had nothing to do with gems. The supposed theme, the jewel-strewn look of the work and several rave reviews made ''Jewels'' the kind of hit that ballet seldom had in the mid-1960s, when the work was first performed.</p>
        <p>Now the work is recognized as substantial Balanchine. Set to scores by Fauré, Stravinsky and Tchaikovsky, ''Jewels'' is not only one of Balanchine's most compelling exercises in making music dance. It is also a telling meditation on the kind of national ballet styles -- here French (''Emeralds''), American (''Rubies'') and the imperial Russian of Balanchine's youth (''Diamonds'') -- that no longer exist in today's global, homogenized dance world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A performance of “Jewels” by the New York City Ballet on Tuesday at the New York State Theater suggested that today’s dancers also add something to the 1967 piece.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>George Balanchine's ''Jewels'' was said to have been inspired by a visit to Van Cleef &amp; Arpels, though he made sure to say publicly that the ballet had nothing to do with gems. The supposed theme, the jewel-strewn look of the work and several rave reviews made ''Jewels'' the kind of hit that ballet seldom had in the mid-1960s, when the work was first performed.</p>
        <p>Now the work is recognized as substantial Balanchine. Set to scores by Fauré, Stravinsky and Tchaikovsky, ''Jewels'' is not only one of Balanchine's most compelling exercises in making music dance. It is also a telling meditation on the kind of national ballet styles -- here French (''Emeralds''), American (''Rubies'') and the imperial Russian of Balanchine's youth (''Diamonds'') -- that no longer exist in today's global, homogenized dance world.</p>
        <p>''Jewels'' also gives each new generation of dancers an opportunity to absorb those enriching styles. A performance of the work by the New York City Ballet on Tuesday night at the New York State Theater suggested that today's dancers also add something to the 1967 piece. The performer who most immediately springs to mind is Savannah Lowery, a sexy ''babe'' if ever there was one, in the second female lead in ''Rubies.''</p>
        <p>Some of the glinting color in this playful, jazzy ballet was missing in the otherwise accomplished dancing of Megan Fairchild and Joaquin De Luz, who nearly stole the show with the sharklike intensity of his partnering. Thoughts of Edward Villella's insouciance in the ''follow the leader'' sequence came unbidden as Mr. De Luz tigerishly led the fine male quartet (Kyle Froman, Austin Laurent, Allen Peiffer and Troy Schumacher) across the stage.</p>
        <p>''Emeralds,'' which opens the ballet, is one of Balanchine's most tenderly beautiful works. Stillness reigns, with sudden fleeting eruptions of emotion in choreography as translucent as any jewel. In a role originated by Violette Verdy, Ashley Bouder, dancing with Stephen Hanna, brought just the right offhand quality to the passage for flicking, curling Gallic arms in a musically phrased performance. Jenifer Ringer looked a little small in the exquisite ''walking'' pas de deux, danced with Jonathan Stafford, in which the ballet's simple walking motif blossoms center stage. And Sean Suozzi stood out for the warmth and simplicity of his dancing in the trio of soloists, completed by Alina Dronova and Ana Sophia Scheller.</p>
        <p>But honors of the night went to an exalted Maria Kowroski in the formally grand ''Diamonds.'' The way she used her upper body, allowing herself the time to arch, stretch and expand into the music and the space around her, was a special pleasure. Philip Neal, the most elegant and devoted of partners, squired her, dancing his solos with a clarity and focus that made the pyrotechnics something more than mere razzle-dazzle.</p>
        <p>The New York City Ballet will perform ''Jewels'' tonight, next Thursday, and June 23 and 24 at the New York State Theater, Lincoln Center; (212) 870-5570 or nycballet.com.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
