<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Iran May Know Of Weapons For Taliban, Gates Contends</title>
    <meta content="14gates" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854362"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE REACH OF WAR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Taliban (Afghan Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shanker, Thom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Robert M (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E2DA143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="528" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Iran May Know Of Weapons For Taliban, Gates Contends</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOM SHANKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shanker, Thom</byline>
      <dateline>RAMSTEIN AIR BASE, Germany, June 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Defense Sec Robert M Gates says flow of weapons from Iran to Taliban fighters in Afghanistan is so substantial that it suggests that Iranian government has knowledge of shipments; Gates is highest-ranking Bush administration official to state suspicions that Iran is arming Taliban; he does not offer any evidence to support remarks (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The flow of illicit weapons from Iran to Taliban fighters in Afghanistan has reached such large quantities that it suggests that the shipments are taking place with the knowledge of the government in Tehran, Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates said Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates said he had seen new intelligence analysis over the past couple of weeks ''that makes it pretty clear there's a fairly substantial flow of weapons'' from Iran across its border to assist insurgents in Afghanistan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The flow of illicit weapons from Iran to Taliban fighters in Afghanistan has reached such large quantities that it suggests that the shipments are taking place with the knowledge of the government in Tehran, Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates said Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates said he had seen new intelligence analysis over the past couple of weeks ''that makes it pretty clear there's a fairly substantial flow of weapons'' from Iran across its border to assist insurgents in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>Commenting on potential Iranian government involvement in the arms flow, Mr. Gates said, ''I haven't seen any intelligence specifically to this effect, but I would say, given the quantities that we're seeing, it is difficult to believe that it's associated with smuggling or the drug business or that it's taking place without the knowledge of the Iranian government.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates is the highest-ranking member of the Bush administration to give voice to its suspicions that Iran is arming Taliban insurgents who have attacked forces of the Afghan government as well as American and other coalition troops.</p>
        <p>Given the failings of American intelligence leading up to the war in Iraq, any new analysis of purportedly hostile behavior by adversaries may be greeted with skepticism, especially on Capitol Hill. But Mr. Gates, a former director of the Central Intelligence Agency, gave a measured assessment of the arms smuggling and did not specifically declare direct sponsorship by the Iranian government. He did not offer any evidence to back up his remarks.</p>
        <p>Going further than the defense secretary, R. Nicholas Burns, an under secretary of state, told CNN on Wednesday that there was ''irrefutable evidence'' that the shipments were ''coming from the government of Iran.''</p>
        <p>''It's coming from the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps command, which is a basic unit of the Iranian government,'' he said, as quoted by news agencies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates, speaking with reporters at the large American air base here, noted that ''the irony is, the Afghan government and the Iranian government have pretty good relationships.'' The defense secretary cited a conversation with Afghanistan's president, Hamid Karzai, who spoke with him during a recent visit ''about the importance of good relationships with Iran.''</p>
        <p>Asked to analyze Iranian motives, Mr. Gates responded, ''Whether Iran is trying to play both sides of the street, hedge their bets -- what their motives are, other than causing trouble for us, I don't know.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates declined to describe in detail the recent intelligence analysis, but said the new information came from ''the weapons themselves and the explosives and so on that have been seized.'' The Iranian weapons found smuggled into Afghanistan are of a wide variety, he added.</p>
        <p>There are more than 26,000 American troops in Afghanistan, about 14,000 of them serving in the NATO-led security and assistance force, which numbers over 36,000; 12,000 more American troops are conducting separate counterterrorism and training missions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates was in Germany visiting American forces while en route to Brussels for a meeting of NATO defense ministers on Thursday. The NATO session is expected to include debate on how to remedy shortages in alliance commitments for Afghanistan and how to resolve disputes with Russia over missile defenses.</p>
        <p>THE REACH OF WAR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
