<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Cavaliers-Spurs, Where Have All The Viewers Gone?</title>
    <meta content="14ratings" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/sports/basketball/14ratings.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854441"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TV SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/San Antonio Spurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">San Antonio Spurs</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Cleveland Cavaliers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">James, LeBron</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E4D8143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="648" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Cavaliers-Spurs, Where Have All The Viewers Gone?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Cavaliers-Spurs, Where Have All the Viewers Gone?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What has become of the N.B.A. finals? Yes, they will continue tonight on ABC with San Antonio leading, 3-0, and yes, there will be hopes that LeBron James can lead Cleveland to a victory or two before his Cavaliers succumb to the Spurs. But if fan aversion to this series continues at its current pace, these finals could be the least-viewed in at least 22 years, if not longer.</p>
        <p>This doesn't seem like a series that people are turning off; it appears more like one they're barely tuning in. Even James's sensational performance in Game 5 of the Eastern Conference finals -- which evoked comparisons to Michael Jordan -- did not compel a surge of the curious to watch the start of the finals. Game 1 generated just 9.2 million viewers, down 20 percent from Game 1 of last year's Dallas-Miami finals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>San Antonio, an efficient modern dynasty on the verge of winning its fourth N.B.A. title in nine seasons, lacks the charisma or market size to grab viewers, unlike past champions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What has become of the N.B.A. finals? Yes, they will continue tonight on ABC with San Antonio leading, 3-0, and yes, there will be hopes that LeBron James can lead Cleveland to a victory or two before his Cavaliers succumb to the Spurs. But if fan aversion to this series continues at its current pace, these finals could be the least-viewed in at least 22 years, if not longer.</p>
        <p>This doesn't seem like a series that people are turning off; it appears more like one they're barely tuning in. Even James's sensational performance in Game 5 of the Eastern Conference finals -- which evoked comparisons to Michael Jordan -- did not compel a surge of the curious to watch the start of the finals. Game 1 generated just 9.2 million viewers, down 20 percent from Game 1 of last year's Dallas-Miami finals.</p>
        <p>Game 2 on Sunday dipped 31 percent to 8.6 million viewers. But Game 3, a reasonably competitive but uninspiring 75-72 victory by San Antonio, perked up to 9.5 million viewers, but was still down 22 percent from 2006.</p>
        <p>San Antonio, an efficient modern dynasty on the verge of winning its fourth N.B.A. title in nine seasons, lacks the charisma or market size to grab viewers, unlike past champions in Chicago, Boston, Detroit and Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Regardless of the Spurs' greatness, their Q-less existence helped lead the finals to a viewership nadir four years ago, when they defeated the Nets. But even that series attracted more viewers on average in each game than the Spurs-Cavaliers finals (9.5 million to 9.1 million) -- and the competition in June is largely against repeats on other networks, the biggest exception being the finale of ''The Sopranos'' which faced Game 2 on Sunday night.</p>
        <p>''We've got the 17th market and the 37th market, a matchup of the smallest markets in N.B.A. finals history,'' said Len DeLuca, a senior vice president of ESPN, which oversees ABC Sports, referring to the respective sizes of the Cleveland and the San Antonio markets. ''You can't run away from the low numbers, but we're in this for the long haul; this isn't just the fifth year of a six-year relationship, but Year Five of what we hope will be a 15-year relationship. You have to take the highs and the lows.''</p>
        <p>Despite dismal viewership for the finals, ABC is still winning the more focused race for male viewers -- as it should -- but those demographics have fallen 21 percent to 31 percent through Game 3 of the Spur-Cavaliers series. The games have almost always won the crucial demographic of adults in the 18-to-49 range since Game 1 of the 2003 finals, the first for ABC under its current deal.</p>
        <p>At halftime of Game 3, N.B.A. Commissioner David Stern said that bad games yield bad ratings but that those ratings ''fail to reflect a new audience that is consuming the league via NBA.com and other Internet sites.''</p>
        <p>But if those sites are gobbling up those viewers, what does the digitalization of pro basketball portend for the N.B.A. finals, which, in 1997 (a Michael Jordan year), outdrew the World Series, a feat it repeated in 1998 (Jordan's farewell to the finals), but not again since?</p>
        <p>''With the Age of Jordan, you're comparing Mount Everest to everything else,'' DeLuca said. (Perhaps, then, Dwyane Wade is a little Himalaya.)</p>
        <p>The finals' vulnerability to market vagaries -- and dull teams -- should give leverage to ESPN/ABC and TNT in renewal talks with the N.B.A. to keep rights-fee increases modest.</p>
        <p>But Broadband Dave, with his digital toolbox, is no doubt telling them what their future is, and looking to get far more than the $4.6 billion in total they will pay in the six-year deals that ends next season. Stern knows that ESPN and TNT want to be where their consumers are migrating, even if it means from the live broadcasts of the N.B.A.'s championship.</p>
        <p>TV SPORTS E-mail: sportsbiz@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: sportsbiz@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
