<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Day of Police Chases, Some Woolly, Some Winged, All Wild</title>
    <meta content="14sheep" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/nyregion/14sheep.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854338"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E6DA143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="650" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Day of Police Chases, Some Woolly, Some Winged, All Wild</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Day of Police Chases, Some Woolly, Some Winged, All Wild</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AL BAKER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The stark, hard-edged and dramatically capitalized words of a police bulletin said it all: ''A SHEEP RUNNING IN THE STREET. OFFICERS CANVASSED THE AREA AND LOCATED THE SHEEP/LAMB AND REQUESTED ESU.''</p>
        <p>E.S.U. means Emergency Service Unit: the specialized unit of officers who usually take down heavily armed bad guys, rescue hostages or respond to major catastrophes. Yesterday morning, they were called upon to corral a sheep loose in the Bronx.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wednesday morning, the specialized unit of officers who usually take down heavily armed bad guys were called upon to corral a lose sheep in the Bronx.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The stark, hard-edged and dramatically capitalized words of a police bulletin said it all: ''A SHEEP RUNNING IN THE STREET. OFFICERS CANVASSED THE AREA AND LOCATED THE SHEEP/LAMB AND REQUESTED ESU.''</p>
        <p>E.S.U. means Emergency Service Unit: the specialized unit of officers who usually take down heavily armed bad guys, rescue hostages or respond to major catastrophes. Yesterday morning, they were called upon to corral a sheep loose in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>They got the job done, just like fellow officers in other parts of the city who had to deal with an unusual rash of odd animal exploits the same morning. The other ''actors,'' as the police might have said, were a hawk and a falcon.</p>
        <p>First, that sheep/lamb.</p>
        <p>It was first reported on the loose at 11:08 a.m., the police said. When the Emergency Service Unit officers arrived, it dashed into a garage at 780 East 133rd Street, the police said.</p>
        <p>Pedro Rosario, an animal care worker, said it had probably been on the loose ''a day or so.'' Its fleece had been sullied, possibly from being on the streets, the police said. ''She is like a tan color,'' Mr. Rosario said. ''She was dirty.''</p>
        <p>Police officers used a pole and a noose to corral the young sheep. They took it to one of the city's Animal Care and Control shelters, where it was determined to be a 7-month-old female, weighing about 60 pounds. She was examined by some veterinarians, fed hay and carrots and given a name: Lucky Lady.</p>
        <p>''She's going to have a better life now,'' said Mr. Rosario, a care center supervisor at the shelter, at 326 East 110th Street. He said the lamb, tagged in two places, had probably escaped from a slaughterhouse or a live poultry market. ''She's not going to be put to sleep for any food. She's going to go to a farm in upstate New York. She can spend the rest of her life, whatever she has, on the farm.''</p>
        <p>As for the birds</p>
        <p>At 10:05 a.m., Emergency Service Unit officers responded to 125 West 55th Street, in the area of the back of the Ziegfeld Theater, where a 7-week-old red-tailed hawk had seemingly run into aeronautical difficulty. At 11:26 a.m., other officers went to 938 Third Avenue, where an American kestrel (another kind of raptor, or bird of prey), had flown into the side of a building. The injured bird was placed in a box and given to the police.</p>
        <p>''These animals are very habituated to city life,'' Adrian Benepe, the city's parks commissioner, said of metropolis's varied winged inhabitants. ''They are comfortable. They eat rats, pigeons and squirrels; small mammals.''</p>
        <p>When they are young, however, learning to fly can be a perilous endeavor. ''There's all kinds of things you can bump into,'' Mr. Benepe said.</p>
        <p>A question arose about whether the hawk that crashed on West 55th Street is a relative of Pale Male, the famous red-tailed hawk of Central Park whose nest on an opulent Fifth Avenue co-op captured the attention of the city in 2004.</p>
        <p>Mr. Benepe said Pale Male ''and his various mates'' had been parents over the years to several dozen chicks who had survived and spread out. But parks officials said that it would be difficult to prove a connection, and that the bird would not be subjected to any DNA tests.</p>
        <p>Lincoln Karim, a video engineer for the Associated Press, and a self-described animal lover, said he was more certain. ''The hawk is Pale Male's grandchild,'' Mr. Karim said of the hawk that crash-landed. He said he had been observing and photographing it for months. ''It was born at 888 Seventh Avenue on the 34th floor.''</p>
        <p>Both birds survived their mishaps and are under the care of a wildlife rehabilitator. Urban park rangers helped to rescue them, Mr. Benepe said. After recuperating, they are expected to be returned to freedom.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
