<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Miller's Path to Eight Under Went From Tee to Green</title>
    <meta content="14anderson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/sports/golf/14anderson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854380"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Miller, Johnny</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EEDA143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="851" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Miller's Path to Eight Under Went From Tee to Green</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Miller’s Path to Eight Under Went From Tee to Green</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <dateline>OAKMONT, Pa.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He is golf's most caustic commentator, but as Johnny Miller did his homework for the 107th United States Open, which starts today, he basked in the memory of his record eight-under-par 63 in the final round of the 1973 Open at Oakmont.</p>
        <p>''It's like I'm on a state monument or something when I go around the course,'' he said Tuesday, almost in awe of himself, at his news conference. ''People embrace me, and there's a bit of history, and I'm sort of a part of them. I've never felt that anywhere before that I've ever gone, where people  I'm their Johnny, you know?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>He is golf’s most caustic commentator, but as Johnny Miller prepared for this year’s United States Open, he basked in the memory of his record eight-under-par 63 round during the 1973 Open.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He is golf's most caustic commentator, but as Johnny Miller did his homework for the 107th United States Open, which starts today, he basked in the memory of his record eight-under-par 63 in the final round of the 1973 Open at Oakmont.</p>
        <p>''It's like I'm on a state monument or something when I go around the course,'' he said Tuesday, almost in awe of himself, at his news conference. ''People embrace me, and there's a bit of history, and I'm sort of a part of them. I've never felt that anywhere before that I've ever gone, where people  I'm their Johnny, you know?''</p>
        <p>He's not the pros' Johnny. Many of them don't like his harshly honest comments in the NBC booth about their swing or their sway, but at Oakmont this week, all of them would like to do what he did: win the Open with the most remarkable final round in the history of golf's major tournaments.</p>
        <p>''I'm out there with Tiger and different players, and they go, 'How the heck did you shoot 63?' '' he said with a smile. ''But what they don't realize is that I only had 29 putts that round. I mean, you just don't shoot 63 at Oakmont with 29 putts. I hit the ninth green in two and every other green in regulation. I never had a downhill putt.''</p>
        <p>Over the years, there have been 22 rounds of 63 in the four major tournaments -- 2 at the Masters, 3 others at the United States Open, 7 at the British Open and 9 at the P.G.A. Championship. But none of the others were shot in the final round to win the trophy.</p>
        <p>''It's one thing to do it on the first day,'' Miller said, referring in his harshly honest manner to Jack Nicklaus and Tom Weiskopf at Baltusrol in 1980. ''It's another thing to do it on the last day. Not trying to pat myself on the back, I'm just trying to be as accurate as I can. And it was, tee to green under pressure, the best round I've ever seen.''</p>
        <p>Before that final round, Miller was six strokes off the lead. He trailed 12 golfers, including 8 who had won or would win major titles -- Nicklaus, Gary Player, Arnold Palmer, Lee Trevino, Julius Boros, Gene Littler, Tom Weiskopf and Bob Charles. But his 63 leapfrogged them all, his 279 winning by one shot over John Schlee.</p>
        <p>''Tiger Woods played a better Open; the best performance in history was Tiger Woods at Pebble Beach,'' Miller said, referring to Woods's 15-stroke victory in 2000. ''Greatest performance ever in an Open. Never lipped out one putt in 72 holes and, to my knowledge, never missed a putt inside 8 feet on those bumpy greens.''</p>
        <p>But for one round, Miller's 63 was virtually pluperfect -- nine birdies and one bogey, when he three-putted the eighth green from 30 feet. Renowned for hitting his 4- and 5-irons close, he was inside 6 feet on five greens, inside 10 feet on two greens, inside 15 feet on three greens. He hit a 9-iron to tap-in range, a bunker shot to 6 inches.</p>
        <p>''The players now go, 'How did you shoot that?' acting like they can't do it, but they can do it,'' he said. ''It can be done again. I was a good iron player, obviously, but Tiger could do it, Phil Mickelson could do it.</p>
        <p>''But getting to Oakmont now, all the changes they've made, this is the finest golf course in the world -- the agronomy, the way the bunkers are skulled, the depth of the bunkers, the Church Pews, the greens, the shot values, the trees taken out. You combine it all, this is the greatest course in the world.''</p>
        <p>Miller had some help. Rain had softened the slippery greens, and a lady in the gallery who said she was clairvoyant kept telling him he would win. But when he shot a 76 on Saturday after forgetting his yardage card -- his wife, Linda, went back to their hotel to get it and handed it to him on the 10th tee -- he didn't think he had a chance. On Sunday morning, he told Linda to pack and arrange for a taxi to the airport before he expected the eventual winner to finish. But on the practice range, he heard a voice tell him three times to open his stance.</p>
        <p>''That clear voice said, 'Open it up,' '' he recalled. ''I thought, I don't know if I really want to try this, but it was the most amazing round of golf, tee to green. I would love to have had Ben Hogan caddying for me, because I believe Ben Hogan would have said, 'You've got to be kidding me.'</p>
        <p>''He's a religious word in golf, but that round of golf, every hole, right at the pin, dead underneath the hole, 18 times, average about 9 feet from the hole. Sounds like I'm bragging, but the bottom line, it was a crazy round.''</p>
        <p>Crazy maybe, but Johnny Miller's memory of his 63 is harshly honest, too.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
