<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Mets Just Love To See Clemens Sweat</title>
    <meta content="14clemens" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854443"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE4D8143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Mets Just Love To See Clemens Sweat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the amateur draft in June 1981, the Mets took a college outfielder named Terry Blocker with their first-round pick. Blocker would go on to have one hit for the Mets. With their fifth-round pick, the Mets drafted a high school shortstop named Steve Phillips and signed him for $42,000. Phillips never played in the majors.</p>
        <p>In the 12th round, the Mets drafted an 18-year-old right-hander named William Roger Clemens from San Jacinto College. Three times after the draft, the Mets' scouting director, Joe McIlvaine, attempted to see Clemens pitch. Three times, the game was rained out.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the amateur draft in June 1981, the Mets took a college outfielder named Terry Blocker with their first-round pick. Blocker would go on to have one hit for the Mets. With their fifth-round pick, the Mets drafted a high school shortstop named Steve Phillips and signed him for $42,000. Phillips never played in the majors.</p>
        <p>In the 12th round, the Mets drafted an 18-year-old right-hander named William Roger Clemens from San Jacinto College. Three times after the draft, the Mets' scouting director, Joe McIlvaine, attempted to see Clemens pitch. Three times, the game was rained out.</p>
        <p>Without that final look, the Mets' bonus offer fell $10,000 short of what Clemens was seeking. His mother wanted him to continue his education, and Clemens enrolled at the University of Texas.</p>
        <p>''When I was G.M. of the Mets, I should have fired the scout who signed me,'' Phillips, now an ESPN announcer, said yesterday with a smile. ''He should have taken $10,000 from my bonus and signed Clemens.''</p>
        <p>After beating Pittsburgh in his return to the Yankees last Saturday, Clemens will start against the Mets at home tomorrow, continuing a tangled relationship that began with that long-ago draft. Clemens actually worked out for the Mets in a bullpen at the Astrodome, but he was not comfortable doing it.</p>
        <p>Clemens had asked his catcher to catch the ball in the pocket of the glove, not the webbing, to make his fastball sound more explosive. But as he threw, Clemens noticed the Mets' manager, Joe Torre, and the pitching coach, Bob Gibson, watching from the dugout.</p>
        <p>''I was doing really well during my little tryout session until I turned around and saw Joe's eyes and Gibson's eyes staring at me,'' Clemens, now 44, said yesterday. ''I just started sweating very bad.''</p>
        <p>The Mets have often had that effect on Clemens. In 10 career regular-season starts against them, he is 3-5 with a 5.14 earned run average. That is easily his highest E.R.A. against any team; the Philadelphia Phillies are the next highest, at 4.33, and every other team is under 4.00.</p>
        <p>Much of the damage inflicted by the Mets came from Mike Piazza, who now plays for Oakland. Piazza is 8 for 19 with 4 homers off Clemens in his career, and will always be linked to Clemens for two incidents at Yankee Stadium in 2000.</p>
        <p>Clemens beaned Piazza that July. In Game 2 of the World Series, he threw Piazza's broken bat in his direction in the first inning. Somewhat forgotten is Clemens's sterling performance that night: eight shutout innings, two hits, no walks, nine strikeouts.</p>
        <p>When Clemens next faced the Mets, on June 15, 2002, at Shea Stadium, Mets starter Shawn Estes threw behind him in his first at-bat. Some Mets grumbled that Estes had not gone far enough, but he seemed to get the last word by homering off Clemens in an 8-0 Mets rout. Piazza also homered that day, and Clemens bruised his foot running the bases.</p>
        <p>By the next season, though, most of the ill will was gone. When Clemens beat the Mets on June 28, 2003 -- his last appearance against them as a Yankee -- Timo Perez was the only player in the lineup who had played against him in the World Series.</p>
        <p>''There weren't any residual feelings by then,'' said Arizona's Tony Clark, who played for the Mets in 2003. ''I don't think it resonated.''</p>
        <p>Asked yesterday what stands out about his history with the Mets, Clemens pointed to their current roster, naming Carlos Delgado and Shawn Green and the former Yankees coaches Willie Randolph and Rick Down.</p>
        <p>''I have a few ex-teammates over there I played with, Delgado and Green,'' Clemens said. ''They're tremendous players and they were fun to watch the two years I was in Toronto. And, of course, Willie's there managing, and Rick's over there as one of the coaches.</p>
        <p>''As far as in their past, when I think of the Mets, I think about Nolan Ryan being young. I see the highlights of him. And I think of Seaver.''</p>
        <p>Tom Seaver had 300 victories when he was a teammate with Clemens on the Boston Red Sox in 1986. Now Clemens, who has 349 victories, is enjoying his role as a mentor to the younger Yankees, including Chien-Ming Wang, who idolized Clemens while growing up in Taiwan.</p>
        <p>''I told him I enjoyed watching him work,'' Clemens said, adding, ''I told him it was great to be young.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
