<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Loose Reins on U.S. Teenagers Can Produce Trouble or Entrepreneurs</title>
    <meta content="14scene" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Business; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/business/14scene.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854387"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ECONOMIC SCENE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entrepreneurship</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowen, Tyler</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Casnocha, Ben</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Economic Scene (Times Column)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">My Start-Up Life (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Entrepreneurship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entrepreneurship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E6D9143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="944" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Loose Reins on U.S. Teenagers Can Produce Trouble or Entrepreneurs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Loose Reins on U.S. Teenagers Can Produce Trouble or Entrepreneurs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER COWEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowen, Tyler</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tyler Cowen Economic Scene column on why US has produced so many successful young entrepreneurs; focuses on Ben Casnocha's book My Start-Up Life: What a (Very) Young CEO Learned on His Journey Through Silicon Valley; says Casnocha believes American youths are so successful at entrepreneurship in part because so many older and wealthier people are willing to help them (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michael S. Dell (of Dell Inc.) sold stamps to collectors when he was 12 and Bill Gates founded Microsoft when he was 19. Facebook, the social networking site, was the brainchild of Mark Zuckerberg, a Harvard University sophomore at the time. A study  by the Global Entrepreneurship Monitor showed that the United States was unusual among developed countries in having a higher business start-up rate among its 18- to 24-year-olds than its 35- to 44-year-olds.</p>
        <p>But why has America produced so many successful young entrepreneurs? Ben Casnocha, 19, author of the new book ''My Start-Up Life: What a (Very) Young C.E.O. Learned on His Journey Through Silicon Valley,'' offers clues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The success of young entrepreneurs is rooted in the commercial, competitive, nonegalitarian and open nature of American society.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Michael S. Dell (of Dell Inc.) sold stamps to collectors when he was 12 and Bill Gates founded Microsoft when he was 19. Facebook, the social networking site, was the brainchild of Mark Zuckerberg, a Harvard University sophomore at the time. A study  by the Global Entrepreneurship Monitor showed that the United States was unusual among developed countries in having a higher business start-up rate among its 18- to 24-year-olds than its 35- to 44-year-olds.</p>
        <p>But why has America produced so many successful young entrepreneurs? Ben Casnocha, 19, author of the new book ''My Start-Up Life: What a (Very) Young C.E.O. Learned on His Journey Through Silicon Valley,'' offers clues.</p>
        <p>As he recounts in his book, Ben was 14 when he started Comcate Inc., a Web-based service for helping local governments manage customer service. He called on numerous mentors, many of them initially strangers or casual acquaintances. Some talented and busy people, presumably impressed by the young man, decided to support his enterprise. He also asked for outright grants to get his business off the ground and to help finance his version of the American dream.</p>
        <p>American youths are so successful at entrepreneurship in part because so many older and wealthier people are willing to help them. The broader American success at philanthropy, then, lays the groundwork for American entrepreneurship. By global standards, Americans may have looser networks of friends and family, but Americans are more willing to help relative strangers, and this often helps business.</p>
        <p>America's culture of marketing provided inspiration. Ben Casnocha surveyed his future customers and asked them what services they needed and how much they were willing to pay. He also had to persuade people to do business with a teenager. He had no formal education in marketing but, as a suburban American youth, he was exposed to intense commercial marketing every day. He decided to become an entrepreneur at the age of 12, he says, after being struck by the Apple ''Think Different'' ad. Critics contend that corporate selling and advertising are dumbing down America's young. But marketing often motivates or instructs young people. In addition, it can teach them how to think about marketing messages more critically.</p>
        <p>The fact that American schooling is less disciplined than that in other countries gives young creators the time and the energy to accomplish something outside their formal education. Despite his intellectual talents, Ben, in his book, admits that he received indifferent grades and had little emotional attachment to most of his formal schooling. Whenever he could, he used sick days to set up meetings for his business.</p>
        <p>The longstanding criticism of the American school system is that even in the better schools, too many students just ''get by'' rather than engage in a rigorous curriculum. This academic leniency is bad for many average or subpar students, but it also allows some students to flourish. Relatively loose family structures have similar effects; American children are especially likely to be working on their own projects, rather than being directed by parents and elders.</p>
        <p>Compared with those in other countries, American children play a much more influential role in society and enjoy a remarkable degree of autonomy. American fast food, with its fatty, sweet and bland tastes, is geared toward children, as are many American movies and television shows. Teenagers receive higher allowances, have greater access to credit cards, and have more money to spend on culture, or, in some cases, to spend on starting a business. American labor markets are flexible enough to create a large number of jobs at the lower end of the wage scale. Teenagers are more likely to acquire work experience, and they are more likely to earn a small amount of capital for financing a start-up enterprise.</p>
        <p>It is a common American dream to want to start one's own business, and this cultural influence spreads to the young. It sometimes replaces school and family as a driving force. Ben, in an e-mail message, cited the openness of American culture. ''If starting a business wasn't 'cool,' '' he wrote, ''I doubt very many teens would partake.'' In the relatively nonegalitarian United States, almost everyone likes a winner. Ben also cited outsourcing, in this case the ability to buy cheap programming from abroad, as helping business start-ups.</p>
        <p>The new ideas and business principles behind the Web have carved out the ideal territory for the young. A neophyte is more likely to see that music can come from computers rather than just from stores or radios, or that it is best to book a flight without using a travel agent. Clay Shirky, an associate teacher at New York University, notes that many young people are blessed by an absence of preconceptions about Internet businesses. Years of experience are critical to refining and improving a long-familiar product, like bread. But completely new, outside-the-box ideas -- which typically come from the young -- are more important for founding Napster or YouTube. The Web also makes the human face of a business less important and allows the young to put forward their talents while disguising their inexperience.</p>
        <p>It is well known that American companies have been the most successful at turning information technology into productivity advantages. In part, this is because of American success in mobilizing young talent.</p>
        <p>In 2006, BusinessWeek ranked Ben as one of America's top young entrepreneurs, and he is only this fall enrolling at Claremont McKenna College. Whatever Ben does next, his story shows that economic advantages start early. On a national level, these successes are rooted in the commercial, competitive, philanthropic, nonegalitarian and open nature of American society. America's economic head start probably won't go away anytime soon.</p>
        <p>ECONOMIC SCENE Tyler Cowen is professor of economics at George Mason University and author of the forthcoming book ''Discover Your Inner Economist.'' He can be reached at tcowen@gmu.edu.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Tyler Cowen is professor of economics at George Mason University and author of the forthcoming book ''Discover Your Inner Economist.'' He can be reached at tcowen@gmu.edu.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
