<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Anti-Syrian Lawmaker Killed in Beirut Bombing</title>
    <meta content="14lebanon" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/world/middleeast/14lebanon.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon/Beirut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Beirut (Lebanon)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Lebanon</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3D8143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="533" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Anti-Syrian Lawmaker Killed in Beirut Bombing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Anti-Syrian Lawmaker Killed in Lebanon Blast</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NADA BAKRI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bakri, Nada</byline>
      <dateline>BEIRUT, Lebanon, June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A powerful bomb exploded at a popular seaside club here on Wednesday, killing a prominent lawmaker and nine other people. It was the deadliest in a string of recent explosions that have rattled this city and shaken its fragile sense of stability.</p>
        <p>The bomb, which security authorities say they believe was hidden inside a parked car, exploded as Walid Eido, a Sunni member of Parliament and an outspoken critic of Syria, drove by. He was killed instantly, along with his son and two bodyguards, and six passers-by.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A massive bomb exploded at a popular seaside club in Beirut, killing a prominent lawmaker and nine other people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A powerful bomb exploded at a popular seaside club here on Wednesday, killing a prominent lawmaker and nine other people. It was the deadliest in a string of recent explosions that have rattled this city and shaken its fragile sense of stability.</p>
        <p>The bomb, which security authorities say they believe was hidden inside a parked car, exploded as Walid Eido, a Sunni member of Parliament and an outspoken critic of Syria, drove by. He was killed instantly, along with his son and two bodyguards, and six passers-by.</p>
        <p>The blast occurred near a crowded amusement park along the Mediterranean; it destroyed an adjacent building and shattered windows nearby at a time when sunbathers and swimmers were returning home from a day at the beach.</p>
        <p>There have been five bombings in and around Beirut in the month since the Lebanese Army laid siege to a Palestinian refugee camp in northern Lebanon where it surrounded Islamic militants.</p>
        <p>Security officials said they did not yet have information about the motive for Wednesday's attack, but many fingers pointed at Syria.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eido, 65, was a member of the Future Movement headed by Saad Hariri. Two years ago, Mr. Hariri's father, former Prime Minister Rafik Hariri, was assassinated a few miles away on the same coastal road.</p>
        <p>The killing of Mr. Eido came three days after a United Nations Security Council resolution took effect ordering the creation of an international tribunal to try suspects in the assassination of Mr. Hariri and related crimes. Preliminary investigations of Mr. Hariri's assassination have pointed toward Syria. The government in Damascus vigorously denies it had any involvement.</p>
        <p>The assassination on Wednesday increased concern in a nation already paralyzed by the deadly siege at the Nahr al Bared refugee camp in northern Lebanon. Two Lebanese soldiers died at the camp on Wednesday in clashes between the army and the Qaeda-inspired Fatah al Islam, bringing the total number of deaths to 140, including 63 soldiers and 50 militants.</p>
        <p>Many Lebanese said they feared that Mr. Eido's assassination would inflame tensions between supporters of Prime Minister Fouad Siniora and members of the pro-Iranian, pro-Syrian opposition led by Hezbollah, the militant Shiite Muslim group. Lebanon has been divided by a seven-month sit-in in downtown Beirut that has pressed Mr. Siniora to resign and paralyzed the government.</p>
        <p>In a speech on Wednesday night, Mr. Siniora declared that Thursday would be a national day of mourning and vowed that Lebanon would remain united. ''Our determination to fight evil and betrayal will remain strong and effective because this is a national requirement related to people's safety,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Syria's allies in Lebanon condemned the killing. The speaker of the Parliament, Nabih Berri, a close ally of Hezbollah, said, ''No individual, group, organization or party using terrorism and organized crime will be able to make Lebanon an arena for unrest, strife, wars and score-settling.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Siniora's allies in the so-called March 14 movement -- a reference to the protest that helped force Syria out of Lebanon -- blamed Syria for the killing.</p>
        <p>''It is the same serial killer who wants to liquidate the parliamentary majority; it is a physical liquidation by the Syrian regime,'' said the telecommunications minister, Marwan Hamadeh.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
