<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Former Chairman of G.O.P. Will Join Bush's Inner Circle</title>
    <meta content="14gillespie" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/washington/14gillespie.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854394"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Gillespie, Ed</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E5D9143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="696" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Former Chairman of G.O.P. Will Join Bush's Inner Circle</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Former Chairman of G.O.P. Will Join Bush’s Inner Circle</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERYL GAY STOLBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ed Gillespie, a prominent Washington lobbyist, former chairman of the Republican National Committee and longtime adviser to President Bush, will join the White House inner circle as the next counselor to the president, Mr. Bush said Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush made the announcement in the Oval Office, with Mr. Gillespie and the aide he will replace, Dan Bartlett, by his side. In selecting Mr. Gillespie, Mr. Bush reached for a consummate insider, someone comfortable both in the ways of Washington and the White House itself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In selecting Ed Gillespie as the next counselor to the president, President Bush reached for someone comfortable both in the ways of Washington and the White House itself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ed Gillespie, a prominent Washington lobbyist, former chairman of the Republican National Committee and longtime adviser to President Bush, will join the White House inner circle as the next counselor to the president, Mr. Bush said Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush made the announcement in the Oval Office, with Mr. Gillespie and the aide he will replace, Dan Bartlett, by his side. In selecting Mr. Gillespie, Mr. Bush reached for a consummate insider, someone comfortable both in the ways of Washington and the White House itself.</p>
        <p>It was a revealing change of course for a president who came to Washington more than six years ago with a cadre of Texas outsiders who did not hide their disdain for the city's permanent bureaucracy. But as he approaches the end of his second term, Mr. Bush has been increasingly turning to members of the Washington establishment, including Tony Snow as press secretary, Fred F. Fielding as White House counsel, and now Mr. Gillespie.</p>
        <p>''He is a seasoned hand who has got excellent judgment,'' Mr. Bush said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gillespie's political ties have helped him build a reputation as one of Washington's best-connected lobbyists. Over the years, his firm's corporate clients have included Enron, Viacom, Verizon Wireless, the Atlantic Richfield Company and trade groups representing health insurers and the recording industry.</p>
        <p>''Ed Gillespie has long been part of the Bush money machine,'' said Joan Claybrook, president of Public Citizen, an advocacy group, in a statement criticizing the selection.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gillespie has already served Mr. Bush in various capacities: as a media strategist during the 2000 presidential campaign; spokesman during the Florida election recount and as the manager of the successful effort to win Senate confirmation for John G. Roberts Jr. as chief justice of the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gillespie joins a White House troubled by political woes, from low public approval ratings to deteriorating support for the war to a hostile Democratic Congress. In an interview, he said he saw the job as that of ''utility infielder.''</p>
        <p>Ever the optimist, he predicted the president's fortunes would turn. ''I believe we are on the cusp of a pendulum swing,'' Mr. Gillespie said.</p>
        <p>Joshua B. Bolten, the White House chief of staff, offered the job to Mr. Gillespie about a month ago, before Mr. Bartlett announced publicly that he was leaving to spend more time with his wife and three young children. Mr. Bartlett has been with the president for 14 years, since Mr. Bush's first run for Texas governor, and is among his closest aides.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gillespie's relationship with the president does not date that far back, but he does know Mr. Bush well -- a factor Mr. Bolten said was crucial in his hiring.</p>
        <p>''There needs to be a relationship in which the president has confidence in that person, because he really serves as a counselor, somebody who steps above to give strategic communications advice,'' Mr. Bolten said, calling Mr. Gillespie ''the ideal successor to Dan.''</p>
        <p>Republicans generally speak highly of Mr. Gillespie, citing his wry sense of humor, his good relationships with reporters, members of Congress and the conservatives who make up Mr. Bush's political base. But in picking him, Mr. Bush did not reach for someone who will shake things up.</p>
        <p>''I think Bush is comfortable with him; he's a known commodity; he's trusted,'' said Kenneth Duberstein, a Republican strategist.</p>
        <p>At 45, Mr. Gillespie has been around Washington for more than two decades. He attended Catholic University here and was a Senate parking lot attendant before serving as a Congressional intern for Andrew Ireland, a Reagan Democrat who became a Republican in 1984. ''He changed, and I changed with him, and I never looked back,'' Mr. Gillespie said.</p>
        <p>He was chairman of the Republican Party during Mr. Bush's re-election campaign in 2004, then rejoined his lobbying firm, Quinn Gillespie and Associates. Seven months ago, he became chairman of the Virginia Republican Party. (''I'm working my way down to precinct captain,'' he cracked not long ago.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Gillespie, who will begin work on June 27, said he would sever his ties with his lobbying firm and give up his Republican Party job when he joins the White House.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
