<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Retreat in Ulster County, Shipped Partly From Bolivia</title>
    <meta content="14boli" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/14/garden/14boli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1854319"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E2DB143FF937A25755C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1185" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Retreat in Ulster County, Shipped Partly From Bolivia</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Retreat in Ulster County, Shipped Partly From Bolivia</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRED A. BERNSTEIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOUR years ago Henry Scott, a media consultant living in Manhattan, hired Sergio Guardia to design a weekend house on a wooded site in Kerhonkson, N.Y. Mr. Guardia, an architect who was born in Bolivia and trained at Harvard's Graduate School of Design, came up with plans for a futuristic house set on thick steel beams cantilevered over a hillside.</p>
        <p>The house, which was meant to feel like a capsule suspended in the woods, was perfect for the North Carolina-born Mr. Scott, who said he loves nature -- when it's behind glass. Because of allergies, he said, ''I didn't want to have a lawn to mow or bushes to prune.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The woods outside are locals. The ones inside are imports.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOUR years ago Henry Scott, a media consultant living in Manhattan, hired Sergio Guardia to design a weekend house on a wooded site in Kerhonkson, N.Y. Mr. Guardia, an architect who was born in Bolivia and trained at Harvard's Graduate School of Design, came up with plans for a futuristic house set on thick steel beams cantilevered over a hillside.</p>
        <p>The house, which was meant to feel like a capsule suspended in the woods, was perfect for the North Carolina-born Mr. Scott, who said he loves nature -- when it's behind glass. Because of allergies, he said, ''I didn't want to have a lawn to mow or bushes to prune.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Scott responded enthusiastically to Mr. Guardia's vision. But when they priced the house, he said, ''there was no way I could afford it.'' The steel supports (which ended up costing $47,000) were budget-busters, but they were essential to the design.</p>
        <p>So Mr. Guardia, of the Manhattan firm of Guardia Architects, suggested having the wood parts of the house -- the floors, doors, window frames and cabinetry -- made in Santa Cruz, Bolivia, where his sister-in-law, Cecilia López, is an architect, and where labor costs are much lower than in the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Guardia had ordered kitchen cabinets from a shop in Santa Cruz for another client and had been pleased not just with the cost ($11,000, or about a quarter of what he estimated the cabinets would have cost if made in the United States), but the quality. ''The craftsmanship in Bolivia is excellent,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Even as outsourcing remains a contentious political issue in this country -- and one likely to generate more heat during the 2008 presidential campaign -- Americans have grown used to it in nearly every area of their lives. While outsourcing carpentry is a novel idea, Mr. Scott, 55, said he believes in free markets and was glad to help support workers in Bolivia, one of the poorest nations in the Western Hemisphere.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scott's house required more than a dozen kitchen cabinets, 1,700 square feet of wood flooring and -- perhaps most essential to the modernist box that Mr. Guardia envisioned -- window frames as big as 9 by 11 feet. Mr. Guardia got an estimate from a manufacturer in Michigan for one of the windows: $7,300. Then he got an estimate in Santa Cruz: $1,900. He and Mr. Scott decided to proceed.</p>
        <p>All in all, Mr. Scott paid $52,000, plus $8,000 for shipping, for the Bolivian components, including a one-piece bed that looks as if it's from an Italian design store, and a dining table made of lacquered wood. The pieces would have cost more than $100,000 -- possibly much more -- in the United States, Mr. Guardia said.</p>
        <p>They were two months in the making and were shipped in a single container to Elizabeth, N.J.</p>
        <p>''I had these fears that there would be a squall in the Pacific and my house would end up in the bottom of the ocean,'' Mr. Scott said.</p>
        <p>But things went smoothly. From Elizabeth, the container was trucked directly to the building site in Kerhonkson, which is 90 miles north of New York City. Thanks to careful supervision by Ms. López, Mr. Guardia said, all the pieces fit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Guardia worked with two companies in Santa Cruz, a city of 1.3 million in Bolivia's midland: one made the furniture, the other the doors, floors and windows. Mr. Guardia said that the latter company, Muebles Fátima, told him it paid its carpenters $450 to $500 a month, and the project foreman $1,000 a month. (The average monthly wage in Bolivia in 2003 was about $82, according to the most recent figures available from the Bolivian National Statistics Institute.)</p>
        <p>Certainly, the Santa Cruz firms were happy to have the business, Mr. Guardia said. ''No one spends that kind of money on cabinetry down there,'' he said. ''They charged us more than they would charge a local client, so they made an extra profit.''</p>
        <p>UNDER Bolivian law, Mr. Guardia said, he was required to obtain a permit from the Ministry of Sustainable Development and Environment certifying that the woods he used -- which included tarara (canary wood) for the cabinets and tajibo for windows and doors -- could be exported legally. Those woods, he said, ''are very hard, which gives you great durability, and they have wonderful, dramatic grains that you don't see in the U.S.''</p>
        <p>Two panels of the tarara hide Mr. Scott's refrigerator, an ordinary Whirlpool unit. Mr. Guardia had the panels glued directly to its doors. Set amid cabinets of the same wood, the refrigerator looks built in.</p>
        <p>It was that kind of ingenuity, Mr. Scott said, that allowed him to construct the entire house, which is about 1,700 square feet, for about $400,000. (The five-acre lot, which he bought in 2002, added $25,000 to the total.)</p>
        <p>All the rooms are on one floor. A long hallway -- about five feet wide, with library shelves for Mr. Scott's books -- runs the length of the house, which is 72 by 24 feet, connecting the living room at one end with the master bedroom at the other. In between are a couple of bathrooms, a guest room that Mr. Scott uses as an office and the kitchen, with its dark wood cabinets.</p>
        <p>One metal stairway rises from the ground to the front door. Another, also outside, leads to the roof, where Mr. Scott hopes to install a hot tub and an outdoor shower on what is now a rubberized surface.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scott, a business consultant to newspapers and magazines (his firm is called Gansevoort Media), began his career as a newspaper reporter in North Carolina, where, he says, he so neglected his lawn that the neighbors had to mow it for him. He moved to New York in 1989, and in 2004 helped establish the free daily Metro New York.</p>
        <p>He lived in a series of Manhattan apartments, none especially large or bright, he said. When he decided he wanted to build a weekend house, about six years ago, choosing an architect was easy: he had seen, and admired, the Manhattan apartment that Mr. Guardia had renovated for the restaurateur Florent Morellet in 1999.</p>
        <p>Finding the unspoiled scenery Mr. Scott wanted was harder. Mr. Guardia ended up accompanying him on trips to look for land, which began in Columbia County but ended in the less expensive Ulster County. Kerhonkson is west of New Paltz, in an area where the backdrop includes the spectacular Shawangunk Mountains.</p>
        <p>After moving into the house last year, he gave up his Greenwich Village apartment, and he now spends about half his time with his partner, Robert Pagan, 29, in their apartment on the Upper West Side. (Mr. Pagan is an executive of InterSchool Orchestras of New York, which introduces classical music to schoolchildren.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Pagan accompanies Mr. Scott to Kerhonkson when he can -- ''about half the time I'm there,'' Mr. Scott said. That gives Mr. Scott time to enjoy being alone in the woods.</p>
        <p>''There's no sound except the sound you make yourself,'' Mr. Scott said. ''It was rather startling at first, and rather scary.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
